<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Simple Snapshots To High Concepts</title>
    <meta content="29artsweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29artswe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bronx Museum of the Arts</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Bronx Museum of the Arts</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Simple Snapshots To High Concepts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Simple Snapshots to High Concepts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews annual Artist in the Marketplace show for emerging artists at Bronx Museum of the Arts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few museums pride themselves on supporting emerging artists as much as the Bronx Museum of the Arts, which for 27 years has played host to the annual Artist in the Marketplace program for the professional development of up-and-coming artists. The artists are also given a show, which this year is titled ''AIM 27: Here and Elsewhere,'' in recognition of the cultural diversity of the participants.</p>
        <p>This year's AIM exhibition is the first to be installed in the new museum building that opened last October. It is an attractive, roomy structure built for the display of art and thus in many ways more accommodating than the galleries in the old building next door, which will undergo renovations over the coming years. The new galleries are, however, slightly smaller than the old ones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few museums pride themselves on supporting emerging artists as much as the Bronx Museum of the Arts, which for 27 years has played host to the annual Artist in the Marketplace program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few museums pride themselves on supporting emerging artists as much as the Bronx Museum of the Arts, which for 27 years has played host to the annual Artist in the Marketplace program for the professional development of up-and-coming artists. The artists are also given a show, which this year is titled ''AIM 27: Here and Elsewhere,'' in recognition of the cultural diversity of the participants.</p>
        <p>This year's AIM exhibition is the first to be installed in the new museum building that opened last October. It is an attractive, roomy structure built for the display of art and thus in many ways more accommodating than the galleries in the old building next door, which will undergo renovations over the coming years. The new galleries are, however, slightly smaller than the old ones.</p>
        <p>AIM is always unwieldy, largely because it has to accommodate the work of many artists working with different ideas and in different media. ''Here and Elsewhere'' is no exception, pulling together the work of 36 artists engaged in painting, sculpture, photography, video, collage and installation. But the sensible introduction this year of an exhibition curator -- a first for an AIM show -- also means that it is a tighter, more refined and more orderly show than usual.</p>
        <p>Last year's exhibition contained a lot of works on paper and painting. This year the show is weighted toward installation, with several artists constructing elaborate assemblages out of found materials and everyday objects, much of which is indebted to vintage conceptual art and contemporary sculpture. There is also less video this year, which is somewhat surprising given that so many younger artists these days choose to work in this medium.</p>
        <p>But the little there is includes a couple of exceptional works. Among them is Chihcheng Peng's ''Shadow Your Man,'' a clever reworking of a segment of Buster Keaton's 1924 film ''Sherlock Jr.,'' in which a man walks closely behind another, trying not to run into him. The artist has cut, varied and looped the segment to create one continuous scene. It's hilarious.</p>
        <p>Hector Canonge's interactive new media installation ''Idolatries'' is also notable, full of wistful charms. He has assembled a wide collection of Spanish food products using pictures of Latina stereotypes on their labels -- mother, siren, housewife -- and invites viewers to scan the product barcodes, which then sets off a film display on a nearby monitor showing women conforming to those formulaic, oversimplified images. The work bears witness to the prejudices of consumer culture.</p>
        <p>A number of artworks relate to the Bronx, among them Gail Biederman's weblike installation of yarn and thread installed across a window and wall that takes the form of a map of a neighborhood in the Bronx. Here Ms. Biederman uses her own biography as the basis for the work: The map is of East Tremont, where her family settled when they first came to the United States from her native Germany. Though the artist's basic idea of meshing identity and place sails close to cliché, this is still one of the show's most resolved works.</p>
        <p>There is also a lot of snapshot photography, some of which is very good. Bami Adedoyin's photographs of black youths living in and around New York have a directness that suggests an artist of unusual sensitivity. Nearby, Dorthe Alstrup explores human relationships by casually revealing pictures of the interiors of people's homes. Jayson Keeling's close-up photographs of gang hand signs are also intriguing, capturing how youths communicate with each other.</p>
        <p>Many of the artists this year also appear to have a penchant for high concepts, though thankfully tinged with a sense of humor. Among them is Emily Puthoff, who has assembled a bizarre-looking sculpture with a white flag, which she calls a ''surrender module prototype.'' It is designed, according to the show's catalog, to lure the world's dictators and terrorists into surrendering themselves to justice by playing soppy Whitney Houston songs when you get up close.</p>
        <p>Whereas Ms. Puthoff's gifts for clowning around are on full display, other artists who attempt to broach serious issues using humor sometimes miss the mark. David Politzer's brazenly indulgent installation exploring ''the different sides to his personality'' is sure to leave you scratching your head.</p>
        <p>''AIM 27: Here and Elsewhere,'' Bronx Museum of the Arts, 1040 Grand Concourse (at 165th Street), through Aug. 19. Information: (718) 681-6000 or bronxmuseum.org.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
