<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Eyes for Other Players, Giants Fill a Need With Ross</title>
    <meta content="29giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/football/29giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reese, Jerry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Coughlin, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Eyes for Other Players, Giants Fill a Need With Ross</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giants Fill a Need by Drafting Ross, but They Had Eyes for Other Players</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN BRANCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Branch, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The draft needs of the Giants were obvious, but their first choice was not. In recent weeks, they brought in about two dozen players for visits at Giants Stadium, many of them linebackers and cornerbacks. When it came time for their pick at No. 20 on Saturday, they drafted none of them.</p>
        <p>While the Giants were making their selection, Texas cornerback Aaron Ross was outside his mother's home in San Antonio tossing a football with a nephew. He did not know that the Giants had spent the past couple of hours trying, unsuccessfully, to trade up to nab one of two cornerbacks they had ranked higher. Ross did not know that the Giants had him ranked third, worthy of the 20th pick, and were bent on filling a need at the position.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In recent weeks, the Giants brought in about two dozen players for visits , but when it came time for their pick at No. 20 on Saturday, they drafted none of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The draft needs of the Giants were obvious, but their first choice was not. In recent weeks, they brought in about two dozen players for visits at Giants Stadium, many of them linebackers and cornerbacks. When it came time for their pick at No. 20 on Saturday, they drafted none of them.</p>
        <p>While the Giants were making their selection, Texas cornerback Aaron Ross was outside his mother's home in San Antonio tossing a football with a nephew. He did not know that the Giants had spent the past couple of hours trying, unsuccessfully, to trade up to nab one of two cornerbacks they had ranked higher. Ross did not know that the Giants had him ranked third, worthy of the 20th pick, and were bent on filling a need at the position.</p>
        <p>He did not expect the team to choose him.</p>
        <p>''If it was a poker game, they won,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ross, a Texas team captain and the 2006 Jim Thorpe Award winner as college football's top defensive back, is expected to compete for a starting position at cornerback, trying to take a job from Sam Madison or Corey Webster.</p>
        <p>''He fits our scheme -- a big guy with long arms who can battle big receivers,'' said Jerry Reese, the Giants' first-year general manager.</p>
        <p>Ross, who had three punt returns for touchdowns during his Texas career, will also be given a chance to return punts for the Giants.</p>
        <p>The Giants addressed another hole in their roster in the second round, drafting Southern California receiver Steve Smith. In the third round, they chose Penn State defensive tackle Jay Alford, who had eight and a half sacks in 2005 and eight in 2006.</p>
        <p>The Giants are looking for Smith to assume the role of the crafty, dependable second receiver that has been filled by Amani Toomer, who was the Giants' second-round pick in the 1996 draft. Toomer, who will be 33 when the season starts, missed the final eight games in 2006 with a knee injury.</p>
        <p>The Giants consider Smith deceptively fast; he ran a 40-yard dash in 4.44 seconds at the scouting combine in February. But he is known, as Toomer is, for his ability to run precise routes and to make difficult catches, and for his soft hands.</p>
        <p>''This guy is polished, he is fast,'' Reese said. ''He has the size. He can catch the ball and do something after the catch.''</p>
        <p>Neither Smith nor Ross steps immediately into a starting role, but each will add to the competition at those positions in training camp.</p>
        <p>The Giants expect Ross to become their best coverage option against the league's taller and stronger receivers. He is a fraction over 6 feet tall and weighs 195 pounds, and he excelled in the tight one-on-one ''press'' coverage favored by the Giants' new defensive coordinator, Steve Spagnuolo.</p>
        <p>''I feel like that is my strength, to get down there and lock up on a guy,'' Ross said.</p>
        <p>He ran the 40 in 4.54 seconds at the scouting combine in February, but he may not be faster than his longtime girlfriend, Sanya Richards. She won a gold medal at the 2004 Olympics in Athens in the 4x400-meter relay, and she holds the American record in the 400.</p>
        <p>The Giants like Ross's big-play ability, a much-needed attribute for their secondary, which has struggled to create turnovers. Madison, 33, limited to 12 games because of a sore hamstring, had two interceptions in 2006. Webster, the Giants' second-round draft choice in 2005, is only six months older than Ross. Last season, he had one interception in 12 games, missing time with toe and hip injuries.</p>
        <p>Ross had 6 interceptions and 19 pass deflections last season for the Longhorns. He was third on the team in tackles, with 80.</p>
        <p>''He is a guy that has had tremendous numbers,'' Giants Coach Tom Coughlin said.</p>
        <p>Still, for all the accolades, the Giants made attempts to choose someone different. They tried to do what the Jets did -- trade up to the early teens to snare one of the top two cornerbacks. The Jets, entering with the 25th pick, jumped ahead of the Giants by trading for the 14th pick, held by the Carolina Panthers. The Jets then selected Darrelle Revis out of Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>The Giants, their eye on Michigan's Leon Hall, continued making trade inquiries. No deal was struck. Hall was selected by the Cincinnati Bengals at No. 18.</p>
        <p>''We tried to get up a couple of times, but the price was too high,'' Reese said. ''So we moved on.''</p>
        <p>With Revis, Hall and other intriguing defensive players already selected, the Giants chose Ross.</p>
        <p>''There were several other positions that we were interested in,'' Reese said. ''But this guy was sitting there with all of the production, so it was the right time and the right place for us to pick him.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
