<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Crisis After Another, but Sony Shares Keep Surging</title>
    <meta content="29frenzy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/business/yourmoney/29frenzy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA FRENZY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sony Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1385" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Crisis After Another, but Sony Shares Keep Surging</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Crisis After Another, but Sony Shares Keep Surging</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SIKLOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siklos, Richard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A LOT of the news about the Sony Corporation over the last year has been -- as its Welsh-born chairman, Howard Stringer, might say -- rather dreary.</p>
        <p>Last summer, defective Sony laptop batteries proved liable to burst into flame, prompting an embarrassing recall. The introduction last fall of the company's PlayStation 3 game system was plagued by cost run-ups and delays. Last week, the Sony games god Ken Kutaragi retired. And the company continues to search for an answer to the iPod, in the portable media player business it once ruled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite a number of challenges, Sony has outperformed the Walt Disney Company, Time Warner and Comcast over the past two years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A LOT of the news about the Sony Corporation over the last year has been -- as its Welsh-born chairman, Howard Stringer, might say -- rather dreary.</p>
        <p>Last summer, defective Sony laptop batteries proved liable to burst into flame, prompting an embarrassing recall. The introduction last fall of the company's PlayStation 3 game system was plagued by cost run-ups and delays. Last week, the Sony games god Ken Kutaragi retired. And the company continues to search for an answer to the iPod, in the portable media player business it once ruled.</p>
        <p>Add to that the titanic struggle over Blu-Ray, the high-definition DVD format on which Sony has staked its strategic future. A stubborn rival format, backed by Toshiba and Microsoft, is not backing down.</p>
        <p>Given all these challenges, it is not hard to conjure the image of Mr. Stringer as a stranger in a strange land, struggling to bridge an impossible cultural and operational gulf at his Japanese-based behemoth.</p>
        <p>Despite all this, Sony is, curiously, the land of the rising stock. If you look at the share performance of some of the biggest media companies over the last two years, -- roughly since Mr. Stringer was named as the first non-Japanese head of Sony -- you might be surprised to see Sony near the head of the pack.</p>
        <p>Sony shares closed on Friday at $53.48 -- up more than 45 percent over two years. It has performed far better than the Walt Disney Company, Time Warner and Comcast during that time. In that crowd, it is topped only by Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation for appreciation in that period.</p>
        <p>True, Sony is not precisely a peer of these companies -- it is much more in the business of gear than of TV shows and films. But if you believe in this whole convergence thing, how Sony fares as a media play is as important as how it performs against rivals like Apple and Samsung. (It all depends on the time horizon: Apple has wildly outperformed Sony, but Sony stock has done better than Samsung in the last year or two. Over the last five years, Samsung has been a far better investment, as have any of the media giants mentioned above.)</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Stringer -- who jetted back to his home in New York from Tokyo last week and declined to comment because the company is set to announce year-end financials next month -- would be the first to say that Sony's rank and file ought not to get too chuffed about the stock's trajectory. After all, handling the crisis of the week is still an issue at Sony.</p>
        <p>But there is evidence to suggest that the new course the company has pursued -- not to mention a healthy dollop of luck and timing -- has yielded promising results.</p>
        <p>There are, as near as I can tell, at least three main reasons for this. One is that Sony has gone a long way toward mending its electronics business, which accounts for roughly two-thirds of an expected $70 billion in sales in the year ended in March 2007. The second is that the company's sprawling east-west software-hardware agglomeration may at last be starting to make sense. And, finally, there is Sony's simple recognition of how deep a hole it got itself into -- and how far it still needs to climb back.</p>
        <p>The standout in electronics is the revitalization of Sony's TV business, after earlier bungles -- something that was mainly in the works before Mr. Stringer stepped up to the chairmanship. Despite price pressure and the conventional view that the hardware business is commoditizing, Sony has so far managed to maintain both premium pricing and lead the market in sales for its Bravia L.C.D. sets for two Christmases in a row.</p>
        <p>The TV business still loses money but is ''less of a drag,'' says John McPeake, who follows Sony for the Prudential Equities Group and says he believes its stock will go even higher.</p>
        <p>It is worth noting that the rebound in the television business has come in large measure because of a panel-making joint venture with its rival Samsung -- an arrangement that would have been unthinkable within the Sony product-design fortress of old.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Sony's camera business has improved since it acquired the assets of Konica Minolta last year. And a wildly successful new product for the company globally -- though not very visible in the United States -- has been a line of mobile phone-cum-Walkman players that it is producing in a joint venture with Ericsson.</p>
        <p>A new willingness to let go also led the company to announce that it will no longer put so much emphasis on building advanced semiconductors -- a move that will save Sony some $1.5 billion a year in cash flow alone.</p>
        <p>When it comes to examining Sony's health, the PlayStation, its biggest profit driver in recent history, looms large. The PlayStation 2 remains the biggest seller among all gaming systems.</p>
        <p>But launch delays, cost overruns and some so-so reviews for the PlayStation 3 have stung the company. With the roaring success of Nintendo's new Wii console and the growth of Microsoft's Xbox, the PS3 will end up capturing a smaller share of the games console market than the PS2 has commanded, Mr. McPeake estimates.</p>
        <p>And Sony took a big gamble by building new Blu-Ray players into the PS3, which contributed to delays and higher prices. But while the high-definition DVD wars are far from over, it already seems impossible that Blu-Ray will go the way of the Betamax.</p>
        <p>Sony's efforts to have most of the major studios commit exclusively to the Blu-Ray has given it a considerable early lead in terms of both players available and DVDs sold, compared with its rival, HD DVD.</p>
        <p>The idea of putting Blu-Ray machines inside the PS3, and throwing in a free hi-def disc of ''Talladega Nights'' or ''Casino Royale,'' is just one example of how Mr. Stringer -- and I say this haltingly -- may be starting to demonstrate how Sony's diverse businesses may prove the rationale for their co-existence under one corporate roof. (This despite the company's investment in MGM and a Sony-BMG music venture, which generated more headaches for Mr. Stringer last year.)</p>
        <p>At the very least, the ''Sony United'' strategy of Mr. Stringer has proved that some of the engineers, marketers and Hollywood types can actually talk to one another. And the Sony Pictures Entertainment division, aided by everything from the Spider-Man film franchise to television shows like ''The King of Queens,'' has carried its weight financially for the company of late after being a black hole and distraction for past regimes.</p>
        <p>The company has made clear that if the market continues to assign no value to the $7-billion-a-year entertainment businesses it will look at doing an initial public offering.</p>
        <p>And it has said that it intends at some point to sell part of its financial services business, which has little profile outside Japan but has helped the company through some lean years.</p>
        <p>More dramatically, in the last two years, Sony has cut jobs and costs and exited businesses with the goal of increasing profit margins to a modest 5 percent by this time next year.</p>
        <p>ON many fronts, the company's evolution beyond Japan has been crucial. The pop in Sony's share price has coincided with a considerable shift in its investor base to the United States, which is also its biggest sales market. Today, 14 of the company's top 20 shareholders are now based in the United States and more than half its shares are held outside of Japan. This was not the case two years ago.</p>
        <p>''My sense is that a lot of work is being done in the U.S. but they don't want to shine a spotlight on it and make it seem like a U.S. takeover and offend the Japanese,'' said Mark Stahlman, an analyst at Gartner.</p>
        <p>A stock that is at $53.48 is a clear victory for Mr. Stringer's tenure so far, but the price is only a few ticks above where it stood a decade ago and a very long way from its $150-plus peak in the giddy heights of early 2000.</p>
        <p>The story line here is not so much one of good to great -- to borrow the business book paradigm -- as of middling to better. But something tells me that Mr. Stringer will take it.</p>
        <p>MEDIA FRENZY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
