<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Donny Was the World</title>
    <meta content="29osmo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/thecity/29osmo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK OBSERVED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Osmond, Donny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolitzer, Meg</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Friendship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Friendship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E4DA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Donny Was the World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When Donny Was the World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEG WOLITZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wolitzer, Meg</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Novelist Meg Wolitzer New York Observed essay on infatuation with and rejection of Donny Osmond and his brothers when she was 12 and later fascination with sophisticated New York City teens; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GOD, those city kids were sophisticated -- they were like the Bloomsbury group with acne. I had met them over the summer at an arts camp in the Berkshires called Indian Hill, and now they were my friends.</p>
        <p>On weekends I sometimes took the Long Island Rail Road into Manhattan to meet them, and we'd hang out at someone's town house on a shaded street in the Village, or in one of the Beaux-Arts monoliths along Central Park West. Occasionally we'd saunter in a loose pack to an art-house movie theater like the Thalia -- this was the 1970s -- where we would watch a beautiful print of Ingmar Bergman's ''Persona,'' staring intently at Liv Ullmann's face as she underwent a protracted Swedish nervous breakdown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The girl from the suburbs doted on the Osmonds. Then she met the young sophisticates from the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GOD, those city kids were sophisticated -- they were like the Bloomsbury group with acne. I had met them over the summer at an arts camp in the Berkshires called Indian Hill, and now they were my friends.</p>
        <p>On weekends I sometimes took the Long Island Rail Road into Manhattan to meet them, and we'd hang out at someone's town house on a shaded street in the Village, or in one of the Beaux-Arts monoliths along Central Park West. Occasionally we'd saunter in a loose pack to an art-house movie theater like the Thalia -- this was the 1970s -- where we would watch a beautiful print of Ingmar Bergman's ''Persona,'' staring intently at Liv Ullmann's face as she underwent a protracted Swedish nervous breakdown.</p>
        <p>''The contrast was just gorgeous,'' someone would pronounce afterward over hamburgers at Maxwell's Plum, the popular Art Nouveau restaurant on the East Side, and we'd all nod. Sitting in the middle of the crowd in my Indian-print blouse and my Earth Shoes, I felt thrilled to be there.</p>
        <p>I also felt like a fake. Although I thought I appeared as arty and sophisticated as any of the city kids, with my copy of the play ''Marat/Sade'' tucked under my arm and snippets of Charles Ives's ''Unanswered Question'' in my head as if it were a catchy tune I'd heard on Cousin Brucie's radio show, the truth was that until not long before we'd met, I was nothing like these kids.</p>
        <p>I lived in a suburb about an hour away from the wilds of the city with its skyscrapers and art-house theaters and parks that were conducive to acting out scenes from ''Marat/Sade,'' not to mention Pirandello's ''Six Characters in Search of an Author.'' It had been only a few years earlier that my school friends and I had gone to one another's houses in the afternoon to eat HoHos, tell goony riddles from a joke book we'd ordered from Scholastic's Tab book club and practice the routines we had worked out from various Osmond Brothers albums.</p>
        <p>Though there were five Osmonds, there were only four girls. Our names were Meg, Barbara, Laura and Cynthia, so we referred to ourselves by the acronym ''Mebalacy.''</p>
        <p>Oh, the uncoolth of it all! In someone's suburban den we practiced the choreographed routines we'd seen the Osmonds perform on Glen Campbell's television show on CBS. Because VCRs were relatively new and no one we knew had one, we couldn't slow down the action and get a close look at the footwork. The technique wasn't exactly high Twyla Tharp, but it was complex, and the harmonies had a barbershop flavor lurking beneath that '70s synthesizer. I loved the Osmonds, but more than that, I wanted to be one of them.</p>
        <p>Once in a while on Friday nights in Cynthia's furnished basement, we performed our routine for neighborhood kids. This was long before the term karaoke had entered the lexicon, but with the real Osmonds singing on low volume in the background, we sang and danced, positioning our hands in classic fisted, mike-holding position. As Donny, I knew just how to tilt my head and lower my eyes. All of this was done without any irony.</p>
        <p>What finally ended all this was a prank: One of the girls told the rest of us that we'd been invited to audition for Glen Campbell's show. The fact that we believed her even for an instant demonstrates the kind of 12-year-old fugue state we must have been in.</p>
        <p>Once the truth was revealed, there were no more Friday night performances. I moved on to a new and moodier group of friends, and my tastes in the arts shifted and expanded. A few summers later, when I met those uber-sophisticated city kids, I began to listen to Benjamin Britten, Scott Joplin's ''Treemonisha'' and whatever else they directed me toward. I also performed alongside them in a series of profound if somewhat unintelligible plays, including a theatrical version of T. S. Eliot's poetry in which I played ''Hollow Man No. 3.''</p>
        <p>I rarely think about my brief infatuation with the Osmonds, but a few weeks ago, when I heard that Donny would be performing ''Love Songs of the '70s'' at Feinstein's at Loews Regency, I thought I should go. My friend Deborah Copaken Kogan, another writer who had long ago been an Osmonds fan, agreed to come with me.</p>
        <p>The room had a slightly female hum to it, for there was an unusually high concentration of single-sex tables. Right beside us sat a group of very friendly women, all named Karen, who lived in different cities and had met on the message boards of Donny.com. One of them said she had won a sweepstakes a few years earlier sponsored by I Can't Believe It's Not Butter and that, as a prize, Donny came to her house and was very nice and stayed longer than he had to.</p>
        <p>When Donny walked onto the stage, the women around us lifted their cameras in one swift and elegant movement. He looked a great deal like the former boy version of himself, except fully masculinized, and his voice, of course, was far deeper than the Vienna Boys' Choir upper-register sound I'd remembered. He had made the voyage to adulthood intact and impressive, not in appalling if fascinating tatters like his former brother-band competitor Michael Jackson.</p>
        <p>It would have been easy to be distracted by the phenomenon of a '70s teen idol coming upon the force field of his aging fans, but in fact the show was absorbing and often stirring. Although the song choices fell fully under the easy-listening rubric, Deb and I were struck by his beautiful voice and the unexpectedly emotional atmosphere in the room.</p>
        <p>Was it just because we were remembering how young we'd been when we had first heard him and his brothers, and how shape-shifting and bewildering time is? I kept imagining myself back in Cynthia's basement with my hand curled around an imaginary microphone, and how not long afterward, embarrassed about the cornball nature of the enterprise, I had so easily thrown off that side of myself.</p>
        <p>BUT really, four girls acting out a fantasy of being teen male idols has a certain significance. As I remembered the pleasure I'd felt at pretending to be Donny Osmond, I realized that we had demonstrated a surprisingly transparent kind of role-playing and a desire for power.</p>
        <p>I also realized that my early conception of the city as a purely sophisticated, bohemian backdrop was incomplete. Living here allows and even demands that you accept a multiplicity of tastes and longings. It's not true that here you must only be an ineffably urban person. To think of yourself that way is to live as though you're under continuous observation, which, in a place so distracted and full of forward motion, probably isn't true.</p>
        <p>In some respects, our all-girl Osmond Brothers show back in that basement was more transgressive than the rendition of ''Marat/Sade'' I'd be acting in only a few years later. Maybe the city kids would have actually approved. Maybe I could have told them all about it while we ate dinner at Maxwell's Plum after watching ''The Bicycle Thief'' at the Museum of Modern Art. And maybe everyone would have listened.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK OBSERVED Meg Wolitzer's new novel, ''The Ten-Year Nap,'' will be published next spring.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Meg Wolitzer's new novel, ''The Ten-Year Nap,'' will be published next spring.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
