<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Walling Off Your Enemies: The Long View</title>
    <meta content="29wein" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/weekinreview/29wein.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070506T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IDEA &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Petraeus, David H</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Maliki, Nuri Kamal al-</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thompson, Robert I</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Elkins, Caroline</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E2D7123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Walling Off Your Enemies: The Long View</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Walling Off Your Enemies: The Long View</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM WEINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiner, Tim</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE rulers of China spent 2,000 years building and rebuilding the world's greatest wall, to keep out invaders from the north. The Roman emperor Hadrian built battlements across Britain against the barbarians 19 centuries ago. The Soviets cut Berlin in two; that wall came down when the will to defend it faded. The Israelis now build barricades against the Palestinians, guarding against an Arab population bomb as well as suicide bombers.</p>
        <p>These are walls of war -- the architecture of long struggle. Hard to erect, harder to maintain, they are never stronger than the political skill of their designers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whether in modern-day Baghdad or ancient China, walls of war are the architecture of long struggle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE rulers of China spent 2,000 years building and rebuilding the world's greatest wall, to keep out invaders from the north. The Roman emperor Hadrian built battlements across Britain against the barbarians 19 centuries ago. The Soviets cut Berlin in two; that wall came down when the will to defend it faded. The Israelis now build barricades against the Palestinians, guarding against an Arab population bomb as well as suicide bombers.</p>
        <p>These are walls of war -- the architecture of long struggle. Hard to erect, harder to maintain, they are never stronger than the political skill of their designers.</p>
        <p>Last week, thousands of people in Baghdad were uniting against a wall dividing them. Twelve feet high, it separates Sunnis and Shiites in the Adhamiya district of northern Baghdad, and it is part of the American military's fight against the Iraqi insurgency. Adhamiya is becoming one of many walled and gated communities in Iraq; the Americans have been building them for months. Gen. David Petraeus, the counterinsurgency specialist who leads the American forces in Iraq, said on Wednesday that he was ''walling off neighborhoods'' in order ''to control population and to provide security.'' He spoke of ''the concrete caterpillar that grows 500 meters every night'' in Baghdad.</p>
        <p>The idea is the essence of counterinsurgency: to separate the good guys from the bad guys, and to impose political will to convert or defeat the enemy. History suggests that it can work -- but that it takes many years and a heavy hand.</p>
        <p>The British are the prime example of success in modern times. At the close of their colonial era, after World War II, they isolated the ethnic Chinese population in Malaya, building ''new villages'' and herding hundreds of thousands of people into them. In doing so, they controlled the population within the walls -- actually, fences that included barbed wire -- and attacked Chinese insurgents outside them.</p>
        <p>''If the insurgency is countrywide,'' wrote Sir Robert Thompson, the architect of the idea of the ''new villages,'' ''it is impossible to tackle it offensively in every area. It must be accepted that in certain areas only a holding operation can be conducted.'' Hence the concept of creating walls or fences to separate friends from foes.</p>
        <p>In practice, the British demoralized and defeated enemies of the empire, though thousands of noncombatants died in the process. The moral hazards of their methods seem fairly plain today, and therefore difficult to duplicate. But in its time, Malaya was counted as a famous victory, and the land of present-day Malaysia is peaceful and relatively prosperous.</p>
        <p>''The results speak for themselves,'' notes Lt. Col. Wade Markel, a United States Army strategist, writing last year in Parameters, the quarterly journal of the Army War College: by 1957, the number of insurgents had declined sharply -- to perhaps 200 active combatants from an estimated 8,000 five years earlier -- allowing a new Malay government to take shape.</p>
        <p>''Short-term, it was a success,'' said Caroline Elkins, a Pulitzer Prize-winning historian whose field is the twilight of British empire. ''But what happens within these walls? The British argued that they were winning hearts and minds. But behind the walls, it's all about forcing people to cooperate.''</p>
        <p>Winning the allegiance of civilians within the walls required a strong political will and a degree of violence, she said, and ''the British were much more brutal than the Americans were willing to be in Vietnam.''</p>
        <p>Sir Robert transplanted his theory to South Vietnam, and American advisers in Saigon embraced it in 1962. But they were never skillful enough -- or tough enough -- to sort out their foes, the Vietcong insurgents, from their South Vietnamese friends behind the stockade fences of their ''strategic hamlets.''</p>
        <p>When an American-backed coup took down the Saigon government in November 1963, the hamlets strategy went with it. The Americans could not clear and hold the jungle, and within a year the Vietcong were using roadside bombs, car bombs, and suicide bombers in Saigon. Half a million American troops followed.</p>
        <p>Forty years later, after building billion-dollar bases walled off from Iraqis, American officers are embracing the strategies and tactics of counterinsurgency under the new Baghdad security plan, which adapts concepts used in the countrysides of Malaya and Vietnam to Iraq's urban centers.</p>
        <p>Building concrete walls in Baghdad and controlling gated communities across Iraq is a crucial part of that plan. In the near future, identity cards or internal passports may be issued in an effort to isolate the enemy in Baghdad, as has been done with some success in the embattled city of Falluja.</p>
        <p>General Petraeus, who has said many times in many ways that this war cannot be won with firepower alone, may serve as the late-colonial British governor-generals once did, trying to impose order on chaos with a mix of force and social engineering -- trying ''to stitch together the fabric of society that was so torn,'' as he said Thursday, while building more and more walls to filter out the infiltrators.</p>
        <p>His commanders know that the loyalties of the people of Iraq are the battlefield where the war will be won or lost. The officers have been reading the classics of counterinsurgency, especially the work of David Galula, a French military officer who fought Algerian rebels in their war of independence 50 years ago. Though the French failed there, Galula's insights still resonate.</p>
        <p>''If we distinguish between people and rebels, then we have a chance,'' he wrote. But that is only a start: ''Political, social, economic and other reforms, however much they ought to be wanted and popular, are inoperative when offered while the insurgent still controls the population.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''So intricate is the interplay between political and military actions that they cannot be tidily separated; on the contrary, every military move has to be weighed with regard to its political effects.''</p>
        <p>This is where the Adhamiya wall may have undermined itself. Many hundreds of residents protested in the streets against the wall last week, and their anger flowed from more than the traffic jams the wall had created. The imam of the district's main mosque called it ''the beginning of a huge plan intended to divide Baghdad ethnically and according to sect.''</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki said it reminded people of ''other walls.'' Rightly or wrongly, some Iraqis compared it to the Berlin Wall and the barrier that Israel has built against the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>To date, more than 3,000 American soldiers, 3,500 Iraqi soldiers, and 4,500 Iraqi policemen have died in this war. They have won many battles, but they have not held many battlefields long enough to keep peace, provide security, or establish enough trust to rebuild a shattered society. It will be months before anyone knows if the new strategy will work. But it seems unlikely that any wall can last too long with enemies on both sides.</p>
        <p>IDEA &amp; TRENDS</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 6, 2007, Sunday  A picture caption last Sunday with an article about the use of walls in the history of warfare misstated the length of time the Berlin Wall lasted. It fell after 28 years, not 18, having stood from Aug. 1961 to Nov. 1989.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 6, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption last Sunday with an article about the use of walls in the history of warfare misstated the length of time the Berlin Wall lasted. It fell after 28 years, not 18, having stood from Aug. 1961 to Nov. 1989.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
