<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Desperado Housewife</title>
    <meta content="29lives.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="70" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/magazine/29lives.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Lives"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EED8173EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Desperado Housewife</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Desperado Housewife</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lisa Carver</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carver, Lisa</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For me, getting married has always been like throwing up. I've done it as alone as possible, feeling sick, drastic and doomed. My first one was before a justice of the peace in Philadelphia. I was 19 years old, marrying a 35-year-old Frenchman. I wore my work apron from Kelly &amp; Cohen's diner. We did it between shifts. We did it for our twin, tremulous hearts that somehow reached through age, country and political differences to touch each other. We moved to Paris. He was a composer and a real live Communist. I felt that because I loved him so much, and knew myself so little, I would have to make myself his enemy, his opposite, or else be swallowed whole. For the next two years, my obsession with him grew, and so did my need to see myself as separate from him, until finally all there was to do was leave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not from that day forward, but from this or, rather, this day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For me, getting married has always been like throwing up. I've done it as alone as possible, feeling sick, drastic and doomed. My first one was before a justice of the peace in Philadelphia. I was 19 years old, marrying a 35-year-old Frenchman. I wore my work apron from Kelly &amp; Cohen's diner. We did it between shifts. We did it for our twin, tremulous hearts that somehow reached through age, country and political differences to touch each other. We moved to Paris. He was a composer and a real live Communist. I felt that because I loved him so much, and knew myself so little, I would have to make myself his enemy, his opposite, or else be swallowed whole. For the next two years, my obsession with him grew, and so did my need to see myself as separate from him, until finally all there was to do was leave.</p>
        <p>For years I tried out various boyfriends, places, religions, politics and lifestyles. When I first met future Husband No. 2, I was mesmerized by what he was not. He did not hate and fight God and state and the patriarch. Attractive, reliable, middle-class, he was inexplicable to me. When he asked me to marry him, I said yes for what I thought he could give my son, who was 4 years old: stability, faithfulness, normalcy. I would have said yes to him anyway, even without my son, because to know better, to avoid a mistake, wasn't high on my list of qualities to aspire to.</p>
        <p>We married on a tiny, rocky island in upstate New York in a storm at dusk. I shivered in the rain while the groom looked solemn and right. But nothing else was right: no white dress, no guests, no flowers, no doves. Order of any kind -- tradition, a planned life, even a neat room -- strikes me as suspicious. Having been raised with chaos and abandonment, that's the only life that looks real to me. So I made no arrangements. I guess I thought that by being haphazard and isolated and gloomy, by doing the wedding ceremony all wrong, I was unjinxing the marriage, or at least freeing it up and freeing myself from becoming ''a married woman.'' And it worked. Both my marriages were open. When I fooled around on No. 2 with someone else, I didn't take off my wedding ring. I was vaguely dissatisfied with the arrangement, but I expected to be.</p>
        <p>Then one night, six years into our marriage, we were sitting on the couch and I told him how lonely I was. He said he felt the same. It was the first conversation we'd had in a long time. I think we were able to talk instead of argue because we both knew that this was the end. There was nothing to struggle against anymore. We didn't argue about money or sex, fixable problems if you just go on ''Dr. Phil.'' We argued about what we were arguing about, and you can never bring that to a conclusion because there's no beginning or middle. All you can do, when you see it, is to disengage your hooks from each other's bones, turn away and start walking. Eventually, I lost the house. Our children felt adrift. My divorce dismantled every structure that marriage had put over our heads to protect us.</p>
        <p>Before all that happened, while I was still married, I was talking on the computer with a fellow across the country in even worse straits than I was about to fall into. (Yes, I know, I'm totally sleazy.) He was already divorced, he once spent five days in jail, his guitar was in hock and some guy wanted to kill him. He had left everything behind in the town that was home to the guy, and to the ex-wife, who, for unrelated reasons, also wanted to kill him, and moved to the desert. I can't say exactly why everybody wanted to do him harm, but it must have been the same thing -- somehow -- that made me want to join my life to his ragged, wide-open one. He was the antithesis of everything I'd tried to become by marrying No. 2.</p>
        <p>When we got together two years ago, there was nothing for me to hide or change or try defensively to explain. We were happy, and my kids were happy. I didn't ask him to get a job and behave; he just did. He didn't ask me not to ask things of him; I just didn't. I know it looks bad. But I also know how bad my good-looking marriage actually was. Not that he doesn't irritate me, but you know, I irritate myself. When my mood passes, I just forget how infuriating he is instead of remembering and counting and measuring what this person has done to me and what he owes me and looking for new ways to explain his deficit to him.</p>
        <p>He never asked me to marry him; we have both just assumed that it will happen and that a bunch of people will be there when it does and that I won't be throwing up. I don't feel bad at all that this will be my third marriage. Sometimes you have to try out both coasts before you decide Ohio is the place for you. And even an anxiety-ridden, lonely monster doesn't have to spend her entire life under a rock, all curled up and hissing.</p>
        <p>Lives Lisa Carver is the author of ''Dancing Queen'' and ''Drugs Are Nice.'' This essay is adapted from a contribution to ''Altared,'' an anthology about weddings due out next month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lisa Carver is the author of ''Dancing Queen'' and ''Drugs Are Nice.'' This essay is adapted from a contribution to ''Altared,'' an anthology about weddings due out next month.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
