<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everybody's a Liberal</title>
    <meta content="Lind.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/Lind.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843539"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Freedom's Power: The True Force of Liberalism (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everybody's a Liberal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Everybody’s a Liberal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL LIND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lind, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FREEDOM'S POWER</p>
        <p>The True Force of Liberalism.</p>
        <p>By Paul Starr.</p>
        <p>276 pp. Basic Books. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul Starr grounds liberalism in a centuries-old tradition, not interest-group politics or academic theory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FREEDOM'S POWER</p>
        <p>The True Force of Liberalism.</p>
        <p>By Paul Starr.</p>
        <p>276 pp. Basic Books. $26.</p>
        <p>Since the 1960s, political debate in the United States has been dominated by ideologies of the right: fusionist conservatism, libertarianism, the religious right, neoconservatism. Center-left political thought, when it has not simply rationalized the demands of Democratic Party constituencies, has tended to be academic and remote from politics. In recent years, however, center-left intellectuals including Bruce Ackerman, William Galston, John E. Schwarz and Michael Tomasky have sought to define a body of principles that could inform a practical liberal politics. The newest addition to this literature, Paul Starr's ''Freedom's Power: The True Force of Liberalism,'' is a brilliant and ambitious attempt to provide a public philosophy for 21st-century American liberalism.</p>
        <p>Starr is a Pulitzer Prize-winning sociologist, a co-founder of The American Prospect and a professor of sociology and public affairs at Princeton. In ''Freedom's Power,'' he treats American liberalism as a variant of a common Anglo-American liberal tradition stretching from the 17th century to the present. The first phase of the tradition was ''constitutional liberalism,'' whose defining moments were the Glorious Revolution in Britain in 1688 and the American Revolution in 1776. Constitutional liberalism promoted ''the fundamental principles of constitutional government and individual rights shared by modern liberals and conservatives alike, though often differently interpreted by them.'' What Starr calls ''democratic liberalism,'' beginning in the late 19th century, builds on constitutional liberalism while incorporating previously excluded groups like women and minorities, and giving the government an important if limited role in managing industrial capitalism for the benefit of all. ''The relationship between liberalism in these two phases,'' he writes, ''has been predominantly cumulative: while rejecting laissez-faire economic policy, modern democratic liberalism continues to take the broader tradition of constitutional liberalism as its foundation.''</p>
        <p>Starr performs a great service by insisting that Anglo-American democratic liberalism is the left wing of classical liberalism, not, like European social democracy, the right wing of democratic socialism. A self-described liberal hawk who opposed the Iraq war but supported the Persian Gulf war of 1991 and the war in Afghanistan, Starr does an equally great service by putting war and state-making at the center of the history of Anglo-American liberalism, arguing that it is precisely because of their liberalism that liberal states have repeatedly bested autocracies: ''The lesson drawn by the generation of internationalists that followed Wilson was that it was possible to join a realist's grasp of power politics to a liberal vision of international order.''</p>
        <p>''American liberals do not have to invent something new or import a philosophical tradition from abroad,'' Starr writes. His version of Anglo-American liberalism, however, is as much British as American: 1776 completes 1688, and American Progressives of the 1900s are somewhat less successful versions of their contemporaries and role models, British New Liberals. Starr discusses British politicians like William Gladstone, Joseph Chamberlain, J. A. Hobson and Leonard Hobhouse but does not even mention William Jennings Bryan and needs only a paragraph to dismiss American Populists as irrelevant agrarians.</p>
        <p>Starr prefers the term ''liberal'' to ''progressive,'' which some to the left of center use to evade the stigma that the right has attached to the so-called L-word. Even so, Starr's version of democratic liberalism echoes many themes of early-20th-century American Progressivism, including enthusiasm for professionalism in public administration and journalism. Starr's major policy proposal, a vague ''New Deal for the Young'' or ''Young America program'' resembling the G.I. Bill, is a version of national service, a capital-P Progressive idea going back to William James that has inspired the G.I. Bill, the Peace Corps and AmeriCorps.</p>
        <p>A genealogy of American liberalism that includes upper-middle-class Progressives, civil libertarians, civil rights activists, organized labor and even British New Liberals, while air-brushing American Populists out of the picture, may provide a usable past for the post-1960s liberal coalition, which lost the white working class and rural Americans -- but only at the price of historical accuracy. The 1892 Populist Party platform, which among other things endorsed the progressive income tax and praised organized labor, declared that ''the power of government -- in other words, of the people -- should be expanded ... as rapidly and as far as the good sense of an intelligent people and the teaching of experience shall justify, to the end that oppression, injustice and poverty shall eventually cease in the land.''</p>
        <p>This was nothing if not part of the transition in the United States from laissez-faire constitutional liberalism to the democratic liberalism that Starr defends. He argues persuasively that ''liberalism has no way to advance without a majoritarian politics.'' Whether an American liberalism that disdains populism can create a lasting political majority remains to be seen.</p>
        <p>Still, if details of Starr's grand synthesis can be questioned, his argument for rooting American liberalism in an evolving, centuries-old Anglo-American liberal tradition, rather than in interest-group politics or academic theories, is persuasive. ''Freedom's Power'' is an impressive achievement that deserves to be pondered by the critics of contemporary American liberalism no less than by its supporters.</p>
        <p>Michael Lind, the Whitehead senior fellow at the New America Foundation, is the author of ''The American Way of Strategy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Lind, the Whitehead senior fellow at the New America Foundation, is the author of ''The American Way of Strategy.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
