<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When It Comes to Yield, How High Is Too High?</title>
    <meta content="29divi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/business/yourmoney/29divi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Century Financial Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">ConAgra Foods Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFDA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When It Comes to Yield, How High Is Too High?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When It Comes to Yield, How High Is Too High?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J. ALEX TARQUINIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tarquinio, J Alex</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THROUGHOUT the fall and winter, one stock consistently topped the list of the highest-yielding shares among the 1,900 companies tracked by Morningstar Inc. For months, it was yielding more than 20 percent.</p>
        <p>That stock was New Century Financial, the troubled subprime mortgage lender. Long before the company entered bankruptcy this month, ''the yield was definitely flashing a red light with a horn attached saying, 'Stay away from this stock,' '' said Josh Peters, an equity strategist at Morningstar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Strategists say that many signs, like erratic dividend histories or a high payout ratio, may indicate that a stock’s dividends are on shaky ground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THROUGHOUT the fall and winter, one stock consistently topped the list of the highest-yielding shares among the 1,900 companies tracked by Morningstar Inc. For months, it was yielding more than 20 percent.</p>
        <p>That stock was New Century Financial, the troubled subprime mortgage lender. Long before the company entered bankruptcy this month, ''the yield was definitely flashing a red light with a horn attached saying, 'Stay away from this stock,' '' said Josh Peters, an equity strategist at Morningstar.</p>
        <p>Strategists say that many signs -- like erratic dividend histories or a high payout ratio, which is the percentage of earnings that a company pays as dividends -- may indicate that a stock's dividends are on shaky ground.</p>
        <p>But yield can be a good place to start. Mr. Peters, who edits a monthly newsletter, Morningstar Dividend Investor, said that an extremely high stock yield could offer one of the easiest ways to spot a company on the verge of financial distress. And, of course, there are less dire situations than bankruptcy. A dividend cut by a company, for example, can be enough to send many shareholders toward the exits.</p>
        <p>Yield is a function of two factors: a stock's historical dividend payments and its current share price. Some stocks have high current yields because their share prices have fallen, which can indicate that many investors expect future dividend payments to decline.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peters said that a yield did not have to climb into the double-digit terrain -- as New Century Financial's did -- to make him nervous. ''A food company with a yield of 6 percent, that's pretty scary,'' he said. Although he said there were no hard-and-fast benchmarks for each industry, ''the main thing is that a stock does not have a yield that's way out of line with its peers.''</p>
        <p>If an investor decides that a stock's yield is generous -- but not overly so -- the next step is to determine whether the company has ever cut its dividend. Mr. Peters said investors should have less confidence in a company where dividends have fluctuated widely, based on quarterly results.</p>
        <p>Any break from a long-established pattern may also be a warning sign that a dividend could be cut. For example, Mr. Peters pointed to ConAgra Foods, which is based in Omaha and did not raise its dividend in 2005 -- after 30 consecutive years of dividend increases. Once that happened, Mr. Peters said he was not surprised when ConAgra then cut its quarterly dividend to 18 cents a share in March 2006, from 27.25 cents. He added that he thought ConAgra's new dividend was sustainable. (Shortly after cutting its dividend last year, the company announced that it would focus more on its packaged-food business.)</p>
        <p>Another clue about a possibly wobbly dividend may be found in a stock's payout ratio. Typically, ratios vary considerably among industries. For example, the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index has an average payout ratio of 30 percent. The telecommunications stocks in the index have the highest average ratio, with 64 percent of earnings going to dividends, while the technology stocks in the index have the lowest, at 15 percent.</p>
        <p>Sam Stovall, the chief investment strategist at S.&amp; P., recommends picking stocks with payout ratios that are either in line with or a little below the average for their industry.</p>
        <p>''If you're comparing two similar stocks with the same yield -- and one them has a lower payout ratio -- then it has more room to raise the dividend'' and ''more of a cushion to protect the dividend if earnings fall,'' Mr. Stovall said. ''It's like leaving room for milk in your coffee.''</p>
        <p>Of course, companies in some industries -- from cigarette makers to electric utilities to land-line phone service providers -- have traditionally paid big portions of their profits as dividends. ''They tend to be fairly mature industries that are plowing less of their earnings back into growth,'' he said.</p>
        <p>S.&amp; P. stock quality rankings can also help gauge the possible safety of dividends, Mr. Stovall said. S.&amp; P. stock analysts factor dividends into their rankings; they penalize stocks that have a history of cutting dividends and won't give a ranking above A-minus to a stock that doesn't pay any dividend.</p>
        <p>Strategists say payout ratios can sometimes be misleading indicators for cyclical stocks, like those of commodity producers. Relatively high dividends are an attraction of these stocks, so executives in these industries will strive to keep dividends stable throughout the cycles. That means payout ratios may be higher near the bottom of the earnings cycle and lower near the top, said Richard Bernstein, the chief United States strategist at Merrill Lynch. In that case, ''a very low payout ratio may be a sign that you're at the peak of the cycle,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Investors should also consider how yields and payout ratios are calculated, said Michael Metz, chief investment strategist at Oppenheimer &amp; Company. He pointed out that any extra dividends a company paid in the previous 12 months would be included in the yield calculations seen on financial Web sites. Although many big companies have a tradition of paying frequent special dividends -- as well as declared quarterly dividends -- he said investors should not count on these extra dividends from year to year.</p>
        <p>''The reason that it's an extra is that management is not sure whether the dividend can be maintained,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the moment, Mr. Metz is recommending large-capitalization stocks with a long history of raising dividends. ''They will usually do that at a very slow pace, slower than their rising earnings,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He says energy is now his favorite sector; he likes the shares of Exxon Mobil and Chevron.</p>
        <p>He also says he likes consumer staples stocks, another traditional hunting ground for dividend investors. ''They don't have enormous capital requirements,'' he said, ''so the earnings are really available for dividends and share buybacks.'' His recommended consumer staples stocks include Johnson &amp; Johnson, Coca-Cola and 3M.</p>
        <p>Finally, he said, some of the best dividend stocks may be found among big banks. He favors Bank of America and Citigroup.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Metz recommended avoiding some other sectors where investors have traditionally sought dividends -- including telecom, utilities and real estate investment trusts, or REITs -- because he said they were now too richly priced.</p>
        <p>Although digging through payout ratios and checking for previous cuts in dividends may seem daunting, strategists say investors who depend on dividend income would be well advised to do this homework. Otherwise, said Mr. Bernstein of Merrill Lynch, investors may be attracted to high-yielding stocks without understanding the risks. ''People can be just as greedy for income,'' he said, ''as they can be for capital appreciation.''</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
