<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Simple, Healthy And Easy on the Wallet</title>
    <meta content="29dinectCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29dinect.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/WEST HAVEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saray Turkish Restaurant (West Haven, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyness, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Simple, Healthy And Easy on the Wallet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Simple, Healthy and Easy on the Wallet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE LYNESS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyness, Stephanie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephanie Lyness reviews Saray Turkish Restaurant in West Haven, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT is it about Turkish food that makes it so consistently likable? It starts with its inherent simplicity -- we can count the usual seasonings on two hands and still have a few fingers left over. (Think of the bright taste of lemon and parsley, add the earthiness of chopped walnuts, the exotic sweet and sour of pomegranate molasses, and the astringency of ground sumac, and the cuisine comes into focus.)</p>
        <p>Or perhaps it is the essential health of the cuisine, with its grilled meats and seafood, platters of fresh salads, and meatless dishes. There is a sense of vibrancy and joy to the food that makes it a pleasure to keep coming back to.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saray Turkish Restaurant in West Haven prepares the kind of Turkish food that has a sense of vibrancy and joy that makes it a pleasure to keep coming back to.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT is it about Turkish food that makes it so consistently likable? It starts with its inherent simplicity -- we can count the usual seasonings on two hands and still have a few fingers left over. (Think of the bright taste of lemon and parsley, add the earthiness of chopped walnuts, the exotic sweet and sour of pomegranate molasses, and the astringency of ground sumac, and the cuisine comes into focus.)</p>
        <p>Or perhaps it is the essential health of the cuisine, with its grilled meats and seafood, platters of fresh salads, and meatless dishes. There is a sense of vibrancy and joy to the food that makes it a pleasure to keep coming back to.</p>
        <p>So I was pleased when a friend told me, a few months ago, about Saray, another Turkish restaurant -- the second that I am aware of -- on West Haven's Campbell Avenue. (The first is the Turkish Kebab House, a small dinerlike place that I rated ''very good'' last August). As it turns out, the two are related: Saray's owner, Sammy Kuru, was previously part owner of the Kebab House, which he left to open Saray in July 2006 with his brother.</p>
        <p>The menu is centered on kebabs and abetted by a selection of salads and traditional hot and cold starters. One evening we ordered cacik (a yogurt dip mixed with cucumber and spiked with lots of lemon) and the cold appetizer sampler platter, which included hummus, haydari (another yogurt dip), antep ezme (spicy, garlicky chopped tomatoes, peppers and onions cooked together) and a couple of eggplant salads -- all served with warm, puffy flatbread. These starters were so good that I have been tempted to order them every time.</p>
        <p>The hummus was particularly successful, dense but not oily, and seasoned with cumin, while the rich, smooth haydari was a welcome respite from the heat of the antep ezme. Luckily, we saved some of the haydari and the cacik for the main meal. They both complemented the kebabs beautifully.</p>
        <p>On another night I discovered the spicy burnt-orange-colored muhammara, a grainy-textured yogurt mixture with finely chopped walnuts and drizzled with pomegranate molasses, a potent, sweet-and-sour syrup made from the fruit. If you fall in love with the syrup, as I have, I'd also recommend the gavurdagi salad of chopped fresh tomato, garlic, green pepper, onion, parsley and walnuts, topped with a generous dousing of the molasses.</p>
        <p>The mevsim salad, another fine starter, features feta and a bouquet of fresh vegetables -- slivered red cabbage (pickled overnight in salt, lemon juice and vinegar), grated carrot, sliced cucumber and tomato -- on a generous bed of romaine lettuce seasoned with lemon. It was a better choice than the stuffed grape leaves, which lacked the pine nuts and seasonings noted on the menu.</p>
        <p>Next visit, we sampled some of the hot appetizers: crisp, phyllo-wrapped pastries stuffed with seasoned ground beef and cheese (sigara boregi and icli borek); mujver (soft, fried patties of grated zucchini); flat, lozenge-shaped falafel; and the Turkish ravioli called manti. My favorite was the delicate mujver (also available as an entree); the falafel were heavy, and the manti very light on filling.</p>
        <p>Saray makes a fabulous doner kebab, a mountain of spicy, marinated grilled lamb, the thin slices delectably crisp at the edges. Whole sea bass is perfectly grilled, served with a big salad. Almost as good are the kofte kebabs, flat patties of ground beef seasoned with parsley and onion, then grilled. All of the chicken kebabs on the grilled mixed chicken platter were impressive -- the chicken had more flavor and was more tender than kebabs I've had elsewhere.</p>
        <p>A confirmed nondessert person, I nonetheless couldn't resist Saray's homemade sweets, especially the kazandibi, a caramelized custard that tasted exquisitely of burnt sugar, and the sekerpare, cookies soaked in honey syrup.</p>
        <p>If you like the Turkish Kebab House, you will certainly like Saray. And if you are a stranger to Turkish cuisine, Saray is an excellent introduction. Where else would a sumptuous meal, beautifully prepared, cost about $20 per person?</p>
        <p>Saray Turkish Restaurant</p>
        <p>770 Campbell Avenue  West Haven  (203) 937-0707  www.saraykebab.com</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- The large room, with its central chandelier and wall-to-wall carpet, calls to mind a catering hall, though the Turkish rugs on the walls are beautiful (and many are for sale). There is live music on most Friday and Saturday evenings. Wheelchair access.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- A mix of couples, large groups and families (children's menu available). Staff is extremely hospitable.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Bring your own.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Entrees, $7.95 to $17.50. American Express not accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Mevsim salad, gavurdagi salad, appetizer sampler, cacik, muhammara, icli borek, sigara boregi, mujver, lahmacun; doner kebab, adana kebab, iskender kebab, kofte kebab, chicken adana kebab, chicken shish kebab, chicken kofte kebab, chicken steak kebab, grilled sea bass, savory pies, vegetable guvec; all desserts, but particularly kadayif, baklava, kazandibi and sekerpare.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Open Sunday to Thursday, 11 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 11 a.m. to midnight. Free parking in adjoining lot.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 29, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/WEST HAVEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
