<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Magnificent 'Seven'</title>
    <meta content="29artsnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29artsnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Paper Mill Playhouse (Millburn, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siegel, Naomi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, Scott</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Seven Brides for Seven Brothers (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Paper Mill Playhouse</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFD8153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Magnificent 'Seven'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Magnificent ‘Seven’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NAOMI SIEGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siegel, Naomi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Naomi Siegel reviews Paper Mill Playhouse revival of musical Seven Brides for Seven Brothers, directed by Scott Schwartz; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you're not convinced that the American regional theater community would be a vastly poorer place without the Paper Mill Playhouse, ''Seven Brides for Seven Brothers'' should make the case.</p>
        <p>The playhouse's spanking new show, produced in collaboration with regional theaters in Beverly, Mass., and Houston, is a humdinger. It shouts volumes about the contribution of this venerable arts institution, currently suffering a financial crisis, as guardian, champion and devoted revivalist of classic American musical theater. With ''Seven Brides,'' a cheering audience experiences firsthand the Paper Mill's role as a unique theater resource.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you’re not convinced that the American regional theater community would be a vastly poorer place without the Paper Mill Playhouse, “Seven Brides for Seven Brothers” should make the case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you're not convinced that the American regional theater community would be a vastly poorer place without the Paper Mill Playhouse, ''Seven Brides for Seven Brothers'' should make the case.</p>
        <p>The playhouse's spanking new show, produced in collaboration with regional theaters in Beverly, Mass., and Houston, is a humdinger. It shouts volumes about the contribution of this venerable arts institution, currently suffering a financial crisis, as guardian, champion and devoted revivalist of classic American musical theater. With ''Seven Brides,'' a cheering audience experiences firsthand the Paper Mill's role as a unique theater resource.</p>
        <p>From the rousing overture -- how many Broadway theaters can boast 17 first-class pit musicians? -- the production highlights what the Paper Mill does best. Under Scott Schwartz's stylish direction and with a cast of multitalented players who sing and dance their hearts out, the show offers nonstop pleasure. It does so in spite of a silly book by Lawrence Kasha and David Landry, mostly unmemorable music and lyrics by Gene de Paul and Johnny Mercer (supplemented by Al Kasha and Joel Hirschhorn), and enough macho brawling and female posturing to raise the hackles of those in the audience who are offended by gender stereotypes.</p>
        <p>Movie buffs remember ''Seven Brides'' as a hugely successful 1954 musical starring Howard Keel and Jane Powell. It was adapted for the stage in 1979 and presented briefly on Broadway in 1982. A television series of the same name, loosely based on the film, was yanked after one season. This current adaptation of ''Seven Brides'' features new orchestrations (Tom Helm is the spirited music director), spectacular settings of a pine-forested, snowy-peaked Oregon Territory, circa 1850, designed by Anna Louizos and lighted beautifully by Donald Holder, and charming, homespun period costumes by Jess Goldstein.</p>
        <p>Patti Colombo's choreography is outstanding. While referencing the legendary masters Agnes de Mille and Michael Kidd, she finds her own ballet-informed choreographic language that spins narrative as it delights the eye. The company rises to her challenge with a series of enchanting dance vignettes that are the high points of the show.</p>
        <p>The large cast is led by the vocally gifted Edward Watts and Michelle Dawson. Mr. Watts plays handsome, rugged Adam Pontipee, oldest of the unmarried Pontipee brothers, whose foray into town and ''three weeks' worth of courtin' in five minutes'' results in his marrying sassy Milly Bradon, played by Ms. Dawson. Milly pictures Adam's tiny cabin as a haven of peace and solitude; imagine her shock to discover his six unwashed, uncouth brothers living in the same tiny space.</p>
        <p>''I married seven brothers, became seven wives and seven mothers,'' she yowls in horror as the reality of her situation begins to hit home.</p>
        <p>The Pontipee brothers, each one grosser and wilder than the next, are played with rib-tickling results by Randy Bobish, Luke Longacre, Karl Warden, Travis Kelley, Eric Sciotto and Christian Delcroix. Mr. Sciotto is a hoot as the sixth offspring, the unfortunately named Frankincense (his mom ran out of alphabetically ordered Biblical names when it came to ''F''). Mr. Delcroix, as the youngest brother, Gideon, uses his voice to sweet effect in the lyric trio ''Love Never Goes Away.''</p>
        <p>With Milly taking over the day-to-day running of the household and teaching the brothers how to dance and court women, the stage is set for a second foray into town. This time six young village maidens are kidnapped to serve as six more brides, played fetchingly by Christina Rae Hedrick, Kate Marilley, Denise Payne, Margot De La Barre, Stephanie Fittro and Sarah Marie Jenkins.</p>
        <p>Only after many months of celibate segregation, under Milly's strict supervision, and an isolating avalanche of snow (again strikingly produced by Ms. Louizos), do the couples couple. Adam stops pouting over Milly's take-charge ways and recognizes her for the gem that she is.</p>
        <p>Since ''Seven Brides'' belongs to a musical theater genre where happy endings are a foregone conclusion, you can bet the farm that all will eventually turn out well. One wishes the Paper Mill's future were as assured.</p>
        <p>''Seven Brides for Seven Brothers'' is to run at the Paper Mill Playhouse, Brookside Drive, Millburn, at least through April 29. Information: (973) 376-4343 or at www.papermill.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
