<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ESSAY</title>
    <meta content="Alford.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/Alford.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Essay"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1305" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ESSAY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Literary Misblurbing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Henry Alford</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alford, Henry</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT happened to the Time magazine book critic Lev Grossman last October. Grossman says he was ''quite taken aback'' when he saw a full-page newspaper advertisement for Charles Frazier's novel ''Thirteen Moons'' that included a one-word quotation -- ''Genius'' -- attributed to Time. Grossman was confused because his review ''certainly didn't have that word.'' Eventually, he found it in a preview item he had written a few months earlier, which included the sentence ''Frazier works on an epic scale, but his genius is in the details.'' As Grossman put it, ''They plucked out the G-word.''</p>
        <p>It happened to me about 10 years ago. I had called David Sedaris's memoir ''Naked'' a ''tour-de-farce'' in a review in Newsday. Shortly thereafter, the publisher ran an ad in which my 600-word review had been boiled down to one phrase: ''tour de force.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While movie ads regularly doctor quotes and go a little crazy with the exclamation points, we’d like to think that the genteel world of book publishing is above all that. Think again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT happened to the Time magazine book critic Lev Grossman last October. Grossman says he was ''quite taken aback'' when he saw a full-page newspaper advertisement for Charles Frazier's novel ''Thirteen Moons'' that included a one-word quotation -- ''Genius'' -- attributed to Time. Grossman was confused because his review ''certainly didn't have that word.'' Eventually, he found it in a preview item he had written a few months earlier, which included the sentence ''Frazier works on an epic scale, but his genius is in the details.'' As Grossman put it, ''They plucked out the G-word.''</p>
        <p>It happened to me about 10 years ago. I had called David Sedaris's memoir ''Naked'' a ''tour-de-farce'' in a review in Newsday. Shortly thereafter, the publisher ran an ad in which my 600-word review had been boiled down to one phrase: ''tour de force.''</p>
        <p>Call it misblurbing. We'd like to think that while the quotations in movie ads regularly feature near-hysterical raves from marginal or even nonexistent critics, the genteel world of book publishing is above all that. But that doesn't seem to be the case, and some say publishers are becoming only more brazen. ''It's gotten much worse recently,'' said Po Bronson, the author of ''What Should I Do With My Life?'' and a member of the board of advisers of Consortium, a book distributor that specializes in independent publishers. ''There's a feeling of, 'Ah, no one's looking anymore.' '' The liberal editing of promotional verbiage can extend even to blurbs that publishers ask successful authors to provide for less-established ones. ''Usually they come back with changes and say, 'Is this O.K.?,' and it's very different from what I gave them,'' Bronson said.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the publishers don't even ask. On seeing the finished version of ''Never Eat Your Heart Out,'' a memoir by Judith Moore that he had blurbed, Bernard Cooper was surprised to see that his words of praise had been topped off with the hosanna ''Bravo!'' ''I certainly thought her book was deserving of a hearty exclamation,'' Cooper said. ''It's just that my saying 'Bravo!' is about as likely as my saying 'Touché!' It made me sound like someone who wears an ascot.''</p>
        <p>Most publishers insist they would never knowingly engage in misblurbing. ''We get tempted and we get desperate,'' Morgan Entrekin, the publisher of Grove/Atlantic, said. ''We publish over 100 books a year. I know we make mistakes. But we try to obey the rules.'' To him, that means not changing the wording or the meaning of reviews. Paul Slovak, the publisher of Viking, says part of what keeps the house honest is the desire to maintain ''good relationships'' with book reviewers. ''Michiko Kakutani wouldn't be happy if we pulled two words of praise out of a negative review,'' he said, referring to the chief book critic of The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Tom Perry, the associate publisher of Random House, which published ''Thirteen Moons,'' denies that the ''Genius'' quote was false advertising. ''We were being very short and punchy,'' he said. ''We have limited space.''</p>
        <p>Many who work in publishing argue for a hierarchy of unethical practice. Changing or adding words is the topmost offense. ''We don't do that,'' Slovak said. ''You shouldn't be lying.''</p>
        <p>Taking words or sentences out of context is one level down, while extracting the sole positive comment from a negative review is at the bottom, if it's an offense at all. ''We have a threshold here,'' Richard Nash, the publisher of Soft Skull Press, said. ''If it's a Bâ review or above, we'll look for the positive. But you can't take something that's a C+ or below and pull positive stuff out.''</p>
        <p>The novelist Laura Zigman, a former publicist at several houses, admits to getting a bit creative with the ellipses when excerpting reviews on her Web site. ''Sometimes you have to eliminate 9 or 10 words to find the praise in there,'' she said. ''I'll sit and think, 'Oooh, there's something salvageable.' You're demented. It gives you this weird sense of control and make-believe.'' Zigman suggests there should be a rule: ''Like, there has to be five words in a row from the review.''</p>
        <p>And then there is the question of creative punctuation. As the writer Sarah Vowell says, ''There must be something to be done about inserting exclamation points.''</p>
        <p>The ground rules here are, for some, unclear. ''There's latitude with exclamation points. Anything looks better with an exclamation point,'' said a prominent book editor who spoke on condition of anonymity because he didn't want to discredit his authors' books or books by others. Citing an instance in which an author was allowed to help in the selection of quotations for a paperback, the editor added: ''One author of mine did it, and I looked the other way. We're not violating the Geneva Conventions here.''</p>
        <p>Such an admission might earn a jaundiced laugh from Jonathan Yardley of The Washington Post, whose 1982 pan of Shirley Conran's ''Lace'' -- what Yardley called a ''schlock novel'' written with ''transparent and exquisite cynicism'' -- contained the following sentences: ''Conran knows all the names, brand and otherwise, and she certainly knows where and when to drop them. 'Lace' doesn't sink under the weight of them, it soars -- right up into the same stratosphere where you'll find 'Valley of the Dolls' and 'Scruples.' '' Sleepily pawing through the newspapers after the review ran, he was startled to come across an advertisement for the novel emblazoned with the following testimonial: '' 'It soars!' -- Jonathan Yardley, Washington Post.''</p>
        <p>''It was so transparent a distortion that all I could do was laugh,'' Yardley said. ''It amused me greatly. But it was incredibly stupid of Simon &amp; Schuster,'' Conran's publisher. Yardley subsequently wrote a column chastising Simon &amp; Schuster for potentially eroding the trust he had built with his readers: ''It is for this reason that I find myself distressed and angered by what I would otherwise dismiss, with a degree of amusement, as a cynically resourceful piece of salesmanship.''</p>
        <p>t least one reviewer has taken an even more direct approach to the problem. Christopher Lehmann-Haupt, The Times's daily reviewer for 32 years and now an author himself, recalls being quoted in an advertisement for a book from the publisher Donald I. Fine in a way he felt wasn't ''kosher.'' He ran into Fine at a party and told him, ''Back off if you want your books reviewed by me anymore.'' Lehmann-Haupt says, ''He got the message.''</p>
        <p>But what if the shoe is on the other foot? Would Lehmann-Haupt or Bronson object to a misblurb on the paperback of one of their books? ''I would register very strong objections,'' Lehmann-Haupt said. Bronson agreed. But the novelist Stephen Elliott tells a different story. When his first book, ''A Life Without Consequences,'' received barbed praise from The San Francisco Chronicle -- the review headline called the gritty, semiautobiographical look at homelessness ''required reading for social workers'' -- Elliott's publishers simply reduced the quotation to ''required reading.'' ''I had no problem with it,'' Elliott said, laughing. ''It was kind of a snarky review.''</p>
        <p>The author Joe Queenan, who says he's been misblurbed at least twice, pitches the ''What would you do?'' question even higher: ''If you were in a situation where you could get blurbs from GÃ1/4nter Grass, J. M. Coetzee and John Updike -- who'd all trashed your book -- would you do it? If Updike wrote, 'At least he kept it short,' would you go with it?''</p>
        <p>The book editor who wanted to protect his authors tells a story about a famous writer who was asked to provide a blurb for the debut novel of a friend's child. Despite the novel's poor quality, he offered up the pained encomium ''A classic first novel.''</p>
        <p>''I've always thought that was brilliant,'' the editor said. ''I would have taken that and reduced it to 'A classic!' '' Bravo.</p>
        <p>Essay Henry Alford is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Henry Alford is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
