<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Lie: Newark Seeks Cherry Tree Dominance</title>
    <meta content="29weeknjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cherry Trees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Essex County (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Branch Brook Park (Newark, NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE7D7153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Lie: Newark Seeks Cherry Tree Dominance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Politicians in Essex County, NJ, plan planting spree in Branch Brook Park in Newark that will allow them to claim hegemony over cherry tree world and its capital--Washington, DC--with 3,750 trees; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Branch Brook Park in Newark has a great many cherry trees, and in the spring, the 360-acre grounds erupt in a flurry of pink and white.</p>
        <p>But the nearly 2,000 cherry trees the park has are not nearly enough, according to local officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Branch Brook Park in Newark has a great many cherry trees, and in the spring, the 360-acre grounds erupt in a flurry of pink and white.</p>
        <p>But the nearly 2,000 cherry trees the park has are not nearly enough, according to local officials.</p>
        <p>And so, politicians in Essex County announced last week that they intend to embark on a planting spree that will allow them to claim hegemony over the cherry tree world and its capital -- Washington, with its 3,750 trees. The plan calls for an additional 3,000 trees to be planted in the park over the next few years.</p>
        <p>''It just brings attention here, not just to Essex County, but to New Jersey,'' said Joseph N. DiVincenzo Jr., the county executive, of the decision to add so many trees. ''That would be more than any other place in the United States.''</p>
        <p>But it's not just the number of cherry trees that Branch Brook has, supporters say. There are 20 different types in the park, compared with 16 in Washington, including Amanagowa, weeping Higan and the white-flowered Kwanzan. Barbara Bell Coleman, a co-chairwoman of the Branch Brook Park Alliance, a nonprofit group, said the broad trunks of the weeping trees ''are just as gorgeous as the delicate flowers when they bloom.''</p>
        <p>Since 1976, the park has held a Cherry Blossom Festival. About 50,000 attended this year's festivities, which ended last weekend, Mr. DiVincenzo said.</p>
        <p>The tree drive began when a survey conducted by the alliance last year found that the cherry tree population had declined to about 900. Since then, about 1,000 more trees have been planted, and another 1,000 will go in next spring.</p>
        <p>Backers intend to raise $300,000 in public donations for the additional 2,000 trees (each one costs about $250), with the county's Recreation and Open Space Trust Fund promising to match that amount. Officials hope to have all 5,000 trees in place by 2010. Commerce Bank has already promised $10,000.</p>
        <p>The park, conceived by the designer of Central Park, Frederick Law Olmsted, was created in 1895. The first of the cherry trees were donated in 1927, but their maximum lifespan is about 80 years.</p>
        <p>Of the plan, Ms. Bell Coleman said: ''Our county executive has a motto: 'Putting Essex County first.' So that's his competitive spirit coming through. And I say, God bless him. We just want to see the entire park restored.''</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
