<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: April 29, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Bestpaper.fiction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E4D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: April 29, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended April 14, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended April 14, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>05,06,64</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  FICTION</p>
        <p>1  4  TWO LITTLE GIRLS IN BLUE, by Mary Higgins Clark. (Pocket, $7.99.) A small girl communicates telepathically with her kidnapped twin.</p>
        <p>2  3  THE ROAD, by Cormac McCarthy. (Vintage, $14.95.) A father and son travel in post-apocalypse America.</p>
        <p>3  3  GONE, by Jonathan Kellerman. (Ballantine, $7.99.) Two acting students stage their own disappearance -- but then one of them is murdered; the psychologist-detective Alex Delaware investigates.</p>
        <p>4  2  AT RISK, by Patricia Cornwell. (Berkley, $7.99.) A Massachusetts state investigator applies DNA and other forensic techniques to a cold murder case.</p>
        <p>5  43  THE MEMORY KEEPER'S DAUGHTER, by Kim Edwards. (Penguin, $14.) A doctor's decision to secretly send his newborn daughter, who has Down syndrome, to an institution haunts everyone involved.</p>
        <p>6  2  HOT STUFF, by Janet Evanovich and Leanne Banks. (St. Martin's, $7.99.) When a bartender's apartment is ransacked, she turns to a former police officer for help -- then falls in love with him.</p>
        <p>7  3  MCKETTRICK'S HEART, by Linda Lael Miller. (HQN, $7.99.) A mysterious woman in Indian Rock rouses Keegan McKettrick's suspicions, and his heart.</p>
        <p>8  3  THE HARD WAY, by Lee Child. (Dell, $7.99.) When his wife is kidnapped, a man who deals in illegal soldiers turns to the former military cop Jack Reacher.</p>
        <p>9  3  PROMISE ME, by Harlan Coben. (Signet, $9.99.) Myron Bolitar becomes a suspect when a high school girl disappears after he drives her to a friend's house.</p>
        <p>10  7  JUDGE &amp; JURY, by James Patterson and Andrew Gross. (Warner, $9.99.) An aspiring actress and an F.B.I. agent join forces against a powerful mobster.</p>
        <p>11  6  MORNING COMES SOFTLY, by Debbie Macomber. (Avon, $7.99.) A reprint of a romance involving a librarian from Louisiana and a Montana rancher.</p>
        <p>12*  3  SECOND SIGHT, by Amanda Quick. (Jove, $7.99.) A photographer pretends to be the widow of an alchemist's descendant -- only to find that he's not actually dead, and that her ruse has put her in danger.</p>
        <p>13  1  Suite FRANÃAISE, by IrÃ</p>
        <p>ne Némirovsky. (Vintage, $14.95.) Two novellas, which came to light more than 50 years after the author's death at Auschwitz, about life in France under the Nazis.</p>
        <p>14  7  SNOW FLOWER AND THE SECRET FAN, by Lisa See. (Random House, $13.95.) The lives of two women in 19th-century China.</p>
        <p>15  113  THE KITE RUNNER, by Khaled Hosseini. (Riverhead, $15.95 and $14.) An Afghan-American returns to Kabul to learn how a childhood friend has fared.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1  12  THE MEASURE OF A MAN, by Sidney Poitier. (HarperSanFrancisco, $14.95.) The movie actor's spiritual autobiography.</p>
        <p>2  12  EAT, PRAY, LOVE, by Elizabeth Gilbert. (Penguin Books, $15.) A writer's yearlong journey in search of self takes her to Italy, India and Indonesia.</p>
        <p>3  66  THE GLASS CASTLE, by Jeannette Walls. (Scribner, $14.) The author recalls a bizarre childhood during which she and her siblings were constantly moved from one bleak place to another.</p>
        <p>4  2  BLINK, by Malcolm Gladwell. (Back Bay, $15.99.) The author of ''The Tipping Point'' explores the importance of hunch and instinct to the workings of the mind.</p>
        <p>5  9  THE YEAR OF MAGICAL THINKING, by Joan Didion. (Vintage, $13.95.) The author's attempts to come to terms with the death of her husband and the grave illness of their only daughter.</p>
        <p>6  60  NIGHT, by Elie Wiesel. (Hill &amp; Wang, $9.) The horrors of Auschwitz and Buchenwald.</p>
        <p>7  4  STUMBLING ON HAPPINESS, by Daniel Gilbert. (Vintage, $14.95.) A Harvard professor explores why people can't predict what will make them happy.</p>
        <p>8  25  90 MINUTES IN HEAVEN, by Don Piper with Cecil Murphey. (Revell, $12.99.) A minister describes the otherworldly experience he had after an accident.</p>
        <p>9  5  A MAN WITHOUT A COUNTRY, by Kurt Vonnegut. (Random House, $13.95.) Autobiographical essays and observations from the author of ''Slaughterhouse-Five.''</p>
        <p>10  139  THE TIPPING POINT, by Malcolm Gladwell. (Back Bay/Little, Brown, $14.95.) A journalist's study of social epidemics, otherwise known as fads.</p>
        <p>11  11  THREE CUPS OF TEA, by Greg Mortenson and David Oliver Relin. (Penguin Books, $15.) A former climber builds schools in Pakistan and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>12  21  THE PURSUIT OF HAPPYNESS, by Chris Gardner with Quincy Troupe and Mim Eichler Rivas. (Amistad/HarperCollins, $14.95.) Gardner's life story, from a grim childhood to homelessness to success.</p>
        <p>13  73  DREAMS FROM MY FATHER, by Barack Obama. (Three Rivers, $13.95.) The Democratic senator from Illinois reflects on life as the son of a black African father and white American mother.</p>
        <p>14  140  RUNNING WITH SCISSORS, by Augusten Burroughs. (Picador, $14 and $7.99.) In the 1970s, a young boy lives with a crazy psychiatrist in a squalid household.</p>
        <p>15  10  DON'T MAKE A BLACK WOMAN TAKE OFF HER EARRINGS, by Tyler Perry. (Riverhead, $12.95.) The man behind ''Diary of a Mad Black Woman'' muses on life.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous: Hardcover</p>
        <p>1  14  THE SECRET, by Rhonda Byrne. (Atria/Beyond Words, $23.95.) The law of attraction as a key to getting what you want.</p>
        <p>2  2  EVERYDAY PASTA, by Giada De Laurentiis. (Clarkson Potter, $32.50.) Recipes from the Italian cook and Food Network star.</p>
        <p>3  2  the weight loss cure ''they'' don't want you to know about, by Kevin Trudeau. (Alliance, $24.95.) Diet advice, centering on the role of hormones and supplements.</p>
        <p>4  24  YOU: ON A DIET, by Michael F. Roizen and Mehmet C. Oz et al. (Free Press, $25.) Weight-loss tips, from the authors of ''You: The Owner's Manual.''</p>
        <p>5  7  WOMEN &amp; MONEY, by Suze Orman. (Spiegel &amp; Grau, $24.95.) How women can achieve financial security.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This  On</p>
        <p>Week  List  Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous: Paperback</p>
        <p>1  1  FOOD CURES, by Joy Bauer with Carol Svec. (Rodale, $18.95.) Tips on eating well from the nutritionist for the ''Today'' show.</p>
        <p>2  4  EVERYDAY FOOD. (Clarkson Potter, $24.95.) Recipes from Martha Stewart Living's sister magazine.</p>
        <p>3  309  WHAT TO EXPECT WHEN YOU'RE EXPECTING, by Heidi Murkoff, Arlene Eisenberg and Sandee Hathaway. (Workman, $13.95.) Advice for parents-to-be. ()</p>
        <p>1  4  life: THE OrigInal pICTURE PUZZLE. (Life/Time Home Entertainment, $10.99.) ''Spot the difference'' photographs, from novice to ''genius.''</p>
        <p>5  4  THE LAW OF ATTRACTION, by Esther and Jerry Hicks. (Hay House, $14.95.) Using the laws that govern the universe to improve your life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
