<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fine Art of Helping Your Fellow Beings</title>
    <meta content="29colliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29colli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Make-A-Wish Foundation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LaMantia Gallery (Northport, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEEDF153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fine Art of Helping Your Fellow Beings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Fine Art of Helping Your Fellow Beings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robin Finn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>NORTHPORT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robin Finn The Island column on inaugural Petite Art Exhibition and Fundraiser, which raised money for Make-a-Wish Foundation, at LaMantia Gallery in Northport, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOUGH there's nothing aesthetically wrong with art for art's sake, something felt inherently right about the inaugural Petite Art Exhibition and Fundraiser, a competition and show devoted to a charity, in this case the Make-a-Wish Foundation, and to presenting small-scale creations submitted by 23 local artists. Actually, there are 22 local artists and one Long Island expatriate now painting in Kentucky; why nitpick, figured the judges, led by Ward Hooper, a watercolorist who lives in Northport and teaches at the Art League of Long Island. The painting met the size requirement of 16 by 16 inches (or tinier), so in it went.</p>
        <p>Each artist's $30 entry fee went directly to Make-a-Wish. The artwork received wall space through April 29 at LaMantia Gallery, an internationally recognized storefront where collectibles by far-flung (California, Russia, Germany, New Jersey) artists with name-brand clout -- Brian Davis, Pino (LaMantia's best seller) and the ubiquitous Thomas Kinkade -- carry four- and five-figure price tags. But the gallery is taking no commission on any petite art sold during the show's run; it's an instance of art meeting feel-good commerce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Long Island, one gallery is taking no commission on any petite art sold during the show’s run; it’s an instance of art meeting feel-good commerce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOUGH there's nothing aesthetically wrong with art for art's sake, something felt inherently right about the inaugural Petite Art Exhibition and Fundraiser, a competition and show devoted to a charity, in this case the Make-a-Wish Foundation, and to presenting small-scale creations submitted by 23 local artists. Actually, there are 22 local artists and one Long Island expatriate now painting in Kentucky; why nitpick, figured the judges, led by Ward Hooper, a watercolorist who lives in Northport and teaches at the Art League of Long Island. The painting met the size requirement of 16 by 16 inches (or tinier), so in it went.</p>
        <p>Each artist's $30 entry fee went directly to Make-a-Wish. The artwork received wall space through April 29 at LaMantia Gallery, an internationally recognized storefront where collectibles by far-flung (California, Russia, Germany, New Jersey) artists with name-brand clout -- Brian Davis, Pino (LaMantia's best seller) and the ubiquitous Thomas Kinkade -- carry four- and five-figure price tags. But the gallery is taking no commission on any petite art sold during the show's run; it's an instance of art meeting feel-good commerce.</p>
        <p>Heartwarming, too, that Doug Reina of Stony Brook, winner of the weeklong competition on quaintly cute Main Street, did not even know his oil-on-panel painting ''Baseball Practice'' had netted him anything more than a blue ribbon, a congratulatory e-mail message and a mild ego boost. Mr. Reina, a full-time artist whose 10-year-old son is an active Little Leaguer, painted ''Baseball Practice'' last summer on the playing fields at Murphy Junior High School in Stony Brook.</p>
        <p>''Wow,'' he said, when alerted by telephone that the blue ribbon would be accompanied by a $75 framing credit. And if the work sells, Mr. Reina could earn $700, the price he assigned it. ''I had blitzed out on the fact that there was a prize attached to the competition. Just being the winner was a nice compliment,'' said Mr. Reina, who grew up in Lloyd Harbor, where his mother, an artist and gallery owner, and his father, a sculptor and art professor at Nassau Community College, served as his art critics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reina, arguably the most accomplished artist (that is, he makes a living at it) of those in the show, is represented by Gallery North in Setauket. His personal charity of choice is Splashes of Hope, a group of Long Island artists who donate child-friendly artwork to hospitals; his work hangs at Stony Brook University Medical Center and at Mount Sinai in New York.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Hooper, who would have entered the contest himself had he not been judging (that would have bent the rules a little too much), Mr. Reina's painting ''wonderfully captures the essence of bright sunlight. It's difficult to paint figures on that small of a scale and make it work.'' The second-place work, an unusual combination of colored pencil on wood block, is ''Portrait of Phoebe'' by Yvonne Suzuki Licopoli of Northport. Third place went to a crisply impressionistic photograph, ''River's Edge,'' by James Twomey III, a window clerk at the Northport Post Office.</p>
        <p>''There is talent galore on Long Island,'' Mr. Hooper said, ''and certainly more artists than there are venues. Our entries ran the spectrum from abstract to tight realism, and truthfully, I didn't see anything I would have rejected.'' Besides working four decades in the corporate world, including a stint as design director for J. C. Penney, Mr. Hooper studied with Edgar Whitney, who is to Long Island watercolorists what Walt Whitman is to local poets: a genuine laureate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hooper, Mr. Reina and even James LaMantia, the gallery's tattooed proprietor (a medley of koi, cherry blossoms and dragonflies transforms his right arm into appendage art), plan to enter the plein-air event the gallery is sponsoring June 15 to 17. (Plein air means painted outdoors in natural light.) Artists will be at their easels throughout Northport village on the Friday and Saturday; their paintings will be sold at a silent auction on Sunday to benefit the Northport Arts Coalition.</p>
        <p>''If it works, it's going to be like a 'happening,' '' enthused Mr. LaMantia, who studied painting at SUNY New Paltz before deciding he was better at marrying other people's art to collectors than making it himself. His wooden painting kit sits forlornly beside his desk, waiting for June 15.</p>
        <p>But not every charitable event is strictly local. Mr. LaMantia is raffling off a Brian Davis painting valued at $1,100 at an exhibit of Mr. Davis's work next month. Following the gallery's usual protocol when it holds a major show, the artist is donating the painting, ''Rose Garden at the Huntington.'' Proceeds from the raffle -- Mr. LaMantia hopes to sell 100 tickets at $50 apiece, but he skews optimistic -- will be donated to Autism Speaks, another charity with a strong local presence.</p>
        <p>So an exquisitely rendered painting of white roses could, if Mr. LaMantia's calculations are correct, bring a $5,000 donation to Autism Speaks and a (cheap) thrill to its lucky new owner. Now that's aesthetically pleasing.</p>
        <p>THE ISLAND E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
