<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Family Secrets</title>
    <meta content="Hoffman3.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/Hoffman3.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843538"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Slouka, Mark</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Visible World, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E4D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1244" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Family Secrets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Family Secrets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVA HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Eva</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE VISIBLE WORLD</p>
        <p>By Mark Slouka.</p>
        <p>242 pp. Houghton Mifflin Company. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The narrator of Mark Slouka’s novel tries to uncover his immigrant mother’s hidden past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE VISIBLE WORLD</p>
        <p>By Mark Slouka.</p>
        <p>242 pp. Houghton Mifflin Company. $24.</p>
        <p>Early in Mark Slouka's novel ''The Visible World,'' the protagonist, a child of Czech refugees from World War II, speaks of ''an entire universe and its times, its stained-glass windows and its vaulted ceilings'' he used to sense ''beneath the world I had known -- so very familiar to me, so very American.'' In this thoughtful and evocative if sometimes sentimental novel, Slouka -- himself the son of Czech immigrants -- explores a problem surely familiar to us all, but perhaps especially acute for children of transplanted parents. How do you come to understand a history that has shaped you, but that you have not experienced? How do you fathom a world from which in a sense you come, but which you do not know? How do you penetrate the personalities and pasts of your parents if you have grown up far from the sites of their memories?</p>
        <p>In addressing these questions, Slouka's second novel joins a growing genre of what might be called second-generation quests -- attempts, by children of immigrants or Holocaust survivors, to track down and apprehend a remote and often traumatic ancestral history. Far from being a linear account of a search for roots, however, ''The Visible World'' proceeds through a kind of imaginative archaeology, sending probes into strata of time, examining fragments of excavated evidence and reflecting on layers of meaning concealed under, and revealed through, the familiar appearances of the visible world.</p>
        <p>The first section, ''The New World: A Memoir,'' depicts the ostensibly true events of the narrator's childhood, spent in Queens and in the Poconos. Slouka evokes the wistful atmosphere of an immigrant community, with its disabled war veterans and possible collaborators, its wry humor and bittersweet nostalgia. The narrator grows up surrounded by glimmers of bucolic Czech villages, intimations of illicit secrets and riddling fragments of stories whose veracity is often unclear, and whose significance he only half understands. The novel abounds in metaphors of submerged worlds and, in the child's mind, visions of underwater elves and enchanting forest maidens derived from Czech fairy tales (Czech phrases are sprinkled throughout the text) coexist with the image of a spooky but all too real crypt, in which seven resistance fighters hid after the famous attempt to assassinate the Nazi leader Reinhard Heydrich.</p>
        <p>The most significant unseen presence in the narrator's young life, however, is that of a man whom his mother apparently loved before she married his father and whom she cannot, or will not, forget. The father, a decent, ruefully ironic man, remains devoted to his wife despite her emotional infidelity. She, however, is increasingly claimed by the memory, or fantasy, of a phantom lover. Her moods of affectionate playfulness alternate with bouts of mental and actual absence; eventually, she kills herself by walking under a bus.</p>
        <p>In the novel's second section, ''Prague: Intermezzo,'' the narrator travels to his parents' homeland, in the hope that learning more about their past will help him unravel the sad enigma of his mother's suicide. His searches take him through a series of places and brief encounters, sketched with deft, economical strokes. Slouka has a knack for conveying errant details and impressions, the sense of promise and of sheer haphazardness that constitutes a traveler's reality. The narrator sees an aged crone who might be a personification of time itself; meets with gruff villagers who remember the war sufficiently to quarrel about the details of a particular day's weather; talks with a stranger who may have come close to the Heydrich plot. None of these tantalizing clues, however, yield clear meaning; and in the third, longest section of the novel, the narrator turns to his imagination to supply the missing parts of his mother's story.</p>
        <p>''1942: A Novel'' is that story, in the narrator's fictional version. This is an interesting formal move, and an apt expression of the narrator's -- indeed the second generation's -- quandary. In a sense, children of immigrant parents always have to fictionalize their parents' stories, to construct them from shreds of knowledge and distant recollection. In the shift from ''nonfiction'' to ''fiction,'' Slouka articulates both the uncertainties of cross-generational memory and the need to fill in the gaps.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the fiction the narrator invents is a tale of love and war so fantastically and at the same time conventionally romantic that it strains the modern reader's patience, rather than reinforcing imaginative conviction. In the novel within the novel, the narrator's mother meets Tomas Bem, an imaginary eighth conspirator in the Heydrich plot, at a nighttime session of a resistance cell. They are so irresistibly attracted to each other that after only a few hours they decide to ignore all their obligations -- she is already involved with the narrator's future father -- and walk back into the forest from which they have just emerged. Their affair takes place in this idyllic wilderness, where they cook on an improvised fire, run naked through the rain and find shelter in a rustic cabin. The intensity of their affair is increased by the looming necessity of parting; and after several days, Tomas leaves, just in time to join his fellow conspirators in their dangerous venture.</p>
        <p>The attempt to kill Heydrich goes awry, as it did historically, and the conspirators are forced to go into hiding, in the iconic church crypt of the narrator's childhood mythology. The narrator-novelist has a chance to peer into the crypt once again, this time through a more mature lens; and the passages in which he imagines the conspirators' confinement are grittily suggestive, conjuring the atmosphere of boredom, camaraderie and growing anxiety, especially when the young conspirators learn of Heydrich's death and the terrible reprisals that followed, in which many hundreds of people were murdered.</p>
        <p>In the midst of this collective tragedy, the romance resumes. Tomas comes briefly out of hiding, and the two lovers spend a night together in the relatively safe refuge of a cemetery. It is because Tomas is not with his fellow conspirators that night that he avoids capture and execution. Soon after, however, his guilt, compounded by knowledge that he was probably suspected of betrayal, overwhelms him.</p>
        <p>The interweaving of history and imagination in this section, of fairy-tale motifs with their adult revisions, is effective, braiding together all the elements of the narrator's mental world. The problem is that the excesses of the fictional scenario diminish the seriousness of the ''real'' story, rather than expanding its scope or deepening its significance.</p>
        <p>This is a pity, because ''The Visible World'' is in many ways a delicately imagined and beautifully rendered novel. The descriptions of nature are precise and sensuous; the vignettes of minor characters vivid and razor sharp. Slouka writes perceptively about the ambiguities of human behavior -- both within the ordinary circumstances of marriage, and in the extreme conditions of war. The first two sections can almost stand on their own as a meditation on the impossibility of fully knowing another person, or of plumbing the past.</p>
        <p>If Slouka's attempt to delve directly into that past is less successful than his oblique approach, this may reflect the difficulty -- often discernible in second-generation texts -- of confronting our parents' daunting historical dramas without transmogrifying them into psychological fantasy or flattening them into melodrama. Still, ''The Visible World'' is a sensitive and formally inventive elaboration of complex and elusive themes; despite its flaws, there is much to enjoy in its hidden implications and its nuanced narrative surfaces.</p>
        <p>Eva Hoffman is the author of ''After Such Knowledge: Memory, History, and the Legacy of the Holocaust'' and ''The Secret,'' a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eva Hoffman is the author of ''After Such Knowledge: Memory, History, and the Legacy of the Holocaust'' and ''The Secret,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
