<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's 2 by 3, Plastic and Offers a Concierge Service?</title>
    <meta content="29concierge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/business/yourmoney/29concierge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: SPENDING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customer Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customer Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EFDA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1380" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's 2 by 3, Plastic and Offers a Concierge Service?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What’s 2 by 3, Plastic and Offers a Concierge Service?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STELLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stellin, Susan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Gabriel Levy couldn't remember the best route from Marin County to the San Francisco 49ers' stadium last December, he didn't ask a pedestrian, pull out a map or reach for a gadget with G.P.S. technology. He just dialed the phone number for the concierge service offered with his credit card, and the woman who answered steered him in the right direction.</p>
        <p>''I called and said, 'I'm driving to Candlestick Park and I'm in Mill Valley; can you give me directions to get there?' The woman literally stayed on the phone and walked me through the whole thing,'' Mr. Levy said. A former Bay Area resident who now lives in Manhattan, he defended his need for help by pointing out that the highways through San Francisco have changed since he lived there (as has the name of the stadium, now called Monster Park).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once a benefit offered primarily with credit and charge cards that have significant annual fees, concierge services have trickled down to a wider range of cardholders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Gabriel Levy couldn't remember the best route from Marin County to the San Francisco 49ers' stadium last December, he didn't ask a pedestrian, pull out a map or reach for a gadget with G.P.S. technology. He just dialed the phone number for the concierge service offered with his credit card, and the woman who answered steered him in the right direction.</p>
        <p>''I called and said, 'I'm driving to Candlestick Park and I'm in Mill Valley; can you give me directions to get there?' The woman literally stayed on the phone and walked me through the whole thing,'' Mr. Levy said. A former Bay Area resident who now lives in Manhattan, he defended his need for help by pointing out that the highways through San Francisco have changed since he lived there (as has the name of the stadium, now called Monster Park).</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy has also relied on the concierge service that comes with his credit card -- a Citi PremierPass Elite-Level MasterCard -- to order flowers for his wife, make dinner reservations and confirm the status of a flight. These are all things that he could do himself, but he finds calling a concierge more efficient, not to mention more personal.</p>
        <p>''If I call the airline, it takes me 10 minutes and 8 buttons to get through to a human being,'' he said. ''With these guys, you get through immediately.''</p>
        <p>Once a benefit offered primarily with credit and charge cards that have annual fees of hundreds of dollars or more, concierge services have trickled down to a wider range of plastic. Although access to a concierge is not a typical benefit of no-fee cards, it is becoming more common with cards that have annual fees under $100. For instance, Visa's Signature credit cards and MasterCard's World Elite cards offer a concierge benefit. (Mr. Levy pays an $75 annual fee for his MasterCard.)</p>
        <p>The goal is to give customers a sense of exclusivity by offering 24/7 telephone access to assistants whose help is only limited by what is ''legal, moral and ethical,'' said Denise Thomas, an executive vice president at LesConcierges, one of several companies that provide this service on behalf of credit card issuers and other partners.</p>
        <p>Credit card companies or card issuers pay for the concierge service as one of a number of benefits offered to card holders to compete for their business, along with perks like travel insurance and frequent-flier miles. A call to the card issuer is all it takes to find out if a concierge service is offered.</p>
        <p>Although most requests involve making dinner reservations, helping with travel arrangements or providing shopping assistance, others stray into more challenging territory.</p>
        <p>''We've been asked to arrange a hearing with the pope for newlyweds -- we were actually able to do that,'' Ms. Thomas said, adding that the concierges are also trained to offer imaginative suggestions, like ideas for unusual vacations or Valentine's Day gifts.</p>
        <p>''When people gain an understanding of what's possible, they increasingly use the concierge for things like that,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In fact, that is how Pat Flynn, a Pittsburgh Steelers fan who lives in Spokane, Wash., ended up getting tickets to Super Bowl XL in Detroit in 2006. He had called his credit card company to try to bargain down the $65 annual fee for his United Mileage Plus Visa Signature card, issued by Chase, and was talked into keeping the card when he learned about some of its benefits, including a concierge service.</p>
        <p>He said that when the Steelers made it to the National Football League playoffs, ''I thought, 'Well, let's give this Visa Signature concierge a try.'' Not only did he get tickets to the playoff game through the service, he also used it to buy a Super Bowl package, paying $10,000 for two tickets to the game, hotel accommodations, ground transportation and the chance to meet some of the players.</p>
        <p>The Steelers won the game. But most important, he said, he was able to take along his 10-year-old son, Casey.</p>
        <p>''Long after I'm gone, I'm sure he'll remember going to the Super Bowl with his dad,'' Mr. Flynn said.</p>
        <p>That type of memory is among the things Visa is promoting with its Signature line of credit cards, which was started in the late 1990s and aims for customers with household incomes of $125,000 or more. About 14 million people have Visa Signature cards, said Heather Clifton, Visa's vice president for credit product management. Many of the card benefits, she said, are intended to help customers manage their busy lives.</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Clifton said she did not know how many customers have used the concierge service, she said that 85 percent of cardholders who try it call again -- sometimes just to get an answer to a burning question. ''A group of friends were playing Texas Hold 'Em poker and wanted to know what the worst hand and the best hand were, so they called the concierge,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Many people may not know that their credit cards provide concierge services.</p>
        <p>''We have one issuer who has a huge contingency of international travelers, so they've integrated a link to their concierge program into their Web site,'' said Chris Morris, vice president for business development at MasterCard. ''On the other hand, we have issuers who talk about the concierge service in their benefit package and never mention it again.''</p>
        <p>Alice Hill is among consumers who didn't realize she had access to a concierge through her American Express Platinum card, which costs $450 a year, partly to cover the cost of the concierge benefit as well as perks like free companion airline tickets and access to airport lounges. ''I saw a friend of mine using it and I thought, 'Oh, I guess I could do that, too,' '' Ms. Hill said.</p>
        <p>She now uses the concierge service mostly to make restaurant reservations, thereby avoiding the trouble of having to make the calls herself during the window when reservation lines are open, taking into account any time difference. Most concierge services cultivate relationships with restaurants to give their customers a better shot at getting reservations; American Express has agreements with more than 1,200 restaurants worldwide to reserve at least one table a night for its Platinum or Centurion card holders.</p>
        <p>Still, that's not a guarantee that your card will score you a table at any hot restaurant on a Saturday night.</p>
        <p>For instance, Ms. Hill said she was unable to get a reservation at Per Se during a trip to New York City last year, but she has had better luck getting tables at other restaurants in New York or in her hometown, San Francisco. She has also used the American Express concierge to help resolve a billing dispute over a television she had ordered online, and to inquire about getting seats to a popular Broadway show, though she ultimately didn't buy them. ''They were able to get them, but they were horribly expensive -- it was like $600 a ticket,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Typically, card holders do not pay extra for products or services ordered through a concierge (although last-minute tickets may be available only through sources that do charge a premium ), and customers are usually given several options.</p>
        <p>''Say you called to order flowers -- we would give you a range of prices for a dozen roses and we would charge whatever it cost,'' said Mary Naylor, founder and chief executive of VIPdesk, which provides concierge services for financial institutions and other clients, handling about 50,000 requests a month.</p>
        <p>AMONG the more offbeat inquiries VIPdesk has received are these: getting food for a pet tarantula, arranging for someone to string Christmas lights on a client's grandfather's house and finding a replica of the dress that Julia Roberts wore in the film ''Ocean's 11.''</p>
        <p>''The only type of requests we don't handle is anything that's illegal, and we don't do escort services or anything of that nature,'' Ms. Naylor said.</p>
        <p>She agreed that some credit card holders might not even know that they can consult a concierge. Indeed, some who do use their concierge service have mixed feelings about spreading the word. As Mr. Flynn pointed out, ''The more people who know about this, the less chance I have of ever getting Super Bowl tickets again.''</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: SPENDING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
