<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Dragnet' With Leis, and the Occasional Ghost</title>
    <meta content="29evan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/arts/television/29evan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DVD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallenstein, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hawaii Five-0 (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Lord, Jack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EFDB143EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Dragnet' With Leis, and the Occasional Ghost</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Dragnet’ With Leis, and the Occasional Ghost</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG EVANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Evans, Greg</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses 1968-80 TV show Hawaii Five-0, whose first season has just been released on DVD; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STEVE McGARRETT, the Brylcreemed leader of the elite state police unit that gave ''Hawaii Five-0'' its name, was the kind of guy who knew what to do when duty demanded a necktie but whose maverick nature -- Hawaii's, his own -- whispered ''lei.'' He wore both. And when romance and opportunity presented him with a sandy ''From Here to Eternity'' moment, McGarrett did what McGarrett should: he kept the necktie.</p>
        <p>Overconfident do-rights of McGarrett's stripe don't get love like they used to. Even an authoritarian's pipe dream like ''24'' demands that its saviors show some small capacity for doubt and reflection. A viewer could get through all seven discs of the DVD set of first-season ''Hawaii Five-0'' episodes and discern barely a second thought. Beads of sweat? Not in McGarrett's Honolulu. So what accounts for the show's oddball allure? Certainly television produced few leading men stiffer than Jack Lord, who played McGarrett as a Big Kahuna only occasionally more genial than a wood-carved idol. The surprise here is that he proves just as durable. You watch Mr. Lord the way you listen to the show's immortal, brassy theme song, predicting every beat but caught up in the swell just the same.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before “Law &amp; Order&amp;#8221; and “24, ” there was the elite state police unit with crime-fighting carte blanche of “Hawaii Five-0,” now back in a first-season, seven-disc set.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STEVE McGARRETT, the Brylcreemed leader of the elite state police unit that gave ''Hawaii Five-0'' its name, was the kind of guy who knew what to do when duty demanded a necktie but whose maverick nature -- Hawaii's, his own -- whispered ''lei.'' He wore both. And when romance and opportunity presented him with a sandy ''From Here to Eternity'' moment, McGarrett did what McGarrett should: he kept the necktie.</p>
        <p>Overconfident do-rights of McGarrett's stripe don't get love like they used to. Even an authoritarian's pipe dream like ''24'' demands that its saviors show some small capacity for doubt and reflection. A viewer could get through all seven discs of the DVD set of first-season ''Hawaii Five-0'' episodes and discern barely a second thought. Beads of sweat? Not in McGarrett's Honolulu. So what accounts for the show's oddball allure? Certainly television produced few leading men stiffer than Jack Lord, who played McGarrett as a Big Kahuna only occasionally more genial than a wood-carved idol. The surprise here is that he proves just as durable. You watch Mr. Lord the way you listen to the show's immortal, brassy theme song, predicting every beat but caught up in the swell just the same.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lord, who appeared in the entire run of the series, from 1968 to 1980, took to McGarrett with the intensity of a not-so-young actor who knew he had just found his career. The show's setup had McGarrett answerable only to God and the governor, as one character notes, a crime-fighting carte blanche that allowed the men of the Five-0 and the actors who played them an expanse of adventure that would overwhelm the specializing nitpickers of today's CSIs. Red Chinese supervillains? Check. LSD-dosing hippie gurus? Check. Quack doctors bamboozling desperate patients with room-size computers that might have been lifted from the Batcave? Five-0 was on the case.</p>
        <p>The outlandishness of the capers in this first season might surprise viewers who remember ''Hawaii Five-0'' as ''Dragnet'' with lehua blossoms. Though as tightly structured as any ''Law &amp; Order,'' ''Hawaii Five-0'' could, and often did, get delightfully loopy. Smart writing usually kept things from veering too far afield, but not always: the final episode of the season is a ghost story so ludicrous it would have fans of ''Scooby-Doo'' rolling their eyes. Most weeks, though, the show's scripts took fine advantage of the heady Hawaiian atmosphere and earnest '60s vibe.</p>
        <p>Long before Dick Wolf was ripping from the headlines, the producer Leonard Freeman was commissioning stories like ''Tiger by the Tail,'' an episode plainly riffing on the 1963 kidnapping of Frank Sinatra Jr. The story lines, whether gritty or fanciful, showcased some of the era's most productive character actors (Sal Mineo played the Sinatraesque abductee). In one of the more delirious turns, Gavin MacLeod tears into the sweaty role of a predatory, sexually ambiguous convict (nicknamed Big Chicken, no less) as if relishing his remaining moments untethered to Murray Slaughter's manual typewriter.</p>
        <p>McGarrett's lieutenants (Kam Fong as Chin Ho Kelly, Zulu as Kono Kalakaua) offered steady if not always electrifying support, while lesser roles were often filled with local nonactors, lending more diversity than skill. Only James MacArthur's Lt. Danny Williams, also known as Danno, could hold his ground with Mr. Lord week after week. (Readers wondering how this review could get so far without mentioning ''Book 'em, Danno!'' should note that the catchphrase made fewer appearances in Season 1 than might be expected.) In one Danno-centric episode here, Mr. MacArthur's character suffers a crisis of conscience his boss barely understands. Danno, it seems, was a cop just waiting for Steven Bochco to happen. He could do worse than passing his time in Hawaii.</p>
        <p>GREG EVANS</p>
        <p>DVD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
