<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Surprise on the East Side</title>
    <meta content="29hunt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/realestate/29hunt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE HUNT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinette, Katy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vernon, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Hunt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0D7153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Surprise on the East Side</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Surprise on the East Side</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Hunt column on search by Katy Robinette and David Vernon for one-bedroom rental apartment in Brooklyn's north side for up to $1,800 per month; found one-bedroom on Upper East Side of Manhattan for $1,925; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT wasn't just that Katy Robinette and David Vernon wanted to live in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. They wanted the north side of Williamsburg, that post-collegiate hub where many of their friends had gravitated.</p>
        <p>But after graduating from Vassar College in 2006, they landed, at least for the short term, on the south side, which was nowhere near as trendy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A couple fresh out of college had their hearts set on a hip part of Williamsburg, Brooklyn, but ended up on the Upper East Side.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT wasn't just that Katy Robinette and David Vernon wanted to live in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. They wanted the north side of Williamsburg, that post-collegiate hub where many of their friends had gravitated.</p>
        <p>But after graduating from Vassar College in 2006, they landed, at least for the short term, on the south side, which was nowhere near as trendy.</p>
        <p>Ms. Robinette, who is from Pine Bluff, Ark., and Mr. Vernon, of Potomac, Md., met through friends a month before graduation. She started work as a paralegal in Midtown Manhattan, while he got a job as a research assistant in a circadian-rhythm laboratory at Barnard College.</p>
        <p>The couple, both 22, occupied the largest of three small bedrooms in a rental on South Fourth Street that they shared with two male roommates, also Vassar classmates. Each of the four paid $500 a month.</p>
        <p>But it was the kind of place you planned to leave. The south side location was a 10-minute walk from the Lorimer Street subway station, the second stop on the L train coming from Manhattan. (It was actually closer to the Hewes Street station on the inconvenient and infrequent J, M and Z lines.)</p>
        <p>The area was ''on the verge of gentrified Williamsburg, with this whole clash of cultures and age groups,'' Ms. Robinette said. Rats scampered on streets filled with trash.</p>
        <p>So, last winter, the two began hunting for a bigger, nicer and better-located one-bedroom of their own. They intended to move to the coveted north side, which by now was so familiar to them that they knew the waiters and waitresses at their favorite restaurants.</p>
        <p>The plan was to be within a quick walk of the first or second stops -- Bedford Avenue or Lorimer Street -- on the L train, that metric of desirable Williamsburg geography. Their budget allowed for $1,800 a month.</p>
        <p>Ms. Robinette objected to paying a broker's fee, which seemed an excessive addition to already high rents. Even if a broker found them a less expensive rental, ''it doesn't balance out in the end,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But the type of place they wanted, it seemed, simply didn't exist -- at least not in their preferred location.</p>
        <p>It became easy for them to spot the mistruths in online listings. Desirable-sounding places were typically taken, but there was something else for a higher cost in a worse location. Or there was a broker's fee.</p>
        <p>The two finally found a place that met their criteria: a long, skinny apartment, for around $1,750, situated above the Royal Oak bar on Union Avenue. Mr. Vernon liked it. But Ms. Robinette, working late, couldn't arrive in time to see it, and the landlord already had plenty of qualified and interested renters.</p>
        <p>They decided to broaden their neighborhood reach. ''The farther out on the L line you go, the cheaper prices get,'' Ms. Robinette said. But she wanted to minimize time spent on the L. ''The L is a miserable, miserable train line,'' she said. At rush hour, trains zoomed past without stopping. Or several trains passed before she could get on, and then during the trip, ''someone would be breathing down the front and back of your neck,'' she said. Worse, the trains were often out of service.</p>
        <p>Instead, the two found apartments in their price range in a place they least expected: Manhattan.</p>
        <p>One Saturday, they lined up several places to see, including a one-bedroom on Avenue C for only $1,600. They liked the East Village, which felt like the north side of Williamsburg. They arrived to find a locked front door, a broken buzzer and no answer at the landlord's phone number. ''There was a note on the buzzer saying, 'Come on up,' and we were, like 'How?' '' Mr. Vernon said.</p>
        <p>They hung around the front door, walking in when someone exited the building. The apartment had a bedroom big enough only for a bed, and a sloping floor that looked as if it could buckle at any moment. They left quickly.</p>
        <p>Another one-bedroom, for $1,800, was in Little Italy. They met the building's agent and climbed up six steep flights, but the tenant refused to let them in.</p>
        <p>''The girl is saying, 'I just got out of the shower and never told anyone you could come by -- you need to call the landlord,' and the broker guy is saying he did, and they had this whole back and forth through the closed door,'' Ms. Robinette said.</p>
        <p>The agent said they could return later that day, but they had an appointment uptown. ''We asked if he had other apartments, and he said you are not likely to find anything in this price range,'' Ms. Robinette said. ''I felt it was mostly true, but that is what this whole hunt was about -- something that doesn't usually exist.''</p>
        <p>The uptown place was on York Avenue near 78th Street. Ms. Robinette, who combed the Craigslist Web site relentlessly, was the first to answer a posting from a tenant breaking the lease and returning to her native Peru. The rent on the fifth-floor one-bedroom was $1,925 -- pricey, but it included utilities. So they decided to take a look.</p>
        <p>''I was anti-Upper-East-Side,'' Ms. Robinette said. ''I am really into the artsy multicultural scene, and the Upper East Side isn't like that. I associated it with a stale culture and ex-frat boys working for investment banks.''</p>
        <p>When they stepped inside, ''my jaw dropped,'' Mr. Vernon said. It was a real one-bedroom, in lovely shape, with a big bathroom. ''This was so good we had to take it,'' he said. They were waiting at the management office early the next business day, before it even opened.</p>
        <p>They moved in last month, and are surprised at how much they like the Upper East Side. ''It is a peaceful living environment and has quickly become home,'' Mr. Vernon said.</p>
        <p>They hardly miss the hipster scene, though eateries in their new neighborhood seem pricey, so they find themselves eating out less.</p>
        <p>''Our friends come over and are really impressed, which is a funny feeling,'' Ms. Robinette said. ''We just graduated from college and feel like little yuppies living on the Upper East Side with our one-bedroom apartment.''</p>
        <p>They're thrilled, too, to be free of the L train. Mr. Vernon now has an easy bus commute. Ms. Robinette usually takes the 4, 5 or 6 lines. ''I have never seen a 4-5-6 pass by without stopping, nor have I ever not been able to get on the train because it's been too crowded,'' she said. Compared with the overburdened L, it is ''way more normal.''</p>
        <p>THE HUNT E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
