<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>His Race Not Yet Certain, A Politician Gets Set to Run</title>
    <meta content="29gioia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/29gioia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>His Race Not Yet Certain, A Politician Gets Set to Run</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">His Race Not Yet Certain, a Politician Gets Set to Run</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About 400 people gathered on Thursday in a Manhattan club where a D.J. played '80s and '90s music in an event that was not quite the typical political fund-raiser.</p>
        <p>The crowd was somewhat younger, in part because the host, City Councilman Eric N. Gioia, was celebrating his 34th birthday. And unlike many political fund-raisers that ask guests to make sizable contributions, Mr. Gioia's event was open to anyone who gave as little as a few dollars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>City Councilman Eric N. Gioia has become known as a master fund-raiser, having collected more money for a 2009 city race than all but two other likely candidates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About 400 people gathered on Thursday in a Manhattan club where a D.J. played '80s and '90s music in an event that was not quite the typical political fund-raiser.</p>
        <p>The crowd was somewhat younger, in part because the host, City Councilman Eric N. Gioia, was celebrating his 34th birthday. And unlike many political fund-raisers that ask guests to make sizable contributions, Mr. Gioia's event was open to anyone who gave as little as a few dollars.</p>
        <p>While he has made a name by championing a number of issues, Mr. Gioia, a Democrat from Woodside, Queens, has perhaps become best known as a master fund-raiser, having collected more money for a 2009 city race than all but two other likely candidates.</p>
        <p>The New York City Campaign Finance Board reported that Mr. Gioia had raised more than $700,000 as of January. Only William C. Thompson Jr., the comptroller and a likely mayoral candidate, and Councilman John C. Liu, who is widely expected to run for comptroller or public advocate, have collected more.</p>
        <p>Since that January filing, Mr. Gioia's campaign aides say, he has easily surpassed $1 million. And Mr. Gioia, because of parties like the one in the Flatiron district of Manhattan last week, has a broader base of contributors than any other candidate in the city's campaign finance system. His roster of donors, nearly 1,800 people, is almost twice as long as that of the next closest candidate.</p>
        <p>''There is a reality that you have to raise money,'' Mr. Gioia said. ''But I've chosen to do it in a way that makes people feel empowered. Sometimes people won't participate in politics because it's too expensive. But I want people to give whatever they want. And that brings together in the same room New Yorkers who are united by their desire to see positive things occur.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Gioia has not explicitly said what he will run for next, it has become clear that he may be looking to succeed Betsy Gotbaum as New York City's public advocate, the city's No. 2 position after the mayor. In introducing him at the fund-raiser, Mr. Gioia's wife, Lisa Hernandez Gioia, called him ''the best husband and the best advocate for the public.''</p>
        <p>The early and strong fund-raising for an election that is more than two years away is a byproduct of the city's term limit laws, which took effect in 2001. Because so many officials are barred from running for re-election in 2009, candidates are planning their strategies for running for new positions, including mayor, public advocate, comptroller, council member and borough president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Liu, whose Council district in Queens is adjacent to Mr. Gioia's, may turn out to be a rival. Mr. Liu has been meeting with Democratic leaders across the city to determine which citywide office to seek.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gioia is viewed as a bright, articulate councilman with a command of a range of issues. Just last week, the Amalgamated Bank opened a branch near a public housing complex in Queensbridge, in Mr. Gioia's district, after he and a group that represents public housing residents sought to bring a bank to the area.</p>
        <p>And last summer, after a blackout that left tens of thousands of residents of northwestern Queens without power for more than a week, Mr. Gioia played a major role in criticizing officials of Consolidated Edison for what he called their slow and ineffective response.</p>
        <p>Overwhelmingly, Mr. Gioia's colleagues describe him as bright and determined.</p>
        <p>''He's a very energetic and focused guy,'' said Councilman David Yassky, a Brooklyn Democrat. ''He's smart and full of good ideas.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gioia grew up in the district he represents, where his father runs a century-old flower business. He graduated from New York University and Georgetown Law School.</p>
        <p>''I worked as a janitor, a doorman and an elevator operator to pay for school,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He was an aide in the Clinton White House and then practiced law at Milbank, Tweed, Hadley &amp; McCloy.</p>
        <p>When he ran for the open Council seat in 2001, he was not the candidate supported by the Queens Democratic organization. Nonetheless, with a group of young campaign volunteers and an indefatigable campaign style, he defeated five candidates for the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gioia married after joining the Council. His wife is a fund-raiser who has worked for Gifford Miller, the former Council speaker, and for Gov. Eliot Spitzer. Their daughter, Amelia, is 10 months old.</p>
        <p>One supporter, Brian S. Kightlinger, 33, a magazine publisher, said Mr. Gioia was the ''only politician that I've ever been involved with to this degree.''</p>
        <p>He said, ''What I like about Eric is that there is always diversity in the people who support him, and there is always openness in the way he does business.''</p>
        <p>Scott Levenson, a political consultant, said that people who know Mr. Gioia ''generally believe that he will wake up as early as anyone else and go to sleep later than anyone else.''</p>
        <p>''He has a level of ambition which, even in this very competitive environment, is hard to match,'' Mr. Levenson said. ''And he has a drive that goes along with it.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, many of Mr. Gioia's colleagues privately describe him as being perhaps too driven by ambition, specifically criticizing him for being overly eager to get media attention.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gioia says he has heard the criticism, and is unfazed.</p>
        <p>''The only criteria that public officials should be judged on is results,'' he said. ''If I can change people's lives for the better, that's what I care about.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
