<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Land Preservation to Cost $3 Billion, Report Says</title>
    <meta content="29mainliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29mainli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OPEN SPACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pine Barrens (Li)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Pine Barrens Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Island Pine Barrens Society</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EEDF153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Land Preservation to Cost $3 Billion, Report Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Land Preservation to Cost $3 Billion, Report Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Pine Barrens Society releases report that estimates it will cost $3 billion over next several years to acquire final 35,000 acres earmarked for preservation; says state, county and town land acquisitions on Long island averaged 2,274 acres a year over last seven years; says government needs to coordinate programs better and streamline appraisals and negotiations before farmland and open space run out; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUFFOLK COUNTY and the Town of Brookhaven agreed to the kind of deal in December that has made Long Island a national leader in spending on land preservation. They decided to pay $17.75 million each for 296 acres of pine barrens at the headwaters of the Peconic River. And the state is negotiating to acquire 100 acres in the same area.</p>
        <p>Such efforts have long occurred on Long Island, despite its reputation as the endless suburb. Government, led by Suffolk County, has spent $1.2 billion over the past 50 years to buy and preserve 60,000 acres of farmland and open space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUFFOLK COUNTY and the Town of Brookhaven agreed to the kind of deal in December that has made Long Island a national leader in spending on land preservation. They decided to pay $17.75 million each for 296 acres of pine barrens at the headwaters of the Peconic River. And the state is negotiating to acquire 100 acres in the same area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUFFOLK COUNTY and the Town of Brookhaven agreed to the kind of deal in December that has made Long Island a national leader in spending on land preservation. They decided to pay $17.75 million each for 296 acres of pine barrens at the headwaters of the Peconic River. And the state is negotiating to acquire 100 acres in the same area.</p>
        <p>Such efforts have long occurred on Long Island, despite its reputation as the endless suburb. Government, led by Suffolk County, has spent $1.2 billion over the past 50 years to buy and preserve 60,000 acres of farmland and open space.</p>
        <p>But the Island will need, and should be able to provide, $3 billion more over the next several years to acquire a final 35,000 acres earmarked for preservation before time and space run out, a new report says.</p>
        <p>The report, released this month by the Long Island Pine Barrens Society, a nonprofit land and water conservation group based in Riverhead, estimates that these properties, most of which are in Suffolk, will cost an average of $100,000 an acre for 25,000 acres of open space and $50,000 an acre for development rights to 10,000 farm acres.</p>
        <p>Elected officials and environmental groups say many of the spaces they are seeking to preserve are smaller parcels than those bought in the past. ''The low-hanging fruit is gone,'' Steve Levy, the Suffolk County executive, said.</p>
        <p>The Pine Barrens group said its research showed that state, county and town land acquisitions on Long Island averaged 2,274 acres a year over the last seven years. Unless the pace quickens, the group said, a net of only about 20,000 more acres will be preserved by 2015. That is the year planners estimate the Island will reach build-out, the point at which there is no open space left to preserve or build on.</p>
        <p>The group also said that governments needed to coordinate programs better and streamline appraisals and negotiations.</p>
        <p>''Long Island's preservation efforts are second to none nationally, but unless there is a significant increase in the annual rate of preservation, we are in danger of failing to preserve these 35,000 additional acres,'' said Richard Amper, the group's executive director.</p>
        <p>The 35,000 acres, about half of the open space and farmland still available for development, are identified in land acquisition lists drawn up by Suffolk County, Nassau County, town governments, the Long Island Regional Planning Board and environmental groups.</p>
        <p>They include 2,000 acres in Nassau, 3,000 in western Suffolk, 12,000 in the Town of Brookhaven and 18,000 in the five East End towns, where nearly all of Suffolk's remaining 34,000 acres of farmland are.</p>
        <p>Purchase programs pay the appraised value for properties or development rights and require willing sellers. About half of the land already saved is in the 100,000-acre Long Island Pine Barrens State Preserve in central and eastern Suffolk.</p>
        <p>Desmond Ryan, the executive director of the Association for a Better Long Island, a group in Hauppauge that lobbies for developers, said preservation came at a cost. ''For every piece of open space you preserve, you drive up the price of the existing product in the marketplace,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Wieboldt, the executive vice president of the Long Island Builders Institute, in Islandia, said acquiring 35,000 acres could cost $5 billion. He questioned whether such an expenditure remains a priority.</p>
        <p>''We're not opposed to open space preservation,'' Mr. Wieboldt said. ''It's a matter of scale; $5 billion is an awful lot of money.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ryan did not dispute the report but said governments needed to expand sewer systems and identify lands where greater building density would be permitted.</p>
        <p>The report said that extending existing preservation programs further into the future and borrowing against anticipated revenues could provide more than $2 billion of the $3 billion needed.</p>
        <p>The group recommends extending until 2030 Suffolk's sales tax of one-quarter of 1 percent for land purchases, a bulwark of its preservation efforts since the 1980s. The program, which allows borrowing against future revenues, ends in 2013. An extension would require the approval of the state and county, and from Suffolk voters in a referendum.</p>
        <p>Nassau voters overwhelmingly approved environmental bonds of $50 million in 2004 and $100 million in 2006, but no more are under discussion.</p>
        <p>More than $1 billion of the $3 billion needed on Long Island, the report said, would have to come from three sources that are not in place: the Island's share of a state environmental bond act that has yet to be introduced in the State Legislature; future Nassau and Suffolk county and town bond acts; and the extension to Brookhaven of a 2 percent real estate transfer tax that is already in force in Suffolk's five East End towns (Riverhead, Southold, Southampton, East Hampton and Shelter Island).</p>
        <p>That tax, which homebuyers pay, has generated $400 million and preserved 6,000 acres in the five towns since voters approved it in 1998.</p>
        <p>The report estimates that a 2 percent real estate transfer tax in Brookhaven until 2030 would generate $660 million in anticipated revenues that the town could borrow against to expedite land purchases.</p>
        <p>W. Michael Pitcher, a Brookhaven spokesman, said the town supervisor, Brian X. Foley, and town board were close to approving a transfer tax. It would need voter approval and could be on the ballot in November.</p>
        <p>Lee E. Koppelman, the former chairman of the Regional Planning Board, said that with extension of the transfer tax to Brookhaven and help from a future state bond act, the county and local programs could raise $3 billion. ''It really is not a staggering figure,'' he said.</p>
        <p>OPEN SPACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
