<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Eat; Stalk of the Town</title>
    <meta content="29food.text" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="57" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/magazine/29food.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Food: The Way We Eat"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gray, Rose</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rogers, Ruth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFD8173EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Eat; Stalk of the Town</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stalk of the Town</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Amanda Hesser</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rhubarb, like manioc root, sea urchins and truffles, resides in a category of foods that by rights should never have made their way to the table. The bitter type of manioc can be lethal unless it is processed in some mysterious way. Sea urchins are covered with razor-sharp spines. Truffles are hidden beneath the soil and look like rocks. And rhubarb's majestic leaves, which conceal its edible stalks, are poisonous. Who looked under there to find out?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tart and intense on its own, rhubarb plays well with others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rhubarb, like manioc root, sea urchins and truffles, resides in a category of foods that by rights should never have made their way to the table. The bitter type of manioc can be lethal unless it is processed in some mysterious way. Sea urchins are covered with razor-sharp spines. Truffles are hidden beneath the soil and look like rocks. And rhubarb's majestic leaves, which conceal its edible stalks, are poisonous. Who looked under there to find out?</p>
        <p>Whoever did wasn't greeted with a pleasant-tasting reward. Uncooked rhubarb is about as delectable as pond algae. And yet mankind persevered. We cooked it, we added sugar -- lots of sugar -- and we found out that nature can be kind. If you have ever grown rhubarb, you know that it is a prosperous plant, one that can take over your life every spring as you search for ways to tame its bounty -- much like its cousin, sorrel. This may be why most people settle on rhubarb jam. You can slice up the stalks, simmer them with sugar and be done with it.</p>
        <p>Patience and experimentation, however, pay off with rhubarb: its flavor can be assertive and unforgiving, but it plays well with others. In a syrup for spritzers, rhubarb is mellowed by the gentle scents of lemongrass and basil. It may be roasted in long segments with blood-orange juice and vanilla. Sliced thinly and macerated in white wine and Earl Grey tea scented with cardamom and strawberries, the rhubarb slices remain crisp and tart in a delicate, sweet soup. And if you're feeling courageous, you can reverse gears and play up rhubarb's savory vegetal side, adding as much salt as sugar to it, simmering it along with diced pears, rosemary, honey and beer in a pan sauce for pork. Or balance it with shallots and ginger finished with a swirl of balsamic vinegar and butter, creating a sweet-tart sauce to go with roasted fish. Each of these subdues the aggressor, and why cook if not for a sense of triumph? (Recipes are on the next page.)</p>
        <p>Rhubarb Spritzer</p>
        <p>1/2 cup sugar</p>
        <p>* pound rhubarb, chopped</p>
        <p>1 stalk lemongrass, chopped</p>
        <p>Soda water</p>
        <p>4 basil leaves, for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. In a medium saucepan, bring 1/2 cup water, sugar, rhubarb and lemongrass to a boil. Reduce to a simmer and cook until the rhubarb is tender, about 10 minutes. Push through a fine-mesh sieve. Let cool.</p>
        <p>2. Fill 4 small glasses halfway with ice. Pour into each glass a scant 1/4 cup rhubarb juice, then top with soda water to taste. Garnish with a basil leaf. Makes about 1 1/3 cups rhubarb juice; serves 4 to 5.</p>
        <p>Black Bass With Silky Rhubarb Sauce</p>
        <p>4 6-ounce fillets black bass</p>
        <p>7 tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>Sea salt</p>
        <p>8 ounces shiitake mushrooms, rimmed and cut into 1/4 -inch slices (4 cups)</p>
        <p>1/4 cup thinly sliced shallots</p>
        <p>4 thin slices (the size of a quarter) peeled ginger</p>
        <p>1 1/2 cups diced (1/4-inch) rhubarb</p>
        <p>2 teaspoons sugar</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons butter</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon heavy cream</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon balsamic vinegar.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat the oven to 275 degrees. Lay the fish skin side down in a baking dish just large enough to fit the fillets. Sprinkle with 3 tablespoons olive oil and season with salt. Roast until just cooked through, 15 to 25 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. In a large sauté pan, heat 2 tablespoons olive oil over medium-high heat. Add the shiitakes, season with salt and sauté until lightly browned and just softened. Scrape into a bowl, adjust seasoning and keep warm.</p>
        <p>3. Return the pan to the heat and pour in the remaining 2 tablespoons oil. Add the shallots, ginger and rhubarb. Cook, stirring to scrape up any bits, until the rhubarb softens, about 4 minutes. Add 3/4 cup water and the sugar. Season with salt. Cook until reduced by half. Whisk in the butter and cream and then the vinegar. Press the sauce through a fine-mesh sieve set over a bowl.</p>
        <p>4. To serve, divide the sauce among 4 shallow bowls. Lay a piece of fish in each and top with a spoonful of mushrooms. Serves 4.</p>
        <p>Pork Tenderloin With Rhubarb,</p>
        <p>Pear, Rosemary and Honey</p>
        <p>1 1/2 pounds pork tenderloin, brought to room temperature</p>
        <p>Sea salt</p>
        <p>Freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>1 1/2 tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>3 sprigs rosemary</p>
        <p>1 clove garlic, smashed</p>
        <p>1 cup diced (1/4-inch) rhubarb</p>
        <p>1 Bosc pear, diced (1/4-inch)</p>
        <p>1/2 cup wheat beer</p>
        <p>1/2 cup chicken or beef broth</p>
        <p>1 1/2 tablespoons acacia or other light honey</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon butter.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat the oven to 275 degrees. Place an ovenproof sauté pan, just large enough to fit the tenderloin, over medium-high heat. Season the pork with salt and pepper. Add the olive oil to the hot pan, followed by the pork. Brown on all sides, then tuck 2 rosemary sprigs underneath the meat, transfer to the oven and continue cooking until the internal temperature of the pork at its thickest point reaches 130 degrees, 10 to 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Remove the pork from the oven, transfer to a serving plate and tent with foil. Discard the rosemary. Place the sauté pan over medium heat and add the garlic, rhubarb, pear and remaining rosemary sprig. Sauté until the rhubarb begins to soften, 5 to 7 minutes. Season lightly. Pour in the beer and broth and reduce by half, 5 to 7 minutes. Stir in the honey and butter; then press the sauce though a fine-mesh sieve set over a serving bowl.</p>
        <p>3. Slice the pork and serve, passing the rhubarb sauce at the table. Serves 4.</p>
        <p>Rhubarb Orange</p>
        <p>14 ounces rhubarb</p>
        <p>1 blood or navel orange</p>
        <p>2 vanilla beans</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons Demerara sugar</p>
        <p>2/3 cup creme fraiche.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat the oven to 300 degrees. Cut the rhubarb into 2-to-2 1/2-inch pieces and place in a medium bowl. Finely grate the zest of half the orange over the rhubarb and then squeeze the juice of the whole orange into the bowl. Split the vanilla beans and scrape out the seeds and place both in the bowl. Add the sugar and stir to combine.</p>
        <p>2. Pour the rhubarb into a baking dish and arrange the pieces so that they lie flat. Bake for 15 to 20 minutes. Remove the vanilla pods. Serve with creme fraiche. Serves 4. Adapted from ''Italian Two Easy: Simple Recipes From the London River Café,'' by Rose Gray and Ruth Rogers.</p>
        <p>Crisp Rhubarb in a Sweet Broth</p>
        <p>1/2 pound rhubarb, very thinly sliced</p>
        <p>1/2 cup white wine</p>
        <p>1 cup sugar, more if needed</p>
        <p>1 cardamom pod, crushed in a mortar and pestle</p>
        <p>1 bag Earl Grey tea</p>
        <p>1 pint strawberries, washed, hulled and cut into wedges</p>
        <p>Vanilla ice cream (optional).</p>
        <p>1. Place the rhubarb in a large, heatproof bowl. Bring 1 cup water, wine and sugar to a boil, stirring to dissolve the sugar. Turn off the heat. Add the cardamom and tea bag and infuse for 15 minutes. Return to a boil and strain over the rhubarb. Cover the bowl with plastic wrap. Let cool and then refrigerate for at least 8 hours.</p>
        <p>2. Before serving, taste the broth -- adding more sugar if desired -- and stir in the strawberries. Ladle into parfait glasses or small shallow bowls. If serving with ice cream, place one scoop in each glass and ladle the rhubarb over it. Serves 4. Adapted from Anne Willan, the owner of Ãcole de Cuisine La Varenne.</p>
        <p>NOTE: If local strawberries are not yet available, either omit them or substitute with another fruit.</p>
        <p>Food: The Way We Eat</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
