<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Victim's Daughter</title>
    <meta content="McKelvey.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/McKelvey.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Bigger Than Life: A Murder, a Memoir (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Victim's Daughter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Victim’s Daughter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARA McKELVEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckelvey, Tara</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BIGGER THAN LIFE</p>
        <p>A Murder, a Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Dinah Lenney.</p>
        <p>227 pp. University of Nebraska Press. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dinah Lenney’s memoir about her murdered father focuses on love, betrayal and money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BIGGER THAN LIFE</p>
        <p>A Murder, a Memoir.</p>
        <p>By Dinah Lenney.</p>
        <p>227 pp. University of Nebraska Press. $24.95.</p>
        <p>September 1997. Dinah Lenney is paying respects in a Hackensack, N.J., funeral home to her father, Nelson Gross, who was an unsuccessful candidate for the United States Senate in 1970, an assistant secretary of state under Richard Nixon and, more recently, a millionaire developer and restaurateur. Gross had been kidnapped and robbed by three teenagers, who later stoned, beat and stabbed him near the Hudson River. His body lay there for a week, Lenney's stepmother, Noel, an equestrian and Guggenheim heiress, tells her on the day of the funeral, adding, ''The animals got to him.''</p>
        <p>The funeral -- followed by a well-attended buffet -- is a scene of almost unimaginable horror and dread. Lenney, in a Valium-induced trance, wanders among a crowd that includes her stepmother, various aunts and uncles, and, surprisingly, her father's mistress, a ''trim and pretty'' golf pro who looks as though she has been crying. ''Every time he buys that woman a plane ticket,'' one of Lenney's aunts says that day, ''Noel buys another horse.''</p>
        <p>Love, betrayal and money are the themes of Lenney's memoir, ''Bigger Than Life,'' written some years after her father's murder and organized in quasi-chronological fashion. Lenney, a self-described ''tycoon's daughter,'' is a struggling 40-something actress in Los Angeles when her father disappears. The book records her activities over a seven-day period as she waits for news about him. She makes peanut butter sandwiches for her two children, talks to the F.B.I. and auditions, successfully, for a role in a prime-time show about a criminal psychologist. During this time, she also traces the relationship she had with her father over the previous three decades.</p>
        <p>Gross clearly loved his daughter, but he did not make things easy on her. Lenney's visits with him and her stepmother were tense (she always knocked before entering the house). He would make Lenney promises -- when she was little, a pony; later, a Ford Pinto -- that he did not fulfill. In 1974, he served time for campaign fraud while she was a student at Yale. Yet she is, understandably, under the spell of her charismatic, bigger-than-life father: a man ''easy in his skin,'' who would always drive a BMW, with an ''all-leather interior'' and ''a car phone way before anybody else had one'' and Frank Sinatra playing on the radio.</p>
        <p>She strove to win her father's affection, which, in her view at least, could be expressed through the purchase of appropriate gifts for her children, or a Cartier watch or a partial down payment on a Hancock Park house. None of which were -- to her disappointment, expressed emphatically -- provided. Her father, for example, once gave her children refrigerator magnets as gifts, after she admonished him for bringing them nothing at all. ''The kids whooped over the magnets as though they were real toys, while I stewed in resentment,'' she writes. ''How dare he bring them refrigerator magnets? How dare they be so delighted just because that's what he brought?''</p>
        <p>''Bigger Than Life,'' which is part of Tobias Wolff's American Lives series, is an uneven, confused memoir, guided by emotional logic and a sense of entitlement. This may work in a therapist's office. (Indeed, a brief scene takes place in one, and three Los Angeles child psychologists also make an appearance.) Sadly, though, Lenney seems unable to process the trauma of her father's murder to the extent necessary for a memoir. Instead, she trips over her own knotty feelings, leaving the reader to flounder as well, and the book's ostensible subject -- her father -- remains hazy. To her dismay, she writes, she comes across a 1991 family video and discovers it reveals little about him: ''As it turned out, I never got out of the way long enough for the camera to linger on my father.'' That is a recurring theme.</p>
        <p>Tara McKelvey, a senior editor at The American Prospect, is a frequent contributor to the Book Review and the author of the forthcoming ''Monstering: Inside America's Policy of Secret Interrogations and Torture in the Terror War.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tara McKelvey, a senior editor at The American Prospect, is a frequent contributor to the Book Review and the author of the forthcoming ''Monstering: Inside America's Policy of Secret Interrogations and Torture in the Terror War.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
