<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now; Buzz Factor: Spykes</title>
    <meta content="29wwln--consumed.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/magazine/29wwlnconsumed.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Consumed"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Celiac Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Caffeine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Celiac Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celiac Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Anheuser-Busch Companies Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EED8173EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now; Buzz Factor: Spykes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Buzz Factor</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This past January, Anheuser-Busch rolled out a new product called Spykes. It comes in two-ounce bottles, in flavors like Spicy Lime and Hot Melons. The label says it's a ''premium malt beverage,'' containing caffeine and ginseng; it's meant to be drunk straight, or used as a mixer with beer, or as an ingredient in some new cocktail of your invention. It's ''whatever you want it to be,'' the new brand's Web site says. Spkyes, in other words, is a hodgepodge of every recent trend or fad that has caught the attention of alcohol consumers in the past five years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new product gets a lot of attention  mostly from vehement critics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This past January, Anheuser-Busch rolled out a new product called Spykes. It comes in two-ounce bottles, in flavors like Spicy Lime and Hot Melons. The label says it's a ''premium malt beverage,'' containing caffeine and ginseng; it's meant to be drunk straight, or used as a mixer with beer, or as an ingredient in some new cocktail of your invention. It's ''whatever you want it to be,'' the new brand's Web site says. Spkyes, in other words, is a hodgepodge of every recent trend or fad that has caught the attention of alcohol consumers in the past five years.</p>
        <p>Like all big beverage companies (alcohol or otherwise), Anheuser-Busch has been on a novelty binge lately, trying to come up with new products to break through to fickle consumers or to capture tiny niches. It has marketed wheat beers, a gluten-free beer for people suffering from Celiac Disease and another specifically for Coloradoans. ''The days of only drinking one beverage throughout your whole drinking life -- it's not there like it used to be,'' explains Pat McGauley, the company's vice president of innovations.</p>
        <p>Most such experiments come and go without ever getting on the mainstream consumer's radar. Spykes is different. Since March, it has received a small gusher of media attention, most of it originating with vehement critics who have charged that it is an attempt to attract under-age drinkers, called for legal action against Anheuser-Busch and labeled Spykes ''liquid lunchables.'' George Hacker, who oversees the alcohol policy project at the Center for Science and the Public Interest, lists several ways Spykes might appeal to young people: sweet flavors (Hot Chocolate is one), the promise of a caffeine boost, the easy-to-conceal size, the ''cute'' packaging. Anheuser-Busch, of course, denies trying to sell to those under age 21 with Spykes or anything else. The critics, Francine Katz, the company's vice president of communications and consumer affairs, says, ''thrive on creating these scary sound bites'' to gain attention for themselves. ''They make a living preying upon the good nature of reporters like you, who give their cause prominence,'' she argues, adding (rather quotably) that they also prey upon ''that portion of the population that thinks Prohibition might not have been a bad idea.''</p>
        <p>Benj Steinman hardly paid attention to Spykes before the sound bites started flying, despite the fact that he's the editor of Beer Marketer's Insights, a trade publication. Spykes was merely one of dozens of attempts to counter the sluggishness of the domestic beer market, he says, but ''no one was talking about it. No one was saying, 'This is selling.' '' Nor had there been any reports of under-age drinkers getting hold of Spykes, which is currently available in less than 2 percent of bars and liquor stores nationwide. Jeff Cronin, the spokesman for the C.S.P.I., says the consumer-advocacy group had to try about 10 liquor stores in the Washington area before it could find the stuff.</p>
        <p>This raises the possibility that in media-blitzing an obscure product, advocacy groups have put it on the map. Cronin acknowledges that possibility but says the idea is to take action before it catches on. ''We have a chance of basically drowning it in the bathtub,'' he says. C.S.P.I.'s Hacker adds that one reason his group and others are particularly keen on going after the likes of Anheuser-Busch is that it has massive marketplace reach and influence, and that its innovations are likely to be imitated.</p>
        <p>On this point Katz offers the surprising argument that, actually, there is nothing new about Spykes. The caffeine content is minimal; flavored drinks are old hat. There are hundreds of these single-serve products, ''all different colors, all different sizes,'' she says. The company even sent me a photograph of Spykes surrounded by other tiny liquor bottles with names like Blue 100 and 99 Bananas Schnapps to suggest just how thoroughly noninnovative this particular product is. ''There's an established category out there.'' The corporate dissonance is inescapable: It's an all-new idea -- but there's a shelf full of precedents? Add the gimmicky misspelling of the name, the vaguely heavy-metal logo and the bottle's resemblance to a trial-size shampoo, and it's hard to say with certainty whom Anheuser-Busch had in mind as the target customer. Perhaps the idea was simply to get the stuff out there and hope it would attract the attention of some niche group or other. And of course it did -- a niche group of people who want it banished.</p>
        <p>Consumed</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
