<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Year In the Life Of a Ballet</title>
    <meta content="29sulc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/arts/dance/29sulc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843613"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sulcas, Roslyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martins, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Ballet</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDB143EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Year In the Life Of a Ballet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Year in the Life of a Ballet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSLYN SULCAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sulcas, Roslyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article provides time line in creation of new ballet, Romeo and Juliet, by Peter Martins for New York City Ballet; each stage from early 2006 to April 2007 discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON Tuesday night, a red carpet will lead up to the New York State Theater for New York City Ballet's gala premiere of Peter Martins's ''Romeo and Juliet.'' Women in couture and their dinner-jacketed companions will smile as cameras flash. Inside, Prokofiev's shivery music will swell, the curtain will rise and the eternal tale of the doomed lovers will take its course.</p>
        <p>To much of the audience, it will be just another night at the ballet -- perhaps an exciting one. But for the dancers, balletmasters, designers, production manager, musicians, stagehands, carpenters, fabric painters, costume-makers, sword-fighting teachers and above all the choreographer, this will be the moment when more than a year of intense thought, planning and activity is put to the test.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A behind-the-scenes look at how City Ballet’s “Romeo and Juliet” took shape.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON Tuesday night, a red carpet will lead up to the New York State Theater for New York City Ballet's gala premiere of Peter Martins's ''Romeo and Juliet.'' Women in couture and their dinner-jacketed companions will smile as cameras flash. Inside, Prokofiev's shivery music will swell, the curtain will rise and the eternal tale of the doomed lovers will take its course.</p>
        <p>To much of the audience, it will be just another night at the ballet -- perhaps an exciting one. But for the dancers, balletmasters, designers, production manager, musicians, stagehands, carpenters, fabric painters, costume-makers, sword-fighting teachers and above all the choreographer, this will be the moment when more than a year of intense thought, planning and activity is put to the test.</p>
        <p>Staging such a large production is like first creating, then fitting together thousands of interlocking jigsaw pieces. However the work is judged by critics, audiences and posterity, the requirements are always the same: money, time and very, very hard work. Here is a partial account of City Ballet's year of creating ''Romeo and Juliet,'' along with some recollections by those involved.</p>
        <p>Early 2006 After asking himself ''whether the world really needs another ''Romeo and Juliet,'' Mr. Martins, balletmaster in chief of City Ballet, decides to talk to Per Kirkeby, the Danish visual artist who worked with him on ''Swan Lake.''</p>
        <p>''Peter said to me, 'I'm thinking of ''Romeo and Juliet,'' but I'll only do it if you are part of it,' '' Mr. Kirkeby later recalls. ''I thought to myself, 'It will be endless time and trouble and decision-making.' Then I said O.K.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Martins, signing on Mr. Kirkeby for the costumes and décor was the easy part. ''Romeo and Juliet'' is his first original full-length ballet. (His ''Sleeping Beauty'' and ''Swan Lake'' were based on traditional versions.) And it is a much-choreographed favorite of choreographers and audiences, a staple for big repertory companies of the kind that City Ballet -- famous for its short, abstract works -- is decidedly not.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Martins, who succeeded George Balanchine as balletmaster in chief in 1983, has been brooding on ''Romeo and Juliet'' for years, watching DVDs of other choreographers' versions and obsessively listening to the score. He has a clear idea of what he wants: One intermission. More ballet. Less crowd action. A single-unit set allowing scene changes before the audience's eyes.</p>
        <p>He talks to Perry Silvey, City Ballet's director of production. ''I'm the one who has to bring every idea back to reality,'' Mr. Silvey says later. ''How many people does it take to open up the unit? What kind of casters does it slide on? How many people can it hold and still be moved easily?''</p>
        <p>In Copenhagen, Mr. Kirkeby begins to design the unit and the backdrops. ''I want it to be painterly, scenic,'' he says. ''It's not a movie.''</p>
        <p>Summer Mr. Martins asks the company's music coordinator, Richard Moredock, to work on the Prokofiev score. ''Theatrically, it's hard in many ways,'' Mr. Moredock said. ''There are a lot of cinematic devices -- people are inside, outside, alone, in a crowd -- without much transition in the libretto. I knew before Peter said anything that he would want only one intermission. That is the biggest challenge musically, since Prokofiev didn't write it that way.''</p>
        <p>In August, Mr. Martins meets Rick Washburn of Weapons Specialists Ltd., a company that provides arms for movies and television and teaches performers how to use them. ''The fights in the ballet are so important in story terms, and yet they are often obviously fake,'' Mr. Martins says. ''I want them to be fierce and realistic.'' Although Mr. Washburn and his partners have never worked with dancers, they agree to take on the project .</p>
        <p>September After a week in Copenhagen with Mr. Kirkeby, Mr. Martins, Mr. Silvey and Mark Stanley, the resident lighting designer, have made significant progress, talking through every scene in the ballet. Mr. Martins decides to have the intermission just before the lovers are wed: ''Afterwards everything goes wrong.''</p>
        <p>After returning to New York, Mr. Martins carries out his most controversial artistic decision: to have leading dancers close to the age of Shakespeare's characters. He tells 16-year-old Callie Bachman, a tiny, blond student at the School of American Ballet, that he would like her to learn the role of Juliet. ''Everyone that I discuss it with says, 'But can she act?' '' he says afterward. ''I keep saying, 'I hope not.' I just want her to be what she is: young.'' Ms. Bachman is, understandably, a little overwhelmed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martins plans to ask Jock Soto and Darci Kistler, both teachers at the school, to play the Capulet parents, in tribute to Lincoln Kirstein, who was president of the school and general director of City Ballet. ''I haven't persuaded them yet,'' he says. (They agree.)</p>
        <p>October The men start to learn basic sword-fighting techniques under the watchful eye of Mr. Washburn and the burly Nigel Poulton. A week later, Mr. Poulton begins to choreograph the fights, based on Mr. Martins's instructions, and Mr. Washburn works on the acting and timing. The dancers practice falling, dying. ''It's so cool to work this stuff out,'' says Robert Fairchild, a 19-year-old corps member, who to his surprise is cast as Romeo. The instructors are impressed by how quickly the dancers pick up themoves. ''Compared to actors,'' Mr. Washburn says, ''they are phenomenal.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Martins has begun to choreograph the ballet's opening scenes, and three other female students from the school are learning Juliet. Mr. Martins runs into frequent difficulties as his young principals, unused to pas de deux work, battle with the tricky partnering. ''There is still plenty of time,'' he says to his balletmaster, Russell Kaiser. If the company dancers are annoyed at being supplanted by adolescents with no stage experience, they are not showing it, although Ms. Bachman admits to feeling ''nerve-racked'' the first time she dances in front of a crowded rehearsal room.</p>
        <p>November and December ''Nutcracker'' performances begin. Mr. Fairchild is amused to find himself performing the role of Mother Ginger, ''in drag and on stilts,'' by night and rehearsing Romeo by day. Mr. Martins, Mr. Silvey and Mr. Stanley leave for Copenhagen for another round of design refinements. The set unit becomes smaller.</p>
        <p>''It's huge!'' Mr. Martins exclaims as he sees the unit for the first time in the cavernous Hudson Scenic Studio in Yonkers. ''It looks different from the model. And why is there so little space behind it?'' Mr. Silvey explains that the machinery is positioned behind the set, requiring eight stagehands to remain there throughout the ballet. ''I might have to rechoreograph,'' Mr. Martins says. ''That's what you are here for,'' Mr. Silvey replies.</p>
        <p>January and February Kirsten Lund Nielsen, who is assisting Mr. Kirkeby, has arrived to confer with Marc Happel, the director of costumes at City Ballet, and Holly Hynes, who is coordinating the costume-making. Most of the fabrics are being made in Denmark because Mr. Kirkeby wants particular effects, but the costumes will be made in New York by City Ballet and three outside workshops. There are also boots, gloves, headpieces and sword belts to think about. Ms. Hynes scribblesconstantly in a notebook. Mr. Stanley points out that the colors of Romeo's and Benvolio's costumes will look the same under the lights.</p>
        <p>In the rehearsal rooms, things are not going smoothly. Mr. Martins has fractured his wrist ice-skating with his daughter and cannot demonstrate the intricacies of the partnering to his novice men. Ms. Bachman has hurt her knee. Nonetheless, most of the first act has been choreographed by the time a vital week of stage rehearsals starts at the end of the winter season.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirkeby arrives and goes to Scenic Art Studios in Cornwall, N.Y., where his drops have been painted. The linen fabric is laid flat over stage-size areas, and painters walk over them, applying color with broom-size brushes. The designs are pinned up on a board: the painters have divided them into grids, then expanded the scale as they paint each square separately. Each drop has taken about three weeks.</p>
        <p>''This is really good,'' Mr. Kirkeby says. Then he begins to daub pink and red paint all over the wing drops.</p>
        <p>The week of stage rehearsals is the production team's only opportunity to see ''Romeo'' onstage until just before performances. It is vital for Mr. Stanley, whose lighting plot is all theory until he sees sets and costumes onstage. It is also the only chance to train the stagehands who will move the unit. ''I am the balletmaster for the stagehands,'' Mr. Silvey says. ''They joke that they work better when they hear the music, and it's true. It's like choreography for the set.'' By the end of the week, transitions between scenes are still not seamless. ''We'll have to work it out at the end,'' Mr. Silvey says.</p>
        <p>March and April The dancers have returned from their spring break, and Ms. Bachman has again injured her knee. Mr. Martins is worried. ''I realized that if Callie wasn't my first cast, I had to call on company dancers,'' he said. Sterling Hyltin, a soloist, is asked to learn the part, as are Tiler Peck, a soloist, and Kathryn Morgan, a corps member. One of the students, Erica Pereira, now a company apprentice, is retained.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martins begins to work on Act 2 with Ms. Hyltin, who takes to the drama with alacrity. Ms. Bachman is still marking the role in the background, hoping to be able to dance, but in mid-April Mr. Martins tells her she could endanger her career by dancing with an injury. She behaves like a seasoned professional. ''I have learned a lot,'' she says bravely, ''and it was really fun and exciting.''</p>
        <p>The second act is finished. The costumes have arrived, and the entire team scrutinizes all 77 as the dancers stand, looking self-conscious. Romeo's color has been changed. Ms. Hynes scribbles more notes.</p>
        <p>As the first night draws closer, tension is palpable inside the studios as conductors and Mr. Silvey come and go. Mr. Martins remains unflappable, appearing to enjoy himself as he vividly demonstrates character nuances. But Fayçal Karoui, the company's music director, comments: ''Of course Peter is very nervous. That's normal.'' Ms. Hyltin says she has just realized what a big deal this is: ''When I saw all the posters, I suddenly thought, I am Juliet.''</p>
        <p>One week before Sunday night's open dress rehearsal, thousands line up on a sunny Sunday morning for free tickets. Inside the theater, rehearsals go on. With just nine days until the premiere, there is still much to do.</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
