<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="29listingsLILI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843629"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDF153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Nassau and Suffolk Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to lical@nytimes.com, or by mail to Long Island Weekly, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bay Shore Judy Collins, folk. April 29 at 3 and 7 p.m. $50. Kenny Rankin, singer-songwriter. Friday at 8 p.m. $30. Liz Callaway, vocalist. May 5 at 8 p.m. $35. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>Bay Shore Walter Hilse, organ; works by Buxtehude, Bach, Franck and others. May 6 at 4 p.m. $15; seniors and students, $10. St. Peter's Episcopal Church, 500 South Country Road. (631) 361-3393.</p>
        <p>Brookville Handel's ''Joshua,'' presented by the Great Neck Choral Society. May 6 at 4 p.m. $20. St. Paul the Apostle Roman Catholic Church, Cedar Swamp Road. (516) 536-0451.</p>
        <p>Brookville Festival concert, C. W. Post Band, James W. McRoy and Joel M. Levy, conductors. April 29 at 3 p.m. $8; $5 students. Vladimir Feltsman, piano; works by Beethoven and Mussorgsky. May 5 at 8 p.m. $45 to $90. Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, 720 Northern Boulevard, C. W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Centerport King Wilkie, bluegrass. May 5 at 7:30 p.m. $25; members, $20. Congregational Church of Huntington, 30 Washington Drive. (631) 425-2925.</p>
        <p>Dix Hills ''Mostly Barbershop,'' presented by the Five Towns College's A Cappella Ensembles, the Long Island Sound Men's Chorus and the Island Hills Chorus of Sweet Adelines International. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Five Towns College's Chamber Orchestra. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. ''An Evening of Jazz,'' presented by the Five Towns College's Jazz Orchestra and Vocal Jazz Ensembles. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. All: $10. Five Towns College's Choral Festival. May 5 at 7:30 p.m. $10. Dix Hills Center for the Performing Arts, 305 North Service Road. (631) 656-2148.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale Badfish, Sublime tribute band. May 6 at 6 p.m. $15 to $17. Crazy Donkey, 1058 Route 110. (631) 753-1975.</p>
        <p>Freeport Galliard Brass Ensemble; works by Bach, Wagner and Rodgers and Hammerstein. May 5 at 8 p.m. $20. Freeport High School, 50 South Brookside Avenue. (516) 223-7659.</p>
        <p>Garden City Bethany Yarrow and Rufus Cappadocia, cello and vocal folk duo. Friday at 8 p.m. $15. Unitarian Universalist Church of Central Nassau, 223 Stewart Avenue. (516) 248-8855.</p>
        <p>Huntington Bob James and Angels of Shanghai, jazz and traditional Chinese fusion. May 5 at 8 p.m. $37.50. Inter-Media Art Center, 370 New York Avenue. (631) 549-2787.</p>
        <p>Northport ''Opera Signatures: Lessons in Love From Mozart, Puccini, Bizet, Mascagni, Verdi, Bellini and Massenet,'' presented by the Northport Opera Company. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $20; seniors, $15; children under 16, $5; Veterans, free. Northport VA Medical Center Building Auditorium, 79 Middleville Road. (631) 327-1833.</p>
        <p>Old Westbury ''Great Sounds of Jazz,'' presented by the Agora Quartet. April 29 at 3 p.m. Free. Salten Hall, New York Institute of Technology, Old Westbury Campus, Northern Boulevard. (516) 686-7640.</p>
        <p>Patchogue ''Spring Spectacular,'' presented by the Atlantic Wind Symphony. April 29 at 3 p.m. $15; seniors and students, $12. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Port Jefferson Rudy Perrone, guitar. May 6 at 7:30 p.m. $25. Theater Three, 412 Main Street. (631) 928-9100.</p>
        <p>Sea Cliff The Omega Ensemble, with Denise Djokic, cello, and Nurit Pacht, violin. May 5 at 8 p.m. $15 to $25. Sea Cliff United Methodist Church, Downing and Carpenter Avenue. (516) 944-8995.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Annual Chamber Music Festival with the Emerson String Quartet, master classes and daily performances. Wednesday through May 5. Free. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>West Islip ''Spring Celebration,'' presented by the West Islip Symphony Orchestra, with Jason Dobranski, cello. May 6 at 3 p.m. $10; students, free. Beach Street Middle School, 17 Beach Street. (631) 661-8348.</p>
        <p>Westbury Gordon Lightfoot, folk. April 29 at 7 p.m. $45 to $55. North Fork Theater, 960 Brush Hollow Road. (516) 334-0800.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Bellport ''The Nerd'' by Larry Shue, presented by the Playcrafters. Through May 5. $12 to $25. Bellport Middle School Auditorium, Kreamer Street and Station Road. (631) 924-8516.</p>
        <p>Dix Hills ''Little Women,'' musical by Allan Knee, Mindi Dickstein and Jason Howland, adapted from the book by Louisa May Alcott, directed by Ryan McKinny. April 29. $15; seniors and students, $12. Dix Hills Center for the Performing Arts, 305 North Service Road. (631) 656-2148.</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''Blood Moon,'' by Nicholas Kazan. Through June 3. $18 and $22. ''Another Antigone,'' by A.R. Gurney. Through May 13. $16 to $22. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>Islip ''Proof'' by David Auburn, presented by the Synergy Ensemble Theater Company. Through May 12. $5; seniors, $3. Islip Town Hall Theater, 401 Main Street. (631) 224-5430.</p>
        <p>Northport Neil Simon's ''Last of the Red Hot Lovers,'' presented by the Brookhaven Players. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Northport Public Library, 151 Laurel Avenue. (631) 261-6930.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''Crazy for You,'' musical by Ken Ludwig, George Gershwin and Ira Gershwin. Through May 6. $20; seniors, $18; students, $16. CM Performing Arts Center, 931 Montauk Highway. (631) 218-2810.</p>
        <p>Patchogue ''The Waverly Gallery,'' by Kenneth Lonergan. Through May 12. $14; seniors and students, $12. Clare Rose Theater, St. Joseph's College, Suffolk Campus. (631) 654-0199.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Shakespeare's ''As You Like It,'' directed by Valeri Lantz-Gefroh. Through April 29. $7 and $12. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Brookville ''Faith, Love and Hope,'' documentary about an orphanage in Kenya, directed by Garrett Chapman. Friday at 7 p.m. Free. Hillwood Art Museum Cinema, C. W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-4073.</p>
        <p>Westhampton Beach Finest in World Cinema Series: ''Avenue Montaigne,'' directed by Danièle Thompson. Friday through May 6. $3 to $10. Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center, 76 Main Street. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>Hempstead Dutch Festival; tulip viewing, face painting, music, dance, crafts and Dutch refreshments. May 6, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. $3. Hofstra University South Campus, (516) 463-6644.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Birds and Botany for Beginners,'' adult nature program; bring binoculars. May 6 at 9:30 a.m. $3; reservations required. Caumsett State Historic Park, 25 Lloyd Harbor Road. (631) 423-1770.</p>
        <p>Oyster Bay Arbor Day Festival, with the National Circus Project, tree planting and a family concert. April 29, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. $5; children, $1. Planting Fields Arboretum State Historic Park, 1395 Planting Fields Road. (516) 922-9200.</p>
        <p>Smithtown ''Bird and Breakfast,'' birding basics and continental breakfast followed by observation walk. May 6 at 9 a.m. $3; reservations required. Caleb Smith State Park Preserve, Jericho Turnpike. (631) 265-1054.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>East Hills Jeff Goldberg, author of ''Prisoners: A Muslim and Jew Across the Middle East Divide.'' May1 at 7:30 p.m. $18; members, $15. Sid Jacobson Jewish Community Center, 300 Forest Drive. (516) 484-1545.</p>
        <p>Greenlawn Tom Philbin, author of ''Two Minutes to Glory: The Official History of the Kentucky Derby.'' Tuesday at 7 p.m. Free. Harborfields Public Library, 31 Broadway. (631) 757-4200.</p>
        <p>Huntington Tom Philbin, author of ''Two Minutes to Glory: The Official History of the Kentucky Derby.'' Wednesday at 8 p.m. Tim Gunn, author of ''Tim Gunn: A Guide to Quality, Taste and Style.'' Thursday at 8 p.m. Bruce Dern, author of ''Things I've Said, But Probably Shouldn't Have: An Unrepentant Memoir.'' Friday at 8 p.m. Free. Book Revue, 313 New York Avenue. (631) 271-1442.</p>
        <p>Patchogue Jeffrey Wands, psychic. Monday at 7 p.m. $35. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Port Jefferson ''Masterpiece,'' by M. Z. Ribalow, staged reading presented by the New River Dramatists. May 5 at 3 p.m. Free. Theater Three, 412 Main Street. (631) 928-9100.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bridgehampton ''Build a Bird's Nest,'' family workshop. All ages. May 5 at 10 a.m. $7; children, $3. South Fork Natural History Museum, 377 Bridgehampton/Sag Harbor Turnpike. (631) 537-9735.</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''Velveteen Rabbit,'' adapted from the story by Margery Williams. Through May 27. $8. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Beauty and the Beast,'' children's play followed by tea party. Saturdays through May 5. $8; $20 for show and tea party. BayWay Arts Center, 265 East Main Street. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale ''You're a Good Man, Charlie Brown,'' family musical presented by the Backstage Theater Company. May 5 at 8 p.m. $10; seniors, students and children under 12, $5. Roosevelt Hall Little Theater, 2350 Broadhollow Road, Farmingdale State College. (631) 420-2400.</p>
        <p>Garden City ''Museum Row Family Festival,'' outdoor activities, emergency vehicle display, puppets, food and games; co-sponsored by the Cradle of Aviation and the Nassau County Firefighters Museum. All ages. May 5 and 6, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. $10. ''Broadway for Families,'' introduction to musical theater. Ages 5 and up. May 5 at 1:30 p.m. $5; $3 with museum admission. Seventh Annual Folk Arts Series Family Program: Indian folk dance and music workshop. Ages 4 and up. May 6 at 11 a.m. Classical and Bollywood dance performed by the Young Indian Cultural Group. Ages 4 and up. May 6 at 1 p.m. $5; $3 with museum admission. Long Island Children's Museum, 11 Davis Avenue. (516) 224-5800.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Who's Doing the Blooming?'' Learn about flowers, take a walk and make a craft. Ages 5 and up. May 5 at 10 a.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. ''Flutterbys,'' learn about butterflies. Ages 5 and up. May 5 at 2 p.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Caumsett State Historic Park, 25 Lloyd Harbor Road. (631) 423-1770.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Sheep to Shawl Festival,'' demonstrations of sheep shearing and weaving, petting zoo, crafts, food and entertainment. All ages. May 6, noon to 4 p.m. Free. Daniel Kissam House Museum, 434 Park Avenue. (631) 427-7045, Extension 401.</p>
        <p>Lindenhurst ''Aladdin,'' children's theater followed by a tea party. Saturdays through May 19. $8; $20 for show and tea party. Studio Theater, 141 South Wellwood Avenue. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Long Beach ''Tracks and Traces.'' Learn to read animal clues and create a track book to take home. Ages 6 to 12. May 5 at 10:30 a.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Theodore Roosevelt Nature Center, Ocean Parkway. (516) 679-7254.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''This Old Nest!'' Walk to view nests and young wildlife. All ages. May 5 at 9:30 a.m. ''Windcatchers.'' Learn about wind through games and activities. Ages 5 and up. May 6 at 9:30 a.m. Both: $3; children, $2; reservations required. Connetquot River State Park, Sunrise Highway. (631) 581-1005.</p>
        <p>St. James Drop in Arts Nights: Create a Mother's Day craft. Friday at 7 p.m. $5. Mills Pond House Gallery, 660 Route 25A. (631) 862-6575.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Lazer Vaudeville, juggling, acrobatics, magic and lasers. May 6 at 1 and 4 p.m. $10. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Amagansett ''William King: Sculpture.'' Through May 28. Hours: Fridays through Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Pamela Williams Gallery, 167 Main Street. (631) 267-7817.</p>
        <p>Dix Hills ''Visionary Anatomies,'' works by 11 artists inspired by human anatomical imagery. Through May 31. Reception: April 29, 3 to 5 p.m. Jeanie Tengelsen Gallery, 107 East Deer Park Road. (631) 462-5400.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Surface Impressions,'' works by artists exploring the idea of surface in canvas, sculpture and mixed media. Through June 3. Donation: $3. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Islip Art Museum, 50 Irish Lane. (631) 224-5402.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Joyce Kubat: Ink Drawings.'' Wednesday through May 26. Reception: May 5, 2 to 4 p.m. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Alpan Gallery, 2 West Carver Street. (631) 423-4433.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Long Island's Best: Young Artists at the Heckscher,'' works by high school students. Through May 6. $5; seniors, $3; children ages 5 to 12, $1; under 5, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 8:30 p.m. Heckscher Museum of Art, 2 Prime Avenue. (631) 351-3250.</p>
        <p>Locust Valley ''Frank Olt: Recent Works.'' Through May 10. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Lynda Anderson Galleries, 92 Forest Avenue. (516) 802-3552.</p>
        <p>Rockville Centre ''Irrevocable,'' works by graduating senior art students. May 6 through June 30. Free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Molloy College Art Gallery, 1000 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 678-5000.</p>
        <p>Roslyn Harbor ''Rembrandt to Rosenquist: The Masters of Printmaking.'' Through May 13. ''Twenty-First Century Prints,'' works by Elizabeth Peyton, John Currin and other contemporary printmakers. Through May 13. Admission: $4 to $10; children under 5 and members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4:45 p.m. Nassau County Museum of Art, 1 Museum Drive. (516) 484-9337.</p>
        <p>Southampton Works by Irene Zevon. Through Monday. Free. ''Tschacbasov: Prints and Works on Paper.'' May 5 through 28. Reception: May 5, 5 to 8 p.m. Free. Hours: Daily, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Bravura Art and Objects, 22 Nugent Street. (631) 259-2605.</p>
        <p>Southampton ''Raymond Loewy: Designs for a Consumer Culture,'' works by the 20th-century industrial designer. Through May 27. $7; seniors and students, $5; children under 18, free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Parrish Art Museum, 25 Job's Lane. (631) 283-2118, Extension 32.</p>
        <p>Southampton ''Anatomy of a Whale,'' work created by elementary school students. Through May 19. $4; seniors, $3; students, $2. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Southampton Historical Museum, 17 Meeting House Lane. (631) 283-2494.</p>
        <p>Uniondale ''Evocative Space of the Familiar,'' works by Charles Blake, Carmela Kolman and Robert Mielenhausen. Through May 18. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 6:30 p.m. Omni Gallery, 333 Earle Ovington Boulevard. (631) 589-3093.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Nassau and Suffolk Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to lical@nytimes.com, or by mail to Long Island Weekly, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bay Shore Judy Collins, folk. April 29 at 3 and 7 p.m. $50. Kenny Rankin, singer-songwriter. Friday at 8 p.m. $30. Liz Callaway, vocalist. May 5 at 8 p.m. $35. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>Bay Shore Walter Hilse, organ; works by Buxtehude, Bach, Franck and others. May 6 at 4 p.m. $15; seniors and students, $10. St. Peter's Episcopal Church, 500 South Country Road. (631) 361-3393.</p>
        <p>Brookville Handel's ''Joshua,'' presented by the Great Neck Choral Society. May 6 at 4 p.m. $20. St. Paul the Apostle Roman Catholic Church, Cedar Swamp Road. (516) 536-0451.</p>
        <p>Brookville Festival concert, C. W. Post Band, James W. McRoy and Joel M. Levy, conductors. April 29 at 3 p.m. $8; $5 students. Vladimir Feltsman, piano; works by Beethoven and Mussorgsky. May 5 at 8 p.m. $45 to $90. Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, 720 Northern Boulevard, C. W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Centerport King Wilkie, bluegrass. May 5 at 7:30 p.m. $25; members, $20. Congregational Church of Huntington, 30 Washington Drive. (631) 425-2925.</p>
        <p>Dix Hills ''Mostly Barbershop,'' presented by the Five Towns College's A Cappella Ensembles, the Long Island Sound Men's Chorus and the Island Hills Chorus of Sweet Adelines International. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Five Towns College's Chamber Orchestra. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. ''An Evening of Jazz,'' presented by the Five Towns College's Jazz Orchestra and Vocal Jazz Ensembles. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. All: $10. Five Towns College's Choral Festival. May 5 at 7:30 p.m. $10. Dix Hills Center for the Performing Arts, 305 North Service Road. (631) 656-2148.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale Badfish, Sublime tribute band. May 6 at 6 p.m. $15 to $17. Crazy Donkey, 1058 Route 110. (631) 753-1975.</p>
        <p>Freeport Galliard Brass Ensemble; works by Bach, Wagner and Rodgers and Hammerstein. May 5 at 8 p.m. $20. Freeport High School, 50 South Brookside Avenue. (516) 223-7659.</p>
        <p>Garden City Bethany Yarrow and Rufus Cappadocia, cello and vocal folk duo. Friday at 8 p.m. $15. Unitarian Universalist Church of Central Nassau, 223 Stewart Avenue. (516) 248-8855.</p>
        <p>Huntington Bob James and Angels of Shanghai, jazz and traditional Chinese fusion. May 5 at 8 p.m. $37.50. Inter-Media Art Center, 370 New York Avenue. (631) 549-2787.</p>
        <p>Northport ''Opera Signatures: Lessons in Love From Mozart, Puccini, Bizet, Mascagni, Verdi, Bellini and Massenet,'' presented by the Northport Opera Company. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $20; seniors, $15; children under 16, $5; Veterans, free. Northport VA Medical Center Building Auditorium, 79 Middleville Road. (631) 327-1833.</p>
        <p>Old Westbury ''Great Sounds of Jazz,'' presented by the Agora Quartet. April 29 at 3 p.m. Free. Salten Hall, New York Institute of Technology, Old Westbury Campus, Northern Boulevard. (516) 686-7640.</p>
        <p>Patchogue ''Spring Spectacular,'' presented by the Atlantic Wind Symphony. April 29 at 3 p.m. $15; seniors and students, $12. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Port Jefferson Rudy Perrone, guitar. May 6 at 7:30 p.m. $25. Theater Three, 412 Main Street. (631) 928-9100.</p>
        <p>Sea Cliff The Omega Ensemble, with Denise Djokic, cello, and Nurit Pacht, violin. May 5 at 8 p.m. $15 to $25. Sea Cliff United Methodist Church, Downing and Carpenter Avenue. (516) 944-8995.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Annual Chamber Music Festival with the Emerson String Quartet, master classes and daily performances. Wednesday through May 5. Free. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>West Islip ''Spring Celebration,'' presented by the West Islip Symphony Orchestra, with Jason Dobranski, cello. May 6 at 3 p.m. $10; students, free. Beach Street Middle School, 17 Beach Street. (631) 661-8348.</p>
        <p>Westbury Gordon Lightfoot, folk. April 29 at 7 p.m. $45 to $55. North Fork Theater, 960 Brush Hollow Road. (516) 334-0800.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Bellport ''The Nerd'' by Larry Shue, presented by the Playcrafters. Through May 5. $12 to $25. Bellport Middle School Auditorium, Kreamer Street and Station Road. (631) 924-8516.</p>
        <p>Dix Hills ''Little Women,'' musical by Allan Knee, Mindi Dickstein and Jason Howland, adapted from the book by Louisa May Alcott, directed by Ryan McKinny. April 29. $15; seniors and students, $12. Dix Hills Center for the Performing Arts, 305 North Service Road. (631) 656-2148.</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''Blood Moon,'' by Nicholas Kazan. Through June 3. $18 and $22. ''Another Antigone,'' by A.R. Gurney. Through May 13. $16 to $22. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>Islip ''Proof'' by David Auburn, presented by the Synergy Ensemble Theater Company. Through May 12. $5; seniors, $3. Islip Town Hall Theater, 401 Main Street. (631) 224-5430.</p>
        <p>Northport Neil Simon's ''Last of the Red Hot Lovers,'' presented by the Brookhaven Players. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Northport Public Library, 151 Laurel Avenue. (631) 261-6930.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''Crazy for You,'' musical by Ken Ludwig, George Gershwin and Ira Gershwin. Through May 6. $20; seniors, $18; students, $16. CM Performing Arts Center, 931 Montauk Highway. (631) 218-2810.</p>
        <p>Patchogue ''The Waverly Gallery,'' by Kenneth Lonergan. Through May 12. $14; seniors and students, $12. Clare Rose Theater, St. Joseph's College, Suffolk Campus. (631) 654-0199.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Shakespeare's ''As You Like It,'' directed by Valeri Lantz-Gefroh. Through April 29. $7 and $12. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Brookville ''Faith, Love and Hope,'' documentary about an orphanage in Kenya, directed by Garrett Chapman. Friday at 7 p.m. Free. Hillwood Art Museum Cinema, C. W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-4073.</p>
        <p>Westhampton Beach Finest in World Cinema Series: ''Avenue Montaigne,'' directed by Danièle Thompson. Friday through May 6. $3 to $10. Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center, 76 Main Street. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>Hempstead Dutch Festival; tulip viewing, face painting, music, dance, crafts and Dutch refreshments. May 6, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. $3. Hofstra University South Campus, (516) 463-6644.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Birds and Botany for Beginners,'' adult nature program; bring binoculars. May 6 at 9:30 a.m. $3; reservations required. Caumsett State Historic Park, 25 Lloyd Harbor Road. (631) 423-1770.</p>
        <p>Oyster Bay Arbor Day Festival, with the National Circus Project, tree planting and a family concert. April 29, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. $5; children, $1. Planting Fields Arboretum State Historic Park, 1395 Planting Fields Road. (516) 922-9200.</p>
        <p>Smithtown ''Bird and Breakfast,'' birding basics and continental breakfast followed by observation walk. May 6 at 9 a.m. $3; reservations required. Caleb Smith State Park Preserve, Jericho Turnpike. (631) 265-1054.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>East Hills Jeff Goldberg, author of ''Prisoners: A Muslim and Jew Across the Middle East Divide.'' May1 at 7:30 p.m. $18; members, $15. Sid Jacobson Jewish Community Center, 300 Forest Drive. (516) 484-1545.</p>
        <p>Greenlawn Tom Philbin, author of ''Two Minutes to Glory: The Official History of the Kentucky Derby.'' Tuesday at 7 p.m. Free. Harborfields Public Library, 31 Broadway. (631) 757-4200.</p>
        <p>Huntington Tom Philbin, author of ''Two Minutes to Glory: The Official History of the Kentucky Derby.'' Wednesday at 8 p.m. Tim Gunn, author of ''Tim Gunn: A Guide to Quality, Taste and Style.'' Thursday at 8 p.m. Bruce Dern, author of ''Things I've Said, But Probably Shouldn't Have: An Unrepentant Memoir.'' Friday at 8 p.m. Free. Book Revue, 313 New York Avenue. (631) 271-1442.</p>
        <p>Patchogue Jeffrey Wands, psychic. Monday at 7 p.m. $35. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Port Jefferson ''Masterpiece,'' by M. Z. Ribalow, staged reading presented by the New River Dramatists. May 5 at 3 p.m. Free. Theater Three, 412 Main Street. (631) 928-9100.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bridgehampton ''Build a Bird's Nest,'' family workshop. All ages. May 5 at 10 a.m. $7; children, $3. South Fork Natural History Museum, 377 Bridgehampton/Sag Harbor Turnpike. (631) 537-9735.</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''Velveteen Rabbit,'' adapted from the story by Margery Williams. Through May 27. $8. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Beauty and the Beast,'' children's play followed by tea party. Saturdays through May 5. $8; $20 for show and tea party. BayWay Arts Center, 265 East Main Street. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale ''You're a Good Man, Charlie Brown,'' family musical presented by the Backstage Theater Company. May 5 at 8 p.m. $10; seniors, students and children under 12, $5. Roosevelt Hall Little Theater, 2350 Broadhollow Road, Farmingdale State College. (631) 420-2400.</p>
        <p>Garden City ''Museum Row Family Festival,'' outdoor activities, emergency vehicle display, puppets, food and games; co-sponsored by the Cradle of Aviation and the Nassau County Firefighters Museum. All ages. May 5 and 6, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. $10. ''Broadway for Families,'' introduction to musical theater. Ages 5 and up. May 5 at 1:30 p.m. $5; $3 with museum admission. Seventh Annual Folk Arts Series Family Program: Indian folk dance and music workshop. Ages 4 and up. May 6 at 11 a.m. Classical and Bollywood dance performed by the Young Indian Cultural Group. Ages 4 and up. May 6 at 1 p.m. $5; $3 with museum admission. Long Island Children's Museum, 11 Davis Avenue. (516) 224-5800.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Who's Doing the Blooming?'' Learn about flowers, take a walk and make a craft. Ages 5 and up. May 5 at 10 a.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. ''Flutterbys,'' learn about butterflies. Ages 5 and up. May 5 at 2 p.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Caumsett State Historic Park, 25 Lloyd Harbor Road. (631) 423-1770.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Sheep to Shawl Festival,'' demonstrations of sheep shearing and weaving, petting zoo, crafts, food and entertainment. All ages. May 6, noon to 4 p.m. Free. Daniel Kissam House Museum, 434 Park Avenue. (631) 427-7045, Extension 401.</p>
        <p>Lindenhurst ''Aladdin,'' children's theater followed by a tea party. Saturdays through May 19. $8; $20 for show and tea party. Studio Theater, 141 South Wellwood Avenue. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Long Beach ''Tracks and Traces.'' Learn to read animal clues and create a track book to take home. Ages 6 to 12. May 5 at 10:30 a.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Theodore Roosevelt Nature Center, Ocean Parkway. (516) 679-7254.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''This Old Nest!'' Walk to view nests and young wildlife. All ages. May 5 at 9:30 a.m. ''Windcatchers.'' Learn about wind through games and activities. Ages 5 and up. May 6 at 9:30 a.m. Both: $3; children, $2; reservations required. Connetquot River State Park, Sunrise Highway. (631) 581-1005.</p>
        <p>St. James Drop in Arts Nights: Create a Mother's Day craft. Friday at 7 p.m. $5. Mills Pond House Gallery, 660 Route 25A. (631) 862-6575.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Lazer Vaudeville, juggling, acrobatics, magic and lasers. May 6 at 1 and 4 p.m. $10. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Amagansett ''William King: Sculpture.'' Through May 28. Hours: Fridays through Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Pamela Williams Gallery, 167 Main Street. (631) 267-7817.</p>
        <p>Dix Hills ''Visionary Anatomies,'' works by 11 artists inspired by human anatomical imagery. Through May 31. Reception: April 29, 3 to 5 p.m. Jeanie Tengelsen Gallery, 107 East Deer Park Road. (631) 462-5400.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Surface Impressions,'' works by artists exploring the idea of surface in canvas, sculpture and mixed media. Through June 3. Donation: $3. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Islip Art Museum, 50 Irish Lane. (631) 224-5402.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Joyce Kubat: Ink Drawings.'' Wednesday through May 26. Reception: May 5, 2 to 4 p.m. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Alpan Gallery, 2 West Carver Street. (631) 423-4433.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Long Island's Best: Young Artists at the Heckscher,'' works by high school students. Through May 6. $5; seniors, $3; children ages 5 to 12, $1; under 5, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 8:30 p.m. Heckscher Museum of Art, 2 Prime Avenue. (631) 351-3250.</p>
        <p>Locust Valley ''Frank Olt: Recent Works.'' Through May 10. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Lynda Anderson Galleries, 92 Forest Avenue. (516) 802-3552.</p>
        <p>Rockville Centre ''Irrevocable,'' works by graduating senior art students. May 6 through June 30. Free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Molloy College Art Gallery, 1000 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 678-5000.</p>
        <p>Roslyn Harbor ''Rembrandt to Rosenquist: The Masters of Printmaking.'' Through May 13. ''Twenty-First Century Prints,'' works by Elizabeth Peyton, John Currin and other contemporary printmakers. Through May 13. Admission: $4 to $10; children under 5 and members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4:45 p.m. Nassau County Museum of Art, 1 Museum Drive. (516) 484-9337.</p>
        <p>Southampton Works by Irene Zevon. Through Monday. Free. ''Tschacbasov: Prints and Works on Paper.'' May 5 through 28. Reception: May 5, 5 to 8 p.m. Free. Hours: Daily, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Bravura Art and Objects, 22 Nugent Street. (631) 259-2605.</p>
        <p>Southampton ''Raymond Loewy: Designs for a Consumer Culture,'' works by the 20th-century industrial designer. Through May 27. $7; seniors and students, $5; children under 18, free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Parrish Art Museum, 25 Job's Lane. (631) 283-2118, Extension 32.</p>
        <p>Southampton ''Anatomy of a Whale,'' work created by elementary school students. Through May 19. $4; seniors, $3; students, $2. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Southampton Historical Museum, 17 Meeting House Lane. (631) 283-2494.</p>
        <p>Uniondale ''Evocative Space of the Familiar,'' works by Charles Blake, Carmela Kolman and Robert Mielenhausen. Through May 18. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 6:30 p.m. Omni Gallery, 333 Earle Ovington Boulevard. (631) 589-3093.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
