<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cardinal's Mission, and the Church's Finances</title>
    <meta content="l29egan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4D7123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cardinal's Mission, and the Church's Finances</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''At 75, a Battle-Tested but Unwavering Cardinal'' (front page, April 23):</p>
        <p>Cardinal Edward M. Egan feels that the finances of the Archdiocese of New York are his secret to keep -- or to share only with those he calls ''the best possible people.'' But membership in the Catholic Church that Cardinal Egan serves is not limited to ''the best possible people.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''At 75, a Battle-Tested but Unwavering Cardinal'' (front page, April 23):</p>
        <p>Cardinal Edward M. Egan feels that the finances of the Archdiocese of New York are his secret to keep -- or to share only with those he calls ''the best possible people.'' But membership in the Catholic Church that Cardinal Egan serves is not limited to ''the best possible people.''</p>
        <p>Money in the archdiocesan accounts is contributed by all of the church's people, and the financial decisions made (from closing parishes to settling lawsuits) affect all of the church's people.</p>
        <p>The ''point'' of public inspection of the archdiocesan financial records is to prevent scandalous cover-ups and payoffs. The point is to give grieving people the courtesy of a straight answer when they ask why their parishes must be closed.</p>
        <p>The point is to allow me -- perhaps not one of ''the best possible people,'' but a baptized person nonetheless -- to know what decisions are being made in my name, with my contribution.</p>
        <p>I don't think I would have as much ''fun'' poring over the archdiocese's records as Cardinal Egan suggests, but I would enjoy knowing that my church was protected from further mismanagement and corruption, and that my place in it was respected.</p>
        <p>Mollie Wilson  New York, April 23, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The measure of a religious leader is fidelity to the mission.</p>
        <p>As an old classmate and colleague of Cardinal Edward M. Egan from our days of working in the Vatican Council, I commend him for a private life filled with charity and graciousness led behind an uncomfortable public facade.</p>
        <p>The mission to the city and the faithful of New York has been nothing less than frightening. The city churned with demographic changes, cultural rifts and tragedy of historic proportions, while the church has been mortified by unspeakable scandals in positions of the most tender trust.</p>
        <p>Success of the seven-year mission cannot be appraised by the banker's quotient, as your article tries to do.</p>
        <p>The mission was to the whole church, not just the city, as well as for charities all over this country. The mission was to nourish and support religious conscience in the face of rampant and cruel consumerism.</p>
        <p>I say only God can be sure; we, however, send our warmest congratulations to our learned, talented and feisty Eddy, the cardinal.</p>
        <p>William W. Bassett  San Francisco, April 24, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
