<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Air, a Very Public Failure</title>
    <meta content="29HINDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/automobiles/29HINDEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HYDROGEN'S SECOND COMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E4D6153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Air, a Very Public Failure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Air, a Very Public Failure</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sherman, Don</byline>
      <dateline>LAKEHURST, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE May 6, 1937, crash of the Hindenburg at the Navy base here was the 20th century's first transportation disaster captured by newsreel, audio recordings and still photos.</p>
        <p>The advancement in communications, combined with the observations of more than a thousand witnesses and survivors, is why one calamity with a relatively modest death toll permanently soiled hydrogen's reputation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The image of the Hindenburg crash colored the public’s view of hydrogen for decades. But was hydrogen really to blame?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE May 6, 1937, crash of the Hindenburg at the Navy base here was the 20th century's first transportation disaster captured by newsreel, audio recordings and still photos.</p>
        <p>The advancement in communications, combined with the observations of more than a thousand witnesses and survivors, is why one calamity with a relatively modest death toll permanently soiled hydrogen's reputation.</p>
        <p>In 34 fiery seconds, hydrogen leaped from the No. 1 position on the periodic table of elements to the last thing any citizen would consider pumping into a car's fuel tank.</p>
        <p>But was hydrogen really to blame? Over the last seven decades, countless inquiries, investigations, books, movies, television reports and Internet postings have attempted to answer that question.</p>
        <p>After weighing the evidence, Rick Zitarosa, 45, of Point Pleasant, N.J., said he thought he knew the cause of the Hindenburg's demise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zitarosa, a supervisor for the New Jersey Turnpike Authority, is not a scientist, engineer or lawyer. But since he read a book on the subject as a 10-year old, his passion has been the study of airships in general and the Hindenburg in particular.</p>
        <p>His colleague, Lawrence Lyford, deputy public affairs officer for the Naval Air Engineering Station here, said, ''Rick Zitarosa is our resident expert on the subject of lighter-than-air service. He achieved this standing through extensive document research and numerous interviews.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zitarosa said the ship, the German zeppelin LZ 129, was on its 63rd flight and had logged 3,000 hours of reliable service.</p>
        <p>''It was a large, complex machine, three times as long as a Boeing 747,'' he said. ''Its structure consisted of 12 miles of duralumin, an aircraft alloy, girders joined by over 4 million rivets and 100 miles of brace wires. The outer skin was 40 acres of cotton fabric impregnated with iron oxide, cellulose acetate butyrate and aluminum powder.''</p>
        <p>He added that the zeppelin's 16 cells, made of gas-proof latex-treated cotton, contained seven million cubic feet of hydrogen gas capable of lifting 247,000 pounds. Four Daimler-Benz diesel engines propelled the Hindenburg to a maximum speed of 84 miles an hour. ''A crew of 16 operated the ship and there were cabins inside the hull for 50 passengers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>On May 6, strong Atlantic headwinds and stormy weather on the East Coast had delayed the Hindenburg's arrival by 12 hours.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zitarosa said that Captain Max Pruss ''may have been in a hurry to get the ship on the ground. During a lull in the thunderstorm activity, he made a rather tight turn during its final approach. Gas was vented to bring the ship into trim. During the last 11 minutes of the trip, the ship was tail heavy, so 2,000 pounds of water was dropped from the stern.</p>
        <p>''Electrical conditions in the atmosphere were probably a little risky. Earlier in the day, rubber factories in northern New Jersey had been closed due to static in the air; the fear was that stocks of carbon black might ignite.''</p>
        <p>The Hindenburg's heavy tail just before landing is evidence of a loss of hydrogen, Mr. Zitarosa said, adding that there were two likely explanations for the leak: a stuck valve during maneuvering to reduce altitude or a minor structural failure caused by guy wires snapping during the aggressive turn, resulting in the puncture of a gas cell.</p>
        <p>''U.S. Navy Chief Petty Officer R. H. Ward, from his position at the top of the mooring mast, noticed fluttering in the upper-rear area of the Hindenburg's skin,'' Mr. Zitarosa said. ''That had to be gas rippling in the space between the frame and the outer covering.''</p>
        <p>Another witness saw a likely ignition source. Mr. Zitarosa said a Princeton professor reported seeing a dim blue flame, like St. Elmo's fire, the electrical discharge that sometimes occurs during thunderstorms, flickering along the ship's backbone girder. The ship burst into flame at about 7:25 p.m.</p>
        <p>''In a nutshell, the catastrophe began with escaping hydrogen,'' he said. ''Air mixing with the hydrogen created a combustible mixture. Either a spark jumping from the electrically charged outer covering to the metal framework or the St. Elmo's fire lit the mixture. A puff or pop indicating detonation was heard by several observers.</p>
        <p>''It's important to note that the Hindenburg didn't explode. It was consumed by rapid combustion; this is evident in photographs. Heat produced in the first burning cell raised the temperature of adjacent cells, causing hydrogen to spill out of pressure-relief valves. It took only 34 seconds for fire to engulf the entire ship.'' Thirty-six people were killed.</p>
        <p>What about several sabotage theories that have been debated?</p>
        <p>''Germany had many enemies in 1937,'' Mr. Zitarosa said. ''After the disaster, there were thorough investigations by a very paranoid Nazi government and its notorious secret police, but no smoking gun was found.''</p>
        <p>Theorists have also pointed to hot diesel engines, leaking diesel fuel, and skin allegedly coated with rocket fuel as the cause of the accident. Mr. Zitarosa dismissed that theory, saying that the engines and fuel were in the lower half of the ship, while the fire was clearly observed first in the upper part.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zitarosa also dismissed the incendiary paint theory proposed by a retired NASA technician, Addison Bain, and an author, R. G. Van Treuren. He's not alone. The Discovery Channel's ''Mythbuster'' television show rejected the paint theory after building and igniting three scale-model Hindenburgs.</p>
        <p>Another challenge came from Dr. Alexander Dessler, a University of Arizona space scientist. His 2004 conclusions: the ignition source proposed by Mr. Bain and Mr. Van Treuren lacked the energy to ignite the Hindenburg's outer fabric, and the ship's paint was not a rocket fuel because it contained no oxidant, or chemical source of oxygen. Mr. Dessler added that the space shuttle's solid-rocket booster's burn rate is about half an inch a second versus the burn rate of 25 feet a second recorded during the Hindenburg accident.</p>
        <p>While the accident destroyed the Hindenburg, it didn't harm the base. Seventy years later, Lakehurst is still a Navy facility.</p>
        <p>Before the Navy came to town, the property was used for World War I chemical warfare experimentation by the Army. In 1919, Navy Secretary Franklin D. Roosevelt converted the site to a Navy dirigible field to be equipped with two rigid airship hangars. Hangar No. 1, still standing, was completed two years later.</p>
        <p>The British R-38, the first airship scheduled to arrive at Lakehurst, prophetically suffered structural failure before delivery. Nevertheless, the Navy commissioned rigid airships for use as long-range aerial scouts and nonrigid ships (called blimps) for training and antisubmarine work. All were filled with helium, not hydrogen.</p>
        <p>The German-built U.S.S. Los Angeles, the Navy's most successful airship, had a service life of eight years. The Shenandoah (assembled in Hangar No. 1), the Akron, and the Macon were less fortunate: two were lost at sea and one was destroyed by strong winds.</p>
        <p>After the Navy's interest in lighter-than-air aviation waned, Lakehurst became the western terminus for the German zeppelin company's trans-Atlantic air service.</p>
        <p>The Hindenburg was built in 1935 at a cost of $2.5 million and began commercial operation the following year with 17 trips across the Atlantic, including 10 to the United States. Because of a United States military embargo on helium, the Hindenburg was modified to use hydrogen as its lifting gas.</p>
        <p>During World War II, helium-filled airships resumed their military duty. By 1945, the Navy had a fleet of 141 airships for patrol and escort use, many of which were commissioned at Lakehurst. After the war, training and maintenance continued until 1962. This year, the Navy acquired a commercial blimp that it is testing at Lakehurst.</p>
        <p>Now called Naval Air Engineering Station, Lakehurst specializes in producing aircraft carrier launch, recovery, and support equipment for jets, prop planes and helicopters.</p>
        <p>The Navy Lakehurst Historical Society maintains a collection of photos, mementoes, and scale models from the airship era. Public tours of Hangar No. 1, a national historic landmark, are available. This 966-foot by 350-foot building, with 1,350-ton doors, is so vast that it is said to have its own climate.</p>
        <p>During a visit, Mr. Zitarosa illustrated his point that the Hindenburg's skin was not totally consumed by the fire by showing an odd artifact in a display case.</p>
        <p>''A boy on the base picked up a chunk of the doped fabric and took it home,'' Mr. Zitarosa said. ''Using the material for a crafts project, he carefully cut and stitched it to form a footlong scabbard.'' The boy's faded inscription can still be seen on one side.</p>
        <p>HYDROGEN'S SECOND COMING Don Sherman, technical editor of Automobile magazine, is a frequent contributor to The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Don Sherman, technical editor of Automobile magazine, is a frequent contributor to The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
