<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Governor Of New Jersey Often Wasn't In New Jersey</title>
    <meta content="29acting" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/29acting.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070502T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Codey, Richard J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1436" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Governor Of New Jersey Often Wasn't In New Jersey</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Jersey’s Governor Often Wasn’t in New Jersey</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long before his devastating car accident, New Jersey Gov. Jon S. Corzine often handed the reins of power to State Senate President Richard J. Codey, as he frequently traveled out of state on business or for pleasure -- far more frequently than did his recent predecessors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine designated Mr. Codey, a fellow Democrat, for the first time the day after he was inaugurated, for a day trip to Washington on Jan. 18, 2006. Before the April 12 crash on the Garden State Parkway, Mr. Corzine did so most recently for the Easter weekend, to spend time in the Hamptons with his family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since taking office last year, Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey has traveled outside the state far more than his recent predecessors  nearly one in every four days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Long before his devastating car accident, New Jersey Gov. Jon S. Corzine often handed the reins of power to State Senate President Richard J. Codey, as he frequently traveled out of state on business or for pleasure -- far more frequently than did his recent predecessors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine designated Mr. Codey, a fellow Democrat, for the first time the day after he was inaugurated, for a day trip to Washington on Jan. 18, 2006. Before the April 12 crash on the Garden State Parkway, Mr. Corzine did so most recently for the Easter weekend, to spend time in the Hamptons with his family.</p>
        <p>In all, Mr. Codey, or the next official in the line of succession, has been called on to substitute for Mr. Corzine for nearly one in four days of his 15-month governorship, according to official records reviewed by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>For work, there were visits to Washington, where Mr. Corzine had served five years as a senator; a trade mission to Asia; and a tour of Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>For pleasure, there were long weekends in Europe and the Hamptons, and longer vacations in Telluride, Colo., Italy and St. Bart's.</p>
        <p>In the 450 days between his inauguration and his accident, Mr. Corzine notified Mr. Codey that he would be away for all or part of 111 days, and would sleep out of state on 77 nights, according to letters from Mr. Corzine's chief of staff, Tom Shea, recording the transfer of power.</p>
        <p>And many of Mr. Corzine's overnight visits to Manhattan, where his companion, Sharon Elghanayan, lives, are not included in the tally, because of a memo in April 2006 from Zulima V. Farber, who was then the attorney general.</p>
        <p>''We do not believe that, in the circumstances you describe, an occasional, overnight stay in New York City following a workday in New Jersey and a return to this state in the morning constitutes an absence of the governor that would trigger the devolution of gubernatorial power,'' Ms. Farber wrote in response to an inquiry from Mr. Corzine's legal counsel.</p>
        <p>''The enlightened view was, use a commonsensical approach,'' Ms. Farber, herself one of four people who have served as acting governor during Mr. Corzine's absences, said in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>''My memory is that it was a combination of distance and time,'' she continued, ''so even going out to Long Island by plane, or if the governor goes to Manhattan for dinner, might be O.K.''</p>
        <p>In contrast to Mr. Corzine, his recent predecessors typically left the state during their first year in office for only a dozen or two dozen days, according to interviews with former governors, their chiefs of staff, and political scientists.</p>
        <p>Many said new governors typically had little time to travel, as they scrambled to establish a government, pass a budget and strengthen relationships with legislators and other state officials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, a former co-chairman of the investment bank Goldman Sachs who lives in Hoboken, has been away so much that several friends and fellow Democrats said they had urged him to spend more time in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Last summer, Page Six, a gossip column in The New York Post, began, ''The Garden State whispers are getting louder that New Jersey Gov. Jon Corzine needs to learn how to stay at home.''</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, Anthony Coley, Mr. Corzine's communications director, made no apologies for the boss's absences. ''Wherever Jon Corzine goes, his work goes with him,'' Mr. Coley said.</p>
        <p>''Jon Corzine burns the candle at both ends,'' he said. ''He's a seven-day-a-week type of governor.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coley added: ''He brings a level of gravitas and business expertise that a lot of people don't have in his position. So one of his roles as governor, as marketer-in-chief, is to promote his state abroad.''</p>
        <p>But with Mr. Corzine now facing an extended rehabilitation, his mobility and his approach to his job are likely to change. It will be harder for Mr. Corzine to go on trade missions -- like the one to Israel that had been planned for April 14 -- or to travel great distances for vacation.</p>
        <p>''The accident will certainly have an impact on planned trade missions and other officially connected events that occur out of state,'' Mr. Coley said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, with a net worth valued at hundreds of millions of dollars, has long been accustomed to ducking out of town or out of the country -- often on private jets.</p>
        <p>In his globe-trotting he resembles other wealthy politicians like Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, who sometimes escapes to a home he owns in Bermuda, and Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger of California, who has been criticized for being out of the state frequently -- about one day in five -- and not disclosing his whereabouts.</p>
        <p>Speaking of Mr. Corzine, Bruce Afran, a Princeton lawyer and a government watchdog, said: ''He's the kind of politician who invests his money in the office, and not the kind of politician who rose up through work in the state. I'm sure his travel reflects that. He's still thinking in terms of being a corporate executive.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Afran, who said he generally agrees with Mr. Corzine on issues but who has filed ethics complaints against the governor and others, added: ''I think a governor in the end has to commit himself to being here, and hopefully when he recovers, we'll see more of that, because that's the only way to solve policy problems.''</p>
        <p>But several politicians and political scientists said that while Mr. Corzine's trips were surprisingly numerous, they were not cause for concern given the modern-day communications conveniences of cellphones and BlackBerrys.</p>
        <p>Others said it was good for the state's leader to venture far to promote its interests and image.</p>
        <p>''You've got to find a balance,'' said former Gov. Christie Whitman, who was out of town perhaps a dozen days in her first year but increased her travel as her national political profile rose, both to give speeches and to participate in trade missions. ''You don't want to miss anything, but you also need to get away once in a while and get some perspective.''</p>
        <p>In most states, succession is an afterthought, because power is transferred to a lieutenant governor, who, in many cases, was elected on the same ticket with the governor.</p>
        <p>But when Gov. Jerry Brown of California was spending a lot of time out of state in seeking the 1980 Democratic nomination for president, his lieutenant governor, Mike Curb, a Republican, nominated judges and eased air pollution regulations, leading Governor Brown to sue. The California Supreme Court ruled that Mr. Curb's actions were constitutional.</p>
        <p>Under the New Jersey Constitution, the line of succession begins with the Senate president and proceeds to the Assembly speaker, the attorney general and then the transportation commissioner.</p>
        <p>The general guideline has been that an overnight stay or a day trip beyond the New York metropolitan area triggers succession, according to Michael P. Torpey, who was chief of staff to Mrs. Whitman.</p>
        <p>During March 2006 and again last August, Mr. Corzine left the state four times. He also spent half of last December out of town, and about a third of this February.</p>
        <p>The letters from Mr. Shea to Mr. Codey, standard in form, do not mention Mr. Corzine's destination. But according to news reports, Mr. Corzine traveled to Telluride for five days last July after surviving a crisis over the budget that resulted in a government shutdown.</p>
        <p>A few weeks later, he was in Italy when the authorities revealed that they had thwarted a terrorist plot in Britain to blow up flights to the United States. Mr. Corzine cut short his vacation and returned home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey said that in 2004-5 while he was acting governor for 14 months after the resignation of Gov. James. E. McGreevey, he left the state for about a dozen days.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. McGreevey seldom left during his first year, Mr. Codey said, other than to go to Canada to see his daughter from his first marriage.</p>
        <p>Former Gov. Thomas H. Kean occasionally visited his family's home on Fishers Island, off the North Fork of Long Island. But in his first year, 1982, he suffered a herniated disk and at one point ended up governing from a bed at St. Barnabas Medical Center in Livingston.</p>
        <p>W. Cary Edwards, who served as Mr. Kean's chief counsel and attorney general, said that Mr. Kean sometimes worked too much before his hospitalization.</p>
        <p>''We kept saying, 'Tom, get out of here!' '' Mr. Edwards recalled. ''There's a need to pull the plug once in a while to just relax and take care of yourself.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 2, 2007, Wednesday  An article on Sunday about the frequency of Jon S. Corzine's out-of-state travel during his tenure as governor of New Jersey rendered incorrectly in some copies comments on the matter from Zulima V. Farber, then the New Jersey attorney general, in an April 2006 memo. She wrote, ''We do not believe that, in the circumstances you describe, an occasional, overnight stay in New York City following a workday in New Jersey and a return to this state in the morning constitutes an absence of the governor that would trigger the devolution of gubernatorial power.'' The erroneous version said ''circumstance'' instead of ''circumstances'' and omitted the words ''and a return.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 2, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Sunday about the frequency of Jon S. Corzine's out-of-state travel during his tenure as governor of New Jersey rendered incorrectly in some copies comments on the matter from Zulima V. Farber, then the New Jersey attorney general, in an April 2006 memo. She wrote, ''We do not believe that, in the circumstances you describe, an occasional, overnight stay in New York City following a workday in New Jersey and a return to this state in the morning constitutes an absence of the governor that would trigger the devolution of gubernatorial power.'' The erroneous version said ''circumstance'' instead of ''circumstances'' and omitted the words ''and a return.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
