<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Little Projectors That Pack a Punch</title>
    <meta content="29novel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/business/yourmoney/29novel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NOVELTIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">NEC Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Samsung Electronics Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Little Projectors That Pack a Punch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Little Projectors That Pack a Punch</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE EISENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eisenberg, Anne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONFERENCE rooms usually have digital projectors that presenters can use to show off PowerPoint slides and other visuals stored on their laptops. But road warriors selling goods or giving talks at impromptu sites can't count on this amenity for their presentations. They have to lug along their own projectors, just in case.</p>
        <p>That's less of a chore these days, because the size of projectors has dropped over the last four years, while image quality has risen. Now there is a choice of compact, portable projectors in the under-4-pounds category and are lighter than some city telephone directories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lugging along a digital projector is less of a chore these days, with compact, portable models weighting less than a phone book.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONFERENCE rooms usually have digital projectors that presenters can use to show off PowerPoint slides and other visuals stored on their laptops. But road warriors selling goods or giving talks at impromptu sites can't count on this amenity for their presentations. They have to lug along their own projectors, just in case.</p>
        <p>That's less of a chore these days, because the size of projectors has dropped over the last four years, while image quality has risen. Now there is a choice of compact, portable projectors in the under-4-pounds category and are lighter than some city telephone directories.</p>
        <p>These small, business-style projectors aren't made to show off rich color in darkened rooms, the way that home movie-theater projectors are. Instead, most have optics designed to favor brightness over color so that they can cast crisp images of spreadsheets even when fluorescent lights are on.</p>
        <p>The NEC Corporation offers a good example of these lightweight projectors: the NP60, widely available since January ($1,299 at ProjectorCentral.com). The NP60 has a bulb that puts out 3,000 lumens, enough light to throw a sharp, 100-inch diagonal image onto a screen or wall even when lights are aglow in a conference room.</p>
        <p>The projector weighs only 3.5 pounds; its large display can easily be seen in rooms holding 40 or even more people. The arc bulb that produces the light lasts about 2,000 hours; a replacement costs $329. The projector includes a sensor that automatically squares the images, as well as one that focuses the lens.</p>
        <p>For presentations in smaller sites -- when the audience, say, is two or three people in a cubicle -- another new type of projector works well. These compact devices, called pocket projectors, use L.E.D.'s, or light-emitting diodes, rather than the arc lamps of larger portable projectors. The L.E.D. projectors put out far less raw light and create smaller images than their arc-lamp counterparts. But if no conference room is available and you need to make your sales presentation in a small borrowed office or hotel lobby, these projectors will do the trick -- provided that there is a nearby wall where you can cast the images.</p>
        <p>Samsung offers one of these projectors, the Pocket Imager SP-P310MEMX, ($749), introduced in January. It weighs 1.5 pounds. The power cord attaches to an AC adapter, which adds 1.25 pounds; a battery that is sold separately ($149) lasts for 2.5 hours and weighs less than a pound. The Samsung projector casts 50 lumens, a small amount of light but enough to work effectively at short ranges. For example, it creates a clear 35-inch diagonal image at a distance of four feet. Its L.E.D.'s are far more efficient than incandescent bulbs and have a lifetime of about 10,000 hours.</p>
        <p>Portables like the Samsung and NEC models may be purchased initially for use on the job. But they have other applications, too. When the workweek is done, some people take them home and attach them to game machines, or plug them into a DVD player to watch movies. The cost of the projectors will probably have to drop a bit, though, before they become popular consumer items.</p>
        <p>To see how well the projectors worked, a friend and I tried them out, with both PowerPoint shows and movies. First we experimented with PowerPoint, hooking up the Samsung Pocket Imager to a laptop. This was quick and easy to do. The Pocket Imager, however, comes with a native, or built-in, resolution of 800 by 600 pixels, called S.V.G.A., shown in an aspect ratio or display of 4:3. But the laptop I used with the Pocket Imager has a wider aspect ratio, 16:9, and has a resolution of 1,366 by 768.</p>
        <p>I was concerned that the projector and the laptop did not have a one-for-one match in resolution. In some equipment, this disparity can create problems like chopping off part of the image. But Chris Chinnock, the president of Insight Media, a market research firm in Norwalk, Conn., that specializes in the display industry, said that pixel-to-pixel matches between laptop and projector were not mandatory, because proper software on the projector could handle many differences in input.</p>
        <p>''The projector has to take inputs of all formats and display them on its panel, which has only one resolution,'' he said. ''A good projector can do this within limits.''</p>
        <p>In this case, when I plugged the projector into the laptop, the projector recognized the laptop video input and automatically scaled down to S.V.G.A. The display was clear, easy to read and far preferable to having three people in a huddle around a laptop trying to decipher the same PowerPoint slides.</p>
        <p>I also plugged the Pocket Imager into my DVD player to watch the movie ''Infamous.'' The images were sharp, and, when I turned the lights down, the color was intense. No fan whirred in the projector during the movie; although L.E.D.'s throw off some heat, the amount is far less than that of arc lights, so no cooling fan is needed.</p>
        <p>Because of this quieter background, I thought that the small speakers built into the laptop would be adequate for listening to the movie soundtrack. They were, and I could follow the dialogue. But the sound would have been much improved by connecting the system to external speakers. The image was so compelling, though, that I had to force myself to turn off the show after 20 minutes and get back to work.</p>
        <p>We also tried out the NEC projector. It is easy to set up, and within moments it cast a huge image of both the PowerPoint show and then the movie on my living-room wall. I was ready to invite the neighbors over and serve popcorn.</p>
        <p>Although the portable projectors now on the market are already small, they will be shrinking even more, Mr. Chinnock said. On the horizon, he said, are 100-lumen L.E.D. projectors that put out 40-inch images that stand up to daylight. And even smaller, finger-tip-sized projectors will be arriving that can be used with cellphones and P.D.A.'s, he said.</p>
        <p>''You'll be taking your presentation on a U.S.B. thumb drive and doing your slide shows from a cellphone,'' he said. ''There are going to be many ways to make the projector less tethered to a notebook.''</p>
        <p>NOVELTIES E-mail: novelties@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: novelties@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
