<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When He Speaks, It's in America's Voice</title>
    <meta content="29peoplenjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29peoplenj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gallup Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newport, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Princeton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Princeton (NJ)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Gallup Poll</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFD8153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="625" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When He Speaks, It's in America's Voice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When He Speaks, It’s in America’s Voice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Frank Newport, editor in chief of Gallup Poll; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT wouldn't be much of a stretch to call Frank Newport the mirror of the American public's conscience -- or at least the public's statistician general.</p>
        <p>''I go to a cocktail party and people will ask, say, 'What do you think about the war in Iraq?' '' Mr. Newport said. ''So I'll say, 'Well, 43 percent of the population ' '' And he trails off with a slight laugh.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It wouldn’t be much of a stretch to call Frank Newport the mirror of the American public’s conscience  or at least the public’s statistician general.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT wouldn't be much of a stretch to call Frank Newport the mirror of the American public's conscience -- or at least the public's statistician general.</p>
        <p>''I go to a cocktail party and people will ask, say, 'What do you think about the war in Iraq?' '' Mr. Newport said. ''So I'll say, 'Well, 43 percent of the population ' '' And he trails off with a slight laugh.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newport is the editor in chief of the Gallup Poll, the face and voice -- on TV news programs, radio broadcasts, newspaper articles and the poll's daily Webcasts -- of the survey, which George Gallup developed here during the Depression.</p>
        <p>In his third-floor office at the Carnegie Center along Route 1, Mr. Newport reached on a shelf for a dusty volume containing the results of Mr. Gallup's early polls.</p>
        <p>''The very first question that he ever asked was about welfare,'' Mr. Newport said, reading from the book. '' 'Do you think expenditures for recovery and relief by government are too little, too great or just about right?' ''</p>
        <p>Sixty percent of the respondents said those payments were too great.</p>
        <p>''People were opposed to welfare in the middle of the Depression, mind you,'' Mr. Newport said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newport, 58, has lived in the Princeton area since he became the poll's editor in 1990, but he was born in Oklahoma and grew up in Fort Worth, where his father was a professor at a Baptist seminary. He went to Baylor, in Waco, Tex., the country's largest Baptist university, and then served in the Texas National Guard.</p>
        <p>He earned graduate degrees in sociology at the University of Michigan, then taught at the University of Missouri. He got bored and went to work for a talk radio station in Houston, then for a polling company.</p>
        <p>''I always had that interest in sociology, how people really think,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In 1986, his Houston company was merged with the Gallup Poll. He moved to Princeton to work for the combined company, now called the Gallup Organization, which makes most of its money doing consumer and marketing research for companies. That helps to support the better-known part of the organization, Mr. Newport's beloved Gallup Poll.</p>
        <p>''We have had a continuing commitment to an accurate scientific assessment of public opinion,'' he said. ''It is not the profit center of the company, but it is a commitment Gallup makes to the well-being of the democracy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Newport admitted that was a highfalutin statement, but ''as a whole, I have great respect for the judgment and wisdom of people aggregated together,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Newport is guarded about his own politics, he openly supports one candidate: his wife, Kim, the president of the Hopewell Valley Regional School District Board of Education. They have four children.</p>
        <p>He is pleased with the broadening of the Gallup Poll's reach in recent years, he said. It does polling for USA Today, and Mr. Newport does a 10- or 15-minute spot with NPR, taped Thursdays, of light banter with a reporter about topics from recent polls.</p>
        <p>Each weekday, the poll's Web site has a four- or five-minute Webcast with Mr. Newport as anchor.</p>
        <p>The big problem in polling these days, Mr. Newport said, is the proliferation of cellphones and the idea that phones no longer indicate your geography. ''Cellphones are just not sampleable in the same way,'' he said, noting that his daughter at Notre Dame has a phone based in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>For now, though, Mr. Newport is satisfied that public opinion research remains scientifically valid and that innovation is unnecessary.</p>
        <p>''Dr. Gallup wouldn't know what stem cell was,'' Mr. Newport said, ''but it is just a matter of using his kind of question and plugging that in.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
