<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Businesses and Residents Struggling With Flood Damage</title>
    <meta content="29mainweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29mainwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STORM RECOVERY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Emergency Management Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Businesses and Residents Struggling With Flood Damage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Businesses and Residents Struggling With Flood Damage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>MAMARONECK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Business owners and residents in Westchester County, NY, comment on problems associated with flooding from northeaster that damaged or destroyed properties; some say they are not looking for low-interest loans from Federal Emergency Management Agency, but rather financial aid under federal disaster declaration; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Aristocrat Dry Cleaners in Hartsdale has been closed since the basement flooded to the ceiling in the April 15 northeaster, damaging or destroying much of the equipment. But that doesn't mean it isn't doing business.</p>
        <p>Phil Benincasa Jr. continued to serve customers last week by expanding pick-up and drop-off service as much as possible and benefiting from the kindness of another dry cleaner, who let him use his site to clean and press clothes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mamaroneck.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Aristocrat Dry Cleaners in Hartsdale has been closed since the basement flooded to the ceiling in the April 15 northeaster, damaging or destroying much of the equipment. But that doesn't mean it isn't doing business.</p>
        <p>Phil Benincasa Jr. continued to serve customers last week by expanding pick-up and drop-off service as much as possible and benefiting from the kindness of another dry cleaner, who let him use his site to clean and press clothes.</p>
        <p>''We must have one of the best clienteles ever,'' said Mr. Benincasa, who runs the business with his father. ''Every single one of them has been so understanding and so supportive through this horrible ordeal.''</p>
        <p>But he was not nearly as enthusiastic about the low-interest loans offered to businesses -- up to $1.5 million at a rate of as low as 4 percent -- as part of the federal disaster declaration that was made on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''We need aid, not low-interest loans,'' said Mr. Benincasa, who said he had not bought flood insurance because his business was not in an area that typically floods.</p>
        <p>Other business owners in the county had a similar reaction after being notified of the disaster declaration at a meeting in Mamaroneck on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''I'm not looking for low-interest loans,'' said Frank Picone, owner of Picone Meat Specialties in Mamaroneck. ''FEMA is missing the point. This was an act of God, and when it's an act of God, they should help cover the losses.''</p>
        <p>Under the disaster declaration, individuals and households are eligible for up to $28,200 in financial aid related to loss of housing and property.</p>
        <p>Individuals may also be eligible for low-interest loans of up to $200,000 for structure damage and $40,000 on contents. The rate for those loans is as low as 2.875 percent, said Ed Conley, a spokesman for the Federal Emergency Management Agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Picone estimated that he sustained about $750,000 in damages -- including a piece of machinery that cost $150,000 and had been used for only three days -- but his flood insurance would cover only about $250,000.</p>
        <p>''If I didn't have good credit, I would be out of business,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conley noted that individuals who receive assistance from the federal government are asked to get flood insurance.</p>
        <p>Business and home owners who receive loans of more than $10,000, or are located in a 100-year flood plain, are required to obtain flood insurance.</p>
        <p>The emergency management agency has been encouraging residents and businesses to get flood insurance, particularly with hurricane season starting June 1 and another active season predicted. Mr. Conley said that every community in Westchester participates in the National Flood Insurance Program, which assures that such coverage is available. In addition, property owners who are not in flood-prone areas are encouraged to look for so-called preferred risk policies, which provide such coverage at reduced rates.</p>
        <p>But business owners in Mamaroneck say that flood insurance can be costly and that caps on the amount of coverage -- in some cases $10,000 to $15,000 -- can make it nearly worthless.</p>
        <p>Many business and property owners in Mamaroneck and other parts of the county called on local, state and federal officials to begin addressing drainage problems that were exposed in the storm this month and one on March 2. Several merchants at the meeting Tuesday in Mamaroneck also complained of sewage backups that occurred before the most recent flooding.</p>
        <p>Those seeking federal assistance can call 1-800-621-FEMA (1-800-621-3362) or go to fema.gov.</p>
        <p>In addition, village officials said, the United Way is serving as a clearinghouse for information and donations; residents can call 211 or (800) 899-1479, the number that cable phone customers must use.</p>
        <p>David Currie, the local director for the United Way in Westchester, said those in need could also go to St. Thomas Episcopal Church at 168 West Boston Post Road from 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. tomorrow and Tuesday to meet with case workers.</p>
        <p>STORM RECOVERY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
