<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rescue Me</title>
    <meta content="Cain.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/Cain.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gowdy, Barbara</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Helpless (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rescue Me</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rescue Me</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHELSEA CAIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HELPLESS</p>
        <p>By Barbara Gowdy.</p>
        <p>320 pp. Metropolitan Books. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this novel, a pedophile kidnaps a little girl he imagines is being molested.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HELPLESS</p>
        <p>By Barbara Gowdy.</p>
        <p>320 pp. Metropolitan Books. $24.</p>
        <p>You can tell Barbara Gowdy's new novel is a literary thriller because it doesn't feature a cop, a private investigator, a young lawyer, a bounty hunter, a medical student or an infectious-disease specialist caught up in a hunt for a serial killer, a missing dame, an escaped con or vial of germs. And it's still exciting.</p>
        <p>How is this possible? Through tense prose, plenty of foreshadowing and a plot starring our favorite damsel in distress -- a missing little girl. The girl in this case is Canadian, and adorable.</p>
        <p>In fact, 9-year-old Rachel Fox is so beautiful that strangers comment on her appearance: half black and half Anglo, with ''miraculous chromium yellow'' hair. Rachel's plain single mother, Celia, works two jobs and can't quite believe this tawny, lovely girl is her own flesh and blood. Lurking at the periphery of their lives is Ron, an appliance repairman who becomes convinced that Rachel is being molested and decides to save her by locking her in his basement.</p>
        <p>Gowdy cleverly makes us wait for the kidnapping we know is coming, forcing us to watch as Ron moves closer and closer, like a shark circling its prey. When a blackout gives him his chance, Ron pounces and Rachel is finally his. At this point, another book might have turned to the massive investigation that follows, but Gowdy is a master of restraint. She stays with her main characters: Celia and Rachel, Ron and Ron's girlfriend and co-conspirator, a former meth addict named Nancy.</p>
        <p>They're all helpless, some more obviously than others. Celia, who has always let life simply happen to her, is ill equipped to help the police find her daughter. Rachel, imprisoned in an impeccably appointed basement, is unable to determine whether her ''rescuer'' is telling her the truth. Ron struggles to rein in his predatory sexual instincts, while Nancy is consumed by her neediness. Yet before the book is done, all four will take actions contrary to their natures.</p>
        <p>Gowdy writes as if she's on a sinking boat and needs to throw out all the dead weight. The only words that survive are the ones that matter: no extraneous evidence of her research, no long-winded descriptions, no self-indulgent frills of characterization. And the result is a page turner that finds tension not in the obvious question (Will Rachel be rescued?), but in more personal ones: Will Rachel grow to trust Ron? Will Ron give in to his yearnings? Will Nancy betray Ron and help Rachel?</p>
        <p>Ron is a bravely drawn character -- a three-dimensional pedophile. He isn't likable. He isn't even sympathetic. But he's not a monster. Instead, he has an almost Victorian infatuation with little girls that's somehow both virtuous and creepy. Like Lewis Carroll taking photographs of little Alice Liddell, he has aesthetic leanings that are at first admirable, then troubling. (When Ron looks down at Rachel, ''he can make out only the tender curve of her neck and the earlobe with its pearl stud, like a drop of saliva.'') Gowdy portrays him as a man struggling with his weakness.</p>
        <p>Rachel is, strangely enough, a somewhat less convincing character. Gowdy captures her cockeyed child's view of the world and her emotional unpredictability. (Her mother's ''feathery little head makes Rachel sad.'') There's no introspection attached to her observations, charming in their lack of self-consciousness. But at the same time Rachel seems far too quick to believe her captors are her benefactors and protectors. Ultimately, she's so guileless she doesn't feel fully formed.</p>
        <p>Considering the subject matter, ''Helpless'' is a very chaste book, and Gowdy makes it easy to read disturbing scenes -- which is, in itself, a little disturbing. But perhaps that's appropriate for a novel about self-control, about having the courage not to surrender to your worst urges. And Gowdy holds back across the board: she isn't graphic, and she isn't sentimental. Given her history, that's taking a risk. Remember, this is a woman who wrote a novel told from the point of view of an elephant (''The White Bone'') and a story (in the collection ''We So Seldom Look on Love'') about a woman whose sexual proclivities involved male corpses. Gowdy knows how to push boundaries.</p>
        <p>Crime novels reflect the nature of their times. In the Sherlock Holmes stories, the world is orderly and anything discordant (demon hell hounds, say, or errant mistresses) is to be investigated and corrected. In the noir universe of Chandler and Hammett, the world is corrupt and the pure is to be protected. Gowdy takes the middle ground, where everyone -- not just little girls locked in basements -- has a chance to be saved.</p>
        <p>Chelsea Cain is the author of the novel ''Confessions of a Teen Sleuth.'' Her next book, ''Heartsick,'' a thriller, will be published this fall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Chelsea Cain is the author of the novel ''Confessions of a Teen Sleuth.'' Her next book, ''Heartsick,'' a thriller, will be published this fall.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
