<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fields of Memory</title>
    <meta content="Brouwer.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/Brouwer.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843534"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Halflife (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fields of Memory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fields of Memory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BROUWER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brouwer, Joel</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HALFLIFE</p>
        <p>By Meghan O'Rourke.</p>
        <p>87 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In these poems, Meghan O’Rourke narrows her eyes to discern intelligence from chatter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HALFLIFE</p>
        <p>By Meghan O'Rourke.</p>
        <p>87 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
        <p>A Fun game for poetry nerds: read the first line or sentence of a favorite poet's first book, and imagine it as a summary of the writer's entire career. This works more often than you might think. Muriel Rukeyser's ''Breathe-in experience, breathe-out poetry'' suggests her lifelong commitment to poetry as a praxis; Sylvia Plath's ''Two girls there are: within the house / One sits; the other, without'' conjures a psyche in crisis; Theodore Roethke's ''My secrets cry aloud'' inaugurates a career of passionate self-disclosure.</p>
        <p>Of course, with these examples we have the benefit of hindsight; it might be more challenging to read the tea leaves of a young poet's first words and predict what we might expect from her. Meghan O'Rourke, the culture editor of Slate, offers a terse contribution to the first-sentence genre in this, her debut collection: ''My poor eye.'' Like many of the poems that follow, the sentence can be read as grave or arch, and at first seems straightforward but proves elusive upon closer examination. Is her eye poor because it doesn't work well? Because it hasn't seen enough? Or has seen too much? All three, we come to find. In fact, the sentence neatly encapsulates the central drama of O'Rourke's poems: the tremendous difficulty of writing clearly and accurately (my poor inadequate eye) about things longed for but never seen (my poor impoverished eye) and things so terrible they should never have to be seen (my poor overburdened eye).</p>
        <p>That drama is played out most obviously in the book's two long poems, each of which mourns a relationship torn apart -- torn, one might say, into ''halflives.'' In ''Two Sisters,'' twins (one living, the other never born) speak in alternating sections, each mourning the inaccessibility and invisibility of the other. The speaker of ''Still Life Amongst Partial Outlines'' reflects upon a hideous attack on two young girls -- one of them coincidentally named Meghan O'Rourke -- that one friend survived and the other did not, ''a story that could not be forgotten or owned, / like looking in a mirror and discovering someone else's face.''</p>
        <p>PWhat happened to her</p>
        <p>did not happen to you. You were a child,</p>
        <p>you were safe, you were not harmed. But</p>
        <p>there are fields inside us. They grow.</p>
        <p>How do you choose which ones to make room for</p>
        <p>under the golden sun, and which ones to lock away,</p>
        <p>so that men cannot climb into them at twilight,</p>
        <p>vaulting over the iron fence</p>
        <p>and landing lightly in the grass?</p>
        <p>O'Rourke makes room for many fields of memory in these poems, but locks many others away, often by employing a bemused, detached tone reminiscent of the famously reticent Elizabeth Bishop. The opening lines of ''Sandy Hook'' -- ''The fire burned my cousin here, / first in his bed in the bungalow garage, / then at the lock, scratching in fear'' -- are vivid and horrific, but the frivolity of those that follow (''Quick, quick. The trundle bed / burned. The violin, unpracticed, burned'') and the mischievous rhymes of the poem's final lines (''the hooks of the waves twist / and desist, twist and insist, / like coats hung out beneath / the snailing clouds to dry'') seem oddly aloof choices given the seriousness of the poem's inciting incident.</p>
        <p>O'Rourke's most ambitious and dynamic poems are driven, like so much in our age, by juxtaposition rather than concatenation, association rather than rhetoric. Information pours in until the poem threatens to burst at the seams:</p>
        <p>The blue square of light</p>
        <p>in the window across the street</p>
        <p>never goes dark --</p>
        <p>the cathodes, the cordage, the atoms</p>
        <p>working the hem of dusk --</p>
        <p>traveling past the cranes and the docks</p>
        <p>and the soiled oyster beds,</p>
        <p>the trees loaded with radium,</p>
        <p>colors like guns,</p>
        <p>red pock-pock red and the sea yellow up,</p>
        <p>yellow down.</p>
        <p>But O'Rourke doesn't revel in information saturation; she narrows her eyes and strains to distinguish intelligence from chatter, to discern a path to the authentic. Her effort succeeds more often than not, perhaps most movingly in ''War Lullaby.'' It's not easy to write a politically suggestive poem that's emotional and intelligent but not overbearing or didactic; O'Rourke pulls it off. In quick, deft strokes, she pits the innocent pride of youth (''the boy stretched on the lawn, / fighting sleep, / fingers the tournament ring'') against an atmosphere of gathering menace (''Wet daggers of grass,'' ''eyelashes like / tiny whips''), and ends with an image of Whitmanesque generosity and mournfulness: ''I have seen them / sleepwalk / out of the arms of mothers.''</p>
        <p>If a book's first lines invoke a dilemma, perhaps its final poem will point to some resolution. ''Knives of Light'' tells us that the painter Pierre Bonnard ''kept bits of silver paper / to catch light: so he could work / in the poorest-lit hotel or friend's home.'' It's a striking idea, an artist famed for his lush, refulgent canvases laboring in a dim room by such cold and meager light. His poor eye! We can be thankful that Bonnard in his paintings and O'Rourke in these magnificent poems keep their eyes open despite the darkness. In the book's final lines, O'Rourke suggests -- and I think she's right -- that there's really no other choice: ''Bits of silver turn in the breeze, / knives of light and appetite. / They want to be used.''</p>
        <p>Joel Brouwer is the author of two books of poems, ''Exactly What Happened'' and ''Centuries.'' He teaches at the University of Alabama.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joel Brouwer is the author of two books of poems, ''Exactly What Happened'' and ''Centuries.'' He teaches at the University of Alabama.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
