<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Under African Skies</title>
    <meta content="Williams.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/Williams.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843552"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Exploration and Explorers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration and Explorers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Africa</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Kenya</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Wheeler, Sara</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dinesen, Isak</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Too Close to the Sun: The Audacious Life and Times of Denys Finch Hatton (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1202" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Under African Skies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Under African Skies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE WILLIAMS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TOO CLOSE TO THE SUN</p>
        <p>The Audacious Life and Times</p>
        <p>of Denys Finch Hatton.</p>
        <p>By Sara Wheeler.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 292 pp. Random House. $27.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The story of Denys Finch Hatton, aristocrat, swashbuckling lion slayer and bewitcher of women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TOO CLOSE TO THE SUN</p>
        <p>The Audacious Life and Times</p>
        <p>of Denys Finch Hatton.</p>
        <p>By Sara Wheeler.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 292 pp. Random House. $27.95.</p>
        <p>It's no wonder Karen Blixen fell madly in love with Denys Finch Hatton in 1918. He was arrestingly handsome, intelligent, athletic and courageous. He was a war hero, a pilot and a lover of opera. The younger son of the 13th Earl of Winchilsea (who was also the Eighth Earl of Nottingham), he was equally at ease in the African bush and on the country estate. Immortalized in ''Out of Africa'' (written under Blixen's pen name, Isak Dinesen), he was her artistic muse, but before that he was her escape from the drudgery of a loveless marriage, a failing Kenyan farm and a debilitating bout of syphilis, thanks to her husband, a feckless baron. Who wouldn't want a swashbuckling lion slayer stopping in between safaris to recite poems and embrace her under the mosquito netting?</p>
        <p>Sara Wheeler is the latest in a long line of women to fall under the Finch Hatton spell. (Another was Beryl Markham, who wrote about him in ''West With the Night.'') In many ways, though, Finch Hatton makes an unlikely biographical subject. He left no diaries and only spartan correspondence. He never achieved much. He moved around a lot. He is best known for being a lover of interesting women. There are certainly worse reasons for being famous.</p>
        <p>What is it about these untamable men that makes them so alluring? Wheeler is most drawn to Finch Hatton's strong connection to the land. Moved by the themes of landscape and exploration, she is the author of ''Terra Incognita: Travels in Antarctica'' and ''Cherry,'' a biography of Apsley Cherry-Garrard, a member of Robert Falcon Scott's last, fatal expedition to the South Pole. In Finch Hatton, Wheeler has found the archetypal wanderer forced to straddle multiple worlds. He embodies the contradictions of the early modern age and, in some ways still, of ours. ''He was,'' she writes, ''the open road made flesh.''</p>
        <p>Readers today will recognize his type: a lingering adolescent with little interest in settling down. He would have made a good cowboy, or even ski bum. America would not have been his cup of tea, though. Ambition was not part of his makeup; he never saw the need to work particularly hard. A thorough aristocrat, he liked drinking ChÛteau d'Yquem and wore a brown velvet smoking jacket when he wasn't in the bush shooting bongo and stalking dik-dik. But there was something solid in him. Wheeler makes much of his love of literature and music and of his loyalty to his crumpling class. He was the Last Edwardian Male.</p>
        <p>Finch Hatton was born in 1887. He attended Eton, where he excelled athletically and socially, and then Oxford, where he ran a gambling parlor in his quarters. After earning a spectacularly unheroic fourth-class degree, he lit out for British East Africa in 1911. ''To boys of his background,'' Wheeler writes, ''Africa was a stage on which Europeans enacted their fantasies or lived out the heroic ideal.'' Soon the major themes of Finch Hatton's life were established: his love of open spaces, flying and bohemian women.</p>
        <p>It was a tumultuous time for both England and Africa. At home, the landed gentry was losing its grip on money and power as agricultural taxes rose, the Conservatives were being outflanked, and the stuttering economy was moving toward modernization. European powers were busy dividing Africa after the Boer War but were unsure whether it was worth the effort. British settlers were having a tough time wresting crops from the arid land. Subduing the people was easier-- shockingly so. Wheeler elegantly describes the colonial scene, both in peacetime and during World War I. Despite hating soldiering, Finch Hatton fought German guerrillas in the malarial East African theater. His effortless charm and popularity continued to help him. Soon he became aide-de-camp to a general, while most of his school chums were losing their lives in the European trenches. During the war, he also established what was to be a lifelong friendship with Kermit Roosevelt and learned how to fly.</p>
        <p>Of course, after the long war, nothing was the same. The carefree Edwardian era in which Finch Hatton was so firmly rooted was officially over. His family's long-declining fortune continued its trajectory, and he took up guiding safaris for rich American industrialists, as well as for the future King Edward VIII, whom Wheeler deliciously describes as being as interested in quarrying the settler's wives as he was the big game. In the '20s, Kenya's colonizers entered a brief golden period of prosperity and glamour. Tales emerged of ''Happy Valley'' in all its sybaritic glory. Against this backdrop, which was conveniently in sync with his own anti-bourgeois moral code, Finch Hatton struck up a decade-long love affair with Blixen.</p>
        <p>She was alluring in her own right. Artistic and probably a little nuts, she once said ''it was worth having syphilis to become a baroness.'' Together the lovers read books, listened to Rachmaninoff and picnicked under the African skies. Blixen convinced herself, at least for a time, that the rules-free relationship suited her fine. For both of them, the African landscape was intensely powerful, even redemptive, and it held them together. Wheeler renders these sections convincingly. ''Simple pleasures,'' she writes, ''took on a heightened intensity: the smell of camel milk in a smoke-cleansed gourd, the thin yelling of Somali singing on five sad notes, the purple hieroglyphs of shadow on the sand below a thorn tree.''</p>
        <p>In the end, though, as it is with restless men of the wilderness, Finch Hatton loved the land -- and the freedom it symbolized -- more than he loved her. Even while he participated in its transformation, he grieved for the loss of wild Africa. From his plane, he could see entire herds of migrating animals, and he feared for their future. Toward the end of his short life, he rallied on their behalf, successfully lobbying Parliament and the colonies to establish the first East African wildlife preserves and to ban hunting from vehicles.</p>
        <p>Although Finch Hatton grew in purpose, he managed to resist domestication. He left Blixen for a younger woman, the equally unconventional flier Markham, just as Blixen was losing her farm. Shortly after the breakup, his plane crashed while he was scouting elephant. He was 44.</p>
        <p>If Finch Hatton let down Blixen, he ultimately provided her a royal favor by dying. She achieved worldwide fame with ''Out of Africa,'' wrote other highly praised books and for several years was in the running for a Nobel Prize (when Ernest Hemingway won it in 1954, he said in an interview that he ''would have been happy -- happier -- today if the prize had gone to that beautiful writer Isak Dinesen). ''No one came into literature more bloody than I,'' Blixen once wrote. Loving and then leaving her were perhaps Finch Hatton's greatest deeds.</p>
        <p>Everyone liked and many people loved Denys Finch Hatton. Few knew him well, and no one could ever fully understand him, certainly not his lovers, and, ultimately, not Sara Wheeler. But just as Blixen might have said, knowing him a little was worth the ride.</p>
        <p>Florence Williams is a contributing editor at Outside magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Florence Williams is a contributing editor at Outside magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
