<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sorting Through the Pieces of a Life</title>
    <meta content="29RgenLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29Rgen.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843625"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GENERATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Sally</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Friedman, Sally</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFDF153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sorting Through the Pieces of a Life</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sorting Through the Pieces of a Life</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SALLY FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Sally</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sally Friedman Generations essay on difficulty of sorting through and clearing out her mother's apartment after she died; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE first time I walked into my mother's apartment after she died, I turned and bolted. The smell of her perfume and the sight of her eyeglasses, her magazines and her comb were just too much.</p>
        <p>But no matter how much I wanted to avoid it, there was the inevitable work of clearing out the place where she had lived for 37 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clearing out a parent’s home and wrestling with the memories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE first time I walked into my mother's apartment after she died, I turned and bolted. The smell of her perfume and the sight of her eyeglasses, her magazines and her comb were just too much.</p>
        <p>But no matter how much I wanted to avoid it, there was the inevitable work of clearing out the place where she had lived for 37 years.</p>
        <p>The first challenge: where to start. I knew it wouldn't be the kitchen, where everything had some association with a woman who cooked the best brisket in the universe and could make a tuna salad taste like heaven. And the bedroom felt too private and personal.</p>
        <p>So I headed for what I thought was neutral turf: a hall closet where Mom had kept the miscellaneous stuff every household has. It was not. Behind the light bulbs, the box of trash bags and the extra paper towels was an emotional mine field, a shoe box filled to the brim with every card we'd ever sent her -- each one dated, and in its original envelope. Every sappy birthday card and Mother's Day card was there -- ordinary cards I'd picked out in a moment without even deliberating over the message. Why hadn't I sent her nicer ones?</p>
        <p>No matter where I went in the apartment after that closet, there was something destined to stop me in my tracks. The yellowing, neatly clipped newspaper announcement from 1960 of my engagement to a young man named Victor. A letter I'd sent her during my sophomore year of college complaining about a killer course in James Joyce. A spelling paper from second grade with a gold star stuck to the corner and a note from Miss Goodkin telling Mom that her younger daughter was a ''fine and conscientious speller.''</p>
        <p>Every time I thought I was in a safe zone, there would be other surprises -- something scribbled in Mom's handwriting, or a photograph of her as a very young woman in the back of a dresser drawer.</p>
        <p>I kept postponing the sorting, but there was a beat-the-clock factor even in this painful family business: According to the bylaws of Mom's cooperative, we had to clear out her apartment by a specific deadline, and we were down to the wire.</p>
        <p>So at last I tackled the kitchen. I couldn't throw away the aprons. Not the organdy one she used to wear when she had people over and fluttered around this urban apartment, delighting in playing hostess. Not the flowered one with the missing tie that she would wrap around her body before starting a serious cooking project.</p>
        <p>Her ancient flour sifter, probably a collectible by now, went to my daughter Jill, Mom's oldest granddaughter. A dainty tray she loved went to my daughter Amy, Mom's middle granddaughter. And my daughter Nancy chose her grandmother's favorite serving dishes. The chipped surfaces, she said, made them all the more lovable.</p>
        <p>I carried off the little red pot with the glass lid in which my mother would cook her evening vegetables. Why this pot and not the enamel one in which she made soup? I can't begin to understand. But there seemed a certain determinism about all our choices.</p>
        <p>It took a day to go through my mother's jewelry, little of it of any value, all of it priceless to those of us who remembered her in this or that necklace or pin or bracelet. We ended up keeping most of it.</p>
        <p>And the clothes. Oh my, the clothes that still carried her scent, an occasional lipstick smudge, a strand of blonde hair clinging to a collar.</p>
        <p>What to do with a spunky navy blue jogging suit that my 97-year-old mother had worn in her last days on earth as she pushed herself to walk the halls of her apartment building? Or the pale green dress that she wore to synagogue on the High Holy Days? Pants would never do, my mother had insisted. Pants were not for synagogue.</p>
        <p>One day, I piled all the skirts and blazers and blouses on the bed, then plopped down on top of them and sobbed. They seemed so small, and so forlorn.</p>
        <p>In the end, my sister, Ruthie, and I packed up the clothes to donate to charity. Before the final cut, Ruthie claimed several coats and jackets that she wanted to wear as a way of remembering. I scooped up the wonderful hot-pink dress that my mother had worn to the last family milestone: her great-granddaughter's bat mitzvah, just weeks before she died. Even the color of that dress spoke of the triumph of Mom's being there. And on its lapel, my ever fashion-conscious mother had sewn a beautiful pink silk flower. How those weary hands managed that feat, I'll never know. But the stitches were perfect.</p>
        <p>Carton after carton was loaded onto the apartment house elevator and then into our various cars. Jill took her grandmother's wedding china. Amy took some silver. Nancy found pottery pieces and orphaned bowls and vases that she distributed through her rambling old house in Montclair.</p>
        <p>The furniture was handed off to anyone in the family who wanted it. I have some of the wonderful abstract paintings my mother had lived with for over 70 years, acquired early in her marriage as a ''fee'' for legal work my father had done. My sister has Mom's almost-new white sofa, some of her lamps and a mirror or two. The rest was carted off by a dealer or given to charity.</p>
        <p>And then one day, the apartment we had all known as well as we knew our own homes yawned an empty sigh. Every cabinet, every closet, every surface was bare.</p>
        <p>On that last day, I wandered through the rooms, touching the walls that had enclosed my mother's life. I opened the pale yellow curtains left hanging on her windows, then picked up the last thing I would carry away with me: my mother's sensible tan oxfords, the ones she called her ''old lady shoes.''</p>
        <p>I'll never know why I needed to have them.</p>
        <p>GENERATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
