<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HABITATS/SoHo; A 22-Year Lifetime on Thompson Street</title>
    <meta content="29habi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/realestate/29habi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Habitats | SoHo"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PegLeg NYC (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaw, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Poe, Nick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcnally, Harry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D7153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1254" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HABITATS/SoHo; A 22-Year Lifetime on Thompson Street</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A 22-Year Lifetime on Thompson Street</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN SHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shaw, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Habitats column on roommates Nick Poe and Harry McNally, who occupy four-bedroom, rent-regulated apartment that McNally grew up in on Thompson Street in SoHo section of Manhattan; Poe and McNally started and operated Pegleg NYC, independent clothing line, in apartment until its recent relocation to office on Broadway; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HARRY McNALLY and Nick Poe are arty, neo-Bohemian 20-somethings, the sort of people who can't afford to rent in downtown Manhattan anymore. But they manage to live in the heart of SoHo because they rent the apartment where Mr. McNally spent much of his childhood.</p>
        <p>His father, Keith, who owns quintessential downtown restaurants like Balthazar, Pastis and Lucky Strike, came to the building in 1979. (He has since moved on to a Greenwich Village town house, passing the lease for the regulated rental on to his son.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harry McNally and Nick Poe manage to live in the heart of SoHo because they rent the apartment where Mr. McNally spent much of his childhood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HARRY McNALLY and Nick Poe are arty, neo-Bohemian 20-somethings, the sort of people who can't afford to rent in downtown Manhattan anymore. But they manage to live in the heart of SoHo because they rent the apartment where Mr. McNally spent much of his childhood.</p>
        <p>His father, Keith, who owns quintessential downtown restaurants like Balthazar, Pastis and Lucky Strike, came to the building in 1979. (He has since moved on to a Greenwich Village town house, passing the lease for the regulated rental on to his son.)</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Poe and Mr. McNally's situation may be enviable, they do not live in a spacious loft but in four-bedroom apartment on the fourth floor of a Thompson Street tenement, between Spring and Broome Streets. Other roommates rotate in and out to help pay the $2,400-a-month rent.</p>
        <p>''When I was young,'' said Mr. McNally, 22, ''the apartment ended where the French doors are.'' Pointing to the center hall, he explained that his father got the lease for the adjacent apartment in the late 1990s and knocked down walls to combine the two.</p>
        <p>''Before that, we had a bathtub in the kitchen next to the sink,'' he said. ''There was no shower. And there was just one bedroom and his office where my sister and I stayed on the pullout sofa when we came over.''</p>
        <p>(His parents are divorced, and he spent time near Gramercy Park with his mother, Lynn Wagenknecht, also a restaurateur.)</p>
        <p>When his father got the second apartment, ''I guess he overcompensated,'' Mr. McNally said wryly, ''because he made the bathroom the largest room.'' With its painted paneled walls, chandelier and freestanding claw-foot tub, the bathroom looks like something you'd find in a chic vacation farmhouse in Provence.</p>
        <p>''We bring chairs in there and hang out,'' said Mr. Poe, 22, who is not only Mr. McNally's roommate and best friend but also his business partner. ''We do photo shoots in there, too.''</p>
        <p>The photo sessions feature clothes by Pegleg NYC, the indie clothing line that they operated out of the apartment for 17 months until recently, when they rented an office on lower Broadway.</p>
        <p>Getting the office space has been helpful, said Mr. McNally, who recalled the special challenge of receiving shipments in the apartment. ''We had to carry 45 boxes up three flights of stairs,'' he said, ''and then we'd have to repack them and carry them down three flights to ship them out.''</p>
        <p>They also had roommates and a constant stream of friends stopping by. ''It became hard to distinguish work and play,'' Mr. Poe said. ''There would always be people around, and it would prolong how long it took us get things done. It seemed like we were always working, and finally we decided to separate things.''</p>
        <p>Their first collection was seven styles of graphic T-shirts, which they sold to nearby shops like Union and Charlotte Ronson. These days, they also make sweatshirts, tank tops and boxers; their line is carried by 60 retailers in the United States and abroad.</p>
        <p>''We have a big fan base in Sweden,'' said Mr. McNally, who talks about Pegleg as if it were a cultural movement rather than a brand, and he sees himself more as artist than businessman. ''We sell a lot in Japan. We get e-mails from all over the world.''</p>
        <p>In keeping with this broader perspective, e-commerce is just a small part of their Web site, which includes an interview with Debbie Harry, the iconic '80s pop star, and a video starring Mordechai Rubinstein, a Lubavitcher dandy from Crown Heights.</p>
        <p>''When we started,'' Mr. Poe said, ''we knew clothes would only be one facet of our collective-slash-company. The name would be the platform under which we could exhibit video, film, animation and fine art.'' They even made a video for a better-established SoHo label, Jack Spade, which is also on their Web site.</p>
        <p>Mr. Poe -- whose mother, Sarah Charlesworth, is an artist, and whose father, Amos Poe, is a filmmaker -- grew up on pre-gentrified Great Jones Street nearby. Describing Pegleg as primarily an outlet for creative expression, he said: ''It definitely wasn't some kind of huge moneymaking idea. It was more that we wanted to wear our own clothing. Graphic T-shirts were getting really big, and we didn't like anything that was out there.''</p>
        <p>They borrowed start-up money from family and friends, which they have already repaid in full. Almost everything is now made in China through a production and sourcing agent in Hong Kong. Pegleg T-shirts retail for $48 and its sweatshirts for $150.</p>
        <p>The two men are their own muses. ''We were very fashion-conscious and very particular about what we wore and repping something that was our own look,'' Mr. McNally said with an earnest intensity. ''We design for ourselves. All the stuff we come up with is stuff we want to wear. It kind of distinguishes us a bit.''</p>
        <p>Many of their graphics are inspired by the theories of the art historian Erle Loran, famous for analyzing how Cézanne used form and color. ''We do a lot of color-block design,'' said Mr. Poe, who discovered Loran in an art history class at New York University. ''Everyone else is doing skulls and guns. We are stepping away from adolescent graphics.''</p>
        <p>Their T-shirts are bold, colorful and cheerful, qualities that seem to jibe with their personalities. ''If we are at a party, we stand out,'' Mr. McNally said. ''We're humble but loud. You don't see our names on the clothes. They're for someone who wants to be a little flashy, a bit flamboyant.''</p>
        <p>They apparently know like-minded people, because they say all their friends wear their clothes. ''There's a community basis for the whole thing,'' Mr. Poe said. ''Sometimes we'll be out with 20 Pegleg kids.''</p>
        <p>Even now, with their new office, they still spend almost all their time together, and work is always on their minds. ''I think of school as my extracurricular activity,'' said Mr. Poe, who expects to graduate from N.Y.U. in May. (Mr. McNally attended Santa Clara University in California and the New School.)</p>
        <p>They say they cannot imagine living in Williamsburg or Bushwick like many of their peers. ''I haven't spent much time in Brooklyn,'' Mr. McNally said. ''I'm Manhattan-centric. If we ever have to move, we'll go to Chinatown or further east. We are actually from New York. We are proud New Yorkers.''</p>
        <p>They also like living in a building with a personal history. ''My godfather lives down the hall,'' Mr. McNally said, adding that their neighbors include several only-in-New York characters. ''There's a 90-year-old guy with a pigeon coop on the roof and a woman who walks her cat up there.''</p>
        <p>As he stood on the front stoop of his building, he became uncharacteristically nostalgic for a 22-year-old. He remembered that the nail salon next door used to be a butcher shop. ''I think that's why there are so many rats on this street,'' he said, ''or maybe it's because there is construction at the end of the block. I can't believe they knocked down that great old garage. There is very little about gentrification that is good.''</p>
        <p>Does Mr. McNally eat most of his meals at his father's restaurants? ''I try to keep that separate,'' he said. ''I don't even go once a month.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Poe is less detached. ''I probably eat at the restaurants more than Harry does,'' he acknowledged. ''I love the brunch at Lucky Strike, and if I want to impress a date, I go to Pastis.''</p>
        <p>Habitats | SoHo</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
