<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Widening Problem Is Selig's to Solve</title>
    <meta content="29rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/baseball/29rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070503T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Torre, Joe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cashman, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E5DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Widening Problem Is Selig's to Solve</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Widening Problem Is Selig’s to Solve</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In one corner of the Yankees' dugout yesterday afternoon, Alex Rodriguez sat alone with his thoughts before taking batting practice.</p>
        <p>At the other end, a cluster of 40 members of the news media surrounded Manager Joe Torre. The thrust of their questions was about the Yankees' swoon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This steroids tidal wave will define Bud Selig’s tenure as commissioner. How he handles it will define his baseball life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In one corner of the Yankees' dugout yesterday afternoon, Alex Rodriguez sat alone with his thoughts before taking batting practice.</p>
        <p>At the other end, a cluster of 40 members of the news media surrounded Manager Joe Torre. The thrust of their questions was about the Yankees' swoon.</p>
        <p>Faced with the prospect of losing an eighth consecutive game, Rodriguez and Torre were largely oblivious to the tidal wave that was about to engulf Major League Baseball as a result of testimony from a former Mets clubhouse assistant.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Kirk Radomski, a former bat boy, equipment manager and clubhouse assistant for the Mets, pleaded guilty in federal court to distributing performance-enhancing drugs to dozens of former and current major league players for a 10-year period beginning in 1995.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez, Torre and I were in different worlds. I was stunned by the news about the distribution ring and about the names that will probably surface. Rodriguez was thinking about the Red Sox and the losing streak. He said that he had heard about the steroids story and commented that it would only get juicy once names began to leak out.</p>
        <p>Torre was more attuned to the implications of the news. The losing streak would end, he said, they always do. But baseball's steroids problem keeps going on and on, widening and now deepening. Now names may be named and careers may be ruined.</p>
        <p>''All the players aren't using them,'' Torre said. ''I think the players are the first ones who would like to get this thing solved because they don't want everybody painted with the brush. They don't want fans saying about everybody who hits a home run, 'I wonder.'</p>
        <p>''I think they have to get the trust of the fans back,'' Torre added, referring to Major League Baseball. ''The only way you can do that is to turn over every stone, open every door and just try to get to the bottom of it so that we can gain the fans' trust back.''</p>
        <p>I suggested that a wholesale cleansing might be good for baseball. ''It'll be revealing,'' Torre said. ''If it solves the problem, it's good.''</p>
        <p>At this point, I'm not sure what, besides total honesty, is going to solve baseball's steroid stain. For many, steroids has been a Barry Bonds issues, and the force of national debate has centered on how to stop Bonds, how to ignore Bonds. Clearly, this scandal has a number of faces.</p>
        <p>Each of baseball's nine commissioners has had a mission, though a few stand out. This steroids tidal wave will define Bud Selig's tenure as commissioner. How he handles it will define his baseball life.</p>
        <p>In 1920, Kenesaw Mountain Landis became baseball's first commissioner, after the sport was traumatized by the Black Sox scandal of the previous season. His charge was to purge baseball of evil.</p>
        <p>Happy Chandler (1945-1951) presided over the integration of Major League Baseball; Bowie Kuhn (1969-1984) presided over the players' successful challenge to baseball's suffocating reserve clause.</p>
        <p>Selig's cross to bear is this ever-widening steroids scandal. His mission most closely resembles Landis's, whose charge was to restore public trust and integrity to the game.</p>
        <p>Landis didn't have to worry about a Donald Fehr-led players union and went about the business of housecleaning in an iron-fisted way. He was determined that baseball ''avoid the appearance of evil,'' as he said. He ordered owners to divest themselves of racetrack interests and stopped players, including Babe Ruth, from barnstorming and fined them when they did. It was Landis who came up with the concept of ''conduct detrimental to baseball.'' Landis, were he the commissioner today, would no doubt blacklist every player named in a steroids case and bar anyone else who knew of steroids use.</p>
        <p>I'm not calling for Selig to be a Landis, heaven forbid. But I am calling on him to make a stand, take a position. I am eager to see how wide and how deep baseball's steroids problems run.</p>
        <p>Not everybody is. Torre, probably speaking for many inside baseball, said: ''I don't think every single person needs to be thrown under the bus. Just the process is more important to keep it out of the game than it is to start naming every single player and making an example of them.''</p>
        <p>And Selig?</p>
        <p>The game over which he presides is being embarrassed and torn to shreds by a scandal that is spreading rather than going away. The government has documents, wiretaps, shipping records financial records and contact lists from Radomski.</p>
        <p>The government seems to have overwhelming evidence that points to a widespread steroid use in Major League Baseball. This, officially, is no longer simply a Barry Bonds issue; if Bonds goes down, he'll apparently have plenty of company.</p>
        <p>In March 2005, Selig and Fehr told a Congressional hearing that baseball did not have a major problem with steroids.</p>
        <p>He said this even as Radomski was conducting business.</p>
        <p>There are myriad questions for baseball to confront: How widespread was steroids use? Who was involved? And, most important, what will Selig do once he learns the identity of the players? Will they be expelled or suspended? Will those holding records have the records removed?</p>
        <p>There is a problem, Commissioner, and it's widening.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 3, 2007, Thursday  A Sports of The Times column in some copies on Sunday, about the continuing problems with steroids in Major League Baseball, referred incorrectly to the origin of a rule covering ''conduct detrimental'' to the sport. The top professional leagues included a conduct clause in their governing agreement in 1896, and baseball historians say the notion probably emerged before that. The concept was not created by Kenesaw Mountain Landis, who was elected baseball's first commissioner in 1920, and who is credited with rigorous enforcement of the conduct clause.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 3, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A Sports of The Times column in some copies on Sunday, about the continuing problems with steroids in Major League Baseball, referred incorrectly to the origin of a rule covering ''conduct detrimental'' to the sport. The top professional leagues included a conduct clause in their governing agreement in 1896, and baseball historians say the notion probably emerged before that. The concept was not created by Kenesaw Mountain Landis, who was elected baseball's first commissioner in 1920, and who is credited with rigorous enforcement of the conduct clause.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
