<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>STATE OF THE UNIONS: Featured in Vows on May 28, 1995; Patricia Durkin and Kenneth Wignall</title>
    <meta content="29UNIONS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/fashion/weddings/29UNIONS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDD123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>STATE OF THE UNIONS: Featured in Vows on May 28, 1995; Patricia Durkin and Kenneth Wignall</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Patricia Durkin and Kenneth Wignall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOIS SMITH BRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brady, Lois Smith</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE way Patricia Durkin and Kenneth Wignall met -- barefoot, at a beachfront bar built of driftwood in Jamaica -- set the easygoing pared-down tone for their relationship. The way she knew she might marry him was equally simple: later, when she saw his considerate, gentlemanly nature in the way he opened doors to let moths out. That said everything for her. ''That's it,'' she remembered thinking. ''He's the guy.''</p>
        <p>At their wedding reception on May 20, 1995, outside the ramshackle raccoon-infested Victorian house they bought along the Jersey Shore in Spring Lake, the couple predicted that their marriage would be one long renovation project.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The couple were featured in Vows in 1995. Marriage drastically changed the original plans of both.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE way Patricia Durkin and Kenneth Wignall met -- barefoot, at a beachfront bar built of driftwood in Jamaica -- set the easygoing pared-down tone for their relationship. The way she knew she might marry him was equally simple: later, when she saw his considerate, gentlemanly nature in the way he opened doors to let moths out. That said everything for her. ''That's it,'' she remembered thinking. ''He's the guy.''</p>
        <p>At their wedding reception on May 20, 1995, outside the ramshackle raccoon-infested Victorian house they bought along the Jersey Shore in Spring Lake, the couple predicted that their marriage would be one long renovation project.</p>
        <p>It has been. At the time of the wedding Ms. Durkin was the high-powered advertising director for Tommy Hilfiger, always attending the coolest parties and restaurant openings; Mr. Wignall was the low-key owner of Crystal Beauty Products, his family's supply company based in St. Catharines, Ontario, who liked sport-fishing in the Caribbean or napping in a canoe.</p>
        <p>Marriage drastically changed the plans of both. Among other things, it brought dust, discomfort and pest control into their lives.</p>
        <p>Every Friday night, they would meet in Spring Lake to work on the house together, yanking off ivy that covered windows and clouded views like cataracts, and removing wallpaper that featured kittens holding hand mirrors. They slept for years in a bedroom with dirty-white wallpaper peeling like sunburned skin.</p>
        <p>For some husbands and wives, renovating a house is like going through couples therapy and shock therapy at once. You learn about each other's comfort level with climbing ladders and living without a working shower. But Ms. Durkin, now 52, and Mr. Wignall, 56, found the renovation was less like therapy and more like a magical archaeological dig.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Durkin, the excitement of celebrity sightings was soon replaced by the thrill over finds on the property. Like when Mr. Wignall found a packet of love letters in the attic from a World War II soldier, or when Ms. Durkin discovered a small silk pouch full of gold coins from the late 1800s and early 1900s while cleaning out the garden shed.</p>
        <p>''It's a bit of a metaphor -- we saw beauty where no one else did,'' said Ms. Durkin, who now runs a media consulting business out of a home office with fleur-de-lys wallpaper. Seeing beauty in the same unlikely things, she said, is one of the reasons people marry, and stay married.</p>
        <p>After about 12 years together, Ms. Durkin and Mr. Wignall, who continues to operate the beauty products company, still laugh easily, shrug things off easily and say they can overcome most problems by doing yardwork or the dishes.</p>
        <p>They just seem to have some kind of flotation device that keeps them buoyant. They tried to have children, but never did. ''No regrets!'' Ms. Durkin said lightheartedly. ''I know if we had children our life would be different, and I really like our life the way it is.'' Getting older doesn't bother them. ''Aging is weird, but what's the alternative?'' she said.</p>
        <p>Nor do they get overworked about their wedding anniversary. Each year they celebrate by driving the exact route they took from the church to their house on their wedding day, down a lane lined with a wall of pink and red azaleas, then along the beach, past the saltwater pools where Ms. Durkin swims when she has poison ivy, and then home. Ms. Durkin, who was single until she was 40, said having a husband is a calming experience over all, ''especially when you thought you hit the 'save as' button and you didn't.''</p>
        <p>When he's not working on the property, Mr. Wignall loves rescuing old cars like some people rescue stray cats. ''Last summer I brought home an older M.G.,'' Mr. Wignall said. ''Pat was like, 'Oh, no, what's he brought home now?' '' His motto, about cars, boats, houses and even marriages: ''Restore them, don't crush them.''</p>
        <p>And he continues to save moths, disoriented turtles and at-risk bird's nests. ''He really doesn't care about certain things guys in New York City care about, like Wall Street,'' she said. ''But he does care about our little piece of the world.''</p>
        <p>On most summer evenings, they can be found outside, eating by candlelight at a stone-top table, with Norah Jones playing on the outdoor stereo system. After dinner they often take a drive in one of Mr. Wignall's convertibles, cruising along back roads with dripping ice cream cones. ''We've got a great life,'' he said. ''We know it, too. That's the most important part. It's not about what you have. It's how appreciative you are of what you have and who you spend your time with.''</p>
        <p>They approach their marriage the way they did their house renovation: They are still digging up new and interesting things about each other, things they didn't know were there, like the pouch of gold coins. ''There is always new stuff to learn about each other,'' Ms. Durkin said. ''That's what makes life interesting, still. We still have the 'Tell me more about you' feeling.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
