<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Elias Returns and Quickly Makes His Presence Felt</title>
    <meta content="29devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/hockey/29devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Ottawa Senators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ottawa Senators</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Elias, Patrik</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E3DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Elias Returns and Quickly Makes His Presence Felt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Elias Returns for Devils and Makes His Presence Felt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrik Elias, the Devils' captain, returned to Continental Arena on Saturday, and the team's first sellout crowd of the season showed up.</p>
        <p>Elias gave the 19,040 fans something to roar about early, helping the Devils score on their first shot, and Jamie Langenbrunner gave them something to shout about nearly three and a half hours later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrik Elias, the Devils’ captain, gave the 19,040 fans something to roar about early, helping the Devils score on their first shot en route to a victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Patrik Elias, the Devils' captain, returned to Continental Arena on Saturday, and the team's first sellout crowd of the season showed up.</p>
        <p>Elias gave the 19,040 fans something to roar about early, helping the Devils score on their first shot, and Jamie Langenbrunner gave them something to shout about nearly three and a half hours later.</p>
        <p>Langenbrunner scored on a breakaway 1 minute 55 seconds into the second overtime to give the Devils a 3-2 victory against the Ottawa Senators and tie their best-of-seven Eastern Conference semifinal series at one game apiece.</p>
        <p>Games 3 and 4 will be in Ottawa, on Monday and Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''I don't do a whole lot of moves on breakaways,'' said Langenbrunner, who took a pass from Travis Zajac before skating in and beating Ottawa goaltender Ray Emery. ''I don't want to confuse myself.''</p>
        <p>Devils goalie Martin Brodeur stopped 43 shots, including 14 in overtime, and made several magnificent saves in a frenetic third period.</p>
        <p>Sergei Brylin scored in the final second of the first period, but the Devils could not hold a two-goal lead.</p>
        <p>The Senators tied the score with only 27 seconds left in the third period, after they had pulled Emery for an extra attacker. The Devils could not clear the puck from the zone or stop the big left wing Dany Heatley from taking the low slot.</p>
        <p>Ottawa center Jason Spezza took a pass from Senators forward Antoine Vermette and threaded a pass from behind the goal line to Heatley. He scored his fourth goal of the playoffs by pushing the puck into the left side of the net.</p>
        <p>''No use feeling sorry for yourself,'' forward Scott Gomez said of the tying goal. ''You've got to let go of it as soon as possible.''</p>
        <p>For the first time in 46 regular-season and playoff games this season, the Devils played in front of a packed Continental Arena. Game 1 of the series Thursday drew a quiet crowd of 15,512.</p>
        <p>Elias, who missed Game 1 of the series because of the flu, had an assist on a power-play goal by Brian Gionta 1:43 into the game. Elias was also the one who drew the penalty, making an impact on his first shift. As he worked through the Ottawa zone, Elias was slashed by Senators defenseman Anton Volchenkov with such force that he dropped his stick.</p>
        <p>Volchenkov was called for a penalty, giving the Devils a power play only 67 seconds into the game. They needed 47 seconds to take advantage of it. Gionta scored off a touch pass from Elias as the Devils sped over the Ottawa blue line, beating Emery with a rising slap shot from the right wing.</p>
        <p>The Devils did not allow Ottawa to mount much of an attack, killing off a penalty on Gomez without allowing a shot. With three minutes remaining in the period, Ottawa forward Peter Schaefer leveled Langenbrunner with an inadvertent high stick.</p>
        <p>A Devils trainer sprinted onto the ice and handed Langenbrunner a towel, which he pressed into his bloody forehead. Schaefer received a double-minor for high-sticking, giving the Devils four minutes with a man advantage.</p>
        <p>With the first of Schaefer's penalties 14 seconds from expiring, Senators center Mike Fisher slashed Devils left wing Zach Parise, receiving another penalty.</p>
        <p>The Senators appeared as if they would escape the first period without allowing another goal, but Brylin won a face-off against Spezza and flung the puck past Emery while falling down.</p>
        <p>A replay showed that Brylin's shot had gone over the goal line with two-tenths of a second remaining in the period. After a superb first period, in which they outshot the Senators by 16-5, the Devils had a 2-0 lead.</p>
        <p>But they quickly handed one back in the second period. The Senators had a power play three minutes into the period, and Daniel Alfredsson's shot from the left face-off circle beat Brodeur at 4:23.</p>
        <p>Elias nearly restored the Devils' two-goal lead three minutes later, but Emery made a tremendous pad save. Elias was positioned in front of the goal and attempted to deflect a slap shot by Gionta through Emery's legs, but Emery stopped it.</p>
        <p>Devils defenseman Colin White received a penalty for boarding when he slammed Ottawa's Mike Comrie into the end boards at 13:13. On the power play, the Senators forced Brodeur to swipe the puck from the crease while prone on the ice.</p>
        <p>The Devils are usually good at protecting leads, but this one-goal lead looked shaky.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't matter how long it takes -- it could have taken all night,'' Brodeur said. ''It was important to get that win.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
