<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Colt and His Owner, a Long Ride to the Derby</title>
    <meta content="29racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/othersports/29racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="BEATING THE ODDS: From Broadway to Kentucky" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Beating the Odds"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Thoroughbred Racing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valando, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E2DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Colt and His Owner, a Long Ride to the Derby</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Colt and His Owner, a Long Ride to the Derby</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elizabeth Valando's horse Nobiz Like Shobiz came from being one of 34,642 thoroughbreds foaled in United States in 2004 to being one of just 450 horses nominated for Triple Crown races; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Elizabeth Valando was bundled in fur and looked as if she were at Sardi's awaiting the opening-night reviews of a Broadway show. Instead, she stood shivering in the paddock of Aqueduct racetrack watching her trainer, Barclay Tagg, saddle a colt she had fallen for when he was a spindly-legged foal in the Kentucky bluegrass.</p>
        <p>Behind her serene smile, Mrs. Valando, 82, was a wreck. The colt that she had bred was heading onto the track on April 7 for the Wood Memorial, a race that could send them to the 133rd Kentucky Derby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Elizabeth Valando turned down a $17 million offer for her horse, Nobiz Like Shobiz, after he won his first race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Elizabeth Valando was bundled in fur and looked as if she were at Sardi's awaiting the opening-night reviews of a Broadway show. Instead, she stood shivering in the paddock of Aqueduct racetrack watching her trainer, Barclay Tagg, saddle a colt she had fallen for when he was a spindly-legged foal in the Kentucky bluegrass.</p>
        <p>Behind her serene smile, Mrs. Valando, 82, was a wreck. The colt that she had bred was heading onto the track on April 7 for the Wood Memorial, a race that could send them to the 133rd Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>When the colt was born, Jan. 29, 2004, he faced improbable odds of securing one of the 20 post positions for the Derby.</p>
        <p>He was, after all, one of 34,642 thoroughbreds foaled in the United States in 2004, and Mrs. Valando was just another owner with the first Saturday in May 2007 circled in her fantasies. By 2006, the colt was one of 10,390 from that crop to make it to the racetrack. Now, as a 3-year-old, he is one of 450 horses, including 27 from outside the United States, nominated for the Triple Crown races: the Derby, the Preakness Stakes and the Belmont Stakes.</p>
        <p>The pursuit of a Derby champion has humbled people like George Steinbrenner, the principal owner of the Yankees; the television impresario Merv Griffin; and a who's who of business titans. Last year, horse owners spent more than $1.26 billion at North American thoroughbred auctions.</p>
        <p>Still, when Mr. Tagg, a pessimist by nature, saw Mrs. Valando's bay colt with the white blaze between his eyes for the first time, he said, ''If this isn't a Triple Crown horse, I don't know what one looks like.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tagg knew something about champions as the trainer of the 2003 Derby and Preakness winner, Funny Cide.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Valando called her colt Nobiz Like Shobiz, a name that she had been saving to honor her husband, Tommy, a music publisher and Broadway show backer.</p>
        <p>Like a Member of the Family</p>
        <p>Last September, when Nobiz raced for the first time, he seemed to float to a 10 3/4-length victory, which brought a visit from a representative of Sheik Mohammed bin Rashid al-Maktoum, the ruler of Dubai. He made an offer that was hard to refuse: $17 million for Nobiz.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Valando did refuse. Like Roy and Gretchen Jackson, the owners of Barbaro, who won last year's Derby and was fatally injured in the Preakness, Mrs. Valando had a special relationship with her horse.</p>
        <p>''You're not supposed to fall in love with these animals,'' she said. ''Nobiz is like a member of the family. I cannot sell one of them off.</p>
        <p>''I want him to go to Kentucky, but I want him to go with a chance to win. I don't think people understand what a feat it is to get to the Derby, about how much you endure to get there.''</p>
        <p>In 1991, the Valandos had another good horse, Fly So Free. He was the 2-year-old champion and won 7 of 10 starts. He finished fifth in the Derby. They were hooked.</p>
        <p>When her husband of 32 years died in 1995, Mrs. Valando, a former singer, continued to breed horses. She has eight broodmares in Kentucky and races two or three horses at a time. By breeding her mare Nightstorm with the sire Albert the Great for a modest $7,500, Mrs. Valando produced Nobiz.</p>
        <p>On March 1, two days before the Fountain of Youth Stakes at Gulfstream Park in Florida, Mr. Tagg could be forgiven for believing Nobiz was on a path to greatness. In four races, he had lost once, by less than a length, to the accomplished Scat Daddy in the Champagne Stakes last October. Nobiz turned in a flawless workout, and Mr. Tagg ticked off his plan.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to win this race really easily,'' he said. ''I'd like to go to the Wood Memorial and win that race really easily. I'd like to go to the Kentucky Derby and win that race really easily.''</p>
        <p>Derrick Sturniolo, Nobiz's exercise rider, nicknamed him Junior and talked to him as if he were a brother. Mr. Sturniolo, who raced inexpensive horses for small purses at Midwest tracks, had never been close to such a talented thoroughbred. He marveled at Nobiz's economy of motion, how the colt made him feel like a hummingbird atop a jet.</p>
        <p>''Most of the time, these babies, with all their muscle and talent, can be a little mean or nervous,'' he said, stroking Nobiz's nose. ''But Junior here is two different horses. He's all business on the racetrack. But he's a big old love bug in the barn.''</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Tagg could find little to worry about when it came to Nobiz. At 69, his face is unlined, and he has the lithe build of a dancer. Mr. Tagg, however, blends a barbed sense of humor with exasperation that betrays too many hard years.</p>
        <p>After the success of Funny Cide, Mr. Tagg's stable grew to more than 60 horses, nowhere near the hundreds trained by those who top the earnings list.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it hurt me any, but you know it wasn't like everybody is knocking down my door to give me horses,'' he said. ''I had some owners come back that had been with me before. But they might have come back anyway.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Valando was one of the owners who returned. In the late 1990s, he had trained a few of her horses, including Nightstorm. They did not have much luck, so she did what owners often do: moved on to another trainer, first Todd Pletcher, then Carl Nafzger. Mr. Pletcher has a record-tying five horses pointed to the Derby starting gate, and Mr. Nafzger will saddle Street Sense, last year's 2-year-old champion.</p>
        <p>At Mr. Tagg's barn at Gulfstream, the days begin at 5 a.m. Saddles are waxed to a shine, bridles glimmer and the horses' legs are enveloped in spotless white bandages. Mr. Tagg and his assistant and companion, Robin Smullen, rub the horses, dispense ice and examine the animals throughout the day.</p>
        <p>''He's very antidrugs,'' Mrs. Valando said, noting one of the qualities that brought her back to Mr. Tagg. ''What you see is what you get.''</p>
        <p>She was also pleased by his reaction to her refusal of the sheik's offer for Nobiz, and a $500,000 commission for Mr. Tagg.</p>
        <p>''I didn't go into this business for the money,'' he told her.</p>
        <p>Nor is Mrs. Valando, who has refused to insure Nobiz because she does not want to profit from any injury.</p>
        <p>Getting Serious With Funny Cide</p>
        <p>Mr. Tagg said that another Derby victory is out there for him, and hinted that he should have captured his first one sooner.</p>
        <p>He spoke of Funny Cide as if he were speaking about himself. They were the wrong-side-of-the-tracks winners. He was a little-known horseman, Funny Cide a modest New York-bred gelding. The owners were a consortium of everymen, including six middle-aged high school buddies from Sackets Harbor, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Despite winning the first two legs of the Triple Crown and the Jockey Club Gold Cup the next year, Funny Cide has been underappreciated, Mr. Tagg said.</p>
        <p>''He won stakes every year of his life except as a 5-year-old,'' he said. ''He won a graded stake as a 6-year-old. No Kentucky Derby winner has ever done that before. And everybody still knocks him and knocks me.''</p>
        <p>Now 7, Funny Cide remains in Mr. Tagg's barn even though his best racing days are probably over.</p>
        <p>''He's happy as hell out there,'' Mr. Tagg said. ''He loves to gallop. He loves to breeze, and he loves the training. He loves to go out and roll in the sand in the afternoon, buck and kick and bray.''</p>
        <p>Funny Cide used to be in the No. 1 stall, but he was moved next door to make room for Nobiz.</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Tagg paid attention to the way Michael Matz trained Barbaro at the Fair Hill Training Center in Maryland, where each had a barn.</p>
        <p>''He had the most fabulous horse anybody's seen in a long time,'' Mr. Tagg said. ''It was a machine.''</p>
        <p>He thought he had a colt as capable as Barbaro. It took 1 minute 49.11 seconds to change his mind.</p>
        <p>That was the time it took for Nobiz to finish third behind Scat Daddy and Stormello in the Fountain of Youth. He lost by half a length, but it was the way he finished that worried Mr. Tagg.</p>
        <p>As the field turned for home, jockey Cornelio Velasquez had Nobiz comfortable and in striking range. When Velasquez asked Nobiz to find his finishing gear, it was not there. Scat Daddy surged past in the final 50 yards. When Nobiz found his stride, it was too late.</p>
        <p>In the days that followed, Mr. Tagg watched replays of the race and figured that Nobiz was just immature. He had two months, and one more race, to grow up.</p>
        <p>On March 20, Mr. Tagg sent Nobiz to the track alongside Funny Cide, to get Nobiz used to being challenged in close quarters.</p>
        <p>The two went five furlongs in a blistering pace. It was difficult to tell the old pro who had won more than $3.5 million from the inexperienced colt.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to work him in company, and there aren't many I could send with him other than Funny Cide,'' Mr. Tagg said.</p>
        <p>Tinkering to Victory</p>
        <p>Six days later, Nobiz worked well in tandem again. Still, Mr. Tagg was not done tinkering.</p>
        <p>For the Wood Memorial, Nobiz wore blinkers to force him to focus on the racetrack. He also had his ears stuffed with cotton to block out the crowd noise.</p>
        <p>Either Nobiz was going to run himself into the Kentucky Derby or he was not. Mr. Tagg wondered whether the colt who had always looked the part of a Triple Crown champion was going to act like one.</p>
        <p>That was an excruciating afternoon for Mrs. Valando. She had lunch with friends and relatives in the Trustees Room of Aqueduct, a far cry from Sardi's on opening night, though the tension was about the same.</p>
        <p>If Nobiz performed well, they were going to Churchill Downs. Mrs. Valando seemed to be barely breathing as Nobiz took the lead into the final turn. He beat back the challenge of the highly regarded Any Given Saturday as they hit the stretch. Then Nobiz stayed straight and true, winning by half a length over the late-running Sightseeing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tagg looked relieved. Mrs. Valando was drained and exhausted. In the weeks since, she has been battling bronchitis and an ulcer at her home in Greenwich, Conn.</p>
        <p>She will be at the Derby on Saturday, however, with a horse that she bred and believed in.</p>
        <p>Beating the Odds</p>
        <p>Articles in this series are examining the preparation of horses and the motivation of owners and trainers who are striving to win the Kentucky Derby on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Beating the Odds</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
