<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Steinbrenner Gets Restless, Torre's Job Is in Jeopardy</title>
    <meta content="29torre" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Steinbrenner Gets Restless, Torre's Job Is in Jeopardy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Torre handled the questions yesterday with the calm assurance that has characterized his tenure as Yankees manager, even though his status may be as shaky as it has ever been.</p>
        <p>''The losing is much worse than the questions,'' Torre said. ''So don't worry about it. Knock yourselves out.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Torre handled the questions yesterday with the calm assurance that has characterized his tenure as Yankees manager, even though his status may be as shaky as it has ever been.</p>
        <p>''The losing is much worse than the questions,'' Torre said. ''So don't worry about it. Knock yourselves out.''</p>
        <p>The questioning from reporters, though, is not why Torre's job is in jeopardy. George Steinbrenner, the principal owner, is restless over the Yankees' recent losing streak and is considering whether he should fire Torre after this weekend's series.</p>
        <p>''I think he's going to wait and see what happens this weekend, and then we'll see,'' Steinbrenner's spokesman, Howard Rubenstein, said when asked about Torre before yesterday's game. ''You can imagine how he's feeling, but he's not going to say anything today. He may say something after this weekend, I'm not sure.''</p>
        <p>If Steinbrenner does fire Torre, the leading candidate to replace him is the bench coach Don Mattingly. Although Mattingly has never managed, he has clout with the players and was personally recruited by Steinbrenner to join Torre's staff after the 2003 season.</p>
        <p>General Manager Brian Cashman said he believed there was ''no doubt'' that yesterday's 3-1 victory over the Red Sox would ease the tension coming from the top. Cashman blamed the Yankees' rough April on injuries and said he was more at fault than Torre.</p>
        <p>''As far as I'm concerned, it's my responsibility,'' Cashman said. ''I don't think Joe's at fault, no. If anything, it's me.''</p>
        <p>But the jobs of Cashman and Ron Guidry, the pitching coach, do not appear to be in danger, just as they were safe after the playoff loss to Detroit last fall.</p>
        <p>Now, as it was then, Torre is on Steinbrenner's mind. Cashman saved Torre's job last fall, but no one seems to believe Cashman could do so again. Steinbrenner put the onus on Torre when he let him keep his job, and when Torre called Steinbrenner on Monday, he said he understood his duty was to win, with no excuses.</p>
        <p>''We talked about that the other day,'' Torre said. ''This is my responsibility. For me to say, This, this and this, I don't want to pass it off and say it's not my fault. I'm in charge here. I'm certainly not shying away from any responsibility.</p>
        <p>''If you're going to enjoy the good times, you certainly have to understand that to get there, you've got to deal with some potholes. I'm not going to throw anybody to the wolves. This is a team, and we need to get it done. That's my mentality.''</p>
        <p>One issue in the background is Steinbrenner himself. Although Steinbrenner alone will decide Torre's fate, he has all but removed himself from the public eye. Some people who have known him for years believe his health is in decline.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner, 76, spends almost all his time in Tampa, Fla., and he did not even attend the Yankees' games in St. Petersburg last week. In years past, especially in bad times, Steinbrenner has been known to lean on his Tampa advisers, including some who do not like Torre.</p>
        <p>Torre said he did not feel a need to call Steinbrenner again and affirm that he understood his charge.</p>
        <p>''After the time we've been together now, he pretty much knows me and I know him,'' Torre said. ''I understand he's frustrated and, obviously, the history that goes on here. But that's what you understand when you take the job. As far as everything else, I'm going to do the best I can to please him and make him proud of this ball club.''</p>
        <p>Some people around the Yankees have privately questioned Torre's in-game moves since the departure of the bench coach Don Zimmer after the 2003 season. Torre said he never second-guesses himself because, he said, he is always prepared for the decisions he makes.</p>
        <p>The reason for the poor start is primarily pitching. The starters are averaging 4.68 innings a start, the worst figure in the majors, and Torre has summoned the relievers for 92 appearances, the most in the majors.</p>
        <p>Injuries have been a culprit, with Chien-Ming Wang and Mike Mussina missing time with strained hamstrings and Carl Pavano back on the disabled list with a forearm strain.</p>
        <p>The lack of healthy pitchers could buy Torre some time with Steinbrenner, since it clearly was not Torre's intention to use five rookie starters already this season.</p>
        <p>''This is a good team when it's at full strength,'' said Cashman, who canceled a trip to the Dominican Republic this week to stay in New York and focus on the major league team.</p>
        <p>''You really believe it's going to get right at some point,'' Cashman said. ''We just want that some point to be now, because it's a lot harder to struggle in New York than anywhere else; 0-7 feels like 0-14.''</p>
        <p>Players, as would be expected, said they supported Torre and did not want him to be fired.</p>
        <p>''The Boss should be upset; we haven't played well,'' said Derek Jeter, the team's captain. ''In terms of Mr. T., he's not the one out there playing. He is in no way responsible for how we've been playing.''</p>
        <p>Asked if he believed Torre really could pay for the slow start with his job, Jorge Posada said: ''I don't know. Anything can happen. I don't want it to happen.''</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner habitually fired managers before hiring Torre to replace Buck Showalter on Nov. 2, 1995. Steinbrenner has often said that Torre did not become a winner until he hired him, pointing out that Torre had been fired from three other jobs without winning a pennant.</p>
        <p>Torre said those experiences hardened him to the reality of managing.</p>
        <p>''I've never managed just to try to keep my job, because I think I wouldn't be able to do my job if that was the goal,'' Torre said. ''I just have to continue to do what I do, and hopefully it satisfies everybody. If you do something to change the climate, then you kick yourself in the rear end by not being who you are. Certainly, I need to be that.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
