<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I'll Make You Broadway Stars, He Says, and They Just Bark</title>
    <meta content="29peoplectCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29peoplect.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CANINE CAREERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berloni, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sudyk, Robert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Legally Blonde--the Musical (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I'll Make You Broadway Stars, He Says, and They Just Bark</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">I’ll Make You Broadway Stars, He Says, and They Just Bark</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SUDYK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sudyk, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on William Berloni, Broadway show animal trainer whose latest project is training three shelter dogs for Legally Blonde: The Musical; photo(M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILLIAM BERLONI, Broadway's esteemed animal trainer, is about to leave his mark on yet another show. ''Legally Blonde: The Musical,'' which opens tonight at the Palace Theater, features a 47-pound spotted English bulldog as Rufus and a six-pound blond Chihuahua as Bruiser, both trained by Mr. Berloni.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berloni, who has trained animals for 42 Broadway shows, began his career more than 30 years ago, when he reached instant fame just out of high school with an Airedale Terrier mixed breed who played ''Sandy'' in the Broadway hit ''Annie.'' The terrier performed for the show's entire seven-year run -- 2,377 performances, the longest for any animal in Broadway history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>William Berloni, Broadway’s esteemed animal trainer, is about to leave his mark on yet another show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILLIAM BERLONI, Broadway's esteemed animal trainer, is about to leave his mark on yet another show. ''Legally Blonde: The Musical,'' which opens tonight at the Palace Theater, features a 47-pound spotted English bulldog as Rufus and a six-pound blond Chihuahua as Bruiser, both trained by Mr. Berloni.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berloni, who has trained animals for 42 Broadway shows, began his career more than 30 years ago, when he reached instant fame just out of high school with an Airedale Terrier mixed breed who played ''Sandy'' in the Broadway hit ''Annie.'' The terrier performed for the show's entire seven-year run -- 2,377 performances, the longest for any animal in Broadway history.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berloni, a native of Higganum, in Middlesex County, has used only shelter animals since he cast Sandy, who had been abused, abandoned by his keeper and was only hours away from being euthanized when Mr. Berloni bought him for $7. And as he became known throughout the region for his work, shelters began contacting him when they knew he needed a particular type of dog or cat (or the occasional rat, like the one he trained for ''The Woman in White'').</p>
        <p>He heard about Chloe, the bulldog who plays Rufus in ''Legally Blonde,'' and her understudy, Zizi, from a shelter in Stonington, where the dogs had been left after Connecticut Animal Control had rescued them from a locked crate at an abandoned farm in Mansfield.</p>
        <p>''There is this myth that abandoned animals are less smart or not trainable,'' Mr. Berloni said. ''After you look for a certain breed that fits the script, you seek an animal that can deal with stress. I can't imagine a more stressful situation than being locked in a cage in a pound that carries the smell of death. Some caged animals can become depressed or aggressive. Yet you see some others lying there wagging their tails, taking it all in. Obviously, if an animal can deal with all that and still have spunk, you have a winner.</p>
        <p>''At shelters, you often deal with pets with baggage -- severely abused or neglected. They have a rags-to-riches chance to overcome this on Broadway.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Berloni discovered Chico, who plays Bruiser, in an animal kennel in Newark. ''I went to see four dogs there,'' recalled Mr. Berloni, whose dark beard is whitening with age. ''When I reached in the cage, he bit me. Then I took him out for a walk and immediately he became a different dog -- outgoing and friendly.''</p>
        <p>''I really believe deep down that animals picked from shelters believe they are getting a new lease on life,'' Mr. Berloni said. ''They seem to appreciate kindness much more than pure breeds.''</p>
        <p>Chico's younger understudy, Boo Boo (half the size of Chico), was trucked up from Valley River Humane Society in Murphy, N.C., where he would have been euthanized, to the Connecticut Humane Society in Newington, which notified Mr. Berloni. Boo Boo was such a spunky little guy that he took the place of Teddy, who had been in training as the understudy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berloni has never coached dogs as little as Chico and Boo Boo. ''Chihuahuas are small enough to be stepped on,'' he said. ''The stage is a pretty big place. The actors look like a world of giants around them. I was looking for an Alpha dog which wasn't afraid to take on that world, and I found two. Both of them think they're Great Danes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Berloni also teaches actors how to bond with the animals. ''It's repetition, love and positive reinforcement,'' he said. He actually trains the actors to direct the animals on stage through a system of hand signals and rewards while he is standing in the wings.</p>
        <p>Pure breeds are genetically engineered to do one thing well: sit on your lap, become watchdogs or catch Frisbees, Mr. Berloni said. But ''a mutt is a well-rounded canine.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Berloni and his wife, Dorothy, have a four-acre animal retirement home in Higganum, where they care for 18 former show animals. None of them will be put to sleep before their time.</p>
        <p>CANINE CAREERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
