<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F. Y. I.</title>
    <meta content="29fyi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/thecity/29fyi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="F. Y. I."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homework</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hot Lines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koch, Edward I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollak, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/F.Y.I.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5DA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F. Y. I.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What if the Dog Eats It?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL POLLAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollak, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions about New York City's Dial-a-Teacher homework help line, City Hall portrait of Mayor Edward Koch and noise made when police car doors slam shut; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What if the Dog Eats It?</p>
        <p>Q. I consider the city's Dial-a-Teacher program a great school resource. Since it involves children and telephones, I'm guessing that at least a few of the questions have been amusing, to say the least; any you can share?</p>
        <p>A. Amusing is the word. According to Amina Rachman, director of Dial-a-Teacher, the free homework help line sponsored by the United Federation of Teachers that began in New York in 1980, the very first call was from a kindergarten student who said, ''I don't have any homework, but could you tell me a story?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>I consider the city’s Dial-a-Teacher program a great school resource. Since it involves children and telephones, I’m guessing that at least a few of the questions have been amusing, to say the least; any you can share?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What if the Dog Eats It?</p>
        <p>Q. I consider the city's Dial-a-Teacher program a great school resource. Since it involves children and telephones, I'm guessing that at least a few of the questions have been amusing, to say the least; any you can share?</p>
        <p>A. Amusing is the word. According to Amina Rachman, director of Dial-a-Teacher, the free homework help line sponsored by the United Federation of Teachers that began in New York in 1980, the very first call was from a kindergarten student who said, ''I don't have any homework, but could you tell me a story?''</p>
        <p>Here's another one. ''A call came in recently from two parents,'' she said. ''The call was not about homework but rather about their desire to become American citizens. They were studying for their citizenship test and had some questions about Congress.'' The call was handled completely in Hebrew. Once the teacher pointed out that Congress was similar to the Knesset, things were much clearer.</p>
        <p>The most common calls are about math. ''Students have a hard time when they have to tell us what math book they are using,'' Ms. Rachman said. ''Some funny results ensue: Houghton Mifflin becomes Muffin Mathematics.''</p>
        <p>Dial-a-Teacher's number is (212) 777-3380. Calls are answered from 4 to 7 p.m. Mondays through Thursdays.</p>
        <p>No Oils for Koch</p>
        <p>Q. City Hall's gallery of mayoral portraits has an impressive collection of paintings up through David Dinkins, but Edward Koch's portrait is a photograph. How come?</p>
        <p>A. Mr. Koch didn't think all his predecessors came out looking their best.</p>
        <p>''I was not impressed with the portraits of some of the prior mayors,'' the former mayor said in an interview. ''And when I inquired why they didn't use great photographs, I was told that a photograph has to last at least 300 years,'' for posterity. ''And photographs don't.''</p>
        <p>Gregory Heisler, who had taken a photograph of Mr. Koch that the mayor liked very much, told him that a new printing process would satisfy the archival requirement. The photograph, which originally appeared in The New York Times Magazine with a profile of Mr. Koch in June 1989, was reprinted as a color lithograph, with fine-art lithographic inks, on acid-free paper, and it was mounted under ultraviolet-absorbing glass. The city's Art Commission approved the print.</p>
        <p>''So this is the first,'' Mr. Koch said. ''I hope it's not the last.''</p>
        <p>There is no word yet from the offices of Rudolph Giuliani or Mayor Bloomberg on their plans for mayoral portraits.</p>
        <p>The Thunk of the Law</p>
        <p>Q. Why do New York City police car doors make a deep hollowish pop when slammed shut?</p>
        <p>A. The consensus of the police is that you're probably hearing things -- but not a distinctive noise, since officers exiting squad cars don't always want to announce their presence.</p>
        <p>Paul J. Browne, the department's chief spokesman, noted that the police use a variety of vehicles. ''The odds of our Chevys and Fords, with a few Dodges in the mix, all making the same distinctive sound are remote,'' he said in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>However, since police officers almost always respond in pairs, you may be hearing the sound of two doors slamming, he suggested. You may also be hearing a police radio transmission in the background.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL POLLAK</p>
        <p>F. Y. I.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
