<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nature? Nurture? Never Mind. Here's a Sister Act to Watch.</title>
    <meta content="29chess" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/crosswords/chess/29chess.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5DF133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nature? Nurture? Never Mind. Here's a Sister Act to Watch.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nature? Nurture? Never Mind. Here’s a Sister Act to Watch.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dylan Loeb McClain</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcclain, Dylan Loeb</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Siblings who are elite chess players are rare. The best known are probably the Polgar sisters of Hungary. Susan, the eldest, is a grandmaster and former women's world champion. Sofia is an international master. And Judit, the youngest, is the best woman player in history.</p>
        <p>Other notable chess-playing siblings have included the Byrne brothers, Robert, a grandmaster and the longtime columnist for The New York Times, and Donald, an international master who died at 45; and Gregory Shahade, an international master, and Jennifer Shahade, a two-time United States women's champion, who were taught chess by their father, Michael, a master.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his popular book “The Immortal Game,” David Shenk said great chess players were made, not born.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Siblings who are elite chess players are rare. The best known are probably the Polgar sisters of Hungary. Susan, the eldest, is a grandmaster and former women's world champion. Sofia is an international master. And Judit, the youngest, is the best woman player in history.</p>
        <p>Other notable chess-playing siblings have included the Byrne brothers, Robert, a grandmaster and the longtime columnist for The New York Times, and Donald, an international master who died at 45; and Gregory Shahade, an international master, and Jennifer Shahade, a two-time United States women's champion, who were taught chess by their father, Michael, a master.</p>
        <p>Why so few elite sibling players? Is it simply because it is highly unlikely for a single family to produce multiple elite players? Or do most siblings have different interests?</p>
        <p>The questions go to the heart of a familiar debate: Is chess talent innate or nurtured?</p>
        <p>In his popular book ''The Immortal Game,'' David Shenk said great chess players were made, not born, writing, ''Cognitive chess research punctured the longstanding myth of the chess prodigy, the born genius.''</p>
        <p>The best players, Shenk wrote, are the product of intensive study and training. He said the Polgar sisters, who were raised by their father, Laszlo, from an early age to be chess players, were a prime example.</p>
        <p>Shenk recounts an episode years ago in which Susan was studying with an international master and they had a problem they could not solve. They woke up young Judit, who, half-asleep, found the solution immediately and went back to bed.</p>
        <p>Aren't the varying levels of talent among the Polgar sisters, who all presumably had the same training, evidence of innate differences? Possibly.</p>
        <p>A pair of sisters who have been making a big splash lately do not seem to be separated by ability, at least so far. Nadezhda and Tatiana Kosintseva of Russia are ranked No. 14 and No. 24 in the world among women. But at the European championships, which concluded April 15, Tatiana ran away from a large field, finishing two points ahead of her sister.</p>
        <p>Many of Tatiana's games were drawn-out affairs (one went 126 moves), but against Elina Danielian of Armenia she got a large initiative and pressed it home for a quick victory.</p>
        <p>The opening was the Caro-Kann Defense, which can be hard for White to crack. The drawback to the opening, particularly the advance variation that Kosintseva played, is that Black's development lags.</p>
        <p>With 9 a4, Kosintseva chose an unusual plan. More common is to complete development with 9 Bd2 or play 9 c3 to support the central pawns.</p>
        <p>After 15 Qa4, Danielian could have tried 15  Qd7, but she probably found the position after 16 b5 Rc3 17 Bd2 Rc7 18 ba Qa4 19 Ra4 ba 20 Ba6 unpalatable.</p>
        <p>Kosintseva's 18 c4 was a nice move, prying open the d file.</p>
        <p>Finally, facing the loss of her queen, Danielian gave up.</p>
        <p>The United States Chess Federation has given a lifetime membership to Derek O'Dell, the president of the Virginia Tech chess club, who was shot during the rampage at the campus this month. During the attack, an injured O'Dell helped to block a classroom door, preventing the gunman, Seung-Hui Cho, from re-entering the classroom.</p>
        <p>The federation has also invited O'Dell to play without charge at the United States Open in July and August, in Cherry Hill, N.J. The federation and the New Jersey State Chess Federation will pay for his hotel room if he accepts.</p>
        <p>CHESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
