<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Stakes in the Catskills</title>
    <meta content="29CIelliman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mohawk Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Catskills (NYS Area)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliman, Kim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berry, Nathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Stakes in the Catskills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kim Elliman and Nathan Berry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berry, Nathan; Elliman, Kim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Open Space Institute chief executive Kim Elliman and assistant Nathan Berry holds New York Gov Eliot Spitzer's agreement with St Regis Mohawk Tribe to build Las Vegas-style casino in Catskills raises serious questions about his pre-election commitment to smarter growth; offers reasons to oppose plan and suggests alternatives (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EARLIER this year, Gov. Eliot Spitzer reached an agreement with the St. Regis Mohawk Tribe that brought New York one step closer to having a $600 million Las Vegas-style casino in Sullivan County, in the Catskills. The casino, which still needs final federal approval and faces a lawsuit from environmental groups, could generate up to $100 million for the state and $20 million for the county a year.</p>
        <p>But the economic and environmental downside of this deal needs to be more carefully examined. Particularly worrisome is the casino's planned location within 12 miles of the Catskill Park and New York City's water supply.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EARLIER this year, Gov. Eliot Spitzer reached an agreement with the St. Regis Mohawk Tribe that brought New York one step closer to having a $600 million Las Vegas-style casino in Sullivan County, in the Catskills. The casino, which still needs final federal approval and faces a lawsuit from environmental groups, could generate up to $100 million for the state and $20 million for the county a year.</p>
        <p>But the economic and environmental downside of this deal needs to be more carefully examined. Particularly worrisome is the casino's planned location within 12 miles of the Catskill Park and New York City's water supply.</p>
        <p>The casino is the governor's first major upstate economic development initiative. While it demonstrates his desire to see the Catskills prosper, it raises serious questions about his pre-election commitment to smart growth.</p>
        <p>If approved, the casino will be 85 miles north of New York City, practically on the border of the 700,000-acre Catskill Park, of which 41 percent, or 290,000 acres, has been acquired by the state, with most of the rest privately owned. Unfortunately, there is no regional land-use authority to control development on private lands, which jeopardizes the area's water quality and ecological integrity.</p>
        <p>Perhaps even more dire is the threat the casino would pose to New York City's water supply, the largest unfiltered water system in the United States and the source of 90 percent of the city's drinking water. The city has spent billions of dollars to maintain and improve water quality, which thus far has allowed it to avoid the crippling cost of filtration. Yet today the water supply is in danger, in large part because of development and its associated pollution. Further degradation would require the city to construct a huge filtration plant that would cost as much as $10 billion and push water rates up 50 percent.</p>
        <p>It is clear that the governor cares about the economic vitality of places like Sullivan County, but there are other ways to help that do not jeopardize such important recreational and natural resources.</p>
        <p>Many people fondly recall the Borscht Belt era of the 1950s and '60s, when Jewish summer camps and resorts thrived in the Catskills. Those who wish to romanticize those years should remember that the resorts' success stemmed from the area's natural charms: its rolling farmland, its mountains and streams.</p>
        <p>And despite the decline of the Borscht Belt resorts and counter to popular perceptions of the Catskills and the state of its economy, Sullivan County has recently experienced strong economic and population growth. Its unemployment and poverty rates are below the state average, and only a handful of New York's 62 counties have witnessed a bigger housing boom.</p>
        <p>What's driving this growth? The region's natural resources and beauty. The governor and Sullivan County officials need to approach Catskill development by recognizing that economic prosperity can arise from protecting natural resources.</p>
        <p>Instead of building a casino, the governor should promote a regional approach to development similar to those used in other resource-rich places like the Pine Barrens on Long Island. With or without a casino, the Catskills' natural resources need to be inventoried, and then a plan should be devised to safeguard those resources. Concentrating growth in downtown areas and redeveloping already built sites should be encouraged, while sprawling growth in outlying areas not served by community wastewater treatment facilities, roads and other infrastructure should be strongly discouraged.</p>
        <p>More specifically, the governor should provide tax and other incentives to local governments in the Catskills to adopt zoning regulations that protect scenic and recreational areas. Development is now allowed practically everywhere, including in floodplains and on ridge lines. Smart zoning would preclude development that ruins views, pollutes water and makes floods more damaging.</p>
        <p>He should also establish a program to compensate landowners in natural resource-rich areas who give up their land's development rights or transfer those rights to an area that is already developed and has the capacity for more growth.</p>
        <p>Farms and forests are not only an important part of community character, they also contribute to the tax base while requiring few public services -- cows and trees don't go to school. In recent decades, we have seen increased fragmentation and development of these working lands as small-scale farming and forestry have become less profitable. To counter that trend, Governor Spitzer should support farmers and foresters through market incentives, tax abatement and subsidies.</p>
        <p>And finally, the governor should encourage ecotourism by having the state acquire key parcels of land in the Catskill Park, expand the trail network and increase access points to state lands and waters. There are large gaps in public ownership within the park's boundaries. Increasing the state's share of the park would safeguard its already substantial investment and increase recreational opportunities and public use.</p>
        <p>For more than 100 years, the Catskills have been recognized as a special place. But enlightened planning is necessary. While the casino deal awaits federal approval, let's hope the governor invests in other, more environmentally and economically sound ways to revitalize the region.</p>
        <p>Kim Elliman is the chief executive of the Open Space Institute, a land conservation organization. Nathan Berry is his assistant.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kim Elliman is the chief executive of the Open Space Institute, a land conservation organization. Nathan Berry is his assistant.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
