<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Money for Nothing On Triple Crown Trail</title>
    <meta content="29score" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/othersports/29score.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843903"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="KEEPING SCORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Barbaro (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Belmont Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Money for Nothing On Triple Crown Trail</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Money for Nothing on Triple Crown Trail</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM SQUIRES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Squires, Jim</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Kentucky Derby kicks off racing's Triple Crown series next Saturday, many of the biggest gamblers in the thoroughbred game will have already lost their bets.</p>
        <p>These are the wealthy wannabe kings of the modern-day sport who each year spend hundreds of millions of dollars on yearlings and 2-year-olds trying to buy a horse capable of delivering the glory and return on investment that would come with owning the stallion that sweeps all three American classics. Of the 35 most expensive colts from this year's 3-year-old crop purchased at public auction, only the $1.5 million Cowtown Cat is still on track for the quest. And his early odds are 20-1 in the Derby. This means the other $88.5 million spent on 34 others may be hard to recover.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only 11 horses have won the Derby, Preakness and Belmont to become Triple Crown winners since they began trying in 1919, none since Affirmed in 1978.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Kentucky Derby kicks off racing's Triple Crown series next Saturday, many of the biggest gamblers in the thoroughbred game will have already lost their bets.</p>
        <p>These are the wealthy wannabe kings of the modern-day sport who each year spend hundreds of millions of dollars on yearlings and 2-year-olds trying to buy a horse capable of delivering the glory and return on investment that would come with owning the stallion that sweeps all three American classics. Of the 35 most expensive colts from this year's 3-year-old crop purchased at public auction, only the $1.5 million Cowtown Cat is still on track for the quest. And his early odds are 20-1 in the Derby. This means the other $88.5 million spent on 34 others may be hard to recover.</p>
        <p>But one such bet is very much alive. Majority interest in a colt named Curlin, who had sold for a meager $57,000 as a yearling and won his first race only in February, was sold shortly afterward for a reported $3.5 million to two multimillionaires, Jess Jackson of Kendall Jackson wine and Satish Sanan, an Indian computer guru known for extinguishing the so-called millennium bug. The two are relative newcomers to racing but, like many before them, are hot for a Derby horse.</p>
        <p>Only 11 horses have won the Derby, Preakness and Belmont to become Triple Crown winners since they began trying in 1919, none since Affirmed in 1978. And there is ample evidence that it is harder than ever, largely because of a dramatic shift in the way commercial breeders have responded to market demands that favor early speed in 2-year-olds over the stamina and soundness needed by a Triple Crown winner a year later. Naturally, big money -- mainly the vast sums that ambitious people are willing to pay for a promising 2-year-old -- drove the change.</p>
        <p>It was in the euphoria in the wake of the last three Triple Crown winners -- Secretariat in 1973, Seattle Slew in 1977 and Affirmed in 1978 -- that million-dollar yearlings became the norm at public auctions and breeders began producing precisely the wrong kind of horse needed to win three races in five weeks. In 1985, when a half-brother to Seattle Slew named Seattle Dancer set the yearling sales record at $13.1 million, the corresponding record for 2-year-old-in-training horses -- known in the industry as juvenile sales -- was $800,000.</p>
        <p>Twenty-one years later at a juvenile sale in Florida, the market changes and the level of their absurdity were underscored when the Irish conglomerate Coolmore, the most influential force in the thoroughbred industry, outbid the second-most powerful, Sheik Mohammed bin Rashid al-Maktoum, ruler of Dubai, for a juvenile colt eventually named The Green Monkey. The price was a record for an untried racehorse, $16 million, about what a royally bred Triple Crown champion could be expected to earn every year of his breeding life.</p>
        <p>Seattle Dancer won just two of five races, earning only $150,000, and The Green Monkey has yet to make it to the racetrack, much less a classic. But in the flesh he was exactly what the market wanted: a good-looking cross of two of the most popular modern sire lines, Storm Cat and Unbridled, and, on paper at least, possessing the speed and stamina necessary to wear the crown.</p>
        <p>While there is staying power on both sides of his pedigree, Storm Cat more often passes to his sons his precocious early speed, and the Unbridled line is notorious for a high percentage of horses too unsound to last long on a racetrack.</p>
        <p>Yet it is the industry preoccupation with just such horses and the lure of such extravagant prices that has kept breeders from producing in substantial numbers horses physically capable of enduring the Triple Crown grind. And today's trainers, many of whom weren't born when Secretariat set the standard, are naturally far more adept at conditioning horses for distances of a mile or less, at which most North American races today are run.</p>
        <p>A handful of throwback breeders continue to produce horses genetically capable of contesting the Triple Crown. In this decade alone, the Kentucky Derby winners Monarchos, War Emblem, Barbaro and Giacomo, and the Belmont winners Touch Gold, Point Given, Birdstone, Empire Maker and Afleet Alex were all products of matings planned without market considerations. And the upcoming Derby field is topped by several, including Curlin, Nobiz Like Shobiz, Street Sense, Circular Quay and Tiago.</p>
        <p>But everyone agrees that even the right horse in the hands of the right trainer that wins the tough Kentucky Derby has little chance of winning the next two against a changing array of fresh contenders. What was always difficult is now proving impossible.</p>
        <p>Seattle Slew's trainer, the New Yorker Billy Turner, said you could not buy a horse to do it, or set out to breed one. ''They just show up,'' he said. Even when they do, it helps when their competition is inferior. Secretariat only had to be a much better horse than Sham, which he was. Affirmed had to be only slightly better than Alydar -- three times. Only the most ardent supporters of Seattle Slew can even remember the names of his vanquished foes, the likes of Run Dusty Run.</p>
        <p>Today, synthetic and safer race surfaces are rapidly reducing the number of injuries to promising young horses. Modern medical science can now measure heart and lung capacity and identify the best ratio of short ''fast'' muscle needed for speed to the long ''slow'' muscle of the stayer. Computers can determine the energy efficiency of stride and gait. Even brain functions that determine temperament can be monitored and perhaps manipulated.</p>
        <p>And breeders are finally realizing that stamina attributed to three leading modern sires -- Storm Cat, A. P. Indy and Gone West -- was for the most part inherited from their Secretariat dams and is most often passed on through their daughters -- not their Triple Crown-nominee sons.</p>
        <p>So coming up with a Triple Crown winner may very well get easier soon. But don't bet on it -- yet.</p>
        <p>KEEPING SCORE E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jim Squires, owner of Two Bucks Farm in Versailles, Ky., bred Monarchos, the 2001 Kentucky Derby winner.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
