<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ARMCHAIR TRAVELER</title>
    <meta content="29armchair" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/travel/29armchair.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Armchair Traveler"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oxford (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woodward, Richard B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Attlee, James</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Isolarion: A Different Oxford (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/Oxford</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Oxford (England)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EFD6173EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ARMCHAIR TRAVELER</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Isolarion: A Different Oxford Journey</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD B. WOODWARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woodward, Richard B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Woodward reviews book Isolarion: A Different Oxford Journey, by James Attlee, about voyage around his neighborhood in Oxford, Eng; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Isolarion: A Different Oxford Journey  By James Attlee  University of Chicago Press, 278 pages, $22.50 hardcover</p>
        <p>In the film ''My Dinner With Andre,'' Wallace Shawn wondered if an attentive stay-at-home traveler couldn't plumb existence more deeply than frequent fliers to alien lands. ''I think if you could become fully aware of what existed in the cigar store next door to this restaurant, I think it would just blow your brains out,'' he tells his peripatetic friend Andre Gregory. ''Isn't there just as much 'reality' to be perceived in the cigar store as there is on Mount Everest?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Why make a journey to the other side of the world when the world has come to you,” the author reasons as he explored his local neighborhood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Isolarion: A Different Oxford Journey  By James Attlee  University of Chicago Press, 278 pages, $22.50 hardcover</p>
        <p>In the film ''My Dinner With Andre,'' Wallace Shawn wondered if an attentive stay-at-home traveler couldn't plumb existence more deeply than frequent fliers to alien lands. ''I think if you could become fully aware of what existed in the cigar store next door to this restaurant, I think it would just blow your brains out,'' he tells his peripatetic friend Andre Gregory. ''Isn't there just as much 'reality' to be perceived in the cigar store as there is on Mount Everest?''</p>
        <p>The English art writer James Attlee heartily concurs. Stricken with ennui during commutes to his publishing job in London, he was tempted to set out on an adventure far outside cellphone range of his wife and children. Instead, he put his tape recorder in his pocket, walked out the front door, and embarked on a voyage around his Oxford neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''Why make a journey to the other side of the world when the world has come to you,'' he reasons. Recording not the hallowed academic haven of dreaming spires, but the more recent and fractious multicultural city, he decides that this less venerated England is best seen on Cowley Road, an ancient thoroughfare that once led pilgrims from the colleges to a medieval healing well, and is now home to immigrants from five continents.</p>
        <p>His meandering route takes him into an Irish pub, an African church and a Hasidic Chabad house; around a former leper colony and a century-old car factory; past the venerable publisher Blackwell and halal fast-food outlets.</p>
        <p>In a darker vein, we meet a therapist who works with Balkan refugees and reports that most of them are on antidepressants -- the women trying to blot out the memory of rapes, the men of torture. According to Mr. Attlee, Oxford is still ''a city full of division, ignorance, and mutual incomprehension, in which many nations live side by side.''</p>
        <p>This is a book about the strategies that people adopt to combat despair and homesickness. For Mr. Attlee, his cheerer-upper was always American black music; for many of the characters here, food is the miracle that helps them remember their roots or establish new ones.</p>
        <p>The book's title refers to areas of 15th-century maps where the maker described a place by overlaying detailed fragments of it. Mr. Atlee's non-linear approach may vex those who like rounded narratives.</p>
        <p>I wish that he had not felt the need to filter his observations through the tired theoretical writings of Michel Foucault and Roland Barthes. When simply listing the names of the phone services along Cowley Road -- ''Mama Africa! Pakistan Connect. Hello Arab. Jamaica Direct. Eastern Eurovoice. Taj Mahal'' -- Mr. Attlee paints an iridescent picture of a new Oxford that no guidebook has yet captured.</p>
        <p>RICHARD B. WOODWARD</p>
        <p>Armchair Traveler</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
