<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sizing Up Your Skills For a Return To Work</title>
    <meta content="29career" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/business/29career.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFFICE SPACE: CAREER COUCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Career Couch</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Working at Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0DA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sizing Up Your Skills For a Return To Work</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sizing Up Your Skills for a Return to Work</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EILENE ZIMMERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmerman, Eilene</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. You have been a stay-at-home mother for several years. Your children are in school now, and you are considering re-entering the work force. Will you be able to find fulfilling work?</p>
        <p>A. Absolutely. Even if you haven't been paid, you have still been working. Women often fail to see that while they were raising children, they were honing their skills in time management, people management and organization, said Jen Singer, creator of MamaSaid.net, an online site for part-time and full-time stay-at-home mothers.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the first step a stay-at-home mother should take to re-enter the paid work force?</p>
        <p>A. Figure out what, exactly, you want to do. Start by writing down your goals, priorities, strengths and weaknesses, said Steve McMahan, president of the Atlantic region for Kforce, a professional staffing firm based in Tampa, Fla. Then, analyze those skills and interests to evaluate how they might have changed during the years at home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Be sure of your goals. And remember that your former employees may now want to hire you.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. You have been a stay-at-home mother for several years. Your children are in school now, and you are considering re-entering the work force. Will you be able to find fulfilling work?</p>
        <p>A. Absolutely. Even if you haven't been paid, you have still been working. Women often fail to see that while they were raising children, they were honing their skills in time management, people management and organization, said Jen Singer, creator of MamaSaid.net, an online site for part-time and full-time stay-at-home mothers.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the first step a stay-at-home mother should take to re-enter the paid work force?</p>
        <p>A. Figure out what, exactly, you want to do. Start by writing down your goals, priorities, strengths and weaknesses, said Steve McMahan, president of the Atlantic region for Kforce, a professional staffing firm based in Tampa, Fla. Then, analyze those skills and interests to evaluate how they might have changed during the years at home.</p>
        <p>''Analyze every previous significant work and volunteer experience and break it down into the basic components of what each job entailed -- the ones you liked, and the ones you didn't. Then you'll see opportunities,'' said Carol Fishman Cohen, co-author of ''Back on the Career Track: A Guide for Stay-At-Home Moms Who Want to Return to Work.''</p>
        <p>Q. How can you update your professional skills?</p>
        <p>A. There are a variety of ways, said Nancy Collamer, a career consultant and founder of Jobsandmoms.com, a Web site for professional women looking for flexible work.</p>
        <p>Take continuing education classes to refresh skills. Attend professional conferences and workshops to improve your industry knowledge. Do volunteer work that affects an organization's bottom line or enhances your leadership skills. And start reading industry journals and publications.</p>
        <p>Do ''anything that will show an employer you've kept up with developments in your field,'' said Jo Bennett, a partner at Battalia Winston International, an executive search firm based in New York.</p>
        <p>Q. What resources are available to you as you search for a job? Should you rely on a professional recruiter, job boards, former colleagues?</p>
        <p>A. Former colleagues are a good place to start. Call people you once worked with and take them to lunch. Perhaps most important are junior people who reported to you when you were working, including anyone you mentored.</p>
        <p>''Those people moved up in your absence and in many cases are now in a position to hire you. And they will remember you,'' Ms. Cohen said. Job boards can help you put feelers out broadly and see what jobs are in demand.</p>
        <p>Professional recruiters will probably be of little value, because they generally place executives with traditional work histories, said Lisa Kojis, a managing partner at PrincetonOne, an executive search firm based in Skillman, N.J.</p>
        <p>If you have been out of the work force for less than two years, you may be able to work with a recruiter who specializes in your area, said Ms. Kojis, especially if you are in a high-demand occupation, like accounting or nursing. And a growing number of firms, including On-Ramps, Mom Corps and Ivy Exec, specialize in placing those who have been out of the work force or want flexible hours.</p>
        <p>Q. How should you account for your employment gap on your résumé?</p>
        <p>A. Remove the dates and make it an accomplishments-oriented résumé, rather than a chronological one.</p>
        <p>You still have to address the gap in your work history, but do it in your cover letter and in the ''personal'' section, said Allison O'Kelly, chief executive and founder of Mom Corps in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Remember to include any volunteer work you did while at home. You could include P.T.A. activities, church fund-raisers or work for your homeowners' association. Just make sure you highlight accomplishments that are transferable to the work world.</p>
        <p>''For example, if you can say 'increased ad sales in the elementary school address book from 25 percent over last year,' it shows you have the ability to sell ads,'' Ms. O'Kelly said.</p>
        <p>Also important is a section covering what you have done to prepare to re-enter your career, Ms. Cohen said, like classes you have taken or notable conferences you have attended.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the best way to prepare for an interview if you are out of practice?</p>
        <p>A. Rehearse. The key to a successful interview is self-confidence. Start by just talking about your work plans to friends, family and others who won't be judgmental, Ms. Cohen advised. ''They will ask you what you want to do, and you'll have to figure out what to say,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Write down answers to typical interview questions and those that will focus on your employment gap.</p>
        <p>Then, conduct mock interviews with friends to make sure you sound ''crisp and experienced,'' Ms. Bennett said. ''Like a business person, not someone used to talking to a toddler.''</p>
        <p>OFFICE SPACE: CAREER COUCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
