<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unfamiliar Names On Familiar Streets</title>
    <meta content="l29city-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Names, Geographical</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Streets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ninehan, Karen Squeglio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feldman, Hinda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sears, Helen (Councilwoman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Geographical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD7123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unfamiliar Names On Familiar Streets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karen Squeglio Ninehan, Hinda Feldman and City Councilwoman Helen Sears letters on Stuart Miller's April 22 article on co-naming of New York City streets</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As the person who initiated the renaming of 94th Street at 52nd Avenue in Elmhurst, Queens, I find ''Turn Left at [Your Name Here],'' by Stuart Miller (Op-Ed, April 22), elitist and condescending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As the person who initiated the renaming of 94th Street at 52nd Avenue in Elmhurst, Queens, I find ''Turn Left at [Your Name Here],'' by Stuart Miller (Op-Ed, April 22), elitist and condescending.</p>
        <p>Agreed, a street sign for someone like Florry Burrell, whose contributions to the community are not widely known, would make passers-by wonder. But that exactly was my purpose -- to make people consider, even for a moment, someone who respected, helped and inspired others. Her specific contributions can easily be found through Google.</p>
        <p>A matching piece of aluminum on a pole does not make clutter, nor is it costly. It is a way to remember the lives of residents who did more than pay taxes and obey the law. A humble street sign for one block is small recognition of one individual's selfless contributions to a community, vital to neighborhoods and the city.</p>
        <p>Karen Squeglio Ninehan  Elmhurst, Queens</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Stuart Miller claims that too many street corners are ''cluttered'' with memorial signs.</p>
        <p>Well, I am the mom of the Karl Feldman whom Mr. Miller singled out as a person who, he implies, has a street named after him because he died of cancer at the age of 19. Street renamings must go through a process, and my son's street renaming was not because he had cancer.</p>
        <p>Karl was a cancer patient at N.Y.U. Medical Center, but was an inspiration to other young patients and a source of encouragement to all. He faced tremendous obstacles in life and yet he was able to set an example for others and live his life no matter what one faces.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller claims that the money used on the street signs would better be used as ''historical plaques telling the stories of the deserving dozen.'' Mr. Miller: when people pass Karl Feldman Way they remember a son, a brother, a friend, a student who contributed so much to society and, most important, a human being who had such an impact on the lives of so many!</p>
        <p>Hinda Feldman  Bulls Head, Staten Island</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>My thanks to Stuart Miller for drawing attention to a situation that is changing one of the best aspects of city life. There's nothing quite like the experience of strolling the city streets lost in reverie. And no city offers that experience like New York.</p>
        <p>However, the posting of names of deceased neighbors on city street signs not only clutters the street corners, it also clutters the mind. Not only does one wonder who these people are, but the pleasant mood of a city stroll is destroyed by the feeling that the vibrant city is being turned into a cemetery.</p>
        <p>Eileen Stukane  West Village</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Turn Left at [Your Name Here]'' discussed street co-namings across New York City. Highlighted was Florry Burrell Way, a street co-naming that I sponsored in the City Council. I cannot condone its trivialization of the life of Ms. Burrell or that of Genesis Regalado -- another street co-naming that I sponsored. The co-naming of these streets highlights the life of a woman dedicated to her family and community and a life lost at a young age because of gun violence.</p>
        <p>Some may see the co-namings of streets as unimportant, but to the communities in which the streets are co-named and to the families of those honored, these ceremonies and symbols are of the utmost importance and hold a valuable place in their hearts. It is the efforts of the everyday New Yorkers who commit themselves to their communities that make New York what it is, a city of unique communities with dedicated and dynamic individuals.</p>
        <p>Helen Sears  Jackson Heights, Queens</p>
        <p>The writer is a City Council member.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In spite of his words, Stuart Miller obviously fulfilled more than one major purpose of the ''street co-naming'' effort. He noticed the names, and researched some of these honored individuals. Could any community hope for more?</p>
        <p>Historical plaques rarely draw any attention from the busy walkers in the street and none from motorists. For those who do notice any of these signs, plaques and statues, I suggest a link from the New York City Web site that would detail the reasons and the honorees for each public display.</p>
        <p>Jared L. Rifkin  Utopia, Queens</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
