<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The One That Got Away</title>
    <meta content="Lowry.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/Lowry.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Miracle of Catfish, A: A Novel in Progress (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The One That Got Away</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The One That Got Away</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEVERLY LOWRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lowry, Beverly</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A MIRACLE OF CATFISH</p>
        <p>A Novel in Progress.</p>
        <p>By Larry Brown.</p>
        <p>455 pp. Shannon Ravenel/Algonquin Books</p>
        <p>of Chapel Hill. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A catfish pond and a cast of eccentrics are at the center of Larry Brown’s unfinished posthumous novel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A MIRACLE OF CATFISH</p>
        <p>A Novel in Progress.</p>
        <p>By Larry Brown.</p>
        <p>455 pp. Shannon Ravenel/Algonquin Books</p>
        <p>of Chapel Hill. $24.95.</p>
        <p>On the day before Thanksgiving in 2004, Larry Brown died, suddenly and shockingly, at 53. According to his longtime editor, Shannon Ravenel of Algonquin Books, he had just sent 700 pages of his new novel, ''A Miracle of Catfish,'' to his agent, along with a promise to finish the final chapters after spending the holiday with his family. He died at home, leaving the novel without an ending.</p>
        <p>Now Algonquin has issued Brown's uncompleted manuscript, as well as some notes he made about the final chapters, as a book. The notes don't add up to much. They are suggestive of possibilities only, the kind of list a writer makes to prove to himself that yes, he's really down to the end and yes, he knows what is going to happen next and yes, he is ready to write it. ''Somehow,'' Brown writes to himself, as he foresees a particular scene, and ''maybe,'' about another.</p>
        <p>Brown never moved away from Oxford, Miss., where he was born. He was a working-class boy, and readers loved him not just for his books but for how he lived his life. He served in the Marines, then came home and became a fireman. At 29, he decided to turn himself into a writer. Seven years later, he was one. But he didn't quit the fire department until he'd published a collection of stories, ''Facing the Music,'' in 1988. After that, he published eight other books of fiction and nonfiction, including the novels ''Dirty Work'' and ''Joe.''</p>
        <p>Questions run a reviewer in circles. How should an unfinished, posthumous book be published? Should somebody else write an ending? How much editing should be done? Do you explain Brown's likely intentions? Or simply stash the manuscript in his archives at the University of Mississippi like a museum piece?</p>
        <p>In an editor's note, Ravenel writes that Brown's manuscripts always came in long and that she always suggested cuts -- ''snipping and shaving,'' she calls it -- that Brown didn't much challenge. In time, Brown's widow, Mary Annie Brown, decided to allow Ravenel to publish ''A Miracle of Catfish,'' and to select passages she thought needed paring down. Ravenel worked carefully. No words were added or changed, no syntax improved. When she made cuts, she inserted ellipses in brackets to indicate omitted passages. She also reprinted Brown's hand-drawn map of the novel's setting, and his list of what might be in the final chapters.</p>
        <p>And now we have it, or most of it.</p>
        <p>''A Miracle of Catfish'' takes place in Larry Brown's world, northern Mississippi. He begins by tracking the thoughts of an old farmer who, while in his fields dodging copperheads and bashing at spiderwebs, envisions the catfish pond he plans to have dug and stocked on his land. In the South, catfish ponds were big business for a while, and to the 72-year-old Cortez Sharp, this plan represents a dream of new prosperity and, at his age, a triumphant adventure. Not that Sharp gives much to age. He raises okra and tomatoes, operates a tractor and a Bush Hog, milks and breeds cows, shoots deer that invade his vegetable garden, cares for his wife, who uses a wheelchair, and worries about his daughter's life in Atlanta with a man who has Tourette's syndrome.</p>
        <p>Contemplating catfish, watching out for poison ivy, Sharp lets his mind drift. Drift is not an indulgence in a Larry Brown novel, and it isn't arbitrary. It is a working tool. It provides information about characters and setting, and it moves the plot. Drift is not incidental, it is in everything: voice, tone and story.</p>
        <p>''A Miracle of Catfish'' proceeds by means of changing points of view, one chapter to the next. When the ''dozer dude'' drives his ''American juggernaut'' of an earth-moving machine onto Sharp's land and begins bulldozing big white oaks into a pile, he thinks about the trees' value while he eats lunch, his wife's cooking. From tree limbs over his head, crows keep watch, making comments to one another like Heckle and Jeckle about the driver's fried chicken and biscuits. In Brown's world, birds and animals, even catfish, sometimes need a voice of their own.</p>
        <p>Most of the action of ''A Miracle of Catfish'' takes place in the area pictured in Brown's map. Sharp and his wife live in a nice house on a big piece of land. Down the cutoff road there's a broken-down trailer that contains a family of five, and the father -- another major character -- is known only as Jimmy's daddy. Jimmy's daddy has two grabby stepdaughters, a philandering wife named Johnette and his own biological son, Jimmy. A sweet boy, 9 years old, Jimmy has teeth that are rotting and there's usually nothing but raw wieners to eat, but he's O.K. with that. He manages. He spends many waking hours sitting outside the trailer, watching for his daddy, hoping he'll show up to teach him to fish or shoot or swim, hoping his daddy won't sell his beloved go-kart and hasn't already sold his Indian spear point, hoping most of all that he'll take him to the Kenny Chesney concert in Tupelo.</p>
        <p>From his first book, Brown has been meditating on fatherhood, its sorrows and occasional joys and the mostly desperate and ill-fated attempts to correct horrendous and stupid mistakes and from now on do better. Few of them succeed. Not in the earlier books -- not in ''Joe,'' not in ''Father and Son,'' not in ''Fay'' -- and certainly not in this one. But at least Johnette gets the boy's teeth fixed, a significant event, teaching Jimmy that sometimes what's broken can be repaired and not just abandoned.</p>
        <p>Other major characters include a black man named Cleve who, like Sharp, is worried about his daughter's boyfriend until he finds a way to move him out of the picture for good, and Tommy Bright, a catfish supplier who has gambled away his business and lost his wife (again) as a result. Tommy supplies the plot's additional great character: a mammoth catfish named Ursula, pale and slippery, a beauteous eater of her own species, thrashing in her tank.</p>
        <p>Larry Brown's books have never flinched in the face of the darkest matters and the crummiest behavior imaginable, including rape, incest, wanton murder, thievery and blithe betrayal. His characters are working people who watch the motorcycles and A.T.V.'s roar by but who have never been able to get beyond the county line themselves (except a couple of them, to Memphis and down to the Gulf Coast, where they go quickly under). The most compassionate of writers, Brown loves every living no-good heart he commits to paper.</p>
        <p>Terrible things happen in ''A Miracle of Catfish,'' as well, but the violence is more controlled, the details less lovingly described than in other Brown novels. Rattletrap cars are, as always, all over the place. So is beer, and dogs, and deer, and unwanted pregnancy. There are industrial and farm accidents in which people are crushed by the machines that are supposed to serve them. The wild countryside is, as always, both gorgeous and deadly, perhaps closer to Brown's heart than any human character in the book.</p>
        <p>Unquestionably, Algonquin did the right thing, publishing only words Brown actually wrote. The brackets can be disconcerting, but the curious reader will soon be able to check out the original manuscript at the Ole Miss library, to see what was omitted. Could Shannon Ravenel have trimmed more extensively? Did the descriptions of, say, the dinner Cortez Sharp fixes for himself after his wife's death and of his daughter Lucinda's experiences with her boyfriend go on too long? Well, yes. And if Brown were alive to say one way or the other, maybe Ravenel would have suggested it. And perhaps Brown would have agreed.</p>
        <p>''A Miracle of Catfish'' yields so many pleasures, it hurts to say so. And while a book without an ending is a little like a joke without a punchline, in this case I expect we should be glad for what we have. Ravenel says that what's been published is ''as clear as can be,'' and that seems about right.</p>
        <p>Beverly Lowry teaches at George Mason University. Her new book, ''Harriet Tubman: Imagining a Life,'' will be published in June.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Beverly Lowry teaches at George Mason University. Her new book, ''Harriet Tubman: Imagining a Life,'' will be published in June.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
