<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Help Wanted</title>
    <meta content="29hist" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/thecity/29hist.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STATEN ISLAND UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vandam, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shepherd, Barnett</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salmon, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matteo, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4DA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Help Wanted</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Help Wanted</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF VANDAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vandam, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on request for applications for Staten Island historian; at least three local historians have applied for unpaid post with 10-year term--Barnett Shepherd, Patricia Salmon and Tom Matteo; timeline; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE was a co-author of a five-volume history of Staten Island, but he was no ivory-tower academic. He also traipsed around cemeteries throughout his borough and copied, by hand, thousands of inscriptions from tombstones. His name was Charles W. Leng, and he was the first official historian of Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leng, who also had a great interest in entomology -- tending a collection of 200,000 beetles -- died in 1941, but the office he held is vacant, and candidates who think they can fill his and his learned successors' shoes have a May 1 deadline by which to apply for the job. An unpaid post with a 10-year term, the position comes with an office in Borough Hall and is open to Staten Islanders who, in the words of the official request for applications, are ''eager to disseminate knowledge of our borough's rich and fascinating past.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Proud of its sometimes maligned past, Staten Island seeks a scholar in chief.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE was a co-author of a five-volume history of Staten Island, but he was no ivory-tower academic. He also traipsed around cemeteries throughout his borough and copied, by hand, thousands of inscriptions from tombstones. His name was Charles W. Leng, and he was the first official historian of Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leng, who also had a great interest in entomology -- tending a collection of 200,000 beetles -- died in 1941, but the office he held is vacant, and candidates who think they can fill his and his learned successors' shoes have a May 1 deadline by which to apply for the job. An unpaid post with a 10-year term, the position comes with an office in Borough Hall and is open to Staten Islanders who, in the words of the official request for applications, are ''eager to disseminate knowledge of our borough's rich and fascinating past.''</p>
        <p>At least three local historians have applied, bearing experience and published works -- perhaps continuing Mr. Leng's tradition, one applicant is an expert on cemeteries in the borough -- as well as enthusiastic notes of support from fellow Staten Islanders.</p>
        <p>''Several people, when they read the notice in the paper, they called me up and said, 'Well, aren't you doing it?' '' said Barnett Shepherd, an expert on local architecture and currently the historian for the Snug Harbor Cultural Center.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shepherd is in the running, as are Patricia Salmon, curator of history for the borough's Institute of Arts and Sciences, and Tom Matteo, an associate professor of business administration at St. Peter's College in Jersey City. As to whether other hats have been tossed in the ring, the office of Borough President James Molinaro declined to comment, a spokesman said, until ''after we have reviewed the applications.'' In the opinion of many borough residents, non-islanders are indifferent to Staten Island's heritage. ''We don't get a lot of love over there,'' Andre Cofield, a student at Ralph McKee High School in the St. George neighborhood, said one recent afternoon as he waited for the ferry at Whitehall in Manhattan. In school, Andre has studied Sandy Ground, the island's historic settlement for free blacks, but he couldn't imagine that people outside Staten Island have even heard of it.</p>
        <p>The problem, local residents say, is that outsiders' talk about the island is mostly limited to snide comments about the now-closed Fresh Kills landfill. When Staten Island was considering seceding from the city in the early 1990s, said Howard Weiner, chairman of the history department at the College of Staten Island, ''there were people in other boroughs who kind of shrugged and said, 'What kind of difference could it possibly make?' ''</p>
        <p>Yet scholarship among islanders themselves is widespread. Just this week, for example, NYU Press is publishing ''That Ever Loyal Island: Staten Island and the American Revolution,'' by Phillip Papas, a South Shore resident and an associate professor of history at Union County College in Cranford, N.J.</p>
        <p>''I always say if there are Ph.D. grad students out there who need a dissertation topic, this place is it,'' said Dr. Papas, whose book was prompted by what he saw as historians' neglect of the intense Loyalist sentiment on the island during the Revolution.</p>
        <p>Foremost among the group of contemporary Staten Island historians like Dr. Papas was Richard Dickenson, the most recent borough historian, who died last year and who had a deep interest in local African-American history. His predecessor, Loring McMillen, who held the position from 1934 until 1991, is remembered as the founder of Historic Richmondtown, an inaugural member of the city Landmarks Preservation Commission and the person who preserved the portfolio of the renowned local photographer Alice Austen.</p>
        <p>Apathy toward history greatly annoyed Mr. McMillen. ''How can anybody live in a neighborhood and not know what's been there before?'' he asked in 1988. Other borough history buffs seem to agree that few topics are undeserving of treatment, so much so that The Staten Island Historian, a magazine published from 1938 to 2002, included articles with titles like ''Casement Window Parts, 1660-1760'' and ''Creative Use of Serpentine Rock on Staten Island.''</p>
        <p>APPLICANTS for the historian's job tend to tackle somewhat broader subjects. Ms. Salmon has written a book about Staten Island graveyards and counts the island's natural history and the ferry among her research interests. Dr. Matteo has written a collection of quirky borough facts with the working title ''Staten Island: I Didn't Know That.'' The book, which is being issued by Donning Company Publishers and which Dr. Matteo hopes will be available by Christmas, includes tidbits like the fact that Paul Newman lived in St. George when he was a struggling young actor.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Shepherd, whose interests are broad, identifies as one of his favorite moments in island history the little-known destruction in 1858 of a Tompkinsville hospital, where immigrants with yellow fever and other illnesses were quarantined before being allowed elsewhere in the country. The fire was set by neighbors after repeated attempts to get the hospital moved. In Mr. Shepherd's opinion, the event is an enduring symbol of Staten Islanders' attempts to control their own fate.</p>
        <p>''While I don't advocate violence,'' he said, ''I think it is an exciting development.''</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
