<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Have Backpack, Will Travel (as Dora)</title>
    <meta content="29peopleliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29peopleli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ENTERTAINER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mendez, Melanie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Go, Diego, Go Live] (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EEDF153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Have Backpack, Will Travel (as Dora)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Have Backpack, Will Travel (as Dora)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Melanie Mendez, 21, of Ronkonkoma, NY, who stars as Dora the Explorer in national tour of Go, Diego, Go Live] The Great Jaguar Rescue; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SWINGING from a vine, Melanie Mendez made a grand entrance onstage at Radio City Music Hall. ''Hola,'' she called out to the uproarious cheers of hundreds of children greeting her appearance as Dora the Explorer, the feisty bilingual cartoon character in ''Go, Diego, Go Live! The Great Jaguar Rescue.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mendez, 21, a former cheerleader from Ronkonkoma, jumped into a pretend raft, grabbed a paddle and went singing down the Silly River. Dora was helping her cousin Diego, played by Richie Portela, retrieve Baby Jaguar's growl from the magic bottle so the animal carnival could start.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>SWINGING from a vine, Melanie Mendez made a grand entrance onstage at Radio City Music Hall. “Hola,” she called out to the uproarious cheers of hundreds of children greeting her appearance as Dora the Explorer, the feisty bilingual cartoon character in “Go, Diego, Go Live! The Great Jaguar Rescue.”.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SWINGING from a vine, Melanie Mendez made a grand entrance onstage at Radio City Music Hall. ''Hola,'' she called out to the uproarious cheers of hundreds of children greeting her appearance as Dora the Explorer, the feisty bilingual cartoon character in ''Go, Diego, Go Live! The Great Jaguar Rescue.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mendez, 21, a former cheerleader from Ronkonkoma, jumped into a pretend raft, grabbed a paddle and went singing down the Silly River. Dora was helping her cousin Diego, played by Richie Portela, retrieve Baby Jaguar's growl from the magic bottle so the animal carnival could start.</p>
        <p>This was the second time Ms. Mendez was playing Dora onstage; she first tried out for the part last summer, seeking some auditioning experience before entering her senior year as a musical theater major at Five Towns College in Dix Hills.</p>
        <p>To her surprise, she landed the understudy role for four characters, including Dora, in a four-month United Kingdom ''Dora the Explorer Live!'' tour, a spinoff of the popular interactive television series for preschoolers. Senior year was postponed indefinitely.</p>
        <p>''That was a challenging first job,'' said Ms. Mendez, who at least once a week got to play the role of the spirited, inquisitive 7-year-old adventurer who never leaves home without her backpack or map. ''I kind of got thrown to the wolves.''</p>
        <p>In January she began playing Dora, essentially a cameo, in the national tour of the Diego show, which will travel to about 50 venues this year.</p>
        <p>''It's been kind of surreal,'' Ms. Mendez said. ''I didn't necessarily know I was going to get a job.''</p>
        <p>Like Dora, Ms. Mendez is proud of her Hispanic heritage and said she was inspired by actresses like Salma Hayek, Penélope Cruz and Jennifer Lopez.</p>
        <p>''There are not too many roles for Hispanic women, especially young, so it is really amazing,'' said Ms. Mendez, whose parents, Victor and Maria Mendez, were born in Puerto Rico. Though Ms. Mendez is not fluent in Spanish, the show incorporates Spanish words and phrases, and the actors frequently ask the children to respond in Spanish.</p>
        <p>Dora was a perfect fit, Ms. Mendez said, because she shares the character's boundless energy. To play the wide-eyed explorer, she tucks her long dark hair into a pageboy wig. Like the Dora dolls being sold in the Radio City lobby, she wears a bright pink shirt, orange shorts and yellow socks topped with petals, with a lavender knapsack on her back.</p>
        <p>In college, Ms. Mendez said, she was able to land roles that she doubted she would ever play professionally, like Lois in ''Kiss Me Kate'' and the baker's wife in ''Into the Woods.''</p>
        <p>''Once you start hitting the real stage they generally will not cast you in something that doesn't fit,'' she said. ''I have a very ethnic look.''</p>
        <p>Her ''absolute dream role,'' she said, would be Elphaba, the Wicked Witch of the West, in the Broadway show ''Wicked.''</p>
        <p>At Connetquot High School (class of 2003), Ms. Mendez was captain of the junior varsity cheerleading squad.</p>
        <p>''That helped me with not having stage fright,'' she said. In her senior year she dropped cheerleading to pursue drama and landed a lead role as Laurey in the school's production of ''Oklahoma!''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mendez said her classical training as a mezzo-soprano helps her belt out tunes.</p>
        <p>''I have always loved singing,'' she said. ''I didn't necessarily know that I could make a career out of it.''</p>
        <p>She has not yet had much time to enjoy her success, Ms. Mendez said; ''Go, Diego, Go'' repeats two and sometimes three times a day.</p>
        <p>Then again, she is hardly a celebrity. After all, the audience is mainly 2- to 6-year-olds.</p>
        <p>''They don't know who Melanie is,'' Ms. Mendez said. ''They know Dora.''</p>
        <p>ENTERTAINER E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
