<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Basements Full of Memories, Adrift in the Storm</title>
    <meta content="29colweWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29colwe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mamaroneck (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berger, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basements and Cellars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basements and Cellars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0DB153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Basements Full of Memories, Adrift in the Storm</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Basements Full of Memories, Adrift in the Storm</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE BERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berger, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>MAMARONECK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joe Berger column on scene in Mamaroneck, NY, after flooding from northeaster forced homeowners to rid their basements of muddy stuff they had been saving; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUBURBAN basements are repositories of ambivalence.</p>
        <p>There's that frayed armchair you were about to throw out, but no, maybe your daughter will need it after she moves out. And those file boxes of term papers -- remnants of that hopeful being you were decades ago. Maybe someday you'll need them to seem knowledgeable at the book club. Those drums that filled the house with a clattering and pounding that drove the family crazy? In your empty nest, what you wouldn't give to have your children bang them to their hearts' content. Store them, too, in the basement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suburban basements are repositories of memories, as recent flooding has shown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUBURBAN basements are repositories of ambivalence.</p>
        <p>There's that frayed armchair you were about to throw out, but no, maybe your daughter will need it after she moves out. And those file boxes of term papers -- remnants of that hopeful being you were decades ago. Maybe someday you'll need them to seem knowledgeable at the book club. Those drums that filled the house with a clattering and pounding that drove the family crazy? In your empty nest, what you wouldn't give to have your children bang them to their hearts' content. Store them, too, in the basement.</p>
        <p>But all that hemming and hawing comes to the surface -- quite literally -- when there's a once-in-a-decade event like the northeaster two weeks ago that turned basements in the working-class Washingtonville neighborhood of Mamaroneck into sewage tanks and gave residents a small taste of what New Orleans must have been like circa Katrina. Arrayed on sidewalks over the following days for all to see were the ratty armchair, the file boxes, the drums, and so much mucky more, waiting for the garbage guys to decisively dispose of them forever.</p>
        <p>Two days after the storm, Bob Comblo, a 50-year-old contractor, was pumping out the basement of the small apartment house on Hillside Avenue where he lives and does the superintending and where three feet of water had collected. As his pump roared, Mr. Comblo talked about the motorized Jeeps that his son, Bobbie, 13, had relished driving until he was 5 and that Mr. Comblo was saving for his grandchild, Tatiana.</p>
        <p>''They cost me $550 apiece -- they were brand new,'' he said. ''Now I have to throw them out.''</p>
        <p>Floods can be a great leveler, inundating basements in million-dollar homes in the Orienta section as well as Washingtonville, but the repairs put more of a dent in the bank accounts of the 10 tenants in Mr. Comblo's building. ''Elderly people, middle class, working class -- we're not rich,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Basements are also repositories of memories -- underground museums of a sort. Mary Lou Greco, who lives on Center Avenue, held on to the mirror in which her three daughters successively gazed at themselves as they blossomed into women. There it was on the sidewalk, its glass coated with a film of mud, huddled near the now-grimy Christmas lights and Halloween masks that brought the block so many seasons of cheer. Mrs. Greco did salvage a muddied photograph of a grandson, Anthony, when he was 2 -- he is now 15 -- the frame adorned with the words ''I love my Grandma.''</p>
        <p>George Belsito, 55, a water department worker, was standing in rubber boots and hosing down what looked like a lake of white paint outside his Hillside Avenue home. He rescued what he could, but the overflow from the usually bashful Mamaroneck River was too swift.</p>
        <p>''The water surrounded the house like a peninsula,'' Mr. Belsito said. ''I was a peninsula.''</p>
        <p>Four feet of water ruined his washing machine, tools, old fishing rods and treadmill. ''I'm chubby, but I still work out,'' he said, chuckling. Bunched along with those throwaways on the sidewalk were his 33-r.p.m. vinyl discs (once known as records), which brought to mind Mr. Belsito as a young man in the 1970s dancing the night away to Gladys Knight and the Pips.</p>
        <p>Those objects can all be replaced.</p>
        <p>''The hard part was losing all the stuff from my children -- the tapes of the communion, the children playing in the park,'' he said. ''Everything is gone.''</p>
        <p>Christine is now 28, and Stephanie is 24, but the delightful evidence that they had once been capering girls was on those tapes.</p>
        <p>Of course, some basements are museums in waiting -- the children are still playing with all those Barbie dolls and plastic stoves that will inevitably wind up in cartons. That's why seeing Estella Mendoza standing outside the tall gray clapboard on Madison Street that she bought in November, surrounded by black plastic bags of toys, was so disheartening.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mendoza emigrated from Mexico 15 years ago and works as a housekeeper at a Rye country club (where her husband, Luis, does maintenance). The house had been an immigrant's dream, and she and Luis had just refinished the basement into a playroom for Evelyn 7, and Luis Alexis, 5. Now she was throwing out new Barbies, a toy laptop and miniature kitchen appliances. They were soaked with mud and worse, as were the playroom's leather couch, dresser and VCR.</p>
        <p>Her neighbor Luis Torres, a truck driver, also lost his basement, which he had adapted for his mother-in-law. Her double bed, television and microwave were deluged. Searching the dank, darkened basement with a flashlight, Mr. Torres cheerfully said he could replace the furnishings. What he can't replace is the videotaped chronicle of his daughter, Maggie, soon after she was born. Maggie is now 13.</p>
        <p>''That is something you never have back again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>E-mail: joeberg@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: joeberg@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
