<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Congressman's Rise, Twice-Told Tales and a Fabled Gateway</title>
    <meta content="29read" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/thecity/29read.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: READING NEW YORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rangel, Charles B (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wynter, Leon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jonnes, Jill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cliff, Nigel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">And I Haven't Had a Bad Day Since (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Conquering Gotham:  A Gilded Age Epic (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Satan's Circus (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Shakespeare Riots, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Harlem (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Congressman's Rise, Twice-Told Tales and a Fabled Gateway</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Congressman’s Rise, Twice-Told Tales and a Fabled Gateway</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sam Roberts reviews several new books about or set in New York City; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHARLES RANGEL is the man who brought you Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton. ''No, no, no!'' she protested each time he urged her to run. ''But in the end,'' she recalled, ''like so many women before me, I just couldn't say no.''</p>
        <p>In his irreverent memoir, ''And I Haven't Had a Bad Day Since: From the Streets of Harlem to the Halls of Congress'' (Thomas Dunne Books, $24.95), written with Leon Wynter, Mr. Rangel engagingly recalls his challenging childhood, his introduction into clubhouse politics and his defeat of the formidable Adam Clayton Powell. He also describes his induction into the Gang of Four, as Manhattan's black Democratic power brokers came to be called in 1985, when the mayoral candidacy of Herman Badillo ''helped open up an unfortunate wound of political distrust between blacks and Hispanics in New York that persists to this day.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his irreverent memoir, Charles Rangel, with the help of Leon Wynter, recalls his challenging childhood and his introduction into clubhouse politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHARLES RANGEL is the man who brought you Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton. ''No, no, no!'' she protested each time he urged her to run. ''But in the end,'' she recalled, ''like so many women before me, I just couldn't say no.''</p>
        <p>In his irreverent memoir, ''And I Haven't Had a Bad Day Since: From the Streets of Harlem to the Halls of Congress'' (Thomas Dunne Books, $24.95), written with Leon Wynter, Mr. Rangel engagingly recalls his challenging childhood, his introduction into clubhouse politics and his defeat of the formidable Adam Clayton Powell. He also describes his induction into the Gang of Four, as Manhattan's black Democratic power brokers came to be called in 1985, when the mayoral candidacy of Herman Badillo ''helped open up an unfortunate wound of political distrust between blacks and Hispanics in New York that persists to this day.''</p>
        <p>The reader gets to eavesdrop on conversations with power brokers like Gov. Nelson Rockefeller. The reader can also weigh Mr. Rangel's assessment that the victory in the 1969 mayoral primary of Mario Procaccino, who memorably declared that his heart was as black as any black man's, signaled a conservative shift that led to the election of Edward Koch and Rudolph Giuliani.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel and Mr. Koch became antagonists, but it was mostly business, not personal. Their conflicts, Mr. Rangel says, were rooted in ''my longstanding feeling that his values would be more comfortable in a Giuliani Republican Party'' and represented ''a modern form of ethnic political theater that, however regrettable, I understood.''</p>
        <p>''I wish I could say the same for Mario Cuomo,'' Mr. Rangel laments. ''I still don't get the meaning of Mario Cuomo and his remarkable, dead-end career.''</p>
        <p>From his Harlem apartment, Mr. Rangel can see his grandfather's brownstone on West 132nd Street and Lenox Avenue, but, in many respects, he has come a long way; this year, he was made chairman of the powerful House Ways and Means Committee. Despite this achievement, his book mostly looks back, barely touching on his unfinished political agenda, which, perhaps, befits a memoir by a man who is almost 77.</p>
        <p>He recalls the response of a former Congressional colleague, Claude Pepper, who was about the same age as Mr. Rangel is now when a broker was urging him to make some long-term investment. To which Mr. Pepper replied: ''Young man, at my age, I don't even buy green bananas.'' Mr. Pepper, by the way, served in Congress until his death -- at nearly 89.</p>
        <p>Until 1910, only one railroad provided direct access to Manhattan: Commodore Vanderbilt's New York Central, which snaked along the Hudson from upstate. All the others dead-ended in New Jersey, where passengers were forced to transfer to ferries to reach the city.</p>
        <p>In ''Conquering Gotham: A Gilded Age Epic: The Construction of Penn Station and Its Tunnels'' (Viking Adult, $27.95), Jill Jonnes, whose works include a book about the South Bronx, offers a readable and human account of how a few visionaries from the Pennsylvania Railroad connected the rest of the country to the nation's greatest port, and how their Philadelphia-centric perspective (they lacked the real estate savvy of New Yorkers) ultimately doomed the world's largest train station.</p>
        <p>At the time it was built, Penn Station was the fourth-largest structure on the planet, after St. Peter's Basilica in Rome, the Tuileries in Paris and the czar's Winter Palace in St. Petersburg. Few other buildings, the novelist Thomas Wolfe wrote, were ''vast enough to hold the sound of time.''</p>
        <p>Time passed. But nearly a century later, some of the same transit politics and debates about the efficacy of rail tunnels and development of Manhattan's West Side echo with remarkable resonance.</p>
        <p>For cynics who wonder why we need another book about Penn Station (Lorraine B. Diehl's was a classic), much less why New York needs another glorious new gateway, which the proposed Moynihan Station in the old James A. Farley Post Office Building still holds the promise of becoming, this object lesson offers a sound answer.</p>
        <p>Speaking of oft-told tales, do we really need another book about the person billed as the only police officer executed for murder?</p>
        <p>The execution of Charles Becker in 1915 has spawned an entire genre of books about Manhattan's tenderloin district, so named, legend says, because a ranking officer who was transferred to the graft-rich area boasted that after years of living off rump steak, ''I will have some tenderloin now.''</p>
        <p>Becker's conviction for the murder of the gambler Herman Rosenthal was recounted by Andy Logan of The New Yorker in 1970 and was retold as recently as last year in Stanley Cohen's ''Execution of Officer Becker.'' Still, it's a tale too delicious not to tell, and retell, if only to recall that once the city had a police commissioner named Rhinelander Waldo.</p>
        <p>In ''Satan's Circus: Murder, Vice, Police Corruption and New York's Trial of the Century'' (Crown, $24.95), Mike Dash, a London-based writer, engagingly follows the story to its conclusion, ending with the judgment of Becker's widow, Helen, who died in 1962 after retiring as assistant principal of a Manhattan elementary school. She insisted that her husband, though not necessarily innocent, was not guilty. ''He was not an angel; he never made a pretense of being one,'' she said. ''He was just an ordinary human being, and that is why I loved him so.''</p>
        <p>''The Shakespeare Riots: Revenge, Drama and Death in Nineteenth-Century America'' (Random House, $26.95) is another twice-told tale, not the first word on the tumultuous events that culminated at the Astor Place Opera House on May 10, 1849, and probably not the last.</p>
        <p>In a compelling version of the events leading up to the riots, the author, Nigel Cliff, dissects how a friendship between two Shakespearean actors -- William Charles Macready, ''an intellectual Englishman,'' and Edwin Forrest, ''the first true American star, a national hero and a paladin of democracy to his working-class fans'' -- devolved into a fierce personal rivalry. He also explores what that rivalry represented to New Yorkers already divided between nativist Anglophobes and a gentry that fancied itself more cerebral.</p>
        <p>Suffice it to say that more people died on the street that night than in Macready's rendition of ''Macbeth.'' ''The victory in Astor Place went to the elite,'' Mr. Cliff writes, ''but it was not a victory for Shakespeare.''</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: READING NEW YORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
