<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: On Language; Taking Wraps Off Taking Raps</title>
    <meta content="29wwln--safire.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/magazine/29wwlnsafire.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="On Language"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EED8173EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: On Language; Taking Wraps Off Taking Raps</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fall Guy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The collocation fall guy has been much in the news lately. Accordingly, a few weeks ago I reported the most common meaning of the slang phrase -- ''scapegoat'' -- but then cast a line into the mainstream of native users of the American language with this fishhook on it: ''What was the original fall? A prizefighter 'taking a fall'? Lucifer's 'fall' from paradise? A lover 'falling for' a mate? In other words, who was the original guy?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taking wraps off taking raps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The collocation fall guy has been much in the news lately. Accordingly, a few weeks ago I reported the most common meaning of the slang phrase -- ''scapegoat'' -- but then cast a line into the mainstream of native users of the American language with this fishhook on it: ''What was the original fall? A prizefighter 'taking a fall'? Lucifer's 'fall' from paradise? A lover 'falling for' a mate? In other words, who was the original guy?''</p>
        <p>First, one point of view from Jeffrey Gross in e-mail land: ''A scapegoat is entirely innocent and used as a proxy for those who are really responsible. A fall guy is somewhat complicit but takes the blame for others.''</p>
        <p>Now to the speculations. From a guy in England: ''A penny for the Guy? Guy Fawkes, perhaps?'' From Randall Speer of Reston, Va.: ''the fall guy was the wrestler or boxer designated to 'take the fall' since 'the fix was in.' '' From Jernej Sekolec in Vienna: ''Derived from the Latin locution for 'falling on the sword,' which in turn started with the Roman tradition that military commanders in the face of a bad defeat were expected to fall on their sword.'' From Brenda Lee (I'm sorry, music fans, not the Hall of Fame singer but a high-school student): ''Adam, whose banishment from the Garden of Eden leads to the postlapsarian (after the Fall) world, although Eve was the one duped.'' (And thanks for the parenthetical definition, Brenda.)</p>
        <p>That's not all. ''Based on Harding's interior secretary, Albert Fall,'' suggests Richard Ware, the only official ''convicted over the Teapot Dome scandal.'' Myles Potters: ''Icarus is the penultimate fall guy. His ill-fated flight and premature plunge to death are tragic.'' (He means quintessential; penultimate means ''next to last.'' Mnemonic: in pronunciation, quintessential is a word with a penultimate stress.) Bob Mastrangelo: ''Fall guy came from the silent era of moviemaking after a stunt man who had to jump off a cliff so that the leading man didn't have to risk his life.'' Relatedly to show biz, a bunch of readers pointed to George Abbott's 1925 musical with that title, the pratfalls of vaudeville comics as well as the early-'80s TV series starring Lee Majors also titled ''The Fall Guy.''</p>
        <p>My favorite is from Vance Garnett of Washington: ''The 1930 Dashiell Hammett story and, later, the 1941 film 'The Maltese Falcon' may well be the earliest usage of the word as we've come to know it. Humphrey Bogart as 'Sam Spade' tells Mary Astor, as the femme fatale, 'You're taking the fall.' ''</p>
        <p>I wonder about that; in the Humpty Dumpty world of falls, to take the fall means ''to accept punishment'' but does not necessarily impute unfairness or corruption to the punishment. ''To take a fall,'' however, is equivalent to take a dive, in which the faller is complicit in the trick, dodge or conspiracy in throwing the fight.</p>
        <p>That's my opinion; that's what it means to me. But here is the beauty part: My slang definition may not be yours. In dealing with Standard English, lexicographers, etymologists, semanticists and usage mavenim can bring hard-earned authority to definitions, giving needed precision to the language, but when it comes to slang, the experts are the nonexperts. Slang swings; its meanings are in the heads of the users, who are legion and gleefully bang their different drums. (We report; you decide.)</p>
        <p>Here's a Republican representative saying of the general only recently in charge of Walter Reed hospital -- who was fired for the years of negligence of outpatients -- that ''I don't know him, but I know he's the fall guy.'' And here's a Democratic senator saying of Scooter Libby, convicted of lying about what turned out to be an unprosecuted noncrime, agreeing with an outspoken juror that the vice president's aide had been made ''a fall guy.'' And in that case, here's how to access the words of a First Amendment expert, putting his recent New York Law Review commentary on his Web site -- www.jamesgoodale.net/jailformiller</p>
        <p>.html -- which makes me wonder whether a former colleague was made the fall guy for all of us who urged the invasion of Iraq. (Can a woman be a fall guy? Yes; guy, in slippery Old Slang, has become unisex.)</p>
        <p>Does slang's malleability of meaning suggest that anything goes, that -- to return to Humpty Dumpty -- that a slang word or phrase means what whoever uses it says it means? No; using etymology, where and when it started -- which helps in defining -- we have evidence to refute speculation and track its meanings down.</p>
        <p>''Dan used to be a strong-arm man himself,'' goes a 1904 citation in the Historical Dictionary of American Slang, ''but . . . has turned fall-guy for a fleet [of pickpockets] that operates along the Bowery.'' An editor over at Merriam-Webster, Tom Pitoniak, says that ''the overall evidence points strongly to such criminal origins, not to boxing or theater. I doubt the early crooks who used this slang had postlapsarian theology in mind.'' Nor Lucifer, Fawkes or the dreamy Brigid O'Shaughnessy, the villain Bogart could fall for. (And Brenda and I know what postlapsarian means.)</p>
        <p>Knowing the source helps in defining standard words, but slang often double-crosses its sources. Thus we have these three senses of fall guy branching out: 1) an innocent scapegoat, whipping boy or patsy, meekly absorbing the blame; 2) a dupe, pushover, sucker easily victimized; 3) a confederate taking the rap for others out of fear or in expectation of reward.</p>
        <p>About that rap: from Standard English ''a sharp blow with a stick,'' it was taken up by slang in to beat the rap, ''to escape punishment''; a bum rap, ''unfair punishment''; and to take the rap -- as the fall guy, in whatever sense you choose.</p>
        <p>On Language</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
