<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Friends of Winston</title>
    <meta content="Meacham.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/books/review/Meacham.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Olson, Lynne</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Churchill, Winston Leonard Spencer</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Troublesome Young Men: The Rebels Who Brought Churchill to Power and Helped Save England (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3D8163EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Friends of Winston</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Friends of Winston</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON MEACHAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meacham, Jon</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TROUBLESOME YOUNG MEN</p>
        <p>The Rebels Who Brought Churchill</p>
        <p>to Power and Helped Save England.</p>
        <p>By Lynne Olson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 436 pp.</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $27.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tracing Churchill’s rise to power, a journalist emphasizes the Tories who helped put him there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TROUBLESOME YOUNG MEN</p>
        <p>The Rebels Who Brought Churchill</p>
        <p>to Power and Helped Save England.</p>
        <p>By Lynne Olson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 436 pp.</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $27.50.</p>
        <p>From Isaiah Berlin's landmark Atlantic Monthly essay ''Mr. Churchill in 1940'' to Albert Finney's Emmy Award-winning turn in HBO's ''Gathering Storm,'' the drama of Winston Churchill and World War II has long been a kind of secular passion play. It was Churchill, the story goes, who stood alone against Nazi Germany in the 1930s, a voice without force until Friday, May 10, 1940, when Hitler's invasion of France and the Low Countries swept the appeasers from power. In his inimitable way, Churchill recalled that in those days he felt as though he ''were walking with Destiny, and that all my past life had been but a preparation for this hour and for this trial.'' He added: ''I was sure I should not fail.''</p>
        <p>His confident view of his own capacities was not widely shared in London or in Washington. Churchill was George VI's second choice (Lord Halifax, foreign secretary, high-church aristocrat and reliable Chamberlainite, had been the first); as one Churchill intimate said, ''Winston was often right, but when he was wrong, well, my God.'' At the White House, Franklin Roosevelt and his circle worried that Churchill was unreliable because he was a drinker. To Sumner Welles, then the under secretary of state and a friend of Roosevelt, Churchill was ''a drunken sot'' and ''a third- or fourth-rate man.''</p>
        <p>Yet it soon became clear, even in real time, that the 10th of May was a hinge of history. It is neither sentimental nor simplistic to say that Churchill's ascension and refusal to surrender as he awaited America's entry into the war (which came 19 months later) is one of the great achievements of this or any age. Things were one way before Churchill became prime minister, and another way afterward. We live in the light of Churchill's pugnacious performance under fire.</p>
        <p>It is also true, however, that the story of appeasement and of Britain's slow path to war in the 1930s is more complicated than the usual narrative suggests -- a narrative constructed in large part by Churchill himself, who, in his war memoirs, provided what the historian J. H. Plumb called ''the broad avenues'' on which we still travel through the war years. Churchill was not alone in his opposition to Hitler during what he called his wilderness years, and therein lies the strength of Lynne Olson's brisk, engaging new book, ''Troublesome Young Men.'' Olson, a former White House correspondent for The Baltimore Sun, has given us a fascinating snapshot of the Tory ''rebels,'' as she calls them, who ultimately opposed Neville Chamberlain and helped elevate the then-unbeatified Churchill.</p>
        <p>Olson's characters shared school ties, country houses, London clubs and, in at least one scandalous instance, a woman who was simultaneously the wife of one and the mistress of another. Their names have little resonance now: Harold Macmillan's is familiar, but those of the others -- Robert Boothby, Leo Amery, Ronald Cartland, Robert Cranborne -- have receded into the shadows. Olson's book should help correct that, for these men were early defenders of freedom in the face of Nazism and English appeasement, often taking stands that put them at odds with men and women they had known all their lives and turned them into political targets. Neville Chamberlain -- so seemingly upright and straitlaced in old photographs -- tapped telephones, conducted surveillance and played dirty tricks on opponents within his own party. He reveled in gathering political intelligence against his foes, who were, he boasted, ''totally unaware of my knowledge of their proceedings. I [have] continual knowledge of their doings and sayings.'' In an important by-election in 1938, the Chamberlain machine smeared an anti-appeasement incumbent by sending fake telegrams saying, ''Greetings from Moscow.'' They were signed ''Stalin.''</p>
        <p>The men being monitored were hardly revolutionaries, but they were dissenters, and Chamberlain tended toward the autocratic as the '30s went by. In the shadow of Churchill's wartime leadership it can be difficult to recall just how ascendant Chamberlain was for so long, and how unlikely it seemed that Churchill, or anyone else, might dislodge him. Many Britons, if not most, viewed appeasement as a diplomatic -- even moral -- triumph. Memories of the carnage of the Great War were too fresh, pacifism was understandably in vogue and Moscow was seen as much more of a threat than either Berlin or Rome. ''I will not have another war,'' George V declared toward the end of his reign. ''I will not.'' The king and other well-born Britons remembered, too, the murder of the Romanovs, while observing the apparent efficiencies of totalitarianism. In 1933 the Prince of Wales, the future Edward VIII, said that ''dictators are very popular these days and we might want one in England before long.''</p>
        <p>Ronald Cartland, among others, disagreed. A bright Tory, Cartland (his sister, Barbara, became the prolific romance novelist) had traveled to Hitler's Germany in 1935, Olson reports, and, ''outraged by the Nazis' persecution of the Jews,'' believed war was inevitable. In August 1939, on the eve of Hitler's invasion of Poland, when Chamberlain's government declined to acknowledge the imminent threat, Cartland stood in the House and spoke truth to power: ''We are in the situation that within a month we may be going to fight -- and we may be going to die.''</p>
        <p>Cartland was right, as were others from different precincts of British politics: Churchill, nearly 65; Anthony Eden, younger and seemingly destined for glory; Leo Amery, a Churchill contemporary who, in a moment of great parliamentary courage on May 7, 1940, stood before Chamberlain and, echoing Cromwell, cried: ''You have sat too long here for any good you have been doing! Depart, I say, and let us have done with you! In the name of God, go!''</p>
        <p>But that was the end of the story, not the beginning or even the middle. The strength of Olson's book is how well she writes of the human element in politics and diplomacy. For Tories like Cartland, deviating from the Chamberlain line was seen as betrayal, not disagreement, and the deviators were subjected to raw schoolboy pressure. When Harold Nicolson spoke out against the government's abandonment of Czechoslovakia after Munich, he was reproached on grounds of clubbiness: ''The actual expression used to me was 'You must not bat against your own side' -- as if it were a game of cricket that was being played in this most revered assembly.'' When Cartland defied Chamberlain, he was told he would soon be ruined.</p>
        <p>But Cartland would not be there to savor Churchill's triumph when it came. He was in France, fighting the German troops Chamberlain and others had said would never strike. Cartland died a soldier's death in 1940, and the news took his colleagues back to the moment almost a year earlier when he had told Chamberlain that ''we may be going to die.'' According to Harold Nicolson: ''We shall forever remember him as he was at that moment. Defiant, faithful, devoted and brave beyond compare.''</p>
        <p>Olson writes well, though she has a weakness for the occasional cliché -- Stanley Baldwin is ''on the ropes''; in a moment of crisis Chamberlain has to come to London to ''put outthe fire.'' This is, however, a small flaw in what is largely a successful book.</p>
        <p>''No government can change men's souls,'' Cartland once said. ''The souls of men change governments.'' This new book reminds us that there are others besides Churchill who deserve our thanks for seeing us through freedom's defining storm, those years when everything was at risk, when everything seemed lost, and yet light triumphed over darkness.</p>
        <p>Jon Meacham, the editor of Newsweek, is the author of ''Franklin and Winston'' and ''American Gospel.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jon Meacham, the editor of Newsweek, is the author of ''Franklin and Winston'' and ''American Gospel.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
