<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Young Shoppers: Slaves to Fashion?</title>
    <meta content="l29west-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fitzgerald, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kravet, Sophie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pray, Bethany</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Phyllis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seymour, Lesley Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Young Shoppers: Slaves to Fashion?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Liz Fitzgerald, Sophie Kravet, Bethany Pray and Phyllis Schneider letters on Lesley Jane Seymour's April 22 article on trip to mall with pre-teen girls</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I was intrigued by ''Tweens 'R' Shoppers,'' by Lesley Jane Seymour (April 22).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I was intrigued by ''Tweens 'R' Shoppers,'' by Lesley Jane Seymour (April 22).</p>
        <p>However, I was unsettled by the timing and prominence of this article about under-age shopping when so many of our sound shore families were decimated by the recent natural disaster.</p>
        <p>Unprecedented flooding wiped out whole neighborhoods, leaving hundreds of families without the most basic necessities, including clothes.</p>
        <p>Perhaps some of our savvy tween shoppers will be inspired to go through their closets and donate some of last season's Abercrombies to flood victims. Or, since shopping is a favorite pastime, we can encourage our children to buy something new (socks, underwear and baby clothes are a particular need) for our neighbors in need.</p>
        <p>Liz Fitzgerald  Larchmont</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I am an eighth-grade student at the Hommocks Middle School in Larchmont. I read the article ''Tweens 'R' Shoppers.''</p>
        <p>I felt that the girls who were portrayed in the article were made to seem very materialistic and shallow. I just hope that your readers don't generalize and assume that most of the Hommocks students are so ''shopping crazed.''</p>
        <p>There are many of us who focus on music or sports or community service, and not just shopping in very exclusive stores. I'm sure the three girls in the article have other interests that could have been focused on.</p>
        <p>Sophie Kravet  Larchmont</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Tweens 'R' Shoppers'' lacked any skepticism about the ideas that these children are in control of their choices, that ''it's important for them to feel like they're part of a larger club'' represented by Abercrombie &amp; Fitch, that they are ''incredibly sophisticated'' and ''thoughtful.''</p>
        <p>These ''choices'' are illusory. It takes no thoughtfulness to join the Abercrombie club; it takes merely the desire to conform, plenty of income and parents who are willing to ignore the negative messages of these products (the premium placed on skinniness, overt sexiness, money, and in Abercrombie's case a preference for hiring whites that led to a class action lawsuit and $40 million settlement) and capitulate to the goals of big companies with mammoth bankrolls.</p>
        <p>Bethany Pray  Hastings-on-Hudson</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>How sad that a sociology professor, Sharon Zukin, validates tween super-shoppers with her statement that ''you have to buy things today. In a way, learning how to shop is crucial today for how to survive.'' The article goes on to say that mother-daughter shopping can be a bonding experience.</p>
        <p>If parents want to bond with their kids, why not spend a day together serving meals at a homeless shelter? Or volunteering at some other charity? Or cleaning out closets and donating all those slightly worn clothes to people who actually need them?</p>
        <p>As for teaching kids how to shop, give them a pair of scissors and a batch of coupons. Teach them the value of saving a dollar rather than spending mindlessly. And then write about those kids in the Westchester section of The Times!</p>
        <p>Phyllis Schneider  Yonkers</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
