<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For This Stewart, It's a Wonderful Race</title>
    <meta content="29cheer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/othersports/29cheer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHEERING SECTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Personal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DF133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For This Stewart, It's a Wonderful Race</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For This Stewart, It’s a Wonderful Race</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallozzi, Vincent M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bowling has the Earl Anthony Classic and the Dick Weber Open, named for two of the game's greats. Golf has the Bob Hope Classic, named for the entertainer, and this weekend's Byron Nelson Championship, named for a legend of the links.</p>
        <p>Next Saturday, auto racing fans will have an opportunity to watch the Jim Stewart 400, named for a man who knows that no one has ever heard of him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last October, Jim Stewart was among the 15,000 people who entered a contest to win the naming rights to the Nascar Nextel Cup Series race. The Jim Stewart 400 will take place Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bowling has the Earl Anthony Classic and the Dick Weber Open, named for two of the game's greats. Golf has the Bob Hope Classic, named for the entertainer, and this weekend's Byron Nelson Championship, named for a legend of the links.</p>
        <p>Next Saturday, auto racing fans will have an opportunity to watch the Jim Stewart 400, named for a man who knows that no one has ever heard of him.</p>
        <p>''People are probably asking themselves, 'Jim who?' '' said Stewart, 34, who lives in Houma, La. ''I'd be asking myself the same question.''</p>
        <p>Last October, Stewart was among the 15,000 people who entered a contest to win the naming rights to the Nascar Nextel Cup Series race at Richmond International Raceway on Saturday.</p>
        <p>The contest, sponsored by Crown Royal, required a written or video submission of a memorable occasion worth toasting. Stewart won for a video in which he reminisced about fishing with his father, James, who has been slowed in recent years by diabetes and other health problems.</p>
        <p>''I dedicated it to my dad,'' said Stewart, who took over his father's pipeline construction business three years ago after his parents, James and Dianne, retired to Hazlehurst, Miss. ''When I was young, my dad always took the time to take me fishing. No matter what kind of day he had at work, he took me out on that 30-foot Grady-White, and we went fishing, sometimes overnight, on the lakes around Mississippi, for speckled trout and tuna, wahoo and lemon fish. Those were great days.''</p>
        <p>Stewart and the eight other finalists each received an expenses-paid trip to the Daytona 500 this year, with infield access and a prerace tour of the garage.</p>
        <p>''I never thought I'd get to Daytona,'' he said. ''That would have been enough for me right there.''</p>
        <p>By winning the top prize, Stewart is part of Saturday's race, which will officially be known as Crown Royal Presents the Jim Stewart 400. His name will be printed on tickets and related merchandise and in newspapers and television guides. He will wave the green flag and present the check to the winner.</p>
        <p>Stewart said he hoped that his favorite drivers, Mark Martin and Tony Stewart (no relation), would slow down long enough to say hello.</p>
        <p>''I've had a little time for this to sink in, but it's still overwhelming,'' Stewart said. ''To a racing fan like myself, this is mind-boggling. It's like winning the lottery.''</p>
        <p>Stewart said that his parents; his fiancée, Lacie Broussard; his son Hunter; and 25 others would accompany him to the race.</p>
        <p>''My wife and I both think this is fantastic for Jim,'' James Stewart, 59, said. ''You never know when you raise your children how things will turn out, but it's nice to know that those days we spent fishing are as special a memory to Jim as they are to me, and that he enjoyed it every bit as much as I did.''</p>
        <p>When Nascar lifted its ban on advertising for hard liquor in 2005, Crown Royal sponsored the reigning Nextel Cup champion Kurt Busch. Busch was cited for reckless driving in November that year and was suspended from the Roush Racing team. Crown Royal now sponsors Jamie McMurray, who spun a wheel to choose the winner among the contest finalists two days before the Daytona 500.</p>
        <p>McMurray described Stewart as being ''awfully excited about winning.''</p>
        <p>''To have a major sporting event named after a fan has never been done before, so how could you not get excited?'' McMurray said. ''I think this idea is really cool and really different, a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity for our fans, who are extremely loyal to their drivers. As for Jim, he'll probably be talking about this for the rest of his life.''</p>
        <p>Stewart said that when his dream came to an end, he would go back to work and spend as much quality time as he could on the lakes around Mississippi with his father and his sons, including 22-month-old Logan.</p>
        <p>''It's a nice family tradition,'' he said. ''Who knows? Maybe one day my sons will tell a story about the good times they had fishing with their dad, and their granddad, and maybe they'll get a race named after them.''</p>
        <p>CHEERING SECTION E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
