<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Should Immigration Be a Police Issue?</title>
    <meta content="29MORRISRnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Day Laborers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Morristown (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cresitello, Donald (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fahim, Kareem</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0D8153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Should Immigration Be a Police Issue?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREEM FAHIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fahim, Kareem</byline>
      <dateline>MORRISTOWN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article, in light of small but growing federal program that trains local police officers to enforce federal immigration laws, explores issues about role of police in immigration matters; focuses on Morristown, NJ, where residents protested plan by Mayor Donald Cresitello, and other places in New York metropolitan area where authorities are trying to control undocumented immigrants and enforce federal immigration policy; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE rumors have thinned the morning lines of immigrant men who gather on Morris Street, looking for work. The news -- that the local police might have a hand enforcing federal immigration policy -- has spread throughout this historic, diverse town on the edge of New Jersey's horse country, and a few people have even started to move away.</p>
        <p>It started in early March with Mayor Donald Cresitello's proposal to enroll the police in a small but growing federal program -- now in place in 10 states -- that trains local officers to help enforce federal immigration laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE rumors have thinned the morning lines of immigrant men who gather on Morris Street, looking for work. The news -- that the local police might have a hand enforcing federal immigration policy -- has spread throughout this historic, diverse town on the edge of New Jersey's horse country, and a few people have even started to move away.</p>
        <p>It started in early March with Mayor Donald Cresitello's proposal to enroll the police in a small but growing federal program -- now in place in 10 states -- that trains local officers to help enforce federal immigration laws.</p>
        <p>A grandson of Italian immigrants, Mayor Cresitello said he had the support of most of the town's 18,000 residents, nearly a third of whom are Hispanic. An estimated 1,500 undocumented immigrants live here, the mayor said, adding that police officers, with the training, could break up the overcrowded houses where many day laborers live and could stop contractors who hire them from coming to Morristown.</p>
        <p>But his approach has ignited protests and raised old questions about the role of police departments in immigration matters, a thorny part of the rancorous national debate.</p>
        <p>In Suffolk County, the number of undocumented immigrants referred to federal authorities has surged, from 44 people in 2004, when the county executive, Steve Levy, took office, to 2,289 last year, Mr. Levy said. Police officers ask those they arrest about their immigration status and refer undocumented individuals to federal authorities.</p>
        <p>''Many local governments take the point of view that they don't want to ask that question,'' Mr. Levy said. ''I think it's ridiculous for localities to call themselves sanctuaries.'' He called the notion that some people would stop cooperating with the police ''silly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said the federal government had promised to station immigration officers in two county jails, in Yaphank and Riverhead, to process undocumented criminals. And a recent local law will force businesses with county contracts to verify the status of all employees.</p>
        <p>LAST week in Westchester, County Executive Andrew J. Spano called a press conference asking for more federal resources to speed up deportation proceedings against an estimated 700 undocumented immigrants who are on probation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano said it costs the county about $2 million to $3 million a year to manage these probationers, who represent about 10 percent of the 7,000 people on probation. Of the 700 convictions, about 459 were for misdemeanors, officials said.</p>
        <p>Beyond the cost, Mr. Spano said public safety was at risk. ''Having these individuals in our communities is a serious and ongoing threat to the safety of our residents,'' he said. ''Many of these people are serious, violent offenders, and I want them out of our communities and in federal detention centers now.''</p>
        <p>In the early 1900s, the growth in immigration was linked to an increase in crime rates. While recent polls have shown that there is a perception that the influx of illegal immigrants starting in the 1990s has driven up crime rates, several recent studies show that is not the case and, in fact, some sociologists believe the concentration of immigrants has kept the overall crime rate down in some communities.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ruben Rumbaut, a professor at the University of California at Irvine, who has studied incarceration rates of immigrants, said it was impossible to measure crime rates of immigrants directly, especially illegal immigrants. ''The statistics aren't collected that way,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Rumbaut said incarceration rates of immigrants versus native-born people seemed to indicate that immigrants get in much less trouble with the law. Comparing native and foreign-born men between the ages of 18 and 39, he said, shows that 3.5 percent of native-born men were in jail in 2000, compared with fewer than 1 percent of foreign-born men.</p>
        <p>''People come here to work and stay the heck out of trouble, away from the gaze of authorities,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In Morristown, the police chief, Peter Demnitz, has taken issue with the mayor's plan, saying, among other things, that he was worried that aligning officers with federal authorities might hurt cooperation between the police and parts of the community.</p>
        <p>After those comments, Mr. Cresitello ordered Mr. Demnitz to stop speaking with reporters. ''He doesn't have the scientific precepts to confirm that,'' Mr. Cresitello said.</p>
        <p>Such a clash is not unique. ''Communities across the country are debating what role, if any, their police should play in immigration policy,'' said Michael Wishnie, a professor at Yale Law School who has represented organizations lobbying for the rights of undocumented immigrants. In many cases, he said, ''the elected official asserts some kind of connection between crime and immigrants, and law enforcement folks are saying, 'We have our hands full.' '' Or in other cases, they say the community will lose trust in the police.</p>
        <p>Gene Voegtlin, legislative counsel of the International Association of Chiefs of Police, said more and more local police departments were considering the federal program, in part because it offers training in the complex field of immigration law; others are more skeptical. ''There are those who feel it's the proper role,'' he said, ''and those who think it has a chilling effect on immigrant communities in these towns.''</p>
        <p>In interviews, a handful of police officials talked about the fluid line between their duties and those of federal authorities, separate roles that blur or sharpen because of shifting politics and demographics. Local authorities are permitted but not required to check the immigration status of people they arrest, a process that starts with asking for identification, followed by sending a text message to a center run by Immigration and Customs Enforcement.</p>
        <p>The next step -- detaining a person for illegal presence in the United States -- now requires the participation of federal agents, and it is usually a civil violation, not a criminal one. There are fewer than 6,000 federal immigration agents, so advocates of giving local authorities limited immigration powers describe such partnerships as ''force multipliers.''</p>
        <p>Cities and towns, along with their police departments, have come up with varied ways of dealing with issues that arise with an influx of immigrants.</p>
        <p>Some have taken a harder line. In Danbury, Conn., a raid in January by federal officers drew charges that local police officers had been involved. By contrast, places like Hightstown and New Haven have sought to reassure immigrants -- documented or not -- that cooperating with local authorities is safe and federal officers will not be alerted. In 2003, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg of New York signed an executive order that promised that no immigrant would be arrested for immigration status alone.</p>
        <p>In Westchester, Rocco A. Pozzi, commissioner of probation and corrections, said that about 75 inmates out of the 1,550 now being held in the county jail are undocumented immigrants. He said the county was focusing on those 700 undocumented immigrants on probation whose cases have been reported to federal immigration officials, as part of the presentencing process.</p>
        <p>''This is not an issue to be confused about complaints around day laborers,'' Mr. Pozzi said. ''We are focusing on the people who are not only committing crimes but who have been convicted of crimes.''</p>
        <p>In Morristown, Mr. Cresitello said his thinking was animated by the violent killing of a 10-year-old boy, Walter Contreras Valenzuela, whose beaten body was found by the Whippany River in May 2001. A few weeks later, an undocumented 36-year-old Honduran immigrant, Porfirio Jimenez, was charged with his murder.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jimenez, who is still awaiting trial after various procedural delays, had been arrested by the Morristown police at least three times before Walter was killed, on charges including robbery and threatening a man with a knife.</p>
        <p>After the death of Walter, the son of Guatemalan immigrants, a candlelight vigil seemed to unify a town where the Hispanic population started growing in the 1980s. Now Spanish is spoken by more than a quarter of the town's residents. Hispanic businesses line Speedwell Avenue, which leads to the Morristown Green, site of one of George Washington's winter encampments and now a commercial center.</p>
        <p>Donations were made to the library in Walter's name, and the police hired more Hispanics. Mr. Cresitello's predecessor also hired an adviser for Hispanic affairs.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, there was another sort of candlelight vigil. As the Town Council discussed the mayor's proposal, immigrants and their supporters gathered in protest on the steps outside town hall, saying the measure had sent fear throughout the Hispanic community.</p>
        <p>Inside, during a comment period, an eighth grader named Roel Flores-Pettiford walked slowly to a microphone and read a statement.</p>
        <p>''I was motivated to address you after hearing the concerns of my schoolmates, who are now afraid of cops,'' she began, and presented a petition signed by about 20 of her classmates. The mayor's plan, the petition said, ''targets the Latino community of Morristown and instills fear in the children of this community.''</p>
        <p>Asked later about Roel's speech, Mr. Cresitello said, ''I admire her passion.''</p>
        <p>THE program the mayor wants to join is known as 287(g), for a section of the 1996 Immigration and Nationality Act that allows local officers, after being trained, to ''identify, process, and when appropriate, detain immigration offenders they encounter during their regular, daily law-enforcement activity.''</p>
        <p>Seventeen law enforcement agencies have joined the program, and about 40 applications are pending. Field officers receive five weeks of training with immigration agents, including how to tap into immigration databases and process aliens for deportation proceedings.</p>
        <p>Some agencies have settled on a narrow focus. The Florida Department of Law Enforcement, which has trained 62 officers, limited their scope to ''immigration issues with a domestic security nexus,'' said Mark Zadra, an assistant commissioner with the agency.</p>
        <p>The department was one of the first to join the program, largely because so many Sept. 11 hijackers had passed through the state. Local officers participate in raids when they involve critical infrastructure, like airports, water treatment facilities and cargo ports. But Mr. Zadra said they do not look for undocumented workers in other places. ''If you're out picking tomatoes, we are not going to use our 287(g) authority to do a sweep of the fields,'' Mr. Zadra said.</p>
        <p>But Don Hunter, the sheriff of Collier County, in southwest Florida, plans to apply on behalf of the county for a separate agreement with the immigration authorities. Sheriff Hunter blamed illegal immigration for many local crime problems, especially gang-related violence. Immigrant communities, including Haitians and Mexicans, already have strained relations with the police, he said, adding that he was not worried that closer cooperation between his officers and immigration agents would make things worse.</p>
        <p>''I haven't had that experience of people not coming forward in the most heinous crimes, serious rapes, or a murder,'' he said. ''Our experience has been the reverse.''</p>
        <p>Officials from the Immigration and Customs Enforcement, or I.C.E., said this new program has helped extend its reach. ''There is tremendous oversight in this program,'' said Marcy Forman, who heads investigations for I.C.E., adding that the agency would rescind agreements with any law enforcement agency that did not manage the program properly.</p>
        <p>In New Haven, the police chief, Francisco Ortiz, said: ''I don't want officers on fishing expeditions. I want every citizen to be engaged.'' The town adopted a policy of not asking about immigration status, unless officers are investigating crimes.</p>
        <p>''I have two undocumented individuals who are murder victims,'' Chief Ortiz said. ''You need people to tell you about the lives of the victims.'' If his officers were also charged with enforcing immigration policy -- no matter how small the role -- witnesses would say, ''You're on your own,'' the chief said.</p>
        <p>In many places, a reckoning on the role of the local police has centered on day laborers. Last November, a federal judge ruled against officials in Mamaroneck, N.Y., who had used checkpoints and ticketing to clear the town of day laborers. In Freehold, borough officials settled a three-year-old lawsuit by agreeing to stop fining laborers for seeking work in public.</p>
        <p>The mayor of Edison has been forced to navigate the tricky space between residents and authorities. Last year, during a protest by the town's large South Asian community against alleged police misconduct, federal authorities arrested an Indian man who had argued with an Edison police officer. The man, Rajnikant Parikh, was deported last month. There have also been federal raids on illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>Those raids ''present challenges,'' Mayor Jun H. Choi said. He added, ''The focus for us as a local government is protecting our residents, and making sure there is greater trust, regardless of their background.''</p>
        <p>MR. CRESITELLO, in a series of interviews, stressed that Morristown was still early in the application process. (Federal officials say they have yet to receive its application.) But in any agreement, he would ask the federal government ''to include language for people harboring illegals,'' as a way to deal with the problem of immigrants living in cramped housing. ''My position is that federal law defines those things as crimes.''</p>
        <p>He said the sight of day laborers in front of the train station was disturbing to the community, but added that nothing would happen to them ''unless they were arrested in commission of a crime.'' He added that he hoped contractors who hire undocumented workers would stop coming.</p>
        <p>To the police chief's concern that immigrants would stop cooperating with local law enforcement -- as they were asked to do after the young boy was killed in 2001 -- Mr. Cresitello said: ''We can force them to cooperate. They would be witnesses, not cooperating witnesses.''</p>
        <p>Michael Fabrizio, executive director of the Morristown Partnership, a business improvement group, said that for the most part the business community supported the mayor's proposal, though there had been complaints. ''He's not anti-immigrant,'' Mr. Fabrizio said of the mayor. ''Without the immigrant community, we'd have no restaurants in Morristown. Isn't there a way for them to come in legally?''</p>
        <p>A councilman who supported the mayor's proposal, Dick Tighe, said: ''We're not going to be having jackbooted troopers out searching for illegal immigrants. We're not going to be arresting jaywalkers.''</p>
        <p>Among those protesting the Morristown proposal on a recent Tuesday was Erick Carreto, 26, a day laborer who used to wait in front of the train station. He later worked as a busboy, learned English and now works for a nonprofit group that provides services to the laborers.</p>
        <p>He declined to talk in detail about his status, but said he was in the middle of the long process of ''sorting it out.'' Mr. Carreto said he left Guatemala as a teenager to seek work and is now able to send money back to his mother.</p>
        <p>The mayor's proposal has made him fear random checks by the police, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cresitello said, ''I don't agree that anyone should be fearful.'' The mayor has argued in recent weeks with church leaders, after he said they were doing nothing to ease the hardships faced by immigrants. He also rejected a clergy proposal to build a center for the day laborers. Misinformation about his proposal, he said, has led to unnecessary hysteria in Morristown.</p>
        <p>''They don't have anything to fear,'' he said. ''Unless they have something to fear.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
