<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>French Candidate Holds a Curious Debate</title>
    <meta content="29france" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/world/europe/29france.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bayrou, Francois</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarkozy, Nicolas (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Royal, Segolene</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Royal, Segolene</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bayrou, Francois</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>French Candidate Holds a Curious Debate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">French Candidate Holds a Curious Debate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>French Socialist presidential candidate Segolene Royal stages 100-minute debate with former centrist candidate Francois Bayrou in effort to capture sizable percentage of his voters; Bayrou insists he will not embrace either Royal or her rival Nicolas Sarkozy, who leads in polls after first round of elections; Bayrou also hopes to strengthen his position before June parliamentary elections; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an effort to broaden her appeal, Ségolène Royal engaged in a televised debate on Saturday with a man who is no longer even a candidate for the presidency of France.</p>
        <p>The 100-minute encounter between Ms. Royal, the candidate of the left, and François Bayrou, the centrist candidate who was knocked out of the race in the first round, was a first since presidential debates began in France in the 1974 race. Never before has a candidate who made it into the runoff debated one of the losers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ségolène Royal engaged in a televised debate with a man who is not even her opponent in an effort to broaden her appeal in the campaign for the French presidency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an effort to broaden her appeal, Ségolène Royal engaged in a televised debate on Saturday with a man who is no longer even a candidate for the presidency of France.</p>
        <p>The 100-minute encounter between Ms. Royal, the candidate of the left, and François Bayrou, the centrist candidate who was knocked out of the race in the first round, was a first since presidential debates began in France in the 1974 race. Never before has a candidate who made it into the runoff debated one of the losers.</p>
        <p>The decision to conduct the debate just eight days before the election was a calculated risk for Ms. Royal. She came in six points behind Nicolas Sarkozy, the candidate on the right, in the first round of voting on April 22, and needs to capture a sizable percentage of Mr. Bayrou's nearly seven million voters to win.</p>
        <p>The debate before hundreds of journalists in a Paris hotel ballroom was not shown live on a major French television station because of election broadcast regulations requiring equal airtime for the candidates.</p>
        <p>It was not clear how many French voters saw or heard their exchange, which was shown on BFM TV, a tiny 24-hour news channel, and on RMC, a major radio station. Many French viewers could not gain access to the debate on the television station's Web site, which apparently was overloaded.</p>
        <p>The debate was not a battle of wills; it was not a love fest either.</p>
        <p>''This is an event without precedent that underscores the modernization of political life,'' said Ms. Royal, who called the encounter a ''dialogue'' rather than a ''debate.'' She added that although she and Mr. Bayrou did not agree on everything, ''millions of French think that on certain difficult issues, we can find common ground.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bayrou held firm to his position that he would not endorse either candidate. Asked very early on whether he wanted Ms. Royal to win, he said bluntly, ''I have no intention of entering into this kind of game.''</p>
        <p>Toward the end of the debate, he said, ''Nicolas Sarkozy is not my enemy; Ségolène Royal is not my enemy.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bayrou embraced Ms. Royal's openness, saying that he wanted to ''talk together and see if we can make things move.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Royal was caught in the awkward position of not wanting to appear too friendly toward Mr. Bayrou, should he at any time attack her. The fact that she made such a significant overture to him in appearing together highlights her independence from the left, including critics in her Socialist Party. It also sets her apart from Mr. Sarkozy, whose tone throughout the campaign has been one of confrontation rather than compromise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bayrou, who had nothing to lose in the debate, seemed more at ease. His only goal, he said, was to assert his independence and promote his idea about the need to break down party divisions and create a new conciliatory style of politics for France.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bayrou, who heads the tiny Union for French Democracy party, is also seeking to strengthen his standing before parliamentary elections in June and position himself should he try to run for the presidency again in 2012. This week he announced that before those elections he intended to create a centrist party to be called the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>Ms. Royal was assertive, at times relaxed, at times noticeably tense. She smiled much of the time, but also shifted in her seat, clenched her jaw muscles and fiddled with her hair.</p>
        <p>In a sense, her performance was a window on her debating style before the official debate between her and Mr. Sarkozy that will be broadcast live on national television on May 2.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarkozy, who was campaigning on Saturday with Labor Minister Jean-Louis Borloo in northern France, mocked the Royal-Bayrou debate. ''There they are, the two of them, in a big hotel, chatting together,'' he said, adding, ''I, I am in the midst of the French people.''</p>
        <p>Since his defeat, Mr. Bayrou has been much more critical of Mr. Sarkozy than of Ms. Royal, portraying him this week as having ''a taste for intimidation and threat.''</p>
        <p>But in the debate, Mr. Bayrou also leveled criticism against Ms. Royal -- not for her personality, but for her proposals. He called himself in ''profound disagreement'' with Ms. Royal on her economic projects, for example, which he said depended too much on state intervention.</p>
        <p>''To allow people to dream on that the state will do everything for them -- that's over,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also criticized her proposal that all French people should have a national flag in the cupboard for display on Bastille Day, saying, ''It would be as if I said that all the French people must have a photo of their mothers in the living room.''</p>
        <p>The debate followed a two-day tussle over how it would be organized. At first it was thought that France's regional press would conduct the debate but a journalists' union representing them refused to host it.</p>
        <p>Then a major television channel, Canal Plus, stepped forward to broadcast the debate, only to back out a few hours later, citing election broadcast regulations.</p>
        <p>The cancellations triggered accusations by both Ms. Royal and Mr. Bayrou on Friday that Mr. Sarkozy had used his powerful contacts in the media to prevent the debate from taking place.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bayrou said earlier that although he had no proof, he was ''certain'' that Canal Plus TV had canceled the debate ''at Mr. Sarkozy's demand.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Royal also criticized Mr. Sarkozy, saying earlier, ''All the pressure that has taken place, notably within a media-financial system to which Nicolas Sarkozy is heavily linked, has no place in a democratic country where freedom of speech and debate are very important.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarkozy has denied the accusations, telling a rally in the city of Clermont-Ferrand on Friday, ''I will allow no one to continue to insult and slander me.''</p>
        <p>In agreeing to air the debate, BFM TV has promised Mr. Sarkozy equal time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
