<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Russia, A Bridge Unburned</title>
    <meta content="29myers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/weekinreview/29myers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Yeltsin, Boris N</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5D7123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Russia, A Bridge Unburned</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Russia, a Bridge Unburned</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE extraordinary thing about Boris N. Yeltsin's funeral last week -- the first of a Kremlin leader since Konstantin U. Chernenko died in 1985 -- was not the warm official remembrance of a man who had come to be widely reviled in the popular imagination. Rather it was what the funeral reflected about the kind of country Russia has become, and might yet be.</p>
        <p>After hesitating in the hours after his death on Monday, as if unsure how exactly to respond, the Kremlin employed the full power of the state's servile television networks to transform Mr. Yeltsin's beleaguered image into the religious, patriotic father of the political system he bequeathed to the current president, Vladimir V. Putin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rites of mourning and burial on display during Boris N. Yeltsin’s funeral relied heavily on symbols  some more czarist than Soviet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE extraordinary thing about Boris N. Yeltsin's funeral last week -- the first of a Kremlin leader since Konstantin U. Chernenko died in 1985 -- was not the warm official remembrance of a man who had come to be widely reviled in the popular imagination. Rather it was what the funeral reflected about the kind of country Russia has become, and might yet be.</p>
        <p>After hesitating in the hours after his death on Monday, as if unsure how exactly to respond, the Kremlin employed the full power of the state's servile television networks to transform Mr. Yeltsin's beleaguered image into the religious, patriotic father of the political system he bequeathed to the current president, Vladimir V. Putin.</p>
        <p>In three short days, the authorities here burnished a new founding myth, one that, not incidentally, proved useful for Mr. Putin's own legacy. In this new-minted myth, the bold, firm hand of patriots is what preserves democracy, not the messy, uncertain expression of popular will.</p>
        <p>The elevation of Mr. Yeltsin overlooked the darker side -- the defeat in Chechnya, the rise of the oligarchs, the capitulation to the West, the drunkenness -- partly out of respect for the dead, no doubt, but also because it let Mr. Putin portray himself, too, as a defender of the revolution and restorer of Russian greatness. Mr. Yeltsin became, in this incarnation, what Nina L. Khrushcheva, the great-granddaughter of the Soviet leader Nikita S. Khrushchev, called the ''czar of Russian democracy.''</p>
        <p>''It's an oxymoron,'' she said in a telephone interview from New York, where she teaches international affairs at the New School, ''but in a sense, that's what Putin has made him into.''</p>
        <p>The rites of mourning and burial on display last week were rich with symbolism, as they are anywhere, but they resonated more deeply here, coming barely 15 years after the collapse of the Soviet Union that Mr. Yeltsin helped engineer. And the contrasts, at times, jarred.</p>
        <p>The funeral was the first the Russian Orthodox Church has officiated for a head of state here since the next-to-last czar, Aleksandr III, died in 1894. It took place not in the Column Hall of the House of Trade Unions, where Soviet leaders lie in state, but rather in the Christ the Savior Cathedral, the gold-domed city landmark destroyed on Stalin's orders and rebuilt on Yeltsin's.</p>
        <p>He was buried not along the Kremlin Wall Necropolis, with Stalin, Brezhnev, Andropov and Chernenko, but rather in the historic Novodevichy Cemetery, with thousands of actors, artists and writers, cosmonauts, explorers and scientists.</p>
        <p>He received full military honors, befitting his role as commander in chief, though he was thoroughly blamed for the disastrous decline of the military in the 1990s (and the Russian Army's humiliating defeat in Chechnya in 1996).</p>
        <p>When the white-robed priests completed their incantations, a military band played the old Soviet national anthem, which Mr. Yeltsin abolished but Mr. Putin reinstated, albeit with new lyrics.</p>
        <p>Vladimir N. Shevchenko, the former president's chief of protocol, said in an interview that Mr. Yeltsin's family chose a religious ceremony and a grave in Novodevichy, even though Mr. Yeltsin was not known as a particularly fervent believer. Still, it was hard not to imagine that the church's role in Mr. Yeltsin's funeral would become a standard for those Russian leaders to follow (in Mr. Putin's case, probably decades from now).</p>
        <p>The Orthodox Church's resurrection in Russian society is now firmly established, but the striking tableau of Mr. Yeltsin's coffin, draped in the Russian tricolor, accompanied by a military honor guard and presided over by bearded priests, embodied symbols of a new Russia -- state, military and church -- very much like the Russia of old.</p>
        <p>''Russia has existed for many centuries,'' Georgy V. Velenbakhov, chief heraldry master of the Heraldry Council of Russia, said in a telephone interview. ''It doesn't have to look for a new identity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin was a historic figure, bridging the totalitarian past and the hopes for a democratic future, one that Mr. Putin's critics now say is under assault. His funeral represented a break from the past and, simultaneously, an embrace of it. It served as evidence of a country still searching for the symbols that gird its national idea or identity or, perhaps better to say, a country still arguing over them.</p>
        <p>On the day of the funeral, the lower house of Parliament reversed its earlier vote to remove the Communist hammer and sickle from the Victory Banner, the military flag commemorating the victory over Nazi Germany. Mr. Putin had vetoed the initial legislation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin eulogized his predecessor in a way he rarely did when he was alive, describing him as the steadfast democrat and reformer of ''great Russia,'' not the weakened, chaotic Russia that emerged from the Soviet ruins. It is surely the legacy Mr. Putin would like to embrace as his own.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin's greatest achievement, arguably, was voluntarily surrendering power for the first time in the country's history. The day after the funeral, Mr. Putin addressed Parliament and insisted, despite calls to do otherwise, that he would also step aside, when he finishes his second term next year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Khrushcheva said Mr. Putin embraced Mr. Yeltsin the way Stalin embraced Lenin, appropriating his legacy by transforming him ''into the realm of state propaganda'' to be used for other ends.</p>
        <p>Even so, for many here, Mr. Yeltsin's death served as a reminder of what changes have occurred. More than 20,000 people waited in line for hours for a last glimpse of the man. ''Nobody brought them in buses, like before,'' Mr. Shevchenko said, referring to the grandiose funerals of Soviet leaders. ''They came themselves to say goodbye to the first president of Russia.''</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
