<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Jets Trade Up and Home In for Defensive Help</title>
    <meta content="29jets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/football/29jets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Pittsburgh</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Jets Trade Up and Home In for Defensive Help</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jets Trade Up to Draft Revis With 14th Pick</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., April 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets were aggressive in their pursuit of their first two draft picks Saturday, believing that cornerback Darrelle Revis and linebacker David Harris will add teeth to their defense come September.</p>
        <p>Looking to improve a defense that ranked 20th last season, the Jets traded up in order to select both players. They orchestrated the first trade of a long day when they swapped first-round picks with the Carolina Panthers, moving up 11 spots and making Revis the first cornerback chosen, at No. 14.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In selecting the Pittsburgh cornerback, the Jets addressed their most glaring deficiency and traded away three draft picks to the Carolina Panthers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Jets were aggressive in their pursuit of their first two draft picks Saturday, believing that cornerback Darrelle Revis and linebacker David Harris will add teeth to their defense come September.</p>
        <p>Looking to improve a defense that ranked 20th last season, the Jets traded up in order to select both players. They orchestrated the first trade of a long day when they swapped first-round picks with the Carolina Panthers, moving up 11 spots and making Revis the first cornerback chosen, at No. 14.</p>
        <p>Revis, 21, who bypassed his senior year at Pittsburgh to enter the draft, is expected to compete immediately for a starting spot at the right corner, which was in flux last year. The Jets tried three starters at the position before settling on a fourth, Hank Poteat, whom they had cut earlier in the season.</p>
        <p>In addition to giving the Panthers their first-round pick (25th over all), the Jets parted with picks in the second (59th) and fifth round (164th). They received a sixth-round pick (191st), which they later packaged with their second-round pick (63rd) and a third-round pick (89th) to consummate the trade with the Green Bay Packers that enabled them to select Harris.</p>
        <p>Harris, 23, was projected as a first-round pick by many experts after leading the Wolverines in tackles as a junior and senior. He is expected to compete for the starting position that Eric Barton held last year and bolster a run defense that ranked 24th in the league.</p>
        <p>After the Jets were finished wheeling and dealing, they were left with two picks Sunday, in the sixth (177th over all) and seventh rounds (235th), the latter of which they received from the Packers in their trade. A four-player draft would be the smallest in the team's history, and a far cry from last year when the Jets, coming off a 4-12 season, drafted 10 players.</p>
        <p>''For the quality of players we were able to acquire, we thought it was worth it,'' General Manager Mike Tannenbaum said.</p>
        <p>Revis, whose uncle, Sean Gilbert, played 12 seasons in the N.F.L. as a defensive tackle, said he burst into tears upon hearing that he had been selected by the Jets. In a teleconference, he said that playing in the N.F.L. was ''something I dreamed about my whole life and now it's here.''</p>
        <p>The Steelers, who were picking at No. 15, were thought to covet Revis. When word got out that the Jets had moved into the Panthers' spot, Jets fans at Radio City Music Hall stirred to life. They chanted, ''Brady, Brady,'' in reference to Notre Dame quarterback Brady Quinn, who had not yet been chosen.</p>
        <p>But the Jets did not need to address that position, having selected quarterback Chad Pennington's eventual successor, Kellen Clemens, in the second round of last year's draft. Instead, they jumped at the chance to take Revis, who accounted for one of seven interceptions that Quinn threw in 2005 as a junior.</p>
        <p>Revis, who is 5 feet 11 and 204 pounds, played both left and right cornerback in college while appearing in 35 games, including 34 as a starter. He had eight career interceptions at Pittsburgh and made 39 tackles last season, during which he earned first-team All-Big East Conference honors. He also returned 54 punts for 555 yards.</p>
        <p>''The fact that he's also a punt returner, that's something else that excited us,'' Tannenbaum said, adding, ''As a player and a person we think he's a good fit.''</p>
        <p>Asked about returning punts, Revis said: ''I love the ball in my hands.''</p>
        <p>Revis spent a day in New York interviewing with the Jets but it was unclear what kind of impression he had made. ''I couldn't get a feel for them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tannenbaum and Coach Eric Mangini said Revis impressed them in ways both obvious and subtle. When watching game film, they seldom saw him get beaten by a receiver. That attested to his playing ability.</p>
        <p>The quality of his character manifested itself when Tannenbaum, finding himself in the same limousine that had been used to ferry Revis to the Jets' facility from the airport, quizzed the driver on how he was treated by Revis.</p>
        <p>''It was just another test he passed,'' Tannenbaum said.</p>
        <p>Revis would not have fared well if he had been tested on the Jets' history.</p>
        <p>''The only thing I know about the Jets is Ty Law played there,'' he said with a nervous chuckle.</p>
        <p>Law, who played for Mangini in New England and with the Jets in 2005, is from Aliquippa, Pa., as is Revis, and the two are friendly. Revis has Law's phone number and plans to pick his brain about Mangini and the Jets in the coming weeks.</p>
        <p>''Me and Ty talk all the time,'' Revis said. ''I'm going to continue to talk to him even more just to get more insight into things. He's taught me things from technique to just being a positive person off the field.''</p>
        <p>Harris knows Jets linebacker Victor Hobson, a fellow Wolverine, and he was coached by Jim Hermann before Hermann left Ann Arbor to become the Jets' linebackers coach.</p>
        <p>''They have great linebackers,'' said Harris, who played in the 3-4 during his sophomore season. ''I just want to go in and compete.''</p>
        <p>At the N.F.L. scouting combine, Revis had spoken with a confidence that bordered on conceit. When people look at his name, he said then, ''I want them to look at how many categories in which he never gets beat.''</p>
        <p>Asked Saturday if he pictured himself starting right away, Revis erred on the side of humility. ''My thing,'' he said, ''is just to come in there and learn the system.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
