<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beware Of Too Much Good News</title>
    <meta content="29mark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/business/yourmoney/29mark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFDA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beware Of Too Much Good News</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Beware of Too Much Good News</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De Aenlle, Conrad</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILL 13,000 turn out to be a lucky number on Wall Street? With the Dow Jones industrial average now beyond that milestone, traders will be looking for clues to help them determine whether the index will leave it far behind.</p>
        <p>The first hint may come on Friday, when the monthly snapshot of employment conditions is released. The lucky number there could be 100,000, the estimate of the number of jobs created in April, according to a Bloomberg News poll of economists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Dow Jones industrial average passes 13,000, traders are anticipating slower job growth for the month of April.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILL 13,000 turn out to be a lucky number on Wall Street? With the Dow Jones industrial average now beyond that milestone, traders will be looking for clues to help them determine whether the index will leave it far behind.</p>
        <p>The first hint may come on Friday, when the monthly snapshot of employment conditions is released. The lucky number there could be 100,000, the estimate of the number of jobs created in April, according to a Bloomberg News poll of economists.</p>
        <p>That would be barely half the 180,000 net new jobs reported for March, but it might be close to the right amount for the markets, said Bill Cheney, chief economist at John Hancock Financial Services. A figure near the consensus estimate, which he considers ''pretty reasonable,'' would be a harbinger of strong economic activity, but not so strong that it brings with it the threat of higher inflation and interest rates, he said.</p>
        <p>Much deviation from the anticipated figure is likely to displease one investment constituency or another. If the economy adds significantly fewer jobs than expected, it may signal that ''the other shoe from the housing market is about to drop, that consumers will stop spending,'' he said. That development would be likely to hurt share prices.</p>
        <p>The large number of new jobs last month was mainly a result of construction companies taking advantage of improving weather. A repeat performance is unlikely, Mr. Cheney said, and could be just as unwelcome as a weak report because it would indicate that the economy was growing faster than the Federal Reserve would like.</p>
        <p>Stock traders might not mind such strength, he said, but the bond market probably would be unnerved. Prices would be inclined to fall and yields to rise, as long-dormant fears of an interest rate increase were stirred.</p>
        <p>''There is a point at which news is too good to be good,'' Mr. Cheney said. ''If we get another number like 180,000 and the unemployment rate comes down again, it would definitely get the Fed thinking about the need to do something about incipient inflation pressures.''</p>
        <p>In the Bloomberg poll, the unemployment rate is expected to rise to 4.5 percent from 4.4 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney added that back-to-back shows of strength in the job market would not change what the Fed says about economic conditions -- just what investors hear.</p>
        <p>Fed policy makers ''have been out there saying they're worried about inflation, and the market has been ignoring them,'' he said. ''If we get more data like last month's, the Fed would say the same things, and the market would start to believe them more.''</p>
        <p>DATA WATCH -- The Institute for Supply Management's manufacturing survey for April, to be reported Tuesday, is expected to show slight improvement. The Bloomberg poll predicts a reading of 51, up from 50.9 in March.</p>
        <p>Productivity in the broad economy, to be reported on Thursday, is forecast to have risen at an annual rate of 0.8 percent in the first quarter, a more subdued performance than the 1.6 percent gain for the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>MARKET WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
