<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Goodbye, Newton, Hello, Childhood</title>
    <meta content="29POSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/fashion/shows/29POSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSSESSED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trampolines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trampolines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Rowley, Cynthia</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Goodbye, Newton, Hello, Childhood</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Goodbye, Newton, Hello, Childhood</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID COLMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Colman, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OTHER fashion designers have chic, have irony, have elegance, have attitude. Cynthia Rowley has what you might call boing -- a Spring-O-Lator sense of silliness that, combined with her youthful silhouettes, bright colors and inexpensive but idiosyncratic detailing, adds up to a pretty charming whole.</p>
        <p>This is, after all, a woman who chose to take a tricked-up circus-knife-thrower's target board along when she was having her photo taken by the serious portraitist Timothy Greenfield-Sanders. She wanted to be immortalized as a lovely but nervous knife-thrower's assistant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The designer Cynthia Rowley is happiest bouncing on the 12-foot High Jump trampoline she has in the backyard of the West Village town house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OTHER fashion designers have chic, have irony, have elegance, have attitude. Cynthia Rowley has what you might call boing -- a Spring-O-Lator sense of silliness that, combined with her youthful silhouettes, bright colors and inexpensive but idiosyncratic detailing, adds up to a pretty charming whole.</p>
        <p>This is, after all, a woman who chose to take a tricked-up circus-knife-thrower's target board along when she was having her photo taken by the serious portraitist Timothy Greenfield-Sanders. She wanted to be immortalized as a lovely but nervous knife-thrower's assistant.</p>
        <p>''Well, I asked him if I could bring a prop, and he said yes,'' she explained. And instead of penning a book about her experience in fashion, she has blithely rewritten (and illustrated) her life story as a fantastical children's book cum memoir, ''Slim: A Fantasy Memoir,'' out this month from Rizzoli.</p>
        <p>So it is fitting that while the sociable Ms. Rowley is frequently happy, she is happiest bouncing on the 12-foot High Jump trampoline she has in the backyard of the West Village town house she shares with her husband and two young daughters.</p>
        <p>''It was always my dream to have one when I was little, because Pam Posey had one -- she was fancy,'' she said, referring to her best friend. ''I'm always fulfilling all these childhood dreams I had.''</p>
        <p>It certainly makes her easy to shop for. About 15 years ago, when her business was taking off, her staff pitched in and bought her a trampoline, which she installed at the house she then had in upstate New York. Three weeks later, a Harper's Bazaar photographer shot her jumping on it in a pink ball gown, and she got tangled up in the tulle and broke her arm.</p>
        <p>Undeterred, she bought another trampoline years later when she purchased a beach shack in Montauk, and recently bought another one for her Village house, where she and her daughters have had to keep their ebullience somewhat in check.</p>
        <p>''We do live in a neighborhood where you have to be kind of quiet,'' she said. ''So we're out there before school at 8 in the morning, and I'm always saying, 'Shhh.' I'm sure someone's going to complain about the giggling.''</p>
        <p>On the plus side, she finds she can see into her neighbors' backyards (and second floors) with ease. ''I can almost get up to a third-floor walk-up,'' she boasted. ''I saw a woman in her underwear, but it wasn't that interesting.''</p>
        <p>As irreverent as this suspension of all gravity sounds, Ms. Rowley has turned her colorful spirit into a major business that she owns, a rarity in fashion. But the trampoline is not a piece of brand identity. ''It's been with me my whole life -- at least, the desire to have one as a kid, and then getting it as an adult,'' she said. ''We had our wedding picture taken on it.'' Or rather, above it.</p>
        <p>And one of her favorite books is ''Philippe Halsman's Jump Book,'' a 1959 collection of photographs in which Halsman captured luminaries like Marilyn Monroe, Richard Nixon and Salvador Dalí in midair. In a sudden burst of energy, Halsman wrote, explaining the jump's appeal, ''the real self becomes visible.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Rowley may argue that jumping makes her real self visible all day long. ''There's just an exuberance you get,'' she said. ''It's not like I can do a lot of tricks, but you can't help but laugh when you're jumping.''</p>
        <p>In this house, not taking things seriously is taken very seriously.</p>
        <p>POSSESSED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
