<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Waiting Game On the Draft's Longest Day</title>
    <meta content="29draft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Cleveland Browns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Detroit Lions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Oakland Raiders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5DD133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Waiting Game On the Draft's Longest Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brady Quinn arrived at Radio City Music Hall yesterday morning with a number in mind: nine. That was where the Miami Dolphins were scheduled to pick in the first round of the N.F.L. draft. Like someone conducting a very personal mock draft, Quinn, the former Notre Dame quarterback, identified it as the spot that he could not imagine himself falling beyond.</p>
        <p>He had worked out for the Dolphins, and Miami certainly had a need for a quarterback in its endless quest for the next Dan Marino. So, as each of the first few picks went by, as the green room backstage began to empty of the other top prospects, Quinn could still manage a smile, secure in his own calculations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brady Quinn arrived at Radio City Music Hall yesterday morning with a number in mind: nine. That was where the Miami Dolphins were scheduled to pick in the first round of the N.F.L. draft. Like someone conducting a very personal mock draft, Quinn, the former Notre Dame quarterback, identified it as the spot that he could not imagine himself falling beyond.</p>
        <p>He had worked out for the Dolphins, and Miami certainly had a need for a quarterback in its endless quest for the next Dan Marino. So, as each of the first few picks went by, as the green room backstage began to empty of the other top prospects, Quinn could still manage a smile, secure in his own calculations.</p>
        <p>JaMarcus Russell, the Louisiana State quarterback who outdueled Quinn in the Sugar Bowl, had long since gone to the Oakland Raiders with the first overall pick. It was the rare moment when Al Davis, the Raiders' owner, dovetailed with the conventional wisdom to take a franchise quarterback after he passed on Matt Leinart and Jay Cutler last year. Russell received a telephone call and text message from the Raiders, telling him that he was the choice to revive a franchise that scored only 12 offensive touchdowns last season.</p>
        <p>''I kind of had faith, everybody had been talking about it for a while,'' Russell said of being taken first. ''I would go anywhere in the world and play ball, and I'm just happy that I'm at the Oakland Raiders today.''</p>
        <p>Then it was Georgia Tech receiver Calvin Johnson, who became the fourth receiver taken by General Manager Matt Millen with the Lions' first pick in the past five years. Lions fans at Radio City Music Hall barely waited for Johnson's name to be announced before picking up a familiar cry: ''Fire Millen.''</p>
        <p>The Lions later traded Mike Williams, one of those picks, and the sixth-year quarterback Josh McCown to the Raiders for a fourth-round pick. The deal may indicate the Raiders are preparing to trade Randy Moss.</p>
        <p>''I'm just overwhelmed with excitement right now,'' Johnson said.</p>
        <p>So was Quinn. The Browns were next on the clock, and they needed a quarterback. Quinn went to his first Browns game with his father, uncle and grandfather when he was 7, and said that he wanted to play for the Browns, something not often heard in the N.F.L. since the days of Bernie Kosar. At Notre Dame, Quinn had played for Charlie Weis, a former N.F.L. colleague of Browns Coach Romeo Crennel.</p>
        <p>Still, if Quinn was a little heartbroken when the Browns opted for left tackle Joe Thomas with the third overall pick, he concealed it well. He smiled and shrugged. He had said that he would not worry about sliding, because it only meant he would go to a better team with a chance to win sooner. But maybe Thomas had had the right idea. He declined the N.F.L.'s invitation to come to the green room, and went fishing with his father instead.</p>
        <p>Then the picks went by quickly. Defensive end Gaines Adams to Tampa Bay. Offensive tackle Levi Brown to Arizona, to protect Leinart, who could have offered Quinn some words of wisdom. Leinart dropped to the 10th spot last year. The Redskins picked safety LaRon Landry, and Minnesota, which many believed might consider Quinn, went with running back Adrian Peterson.</p>
        <p>That left Quinn alone in the green room. His number had not come yet. Atlanta picked defensive end Jamaal Anderson, then the Dolphins were on the clock.</p>
        <p>The Dolphins' fans at Radio City started chanting his name and the Quinn highlight reel was cued up on the big screens. But the Dolphins pulled off the first shocker of the draft, selecting receiver and kick returner Ted Ginn Jr.</p>
        <p>Quinn's face, captured at the moment of the announcement, tightened and turned grim. Commissioner Roger Goodell approached him. Perhaps, Goodell said to Quinn, you would like to sit in a private suite, away from the cameras, because you might not be picked for a while. A look at the draft order made that clear. Houston, San Francisco, Buffalo, St. Louis -- none of them needed quarterbacks. The stunned Quinn agreed and went off to his exile. In Miami, fans booed the new coach, Cam Cameron.</p>
        <p>''At a certain point, when you're past those teams that you've built some sort of relationship with, you're entering an unknown,'' Quinn said later.</p>
        <p>He stayed in exile for several excruciating hours. This had happened before to quarterbacks. Leinart's slide was one of the most compelling stories of last year's draft. In 2005, Aaron Rodgers sat in the green room until the Packers took him with the 24th pick. But Quinn's wait was the worst. This ended up being the longest first round in the history of the draft -- 6 hours 8 minutes.</p>
        <p>While Quinn sat, there was a run on defensive players, with 13 of 16 picks in the middle part of the first round going to defense, including nine in a row. That included the Jets, who traded up to the 14th pick from the 25th to take cornerback Darrelle Revis, and the Giants, who took cornerback Aaron Ross at No. 20. Jacksonville, which had traded with Denver to get the 21st spot, picked safety Reggie Nelson.</p>
        <p>Then Quinn's phone rang. It was the Baltimore Ravens. They were working on a trade to get him. The Ravens' interest perhaps indicated that the wait for Kyle Boller to become their quarterback of the future was nearing its end. During the day, Quinn had already begun to think that once he finally landed with a team, he would work to show the Browns what they missed. Perhaps he would do that for Baltimore. He hung up, and his cellphone rang again. This time it was the Browns. Dallas was on the clock with the 22nd pick.</p>
        <p>''We made a trade, we are going to come get you right now,'' Quinn said the Browns told him.</p>
        <p>If it sounded a bit like a rescue, perhaps it was. As soon as Quinn started falling, the Browns began working the phones, calling teams as high as No. 12, hoping to find a trading partner. When Goodell finally called his name, Quinn looked to the heavens and exhaled heavily.</p>
        <p>''I felt like the weight of the world was lifted off my shoulders,'' he said.</p>
        <p>General Manager Phil Savage is banking on Quinn to improve the Browns' record immediately. He traded the team's first-round pick next year to Dallas to get Quinn. ''We didn't expect Brady Quinn to fall as far as he did,'' Savage said. ''We had Brady rated very high on our board, just not top three.''</p>
        <p>Weis had already called Quinn. Quinn told him that things had a funny way of working out.</p>
        <p>''Well, it ended up working out how we wanted it to, not exactly, but how we wanted it to,'' Quinn said Weis told him. ''Go out and prove everyone wrong.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
