<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When State Laws Do Not Apply</title>
    <meta content="29mort" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/realestate/29mort.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MORTGAGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wachovia Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tedeschi, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EED7153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When State Laws Do Not Apply</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When State Laws Do Not Apply</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB TEDESCHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tedeschi, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mortgages column on Supreme Court ruling that national banks' mortgage-lending subsidiaries do not have to obey state banking regulations; in finding in favor of defendant Wachovia Bank, court cited longstanding precedent against state regulation of interstate banks; impact on borrowers discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EARLIER this month, Countrywide Home Loans, one of the nation's biggest mortgage lenders, paid Connecticut $500,000 as a penalty for violating the state's lending laws. But if other national lenders were to engage in the same practices today, consumers would have little recourse.</p>
        <p>That's because the United States Supreme Court ruled, just days after Countrywide's settlement, that national banks' mortgage-lending subsidiaries do not have to obey state banking regulations. And because the federal government has not established a broad set of regulations against predatory lending, borrowers face new issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new Supreme Court ruling may make it harder for mortgage customers to fight back against predatory lending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EARLIER this month, Countrywide Home Loans, one of the nation's biggest mortgage lenders, paid Connecticut $500,000 as a penalty for violating the state's lending laws. But if other national lenders were to engage in the same practices today, consumers would have little recourse.</p>
        <p>That's because the United States Supreme Court ruled, just days after Countrywide's settlement, that national banks' mortgage-lending subsidiaries do not have to obey state banking regulations. And because the federal government has not established a broad set of regulations against predatory lending, borrowers face new issues.</p>
        <p>''Consumers should be disappointed,'' said Richard H. Neiman, New York's superintendent of banks. ''It's unfortunate that the national banks' mortgage subsidiaries will not be obligated to conform to the more protective state consumer laws that may apply to a state institution.''</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court's decision focused on whether Wachovia Bank's mortgage-lending unit was subject to Michigan's banking laws and whether any national bank's mortgage subsidiaries were subject to those regulations. In finding in favor of Wachovia, the court cited longstanding precedent against the state regulation of interstate banks.</p>
        <p>For consumers, the decision raises a new question: How do you tell if a lender is regulated by state lending laws? The short answer is: Check with your state's banking regulator. ''That's why we're here,'' said Howard Pitkin, commissioner of the Connecticut Department of Banking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pitkin says his office regulates 44 state-chartered banks with about 20,000 lending officers. ''But Bank of America, People's, Citizen's, Wachovia, Citi -- they're huge, and they all have mortgage subsidiaries in the states,'' meaning that they are not covered by state regulations.</p>
        <p>As the Countrywide settlement shows, even well-established financial institutions can violate lending laws. From October 2001 to August 2005, Countrywide made at least 473 mortgage loans in Connecticut that included closing costs -- chiefly prepaid interest charges -- exceeding 5 percent of the loan's principal, or $2,000, in violation of state law. It also retained or employed at least 147 loan officers without registering them with the state.</p>
        <p>As part of the settlement, Countrywide refunded the excess finance charges. Rick Simon, a spokesman, released a statement last Tuesday in which the company denied ''intentional wrongdoing.''</p>
        <p>''Countrywide has taken steps to assure proper understanding and ongoing compliance with Connecticut regulations,'' the statement said. (Because Countrywide's Connecticut lending operation is not considered a subsidiary of a national bank, it is subject to state laws.)</p>
        <p>Connecticut, New York and New Jersey have enacted more stringent lending laws in recent years, after booming home sales brought sharp increases in mortgage complaints.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's Home Ownership Security Act, approved in May 2003, contains restrictions on closing costs similar to Connecticut's. ''Often in predatory lending, you'll see very attractive interest rates,'' said Jim Gardner, a spokesman for the New Jersey Department of Banking and Insurance, ''but then they start slapping on fees, and in the end the interest is far, far beyond what you thought you were paying.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gardner said that before the Home Ownership Security Act was passed, his department received 616 consumer complaints about lenders in 2002. That dropped to 265 last year.</p>
        <p>New York's lending laws include, among other provisions, a limit on prepayment penalties to the first year of the loan. The limit is useful for borrowers facing spikes in interest rates after two or three years.</p>
        <p>Borrowers looking for more information can check the appropriate Web site: Connecticut's Department of Banking at ct.gov/dob; New Jersey's Department of Banking and Insurance at state.nj.us/dobi; and New York's Banking Department at banking.state.ny.us.</p>
        <p>MORTGAGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
