<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Family First, Then Task Forces</title>
    <meta content="29boss" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/business/yourmoney/29boss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843800"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Boss</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0DA123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Family First, Then Task Forces</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Family First, Then Task Forces</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOIS QUAM; As told to Amy Zipkin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zipkin, Amy; Quam, Lois</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I GREW up in Marshall, Minn. My grandparents all spoke Norwegian. We spoke English at home but we would say ''takk for maten,'' which means thank you for the food.</p>
        <p>I vividly remember a sleepover at someone's house. I said ''takk for maten'' after dinner and no one understood a word I said. I didn't realize they weren't English words.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“I was a good student, but what I really liked to do was organize a group of people to do something,” said Lois Quam, president of public and senior markets groups forUnited HealthCare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I GREW up in Marshall, Minn. My grandparents all spoke Norwegian. We spoke English at home but we would say ''takk for maten,'' which means thank you for the food.</p>
        <p>I vividly remember a sleepover at someone's house. I said ''takk for maten'' after dinner and no one understood a word I said. I didn't realize they weren't English words.</p>
        <p>My father was a Lutheran minister and knew people from all walks of life. When I was about 7, a tornado hit the town of Tracy. You could see the tornado from our town. And there were people who were wounded and killed as a result. At any moment your plans could be interrupted.</p>
        <p>I was a good student, but what I really liked to do was organize a group of people to do something. When I was 16, I was elected president of the Southwestern Minnesota District Luther League and later was the youngest member of the Commission for a New Lutheran Church.</p>
        <p>At college one of my professors recommended me for a Rhodes scholarship. The interviews were at the Minneapolis Club, a private business club. I had never been to a club like that. I was wearing a blue suit my grandmother had helped me pick out. There was a wine-and-cheese reception, and many of the students knew each other from high school and were now in the Ivy League. I felt kind of out of place.</p>
        <p>One question at the interview was what I wanted to be professionally. I said I wanted to be a college professor. After I received the scholarship one of the interviewers said to me: ''I want you to know none of us think you'll be a college professor. We think you'll be head of an organization.''</p>
        <p>I was at Oxford for four years. I studied at Trinity College and then I was affiliated with the Centre for Socio-Legal Studies. While there, I worked on a two-part article about the impact of medical malpractice that was published in the British Medical Journal in June 1987. I was the lead author. After publication I got a couple of bottles of Champagne, and we were sitting around celebrating. One of the other authors started considering the next set of articles. I was much more interested in fixing the problem.</p>
        <p>When I returned to the United States I got a job as director of research at Partners National Health Plans in Minnesota and joined United HealthCare two years later.</p>
        <p>I was expecting my first child in late August 1989. He was born on a Sunday at 5 p.m. The next morning I called my assistant at 9 a.m. and she said, ''The governor's office has called three times already this morning.''</p>
        <p>I called the governor's office and his chief of staff, Lynn Anderson, said, ''The governor would like to meet with you this afternoon.'' I said any other day I could rearrange my schedule but I just had a baby.</p>
        <p>The governor, Rudy Perpich, was setting up the Minnesota Health Care Access Commission to look for ways to develop a state universal health plan within a budget.</p>
        <p>The Minnesota State Fair was going on at the time. Five days later I fed the baby and then a friend dropped me off at the fairgrounds, which were two miles from my house. I met the governor, who asked me to be chairman of the commission and then announced its creation. Then the same friend picked me up at the fair gates. I went home to feed the baby.</p>
        <p>During the course of the commission's work I found out I was expecting twins. I ended up on two months of bed rest. The legislature didn't fully finance the health care plan we proposed.</p>
        <p>In January 1993 I got a call from an assistant in the White House policy office asking me to serve on the President's Task Force on National Health Care Reform. The boys were 1 1/2 and 3 1/2.</p>
        <p>My husband and I talked about the challenges of a commute. The idea was that I'd come home every third weekend, but I ended up coming home two out of four weekends. I commuted for six months and lived with friends. My husband, parents, mother-in-law and a baby sitter watched the boys. About a week and a half after I arrived home, they got the chickenpox.</p>
        <p>I cook breakfast instead of dinner. It can be blueberry pancakes and eggs or bacon and grits. It's recognizing the things that are most important. I learned that, having three kids.</p>
        <p>LOIS QUAM  President of public and senior markets groups, United HealthCare</p>
        <p>BIRTH DATE  June 12, 1961</p>
        <p>PASTIME  Enjoys visiting greenmarkets and cooking for family and friends.</p>
        <p>OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
