<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Conflicts Accompany Nepal's Efforts at Democracy</title>
    <meta content="29nepal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/world/asia/29nepal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nepal</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nepal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Nepal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Nepal</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EFD6123EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1258" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Conflicts Accompany Nepal's Efforts at Democracy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Conflicts Accompany Nepal’s Efforts at Democracy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA; Angelica Medaglia and Tilak Pokharel contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <dateline>KATMANDU, Nepal, April 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New but not unexpected fissures have cut through Nepal's body politic as it struggles to recover from decade of Maoist insurgency and redefine grounds of nationhood; divisions stem from old grievances over how Nepal's many ethnic groups, castes and language minorities will be treated by state; questions of regional and ethnic autonomy have sparked violent uprisings; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year after the return of democratic rule to Nepal, the scene in Parliament went something like this:</p>
        <p>No sooner had it officially opened for business Monday afternoon, nearly six hours past schedule and with the benches barely filled to quorum, than some parliamentarians rushed the dais, raising fists and shouting slogans to protest a police crackdown in the southeast early this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year after a return to democratic rule, a useless session of Parliament represents the fissures that have cut through Nepal’s body politic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year after the return of democratic rule to Nepal, the scene in Parliament went something like this:</p>
        <p>No sooner had it officially opened for business Monday afternoon, nearly six hours past schedule and with the benches barely filled to quorum, than some parliamentarians rushed the dais, raising fists and shouting slogans to protest a police crackdown in the southeast early this year.</p>
        <p>The speaker's pleas for them to return to their seats were ignored. Within 10 minutes, unable to do any legislative work, Parliament was adjourned. It was the third such useless session in less than two weeks.</p>
        <p>The scene represented much more than the routine fracas of democracy. It was a snapshot of the new, though not entirely unexpected, fissures that have cut through Nepal's body politic, as it struggles to recover from more than a decade of Maoist insurgency and redefine the very ground rules of its nationhood.</p>
        <p>The divisions stem from old grievances over how Nepal's many ethnic groups, castes and language minorities will be treated by the state, long dominated by members of the upper-caste elite from the hills. The parliamentarians who raised the ruckus represented the people of the southeastern plains, known here as Madhesis, who had staged an uprising that the police quashed.</p>
        <p>The politicians, who now include the Maoists, who have joined the cabinet, have been caught off guard by the ferocity of the complaints.</p>
        <p>''We are in an awkward position,'' said Ram Chandra Poudel, the beleaguered minister for peace and reconstruction, on Monday, adding that he had not expected to face so many grievances from so many quarters, so soon after the restoration of democracy. ''These demands may be genuine, but these demands should not come out so aggressively.''</p>
        <p>As if on cue, the next day a particularly aggressive show of frustration against the government occurred. When Mr. Poudel tried to speak at a rally to commemorate the anniversary of democratic rule in a public square in this capital, he was hit by empty water bottles and booed.</p>
        <p>Ambling through the public square in matching gray tracksuits were members of the Maoists' latest subsidiary, a pack of young men and women known as the Young Communist League and led by former guerrillas. They said they had been assigned to provide security. Among their duties these days is the demolition of illegal structures, traffic management, capturing people accused of being gangsters and acting against what they call ''regressive forces.'' At times, that includes disrupting other political party meetings or thrashing political opponents.</p>
        <p>The new uncertainties have come in a country transforming itself remarkably fast. A year ago, King Gyanendra, who had seized absolute control of the state, was forced by a swell of street protests to return the government to an elected parliament. The government signed a peace deal with the Maoists, ending a war that had lasted 11 years. The Maoists then sequestered their fighters and put weapons into cantonments, monitored by the United Nations.</p>
        <p>An interim Constitution was put in place. A coalition government took over, including even the Maoists, who traded their fatigues for safari suits.</p>
        <p>Over the last year, symbols of the old Nepal were scrapped: A new national anthem was drafted, ''Royal'' was dropped from the name of the Nepalese Army and the state-owned Nepal Airlines, and the government promised to tax the king's property.</p>
        <p>A critical issue remains unresolved in the new Nepal, and it is the root of widespread public frustration: whether and how Nepal will become a federal state with some degree of autonomy for its ethnic groups and regions.</p>
        <p>It is a question that has sparked a sometimes violent uprising over the last three months by the Madhesis, who say people from the hills have long discriminated against them. Demands for representation have come from other socially marginalized groups, too, like low-caste Dalits and indigenous people, called Janjatis.</p>
        <p>Nepal seems to be in no immediate danger of sliding into prolonged ethnic conflict. But the questions that confront Nepal are nothing short of existential. ''What is the new Nepal? What does it mean to be a Nepali? That's absolutely what's being debated,'' said Manjushree Thapa, a writer.</p>
        <p>That debate has made the peace process miss a crucial deadline. June elections to choose a national assembly to rewrite the Constitution, have been indefinitely postponed. A new Constitution will determine many vital issues, including whether Nepal will retain its monarchy.</p>
        <p>Abolishing the Constitution is the Maoists' principal demand, and they now want the government to declare Nepal a republic rather than wait for the voters' verdict.</p>
        <p>The Maoists have vowed to resume what they call ''the people's movement,'' though peacefully this time, fearful that the palace may try to stage a comeback. ''The main challenge is the backlash of regressive forces,'' is how Baburam Bhattarai, the second-in-command of the Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist) put it. ''They will try to turn the wheel of history backwards.''</p>
        <p>This week, two cabinet members suggested that elections could be organized by November, when there is a tiny window in Nepal's difficult social and climatic calendar -- after the rains and autumn festival season and before the harvest. The United Nations urged the government this week to act to hold elections quickly.</p>
        <p>''This constituent assembly election is not any old parliamentary election,'' said Ian Martin, the head of the United Nations Mission in Nepal, which will help with the vote. ''This is the key moment in shaping the future of Nepal. It is indeed essential that the constituent assembly looks like Nepal and like a body in which all groups feel like they are represented.''</p>
        <p>Representation was the fuel that fired the Madhesi revolt in the plains early this year. They were particularly aggrieved by the interim Constitution, which, when promulgated in January, included no mention of regional or ethnic autonomy.</p>
        <p>It was not an issue that should have surprised anyone, least of all Nepal's political leaders, who are largely upper-caste men from the hills. Madhesis had been raising the issue in their own parties for years.</p>
        <p>''They are not honest, they are not sincere, they talk about republic but they are not ready to share political rights with marginalized people,'' Jeetendra Dev said. He included the United Marxist-Leninist, his party, whose Madhesi wing he heads.</p>
        <p>Three major violent clashes have occurred in the plains since January. The latest erupted in March in Gaur, a town in the southeast, after Maoist cadres, including members of the Young Communist League, attacked meetings of Madhesi organizations.</p>
        <p>Retaliation was brutal, and law enforcement was largely absent. Twenty-seven people were killed, most of them Maoists, and most of them beaten bloody with bamboo sticks, according to a report by the United Nations human rights office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Poudel noted that the government had since agreed to the demand for federalism, though it had yet to resolve the details.</p>
        <p>''They're the same as before,'' said Laxmi Dahal, 29, a trade union advocate who attended the commemoration on Tuesday of the return to democracy, with hundreds of others.</p>
        <p>Last year, she said, she marched day after day in the pro-democracy demonstrations and was beaten by the police during one. Today, she said she had come to ''warn'' the political leaders to keep their word to those who had marched for freedom.</p>
        <p>In the crowd, Bijay Paudel, a graduate student, echoed Ms. Dahal's misgivings. ''Everyone wants a change, but the political parties who have been leading the nation are not listening to the voice of the people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
