<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mark on Baseball That Continues To Grow Darker</title>
    <meta content="29base" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/sports/29base.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Selig, Bud</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, George</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E6DE133EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mark on Baseball That Continues To Grow Darker</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Mark on Baseball That Continues to Grow Darker</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An aide could have called Commissioner Bud Selig on Friday and said, ''Sir, I have good news and bad news for you.''</p>
        <p>''Let me have the good news first,'' Selig might have replied. ''I could use some good news today.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even if names don’t surface in baseball’s most recent steroid scandal, the stain is there, indelibly embedded in the game’s fabric.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An aide could have called Commissioner Bud Selig on Friday and said, ''Sir, I have good news and bad news for you.''</p>
        <p>''Let me have the good news first,'' Selig might have replied. ''I could use some good news today.''</p>
        <p>''O.K., Mr. Selig. The good news is the feds in San Francisco have nailed a former Mets clubhouse kid as a big-time steroids distributor to major league players, and as part of his plea agreement with the government, he will cooperate with George Mitchell's investigation and give him the names of the players he sold steroids to.''</p>
        <p>''That's a big break for Mitchell,'' Selig replied. ''Now tell me the bad news.''</p>
        <p>''The feds in Frisco have nailed a former Mets clubhouse kid as a big-time steroids distributor to major league players, and as part of his plea agreement with the government, he will give George Mitchell the names of the players he sold steroids to.''</p>
        <p>The conversation never took place, but even fictionally it reflects the quandary facing Major League Baseball.</p>
        <p>The last thing Selig wants is a Kirk Radomski to come forward and name names of players past and present whom he supplied with steroids. Even if the names don't surface -- the government, it should be noted, has never disclosed or leaked any names in any investigation -- the stain is there, indelibly embedded in the game's fabric.</p>
        <p>In his consideration of Pete Rose's application for reinstatement from the permanently ineligible list, Selig has always had to be concerned about the possibility that as soon as he lifted the ban, a new development would come to light about Rose's baseball betting, embarrassing baseball all over again.</p>
        <p>With steroids, Selig might have hoped the incriminating evidence would end with Balco and Barry Bonds. That was bad enough because it focused on the man who will soon become the career home run leader. But in these matters, there is always a Kirk Radomski lurking in the weeds.</p>
        <p>Someone was quoted Friday as saying that after Balco, Radomski was the man to see about steroids and other performance-enhancing substances. But like the baseball cocaine cases in the 1980s, it is highly likely that other Kirk Radomskis are in other patches of weeds, and just when baseball would think it was safe to go outdoors again, another would pop up.</p>
        <p>Is there any reason to think a former clubhouse kid -- and baseball has plenty of clubhouse kids -- from another clubhouse didn't build himself a business of selling stuff to players?</p>
        <p>Give Radomski credit. He did it the American way. He worked in the Mets' clubhouse for a decade and made enough contacts that he could go into business for himself and use those contacts to create a potentially flourishing business. Stick with it long enough, and maybe the competition will encounter problems and go out of business.</p>
        <p>This is the entrepreneurial spirit. America was built on such things. Give the kid a pat on the back and send him on his way -- except don't stop at Go but go directly to jail. You don't get a get-out-jail-free card, but you do get a card that will let you out of jail earlier if you provide a list of your customers.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the steroids coin, the Mitchell investigation has its first big break. Mitchell and his people have been quiet about their efforts, but it is believed that they have had difficulty getting players to talk to them.</p>
        <p>It's understandable that players would be reluctant to talk to Mitchell. Even if a player never used a performance-enhancing substance, the Mitchell men would ask if he knew of any player who did. If the player did know of such players, he would be reluctant to name them.</p>
        <p>In getting names from Radomski, on the other hand, Mitchell isn't guaranteed anything. The Radomski list will give Mitchell leads, but why should those players talk to Mitchell? He can't force them to talk because he has no subpoena power, and they would only be putting themselves in jeopardy with the law.</p>
        <p>Yes, the feds have the names, but there's a difference between having names, and even checks, and a person's admission that he used. That's why the United States Attorney's office has not indicted Bonds and is still waiting for his former trainer to tell what he knows about Bonds's alleged use of steroids.</p>
        <p>Anything a player would tell Mitchell would subject him to a subpoena by the government. Players who tell Mitchell of their purchase and use of steroids would be incriminating themselves before the law.</p>
        <p>If the Radomski-named players refuse to talk, Mitchell could threaten to take the matter to a Congressional committee, which does have subpoena power. Then baseball's dirty laundry would be out in public for all to see. That's not what Selig wants, but it's what he could get.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
