<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Flavors of Argentina, From Tapas to Steaks</title>
    <meta content="29dineliLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29dineli.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/HUNTINGTON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cafe Buenos Aires (Huntington, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDF153EF93AA15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Flavors of Argentina, From Tapas to Steaks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Flavors of Argentina, From Tapas to Steaks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Cafe Buenos Aires in Huntington, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CAFE BUENOS AIRES blew into Huntington in February like a fresh breeze, announcing to all that this was not a typical Long Island restaurant. Diners could be seen ordering baked creamed corn as an appetizer or spreading chimichurri (the condiment of chopped parsley, garlic and olive oil) on slices of crusty bread. On occasion, tango dancers could be spotted dipping in one of the dining rooms, as the waiters gingerly sidestepped them.</p>
        <p>Cafe Buenos Aires is the longtime dream of Hugo Garcia, a native of Argentina and principal owner here. He is well known in Huntington, having worked as waiter, maître d' hôtel or manager at a number of nearby restaurants including Mac's Steak, Piccolo and Bistro Cassis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cafe Buenos Aires blew into Huntington in February like a fresh breeze, announcing to all that this was not a typical Long Island restaurant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CAFE BUENOS AIRES blew into Huntington in February like a fresh breeze, announcing to all that this was not a typical Long Island restaurant. Diners could be seen ordering baked creamed corn as an appetizer or spreading chimichurri (the condiment of chopped parsley, garlic and olive oil) on slices of crusty bread. On occasion, tango dancers could be spotted dipping in one of the dining rooms, as the waiters gingerly sidestepped them.</p>
        <p>Cafe Buenos Aires is the longtime dream of Hugo Garcia, a native of Argentina and principal owner here. He is well known in Huntington, having worked as waiter, maître d' hôtel or manager at a number of nearby restaurants including Mac's Steak, Piccolo and Bistro Cassis.</p>
        <p>This exciting new place is a family affair. Mr. Garcia's son is the assistant manager, his daughter a bartender. His wife, Romana, supplied some of the recipes and has been known to pop into the kitchen and help out making empanadas. Even distant relatives in Argentina have gotten into the act. One cousin painted one of the pictures of tango dancers on the walls, while another created the hand-tooled leather covers for the menus and wine lists.</p>
        <p>The friendly family and the spirited bar scene create a welcoming atmosphere. The carved wood bar, nearly a century old, is a beauty. Nearby is a line of tiny tables, perfect for those who want to sample tapas before or after the movies. (The theater is less than a block away.)</p>
        <p>The décor in the attractive dining rooms is a subtle tribute to Argentina, with wrought-iron lanterns and depictions of tango dancers.</p>
        <p>Some of the waiters are experienced servers whom I recognized from Bistro Cassis. All did a fine job explaining unfamiliar dishes. When we ordered short ribs one evening, our waiter warned us that the meat was grilled, not braised, so though it was flavorful, it was not tender.</p>
        <p>Patrons in the dining room may order starters from the separate tapas menu. They have to know to ask for that list, though; it doesn't arrive automatically. Good tapas choices included grilled chorizo, tasty meatballs, small brochettes of tender grilled meats atop a haystack of frizzled leeks and salt cod croquettes. The last were delicately flavored and greaselessly fried.</p>
        <p>Two of the best tapas were also listed among the appetizers on the regular menu: firm shrimp sautéed with plenty of garlic and wonderful empanadas, little turnovers filled with ground beef, chicken or creamed corn. All three were winners, but the corn was the favorite at our table. Another pleasing opener was the ramekin of baked creamed corn, though I would have preferred it as a side dish. Salad lovers should try the mixed salad, which contained hearts of palm, tomatoes, onions, apples, Roquefort cheese and pancetta, dressed in a smooth sherry vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>Argentines are passionate carnivores. (We have Argentine friends who serve steak as a side dish to their Thanksgiving turkey.) The steak to try at Cafe Buenos Aires is the New York strip: thick and juicy with a glaze of chimichurri sauce. The skirt steak was also flavor-packed but chewy. Its accompaniments of sliced red onions and pale, anemic tomatoes are best forgotten. The roasted pork tenderloin with caramelized bananas and the grilled lamb chops paired with a sweet potato cake are both highly recommended.</p>
        <p>Fish fared as well as the meats. We were impressed by the pan-seared striped bass with its crisp skin, served over creamy risotto, and by a perfectly cooked salmon special in a light mustard sauce. The delicate fillet of sole atop a tasty mélange of asparagus and onions, garnished with a few jumbo shrimp, was another delicious treat.</p>
        <p>All the desserts were satisfying. They ranged from the familiar (warm molten center chocolate cake) and the traditional (the silky flan) to the unusual: called meringue pie, it was a ball of crushed, crunchy meringue encasing whipped cream and fruit. Two other showstoppers were an apple crepe flamed at tableside and a bowl of airy dulce de leche mousse crowned with whipped cream.</p>
        <p>Cafe Buenos Aires</p>
        <p>23 Wall Street  Huntington  (631) 603-3600</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Attractive, multileveled Argentine restaurant. Not wheelchair accessible.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Noisy and fun-loving. Couples and small groups. Very few children.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- An antique, hand-carved beauty, the place for tapas. Reasonably priced list of 84 still wines ($22 to $165) weighted toward reds from Argentina. Also, 16 wines by the glass ($6 to $8).</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Lunch entrees, $7 (ham and cheese sandwich) to $25 (strip steak). Dinner entrees, $12 (chicken sandwich) to $27. American Express, MasterCard, Visa and Discover are accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Grilled chorizo, grilled meat brochettes, salt cod croquettes, meatballs, shrimp in garlic sauce, empanadas, creamed corn, mixed salad, strip steak, lamb chops, roast pork tenderloin, striped bass, fillet of sole with shrimp, salmon in mustard sauce, all desserts.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Lunch: 12 to 3 p.m. Monday to Saturday. Dinner: 5 to 10 p.m. Monday to Thursday, till 11 p.m. Friday and Saturday and 3 to 10 p.m. Sunday. Reservations accepted only for six or more.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 29, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/HUNTINGTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
