<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Orpheus Descending, Composer Remembering</title>
    <meta content="13mars" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/arts/music/13mars.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839865"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Orpheus Chamber Orchestra</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E2DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Orpheus Descending, Composer Remembering</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Orpheus Descending, Composer Remembering</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sentiment is not a quality often associated with concerts of new music. So a friend of mine was struck, after a performance of new work by the American Composers Orchestra some years ago, to find two industry insiders in the audience reduced to tears, simply because they found one of the pieces so beautiful. It was ''Kingdom Come,'' by Ingram Marshall.</p>
        <p>Plenty of people describe ''Kingdom Come'' in terms reserved for masterworks. Steve Reich, the composer, apostrophized it as ''some of the most beautiful music I've heard.'' Mark Swed, the music critic of The Los Angeles Times, called it ''downright addictive'' in a review of the CD (which came out in 2001), adding, ''Every time I hear it, I immediately want to start it over (and usually do).''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A musician’s musician offers a new piece for his famous fans at Carnegie Hall on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sentiment is not a quality often associated with concerts of new music. So a friend of mine was struck, after a performance of new work by the American Composers Orchestra some years ago, to find two industry insiders in the audience reduced to tears, simply because they found one of the pieces so beautiful. It was ''Kingdom Come,'' by Ingram Marshall.</p>
        <p>Plenty of people describe ''Kingdom Come'' in terms reserved for masterworks. Steve Reich, the composer, apostrophized it as ''some of the most beautiful music I've heard.'' Mark Swed, the music critic of The Los Angeles Times, called it ''downright addictive'' in a review of the CD (which came out in 2001), adding, ''Every time I hear it, I immediately want to start it over (and usually do).''</p>
        <p>In light of his rapturous reception -- which is by no means restricted to ''Kingdom Come'' -- it's odd that Mr. Marshall, at nearly 65, remains something of a musician's musician. He is wildly popular among those in the know, but without the immediate name-brand recognition of, say, his close friend and colleague John Adams.</p>
        <p>For those in the know, this weekend offers a treat: Mr. Marshall's new piece, ''Orphic Memories,'' written for the Orpheus Chamber Orchestra, which will play it at Carnegie Hall tomorrow night.</p>
        <p>Not that Mr. Marshall has been laboring in obscurity. He has been churning out a steady stream of works that have been performed and recorded in notable places: ''Hymnodic Delays,'' played in the early days of Zankel Hall; ''Dolce Far Niente,'' for the St. Louis Symphony; ''Fog Tropes II,'' for the Kronos Quartet. Most of his major works are available on CD from labels like Nonesuch.</p>
        <p>So why isn't he better known? Is it his relatively slow output? The fact that his work has a dark beauty, a kind of open simplicity, even spirituality? Or just that Mr. Marshall, a soft-spoken and gentle man born in Westchester County, spends more time writing music in his studio in Hamden, Conn., or in his cabin in the Sierras, than playing the game of composer hustle?</p>
        <p>''I wrote an article about this very issue about a year ago,'' Mr. Marshall said by phone from his home in Connecticut. The online music magazine New Music Box had asked him to write about the ''tipping point'' in a composer's career.</p>
        <p>''I realized I have been at many tipping points,'' Mr. Marshall said, ''when I thought something big was going to happen, and I would become as popular as Steve Reich overnight.''</p>
        <p>''You have to realize,'' he continued, that success ''is not what your work is about.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marshall's music is definitely about something. His pieces have evocative, gently poetic titles: ''Hidden Voices,'' ''Evensongs.'' Much of his work has an electronic element: pieces of tape are woven into the music, adding sound and significance. ''Fog Tropes'' began as a loop tape of foghorns in the San Francisco Bay, an atmospheric, gently keening sea chantey. ''Kingdom Come'' includes music he recorded in churches in Serbia and Croatia; the piece is a memorial to his brother-in-law, a journalist who was killed by a mine in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>In writing for Orpheus, the conductorless chamber ensemble, Mr. Marshall decided to tackle the Orpheus story.</p>
        <p>''No one's ever done an Orpheus piece for them,'' he said. ''My take is to do a narrative about Orpheus' descent into hell, but to imagine him remembering it in kind of a blurred way. This is a memory piece; to me, it's a personal piece, with a lot of musical memories and all their associations. Some of them are obvious; others are very intimate and personal.''</p>
        <p>The obvious ones include quotes from five composers: Arvo Pärt; Stravinsky (whose ballet ''Orpheus'' makes a fleeting appearance); Beethoven (the ''Heilige Dankgesang,'' the convalescent's hymn of thanks from the Opus 132 quartet); John Adams ('' 'Shaker Loops,' I ripped that off,'' Mr. Marshall said); and one of his favorite composers, Sibelius.</p>
        <p>''Sibelius always gets in,'' Mr. Marshall said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marshall has been called a postminimalist, a term he dislikes. He prefers the term postmodern, noting that although he has drawn on textures and techniques of composers like Mr. Reich, ''what was important was not the process as much as the expressive use of it.'' Some people, looking for a label for Mr. Marshall's music, have even called it romantic.</p>
        <p>Its quality of intimacy may be one reason the work connects with hearers so profoundly. Even the Orpheus musicians, who will have played ''Orphic Memories'' four times this week before the Carnegie performance, are responding.</p>
        <p>''I feel Ingram's music is speaking more to members of the group,'' said the clarinetist Alan R. Kay. ''Ingram's piece goes a little deeper. The piece is about memory, he calls it a memory trip. There are more levels that are more engaging to the group. There is more of a serious level of commitment.''</p>
        <p>Not that the new piece is all about sentiment. It also has some signal difficulties. Mr. Kay said that in some tricky passages, like the movement called ''Lost,'' the players have to conduct one another from their seats.</p>
        <p>''I don't mind if they get a little bit out of kilter,'' Mr. Marshall said, slightly mischievously. ''When I was writing the piece, I thought I might try to get them lost; they're so famous for playing without a conductor. I imagine Orpheus is remembering his trip to hell and back, getting lost. But I think it was stretching the metaphor a little bit too much.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
