<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: April 13 - April 19</title>
    <meta content="13spare" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2223" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: April 13 - April 19</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Around Town</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>HISTORIC RICHMOND TOWN Staten Island Historical Society, 441 Clarke Avenue, Richmond Town. More than 25 buildings, from the late 17th to the 19th centuries, restored and furnished. Tavern Concert Series: tomorrow at 7:30 and 9 p.m., Point Cross; $15, members $12; requires reservation. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. $5; $4 for 62+; $3.50 for students and 5 to 17; free for children under 5 and members. (718) 351-1611.</p>
        <p>MERCHANT'S HOUSE MUSEUM, 29 East Fourth Street, East Village. Through Sunday, ''Don't Be Fooled: A Mid-19th-Century Mix-Up,'' a scavenger hunt for visitors to identify items from different time periods intermingled with the museum's regular furnishings. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, noon to 5 p.m. $8, $5 for students and 65+, free for members and under 12. (212) 777-1089.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. Tomorrow from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., ''Home Design in New York,'' discussions by top designers, architects and writers about interior design in private homes in the city; buffet lunch included; $30, $25 for members; reservations required. Tuesday night at 6:30, ''Art Moderne to American Modern: The Legacy of the American Designers' Gallery,'' a lecture by Marilyn Friedman, author of ''Selling Good Design: Promoting the Early Modern Interior''; $9, $5 for members and students. Wednesday night at 6:30, ''New Yorkers Remember the Spanish Civil War,'' a discussion with veterans of the Lincoln Brigade and a video presentation; $9 and $5. Through May 28, ''Robert Moses and the Modern City: Remaking the Metropolis,'' one of three exhibitions dedicated to Moses at cultural institutions in the city; the others are at the Queens Museum of Art and the Wallach Art Gallery at Columbia University. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $9; $5 for students and 62+; free for children under 12; $20 for families; free on Sundays, 10 a.m. to noon. (212) 534-1672, mcny.org.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens. Through Sunday, ''Star Trek: 40 Years of Fandom,'' an exhibition of figures, games, comic books and magazines, and fan-produced films. Wednesdays and Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, noon to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6:30 p.m.; and by appointment. Films and videos, unless noted, are free with admission: $10; ages 65+ and students, $7.50; 5 to 18, $5; free for members and children 4 and younger; free for everyone on Fridays from 4 to 8 p.m. (but with admission required for Friday night screenings). (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL MUSEUM OF THE AMERICAN INDIAN, United States Custom House, 1 Bowling Green, Lower Manhattan. Today at noon, a talk with the artist Larry McNeil. Tomorrow at noon, readings from North American Indian stories. Through Sept. 3, ''Off the Map: Landscape in the Native Imagination,'' an exhibition of paintings, drawings, sculpture and installations devoted to the representation of landscape. Through May, ''Born of Clay: Ceramics From the National Museum of the American Indian.'' Daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays to 8 p.m.; free. (212) 514-3700, www.nmai.si.edu.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN, 1000 Washington Avenue, Prospect Heights. Through May 6, ''Hana to Mushi -- Flowers and Insects,'' with artwork by April Vollmer and Kako Ueda. Tomorrow and Sunday at 1 p.m., Seasonal Highlights Tours. Tuesdays through Fridays, 8 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. $5; $3 for students and 65+; free for under 16. Free admission all day Tuesdays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to noon. (718) 623-7200; bbg.org.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN, Southern Boulevard and 200th Street, Bedford Park, the Bronx. Today from 10 a.m. to 3:30 p.m., second annual Green Roof Conference, with lectures and workshops about roof gardens conducted by architects, builders and members of community organizations. Full day admission $75, members $68; morning session, $45 and $41; (718) 817-8747. Tomorrow and Sunday at 1:30 p.m., ''Daffodil Delight: Adding Color to Your Home in Spring,'' a gardening demonstration. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Parking, $10. $18; students and 62+, $16; children under 13, $5. Garden grounds admission: $6; $3 for 62+; $2 for students; $1 for children 2 to 12; free for children under 2. Combination ticket, including all admissions and a tram tour: $13; $11 for students and 62+; $5 for children 2 to 12; free for children under 2. Tram tours daily, every 20 minutes. Conservatory admission: $5; $4 for students and 62+; $3 for children 2 to 12; free for children under 2. Grounds admission free on Wednesdays and 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. (718) 817-8700; nybg.org.</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL, Independence Avenue and West 249th Street, Riverdale, the Bronx. The 28-acre site includes gardens, greenhouses and woodlands. Tomorrow at 1 p.m., Woodland community volunteering, information and directions, (718) 549-3200, Ext. 221; at 2 p.m., a workshop on garden tool maintenance, at the Wave Hill House. Tomorrow and Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Daffy for Daffodils,'' an art project. Through May 25, ''Emily Dickinson Rendered,'' an exhibition of contemporary artwork inspired by Dickinson's writing. Sunday at 1 p.m., exhibition reception at the Glyndor Gallery. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. $4; $2 for students and 65+; free for children under 6 at all times and for everyone all day Tuesdays and 9 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>'Design Made in Africa,' Courtyard Gallery, World Financial Center, West Street, south of Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan. A traveling exhibition of 30 designers from 14 African countries. Through June 24. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 6 p.m., Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. (212) 945-0505.</p>
        <p>WEST FOURTH STREET FESTIVAL, from Washington Square East to Lafayette Street, West Village. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>17TH UPPER BROADWAY SPRING CELEBRATION, Broadway between 110th and 118th Streets, Morningside Heights. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Broadway Mall Association. (212) 764-6330.</p>
        <p>GREEK INDEPENDENCE DAY PARADE, Fifth Avenue, from 61st to 79th Streets, Manhattan. Sunday at 1:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>UNION SQUARE COMMUNITY COALITION FESTIVAL, Broadway, from 17th to 23rd Streets. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>MUSIC OFF THE SHELVES, the last two free concerts by the Brooklyn Philharmonic at Brooklyn libraries. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m. at the Brooklyn Heights Branch, 280 Cadman Plaza West, at Tillary Street; at 4 p.m. at the Central Branch, Grand Army Plaza.</p>
        <p>27TH NEW YORK INTERNATIONAL ORCHID SHOW, Rockefeller Center, 30 Rockefeller Plaza. Wednesday through April 22, a display of more than 50,000 orchids, with workshops, tours and lectures, co-sponsored by the Greater New York Orchid Society. $5, free for children under 12. Hours and other information, (212) 332-6553; rockefellercenter.com; or gnyos.org.</p>
        <p>MULTICULTURAL CELEBRATION, Grand Street Settlement, 80 Pitt Street, Lower East Side. Wednesday, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m., a celebration of Immigrant History Week, with displays, music, dancing and food. Free. (212) 674-1740, Ext. 481.</p>
        <p>'Japan100: Celebrating a Century,' Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30 p.m., ''Curlew River,'' an opera composed by Benjamin Britten and based on the play ''Sumidagawa.'' $52, members $45. (212) 832-1155; japansociety.org.</p>
        <p>The eighth annual havana film festival in new york Locations throughout the city. Through Thursday. Screenings of Spanish-language films, including children's films, as well as panel discussions, special programs and musical events. Schedule and locations: hffny.com.</p>
        <p>Humane Society of New York's SECOnd Annual Fine ARt Photography Auction, Monday at 7 p.m., Baryshnikov Arts Center, 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan. humanesocietyny.org.</p>
        <p>WATSON ADVENTURES Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''The Gangsters' New York Scavenger Hunt,'' exploring the haunts of some of New York's most nefarious characters, $24. Meeting place and reservations: (877) 946-4868.</p>
        <p>CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK GRADUATE CENTER, 365 Fifth Avenue, at 34th Street. Today at 4 p.m., a talk with Timothy J. Gilfoyle, author of ''A Pickpocket's Tale: The Underworld of Nineteenth-Century New York''; (212) 817-2005. Monday night at 6:30, an evening of puppet theater with Great Small Works, a New York company, and Teatro Tinglado, from Mexico; (212) 817-1861. Both events are free.</p>
        <p>92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue. Tomorrow 4 p.m., ''Opera and Anti-Semitism in 19th-Century France: Meyerbeer, 'La Prophète' and Richard Wagner,'' a lecture by Joelle Wallach, a composer, $35. Sunday at 11 a.m., ''Synagogues of Greece and Eastern Europe,'' a walking tour of the Lower East Side; $25. Sunday at 7:30 p.m., ''For Those I Loved: An Evening With Holocaust Survivor Martin Gray and the Young People's Chorus,'' in observance of Holocaust Remembrance Day, free. (212) 415-5500.</p>
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHS OF THE LOWER EAST SIDE, 1937-2007 Educational Alliance, 197 East Broadway, between Jefferson and Clinton Streets, Lower East Side. Through Thursday, a display featuring works by members of the art school and the young artists' program. Fridays through Sundays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Mondays through Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. (212) 780-2300.</p>
        <p>Walking Tours</p>
        <p>SHOREWALKERS Tomorrow at 10 a.m., ''Walk off the Lamb,'' a post-Easter walk along the Harlem and East Rivers, meeting at the entrance to Inwood Park, Seaman Avenue and Isham Streets. Bring lunch, water and a MetroCard. $3. (718) 398-3561.</p>
        <p>DR. PHIL: NEW YORK WALKS AND TALKS Sunday at 1:30 p.m., ''Ghosts of Greenwich Village,'' meeting at the southwest corner of Fifth Avenue and 10th Street. $15. (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN CENTER FOR THE URBAN ENVIRONMENT Tomorrow at 11 a.m., ''Mansions of Clinton Hill,'' meeting in Brooklyn at the corner of Clinton and Gates Avenues; Sunday at 1 p.m., ''A Meet-and-Greet Tour of Fort Greene,'' meeting in front of Cuyler Gore Park at Fulton Street and Greene Avenue. Each, $13; members, $10; 62+ and students, $8. (718) 788-8500, Ext. 208.</p>
        <p>IN-DEPTH WALKING TOURS Sunday at 10 a.m., ''Down With King George!'' explores New York's Revolutionary War history, meeting at the steps of the Museum of the American Indian, 1 Bowling Green, Lower Manhattan, $20. (917) 607-9019; indepthwalkingtours.com.</p>
        <p>NOSHWALKS Tomorrow at 2:30 p.m., exploring the diverse culinary tastes of Woodside, Queens, meeting at Vincent Daniels Square, 52nd Street and Roosevelt Avenue; $33, including food. (212) 222-2243; noshwalks.com.</p>
        <p>ADVENTURE ON A SHOESTRING Tomorrow at 4 p.m., ''Splendid Grand Central Terminal,'' meeting at the northeast corner of 42nd Street and Lexington Avenue. $5. (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>GARGOYLES IN MANHATTAN WALKING TOUR Sunday at 2 p.m., meeting in front of 51 Madison Avenue, between 26th and 27th Streets. $15. Sponsored by New York City Cultural Walking Tours. (212) 979-2388; nycwalk.com.</p>
        <p>east village WALKING TOUR, tonight at 6, explores bohemian lifestyles with visits to tattoo parlors and piercing shops. For ages 21+. Meets at the black cube at Astor Place, East Village. Sponsored by Mike's NYC Tours. $15. (212) 370-4214; mikesnyctours.com.</p>
        <p>I'LL TAKE MANHATTAN TOURS Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''Grandeur and Elegance, Carnegie Hall'' explores sites associated with some of New York's most famous families, meeting at the southwest corner of Fifth Avenue and 79th Street; $15. (732) 270-5277.</p>
        <p>STREET SMARTS N.Y.  Tomorrow: at 2 p.m., ''Stanford White -- Splendor and Scandal'' visits buildings designed by the architect; at 6 p.m., ''Ghostly Greenwich Village.'' Both meet at the Washington Arch in Washington Square Park. Each, $10. (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Jazz Age Towers of Midtown,'' focuses on some of Manhattan's admired buildings, meeting on the southwest corner of Lexington Avenue and 43rd Street; $15, for members $12; (212) 439-1049; mas.org.</p>
        <p>JOYCE GOLD HISTORY TOURS OF NEW YORK Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Wall Street: A Colonial Melting Pot With Hearty Dutch Influence,'' meeting at Trinity Church, Broadway and Wall Street, Lower Manhattan. $15; $12 for 65+. (212) 242-5762.</p>
        <p>'The Old and The New,' explores Astor Place and the East Village, meeting on the southeast corner of East 11th Street and Second Avenue. Sponsored by Bernie's New York; $10. (718) 655-1883.</p>
        <p>WALKABOUT NEW YORK Sunday at 1 p.m., a tour of the Upper East Side, meeting in front of the Pulitzer Memorial Fountain at Grand Army Plaza, Fifth Avenue and 59th Street; $15. (347) 463-2864.</p>
        <p>BOWERY AND CANaL WALKING TOURS Sunday at 1 p.m., ''New York in the Civil War,'' meeting in front of the Seward statue on East 23rd Street and Broadway; $12, students and 65+, $10. (917) 602-3543.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY Free weekend tours of Central Park. Tomorrow at 10 a.m. and Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Views From the Past,'' meeting at the Dairy, midpark at 65th Street. Sunday at 11 a.m., ''Seneca Village'' covers one of the earliest communities of black American property owners, meeting at the southeast corner of Central Park West and 85th Street. centralparknyc.org.</p>
        <p>METRO TOUR SERVICE Today through Sunday at 2 p.m., Brooklyn Heights, Fort Greene and Clinton Hill, Brooklyn, meeting in front of the Marriott Hotel, Adams and Tillary Streets, downtown Brooklyn. $25. (718) 789-0430.</p>
        <p>Recreation</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ROAD RUNNERS CLUB Tomorrow at 8 a.m., the third race in the Half-Marathon Grand Prix, starting in Brooklyn at the Coney Island boardwalk and ending in Prospect Park. Advance fee $30, $20 for members, $14 for members 18 and younger and 62+; race-day, $35, $25 and $15. (212) 860-4455; nyrrc.org.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Around Town</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>HISTORIC RICHMOND TOWN Staten Island Historical Society, 441 Clarke Avenue, Richmond Town. More than 25 buildings, from the late 17th to the 19th centuries, restored and furnished. Tavern Concert Series: tomorrow at 7:30 and 9 p.m., Point Cross; $15, members $12; requires reservation. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. $5; $4 for 62+; $3.50 for students and 5 to 17; free for children under 5 and members. (718) 351-1611.</p>
        <p>MERCHANT'S HOUSE MUSEUM, 29 East Fourth Street, East Village. Through Sunday, ''Don't Be Fooled: A Mid-19th-Century Mix-Up,'' a scavenger hunt for visitors to identify items from different time periods intermingled with the museum's regular furnishings. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, noon to 5 p.m. $8, $5 for students and 65+, free for members and under 12. (212) 777-1089.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. Tomorrow from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., ''Home Design in New York,'' discussions by top designers, architects and writers about interior design in private homes in the city; buffet lunch included; $30, $25 for members; reservations required. Tuesday night at 6:30, ''Art Moderne to American Modern: The Legacy of the American Designers' Gallery,'' a lecture by Marilyn Friedman, author of ''Selling Good Design: Promoting the Early Modern Interior''; $9, $5 for members and students. Wednesday night at 6:30, ''New Yorkers Remember the Spanish Civil War,'' a discussion with veterans of the Lincoln Brigade and a video presentation; $9 and $5. Through May 28, ''Robert Moses and the Modern City: Remaking the Metropolis,'' one of three exhibitions dedicated to Moses at cultural institutions in the city; the others are at the Queens Museum of Art and the Wallach Art Gallery at Columbia University. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $9; $5 for students and 62+; free for children under 12; $20 for families; free on Sundays, 10 a.m. to noon. (212) 534-1672, mcny.org.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens. Through Sunday, ''Star Trek: 40 Years of Fandom,'' an exhibition of figures, games, comic books and magazines, and fan-produced films. Wednesdays and Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, noon to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6:30 p.m.; and by appointment. Films and videos, unless noted, are free with admission: $10; ages 65+ and students, $7.50; 5 to 18, $5; free for members and children 4 and younger; free for everyone on Fridays from 4 to 8 p.m. (but with admission required for Friday night screenings). (718) 784-0077, movingimage.us.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL MUSEUM OF THE AMERICAN INDIAN, United States Custom House, 1 Bowling Green, Lower Manhattan. Today at noon, a talk with the artist Larry McNeil. Tomorrow at noon, readings from North American Indian stories. Through Sept. 3, ''Off the Map: Landscape in the Native Imagination,'' an exhibition of paintings, drawings, sculpture and installations devoted to the representation of landscape. Through May, ''Born of Clay: Ceramics From the National Museum of the American Indian.'' Daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays to 8 p.m.; free. (212) 514-3700, www.nmai.si.edu.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN, 1000 Washington Avenue, Prospect Heights. Through May 6, ''Hana to Mushi -- Flowers and Insects,'' with artwork by April Vollmer and Kako Ueda. Tomorrow and Sunday at 1 p.m., Seasonal Highlights Tours. Tuesdays through Fridays, 8 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. $5; $3 for students and 65+; free for under 16. Free admission all day Tuesdays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to noon. (718) 623-7200; bbg.org.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN, Southern Boulevard and 200th Street, Bedford Park, the Bronx. Today from 10 a.m. to 3:30 p.m., second annual Green Roof Conference, with lectures and workshops about roof gardens conducted by architects, builders and members of community organizations. Full day admission $75, members $68; morning session, $45 and $41; (718) 817-8747. Tomorrow and Sunday at 1:30 p.m., ''Daffodil Delight: Adding Color to Your Home in Spring,'' a gardening demonstration. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Parking, $10. $18; students and 62+, $16; children under 13, $5. Garden grounds admission: $6; $3 for 62+; $2 for students; $1 for children 2 to 12; free for children under 2. Combination ticket, including all admissions and a tram tour: $13; $11 for students and 62+; $5 for children 2 to 12; free for children under 2. Tram tours daily, every 20 minutes. Conservatory admission: $5; $4 for students and 62+; $3 for children 2 to 12; free for children under 2. Grounds admission free on Wednesdays and 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. (718) 817-8700; nybg.org.</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL, Independence Avenue and West 249th Street, Riverdale, the Bronx. The 28-acre site includes gardens, greenhouses and woodlands. Tomorrow at 1 p.m., Woodland community volunteering, information and directions, (718) 549-3200, Ext. 221; at 2 p.m., a workshop on garden tool maintenance, at the Wave Hill House. Tomorrow and Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Daffy for Daffodils,'' an art project. Through May 25, ''Emily Dickinson Rendered,'' an exhibition of contemporary artwork inspired by Dickinson's writing. Sunday at 1 p.m., exhibition reception at the Glyndor Gallery. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. $4; $2 for students and 65+; free for children under 6 at all times and for everyone all day Tuesdays and 9 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>'Design Made in Africa,' Courtyard Gallery, World Financial Center, West Street, south of Vesey Street, Lower Manhattan. A traveling exhibition of 30 designers from 14 African countries. Through June 24. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 6 p.m., Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. (212) 945-0505.</p>
        <p>WEST FOURTH STREET FESTIVAL, from Washington Square East to Lafayette Street, West Village. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>17TH UPPER BROADWAY SPRING CELEBRATION, Broadway between 110th and 118th Streets, Morningside Heights. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Broadway Mall Association. (212) 764-6330.</p>
        <p>GREEK INDEPENDENCE DAY PARADE, Fifth Avenue, from 61st to 79th Streets, Manhattan. Sunday at 1:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>UNION SQUARE COMMUNITY COALITION FESTIVAL, Broadway, from 17th to 23rd Streets. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>MUSIC OFF THE SHELVES, the last two free concerts by the Brooklyn Philharmonic at Brooklyn libraries. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m. at the Brooklyn Heights Branch, 280 Cadman Plaza West, at Tillary Street; at 4 p.m. at the Central Branch, Grand Army Plaza.</p>
        <p>27TH NEW YORK INTERNATIONAL ORCHID SHOW, Rockefeller Center, 30 Rockefeller Plaza. Wednesday through April 22, a display of more than 50,000 orchids, with workshops, tours and lectures, co-sponsored by the Greater New York Orchid Society. $5, free for children under 12. Hours and other information, (212) 332-6553; rockefellercenter.com; or gnyos.org.</p>
        <p>MULTICULTURAL CELEBRATION, Grand Street Settlement, 80 Pitt Street, Lower East Side. Wednesday, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m., a celebration of Immigrant History Week, with displays, music, dancing and food. Free. (212) 674-1740, Ext. 481.</p>
        <p>'Japan100: Celebrating a Century,' Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30 p.m., ''Curlew River,'' an opera composed by Benjamin Britten and based on the play ''Sumidagawa.'' $52, members $45. (212) 832-1155; japansociety.org.</p>
        <p>The eighth annual havana film festival in new york Locations throughout the city. Through Thursday. Screenings of Spanish-language films, including children's films, as well as panel discussions, special programs and musical events. Schedule and locations: hffny.com.</p>
        <p>Humane Society of New York's SECOnd Annual Fine ARt Photography Auction, Monday at 7 p.m., Baryshnikov Arts Center, 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan. humanesocietyny.org.</p>
        <p>WATSON ADVENTURES Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''The Gangsters' New York Scavenger Hunt,'' exploring the haunts of some of New York's most nefarious characters, $24. Meeting place and reservations: (877) 946-4868.</p>
        <p>CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK GRADUATE CENTER, 365 Fifth Avenue, at 34th Street. Today at 4 p.m., a talk with Timothy J. Gilfoyle, author of ''A Pickpocket's Tale: The Underworld of Nineteenth-Century New York''; (212) 817-2005. Monday night at 6:30, an evening of puppet theater with Great Small Works, a New York company, and Teatro Tinglado, from Mexico; (212) 817-1861. Both events are free.</p>
        <p>92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue. Tomorrow 4 p.m., ''Opera and Anti-Semitism in 19th-Century France: Meyerbeer, 'La Prophète' and Richard Wagner,'' a lecture by Joelle Wallach, a composer, $35. Sunday at 11 a.m., ''Synagogues of Greece and Eastern Europe,'' a walking tour of the Lower East Side; $25. Sunday at 7:30 p.m., ''For Those I Loved: An Evening With Holocaust Survivor Martin Gray and the Young People's Chorus,'' in observance of Holocaust Remembrance Day, free. (212) 415-5500.</p>
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHS OF THE LOWER EAST SIDE, 1937-2007 Educational Alliance, 197 East Broadway, between Jefferson and Clinton Streets, Lower East Side. Through Thursday, a display featuring works by members of the art school and the young artists' program. Fridays through Sundays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Mondays through Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. (212) 780-2300.</p>
        <p>Walking Tours</p>
        <p>SHOREWALKERS Tomorrow at 10 a.m., ''Walk off the Lamb,'' a post-Easter walk along the Harlem and East Rivers, meeting at the entrance to Inwood Park, Seaman Avenue and Isham Streets. Bring lunch, water and a MetroCard. $3. (718) 398-3561.</p>
        <p>DR. PHIL: NEW YORK WALKS AND TALKS Sunday at 1:30 p.m., ''Ghosts of Greenwich Village,'' meeting at the southwest corner of Fifth Avenue and 10th Street. $15. (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN CENTER FOR THE URBAN ENVIRONMENT Tomorrow at 11 a.m., ''Mansions of Clinton Hill,'' meeting in Brooklyn at the corner of Clinton and Gates Avenues; Sunday at 1 p.m., ''A Meet-and-Greet Tour of Fort Greene,'' meeting in front of Cuyler Gore Park at Fulton Street and Greene Avenue. Each, $13; members, $10; 62+ and students, $8. (718) 788-8500, Ext. 208.</p>
        <p>IN-DEPTH WALKING TOURS Sunday at 10 a.m., ''Down With King George!'' explores New York's Revolutionary War history, meeting at the steps of the Museum of the American Indian, 1 Bowling Green, Lower Manhattan, $20. (917) 607-9019; indepthwalkingtours.com.</p>
        <p>NOSHWALKS Tomorrow at 2:30 p.m., exploring the diverse culinary tastes of Woodside, Queens, meeting at Vincent Daniels Square, 52nd Street and Roosevelt Avenue; $33, including food. (212) 222-2243; noshwalks.com.</p>
        <p>ADVENTURE ON A SHOESTRING Tomorrow at 4 p.m., ''Splendid Grand Central Terminal,'' meeting at the northeast corner of 42nd Street and Lexington Avenue. $5. (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>GARGOYLES IN MANHATTAN WALKING TOUR Sunday at 2 p.m., meeting in front of 51 Madison Avenue, between 26th and 27th Streets. $15. Sponsored by New York City Cultural Walking Tours. (212) 979-2388; nycwalk.com.</p>
        <p>east village WALKING TOUR, tonight at 6, explores bohemian lifestyles with visits to tattoo parlors and piercing shops. For ages 21+. Meets at the black cube at Astor Place, East Village. Sponsored by Mike's NYC Tours. $15. (212) 370-4214; mikesnyctours.com.</p>
        <p>I'LL TAKE MANHATTAN TOURS Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''Grandeur and Elegance, Carnegie Hall'' explores sites associated with some of New York's most famous families, meeting at the southwest corner of Fifth Avenue and 79th Street; $15. (732) 270-5277.</p>
        <p>STREET SMARTS N.Y.  Tomorrow: at 2 p.m., ''Stanford White -- Splendor and Scandal'' visits buildings designed by the architect; at 6 p.m., ''Ghostly Greenwich Village.'' Both meet at the Washington Arch in Washington Square Park. Each, $10. (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Jazz Age Towers of Midtown,'' focuses on some of Manhattan's admired buildings, meeting on the southwest corner of Lexington Avenue and 43rd Street; $15, for members $12; (212) 439-1049; mas.org.</p>
        <p>JOYCE GOLD HISTORY TOURS OF NEW YORK Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Wall Street: A Colonial Melting Pot With Hearty Dutch Influence,'' meeting at Trinity Church, Broadway and Wall Street, Lower Manhattan. $15; $12 for 65+. (212) 242-5762.</p>
        <p>'The Old and The New,' explores Astor Place and the East Village, meeting on the southeast corner of East 11th Street and Second Avenue. Sponsored by Bernie's New York; $10. (718) 655-1883.</p>
        <p>WALKABOUT NEW YORK Sunday at 1 p.m., a tour of the Upper East Side, meeting in front of the Pulitzer Memorial Fountain at Grand Army Plaza, Fifth Avenue and 59th Street; $15. (347) 463-2864.</p>
        <p>BOWERY AND CANaL WALKING TOURS Sunday at 1 p.m., ''New York in the Civil War,'' meeting in front of the Seward statue on East 23rd Street and Broadway; $12, students and 65+, $10. (917) 602-3543.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY Free weekend tours of Central Park. Tomorrow at 10 a.m. and Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Views From the Past,'' meeting at the Dairy, midpark at 65th Street. Sunday at 11 a.m., ''Seneca Village'' covers one of the earliest communities of black American property owners, meeting at the southeast corner of Central Park West and 85th Street. centralparknyc.org.</p>
        <p>METRO TOUR SERVICE Today through Sunday at 2 p.m., Brooklyn Heights, Fort Greene and Clinton Hill, Brooklyn, meeting in front of the Marriott Hotel, Adams and Tillary Streets, downtown Brooklyn. $25. (718) 789-0430.</p>
        <p>Recreation</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ROAD RUNNERS CLUB Tomorrow at 8 a.m., the third race in the Half-Marathon Grand Prix, starting in Brooklyn at the Coney Island boardwalk and ending in Prospect Park. Advance fee $30, $20 for members, $14 for members 18 and younger and 62+; race-day, $35, $25 and $15. (212) 860-4455; nyrrc.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
