<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Space Redefined in Chelsea</title>
    <meta content="13chel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/arts/design/13chel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chelsea (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Dia Art Foundation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">PaceWildenstein</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Academy Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EFDE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Space Redefined in Chelsea</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Space Redefined in Chelsea</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In art, space is a frontier, but there is nothing final about it. It is a complicated, layered place that artists continually explore, manipulate and expand, transforming our understanding of it and of art's potential too. And the best place to experience recent activity on this frontier is the space walk that is west Chelsea.</p>
        <p>In a sense art has been a space race at least since the onset of Cubism, which shattered the calm of one-point perspective and, with collage, punctured the barrier between art and reality. Art's spaces really started multiplying in the 1960s, with the successive splinterings of Fluxus, Happenings, Pop, Minimalism, Arte Povera and Neo-Concrete and the Post-Minimalist flotilla of Conceptual Art, performance, earthworks, installation art and video. Today in art there are so many permutations and gradations of space that there could be dozens of names for them. Instead we have adjectives. Space can be pictorial, mystical, fictive, real, social, geographical, male, female, architectural, fragmented, whole, distorted, compressed and mental. Space also has become an essential commodity for making and selling art, for which we do have a name: real estate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A sampling of current shows in Chelsea’s big-box galleries offers a map to some of the ways artists use space in, and also around, art these days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In art, space is a frontier, but there is nothing final about it. It is a complicated, layered place that artists continually explore, manipulate and expand, transforming our understanding of it and of art's potential too. And the best place to experience recent activity on this frontier is the space walk that is west Chelsea.</p>
        <p>In a sense art has been a space race at least since the onset of Cubism, which shattered the calm of one-point perspective and, with collage, punctured the barrier between art and reality. Art's spaces really started multiplying in the 1960s, with the successive splinterings of Fluxus, Happenings, Pop, Minimalism, Arte Povera and Neo-Concrete and the Post-Minimalist flotilla of Conceptual Art, performance, earthworks, installation art and video. Today in art there are so many permutations and gradations of space that there could be dozens of names for them. Instead we have adjectives. Space can be pictorial, mystical, fictive, real, social, geographical, male, female, architectural, fragmented, whole, distorted, compressed and mental. Space also has become an essential commodity for making and selling art, for which we do have a name: real estate.</p>
        <p>It all comes together in Chelsea, epicenter of the big-box art gallery. A sampling of current shows in galleries whose square footage and multiple addresses can be spatial to the point of palatial offers a map to some of the ways artists use space in, and also around, art these days.</p>
        <p>Messy</p>
        <p>Clustered in lower Chelsea, three shows with large works from different decades by four artists convey the lay of the artistic territory. Convivial, participatory messiness -- with origins in 112 Greene Street, a vast, scruffy artist-run space that flourished in SoHo in the early 1970s -- is wonderfully prominent in a pair of historic re-creations in the roughest of David Zwirner's three adjacent galleries on West 19th Street. (The other two are more representative of the hyperimmaculate big box, as enshrined by the Dia Art Foundation, which took shape in SoHo in 1974, then moved to Chelsea before decamping to Beacon, N.Y., in 2003.)</p>
        <p>At Zwirner, to one side of a double garage whose doors are usually raised, is ''Open House,'' a piece that Gordon Matta-Clark orchestrated 35 years ago in front of 112 Greene Street, which he helped found. Walk through the narrow corridors of this replica made mostly of old doors, and maybe add to the graffiti. (Spray paint is provided.) The space is socially charged and liberating: it could be a prototype for cheap (extremely cheap) housing, a shooting gallery or a teenage hangout.</p>
        <p>Next to it looms ''Untitled 1992 (Free),'' or installation-art-as-cooking-spree that the artist Rirkrit Tiravanija, with Matta-Clark in mind, unleashed in 1992 at the 303 Gallery, then on Greene Street. In ''Free'' you can steam your sinuses with a slightly exotic version of the free lunch: some Thai curry on rice. Serve yourself, and settle in at the rickety folding tables and stools, in an actual-scale plywood replica of the original 303 space. Some reciprocal historical validation is at work here, but the works' shared concept of art as social space feels as fresh as the day after tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Clean</p>
        <p>The hyperclean Dia style, evident in all large Chelsea galleries, is in full cry around the corner at the new Gagosian space on West 21st Street. On view is a beautiful if icy installation piece from 1984 by Walter De Maria, arguably the first Dia art star and one of the main beneficiaries of its artwork-as-pilgrimage philosophy. (Dia built and still maintains his ''New York Earth Room'' and ''Broken Kilometer'' installations in SoHo, as well as his ''Lightning Field'' in New Mexico.)</p>
        <p>Mr. De Maria's weakness for highly polished metals can cause ambivalence, especially when they are seen without the contrasting harshness of the New Mexican desert. At Gagosian, ''A Computer Which Will Solve Every Problem in the World/3-12 Polygon'' has a pricey-looking lunar stillness. It consists of 75 solid meter-long stainless steel rods, laid out in 10 widely spaced diagonal rows, and seems to levitate slightly above the polished concrete floor. It has an uncharacteristic clarity. The three rods in the first row are three-sided; the four in the second are four-sided; the five after that are five-sided, and so on, to 12. It's simple geometry with money. No one owns the triangles, squares or pentagons, but Mel Bochner's use of these shapes in the early 1970s, without money, is germane.</p>
        <p>A similar but more obscure piece by Mr. De Maria, from 1985, is at Gagosian's 24th Street flagship, where its perfection brings out the older space's mild wear and tear. Real estate can be cruel.</p>
        <p>Full</p>
        <p>Nearby, at Yvon Lambert New York's new space, on West 21st Street, the veteran performance-installation artist Joan Jonas fills the gallery space, but in a porous, semi-transparent way, with a space-multiplying, walk-in-collage of sculpture, objects and six video projections. Called ''The Shape, the Scent, the Feel of Things,'' it combines a Fluxus playfulness with the task-oriented gestures of early '70s dance to achieve a mysterious visual poetry reminiscent of Joseph Cornell, decanted. The piece developed first as an astounding work of performance art commissioned by Dia. Resonantly site-specific, it unfolded grandly, surreally, in Dia:Beacon's huge empty basement, making excellent use of tall cement columns that suggest a monumental forest.</p>
        <p>Based on a poignant, searching memoir that the German art historian Aby Warburg wrote while recovering from a nervous breakdown, ''The Shape'' is a meditation on memory and civilization. At Dia it was also a kind of spoken opera with musical accompaniment composed and played by the jazz pianist Jason Moran. Warburg was brilliantly portrayed by José Luis Blondet, a former actor who is Dia's director of education. Backed, and often interacting with, a large video projection and assisted by the performance artist Ragani Haas, Ms. Jonas moved about, functioning as spirit guide, narrator, artist in residence, stagehand and no-tech sound technician, often creating a great percussive racket.</p>
        <p>A film of the Dia performance plays in a room next to the installation, providing its soundtrack and allowing visitors to move between the two, seeing various objects on view in action and watching the spaces multiply on screen to include additional outdoor performances in Nova Scotia. At the Yvon Lambert flagship space on 25th Street, you can see two more recent intimate video pieces that confirm Ms. Jonas's quiet, offhand charisma, and her status as a national treasure.</p>
        <p>Fuller</p>
        <p>There is a long tradition of filling galleries to overflowing with one thing or another. Sometimes the point is mockery of the big box's commercial, product-pushing side; sometimes it is glorification of a volume that we usually just take for granted. Sometimes it is a little of both. The permutations can be crazily polymorphous, like ''Hole,'' Christoph Büchel's immense installation of abandoned structures and vehicles that Hauser &amp; Wirth opened in London last fall, or they can be crazily pure and single-minded, like Orly Genger's must-see if familiar show at the Larissa Goldston Gallery.</p>
        <p>Most of Ms. Genger's previous efforts have been knitted wool and manageable. But with ''Masspeak,'' she has used a knot of her own devising to wrestle hundreds of lengths of nylon climbing rope (about 250,000 feet in all) into three tons of, basically, gigantic dishcloths and piled them around the gallery. The result is at once dour and hilarious, like a playground designed by a Welsh miner. It might also be considered a feminist response to the De Maria ''Earth Room'' that is generously available for a little climbing.</p>
        <p>But sometimes the emphasis on art as product seems unintentionally self-denigrating , as in James Turrell's overfull exhibition at PaceWildenstein. Here the walls are lined with paintinglike clouds of color (actually computerized neon) that slowly change from hazy blues to greens, or from oranges to magentas. Side galleries contain a series of smaller, even hokier holographic pieces that suggest three-dimensional Malevich paintings.</p>
        <p>It is understandable if Mr. Turrell is turning out product to support ''The Roden Crater,'' his massive earthwork in Arizona. Harder to countenance is the way the perceptual and spatial changes that, with patience, emerged from his earlier noncomputerized light pieces are now being juiced up and handed to the viewer on a platter. These are gorgeous, very expensive lava lamps, Rothkos by Disney.</p>
        <p>Down the block from PaceWildenstein, the Mitchell Algus Gallery offers an interesting retort to the Turrell circus, and a twist on the full-gallery tradition. Mr. Algus's space, tiny by Chelsea standards, is lined with eight paintings from 1968-73 by Roy Colmer, a painter and video artist whose work stands out in ''High Times, Hard Times'' at the National Academy Museum. The totality forms a modest but accidental environmental piece; the space seems nearly filled by the painting's slinky, smoky opticality and color clouds, achieved through simple combinations of tape and spray paint.</p>
        <p>A block away, at Luhring Augustine, you'll find another cheek-by-jowl display of paintings functioning as an installation, on purpose, as a way to stress the gallery's commercial function. This is the Chelsea debut of Josh Smith, well known for similar, if smaller, scruffier and smarter installations at Reena Spaulings Fine Art on the Lower East Side. Most of these boisterously haphazard paintings look like blowups of details from minor, Kandinsky-flavored abstractions from the mid-20th century, now seen as the Stone Age of the gallery scene.</p>
        <p>Among them are a few even more cursory works, reminiscent of the ''abstractions'' found in comic strips. Mr. Smith is a welcome addition to Chelsea, but his ironic-serious approach to painting is usually better balanced.</p>
        <p>Empty</p>
        <p>Chelsea usually offers something in the way of the empty- or nearly empty gallery tradition. Sometimes it is an attempt to link the gallery space with the outside world by doing almost nothing. For example, the first gallery of Spencer Finch's show at Postmasters contains only a semicircular wall of electric fans turning on and off at random. Actually, they are programmed to replicate the shifting speeds and directions of the wind as measured by Mr. Finch one day last month at Walden Pond, far from the wilds of Chelsea.</p>
        <p>In other instances, the emptiness turns inward to emphasize mental space, as is the case with Jonathan Monk's show at the Casey Kaplan Gallery. Although the show contains some paintings and sculptures, the best works are the slightest ones, as when Mr. Monk pays tribute to Frank Sinatra and Bruce Nauman with one image, pointedly tacked to the wall; adds mystical circles (CD tracings) to the covers of used books; and creates a smoke-filled, laser-beam nod to Magritte.</p>
        <p>The most effective work is a tiny projection of ''The Cheat,'' an early silent film, with sound accompaniment provided by a boom box tuned to a classical music station. Both times I visited, operas were playing, which turned out to be perfect.</p>
        <p>Giant</p>
        <p>One way to emphasize space is to render it simultaneously empty and full, by putting one or two outlandishly scaled-up things in it. Descended from Claes Oldenburg's Pop Art sculptures, this idea is almost always a crowd-pleaser.</p>
        <p>At the Mary Boone Gallery, Pierre Bismuth's version of this strategy shows how an excess of space can bring out the grandiose in an artist. Part of a triple solo New York debut -- the other parts are at Ms. Boone's Fifth Avenue gallery and Team Gallery in SoHo -- it consists of three large, tilted planes as massive as Richard Serra sculptures, but covered with giant replicas of Artforum and Art in America magazine pages that included ads for Mr. Bismuth's shows. They are art-about-art clichés as indoor billboards. Someday maybe there will be a word for wasted space.</p>
        <p>Fresher is Darren Almond's exhibition at Matthew Marks on West 22nd Street, whose centerpiece is a red digital clock one inch short of 13 feet tall. Visible through the gallery's glass front, it can attract groups of people to watch the changing of the hour. The anticipation lasts longer than you might think. It's strange how time drags when your timepiece is the size of a shipping container.</p>
        <p>Art in Big Packages</p>
        <p>Here is information about the Chelsea shows mentioned:</p>
        <p>GORDON MATTA-CLARK/RIRKRIT TIRAVANIJA AT DAVID ZWIRNER GALLERY, 525 West 19th Street, (212) 727-2070. Through May 19.</p>
        <p>WALTER DE MARIA AT GAGOSIAN GALLERY, 522 West 21st Street, (212) 741-1717, and 555 West 24th Street, (212) 741-1111. Through May 5.</p>
        <p>JOAN JONAS AT YVON LAMBERT NEW YORK, 550 West 21st Street and 564 West 25th Street, (212) 242-3611. Through April 26.</p>
        <p>ORLY GENGER AT LARISSA GOLDSTON, 530 West 25th Street, third floor, (212) 206-7887. Through May 5.</p>
        <p>JAMES TURRELL AT PACEWILDENSTEIN GALLERY, 534 West 25th Street, (212) 929-7000. Through April 28.</p>
        <p>ROY COLMER AT MITCHELL ALGUS GALLERY, 511 West 25th Street, second floor, (212) 242-6242. Through tomorrow.</p>
        <p>JOSH SMITH AT LUHRING AUGUSTINE GALLERY, 531 West 24th Street, (212) 206-9100. Through April 28.</p>
        <p>SPENCER FINCH AT POSTMASTERS GALLERY, 459 West 19th Street, (212) 727-3323. Through April 21.</p>
        <p>JONATHAN MONK AT CASEY KAPLAN, 525 West 21st Street, (212) 645-7335. Through May 5.</p>
        <p>PIERRE BISMUTH AT MARY BOONE GALLERY, 541 West 24th Street, and 745 Fifth Avenue, at 58th Street in Manhattan, (212) 752-2929. Through April 28.</p>
        <p>DARREN ALMOND AT MATTHEW MARKS GALLERY, 523 West 22nd Street, (212) 243-0200. Through tomorrow.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
