<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Restaurateur and a Chef Part Ways, and Their Dispute Is Heading Toward Criminal Court</title>
    <meta content="13chef" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/nyregion/13chef.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE0DC133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Restaurateur and a Chef Part Ways, and Their Dispute Is Heading Toward Criminal Court</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Restaurateur and a Chef Part Ways, and Their Dispute Is Heading Toward Criminal Court</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WILSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What began as a falling-out between the owner of an Italian restaurant in Brooklyn and its chef has moved from the kitchen to the courthouse, with the owner filing theft charges against the chef and the chef surrendering at a police station.</p>
        <p>The police said the chef, Jason Neroni, 30, had forged two checks to himself from the restaurant, Porchetta, on Smith Street in Carroll Gardens, as he was leaving there for good.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What began as a falling-out between the owner of an Italian restaurant in Brooklyn and its chef has moved from the kitchen to the courthouse</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What began as a falling-out between the owner of an Italian restaurant in Brooklyn and its chef has moved from the kitchen to the courthouse, with the owner filing theft charges against the chef and the chef surrendering at a police station.</p>
        <p>The police said the chef, Jason Neroni, 30, had forged two checks to himself from the restaurant, Porchetta, on Smith Street in Carroll Gardens, as he was leaving there for good.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neroni would not comment yesterday, but a spokesman for the chef said that he had simply written out a check for his own pay, as he had done in the past without complaint from the owner, Marco Rivero. He paid himself $900, signing Mr. Rivero's name to the checks, said the spokesman, Steven Hall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall, a veteran of the New York restaurant scene who has done public relations work for a number of chefs, said yesterday: ''He has written checks before and the owner has never said anything. He's paid his staff, vendors, delivery people with checks, and the owner has never said anything.''</p>
        <p>The police said that Mr. Neroni was charged with third-degree forgery and petit larceny, both misdemeanors, and that he appeared on Wednesday at the 76th Precinct station house, where he was issued a desk appearance ticket, routine in such cases. The Brooklyn district attorney's office said he is scheduled to appear in criminal court on May 14.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neroni was hired at Porchetta with fanfare in October, after having worked as executive chef at 71 Clinton Fresh Food until that restaurant on the Lower East Side of Manhattan closed in March 2006.</p>
        <p>In his review of Porchetta on Jan. 17 in The New York Times, the restaurant critic Frank Bruni called Mr. Neroni ''a restless sort, brimming with ideas, bursting with ambition.'' He praised some dishes (''Mr. Neroni's sense of enterprise and thoughtfulness served him brilliantly'') while finding fault with others. Of the gnocchi, the critic wrote: ''In a flourish too far and too abundant, he added candied lemon zest. The way it interacted with other ingredients made the dish taste as if someone in the kitchen had inadvertently sprayed it with a bit of Pledge furniture polish.''</p>
        <p>On April 5, Mr. Neroni said in a statement on the dining Web site Eater.com that he was leaving Porchetta ''due to irreconcilable differences.''</p>
        <p>Five days later, Mr. Rivero wrote on the same site: ''Jason was fired for unauthorized misappropriation of funds from the business. A warrant is currently out for his arrest.'' Mr. Rivero wrote that there had been ''invectives and mistruths directed against us'' by Mr. Neroni.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neroni has also worked for the New York City restaurants Alain Ducasse at the Essex House, Blue Hill, Tabla and the Tasting Room.</p>
        <p>His spokesman said the dispute with Mr. Rivero followed remarks the chef had made that upset the restaurateur. ''Marco told Jason he would drop the charges if Jason would publicly apologize to him,'' Mr. Hall said. ''Jason said he didn't think he had anything to apologize for. He just quit his job. They weren't getting along.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall added, ''If Marco didn't want anyone signing checks, including Jason, he should have put the checkbook in the safe.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
