<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antiques</title>
    <meta content="13anti" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/arts/design/13anti.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Antiques"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Christie's</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E7DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1072" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antiques</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Definitely Imperial but Way Too Tiny for Napoleon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Definitely Imperial But Way Too Tiny For Napoleon</p>
        <p>Why have Fabergé objects been treasured ever since Gustav Fabergé opened his jewelry emporium in St. Petersburg in 1842, an enterprise he and his children ran for 75 years?</p>
        <p>The question comes up again because Sotheby's Russian art sale on Monday has several works by Fabergé, including a rare enameled miniature chair that is estimated to sell for $1 million to $1.5 million. Christie's Russian sale, with 38 Fabergé works (but no chairs), is on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two Russian art sales at Sotheby’s and Christie’s feature works by Fabergé, including a rare enameled miniature chair that is estimated to sell for $1 million to $1.5 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Definitely Imperial But Way Too Tiny For Napoleon</p>
        <p>Why have Fabergé objects been treasured ever since Gustav Fabergé opened his jewelry emporium in St. Petersburg in 1842, an enterprise he and his children ran for 75 years?</p>
        <p>The question comes up again because Sotheby's Russian art sale on Monday has several works by Fabergé, including a rare enameled miniature chair that is estimated to sell for $1 million to $1.5 million. Christie's Russian sale, with 38 Fabergé works (but no chairs), is on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Americans, especially, seem attracted to Fabergé objects, whether tiny terriers in white chalcedony with ruby eyes, pink-enameled picture frames or bejeweled imperial Easter eggs made for the wives and mothers of the Romanov czars.</p>
        <p>''Everyone can relate to Fabergé,'' said Mitchell Merling, a curator at the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, which has a substantial Fabergé collection. ''Fabergé was very original in inventing different kinds of objects and in applying different historical styles, whether Italian Renaissance, Baroque, Louis XVI or Old Russian. The superiority of the craftsmanship is self-evident.''</p>
        <p>Geza von Habsburg, a Fabergé authority who has organized several museum exhibitions, had his own thoughts.</p>
        <p>''From a purely artistic point of view, you must understand Fabergé produced more than 150,000 objects, and every single piece is different,'' he said. ''Fabergé also has something none of the other jewelers have: the romance of the Romanovs. Americans have this love affair with the Romanov family, perhaps due to their tragic, terrible fate. Today owning a Fabergé is a status symbol, like having a Picasso on the wall.''</p>
        <p>Made about 1900, the 2.25-inch-tall Fabergé gold and enameled chair at Sotheby's is in the French Empire style. In form it is a ''fauteuil en gondole,'' an 18th-century French term for an armchair with a rounded back.</p>
        <p>It has saber legs, and its gold base is engraved to simulate wood graining, then covered with a translucent red enamel so it looks like mahogany. The back is a frieze of golden lyres. The seat is ''upholstered'' in translucent green enamel to resemble lustrous silk. A tiny removable drawer beneath the seat has the initials of the Fabergé workmaster, Michael Perchin of St. Petersburg. There are no precious or semiprecious gemstones.</p>
        <p>Why Fabergé would create a tiny chair in the Empire style made famous by Napoleon, Russia's former enemy, can be explained only by changes in fashion.</p>
        <p>Gerard Hill, Sotheby's Russian-art specialist, said the form was based on the designs of the Bavarian crown architect Leo von Klenze (1784-1864), a promoter of the Greek Revival style. In 1839 Czar Nicholas I commissioned von Klenze to design the New Hermitage in St. Petersburg, next to the Winter Palace. He did both the architecture and the interiors, which were well received and helped to popularize neo-Classicism and the Empire style in Russia. Fabergé must have taken his cue from von Klenze's furniture when he created the little chair.</p>
        <p>Fabergé did not make many pieces of miniature furniture.</p>
        <p>''There are two pieces in the Cleveland Museum and others in the collection of the queen of England,'' said Anne Odom, curator emerita of the Hillwood Museum in Washington. ''There are definitely not a lot of pieces out there.''</p>
        <p>But Peter L. Schaffer, co-owner of À La Vieille Russie in Manhattan, said Fabergé miniature furniture was ''rarish but not that rare.''</p>
        <p>Dr. von Habsburg disagreed. ''Fabergé miniature furniture is exceedingly rare, which accounts for it enormous value,'' he said. ''The number of pieces is infinitesimally small, smaller even than the number of surviving Fabergé Easter eggs, which is about 42. An Easter egg is now $10 million plus, so the Sotheby's estimate for the chair, while staggering, is perfectly realistic. Clocks that were $30,000 now go for $500,000.''</p>
        <p>Was the chair made to furnish an imperial dollhouse? Or is it a salt cellar or candy dish?</p>
        <p>''It is a bibelot,'' said Bill Johnston, the senior curator of 18th- and 19th-century art at the Walters Art Museum in Baltimore, which houses the extensive Fabergé collection of its founder, Henry Walters. ''It was not meant to hold salt or candy.''</p>
        <p>A European family consigned the chair to Sotheby's anonymously. ''This chair has been in the same princely family since the day it was purchased,'' Mr. Hill said.</p>
        <p>The Fabergés were always ingenious. Originally from northern France, the Fabergé family fled the country seeking religious freedom, as did many other Protestant Huguenots, after Louis XIV revoked the Edict of Nantes in 1685. They did not reach St. Petersburg until 1842. Gustav Fabergé opened his shop there but sent his two sons abroad for training. His older son, Peter Carl, apprenticed with a goldsmith in Paris. Agathon worked in Dresden, Germany. In 1870 the older son, always known as Carl, took over the family firm.</p>
        <p>In the early 1880s Carl Fabergé was appointed official jeweler to the imperial court. By 1900 he employed several hundred craftsmen: designers, modelers, gem cutters, goldsmiths and enamelers. The firm provided diplomatic gifts to be sent abroad and family presents for imperial birthdays, weddings and coronations.</p>
        <p>Gentlemanly, tolerant, cheerful and gentle, Carl Fabergé was not only amazingly inventive but also frugal on the nation's behalf. He was more interested in creating works of fantasy -- snuff boxes, cigarette cases, hard-stone animals, sprays of flowers, miniature picture frames and clocks -- than jewelry encrusted with diamonds and precious stones. He appreciated native materials like Siberian nephrite, rhodonite, aventurine, agate, quartz and chalcedony.</p>
        <p>In 1949 Henry Charles Bainbridge, once manager of the firm's London branch and a longtime friend of Carl Fabergé, wrote his biography.</p>
        <p>Carl Fabergé ''materialized in gold, enamel and rare stones, the delicacy, the love, aye, the madness of a glamorous age,'' he wrote, and added that ''he has left for grim posterity a legacy of delight which is evidenced by the eagerness with which men now surround themselves with his handiwork.''</p>
        <p>After the Russian Revolution in 1917 the Bolsheviks nationalized the Fabergé firm and sold its stock. With great difficulty Carl Fabergé and his wife made their way to Lausanne, Switzerland, where he died in 1920.</p>
        <p>Today there are many ''fauxbergés'' on the market, but experts like Dr. von Habsburg say they can spot them. ''Having dealt with forged Fabergé for 35 years, I find it easy,'' he said, adding that just last month he had weeded out a few while serving as a vetter at the European Fine Art Fair in Maastricht, the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>Antiques</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
