<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bibles Thumping, Suspenders Snapping</title>
    <meta content="13wind" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/theater/reviews/13wind.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839862"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lawrence, Jerome</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Robert E (Playwright)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, Doug</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Plummer, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dennehy, Brian</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Inherit the Wind (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Plummer, Christopher</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dennehy, Brian</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Inherit the Wind (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E3DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1381" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bibles Thumping, Suspenders Snapping</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bibles Thumping, Suspenders Snapping</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews revival of Jerome Lawrence and Robert E Lee play Inherit the Wind, directed by Doug Hughes; Christopher Plummer and Brian Dennehy star; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The handsome wooden courtroom that has been erected on the stage of the Lyceum Theater is Christopher Plummer's personal playground. This may sound like a frivolous description of a forum for the lofty and abidingly important debate that occupies ''Inherit the Wind,'' the 1955 drama that opened last night, also starring Brian Dennehy, in a revival that is just about as wooden as its set.</p>
        <p>But while the subject of teaching evolution and religion in public schools is even more topical than it was when Jerome Lawrence and Robert E. Lee's worthy war horse first galloped onto Broadway more than half a century ago, Mr. Plummer at play is something sacred. If the Bible-quoting fundamentalists in ''Inherit the Wind'' want to make a case for the spark of divinity that separates man from beast, they need only point to the show's august star, having the time of his life, as Exhibit A.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since not one soul in this revival has a flicker of Christopher Plummer’s fire, this play is not the crackling courtroom drama it was intended to be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The handsome wooden courtroom that has been erected on the stage of the Lyceum Theater is Christopher Plummer's personal playground. This may sound like a frivolous description of a forum for the lofty and abidingly important debate that occupies ''Inherit the Wind,'' the 1955 drama that opened last night, also starring Brian Dennehy, in a revival that is just about as wooden as its set.</p>
        <p>But while the subject of teaching evolution and religion in public schools is even more topical than it was when Jerome Lawrence and Robert E. Lee's worthy war horse first galloped onto Broadway more than half a century ago, Mr. Plummer at play is something sacred. If the Bible-quoting fundamentalists in ''Inherit the Wind'' want to make a case for the spark of divinity that separates man from beast, they need only point to the show's august star, having the time of his life, as Exhibit A.</p>
        <p>Approaching the end of his eighth decade, Mr. Plummer knows that if all the world's a stage, few places in it are more temptingly so than a courtroom, an arena that would seem to have been conceived expressly for showboats with scripts.</p>
        <p>Aside from playing another actor (and Mr. Plummer won his last Tony in 1997 for portraying John Barrymore), nothing lets an actor act, with the full panoply of shameless tricks, like the role of a lawyer. So it should surprise no one that as Henry Drummond -- a character based on Clarence Darrow, the granddaddy of grandstanding lawyers -- Mr. Plummer has the audience eating from his hand as soon as he snaps his suspenders.</p>
        <p>It is meant as no discredit to Mr. Plummer that for New York theatergoers, or at least the subset that would automatically attend ''Inherit the Wind,'' pretty much anyone who played Drummond would have the house in his corner.</p>
        <p>In this fictional re-creation of the Scopes ''monkey trial'' of 1925 -- in which a Tennessee high-school science teacher was tried for including Darwin's theories of evolution in his curriculum -- Drummond stands for freedom of belief. Written in the anxious shadow of the McCarthy hearings, ''Wind'' turned its Darrow surrogate into a salty saint who unquestionably had the angels -- the secular kind, anyway -- on his team.</p>
        <p>Still, for this play to be the crackling courtroom drama it was intended to be, we need to feel the force of Drummond's opposition. And not one soul on the side of creationism in this revival, directed by Doug Hughes, has a flicker of Mr. Plummer's fire. Sadly, that includes the estimable Mr. Dennehy, the two-time Tony winner who plays Drummond's formidable adversary, Matthew Harrison Brady, a character inspired by the grandiloquent politician William Jennings Bryan.</p>
        <p>This glaring imbalance means that ''Wind'' never musters much more velocity than that of a drugstore fan. Mr. Hughes, whose credits include the gripping Broadway productions of ''Doubt'' and ''Frozen,'' has made a stilted attempt to reconceive the play as a sort of Brechtian exercise.</p>
        <p>The line between the ''us'' of now and the ''them'' of then is blurred by placing audience members in risers on the stage. (Santo Loquasto did the effective world-on-trial set.) A gospel quartet sings directly to the house. And the show makes striking use of oversize signs and frozen phalanxes of townspeople, ominously lighted by Brian MacDevitt.</p>
        <p>This atmosphere, meant to conjure the dangerous spirit of down-home fascism, extends into first-act set pieces like the revival meeting led by the Rev. Jeremiah Brown (played by Byron Jennings with a ramrod posture and maniacal gaze). The good folk of Hillsboro sport feverish looks of vengeance and giant torches for the occasion, as if they were planning to lynch Frankenstein's monster after prayers.</p>
        <p>But once the play settles into the trial, expressionist flourishes are abandoned, as they must be. The enduring appeal of ''Inherit the Wind'' is not as a play of ideas, which are mostly expressed in the manner of stump speeches, but as an occasion for two seasoned stars to trade punches in the boxing ring of the courtroom. Over the years the sparring partners in stage, film and television versions of ''Wind'' have included Paul Muni, Ed Begley, Spencer Tracy, Fredric March, Jason Robards, Jack Lemmon and, for the previous Broadway revival (in 1996), George C. Scott and Charles Durning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Plummer and Mr. Dennehy seemed as promising a pair of boxers as any of the above. Yet almost from the moment he first speaks, Mr. Dennehy is down for the count. As written Brady is a man of luxuriant bombast and self-importance, an overinflated balloon ripe for the pricking. A three-time candidate for the United States presidency, he has become an eternal also-ran, and the spreading cracks in his confidence lead to a shattering public breakdown.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dennehy (who has lost a lot of weight since he dazzled New Yorkers as Willy Loman in ''Death of a Salesman'') has never seemed in better shape. Right up unto that annihilating standoff with Drummond, this Brady seems so coolly self-assured that you never fear for his health or sanity, as his wife (the excellent Beth Fowler) obviously does. It is said that the temperature in the courthouse is 97 degrees, but Mr. Dennehy never breaks a sweat.</p>
        <p>The glad-handing, hard-smiling persona of the inveterate politician comes easily to Mr. Dennehy. (He seems to lead with his upper row of teeth.) But there's little evidence of Brady's fanatical faith or hunger for admiration. Without that, it's hard to care what happens to him, one way or the other.</p>
        <p>Much of the rest of the cast seems similarly uninvested in the proceedings. Exceptions include Ms. Fowler, who watches Mr. Dennehy with a vigilant fierceness that recalls Nancy Reagan in the White House, and Benjamin Walker, who radiates the requisite sincerity as the Darwinist defendant.</p>
        <p>Denis O'Hare, who plays a cynical newspaper reporter inspired by H. L. Mencken, cannot be accused of apathy. But his stylized vaudeville performance belongs to another show (maybe ''George M'').</p>
        <p>Which leaves us with Mr. Plummer, which is not nothing. Last seen on Broadway as a magnificently human King Lear, he manages to milk Shakespearean music from Drummond's long courtroom musings.</p>
        <p>He has some of the irascible twinkliness of Spencer Tracy in the film. But he doesn't coast on the plain-spoken wisdom of a character presented as the Will Rogers of jurisprudence. I believed that this Drummond felt his age, felt the years he'd known Brady, felt the tragedy of a situation in which no one, personally, would win.</p>
        <p>I also believed that he -- unlike most of the others onstage -- truly felt the heat of a stuffy summer courtroom in the days before air conditioning. This may sound like a minor point. But for ''Inherit the Wind'' to be more than a yellowing position paper, you must be convinced that these are characters who exist in a very particular time and place, where it happens to be hotter than, well, hell.</p>
        <p>Mr. Plummer alone takes us there. For this ''Wind'' to achieve anything approaching gale force, he needs a lot more assistance than he's getting.</p>
        <p>Inherit the Wind</p>
        <p>By Jerome Lawrence and Robert E. Lee; directed by Doug Hughes; sets and costumes by Santo Loquasto; lighting by Brian MacDevitt; original music and sound by David Van Tieghem; hair and wig design by Paul Huntley; production stage manager, Michael Brunner; technical supervisor, Peter Fulbright; general manager, 101 Productions, Ltd.; associate producer, Judith Resnick. Presented by Boyett Ostar Productions, the Shubert Organization, Lawrence Horowitz, Jon Avnet/Ralph Guild, Roy Furman, Debra Black/Daryl Roth, Bill Rollnick/Nancy Ellison Rollnick and Stephanie McClelland. At the Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, Manhattan; (212) 239-6200. Through July 8. Running time: 2 hours.</p>
        <p>WITH: Christopher Plummer (Henry Drummond), Brian Dennehy (Matthew Harrison Brady), Denis O'Hare (E. K. Hornbeck), Byron Jennings (Reverend Jeremiah Brown), Terry Beaver (Judge), Beth Fowler (Mrs. Brady), Anne Bowles (Mrs. Loomis), Bill Buell (Bannister), Bill Christ (Vendor), Conor Donovan (Howard), Lanny Flaherty (Elijah), Maggie Lacey (Rachel Brown), Jordan Lage (Tom Davenport), Kevin C. Loomis (Monkey Man), Charlotte Maier (Mrs. Krebs), Matthew Nardozzi (Timmy), Randall Newsome (Photographer), Jay Patterson (Dunlap), Pippa Pearthree (Mrs. Blair), Scott Sowers (Mr. Meeker), Amanda Sprecher (Melinda), Jeff Steitzer (Mayor), Henry Stram (Mr. Goodfellow), Benjamin Walker (Bert Cates) and Andrew Weems (Sillers).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
