<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When a Piano Isn't Playing Second Fiddle to a Cello</title>
    <meta content="13schi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/arts/music/13schi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Schiff, Andras</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When a Piano Isn't Playing Second Fiddle to a Cello</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When a Piano Isn’t Playing Second Fiddle to a Cello</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These days, we reflexively think of Beethoven's works for cello and piano as cello works with piano accompaniment. But as collaborative pianists never tire of pointing out, that isn't how Beethoven or his first audiences regarded them, and the scores' titles support that view: the sonatas, formally, are ''for piano and cello.'' And that was how the pianist Andras Schiff and the cellist Miklos Perenyi played them on Wednesday evening, in the first of two concerts at the 92nd Street Y devoted to all the Beethoven piano and cello works. (The second was last night.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Schiff, playing a beefy Bösendorfer piano with the lid open, addressed the music with the same assertiveness and clarity of detail that he brings to his solo recitals, and when Beethoven put the main action in the piano line -- as he did much of the time -- Mr. Schiff was ready to claim the spotlight. Mr. Perenyi, by contrast, produced a modest sound. He is an agile player with an appealing tone, but one that is never so lush as to be overwhelming, even when Beethoven put the cello in the lead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mr. Schiff addressed Beethoven’s music with assertiveness and clarity of detail, and Mr. Perenyi, by contrast, produced a modest sound at the 92nd Street Y on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These days, we reflexively think of Beethoven's works for cello and piano as cello works with piano accompaniment. But as collaborative pianists never tire of pointing out, that isn't how Beethoven or his first audiences regarded them, and the scores' titles support that view: the sonatas, formally, are ''for piano and cello.'' And that was how the pianist Andras Schiff and the cellist Miklos Perenyi played them on Wednesday evening, in the first of two concerts at the 92nd Street Y devoted to all the Beethoven piano and cello works. (The second was last night.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Schiff, playing a beefy Bösendorfer piano with the lid open, addressed the music with the same assertiveness and clarity of detail that he brings to his solo recitals, and when Beethoven put the main action in the piano line -- as he did much of the time -- Mr. Schiff was ready to claim the spotlight. Mr. Perenyi, by contrast, produced a modest sound. He is an agile player with an appealing tone, but one that is never so lush as to be overwhelming, even when Beethoven put the cello in the lead.</p>
        <p>It was as if these players had determined that any excitement in this music -- or in this reading of it -- had to be rooted in collaboration and interplay, rather than in the seductiveness of one player's sound.</p>
        <p>In this first installment, Mr. Schiff and Mr. Perenyi offered the Sonatas in F (Op. 5, No. 1); C (Op. 102, No. 1); and A (Op. 69), as well as the Variations on Mozart's ''Ein Mädchen oder Weibchen'' (Op. 66). They did little to distinguish between Beethoven's early, middle and late works, playing each sonata with essentially the same dramatic accenting and muscularity.</p>
        <p>But the readings had other charms. You had to admire the zesty brightness of the finale in the Sonata in F and the broadly contrasting passages of storminess and lyricism in the opening movement of the Sonata in A. The tightly linked syncopations in that work's Scherzo were executed with flawless precision. And there was no resisting the alternation of dark meditations and energetic outbursts in the slow movement of the C major Sonata.</p>
        <p>Yet it was the slightest work that made the most lasting effect. In the variations, the give and take was as good as it gets. Beethoven cast these elaborations on an aria from ''The Magic Flute'' as a balanced dialogue -- almost a contest -- between the piano and the cello, and Mr. Schiff and Mr. Perenyi honored both the letter and the spirit of that intent.</p>
        <p>Andras Schiff and Miklos Perenyi will perform Beethoven works for piano and cello at the Seligman Center in Detroit on Saturday, the Independence Seaport Museum in Philadelphia on Tuesday and the Coolidge Auditorium in Washington on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
