<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>And in This Corner, the Sponsors</title>
    <meta content="13sandomir" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/sports/othersports/13sandomir.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mayweather, Floyd Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">De La Hoya, Oscar</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDA133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>And in This Corner, the Sponsors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">And in This Corner, the Sponsors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boxing may fade from the sports consciousness for long stretches, as if doing jail time for losing its once-broad appeal, but it will be tough to ignore the May 5 fight between Oscar De La Hoya and Floyd Mayweather Jr.</p>
        <p>The bout is backed by so much marketing -- like promotions for Cazadores tequila, Tecate beer and Rockstar energy drink appearing in a combined 45,000 7-Elevens, Circle K's and local grocery stores -- that explaining it required an hourlong Power Point presentation yesterday at a news media briefing at the 21 Club, in a room with shelves of classic beer steins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boxing may fade from the sports consciousness for long stretches, but thanks to heavy marketing, it will be tough to ignore the May 5 fight between Oscar De La Hoya and Floyd Mayweather Jr.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Boxing may fade from the sports consciousness for long stretches, as if doing jail time for losing its once-broad appeal, but it will be tough to ignore the May 5 fight between Oscar De La Hoya and Floyd Mayweather Jr.</p>
        <p>The bout is backed by so much marketing -- like promotions for Cazadores tequila, Tecate beer and Rockstar energy drink appearing in a combined 45,000 7-Elevens, Circle K's and local grocery stores -- that explaining it required an hourlong Power Point presentation yesterday at a news media briefing at the 21 Club, in a room with shelves of classic beer steins.</p>
        <p>''I have no doubt that we have the most aggressive lineup of sponsors for any fight ever,'' said Richard Schaefer, the chief executive of Golden Boy Promotions, De La Hoya's company, which is promoting the bout. It will be at the MGM Grand in Las Vegas, which grossed $19 million in ticket sales in a three-hour buyer binge as soon as tickets became available.</p>
        <p>The efforts by Golden Boy and HBO, which will televise the match, are in the service of exceeding the pay-per-view record of 1.99 million purchases for the 1997 Evander Holyfield-Mike Tyson rematch (distinguished by Tyson's gnawing of Holyfield's ear). They would be pleased to outdo the nonheavyweight pay-per-view record of 1.4 million, for De La Hoya's 1999 loss to Felix Trinidad, but they really want to shatter the 2 million mark.</p>
        <p>One of the television initiatives by HBO is production of a four-part documentary series, ''De La Hoya/Mayweather 24/7,'' a look at the fighters as they prepare for their junior middleweight title bout. It will make its debut Sunday at 10:30 p.m., in an enviable position -- after ''The Sopranos'' and ''Entourage.'' The time slot offers a large tune-in audience (last week, ''The Sopranos'' drew 7.7 million viewers, ''Entourage'' about 3.8 million), but it imposes pressure on ''24/7'' to be a quality product.</p>
        <p>''It took a little convincing, but I thought we should bust into some high-rent real estate,'' said Ross Greenburg, the president of HBO Sports.</p>
        <p>He said that his best hope was that the three episodes that will air in that prime-time slot would retain half of ''Entourage's'' audience. The fourth installment will be shown on May 3, two days before the bout, at 9:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>It is accurate to say that HBO created this series to promote the fight to its viewership in a way that improves upon traditional on-air marketing, and just as correct to believe that HBO was looking to create programming that would complement its terrific historic boxing series, ''Legendary Nights.''</p>
        <p>Rick Bernstein, executive producer of HBO Sports, said the ''24/7'' series was not originally intended as a kind of big-fight informercial, but the fighters would not do the series if they did not benefit from it.</p>
        <p>Bernstein said that he and Greenburg had contemplated producing a series like ''24/7'' before, seeking high-profile fighters with potent, contrasting personalities. They looked at the De La Hoya-Bernard Hopkins fight in 2004, the Mayweather-Arturo Gatti fight in 2005 and last year's Hopkins-Antonio Tarver match, but did not pull the trigger on any of them.</p>
        <p>''What we see is the honest distaste that Mayweather and De La Hoya have for each other, coming off their 11-city publicity tour,'' Greenburg said.</p>
        <p>HBO has ventured into this type of programming territory before, with NFL Films. The two ''Hard Knocks'' series chronicled the training camps of the Baltimore Ravens in 2001 and the Dallas Cowboys a year later.</p>
        <p>Bernstein said the main lesson learned from ''Hard Knocks'' was not to overload the first episode of ''24/7'' with more back stories than viewers can digest. That should be simpler with two main characters rather than a full team.</p>
        <p>Some Ravens and Cowboys were paid extra fees by NFL Films, but De La Hoya and Mayweather are getting nothing more than their multimillion-dollar guarantees and participation in the expected financial upside.</p>
        <p>The fighters have granted HBO almost complete access, which should take full advantage of the boxers' different training routines (De La Hoya's is highly disciplined, Mayweather's is less structured) and of Mayweather's hammish personality, willingness to play the bad guy and desire for acclaim.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya is usually guarded, but he has beaten HBO's expectations for openness, Bernstein said.</p>
        <p>Schaefer said: ''You've not seen his wife, Millie, or his son, much before on the air. But this will be an intimate portrait.''</p>
        <p>The production crews in each camp (De La Hoya's in Puerto Rico, Mayweather's in Las Vegas) must follow general guidelines not to shoot training footage that might give away any strategy.</p>
        <p>''So far,'' Bernstein said, ''Oscar's people have had no issues with us, but Mayweather has been a bit more difficult. We haven't gotten quite the access we hoped for.''</p>
        <p>But if the series had to depend on sparring footage, it might as well close down now.</p>
        <p>If ''24/7'' provides what is promised, it will be a vast improvement over last year's ESPN series ''Bonds on Bonds.'' That series had the challenge of following a star implicated in a drug scandal who couldn't, or wouldn't, answer questions about his alleged steroid use, and who tried to impose editorial control over the program, which led to its demise.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
