<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Reeling Richardson Keeps Hope Afloat</title>
    <meta content="13araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/sports/basketball/13araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Richardson, Michael Ray</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E6D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Reeling Richardson Keeps Hope Afloat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Reeling Richardson Keeps Hope Afloat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''How are you doing?'' I said to the recently unemployed Micheal Ray Richardson earlier this week.</p>
        <p>''I'll tell you what, I'm not sinkin','' he said by telephone from Albany in the 25th anniversary year of his most famous quotation until late last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Micheal Ray Richardson was a gifted athlete who snorted away his N.B.A. career. Now his C.B.A. coaching career has been derailed after making insensitive comments to a fan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''How are you doing?'' I said to the recently unemployed Micheal Ray Richardson earlier this week.</p>
        <p>''I'll tell you what, I'm not sinkin','' he said by telephone from Albany in the 25th anniversary year of his most famous quotation until late last month.</p>
        <p>Richardson's ship may not be going down as the Knicks did during the spring of 1982 and as his N.B.A. career did four years later. But his hope of rising in the coaching ranks is listing perilously after his suspension from the Albany Patroons' Continental Basketball Association championship series against the Yakama Sun Kings.</p>
        <p>He wasn't trying to be funny, wasn't prostituting his values for the sake of ratings and profit, when he cursed out a courtside fan during the first game of the series in Albany. But he embellished the attack with an anti-gay slur, and this after giving a pregame discourse to two reporters from The Albany Times-Union that was interpreted by some, not all, probably not even most, to be anti-Semitic.</p>
        <p>Even if it was, in the case of the fan, an angry slip of the tongue, and even if it was just awkward phrasing in the discussion with reporters that ensued after his quip about being represented by ''big-time Jew lawyers,'' Richardson is out of work now, begging not to be written off and remembered as a bigot.</p>
        <p>''I'm 52 years old and all I want is some peace,'' he said. ''I never judge anyone, not after all the things that have happened to me.''</p>
        <p>He was a gifted athlete who snorted away what might have been a Hall of Fame career, who survived the worst of times when many expected him to one day turn up dead. After eight stormy years, Richardson was banished from the N.B.A. by Commissioner David Stern for failing a drug test in 1986, and he went off to play abroad, from Italy to, yes, Israel, deep into his 40s.</p>
        <p>Defrocked jock and shock jock, Richardson and Don Imus, whose failures to mince their messages occurred one week apart and have resulted in screeching employment derailment, have operated in separate universes, but not without lifestyle parallels.</p>
        <p>Both came to stardom young and couldn't resist the potentially ruinous temptations of the New York City high life. Through good times and bad, both had defenders and sycophants to forgive them, swear by their intentions, by their good hearts.</p>
        <p>People, myself included, who have known Richardson from the beginning, long ago reached the conclusion that he is an endearing soul with a nasty habit of making trouble for himself. We fondly remember him coming to New York for the first time as an N.B.A. rookie from the University of Montana, being asked how he came by the nickname of Sugar, and the uncomfortable seconds that ensued as Richardson, with a chronic stutter, struggled to say, ''Because I'm sweet on the court.''</p>
        <p>So those of us who rooted for him to survive and succeed will be quick to point out that Richardson telephoned the Albany fan the next day to apologize for the outburst -- contrary to Imus's second-day suggestion that those upset by his horrific and now job-fatal slander of the Rutgers women's basketball players needed to get a life.</p>
        <p>Soon as Richardson realized that a firestorm was brewing over his comments on Jewish ingenuity and influence, he called Stern, who had arranged a job for him in the Denver Nuggets' community relations department when Richardson returned from Europe in 2003, leaving behind in France a Moroccan wife and two young children. Then he contacted Joe Taub, the former owner of the Nets and a longtime Richardson supporter.</p>
        <p>Both men, at times filling the paternal void in Richardson's life, are Jewish. Richardson had to explain what he had been trying to say.</p>
        <p>''Micheal has played and lived in Israel, has been to that airport in Tel Aviv,'' Stern said in a telephone interview, insisting Richardson would not be excommunicated from his league this time, that he was still on the active list to staff brand clinics. ''He knows the Middle East is a tough neighborhood. Saying Jewish people have to be smart to survive didn't strike me as anti-Semitic.''</p>
        <p>Stern's support didn't get Richardson reinstated in Albany or a contract for next season. Jim Coyne, the Patroons' general manager, said there were other issues: a midseason powder Richardson took to attend the N.B.A. All-Star Game in Las Vegas, a trade he made without consulting Coyne.</p>
        <p>There were also earlier exchanges with fans, Coyne said, situations that ''a coach should be above.'' Coyne and the team's president and owner, Benito Fernandez, decided after the playoffs that it was best for Richardson to move on. But where?</p>
        <p>''The best thing for Micheal would be to work for the N.B.A. or one of its teams, scouting in Europe,'' Coyne said. ''He knows the territory, he knows talent, and that would take him away from the pressure of the game, the heat of the moment.''</p>
        <p>And out of the combustible environment that always made him such a risk to implode.</p>
        <p>It has been 10 years since Richardson startled Stern in Paris at a McDonald's Open game, held out his hand and thanked him for sending him away, for setting him straight. Kicking Richardson out of the N.B.A. was no act of friendship. Hindsight allows us to define it, in part, as one of mercy.</p>
        <p>Hard truths are invaluable for those who believe they are untouchable, who stretch the rules, or the limits of decency. As he most likely heads to the satellite dial, the talk-radio European league, think Imus isn't wishing that some of his big-shot friends had been willing to sacrifice their own airtime and agendas until he curtailed the crudeness? That he had had a corporate commissioner to administer tough love?</p>
        <p>Maybe Stern can sit Richardson down soon, tell him to forget another C.B.A. coaching job and the lawsuit against the Albany reporter and his corporate superiors that Richardson's attorney has been crowing about this week. Maybe Stern can send Richardson back to Europe and to his family, to where he resumed his livelihood two decades ago and saved something worth much more. His soul.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
