<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Apple Says It Will Delay OSX Release For 4 Months</title>
    <meta content="13apple" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/technology/13apple.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Apple Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Apple Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFDB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Apple Says It Will Delay OSX Release For 4 Months</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Apple Says It Will Delay OS X Release for 4 Months</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markoff, John</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Apple Inc say it will delay introduction of Macintosh OSX operating system as much as four months due to quality issues; software was previously expected to ship this spring; analysts do not expect any long-term damage from delay (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Apple Inc., the computer and consumer electronics company, said Thursday that the introduction of the new version of its flagship Macintosh OSX operating system would be delayed as much as four months because of quality issues.</p>
        <p>The company previously said the program would ship this spring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Quality issues will delay the release, an uncharacteristic schedule slippage that is particularly embarrassing for Apple.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Apple Inc., the computer and consumer electronics company, said Thursday that the introduction of the new version of its flagship Macintosh OSX operating system would be delayed as much as four months because of quality issues.</p>
        <p>The company previously said the program would ship this spring.</p>
        <p>The uncharacteristic schedule slippage is particularly embarrassing for Apple, which is based in Cupertino, Calif., because it had previously poked fun at Microsoft's struggles to complete its Vista operating system.</p>
        <p>Microsoft finally shipped the consumer version of its Vista operating system in January -- roughly two years late -- after starting the project over in the face of technology and security challenges. Since its release, Vista has generally received a lukewarm or negative reception from software reviewers.</p>
        <p>Last year at a conference, Apple's head of software development, Bertrand Serlet, took the stage to illustrate how a number of Vista's features were similar to those in Apple's current operating system, known as Tiger.</p>
        <p>''If you can't innovate, I guess you just imitate,'' he said. ''But it's never quite as good as the original.''</p>
        <p>Thursday afternoon, Microsoft executives declined to comment on the delay, which was announced after the close of the stock market.</p>
        <p>But the company took a philosophical stance in a news release.</p>
        <p>Pointing to the time needed to shake out the errors from the software code for the program, called Leopard, the company said in a statement, ''Life often presents trade-offs, and in this case we're sure we've made the right ones.''</p>
        <p>In the release Apple stated that it now planned to give Macintosh software developers a test version of the program when they attend the company's Worldwide Developers Conference in early June and that the final software would ship in October.</p>
        <p>In its statement, Apple cited the need to divert its team of programmers to the challenge of introducing the iPhone, which it said was still on track for shipment in ''late June.''</p>
        <p>Apple's chief executive, Steven P. Jobs, has been promoting new features expected to be introduced in Leopard since the program was first announced at the company's World Wide Developer Conference last June.</p>
        <p>Leopard is expected to have a series of consumer-oriented features including sophisticated data backup, improved graphics and a series of new user control abilities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jobs also said the program had ''secret'' features that would be unveiled closer to the program's commercial introduction.</p>
        <p>''This throws a little bit of water on their parade,'' said David Smith, an analyst who tracks operating systems at Gartner Inc., a market research firm. But he noted that large software projects were frequently late and said that the slip would not prove damaging to Apple over the long run.</p>
        <p>In the past, Apple under Mr. Jobs's leadership has executed several earlier technology transitions relatively flawlessly, including the introduction of the conversion of his Next operating system to Macintosh and the shift from Power PC to Intel microprocessors.</p>
        <p>Apple stock dipped $1.71, to $90.48, in after-hours trading after the announcement.</p>
        <p>The operating system delay is the second slip for Apple this year. The company had said that it would ship its AppleTV video system in February, but it was not available until March 21.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
