<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Win Game 1 Mixing Poise and Panache</title>
    <meta content="13rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/sports/hockey/13rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839996"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Thrashers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jagr, Jaromir</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lundqvist, Henrik</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Win Game 1 Mixing Poise and Panache</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers Win by Mixing Poise and Panache</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers skated into a thunderous atmosphere Thursday night, an arena charged with fans celebrating the first playoff game in Thrashers history, and they had to battle the weight of their own history as well.</p>
        <p>But the din did not rattle the Rangers, who calmly went about taking a two-goal lead, which led to a late two-goal lead, eventually quieting the Philips Arena crowd with a 4-3 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers played like a playoff-tested team holding a two-goal lead until late in the game to win their first playoff game in almost 10 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rangers skated into a thunderous atmosphere Thursday night, an arena charged with fans celebrating the first playoff game in Thrashers history, and they had to battle the weight of their own history as well.</p>
        <p>But the din did not rattle the Rangers, who calmly went about taking a two-goal lead, which led to a late two-goal lead, eventually quieting the Philips Arena crowd with a 4-3 victory.</p>
        <p>It was only one game in a best-of-seven, first-round series, but it was a big step for a franchise that had not won a playoff game since 1997 and whose last brush with the postseason ended in a four-game sweep by the Devils last year.</p>
        <p>''The start is important, everybody knows,'' Rangers forward Jaromir Jagr said. ''I think you should take the advantage. If you've got experience, you should take the advantage.''</p>
        <p>The first game of the playoffs, Jagr said, is always about nerves. Thrashers players admitted to a bad case of them. But Jagr said he felt none, and he certainly looked anything but tense, scoring the Rangers' first goal on a monstrous slap shot with 7 minutes 10 seconds left in the first period.</p>
        <p>Considering how the first game of last year's playoffs went for Jagr -- he injured his shoulder throwing a punch at Devils center Scott Gomez in a 6-1 loss -- his fast start Thursday sent a jolt through the Rangers.</p>
        <p>''It's always great when you know the big boy is getting off to a good start,'' Rangers forward Brendan Shanahan said. ''He's been playing great for us the last six weeks and not always judging his play on goals and assists.''</p>
        <p>The victory did not come easily, but the Rangers came to expect nothing else in their frantic scramble late in the season just to make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''The advantage for us is we had to face that kind of game for the last 20 games, even more important I would say,'' Jagr said. ''We couldn't lose. Every game we play, we couldn't lose. Now, there is a time for error. I thought that would get us ready.''</p>
        <p>The fans filled the arena with the Thrashers' blue jerseys and waved blue scarves given out at the door. They roared early in the game, even giving their goalie, Kari Lehtonen, a standing ovation after he made several consecutive saves.</p>
        <p>The Rangers played steadily despite the noise, following Jagr's goal with a power-play goal late in the first by defenseman Michal Rozsival. After Atlanta got its own power-play goal, by Éric Bélanger, in the final minute of the first, the Rangers kept doing just enough to stay ahead.</p>
        <p>Marcel Hossa scored by deflecting a shot by defenseman Fedor Tyutin in the second, and after Shane Hnidy scored to cut the Rangers' lead to 3-2, Michael Nylander scored when a shot by Petr Prucha popped out of Lehtonen's glove and onto Nylander's backhand.</p>
        <p>''I could feel that Kari wasn't as comfortable as he would like, but that's called experience,'' Thrashers Coach Bob Hartley said. ''You need to go through this at some point in your career.''</p>
        <p>For Rangers goalie Henrik Lundqvist, that experience came last year, the hard way. This time, he gave up a goal to Pascal Dupuis early in the third to make it a one-goal game and had to hold off an Atlanta onslaught to win.</p>
        <p>''The last 20 seconds felt like two minutes,'' Lundqvist said.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers did hold on, with Lundqvist making crucial saves. Their defense tried to make the simple plays, clearing the puck when it could, keeping it away from the front of the net. It was a remarkable display of poise.</p>
        <p>Despite losing, the Thrashers took confidence from their third period. Almost to a man, they said that they believed they took a while to shake their nerves and find their game and that they left the ice feeling like they had simply run out of time.</p>
        <p>''Especially when you score, you are one shot away from tying it, the crowd gets into it at home,'' Dupuis said. ''I really thought we were going to come back, but it's a good sign for the next game.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers have come to believe in living in the present, and by winning they also helped put their past behind them.</p>
        <p>''It's still in the back of your mind what happened last year with the sweep,'' Shanahan said, despite joining the team only this season. ''It was such a big high making the playoffs last year and such a big crash. We know now we can win in the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Rangers forward Marcel Hossa returned to the lineup after missing 16 games with a knee injury, playing against his brother Marian, a star for Atlanta. They started the game, facing each other for the face-off. ''It was nice,'' Marcel said. ''We didn't say anything to each other. We took it seriously.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
