<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="13biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4DA133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SALLIE MAE IN TALKS TO BE SOLD -- Sallie Mae, the nation's largest lender to college students, is in talks to be bought out by private equity in what could be a deal for more than $20 billion, people briefed on the discussions said. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>DOW FIRES 2 FOR PLANNING BUYOUT -- Dow Chemical fired two executives who it said held a series of secret meetings with bankers and prospective investors about selling the company in a leveraged buyout. [C1.]</p>
        <p>CBS CANCELS IMUS PROGRAM -- CBS brought the weeklong confrontation over racial and sexual insults by the radio host Don Imus to an end when it canceled the ''Imus in the Morning'' show, ending a program that had been broadcasting for more than 30 years.[C1.]</p>
        <p>FLYING INTO A MAELSTROM -- During Don Imus's week of public mortification, his backers began to see what he did not: the drumbeat was not going to stop. The Media Equation: David Carr. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A EUROPEAN POWERHOUSE -- Germany's transformation from Europe's sick man to its most stalwart performer, thanks to an export-led recovery, is one more sign that the rest of the world does not depend as much on the American economy as it once did. [C1.]</p>
        <p>ROYALTY DISPUTE IS SETTLED -- The company that manages the Beatles' commercial interests and the EMI Group, which holds the rights to the band's recordings, said that they had settled a dispute over royalties, renewing speculation that a deal to release the Beatles' music in digital form might be near. [C3.]</p>
        <p>APPLE DELAYS OPERATING SYSTEM -- Apple said that the introduction of the new version of its Macintosh OSX operating system would be delayed as much as four months because of quality issues. The company had previously said the program would ship this spring. [C3.]</p>
        <p>VIOLENT FILMS DRAWING YOUTH -- The entertainment industry's promise not to entice youth with their violent fare has been eroded by online promotions and a proliferation of unrated DVDs, a Federal Trade Commission report said. [C3.]</p>
        <p>MEASURING OFF-SOFA VIEWERSHIP -- The Nielsen Company will begin providing national ratings for TV viewing away from home in places like bars, hotels, gyms and offices. For some types of programs, such as sports shows, the new ratings may provide a significant boost. Advertising. [C5.]</p>
        <p>VONAGE CHIEF STEPS DOWN -- Vonage Holdings, the Internet phone company, said that Michael F. Snyder, who has led Vonage for slightly more than a year, had stepped down as chief executive. Jeffrey A. Citron, who founded the company, will serve as chief executive until a permanent successor is found. [C3.]</p>
        <p>RETAILERS SEE CLOUDS AHEAD -- After robust sales in March, there are signs that consumers are already spending less, and many stores that reported sales surpassing expectations last month warned of disappointments ahead. [C2.]</p>
        <p>JURY GETS NACCHIO CASE -- Jury deliberations began in the insider-trading trial of Joseph P. Nacchio, former chief executive of Qwest Communications International.[C8.]</p>
        <p>F.D.A. PANEL REJECTS MERCK DRUG -- A panel of federal drug advisers voted 20 to 1 to reject an application by Merck to sell its pain pill Arcoxia because of concerns the drug could cause as many as 30,000 heart attacks annually if widely used. [A14.]</p>
        <p>A FIRST FOR THE TOYOTA BOARD -- Toyota announced a management shuffle that would elevate the president of its North American operations, James E. Press, to be the first non-Japanese to sit on the automaker's board. [C4.]</p>
        <p>SIGNS OF A EUROPEAN RATE INCREASE -- The European Central Bank fed widespread expectations that it would raise interest rates again in June, its eighth increase since December 2005. [C4.]</p>
        <p>THE COSTS OF NOTORIETY -- Hundreds of venture capitalists will gather in Washington next week. Among the questions on the table: Is private equity -- including venture capital -- becoming too public for its own good? V.C. Nation. [C6.]</p>
        <p>THE INVASION OF MUMBAI -- Mumbai, India's financial capital, is under siege as foreign investment banks and brokerage firms jostle for office space and bid for employees. [C6.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>The number of workers filing new claims for jobless benefits rose last week to the highest level in two months. Another report said that import prices jumped 1.7 percent in March as crude oil futures prices surged. (AP)</p>
        <p>The drug company MedImmune said that it was willing to consider takeover offers because of interest from big pharmaceutical companies and investor unhappiness with the company's performance. (AP)</p>
        <p>Nestlé, the food and drink company, announced that it would buy the Gerber Products Company for $5.5 billion, giving the world's biggest food and drink company the largest share of the global baby food market. (AP)</p>
        <p>Jurors at the fraud trial of the toppled newspaper tycoon Conrad M. Black were told that Hollinger executives relied on the advice of outside lawyers and accountants for how to account for the payments they had made to themselves. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>Pier 1 Imports, the home furnishings retailer, reported a wider quarterly loss and lower sales as customers gave a cool reception to its revamped product selection. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>The case of the former vice chairman of Wal-Mart Stores, Thomas M. Coughlin, was back in court as an appellate court took up a prosecutor's plea that Mr. Coughlin's sentence was too light. (REUTERS)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SALLIE MAE IN TALKS TO BE SOLD -- Sallie Mae, the nation's largest lender to college students, is in talks to be bought out by private equity in what could be a deal for more than $20 billion, people briefed on the discussions said. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>DOW FIRES 2 FOR PLANNING BUYOUT -- Dow Chemical fired two executives who it said held a series of secret meetings with bankers and prospective investors about selling the company in a leveraged buyout. [C1.]</p>
        <p>CBS CANCELS IMUS PROGRAM -- CBS brought the weeklong confrontation over racial and sexual insults by the radio host Don Imus to an end when it canceled the ''Imus in the Morning'' show, ending a program that had been broadcasting for more than 30 years.[C1.]</p>
        <p>FLYING INTO A MAELSTROM -- During Don Imus's week of public mortification, his backers began to see what he did not: the drumbeat was not going to stop. The Media Equation: David Carr. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A EUROPEAN POWERHOUSE -- Germany's transformation from Europe's sick man to its most stalwart performer, thanks to an export-led recovery, is one more sign that the rest of the world does not depend as much on the American economy as it once did. [C1.]</p>
        <p>ROYALTY DISPUTE IS SETTLED -- The company that manages the Beatles' commercial interests and the EMI Group, which holds the rights to the band's recordings, said that they had settled a dispute over royalties, renewing speculation that a deal to release the Beatles' music in digital form might be near. [C3.]</p>
        <p>APPLE DELAYS OPERATING SYSTEM -- Apple said that the introduction of the new version of its Macintosh OSX operating system would be delayed as much as four months because of quality issues. The company had previously said the program would ship this spring. [C3.]</p>
        <p>VIOLENT FILMS DRAWING YOUTH -- The entertainment industry's promise not to entice youth with their violent fare has been eroded by online promotions and a proliferation of unrated DVDs, a Federal Trade Commission report said. [C3.]</p>
        <p>MEASURING OFF-SOFA VIEWERSHIP -- The Nielsen Company will begin providing national ratings for TV viewing away from home in places like bars, hotels, gyms and offices. For some types of programs, such as sports shows, the new ratings may provide a significant boost. Advertising. [C5.]</p>
        <p>VONAGE CHIEF STEPS DOWN -- Vonage Holdings, the Internet phone company, said that Michael F. Snyder, who has led Vonage for slightly more than a year, had stepped down as chief executive. Jeffrey A. Citron, who founded the company, will serve as chief executive until a permanent successor is found. [C3.]</p>
        <p>RETAILERS SEE CLOUDS AHEAD -- After robust sales in March, there are signs that consumers are already spending less, and many stores that reported sales surpassing expectations last month warned of disappointments ahead. [C2.]</p>
        <p>JURY GETS NACCHIO CASE -- Jury deliberations began in the insider-trading trial of Joseph P. Nacchio, former chief executive of Qwest Communications International.[C8.]</p>
        <p>F.D.A. PANEL REJECTS MERCK DRUG -- A panel of federal drug advisers voted 20 to 1 to reject an application by Merck to sell its pain pill Arcoxia because of concerns the drug could cause as many as 30,000 heart attacks annually if widely used. [A14.]</p>
        <p>A FIRST FOR THE TOYOTA BOARD -- Toyota announced a management shuffle that would elevate the president of its North American operations, James E. Press, to be the first non-Japanese to sit on the automaker's board. [C4.]</p>
        <p>SIGNS OF A EUROPEAN RATE INCREASE -- The European Central Bank fed widespread expectations that it would raise interest rates again in June, its eighth increase since December 2005. [C4.]</p>
        <p>THE COSTS OF NOTORIETY -- Hundreds of venture capitalists will gather in Washington next week. Among the questions on the table: Is private equity -- including venture capital -- becoming too public for its own good? V.C. Nation. [C6.]</p>
        <p>THE INVASION OF MUMBAI -- Mumbai, India's financial capital, is under siege as foreign investment banks and brokerage firms jostle for office space and bid for employees. [C6.]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing  Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>The number of workers filing new claims for jobless benefits rose last week to the highest level in two months. Another report said that import prices jumped 1.7 percent in March as crude oil futures prices surged. (AP)</p>
        <p>The drug company MedImmune said that it was willing to consider takeover offers because of interest from big pharmaceutical companies and investor unhappiness with the company's performance. (AP)</p>
        <p>Nestlé, the food and drink company, announced that it would buy the Gerber Products Company for $5.5 billion, giving the world's biggest food and drink company the largest share of the global baby food market. (AP)</p>
        <p>Jurors at the fraud trial of the toppled newspaper tycoon Conrad M. Black were told that Hollinger executives relied on the advice of outside lawyers and accountants for how to account for the payments they had made to themselves. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>Pier 1 Imports, the home furnishings retailer, reported a wider quarterly loss and lower sales as customers gave a cool reception to its revamped product selection. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>The case of the former vice chairman of Wal-Mart Stores, Thomas M. Coughlin, was back in court as an appellate court took up a prosecutor's plea that Mr. Coughlin's sentence was too light. (REUTERS)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
