<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trail Led to Macao as Focus of North Korean Corruption</title>
    <meta content="13macao" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/world/asia/13macao.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assets, Frozen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Money Laundering</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Macao</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenlees, Donald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lague, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Macao</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Macao</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Counterfeit Money and Financial Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Counterfeit Money and Financial Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Macao</location>
        <location class="online_producer">North Korea</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hong Kong</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">North Korea</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFDB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trail Led to Macao as Focus of North Korean Corruption</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trail Led to Macao as Focus of North Korean Corruption</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONALD GREENLEES and DAVID LAGUE; Donald Greenlees reported from Hong Kong, and David Lague from Beijing and Macao.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lague, David; Greenlees, Donald</byline>
      <dateline>HONG KONG, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States decision to place financial sanctions against Macao bank became major sticking point in international efforts to dismantle North Korea's nuclear weapons; decision was prompted by investigations of smuggling and money laundering, resulting in conclusion that criminals linked to North Korea were laundering their earnings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For American law enforcement agencies the smuggling investigations were among their most elaborate, producing dozens of arrests and hard evidence that Chinese criminal gangs had smuggled counterfeit United States currency, cigarettes and drugs made in North Korea into the United States.</p>
        <p>The investigations, concluded 20 months ago, also produced a money trail that led to the Chinese gambling enclave of Macao, where American investigators concluded that criminals linked to North Korea were laundering their earnings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investigations produced evidence that Chinese criminal gangs had smuggled counterfeit currency, cigarettes and drugs made in North Korea into the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For American law enforcement agencies the smuggling investigations were among their most elaborate, producing dozens of arrests and hard evidence that Chinese criminal gangs had smuggled counterfeit United States currency, cigarettes and drugs made in North Korea into the United States.</p>
        <p>The investigations, concluded 20 months ago, also produced a money trail that led to the Chinese gambling enclave of Macao, where American investigators concluded that criminals linked to North Korea were laundering their earnings.</p>
        <p>This effort produced the hard evidence for the United States to place financial sanctions against Banco Delta Asia, a small, family-owned bank in Macao, near Hong Kong. But those sanctions became a major sticking point in international efforts to dismantle North Korea's nuclear weapons program.</p>
        <p>The investigations ''were just incontrovertible proof of the role of Macao banks, Macao gangsters, North Koreans in Macao,'' said David Asher, an outspoken critic of North Korea who at the time of the investigation was one of the most senior State Department officials dealing with the country.</p>
        <p>''In effect, they also demonstrated the awareness of the Macao authorities to these things,'' he said. ''This stuff was going on on such a large scale, going through several different banks.''</p>
        <p>As a result of the sanctions, accounts linked to North Korea at Banco Delta Asia holding about $25 million were frozen.</p>
        <p>North Korea had refused to move ahead with a plan to deal with its nuclear program unless the funds were released, and this week, after protracted wrangling, the last obstacles were removed.</p>
        <p>But information collected in the course of the Treasury Department's investigations gave it the grounds to designate Banco Delta Asia as a ''primary money-laundering concern'' under the USA Patriot Act and to consider applying the same designation to much larger banks operating in Macao, including the local branch of the Bank of China. The owners of Banco Delta Asia have denied any wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has not acted against the Bank of China, and its officials in Beijing did not respond to questions about the American findings.</p>
        <p>The declaration against Banco Delta Asia had immediate and far-reaching results, though. A run on the bank by customers drained about $133 million, about one-third of its deposits, said the bank's lawyers.</p>
        <p>The Monetary Authority of Macao replaced the management of the bank and froze the $25 million held in North Korea-linked accounts. Macao, which has attracted billions of dollars of American and other foreign investment into a casino-building boom, was forced to tighten laws against money laundering and criminal banking activity.</p>
        <p>The Macao Government Information Bureau did not respond to questions about the bank, and a request for an interview with the head of the Monetary Authority of Macao went unanswered.</p>
        <p>Banks around the world, fearing exclusion from the American banking system, started to shun business with North Korea, setting off an informal financial embargo of that country.</p>
        <p>By the time North Korea tested a nuclear device in October and returned to nuclear disarmament talks, one of its chief demands was that the frozen funds be released.</p>
        <p>When the United States moved against the bank, it was clear that the Bush administration believed it had a strong case. North Korea's links to trafficking narcotics and counterfeit products were widely documented in numerous law enforcement investigations and prosecutions over many years, including in Japan and Taiwan.</p>
        <p>In its action, the Treasury Department accused the bank of a range of financial crimes on behalf of North Korean clients. It also accused some of the bank's North Korean clients of involvement in drug trafficking, facilitating the sale of unconventional weapons and smuggling counterfeit cigarettes.</p>
        <p>But American officials made no mention of the two racketeering investigations that had ended a month earlier, which produced evidence of illicit financial transactions through Macao that was strong enough to be presented in court and meet the test for designating banks as money-laundering concerns, said American officials who reviewed the results of the investigations.</p>
        <p>According to briefings given in August 2005 by Justice Department officials, the investigations produced 59 arrests as a result of more than four years of work involving the use of undercover agents who posed as members of an organized crime group.</p>
        <p>The contraband seized by law enforcement agencies included about $4.5 million in counterfeit $100 bills, and millions of dollars of counterfeit cigarettes, Ecstasy pills and fake Viagra.</p>
        <p>During one phase of the undercover operation, Justice Department officials said two agents had acted as lovers and had led their contacts in the smuggling ring to believe they planned a wedding aboard a boat moored off Atlantic City. Many of the arrests were made as guests showed up for the wedding.</p>
        <p>Large parts of the indictments prepared by federal prosecutors in New Jersey and California, including details of financial transactions and banks used by the criminal organization, remain sealed.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Asher, who at the time of the investigations was coordinator of the State Department's North Korea Working Group, said in an interview that investigators had been able to track the financial pathways used by the smuggling operation. ''Banco Delta was one place they put their money,'' he said. But he added that the investigations also pointed to almost every bank in Macao.</p>
        <p>Another former State Department official, Matthew Daley, agreed with Mr. Asher's account of the evidence produced by the investigations. ''I am personally convinced it is a really solid case,'' said Mr. Daley, who was deputy assistant secretary of state for East Asian and Pacific affairs until January 2005.</p>
        <p>Officials from the United States Justice Department and the Treasury Department declined to respond to written questions about Mr. Asher's statements.</p>
        <p>But from the outset, the owner of Banco Delta Asia, Stanley Au, who has a high profile in Macao and is an adviser to China's central government, has said his bank did nothing wrong. ''There was no evidence that B.D.A. and its subsidiaries participated or were involved in the illicit activities as stated, and B.D.A. and its subsidiaries deny such allegations,'' Mr. Au said in a statement on March 26.</p>
        <p>Still, the Macao government removed him from the bank's management, and the bank immediately cut all ties with North Korea. The accounts of about 50 entities were closed, including North Korean banks, companies and individuals, according to a letter from the bank's lawyers to the Treasury Department.</p>
        <p>The Treasury Department has praised Macao's get-tough stance, including new anti-money-laundering laws, but Treasury finalized a ruling against the bank last month that barred it from doing any business with American financial institutions. Treasury said its ''primary concern'' was that Macao had not taken steps to bar Mr. Au from returning to the bank.</p>
        <p>Yet Banco Delta Asia had never been the main offender in Macao. ''The fact is that Banco Delta was an easy target in the sense that it was not so large that its failure would bring down the financial system,'' said Mr. Asher, who is now a senior associate fellow with the Asian Studies Center of the Heritage Foundation.</p>
        <p>''Banco Delta may be a sacrificial lamb in some people's minds, but it is not about Banco Delta,'' he said. ''It's about Macao, Macao's government, China, the Chinese government and their complicity and their accommodative behavior toward North Korea's illegal activities, proliferation activities and leadership financial activities.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
