<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chief Executive Resigns From Vonage; Founder Returns</title>
    <meta content="13vonage" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/business/13vonage.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070417T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Vonage</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Verizon Communications</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Citron, Jeffrey A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chief Executive Resigns From Vonage; Founder Returns</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vonage’s Chief Executive Steps Down</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jeffrey A. Citron is back at the helm of Vonage Holdings, the Internet phone company he founded seven years ago, which has stumbled lately amid intense competition and a bruising lawsuit.</p>
        <p>The company announced yesterday that Michael F. Snyder, who has led Vonage for slightly more than a year, stepped down as chief executive Wednesday and also resigned his board seat. Mr. Citron, Vonage's chairman and its largest individual shareholder, said he would act as chief executive only until the company found a permanent successor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The successor immediately announced plans to restructure the company and slash marketing costs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jeffrey A. Citron is back at the helm of Vonage Holdings, the Internet phone company he founded seven years ago, which has stumbled lately amid intense competition and a bruising lawsuit.</p>
        <p>The company announced yesterday that Michael F. Snyder, who has led Vonage for slightly more than a year, stepped down as chief executive Wednesday and also resigned his board seat. Mr. Citron, Vonage's chairman and its largest individual shareholder, said he would act as chief executive only until the company found a permanent successor.</p>
        <p>Vonage's patent battle with Verizon Communications is continuing to intensify, fueling concern that the dispute is taking a toll on Vonage's financial performance.</p>
        <p>In a conference call with investors early yesterday, Mr. Citron announced plans to rethink the marketing strategy, lay off 10 percent of the 1,800 workers and reduce marketing costs by $110 million in 2007, a cut of nearly a quarter. The company said it would save another $30 million annually by reducing other expenses.</p>
        <p>''The whole entire marketing strategy is going to be under review over the next few days,'' Mr. Citron said. He defended the cuts, saying that while less marketing could result in fewer new subscribers, the improved efficiency would enhance the value of each new line.</p>
        <p>Investors appeared to applaud the changes. Shares of Vonage rose nearly 7 percent, or 20 cents a share, after the company announced the changes, closing at $3.20.</p>
        <p>Vonage was one of the first to offer a low-cost phone service that transmits calls over the Internet rather than over standard phone and wireless networks. But competition has recently become heated as well-established telephone and cable companies have begun offering low-cost service packages.</p>
        <p>Vonage went public last May in a highly publicized offering priced at $17. The shares fell nearly 13 percent on the first day, closing at $14.85, and have lost more than 80 percent of their value since then.</p>
        <p>In the patent dispute, Verizon accuses Vonage, based in Holmdel, N.J., of violating patents covering technology for making voice calls over the Internet.</p>
        <p>Last Friday, Vonage endured a roller coaster day in court when a federal judge in Alexandria, Va., barred the company from signing up new customers, citing a jury decision in early March that found Vonage in violation of three Verizon patents. Later in the day, a federal appeals court gave Vonage a temporary stay of that injunction, permitting it to sign on new customers while it appeals the lower court ruling.</p>
        <p>The company has already been ordered to pay $58 million in damages and royalties of 5.5 percent. Yesterday, a federal judge denied Verizon's request to require Vonage to post $255 million in bonds during the appeal, a move that would have seriously depleted Vonage's cash reserves and hampered its ability to market its service.</p>
        <p>Vonage is seeking to make the stay permanent, but it is far from certain that the appeals judge will grant its request. A hearing is scheduled for April 24.</p>
        <p>In the conference call with investors, Vonage executives said they were certain the company would ultimately prevail.</p>
        <p>Sharon A. O'Leary, Vonage's chief legal officer, said the court's decision was based on an overly broad definition of Verizon's patents. Ms. O'Leary said she expected the appeals process to take up to two years.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Vonage is developing ''workaround'' technology that would avoid Verizon's patents, but that process is still in the design phase.</p>
        <p>Richard Greenfield, an analyst with Pali Research, said that the lawsuit made it difficult to judge whether Vonage was making any real progress in its business.</p>
        <p>''There are so many moving pieces that it's hard to say if things are getting better or worse,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Executives at the company, which has yet to turn a profit, said first-quarter revenue was about $195 million, slightly below analysts' forecast of $197.4 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Citron conceded that Vonage was not meeting expectations in its core business and that its marketing programs had been ''disappointing.'' Yet the company is not seeing any widespread loss of customers as a result of the Verizon suit.</p>
        <p>The company said it added 166,000 net phone lines in the first quarter, ending the quarter with 2.39 million lines in service, meaning that for every two new subscribers, one current subscriber left.</p>
        <p>During the first quarter the company reduced its acquisition cost to $275 a subscriber, down from $306 in the previous quarter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Citron's return is the latest in a series of second acts for founders in the technology industry, including Michael S. Dell's return to leadership of Dell Inc. in February.</p>
        <p>Mr. Citron's history is tainted slightly by an accusation by the Securities and Exchange Commission that he committed fraud while an executive of the Tyco Corporation. Mr. Citron and the S.E.C. settled that dispute in 2003, but it was the main reason behind Vonage's decision last year to have Mr. Citron step aside just months before the company's initial public offering.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 17, 2007, Tuesday  An article in Business Day on Friday about the return of Jeffrey A. Citron, founder of the Internet phone company Vonage, to be its chief executive misstated the company he was with in the late 1990s when he was accused of fraud by the Securities and Exchange Commission. Mr. Citron was an executive at Datek Online Holdings, not the Tyco Corporation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 17, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Friday about the return of Jeffrey A. Citron, founder of the Internet phone company Vonage, to be its chief executive misstated the company he was with in the late 1990s when he was accused of fraud by the Securities and Exchange Commission. Mr. Citron was an executive at Datek Online Holdings, not the Tyco Corporation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
