<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Owners And Same Struggles In Nation's Capital</title>
    <meta content="13nationals" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/sports/baseball/13nationals.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Washington Nationals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Nationals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Acta, Manny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E1DA133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Owners And Same Struggles In Nation's Capital</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Early-Season Losses Mount, the Nationals Look to the Future</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Washington Nationals played their first opening day game at home under their new ownership last week at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium, their fans complained about the late delivery of season tickets, parking problems and cold hot dogs at the concession stands.</p>
        <p>What else could go wrong? Only the pitching, the fielding, the hitting and the health of the players. Before the Nationals beat Atlanta, 2-0, here Thursday night to improve to 2-8 over all, they were on a six-game losing streak. On Thursday, Washington starter Jason Bergmann gave up one hit in six innings and Chad Cordero got the save despite allowing the Braves to load the bases in the ninth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Washington Nationals, with the third-lowest payroll in the major leagues, have started the season 2-8. But with a new stadium on the way, there are signs of hope for the future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Washington Nationals played their first opening day game at home under their new ownership last week at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium, their fans complained about the late delivery of season tickets, parking problems and cold hot dogs at the concession stands.</p>
        <p>What else could go wrong? Only the pitching, the fielding, the hitting and the health of the players. Before the Nationals beat Atlanta, 2-0, here Thursday night to improve to 2-8 over all, they were on a six-game losing streak. On Thursday, Washington starter Jason Bergmann gave up one hit in six innings and Chad Cordero got the save despite allowing the Braves to load the bases in the ninth.</p>
        <p>''If I would have blown this it would have been devastating to me and to the whole team,'' Cordero said.</p>
        <p>Three players were already injured on a roster with the third-lowest payroll in the major leagues, $36 million. Several others fought the flu as the team prepared to travel to New York for a three-game series with the Mets, a team that last year employed Manny Acta as a third-base coach.</p>
        <p>Acta, the Nationals' first-year manager, is 38, the youngest manager in the majors and the only current one from the Dominican Republic. He kept the clubhouse closed longer than usual after Wednesday's 8-3 defeat to speak to his team.</p>
        <p>''It's time to cut it off,'' he said of the losing streak, but not of his beard. Earlier, he joked that he would not shave his fledgling goatee until the team started winning. Acta said it was important that his players not start to believe that, 'Jeez, we might be as bad as people are saying.' ''</p>
        <p>The Nationals were wards of Major League Baseball as the Montreal Expos from early 2002 through 2004 and for almost two seasons after that in the District of Columbia until the franchise was sold last season to the Theodore Lerner family for $450 million.</p>
        <p>The owners, who are real estate developers, are rebuilding the operation even as the city spends $611 million on a stadium to open next year. Much is promised by Stan Kasten, the new team president, who built the Braves into a perennial contender in his previous job.</p>
        <p>For the time being, however, the Nationals resemble not so much the current Braves but the old Washington Senators, who inspired the witticism that the nation's capital was ''first in war, first in peace and last in the American League.''</p>
        <p>Kasten said he understood the frustration of a city that went without a major league team from 1972 through 2004. But he takes a longer view.</p>
        <p>''To build a stadium from scratch and a franchise from scratch in the most important city in the world is the coolest challenge that there is,'' Kasten said. ''I'm pretty confident it's going to happen quicker than what most people expect.''</p>
        <p>He said he was more prepared for the challenges of rebuilding than the news media and the fans because he went through the same process with the Braves. But, he acknowledged, ''For the next little while, I'm going to be the village idiot every night.''</p>
        <p>The Nationals are a curious collection. After trimming $25 million in payroll, they invited 37 pitchers to training camp. The 2007 starting rotation won a total of two major league games last season. Their ace is the right-hander John Patterson, who is coming off arm surgery.</p>
        <p>Their cleanup hitter, Dmitri Young, is a first baseman shed late last season by Detroit. As the Tigers were on their way to the World Series, Young battled depression, alcohol abuse and domestic-violence charges.</p>
        <p>He joined camp on a minor league contract and did not have many other options. But he used to play for Jim Bowden, the Nationals' general manager, when both were in Cincinnati. Because Nick Johnson is still recovering from a broken leg, Young found work. ''I let God take care of the situation, and he did,'' Young said.</p>
        <p>He knows something about miraculous franchise turnarounds. Young played for the Tigers in 2003 when they lost 119 games. He said he could share his perspective with the many young players around him.</p>
        <p>''You get beat up and you learn from it,'' Young said. ''This team is going to start spending money next year. Whether I'm here or not, I'm going to wish these guys well. They have a top-notch organization and a lot of young guys who want to prove themselves in the big leagues.''</p>
        <p>Young, 33, noted that he was only five years younger than Acta. Among the younger players with the highest potential is Ryan Zimmerman, the 22-year-old third baseman who finished second last year in the voting for National League rookie of the year with a batting average of .287, 20 home runs and 110 runs batted in.</p>
        <p>''The experience I'm getting is going to help me a lot later in my career,'' Zimmerman said. ''I'm very lucky to have the opportunity I have at the age I'm at.'' As for this season, he said: ''There's no way it can go like this all year. It's still early. There's plenty of time to turn it around.''</p>
        <p>And there is much to turn around. In Wednesday's loss, a throw to second base by pitcher Jerome Williams skipped out to center field. A throw toward home plate by left fielder Kory Casto skipped by a cutoff man as a run scored.</p>
        <p>With one out and his team trailing by two runs, shortstop Felipe López inexplicably tried to steal third base and was thrown out. The Nationals lead the majors in errors with 11. After second baseman Ronnie Belliard dropped a pop-up to aid a Braves rally on Tuesday, he said, ''Nobody's perfect.''</p>
        <p>Kasten has vowed to build the farm system. He said he was surprised to discover that the Nationals had no minor league prospects from the Dominican Republic, so the team spent $1.4 million to sign Esmailyn Gonzalez, a 17-year-old switch-hitting shortstop known as Smiley who will play for Class A Vermont this summer.</p>
        <p>One reason Acta was hired, Kasten said, was that he managed the Dominican Republic last spring in the World Baseball Classic. José Rijo, a former Reds pitcher from the Dominican Republic, is a special assistant to the general manager and is chief administrator of the Nationals' Dominican Academy in San Cristobal.</p>
        <p>''Dominicans are fairly important to modern-day baseball,'' Kasten said with wry understatement. The Nationals' presence in Latin America, he said, was being announced ''with big, bold, neon letters.''</p>
        <p>Other repairs completed or in progress include improving the television exposure in a region shared with the Baltimore Orioles and healing a rift with Frank Robinson, the former manager who left with harsh words after he was not retained in a front-office position. The Nationals want to hold a ''Frank Robinson Day'' at R.F.K.</p>
        <p>''We continue to leave that door open,'' Kasten said. As for all the problems the fans faced on opening day, Kasten said, ''I saw a lot of things that need to be fixed and need to be changed, and they will be.''</p>
        <p>For now, the Nationals' winning percentage of .200 puts Washington exactly where the city ranks alphabetically among 30 teams: last. But in sports, ''W'' also stands for ''win.'' Beyond the fence in the new stadium, they are planting cherry trees, establishing roots, hoping things soon blossom.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
