<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drinks With Youth Appeal Draw Growing Opposition</title>
    <meta content="13drink" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/us/13drink.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcohol Abuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marshall, Carolyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcohol Abuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDC133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drinks With Youth Appeal Draw Growing Opposition</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Drinks With Youth Appeal Draw Growing Opposition</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLYN MARSHALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marshall, Carolyn</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Health reseachers say flavored alcoholic beverages that look and taste like soda have become popular with young drinkers, especially girls, who often dislike taste of alcohol but are curious about it; opposition to beverages, in turn, is gaining momentum; critics, including state lawmakers, say products are contributing to under-age drinking; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three years ago, at the age of 15, Jimmy Jordan says, he got his first taste of what it was like ''to be cool and fit in.'' While watching a video with friends, a buddy urged him to try a Smirnoff Ice, one of dozens of flavored alcoholic beverages that look and taste like soda but offer the kick of a cocktail.</p>
        <p>''It tasted like a Sprite with a splash of 7-Up,'' said Mr. Jordan, now a senior at Elk Grove High School near here. ''It didn't taste at all like alcohol.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Products like Mike’s Hard Lemonade, Bacardi Silver and Zima have become popular with young drinkers, health researchers say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three years ago, at the age of 15, Jimmy Jordan says, he got his first taste of what it was like ''to be cool and fit in.'' While watching a video with friends, a buddy urged him to try a Smirnoff Ice, one of dozens of flavored alcoholic beverages that look and taste like soda but offer the kick of a cocktail.</p>
        <p>''It tasted like a Sprite with a splash of 7-Up,'' said Mr. Jordan, now a senior at Elk Grove High School near here. ''It didn't taste at all like alcohol.''</p>
        <p>Health researchers say that is one reason products like Mike's Hard Lemonade, Bacardi Silver and Zima have become popular with young drinkers, especially girls, who often dislike the taste of alcohol but are curious about it.</p>
        <p>Opposition to the beverages, in turn, is gaining momentum. Critics, including youth counselors and state lawmakers, say the products are contributing to under-age drinking.</p>
        <p>''These drinks are a transitional, training beer,'' said Jim Kooler, the administrator of California Friday Night Live, a state-sponsored group that promotes healthy lifestyles for teenagers. ''They represent an insidious strategy to get teens comfortable with alcohol.''</p>
        <p>With guidance from Dr. Kooler, several youth groups in California have asked the State Board of Equalization, which taxes alcoholic beverages, to adopt stricter rules for drinks that contain distilled spirits but are sold and taxed as beer.</p>
        <p>Maine has already reclassified the drinks, commonly known as alcopops and flavored malt beverages, as hard liquor. There are proposals to do the same in Arkansas, Illinois and Nebraska. The California board is holding a series of public hearings, including one in May, that could lead to new restrictions by the end of the summer.</p>
        <p>If the drinks in California were reclassified as hard liquor, they would become more expensive (the tax would jump to $3.30 a gallon from 20 cents a gallon) and more difficult to buy (they would no longer be sold in the state's 24,000 convenience stores).</p>
        <p>''The price will go up, and that will make it harder for kids to afford,'' said Mr. Jordan, the high school student, who never acquired a taste for alcohol and is among a dozen youth leaders pushing for the changes.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the effort in California, including small-business owners, the Flavored Malt Beverage Coalition and other industry groups, argue that the debate about the drinks is surrounded by ''significant misconceptions,'' in the words of Gary Galanis, a spokesman for Diageo, one of the world's largest alcohol manufacturers and the maker of Smirnoff.</p>
        <p>Mr. Galanis and others say flavored malt beverages are roughly as potent as beer, containing 5 percent to 7 percent alcohol per volume compared with 4 percent to 6 percent in beer. The drinks come from brewing not distilling, he said, and the alcohol in the beverages stems from added flavoring, not hard liquor.</p>
        <p>''There is no reason to change the definition of the product,'' Mr. Galanis said.</p>
        <p>But Jim Mosher, a lawyer with the Pacific Institute for Research and Evaluation, an independent public health group that studies under-age drinking, said the arguments offered by the industry were ''nonissues under the law.''</p>
        <p>''If beer has alcohol in it, it's a distilled spirit,'' Mr. Mosher said. ''It doesn't matter what you start with. You look at the end product.''</p>
        <p>Flavored alcoholic drinks have been sold for decades, with wine coolers greatly expanding the market in the 1980s. Producers moved from wine to beer bases in the 1990s with hard lemonades and teas that often included flavorings containing alcohol.</p>
        <p>A Federal Trade Commission report in 2003 found no evidence that the industry had intentionally focused on minors, but many parents and other critics have complained about the advertising.</p>
        <p>''Everything about the product, its placement, color, name, targets teens,'' said Steve Powell, whose daughter Alix, 14, participates in the anti-alcopop campaign in California.</p>
        <p>The federal Department of Health and Human Services estimates that more than 10 million Americans under age 21 drink alcohol. A federally financed survey by the University of Michigan of 50,000 students at more than 400 schools found that 26.8 percent of eighth graders, 48.8 percent of 10th graders and 54.7 percent of 12th graders drank one or more alcopops in 2006.</p>
        <p>At McClatchy High School here in Sacramento, several students acknowledged that drinking was common but they described alcopops as the drink of last resort.</p>
        <p>''Most high school students drink with a purpose: to get drunk,'' said Nina Hankard, 17, a senior. ''Alcopops are not very effective unless you are a lightweight.''</p>
        <p>She and several other girls said teenagers prefer shots of whiskey or vodka, chased with soda.</p>
        <p>Julia Jones, 17, said drinking a syrupy beverage seemed counterproductive.</p>
        <p>''Personally, I want to get the drinking part over with,'' Ms. Jones said. ''You want something fast. It's not about walking around, nursing a drink.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hankard said her earliest experience with drinking involved an alcopop. But the drink was not exactly a stepping stone.</p>
        <p>''Kids don't need a transfer drink,'' she said. ''They are going to go to hard liquor anyway. It's not like we need to be trained.''</p>
        <p>The alcohol industry says the real problem with under-age drinking is access to alcohol, not alcopops. In March, the Distilled Spirits Council announced a public relations campaign directed, in part, at adults.</p>
        <p>''The numbers show under-age drinkers get the alcohol from siblings over 21 or parents,'' Mr. Galanis said. ''We have to work with them.''</p>
        <p>To that end, Diageo has actively sponsored legislation in 20 states, Mr. Galanis said, and bills have passed in Arizona, Colorado and Virginia. The bills are intended to penalize adults who provide alcohol, rather than to further regulate the product.</p>
        <p>But the industry has been unsuccessful in California, where Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger vetoed a bill in 2005 that would have defined the alcopop as beer. Heated public debates continued in 2006 but the industry gained little traction. Two new bills against alcopops were introduced in February.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the student petitioners, including Mr. Jordan, are preparing for a Board of Equalization hearing in May.</p>
        <p>''I've told the kids it's an uphill battle and they may not win,'' said Dr. Kooler, the Friday Night Live administrator. ''But there's a lesson either way: sometimes you don't win in politics, even if you're fighting the good fight.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
