<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Berkshires, Land of Dance, Art and Llamas</title>
    <meta content="13kids" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/travel/escapes/13kids.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839859"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEEKEND WITH THE KIDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Berkshires (Mass)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Massachusetts</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siwolop, Sana</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Berkshires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Berkshires (Mass)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE4DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Berkshires, Land of Dance, Art and Llamas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Berkshires, Land of Dance, Art and Llamas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANA SIWOLOP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siwolop, Sana</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Weekend With the Kids column on visit to Berkshires in western Massachusetts; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S easy spending a cultured weekend in the Berkshires, given the area's heady mix of some four dozen museums, theater companies, music festivals and historic homes. But this lushly scenic part of western Massachusetts also offers plenty of fun for even the most turbocharged families.</p>
        <p>Whether it's kayaking the Housatonic River, exploring an old abandoned granite quarry or biking the 11-mile-long Ashuwillticook Rail Trail, there's plenty to do outdoors. But for slightly less kinetic times, many of the area's cultural attractions play host to family-friendly gatherings like a jazz funk dance party at Mass MoCA, the area's contemporary arts center (www.massmoca.org). There are also offbeat events, like a trivia bee to be held in Great Barrington at the wonderfully restored Mahaiwe Theater (www.mahaiwe.org).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There’s music to listen to, trails to stroll, chocolates to eat and a fiberglass cow to milk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S easy spending a cultured weekend in the Berkshires, given the area's heady mix of some four dozen museums, theater companies, music festivals and historic homes. But this lushly scenic part of western Massachusetts also offers plenty of fun for even the most turbocharged families.</p>
        <p>Whether it's kayaking the Housatonic River, exploring an old abandoned granite quarry or biking the 11-mile-long Ashuwillticook Rail Trail, there's plenty to do outdoors. But for slightly less kinetic times, many of the area's cultural attractions play host to family-friendly gatherings like a jazz funk dance party at Mass MoCA, the area's contemporary arts center (www.massmoca.org). There are also offbeat events, like a trivia bee to be held in Great Barrington at the wonderfully restored Mahaiwe Theater (www.mahaiwe.org).</p>
        <p>Berkshire County stretches from the border of Connecticut on the south to the edge of Vermont on the north, and many of the area's attractions are seasonal, so plan ahead. In Hancock, for example, the Mountain Adventure Park at Jiminy Peak won't be open for activities like its Euro-bungee trampoline or rides along its new ''mountain coaster'' until the end of May. Travelers should also know that 3,491-foot-tall Mount Greylock, the highest point in Massachusetts, will be closed to cars until the spring of 2009 because of major construction in the area. Hikers can enjoy the 70 miles of trails in the area around the mountain, but car trips to the summit will have to wait.</p>
        <p>Attractions</p>
        <p>You can get a jump on summer by visiting Hancock Shaker Village (in Pittsfield, on Route 20, west Route 41, 800-817-1137; www.hancockshakervillage.org), a thoughtfully restored, 20-building village that depicts Shaker life on 1,200 acres of farm and woodland. Through April 22, the Round Stone Barn, built in 1826, will be turned into a spring nursery for newly born lambs, goats, piglets and calves. Children can help with farm chores, but if the idea doesn't go over well with your family, take a stroll to the Discovery Room for a chance to build a Shaker chair, or ''milk'' Mary Jane, a large fiberglass cow (look for water, not milk). Admission is $12.50 for adults, $4 for children 13 to 17, and free for 12 and younger.</p>
        <p>For an offbeat animal encounter, visit Richard Cleaver and his seven toothy but winsome llamas at Hawkmeadow Farm, a five-minute drive from downtown Lee (322 Lander Road, 413-243-2224; www.hawkmeadowllamas.com). The farm abuts land that includes October Mountain State Forest, and Mr. Cleaver offers family llama hikes that are up to two hours long, but on relatively easy terrain. All the llamas are good with children, but Magic, a black-and-white 12-year-old who is the brains of the herd, is especially willing to be led by 2- and 3-year-olds. During a recent hike, Mr. Cleaver pointed out local flora as well as animal tracks while our family of four happily hiked along with Magic, Handsome Jack, Cuzco and Tanner, the alpha male who likes to lead. A four-person hike costs $50 for the first hour, and $20 for the second hour. Hikes are scheduled by appointment only.</p>
        <p>The Norman Rockwell Museum in Stockbridge (9 Glendale Road, 413-298-4100; www.nrm.org) is always a popular draw, but for something different visit the Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute (225 South Street, Williamstown; 413-458-2303; www.clarkart.edu: free Nov. 1 to May 31, $12.50 for adults otherwise, always free for children). With a distinguished collection of American and European art, particularly French Impressionist paintings, the Clark looks like a formal art museum, but its 140-acre campus offers hiking trails and picnicking. The institute offers a family day almost every month, like the one planned for April 21, when children will be able to explore the myths and mosaics of ancient Rome and make their own togas.</p>
        <p>Downtime</p>
        <p>The Berkshires are filled with beguiling rest stops, like Catherine's Chocolates in Great Barrington (260 Stockbridge Road, 800-345-2462). Founded by Catherine Keresztes in 1957, the store is now run by fourth-generation members of her family, who offer a wonderland of treats, including a dozen flavors of fudge and 17 kinds of truffles. The store's best sellers are its cordial-stem cherries and chocolate Butterkrunch. Both are $19.95 a pound; mail order prices are slightly higher.</p>
        <p>In North Otis, many families like to stop at the Otis Poultry Farm (1570 North Main Road, 800-286-2690) even if they are not going to a performance at Jacob's Pillow, the dance festival in nearby Becket. The farm's poultry operations were shut down about a year ago, but there is still a large general store that manages to stop traffic, as well as a new cafe that serves breakfast, lunch and some 25 different kinds of pies. Before driving home, pick up one of the chicken or turkey pies, from $3.50 for an individual pie, to $12.99 for a pie that serves six.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Family dining in the Berkshires doesn't have to mean visiting one of the big restaurant chains now in the area, or eating at a high-brow establishment that is priced to match. For enjoyable, inexpensive fare, a long-standing favorite is Baba Louie's in downtown Great Barrington (286 Main Street, 413-528-8100). Seating can be tight at this tiny tropical-hued establishment, where reservations are not accepted, but the delicious, thin-crust pizzas -- with toppings as eclectic as dried figs, smoked gouda and roasted parsnips -- are outstanding, as are the salads. Plan on spending about $10.95 for a small pizza, which feeds one to two, and $15.95 for a large, which feeds two to three.</p>
        <p>Don't be put off by the old-time mariner's décor at Salmon Run Fish House, a reasonably priced family restaurant in downtown Lee that is a local favorite (78 Main Street, 413-243-3900). Adults can happily dine on fresh salmon prepared 10 different ways (garlic potato-crusted salmon is $15.95), as well as create their own seafood combination plates for $16.95, while kids can order smaller portions of seafood, as well as items like cheese ravioli and grilled steak. The signature dish here is a baked lobster pie, made from bits of Maine lobster in a sherry cream sauce ($22.95).</p>
        <p>Pretend you're eating inside a giant log cabin when you visit the Dakota Steakhouse on Route 7 in Pittsfield (1035 South Street, 413-499-7900). The restaurant gets a thumbs-up from families, who are particularly keen on the dinnertime salad bar, which comes with most entrees, and the Sunday buffet brunch, $16.95 for adults and $7.95 for children. During the summer, it's open for lunch, conveniently for concerts at Tanglewood.</p>
        <p>Where to Sleep</p>
        <p>The Comfort Inn &amp; Suites hotel on Route 7 (249 Stockbridge Road, Great Barrington; 413-644-3200;  www.berkshirecomfortinn.com ) is not inexpensive in summer or winter, but families generally come away happy from this three-story motor inn, where a stay includes amenities like breakfast, an indoor pool and in-room microwaves and refrigerators. In April and May, rooms with two double beds start at $120 a night.</p>
        <p>From the road, the Cranwell Resort, Spa &amp; Golf Club on Route 20 in Lenox (55 Lee Road, 413-637-1364; www.cranwell.com) looks like a Gilded Age retreat for adults only, but this 380-acre property gets high marks from families too. The 35,000-square-foot spa, one of the largest in the Northeast, is for adults only, but children are welcome at the outdoor and large indoor pools. Rather than staying in the mansion itself, opt for a room in Beecher's Cottage, the Carriage House, or one of the town houses. Spring and summer prices for cottage suites start at $395 a night.</p>
        <p>Design-savvy teenagers will like the Porches Inn (231 River Street, 413-664-0400; www.porches.com), an unconventional but comfortable place to stay in North Adams, across the street from Mass MoCA. It consists of eight old Victorian row houses, which used to be for mill workers and which now have vibrant hues, as well as two porches lined with rocking chairs. Inside, rooms have lots of vintage furniture and sometimes a clawfoot bathtub. From May through November, expect to pay between $195 and $410 a night for a room that sleeps four.</p>
        <p>WEEKEND WITH THE KIDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
