<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For New Jersey Governors, Plenty of Time on the Road Is a Job Requirement</title>
    <meta content="13travel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/nyregion/13travel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E0DA133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For New Jersey Governors, Plenty of Time on the Road Is a Job Requirement</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For New Jersey Governors, Plenty of Time on the Road Is a Job Requirement</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER 8. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Jennifer 8</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The perks of being a New Jersey governor are considerable: the power to appoint the entire state cabinet, and the availability of an ornate mansion named Drumthwacket to call home.</p>
        <p>But one downside of being governor is classically New Jersey: having to spend a lot of time in the car -- and a lot of time on the highway, in traffic, and on toll roads. That was the case yesterday when Gov. Jon S. Corzine was injured in a car accident while traveling from Atlantic City to Drumthwacket. New Jersey is one of the most compact states in the country; it can be traveled by car from north to south in some four hours. So unlike states like New York, California or Texas, where governors have to hop in a plane to get from one part of the state to the other, being too far away is never an excuse for missing an appointment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey was injured in a car accident Thursday, he was doing what most New Jersey governors do: spending a lot of time on the road.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The perks of being a New Jersey governor are considerable: the power to appoint the entire state cabinet, and the availability of an ornate mansion named Drumthwacket to call home.</p>
        <p>But one downside of being governor is classically New Jersey: having to spend a lot of time in the car -- and a lot of time on the highway, in traffic, and on toll roads. That was the case yesterday when Gov. Jon S. Corzine was injured in a car accident while traveling from Atlantic City to Drumthwacket. New Jersey is one of the most compact states in the country; it can be traveled by car from north to south in some four hours. So unlike states like New York, California or Texas, where governors have to hop in a plane to get from one part of the state to the other, being too far away is never an excuse for missing an appointment.</p>
        <p>''When you spend your day in Trenton, which is right in the middle of the state, everyone thinks that you can get from there to where they are,'' said Thomas H. Kean, the former New Jersey governor. ''There is no event in the state where people think that the governor shouldn't be there. So it means that the governor has to travel around a lot. Sometimes you will have to have three or four dinners a night.''</p>
        <p>A typical schedule can have a governor spending two or three hours of his day in a car -- and sometimes as much as two and a half hours at a stretch.</p>
        <p>Most governors use the traveling time for work, catching up with paperwork or making phone calls. Both Mr. Kean and former Gov. James E. McGreevey said the back seats of the cars became a second office. But Governor Corzine liked to sit in the front seat, which is where he was at the time of the accident.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGreevey said a ''different psychology'' was in play in New Jersey than in states like Nevada or Wyoming. where ''the expectation to be at an event at the other side of the state is so much less and flight is the norm as opposed to the exception.''</p>
        <p>New York, for example, has state-owned helicopters and twin-engine turboprop airplanes that can be used at the governor's discretion.</p>
        <p>''In New Jersey, by contrast, pulling up in a Buick is a typical route,'' Mr. McGreevey said.</p>
        <p>To be sure, New Jersey has a few aircraft on hand, though more modest ones. Helicopters that are often used for medical emergencies can also be used by governors.</p>
        <p>The responsibility of escorting the governor across the state falls to the state police, who typically provide a state trooper as a driver for the governor's car and an additional car with one or two other troopers as an escort.</p>
        <p>''They map out the most efficient routes. They are mindful about the ever-present New Jersey traffic jam,'' Mr. McGreevey said. Unlike the normal New Jersey commuter, however, the state trooper has access to better traffic information.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
