<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Was There a Ghost, or Just a Tunnel, At the Latest Subway Groundbreaking?</title>
    <meta content="13tunnel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/nyregion/13tunnel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Was There a Ghost, or Just a Tunnel, At the Latest Subway Groundbreaking?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Was There a Ghost? No, Just a Tunnel at the Latest Subway Groundbreaking</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM NEUMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Neuman, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The politicians and dignitaries sat on a stage about 40 feet under Second Avenue and 99th Street, at the dead end of a 35-foot-wide tunnel built in the 1970s for the on-again-off-again Second Avenue subway. The tunnel was sealed when New York City's fiscal crisis hit, and ever since then it has been waiting for a day like yesterday -- a day of cleansing spring rains and underground rites.</p>
        <p>With the latest groundbreaking, the Metropolitan Transportation Authority went to extremes to wash away the memory of its past failures on Second Avenue and create what it hoped would be a dramatic setting for a fresh start. It spent more than $40,000 to prepare the tunnel for the event, according to Jeremy Soffin, a spokesman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Politicians and dignitaries gathered Thursday at the latest groundbreaking for the on-again-off-again Second Avenue subway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The politicians and dignitaries sat on a stage about 40 feet under Second Avenue and 99th Street, at the dead end of a 35-foot-wide tunnel built in the 1970s for the on-again-off-again Second Avenue subway. The tunnel was sealed when New York City's fiscal crisis hit, and ever since then it has been waiting for a day like yesterday -- a day of cleansing spring rains and underground rites.</p>
        <p>With the latest groundbreaking, the Metropolitan Transportation Authority went to extremes to wash away the memory of its past failures on Second Avenue and create what it hoped would be a dramatic setting for a fresh start. It spent more than $40,000 to prepare the tunnel for the event, according to Jeremy Soffin, a spokesman.</p>
        <p>Workers used pressure-washing machines to clean the walls, ceiling and floor. They equipped the tunnel with new lights, rebuilt the stairs from the street and constructed a stage. There was even a screen on which they played a brief video that recounted the history of the Second Avenue subway and projected the confidence of officials that this time around trains would really run below Second Avenue. Guests at the ceremony were given copies of the video in bags adorned with a miniature keepsake pickax inscribed with yesterday's date.</p>
        <p>But for all that, the ceremony was haunted by the ghosts of broken promises.</p>
        <p>''Why is this groundbreaking different from all the other groundbreakings,'' joked Peter S. Kalikow, the authority's chairman, evoking the ritual question of Passover and the history of previous groundbreakings that had not led to a finished subway line.</p>
        <p>The answer, according to Mr. Kalikow and several other speakers, including Gov. Eliot Spitzer, was that this time the financing for the first section of the project -- from 96th Street to 63rd Street -- which is expected to cost $3.8 billion, is secure.</p>
        <p>Others at the ceremony included the Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, whose district is in Lower Manhattan; Representative Carolyn B. Maloney, who represents the Upper East Side; the chief executive of the transportation authority, Elliot G. Sander; the Manhattan borough president, Scott M. Stringer; the City Council speaker, Christine C. Quinn; the administrator of the Federal Transit Administration, James S. Simpson; members of the transportation authority's board; and the transit union's president, Roger Toussaint.</p>
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg was not on hand, however, making yesterday's ceremony the only Second Avenue subway groundbreaking on record without a mayor in attendance. He was in Cincinnati for an announcement about his campaign to keep illegal guns off the streets, and sent Deputy Mayor Daniel L. Doctoroff in his place.</p>
        <p>Planning for the Second Avenue subway dates back to the 1920s. Yesterday's ceremony was at least the fourth groundbreaking for the line. Three previous ones were held in 1972, 1973 and 1974 when politicians, including two governors (Nelson A. Rockefeller and Malcolm Wilson) and two mayors (John V. Lindsay and Abraham D. Beame) hacked away at the Manhattan pavement with pickaxes or jackhammers to symbolically start work on different segments of the project.</p>
        <p>Once yesterday's speeches were over, Mr. Sander announced, ''We are now going to hit the wall.''</p>
        <p>It turned out that no actual ground was going to be broken. A section of wall where the 1970s tunnel ended had been prepared with a false front of quick-drying cement, half an inch thick, which would fall away when it was tapped with a hammer.</p>
        <p>For that purpose, 11 shiny brick hammers with plastic-covered handles had been laid out on a table on the side of the stage.</p>
        <p>At that point, the delicate etiquette of breaking ground broke down. As soon as Mr. Sander made his announcement, a scrum of photographers rushed the stage and crowded around the governor.</p>
        <p>That blocked the view of the television cameras that had been set up farther away on stands and may have frustrated public relations officials at the authority, who had hoped to create an iconic image for the governor and their project for the evening news.</p>
        <p>The first section of the new subway will have stations along Second Avenue at 96th, 86th and 72nd Streets and at 63rd Street and Lexington Avenue.</p>
        <p>It will operate as an extension of the Q line and is scheduled to open in 2013. Plans call for the line to run from 125th Street to Lower Manhattan, but financing for work beyond the first section has not been arranged.</p>
        <p>Actual work will begin April 23. Workers will close two lanes of Second Avenue between 92nd and 95th Streets for preliminary excavation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
