<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italy Proposes Rules for Handling Abductions</title>
    <meta content="13kidnaps" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/world/europe/13kidnaps.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ramallah (West Bank)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">British Broadcasting Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mastrogiacomo, Daniele</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Naqshbandi, Ajmal</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'Alema, Massimo (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abbas, Mahmoud (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E2DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italy Proposes Rules for Handling Abductions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Italy Proposes Rules for Handling Abductions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER; Isabel Kershner contributed reporting from Jerusalem.</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Italy's fragile government is under fire for pressuring Afghan government to release five Taliban prisoners to win release of kidnapped Italian journalist Daniele Mastrogiacomo; criticism rises after Mastrogiacomo's Afghan interpretor Ajmal Naqshbandi is killed by Taliban; Foreign Min Massimo D'Alema, defending deal to free Mastrogiacomo, claims Italy thought trade for Mastrogiacomo included Naqshbandi; new appeals go out for Alan Johnston, BBC reporter kidnapped at gunpoint in Gaza month ago; BBC's director general Mark Thompson says at news conference in Ramallah that Palestinian Pres Mahmoud Abbas told him there is 'credible evidence' that Johnston is safe and well; Palestinian journalists in Gaza City rally for his release; about 18 foreign journalists and aid workers have been kidnapped in Gaza in past year, most of them released unharmed within hours or days; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Italy's fragile government, under fire for making a deal to free an Italian journalist in Afghanistan, on Thursday proposed international standards for confronting the rising number of high-profile kidnappings in war zones.</p>
        <p>The Italian move came as new appeals went out for Alan Johnston, the BBC reporter kidnapped at gunpoint in Gaza a month ago. In New York, the United Nations secretary general, Ban Ki-moon, called for Mr. Johnston's release, saying that freedom of the press should be protected ''as a matter of principle.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Italy’s government proposed international standards for confronting the rising number of high-profile kidnappings in war zones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Italy's fragile government, under fire for making a deal to free an Italian journalist in Afghanistan, on Thursday proposed international standards for confronting the rising number of high-profile kidnappings in war zones.</p>
        <p>The Italian move came as new appeals went out for Alan Johnston, the BBC reporter kidnapped at gunpoint in Gaza a month ago. In New York, the United Nations secretary general, Ban Ki-moon, called for Mr. Johnston's release, saying that freedom of the press should be protected ''as a matter of principle.''</p>
        <p>There has been no word from Mr. Johnston, 44, since he disappeared on March 12. On Thursday, however, a Palestinian official, Saeb Erekat, said the government ''has been reassured by many sources that Mr. Johnston is alive.''</p>
        <p>Hostage-taking has long been a threat in the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq, though concerns have recently risen on several fronts. Among them was the two-week detention of 15 British sailors and marines by Iran, which accused them of trespassing in its national waters. All were released unharmed last week, amid allegations, denied by Britain, that an exchange was made for an Iranian diplomat arrested in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Here in Italy, the government has faced criticism at home and abroad for pressuring the Afghan government to release five Taliban prisoners for Daniele Mastrogiacomo, a reporter for La Repubblica, kidnapped last month. The United States, Britain and other nations contended that the deal would encourage more kidnappings.</p>
        <p>Inside Italy, that criticism rose on Sunday after Mr. Mastrogiacomo's Afghan interpreter, Ajmal Naqshbandi, was killed by the Taliban, which were demanding the release of two other prisoners.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Massimo D'Alema, foreign minister for Italy's center-left government, strongly defended the deal to free Mr. Mastrogiacomo.</p>
        <p>''We acted on the basis of one criterion: that of giving priority to the safety of the hostages,'' he said in a speech to the lower house of Parliament. ''This is an established principle, used over the years by various governments and always supported.''</p>
        <p>In this case, he said, Italy had been tricked, because it believed that the trade for Mr. Mastrogiacomo had included Mr. Naqshbandi as well. More generally, he said he believed that there should always be room for negotiation if it would save a hostage's life.</p>
        <p>''At the same time, I think it's time to explore the possibility of guidelines shared on an international level, a code of shared behavior,'' he said. ''I think, for example, in the case of Afghanistan, of a discussion at NATO.''</p>
        <p>Center-right opposition leaders have accused the government of putting undue pressure on the Afghan government to swap the prisoners, and for caring more about the life of an Italian journalist than his Afghan interpreter. Mr. Mastrogiacomo's driver was also killed, shortly after he was kidnapped in southern Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>In the West Bank city of Ramallah, the BBC's director general, Mark Thompson, said at a news conference that he had met with the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas, on Wednesday evening to discuss Mr. Johnston, and that Mr. Abbas had told him there was ''credible evidence'' that Mr. Johnston was safe and well.</p>
        <p>In Gaza City, Palestinian journalists rallied for Mr. Johnston's release, and they drove a convoy of cars through the city's streets.</p>
        <p>About 18 foreign journalists and aid workers have been kidnapped in Gaza in the past year, but most have been released unharmed, within hours or days.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
