<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study Finds State Far Behind in Review of Pollution Permits</title>
    <meta content="13permits" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/nyregion/13permits.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study Finds State Far Behind in Review of Pollution Permits</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Study Finds New York State Behind in Pollution Permit Reviews</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York State routinely fails to review the pollution permits of hundreds of factories, generating stations, sewage treatment plants and other operations that discharge contaminants into the state's rivers and lakes, according to a study released yesterday by Environmental Advocates of New York, a citizens' group.</p>
        <p>The lack of regular reviews means that regulators cannot accurately keep track of the substantial amount of pollutants that are allowed to enter the state's waters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because of the lack of regular reviews, regulators cannot accurately keep track of the substantial amount of pollutants that are allowed to enter the state’s waters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York State routinely fails to review the pollution permits of hundreds of factories, generating stations, sewage treatment plants and other operations that discharge contaminants into the state's rivers and lakes, according to a study released yesterday by Environmental Advocates of New York, a citizens' group.</p>
        <p>The lack of regular reviews means that regulators cannot accurately keep track of the substantial amount of pollutants that are allowed to enter the state's waters.</p>
        <p>The failure to conduct these evaluations is considered a violation of the federal Clean Water Act. Under the act, the state's Department of Environmental Conservation is required to review all major pollution discharge permits every five years.</p>
        <p>Environmental Advocates found, however, that more than 90 percent of the permits had not been evaluated in more than five years.</p>
        <p>For example, the discharge permit for the General Electric silicone plant in Waterford has not been reviewed since 1992, according to records that Environmental Advocates obtained from the state in response to a Freedom of Information Law request. The Eastman Kodak plant in Rochester has gone without extensive review since 1995. And the environmental department has even had trouble meeting review requirements on some of its own operations, including the state fish hatchery at Caledonia, which has not been evaluated in 16 years.</p>
        <p>''It means we don't know if these operations are endangering our waters, and we should know,'' said Robert J. Moore, executive director of Environmental Advocates. ''New York promised the federal government that it would oversee discharges, and it promised the people of the state that it would be a responsible steward for its lakes and streams. And New York is not doing that.''</p>
        <p>Many people believe that since the Clean Water Act was passed in 1972, discharging industrial waste into rivers and streams has not been allowed. In fact, however, more than 8,000 operations across New York have permits to discharge tens of billions of gallons of wastewater every day.</p>
        <p>The state is simply overwhelmed by the number of reviews required, Mr. Moore said.</p>
        <p>Staff reductions at the Department of Environmental Conservation over the last two decades cut the number of reviewers to 15. In 1992, the state chose what it called the environmental benefit permit strategy to select the few permits that could be reviewed.</p>
        <p>''There was no environmental benefit and not much of a strategy,'' Mr. Moore said.</p>
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer has said that rebuilding the department is a priority. His first budget included funds for more than 100 additional positions at the department, including 10 that have been assigned to the bureau that reviews water pollution permits, bringing the staff of that bureau to 25.</p>
        <p>Judith A. Enck, the governor's deputy secretary for environment, said the lack of proper review was a serious problem and one that probably resulted in more pollution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moore said that the 10 additional reviewers would help, but that the department needed to add 30 reviewers to the current staff of 15 to handle the required permit reviews and safeguard the state's waters adequately.</p>
        <p>Ms. Enck said it would be difficult to add more staff members, and therefore other strategies might have to be used.</p>
        <p>''We're never going to have enough staff to do the thorough review that is warranted,'' she said. Instead, the department may marshal its resources to focus on critical areas like the Lake Champlain watershed.</p>
        <p>It is not uncommon for responsibility for enforcing federal environmental regulations to be delegated to states, which then agree to conduct regular reviews. The five-year reviews can ensure that pollution standards are met, and also help ensure that as pollution control technology advances, those new methods are written into updated permits, Mr. Moore said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
