<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bodega's Failure Spawns a Successful Movement</title>
    <meta content="13lives" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/nyregion/13lives.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Crime and Law Enforcement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Jose Fernandez</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFDC133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bodega's Failure Spawns a Successful Movement</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Bodega’s Failure Spawns a Successful Movement</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR most readers of the city's newspapers, the tales are bitter, if familiar: immigrant owner of bodega is robbed, or killed, often for petty cash. A family grieves.</p>
        <p>But behind the headlines is Jose Fernandez's life. He is president of the Bodega Association of the United States, which claims membership of 7,800 of New York City's 12,500 bodegas, or neighborhood groceries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president of a bodega association plans to train other owners on how to deal with robberies and other crime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR most readers of the city's newspapers, the tales are bitter, if familiar: immigrant owner of bodega is robbed, or killed, often for petty cash. A family grieves.</p>
        <p>But behind the headlines is Jose Fernandez's life. He is president of the Bodega Association of the United States, which claims membership of 7,800 of New York City's 12,500 bodegas, or neighborhood groceries.</p>
        <p>This summer, as part of a continuing effort to improve safety at the city's bodegas, his group plans to expand a program with the Police Department to train bodega owners on how to deal with robberies and other crime through increased use of surveillance cameras and other techniques.</p>
        <p>Like most New Yorkers, bodega owners suffer less from crime than they did years before. Twenty-five bodega owners were injured last year in violent crime, down from more than 500 in 1993, Mr. Fernandez said.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, ''the No. 1 problem for bodega owners is still safety,'' said Mr. Fernandez, a short, soft-spoken man who wears cowboy boots and the kind of embroidered jeans favored by some rodeo riders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fernandez helped found the association in 1996 when he and other bodega owners realized there was no one that they, mostly Spanish speakers, could turn to for advice on credit, store maintenance, or what to buy for a store with more than 3,000 products.</p>
        <p>Of course, bodegas have been around for generations. When the Irish and Italians ran them, they were food stands, Mr. Fernandez said. But they came to be known as bodegas when the Hispanics in the city named them after small markets where friends met to drink wine and beer and play dominoes.</p>
        <p>Although bodegas function as grocery stores, they are often in converted space and usually have only one or two narrow doors and no windows. It is hard to see inside the shops from the street, making them easy crime magnets, Mr. Fernandez said. And since bodega owners are typically renters, they hesitate to install costly windows, even if they do enhance security.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fernandez, 39, was born in Santiago Rodríguez, the Dominican Republic. The son of a police officer, he felt estranged from his father and left with his mother, Maria Carrasco, and two sisters for New York City in 1983. After graduating in 1993 from Lehman College, where he studied public health, Mr. Fernandez spent a few years working in a shelter for battered women.</p>
        <p>On impulse, in late 1996, he bought a 500-square-foot bodega near Crotona Park in the Bronx for $120,000 by maxing out his credit cards, borrowing money from friends and family and borrowing the rest from a loan shark. His wife, Anna Marquez, a bank teller, advised against the venture.</p>
        <p>THINGS quickly fell apart. Some of the food in the store was expired, Mr. Fernandez discovered. He ran out of popular items. He worked seven days a week, from 7 a.m. to 11 p.m. He fell behind on his credit payments for the business, $750 payable weekly, as well as the rent. The landlord sued. His marriage almost ended in divorce. The previous owners repossessed the bodega.</p>
        <p>While he was struggling with his business, Mr. Fernandez organized the bodega association with Ramon Murphy, a friend and fellow bodega owner, who is now chairman of the group. On one shopping excursion for store supplies, Mr. Murphy and Mr. Fernandez agreed that bodega owners needed to join forces. Mr. Murphy wanted to restrict membership to Dominicans, but they decided to make the group open to all.</p>
        <p>In the beginning, each bodega owner had to bring in five other owners, and each one of those had to bring in five more. In less than a year, they had more than 1,000 members. There is no membership fee, and Mr. Fernandez is not paid a salary.</p>
        <p>Building membership was easy because bodega owners shopped in the same places. Hundreds, for example, would buy at Jetro Cash &amp; Carry on East 149th Street, near the Bruckner Expressway.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Fernandez was learning how to run a bodega from other bodega owners.</p>
        <p>In 1997, he bought a dilapidated 800-square-foot bodega on East 189th Street near the Rose Hill campus of Fordham University. He stocked Budweiser for Fordham students, as well as Newport and Marlboro cigarettes for residents. He learned what brands to buy of potato chips, rice and beans, paper towels and, especially, phone cards.</p>
        <p>The bodega's success helped Mr. Fernandez pay back his debts, but he sold the store two years ago after a burst of violent crime engulfed the neighborhood. His mother and his stepfather, who were helping him run the store, returned to the Dominican Republic after they were robbed five times in three years. Mr. Fernandez no longer owns a bodega, and now buys and sells real estate in the Bronx and the Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>When he was told that he seemed determined, Mr. Fernandez said no. ''I'm not tough,'' he said. ''My mother is tough.'' And he told a story.</p>
        <p>A young Ms. Carrasco used to drive a gypsy cab in Washington Heights. She was robbed some 25 times, Mr. Fernandez said. One night, a robber, brandishing a gun, threatened to kill her, and barked at her to drive. Anywhere.</p>
        <p>So she drove the cab to the nearest precinct house, aimed the cab at the front door, and plowed into it.</p>
        <p>The police piled out. The stunned robber was immediately arrested. Mr. Fernandez's mother emerged from the cab.</p>
        <p>With only a scratch.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
