<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can It Be? A Miracle On 2nd Ave.</title>
    <meta content="13nyc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can It Be? A Miracle On 2nd Ave.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here are some of the amazing things that are going to happen now:</p>
        <p>Writers with books to peddle and politicians with ambitions to nourish will set aside self-interest and not lend respectability to routinely offensive radio shows like the one that Don Imus had taken from him yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here are some of the amazing things that are going to happen now:</p>
        <p>Writers with books to peddle and politicians with ambitions to nourish will set aside self-interest and not lend respectability to routinely offensive radio shows like the one that Don Imus had taken from him yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Al Sharpton, self-anointed confessor to sinning white men, will finally apologize for the racial fires he ignited in the Tawana Brawley hoax.</p>
        <p>Former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani will acknowledge that his failure to ensure adequate radio communications cost firefighter lives at the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>The city's tabloid newspapers will renounce their preoccupation with Anna Nicole Smith and spend a sliver of their owners' billions to cover something only slightly less important, like the war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg will announce that he doesn't always know what is best for New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>All this, and more, will happen because we live in the age of miracles. We saw the evidence yesterday. There was a groundbreaking for the Second Avenue subway. It doesn't get more miraculous than that. Now anything is possible, including behavior change that had seemed unimaginable.</p>
        <p>The notion of an underground railway along Second Avenue has roots in the Jazz Age. Across eight decades, there were at least three previous groundbreakings. Nothing came of them other than a few truncated tunnels to nowhere. For New Yorkers, the Second Avenue subway has been what a pennant is for the Chicago Cubs, what peace is for the Middle East, what wisdom is for General Motors: the unattainable.</p>
        <p>That reality was on the minds and tongues of officials who gathered yesterday for a ceremony in a section of tunnel about 40 feet below Second Avenue, at East 99th Street.</p>
        <p>''For too many years, the Second Avenue subway was a bad joke,'' said Elliot G. Sander, the executive director of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority. Representative Carolyn B. Maloney borrowed from Langston Hughes to describe the subway line as ''a dream deferred.'' Gov. Eliot Spitzer drew on a different muse, Yogi Berra, to call the groundbreaking ''déjà vu all over again, all over again, all over again.''</p>
        <p>But the Second Avenue subway is more than a laugh line. It is as good a symbol as any of New York's shrunken will to build on a grand scale whenever a project needs significant government involvement.</p>
        <p>Delay, for years, has been the city's default position. Sometimes the blame lies with financial troubles. Often, delay goes hand in hand with New York's favorite indoor sport: filing lawsuits. Whatever the reason, you have to wonder if the Latin words on the City Seal should be replaced with a quotation from Cicero: Nihil agere delectat. It is pleasant to do nothing.</p>
        <p>PICK a world city -- Paris, Tokyo, London -- and you will find that it has invested heavily to expand its mass transit system. Pick any city except New York, of course. Ideas come and ideas go, and nothing happens. For decades.</p>
        <p>That is true, most conspicuously, of the desperately needed Second Avenue subway. In its absence, the crowded East Side of Manhattan has only the trains running beneath Lexington Avenue. Some stations on the Lexington line, notably the one at 86th Street, are so jammed during rush periods that the real miracle is that riders have not been accidentally pushed en masse onto the tracks.</p>
        <p>Daniel L. Doctoroff, Mr. Bloomberg's deputy mayor for economic development and rebuilding, suggested at yesterday's ceremony that more than a shortage of money kept the Second Avenue line in limbo. ''We lost our nerve,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the bad old days are over, he and other officials insisted. This time, it's ''the real deal,'' Mr. Sander said. This time, said Peter S. Kalikow, the transportation authority's chairman, ''we do have the money.''</p>
        <p>We'll see. Things could still go wrong. For Gene Russianoff, a leader of the Straphangers Campaign, a riders' advocacy group, it will be no shock if financing for mass transit ''turns to guacamole.'' The city may yet be left with a runt of a line consisting of only a few stations -- a stubway, as some have called it.</p>
        <p>Ah, but why be glum? Maybe, as Ms. Maloney said, ''the fourth groundbreaking is the charm.'' And with a Second Avenue subway, all those other miracles -- an apologetic Mr. Sharpton, a remorseful Mr. Giuliani, a humble Mr. Bloomberg -- should fall seamlessly into place.</p>
        <p>NYC E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
