<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art in Review; Philip Pearlstein</title>
    <meta content="13gall-2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E7D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art in Review; Philip Pearlstein</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kimmelman, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Betty Cuningham Gallery  541 West 25th Street, Chelsea  Through April 28</p>
        <p>Anybody who brings the level of patience and single-minded devotion that Philip Pearlstein has applied for nearly 50 years to his paintings of nudes can only be said to be in a state akin to rapture. That's not the initial conclusion to draw from the pictures, whose deadpan manner has long been a problem for many people. They miss the point.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Betty Cuningham Gallery  541 West 25th Street, Chelsea  Through April 28</p>
        <p>Anybody who brings the level of patience and single-minded devotion that Philip Pearlstein has applied for nearly 50 years to his paintings of nudes can only be said to be in a state akin to rapture. That's not the initial conclusion to draw from the pictures, whose deadpan manner has long been a problem for many people. They miss the point.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pearlstein, at 83, still declines to please in the easy ways figure painters can. His dour nudes doze amid a clutter of kilims, plastic blow-up chairs, antique toys, weathervanes, fluorescent Mickey Mouse signs and model boats. They're frankly artificial. The contrived setups exploit vertiginous views and other, often dizzying complexities of organization, light and shadow, which demand a virtuosity superficially belied by occasional passages of seeming awkwardness.</p>
        <p>This awkwardness derives not from bad design but from a painstaking attempt to render exactly what Mr. Pearlstein sees in front of him. ''Optical truth reveals the lie of conventional schoolbook perspective,'' he has said. ''Cézanne was right.'' What results is a kind of dense, baroque patterning, bordering on abstraction.</p>
        <p>His new works are among his best in years. They're filled with subtle signs of optimism: a butterfly kite, the bright light of the Mickey sign, which casts a blue halo around the bodies of reclining models, like the nostalgic blue halos that Wayne Thiebaud casts around cream pies and gumball machines. Multiple lights collapse space and make criss-crossing lines against bare white walls, bringing to mind Franz Kline.</p>
        <p>A pair of large watercolors of models with whirligigs are remarkable feats, like the large painting in which a reclining model's legs thrust up from the bottom of the picture onto a transparent plastic chair, Mr. Pearlstein presumably standing astride her head. The mix of dry comedy, sex and theatrics is typical of him.</p>
        <p>It's as if he's so endlessly excited by the problem-solving aspect of painting nudes that he needs each time to reinvent for himself the process from scratch, discovering its hitches and mysteries, like a musician who builds a piano whenever he wants to play. Morandi had his bottles and bowls. Mr. Pearlstein has his bodies and props. For him they have remained inexhaustible.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
