<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>8 IRAQIS KILLED IN BOMB ATTACK AT LEGISLATURE</title>
    <meta content="13iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/world/middleeast/13iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REACH OF WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Alissa J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFDA133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1426" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>8 IRAQIS KILLED IN BOMB ATTACK AT LEGISLATURE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">8 Iraqis Killed in Bomb Attack at Legislature</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISSA J. RUBIN; Reporting was contributed by Ahmad Fadam, Qais Mizher, Khalid al-Ansary and Edward Wong.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubin, Alissa J</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Suicide bomber kills 8 people inside Iraqi Parliament building, few feet from main chamber, in worst attack in heavily fortified International Zone since area was established four years ago; image of International Zone as impregnable fortress has been on wane; regular rocket and mortar attacks on United States Embassy compound in recent weeks have killed civilian and soldier, and wounded others; senior military officials reported finding two suicide vests in garbage bin two weeks ago; Baghdad residents learn of attack on Parliament after equally traumatic attack earlier in day in which truck bomb destroys beloved 60-year-old Sarafiya bridge across Tigris, killing six people; bridge has long been symbol of Baghdad from more peaceful time; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A suicide bomber struck deep inside the heavily fortified International Zone on Thursday, killing eight people when he detonated his explosives inside the Parliament building, just a few feet from the main chamber.</p>
        <p>In a separate and in some ways equally traumatic attack early in the day, a truck bomb destroyed the beloved 60-year-old Sarafiya bridge across the Tigris and killed six people. The heavily traveled bridge has long been a symbol of Baghdad, illustrated on old postcards and drawings from a more peaceful time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An attack on Parliament was the worst in the International Zone since it was created four years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A suicide bomber struck deep inside the heavily fortified International Zone on Thursday, killing eight people when he detonated his explosives inside the Parliament building, just a few feet from the main chamber.</p>
        <p>In a separate and in some ways equally traumatic attack early in the day, a truck bomb destroyed the beloved 60-year-old Sarafiya bridge across the Tigris and killed six people. The heavily traveled bridge has long been a symbol of Baghdad, illustrated on old postcards and drawings from a more peaceful time.</p>
        <p>The attack on Parliament was the worst in the International Zone since the area was established four years ago, when it was known as the Green Zone. At a time when Iraqis are increasingly questioning the government's ability to protect them, the bombing raised the troubling possibility that it could not even fully protect itself, although the zone is at the wellspring of American and Iraqi military power in the city.</p>
        <p>The bomber struck a half hour after the day's session had closed, in a cafe area where lawmakers were lingering, across from the main chamber. Among the dead were at least two legislators, both from Sunni parties. Of the 23 people wounded, 11 were members of Parliament, the United States military reported.</p>
        <p>''This is a cowardly act,'' said Deputy Prime Minister Barham Ahmad Saleh, ''and this proves that terrorism is indiscriminate. Sunnis, Shia, Kurds have been injured and maimed and killed in this attack. This should be a reminder that all Iraqis are targeted.'' He visited the wounded at Ibn Sina Hospital, which is run by the United States military.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saleh and Mowaffak al-Rubaie, the national security adviser, who was also visiting the wounded, called the attack a major security breach. Regulations in the zone require visitors to undergo several screenings by Iraqi forces, foreign contractors and American soldiers.</p>
        <p>The image of the International Zone as an impregnable fortress had been on the wane. Regular rocket and mortar attacks on the United States Embassy compound in recent weeks have killed a civilian and a soldier, and wounded several others. And senior military officials said two suicide vests were found in a garbage bin about two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, news of the attack on Thursday came less as a shock than as further evidence of the government's impotence, even in the midst of a major security push in the city.</p>
        <p>''I am not surprised this happened at the Parliament,'' said Waqas al-Ubaidi, 30, who was standing outside the hospital waiting for news of his uncle, a member of Parliament, Salman al-Jumaili. ''The coming days will be worse; every day is worse.''</p>
        <p>But Baghdad residents had already been horrified by news of the bridge bombing, a demoralizing attack that stole one of the few remaining reminders of better days in the capital.</p>
        <p>The bomber drove a tanker truck loaded with explosives onto the bridge at 7 a.m. and brought it to a halt midway, according to American military officials and witnesses. The driver examined the truck's underside and then disappeared. With the truck blocking traffic, motorists stopped a police patrol crossing the bridge and asked them to do something about it.</p>
        <p>Immediately suspicious, the police moved cars and people off the bridge and radioed to the patrols on the opposite side to stop people from starting across. One witness, a tractor driver, described a policeman opening the passenger door of the truck, seeing a mass of wires and batteries, and running away.</p>
        <p>Ten minutes later the bomb exploded, so powerfully that it killed six people some distance away, sent several cars careening into the river and destroyed 65 percent to 75 percent of the steel structure. Politicians, immediately sensitive to the impact of the bombing, swiftly condemned it, eulogized the structure and promised to rebuild it.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki, who was traveling in South Korea, released a statement describing the bridge as ''one of the oldest and loveliest city bridges.''</p>
        <p>In the Parliament attack, several lawmakers expressed bitterness at both the government and the Americans for failing to protect them and said the attack must have been carried out by someone who had security clearance and was able to avoid the multiple searches.</p>
        <p>''This is a great blow to the government, which is always talking about security and how it is improving with the Americans, but it's a great violation of their security plan,'' Ali al-Mayali, an injured legislator from the bloc allied with the militant Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr, said as he sat outside the hospital, holding gauze to his head to stanch bleeding from a shrapnel wound.</p>
        <p>''This is the International Zone, protected by the Americans,'' Mr. Mayali said. ''It's a big violation that they reached the center of decision-making.''</p>
        <p>Another Sadr bloc legislator, Asma al-Musawi, who hurried to the hospital to find wounded colleagues, expressed similar dismay. But she said the attack was also a reminder to members of Parliament what life was like for their constituents, who lived with far less protection.</p>
        <p>''We must expect this,'' Ms. Musawi said. ''It is worse outside in Baghdad, so the violence will definitely, eventually reach into the International Zone. If you are unable to protect your people, eventually you will be unable to protect yourself.</p>
        <p>''But this is an alarm for the government, for security inside the International Zone, for the coalition forces, for the people leading Iraq.''</p>
        <p>Maj. Gen. William Caldwell IV, the chief American military spokesman in Iraq, condemned the bombing, saying: ''We in the multinational force Iraq condemn these attacks. These are clearly attacks on Iraqi institutions. We try to build hope and they are trying to instill fear. But we remain committed to the Iraqi people.''</p>
        <p>The bomb exploded less than half an hour after Parliament had recessed for the day. Because it was Thursday afternoon and Friday is typically a day off, many people had already left when the bomber detonated his explosive, apparently in a vest.</p>
        <p>But a handful of legislators were eating lunch in the cafe area, and one Shiite member, Imam Jalaluddin al-Sagheer, was giving an interview on television. When the explosion happened, he ducked and was engulfed in a cloud of smoke and dust.</p>
        <p>The glass tables in the cafe shattered, becoming dangerous shards that left people bleeding from numerous small wounds, Mr. Mayali said.</p>
        <p>The Parliament building has its own security arrangements, not managed by either the American military or by the Interior Ministry of Police or Ministry of Defense, said Mr. Rubaie, the security adviser to Prime Minister Maliki.</p>
        <p>''We need to work out new measures,'' Mr. Rubaie said. ''We advised the Parliament that no visitors should go into the building, and secondly, that they should give us responsibility for the force protection and we would be in charge, but they didn't want it.''</p>
        <p>He added that three weeks ago, he had insisted on a top to bottom check of the entire building and that his security staff had found 19 pistols that were unaccounted for. The search ''was a very unpopular move,'' he said. ''The Parliament didn't like it.''</p>
        <p>Several lawmakers said that their guards were often able to bully their way through checkpoints without being searched and that some carried high-level badges that made them and their vehicles exempt from being examined when the entered the zone.</p>
        <p>''No one can bring bombs into this zone or this building except the lawmakers and their guards, and some of the lawmakers' convoys are not searched,'' said Wail Abdul Latif, a legislator from the secular Iraqiya bloc led by the former interim prime minister, Ayad Allawi. ''Some of the lawmakers' guards make trouble at the checkpoints, some of them refuse to be searched. They are not very professional.''</p>
        <p>He added that he wanted the American military to take over securing the Parliament, as it had done before the new government was put in place.</p>
        <p>After emerging from the hospital, Mr. Rubaie, a man who usually exudes confidence, seemed a little shaken by the two bombings. ''These are historic things,'' he said. ''This is what the terrorists want to do to us.''</p>
        <p>''What happened today, the Parliament, the bridge, the Mutanabi Street book market, these are places very dear to the hearts of Baghdadis, of Iraqis,'' he said, referring to a bombing a few weeks ago at the city's historic Mutanabi Street book market.</p>
        <p>''These places are very dear, way dear to us,'' he said. ''This is what they want to destroy.''</p>
        <p>THE REACH OF WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
