<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City's Catskill Water Gets 10-Year Approval</title>
    <meta content="13water" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/nyregion/13water.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1DC133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City's Catskill Water Gets 10-Year Approval</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">City’s Catskill Water Gets 10-Year Approval</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After an exacting review that lasted several years, federal environmental officials have concluded that New York City's upstate water supply is still so clean that it does not need to be filtered for another decade or longer.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency's announcement yesterday extending the city's current exemption from filtration requirements means that at least until 2017, New York City will not have to spend as much as $8 billion to build a filtration plant that would cost millions of dollars a year to operate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After an exacting review that lasted several years, federal environmental officials have concluded that New York City’s upstate water supply is still so clean that it does not need to be filtered for another decade or longer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After an exacting review that lasted several years, federal environmental officials have concluded that New York City's upstate water supply is still so clean that it does not need to be filtered for another decade or longer.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency's announcement yesterday extending the city's current exemption from filtration requirements means that at least until 2017, New York City will not have to spend as much as $8 billion to build a filtration plant that would cost millions of dollars a year to operate.</p>
        <p>About 90 percent of the one billion gallons used in the city each day comes from a system of huge reservoirs in the Catskill Mountains, 120 miles north of the city. The remaining 10 percent is drawn from closer reservoirs surrounded by development in Westchester County and will have to be filtered. A $2 billion filtration plant under construction in the Bronx is scheduled to be operational by 2012.</p>
        <p>As a condition for the extension for the Catskill filtration exemption, the city has agreed to set aside $300 million over the next 10 years to acquire land upstate to restrain development that causes runoff and pollution.</p>
        <p>The city will purchase land outright, or work with nonprofit land trusts to acquire easements that would keep land in private hands but prohibit them from being developed.</p>
        <p>The city also committed itself to reducing the amount of turbidity, or cloudiness, in certain Catskill reservoirs by erecting screens, building baffles and using other technology to allow sediment to settle before water enters the final parts of the drinking water system.</p>
        <p>Environmental advocates had expected the federal government to issue a five-year extension and were pleased that it turned out to be twice as long.</p>
        <p>''It represents a commitment among all of the parties -- the city, state and federal government -- to focus on the challenges of protecting the source water supply rather than pursue a costly and gargantuan construction project,'' said Eric A. Goldstein, a senior lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council.</p>
        <p>New York is one of the few major water systems in the country that are exempt from the filtration requirements. They are evaluated every five years by federal officials to ensure that the water remains pure.</p>
        <p>A standard five-year filtration avoidance renewal was about to be issued last month before Gov. Eliot Spitzer's office raised concerns about the size of the city's land acquisition program, according to people involved in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>The city had proposed spending $89 million over five years, a significant decrease from the $30 million a year that it had allocated over the previous decade.</p>
        <p>Judith A. Enck, the governor's deputy secretary for the environment, felt the proposal was not ambitious enough. ''We were hoping for a more significant commitment to land preservation,'' she said, especially in the agricultural sector. After reopening negotiations, the city promised to increase its commitment to acquiring land in exchange for a longer exemption from the filtering requirement.</p>
        <p>''The pieces shifted slightly and a new opportunity opened up,'' said Emily Lloyd, commissioner of the city's Department of Environmental Protection, which runs the water system. ''There was also a lot of interest on the part of everyone seeing the land protection program going forward.''</p>
        <p>In the end, the city agreed to duplicate its successful land acquisition effort over the last decade. It applied $59 million that is left over from the previous $300 million commitment, and agreed to add an additional $241 million over 10 years.</p>
        <p>As in the past, the city will acquire land when owners are willing to sell it, rather than through condemnation.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lloyd said that the city had not set a goal for the number of acres to acquire, and that it would not establish yearly quotas as some advocates have suggested, because that could lead to inflated prices and purchases not critical to watershed protection.</p>
        <p>In some major watersheds around the country, 100 percent of the land is publicly owned or otherwise protected from development.</p>
        <p>Even with recent land purchases, New York City remains far behind other systems in protecting its watershed. Over the last 10 years, the city has added about 78,000 acres to its holdings in the Catskill and Delaware watersheds, bringing its total to about 114,000 acres. That, combined with state forestry land, means 31 percent of the one-million-acre watershed is currently protected.</p>
        <p>Still, federal officials are confident that the city's water will continue to meet health standards and that the economies of communities in the watershed can be preserved.</p>
        <p>''We realize that we can't take all the land out of circulation and that there is a need for both environmental protection and economic development,'' said Alan J. Steinberg, regional administrator of the federal environmental agency. ''This plan shows a way to balance them.''</p>
        <p>Walter Mugdan, the federal agency's director of environmental planning, said the city had until December to complete a review of proposed projects intended to clear up the Catskill water supply and reduce the amount of chemical additives that are now used to remove sediment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
