<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toll in Bombings in Algeria Rises to 33; Manhunt Begins</title>
    <meta content="13algeria" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/world/africa/13algeria.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Algeria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Algiers (Algeria)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Algeria</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toll in Bombings in Algeria Rises to 33; Manhunt Begins</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Toll in Bombings in Algeria Rises to 33; Manhunt Begins</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Death toll from two suicide bombings in and near Algiers rises by 10, to 33, as police find third bomb in car near home of director general of national police; nationwide manhunt is mounted for those responsible; Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb, most active terrorist group in area, claims responsibility for twin bombings; Algeria has only recently emerged from shadows of brutal civil war; committed core of Islamists have kept up fight; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The death toll from Wednesday's suicide bombings in Algeria rose by 10 on Thursday, to 33, and the police mounted a nationwide manhunt for those responsible for the attacks.</p>
        <p>Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb, North Africa's most active terrorist group, claimed responsibility for the twin bombings, which were directed at the main government building in Algiers and at a police station east of the city. More than 200 people were wounded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb, North Africa’s most active terrorist group, claimed responsibility for the twin bombings, which killed 33 and wounded more than 200.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The death toll from Wednesday's suicide bombings in Algeria rose by 10 on Thursday, to 33, and the police mounted a nationwide manhunt for those responsible for the attacks.</p>
        <p>Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb, North Africa's most active terrorist group, claimed responsibility for the twin bombings, which were directed at the main government building in Algiers and at a police station east of the city. More than 200 people were wounded.</p>
        <p>It could have been even worse: the police found a third bomb in a Mercedes-Benz sedan near the home of Ali Tounsi, director general of the national police, according to witnesses and local press reports. The bomb was defused.</p>
        <p>It was apparently one of the bombs referred to on Islamist Web sites on Wednesday, which claimed that a third suicide bomber was attacking the Algerian headquarters of Interpol. Interpol links police forces in 186 countries around the world.</p>
        <p>The police set up checkpoints around Algiers and increased patrols on the outskirts, but the mood there had already darkened. The French-language daily newspaper Liberté wrote that the attacks ''have wakened the demons of a violence we believed had been contained.''</p>
        <p>Algeria has only recently emerged from the shadows of a brutal civil war, set off when the military canceled elections in 1992 that a fundamentalist Islamic party was poised to win. The war, which wound down after a government amnesty in 1999, was marked by horrific massacres of men, women and children -- slitting throats was common-- that left deep scars in the national psyche.</p>
        <p>A national reconciliation program last year sought to shut that history firmly in the past with a new amnesty for the remaining Islamist fighters and with the release of hundreds of former fighters from jail. Even talking of the past atrocities became illegal.</p>
        <p>A committed core of Islamists kept up the fight, but most Algerians were confident that the movement had been defeated, as repeated government pronouncements claimed.</p>
        <p>Islamists warned otherwise, however. ''When you leave a small fire burning, it can spread,'' Abdelhak Layada, a founder of the Armed Islamic Group, said in an interview last June, shortly after he was freed under the reconciliation program.</p>
        <p>The Armed Islamic Group was a precursor to the Salafist Group for Preaching and Combat, which announced an alliance with Al Qaeda last year and recently changed its name to Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb.</p>
        <p>The bombings took place on the fifth anniversary of a deadly truck bombing at El Ghriba Synagogue in Djerba, Tunisia, for which the Salafists claimed responsibility. Twenty-one people died in that attack.</p>
        <p>Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb continues to claim that it does not attack ordinary Algerians, but Wednesday's bombings showed otherwise. Many of the people who died were office workers or bystanders outside the government building.</p>
        <p>People were quick to blame the government, saying lenience toward former rebels encouraged the movement and weakened the resolve of the army and the police.</p>
        <p>''There's been a lack of vigilance on the part of the security forces,'' said Mahmoud Belhimeur, an editor at El Khabar newspaper. ''They said that it's over, but they forgot that these people operate best when it's calm.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
