<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Report Says the Young Buy Violent Games and Movies</title>
    <meta content="13violence" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Movies; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/business/media/13violence.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Trade Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFDB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Report Says the Young Buy Violent Games and Movies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Report Says the Young Buy Violent Games and Movies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL CIEPLY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cieply, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A surge in online promotion and the proliferation of unrated DVDs has eroded the entertainment industry's promise not to entice youth with violent fare, according to a Federal Trade Commission report on the marketing of violence to teenagers.</p>
        <p>Movie companies have been routinely pushing R-rated films on Web sites with a high number of young users, even while largely honoring a commitment not to buy ads on TV shows with a similar audience, according to the report.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal Trade Commission report found that online promotions and a proliferation of unrated DVDs have eroded the entertainment industry’s promise not to entice youth with violent fare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A surge in online promotion and the proliferation of unrated DVDs has eroded the entertainment industry's promise not to entice youth with violent fare, according to a Federal Trade Commission report on the marketing of violence to teenagers.</p>
        <p>Movie companies have been routinely pushing R-rated films on Web sites with a high number of young users, even while largely honoring a commitment not to buy ads on TV shows with a similar audience, according to the report.</p>
        <p>And despite industry controls, buyers from the ages of 13 to 16, unaccompanied by adults, were able to purchase tickets to R-rated films in 39 percent of their attempts, and successfully bought unrated or R-rated DVDs 71 percent of the time.</p>
        <p>The 140-page document, released Thursday, was a follow-up to the commission's 2000 report, which censured the entertainment business for selling violence to the young. The most recent previous follow-up, in July 2004, had found some improvement.</p>
        <p>But the years since have brought increased spending on Web advertising, rapid expansion on social networking sites like MySpace, and an explosion in the R-rated horror market, driven in part by films like ''Hostel'' and ''Saw,'' which some in Hollywood have called ''torture porn.''</p>
        <p>In the report, the commissioners asked film, music and video-game producers to reconsider their voluntary controls. They said they found ''general compliance with existing voluntary standards, but insufficient attention to the development and application of these standards to evolving marketing trends.''</p>
        <p>The finding was expected to prompt companies to try to keep violent entertainment from erupting as a political issue in the presidential race. That happened seven years ago, when the top film studio executives were called to testify before a Senate committee that considered regulating their marketing practices. To placate the politicians and fend off the unwanted regulation, the movie industry adopted the voluntary guidelines.</p>
        <p>''The report will certainly sharpen the focus on unrated DVDs,'' said Kendrick Macdowell, general counsel of the National Organization of Theater Owners. Mr. Macdowell's organization has argued that the film companies' promotion of unrated versions of films like Warner's ''Sublime'' -- whose theatrical version was rated R for disturbing violent content, language and sexuality -- has become a major loophole in a rating system.</p>
        <p>The studios increasingly slip unrated material into DVDs, then sell them as being somehow more attractive than the rated versions.</p>
        <p>''That's a real issue for parents,'' James Steyer, chief executive of Common Sense Media, which provides supplemental ratings of entertainment products. ''When you get a bunch of new or unrated scenes, that just raises new red flags.''</p>
        <p>Gayle Osterberg, vice president for corporate communications at the Motion Picture Association of America, which maintains the film ratings system, said the group was constantly updating its standards. ''Most of the unrated versions of previously rated theatrical releases are explicitly marketed as containing edgier content, so there should be no confusion in the marketplace,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Commission investigators also found that youth access to violent fare had fallen since 2000, especially in video games. Only 42 percent of unaccompanied young buyers were able to buy games rated M (for mature), down from 85 percent seven years ago.</p>
        <p>In a spot check of television advertising for R-rated films, only a handful were found to have been promoted during shows with youth audiences of more than 35 percent, the self-imposed cutoff agreed to by the major film companies. Of five films the report found to have advertised on youth-oriented programs, three -- ''Slither,'' ''Inside Man,'' and ''Waist Deep'' -- came from units of NBC Universal, whose executives did not respond to a request for comment.</p>
        <p>The bigger problem for the film industry appeared to be its developing relationship with Web sites and chat rooms. The demographics of these sites are not always clear, and marketing, once unleashed in a so-called viral environment, can quickly slip beyond a studio's control.</p>
        <p>The report noted that studios seldom placed full rating information on their MySpace profile pages. It also said it found that visitors to MySpace under the age of 16 made up less than 24 percent of the total, but accounted for 40 percent of page views, when measured in 2006 by Nielsen/NetRatings.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for MySpace took issue with those numbers, saying that an assessment by comScore MediaMetrix, a rival of Nielsen/NetRatings, showed 80 percent of its audience to be over 18.</p>
        <p>The commission also found that film companies routinely advertised R-rated fare on sites like that of the Cartoon Network, where it said under-17 visitors made up 54 percent of the total during a monitored period ending last August.</p>
        <p>It suggested that the film and music industries impose outright bans on ads for R-rated movies, similar to one enforced in the video-game industry, which prohibits advertising on sites where more than 45 percent of the visitors are under 17.</p>
        <p>Even so, the report found that game companies routinely violated that prohibition, and recommended further tightening, perhaps by banning ads on sites with obvious youth appeal.</p>
        <p>Patricia Vance, president of the Entertainment Software Ratings Board, which oversees game ratings, expressed wariness of any measure that might open the door to broadly subjective judgments.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
