<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surveillance and Subterfuge in Corporate Shadows</title>
    <meta content="13stra" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/movies/13stra.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foley, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berry, Halle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Willis, Bruce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Perfect Stranger (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Foley, James</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Perfect Stranger (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surveillance and Subterfuge in Corporate Shadows</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Surveillance and Subterfuge in Corporate Shadows</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film Perfect Stranger, directed by James Foley; Halle Berry and Bruce Willis star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the sleek, paranoid world of ''Perfect Stranger,'' the Internet and the ugly side of human nature converge to evoke a treacherous corporate climate of multiple identities, high-tech spying, obsessive prurience, blackmail and murder. Communication is carried on under assumed names in e-mail messages, instant messages and coded cellphone texts. Every character is an unscrupulous go-getter with a cache of guilty secrets to protect.</p>
        <p>There is enough of a grain of truth in this noirish thriller, directed by James Foley from a screenplay by Todd Komarnicki, that even after it lurches from the far-fetched into the preposterous, ''Perfect Stranger'' leaves a clammy residue of unease. Although set in the corridors of New York media giants, it often feels like a Hollywood fever dream responding to the wave of scandals and cover-ups coming out of Washington. To the movie's ruthless power brokers and climbers, the most precious human commodity is loyalty, the ability to keep a dirty secret under wraps. But loyalty has its price.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even after it lurches from the far-fetched into the preposterous, “Perfect Stranger” leaves a clammy residue of unease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the sleek, paranoid world of ''Perfect Stranger,'' the Internet and the ugly side of human nature converge to evoke a treacherous corporate climate of multiple identities, high-tech spying, obsessive prurience, blackmail and murder. Communication is carried on under assumed names in e-mail messages, instant messages and coded cellphone texts. Every character is an unscrupulous go-getter with a cache of guilty secrets to protect.</p>
        <p>There is enough of a grain of truth in this noirish thriller, directed by James Foley from a screenplay by Todd Komarnicki, that even after it lurches from the far-fetched into the preposterous, ''Perfect Stranger'' leaves a clammy residue of unease. Although set in the corridors of New York media giants, it often feels like a Hollywood fever dream responding to the wave of scandals and cover-ups coming out of Washington. To the movie's ruthless power brokers and climbers, the most precious human commodity is loyalty, the ability to keep a dirty secret under wraps. But loyalty has its price.</p>
        <p>Halle Berry, not the warmest actress, is the putative heroine, Rowena Price, a star investigative reporter for a rag called The New York Courier. Rowena, who dishes out sensational exposés under a male pseudonym, doesn't resemble any journalist I've ever met. As she slithers through the movie's chilly upscale jungle, her only ethical principle seems to be that in the pursuit of dirt, the ends always justify the means.</p>
        <p>In the film's creepy opening scene, she visits a married congressman with gubernatorial aspirations under friendly pretenses and confronts him with evidence of his sexual relationship with a male intern. When he offers her ''anything you want'' not to print the revelation, she refuses. But he pulls strings with her bosses and gets his way, and Rowena quits in a huff.</p>
        <p>An encounter in the subway with a childhood friend, Grace (Nicki Aycox), leads Rowena to her next sleuthing expedition. Not long after their meeting, Grace is found dead, the victim of poisoning. Rowena suspects that the killer is Harrison Hill (Bruce Willis), a married, compulsively philandering advertising mogul whom Grace had stalked relentlessly after he ended their affair.</p>
        <p>Enlisting her journalistic sidekick Miles Haley (Giovanni Ribisi), a ratty cyber-wizard who can hack his way through any firewall, she initiates a seductive cat-and-mouse game with Harrison in which she assumes two identities. She becomes both Katherine Pogue, an office temp who takes a job at Harrison's agency, catches his roving eye and begins a dangerous flirtation, and Veronica, who rubs libidos with Harrison in a chat room where he bombards her with the usual coy questions about lingerie. (The movie has blatant and extended product plugs for Victoria's Secret and Reebok.)</p>
        <p>Before long Katherine and Harrison are in a chic restaurant, sipping the movie's cocktail of choice, a ''Hemingway daiquiri,'' and he is nuzzling her neck. Harrison and Veronica also arrange an assignation in a downtown hotel. None of it makes much sense. Although the movie pretends otherwise, the supposed evidence that Rowena compiles against Harrison is flimsy at best.</p>
        <p>Nor is Ms. Berry able to untangle her character's personalities, one of which emerges in a ludicrous bombshell revelation in the movie's final scene. Ms. Berry, as always, looks great but fails to project the innate sensuality you expect to accompany such beauty. Tense and snippy, she conveys the wary insecurity of an actress who is unaware of her charms and overcompensates by trying too hard to act.</p>
        <p>Mr. Willis strolls through the role of a smirking cobra with the blithe detachment of an actor who knows that when playing a master of the universe, less is more. All that's required is the narrowing of his eyes, then sweeping the room with a cunning gaze. Only once does Harrison blow his cool, in a scene in which he fires and replaces a disloyal employee in a violent 30-second explosion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ribisi's Miles appears to be a devoted puppy until the moment we observe him hiding in a dark corner of Rowena's apartment while she makes love with her boyfriend, Cameron (Gary Dourdan), a character so cursory that he barely exists.</p>
        <p>The director, as he showed in movies like ''After Dark, My Sweet,'' and ''Fear,'' specializes in conjuring conspiratorial atmospheres in which anxiety and sexual menace hang in the air like a heavy, bitter perfume. Long after you've dismissed the movie's ridiculous, convoluted story, traces of that scent may linger.</p>
        <p>''Perfect Stranger'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has sexual situations, some nudity, violence and strong language.</p>
        <p>Perfect Stranger  Opens today nationwide.</p>
        <p>Directed by James Foley; written by Todd Komarnicki, based on a story by Jon Bokenkamp; director of photography, Anastas Michos; edited by Christopher Tellefsen; music by Antonio Pinto; production designer, Bill Groom; produced by Elaine Goldsmith-Thomas; released by Columbia Pictures and Revolution Studios. Running time: 109 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Halle Berry (Rowena Price), Bruce Willis (Harrison Hill), Giovanni Ribisi (Miles Haley) and Gary Dourdan (Cameron).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
