<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. Agent's Hometown Gives a Lavish Send-Off</title>
    <meta content="13bury" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/nyregion/13bury.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Funerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. Agent's Hometown Gives a Lavish Send-Off</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">F.B.I. Agent’s Hometown Gives a Lavish Send-Off</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD G. JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Richard G</byline>
      <dateline>POTTSTOWN, Pa., April 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A bagpipe wailed. A siren droned. Police motorcycles revved. And within moments a procession was under way to carry Barry Lee Bush -- the F.B.I. agent who was killed last week while staking out bank robbers in central New Jersey -- to his final rest.</p>
        <p>Under somber skies, hundreds of officials from the Federal Bureau of Investigation, police departments as far away as Michigan and state and federal governments gathered at the Hill School here to remember Mr. Bush's life, mourn his death and offer his family the universal embrace of law enforcement. Among the 3,000 mourners were Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales; the F.B.I. director, Robert S. Mueller III; and Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dignitaries were among the 3,000 mourners who gathered Thursday in Pottstown, Pa., to bury Barry Lee Bush, the F.B.I. agent who was killed last week in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A bagpipe wailed. A siren droned. Police motorcycles revved. And within moments a procession was under way to carry Barry Lee Bush -- the F.B.I. agent who was killed last week while staking out bank robbers in central New Jersey -- to his final rest.</p>
        <p>Under somber skies, hundreds of officials from the Federal Bureau of Investigation, police departments as far away as Michigan and state and federal governments gathered at the Hill School here to remember Mr. Bush's life, mourn his death and offer his family the universal embrace of law enforcement. Among the 3,000 mourners were Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales; the F.B.I. director, Robert S. Mueller III; and Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>In a eulogy, Mr. Mueller called Mr. Bush, the 51st agent to be killed on duty, one of the agency's finest and ''a model of everything the badge should represent.''</p>
        <p>''Barry's death reminds us that the men and women of law enforcement put their lives on the line every day,'' he said. ''Each morning when they pick up their badges, they know there is a possibility they might not make it home that night. And that is where heroism lies: recognizing the risk, and choosing to accept it so that others don't have to.''</p>
        <p>Even those who did not know Mr. Bush, a nearly 20-year F.B.I. veteran, seemed shaken by his death, which the authorities said was caused by a bullet from another agent's gun as they swarmed the suspected robbers to thwart the latest planned holdup. The F.B.I. has refused to release the name of the agent whose weapon was fired or any detail about how it happened last Thursday in Readington Township, N.J.</p>
        <p>''You can see by the outpouring that any time we lose a member of law enforcement it affects each and every one of us,'' said Dennis J. Hallion, president of the New Jersey State Troopers Non-Commissioned Officers Association. ''A little piece of us dies.''</p>
        <p>Patrol cars from the Pennsylvania State Police were triple-parked along the curb of Pottstown's narrow streets. There were scores of federal agents, unmistakable in dark suits with elastic black mourning bands stretched over their badges. Nearly 400 state troopers -- about 200 each from Pennsylvania and New Jersey -- flanked a road outside the center, marching in military formation while Mr. Bush's funeral was under way and saluting the hearse bearing his coffin as it passed.</p>
        <p>About 750 people filled the arts center where Mr. Bush's flag-draped coffin -- made of polished wood with gold trim -- lay in repose. At one point, a line for the viewing at Mr. Bush's funeral snaked about a quarter of a mile.</p>
        <p>''It was a righteous celebration,'' said John Gibson, 49, a Pottstown resident, who attended the service. ''I'm sure hearts were broken, but it was a celebration of a good person's life.''</p>
        <p>After a four-hour viewing, the funeral for Mr. Bush, 52, included eulogies from Mr. Mueller, the reading of a letter to Mr. Bush from his wife, Karen, and a testimonial from Mr. Bush's fellow F.B.I. agent and friend of 15 years, Gabriel J. Scala.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, who lived in Easton, Pa., was reared in Pottstown, about 40 miles northwest of Philadelphia. Although he did not attend the Hill School, the arts center there was one of the only sites in this working-class town of about 20,000 large enough to accommodate the crowd.</p>
        <p>Kevin Poole, 51, a community activist in the area, said that Mr. Bush's hometown would always hold him in high regard.</p>
        <p>''We're famous for Mrs. Smith's pies and steel and things like that, but it's a sad but honorable thing to have a man that served in this capacity,'' he said. ''We're really saddened but honored to have a guy like this come from our community.''</p>
        <p>After the service, Mr. Bush's coffin was taken to the Policeman's and Fireman's Mausoleum at Highland Memorial Park in Pottstown. Outside the cemetery, eight pallbearers transferred the coffin from the hearse to a glass horse-drawn carriage, which -- preceded by a horse with no rider and followed by 40 of Mr. Bush's friends, family and F.B.I. agents -- finished the journey to the gravesite.</p>
        <p>''It's another loss,'' said Sgt. Dave Dilks, a member of the Camden County Emerald Society Pipes and Drums band, which performed at the services for Mr. Bush. ''It's another good guy gone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
