<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tax-Wary Investors May Be Finding the Limelight Too Bright</title>
    <meta content="13venture" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/business/13venture.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="V.C. NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Startup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E3DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tax-Wary Investors May Be Finding the Limelight Too Bright</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tax-Wary Investors May Be Finding the Limelight Too Bright</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TECHNOLOGY investors were once lone rangers, mostly West Coasters who flew under the radar of the press and politicians, and they liked it that way. That changed with the dot-com boom, when these venture capitalists became quasi-celebrities, and many of them liked that, too.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of them will gather in Washington, starting on Monday, for an annual meeting combining policy debate and schmoozing. They will do so facing a question that has political and public relations ramifications: Is private equity -- including venture capital -- becoming too public for its own good?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Venture capitalists face a question: Is private equity becoming too public for its own good?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TECHNOLOGY investors were once lone rangers, mostly West Coasters who flew under the radar of the press and politicians, and they liked it that way. That changed with the dot-com boom, when these venture capitalists became quasi-celebrities, and many of them liked that, too.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of them will gather in Washington, starting on Monday, for an annual meeting combining policy debate and schmoozing. They will do so facing a question that has political and public relations ramifications: Is private equity -- including venture capital -- becoming too public for its own good?</p>
        <p>The most notable challenge has come in recent weeks. Talk has begun on Capitol Hill that one way to reduce the deficit would be to raise the tax rate paid by venture capitalists. The chatter has sent a shudder through the industry, where some believe that the visibility of their wealth has made them political targets.</p>
        <p>''I'm hearing, 'The sky is falling,' '' said Mark G. Heesen, president of the National Venture Capital Association, which is organizing the annual industry meeting.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Heesen said he had rewritten his opening remarks for the conference to explain that an imminent change in the tax code is not likely. ''I'm going to ask them to please let calmer heads prevail.''</p>
        <p>Congress's interest has been aroused at the same time that there has been a greater public recognition of the role and contributions of venture capitalists. They have largely brought the limelight on themselves, through increasing promotion of their trade, and they tend not to shy away from the visibility.</p>
        <p>Indeed, a growing number of firms have public relations specialists. As a further reflection of that trend, the venture capital trade group is allowing the news media to attend its annual gathering for the first time.</p>
        <p>And the industry is becoming more political, in particular seeking policies that benefit its alternative energy investments.</p>
        <p>''Private equity is no longer private,'' said Emily Mendell, spokeswoman for the venture capital association.</p>
        <p>The attention has had benefits. It has given the industry greater visibility among pension funds and institutions that invest billions of dollars with venture capitalists. And it has allowed the more media-astute venture capital firms to make a name for themselves among entrepreneurs whose innovations the firms compete to back.</p>
        <p>But the investors are learning that becoming more visible has its price. One obvious downside is that it has invited media scrutiny of the dismal returns in the post-dot-com years.</p>
        <p>The double-edged nature of venture capitalists' rising profile is also demonstrated with the theme of this year's venture capital association meeting: globalization.</p>
        <p>The spread and visibility of venture capital across the globe has created new investment opportunities overseas, but it has also created imitators and competitors in local markets who are increasingly asserting themselves, said Mr. Heesen, the association's president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heesen likened the new crop of overseas venture capitalists to teenagers; they were reared and taught by American investors but now want independence.</p>
        <p>Over all, venture capitalists said, their newfound visibility is a natural evolution, one they cannot really fight and one that could serve them well in their policy struggles.</p>
        <p>Among the battles they will discuss next week is one to raise the number of visas allotted for skilled technical immigrant workers. And they will continue to push for changes in the Sarbanes-Oxley Act, whose regulatory requirements they say are onerous.</p>
        <p>But the overriding policy concern for venture capitalists is that Congress will increase the tax rate on ''carried interest.'' That refers to the 20 to 25 percent cut that venture capitalists get of their investors' returns when start-ups they have financed are sold or go public.</p>
        <p>That money is now taxed as capital gains, at a 15 percent rate. But there has been talk in Congress of classifying those returns as income, which for most venture capitalists could raise the tax rate by nearly 20 percentage points, Mr. Heesen said.</p>
        <p>Venture capitalists argue that carried interest has characteristics of capital gains; for example, that it takes five years or more to realize a return. But proponents of the change say private equity firms in general are enjoying one of the lowest tax rates even as the industry has become a much bigger and more powerful force.</p>
        <p>Kate Mitchell, managing director at Scale Venture Partners, said she understood why venture capitalists have invited Congressional interest. ''People really gag at the megabucks being paid in the industry,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But she and others argue that taxing the carried interest as capital gains gives venture capitalists incentives to take risks -- risks that take many years to pay off and that can yield returns not just for them but also in innovation and job creation.</p>
        <p>Heidi Roizen, a managing director at Mobius Venture Capital and a board member for the National Venture Capital Association, said she hoped the industry could use its growing visibility to make its case to keep the capital gains rate, rather than have the industry's prominence work against it.</p>
        <p>''The more we raise visibility about how venture works and what it helps create,'' Ms. Roizen said, ''the more we can bring focus to the issues and legislation that could harm the entrepreneurial ecosystem.''</p>
        <p>V.C. NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
