<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nielsen to Follow TV Viewers Out of the House and Into the Streets</title>
    <meta content="13adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/business/media/13adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nielsen Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Story, Louise</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nielsen Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nielsen to Follow TV Viewers Out of the House and Into the Streets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nielsen to Follow TV Viewers Out of the House and Into the Streets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUISE STORY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Story, Louise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nielsen Company will begin measuring television viewing away from home in places like bars, hotels, gyms and offices; may provide boost in viewership numbers for certain types of programs; networks have often complained that out-of-home viewing has not been counted in past, costing them money from advertisers that pay based on Nieslen's numbers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO watches more television -- the business traveler or the sports fan?</p>
        <p>The Nielsen Company, the longtime arbiter of television viewing, may soon suggest an answer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nielsen will release national ratings for TV viewing away from home in places like bars, hotels, gyms and offices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO watches more television -- the business traveler or the sports fan?</p>
        <p>The Nielsen Company, the longtime arbiter of television viewing, may soon suggest an answer.</p>
        <p>Beginning in September, Nielsen will release national ratings for TV viewing away from home in places like bars, hotels, gyms and offices. For decades, Nielsen has rated television viewing based on what viewers in its panel watch while at home. The moment those viewers traveled or went to the gym, any television they watched was not recorded.</p>
        <p>For some types of programs, the new ratings may provide a significant lift. Sports fans, for example, often watch games in restaurants or bars, and business executives often watch the news in airports, their offices or at hotels.</p>
        <p>Networks like ESPN, CBS and CNN have complained for years that out-of-home viewing was not counted and was costing them money -- advertisers generally base their payments on Nielsen's numbers.</p>
        <p>Networks and advertisers have criticized Nielsen for being slow to update its technologies. But Nielsen has been trying to respond. The ratings company started tracking delayed viewing on digital video recorders last year and will release ratings of commercials separate from its program ratings starting in May.</p>
        <p>In addition, Nielsen is working to replace the diaries, used in many local markets to record viewing, with automatic meters, since what people say they watch is not always the same as what they actually watch.</p>
        <p>Nielsen has also announced ambitious plans to measure viewership everywhere it occurs, whether on televisions, computers, iPods, cellphones and other mobile devices. And it is working with large advertisers like Procter &amp; Gamble to measure how many people watch programs and ads on television screens in retail stores.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Nielsen plans to introduce ratings that roll viewing on all of these platforms into one comprehensive ranking.</p>
        <p>''Nielsen has a mandate to follow the video wherever it goes,'' said Sara Erichson, executive vice president for client services at Nielsen Media Research North American, a unit of the Nielsen Company. ''A lot of where video is going is outside the home.''</p>
        <p>The ratings will be calculated using cellphone tracking devices that recognize programs by sounds. The cellphone will be provided free to 4,700 participants, who will be paid a small fee each month. The participants pay their own cellphone bills. Integrated Media Measurement has recruited 3,000 people who are in six cities -- Chicago, Denver, Houston, Los Angeles, Miami and New York -- and Nielsen will recruit 1,700 others, aiming for a cross-section of viewers.</p>
        <p>Nielsen will sell the national ratings as an additional product to television networks and advertising agencies and deliver regular reports. Ratings will also be available for the six cities with the majority of the cellphone participants.</p>
        <p>Nielsen will share income from the out-of-home ratings with Integrated Media Measurement, a company based in San Mateo, Calif., that developed the phone technology. Eventually, Nielsen plans to integrate out-of-home ratings with its standard at-home ratings.</p>
        <p>Network executives said the new ratings were an important step in following television consumption wherever it occurs. As much as 20 percent to 30 percent of people watching major sports events may view them away from their houses, said David Poltrack, the chief research officer of the CBS Corporation. In January, Nielsen started tracking TV viewing on college campuses for the first time, which jolted ratings of shows with lots of young fans.</p>
        <p>CBS, Fox, NBC, Turner and other television networks have already been buying data from Integrated Media Measurement as they tried to track viewership of their programs and their commercials. The company helps networks and movie studios determine whether their commercials or radio ads drive viewers to watch their shows or movies, the chairman and chief executive of Integrated, Tom Zito, said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zito's company will continue to offer its custom services to advertisers separate from Nielsen. The company can tell retail and food advertisers if more customers visit their shops after hearing their ads, and its cellphones can track programs played on computers.</p>
        <p>The company's cellphones may also help networks offer advertisers more data about how often ads on their networks drive sales, said Jack Wakshlag, chief research officer for Turner Broadcasting Systems.</p>
        <p>''If you use your imagination, this has a much richer potential,'' Mr. Wakshlag said.</p>
        <p>Networks have tried to measure TV viewing outside of the home on their own, and some networks have presented their findings to advertisers, hoping to persuade them to pay for those viewers.</p>
        <p>But Nielsen will be the first neutral source to produce the ratings nationally on a regular basis, and advertisers might be more inclined to pay for out-of-home viewing when they can compare that viewing across all television programs.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time there will be broad-based measuring of out-of-home viewing,'' said Taddy Hall, chief strategy officer at the Advertising Research Foundation, a nonprofit group in New York that studies advertising. ''Think of it as a streetlamp on a dark street. This just expands the area on which there's some lighting.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
