<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Action on Troop Reshapes Bush's Debate With Congress</title>
    <meta content="13cong" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/washington/13cong.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REACH OF WAR: CONGRESSIONAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulse, Carl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDA133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Action on Troop Reshapes Bush's Debate With Congress</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Action on Troops Reshapes Bush’s Debate With Congress</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pentagon's announcement that US troops in Iraq will have tours extended by three months injects volatile new element into standoff over war spending, complicating Republican plan to hold Democrats accountable for any strain on military; Democrats say decision is evidence that Pres Bush and inner circle are in denial about Iraq situation, but will discuss spending measure with Bush (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Tuesday, President Bush insisted to members of an American Legion post in Virginia that Democratic political maneuvering over a war spending measure would force troops in Iraq to remain overseas longer.</p>
        <p>''This is unacceptable,'' the president said. ''It's unacceptable to me, it's unacceptable to our veterans, it's unacceptable to our military families, and it's unacceptable to many in this country.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Democrats have seized on the announcement of troop extensions as evidence that the president and his inner circle are in denial about what is going on in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Tuesday, President Bush insisted to members of an American Legion post in Virginia that Democratic political maneuvering over a war spending measure would force troops in Iraq to remain overseas longer.</p>
        <p>''This is unacceptable,'' the president said. ''It's unacceptable to me, it's unacceptable to our veterans, it's unacceptable to our military families, and it's unacceptable to many in this country.''</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, however, the Pentagon announced that the tours of members of the armed forces serving in Iraq would automatically be extended by three months to accommodate the administration's push to secure Iraq. That announcement injected a volatile new element into the standoff over war spending, complicating the Republican plan to hold Democrats accountable for any strain on the military.</p>
        <p>''It makes it harder,'' acknowledged Senator John Cornyn, Republican of Texas and an administration ally, referring to the Pentagon announcement's clash with the president's declaration just a day earlier.</p>
        <p>Senate Democrats seized on the troop announcement and the sensational attacks in Baghdad on Thursday as evidence that the president and his inner circle are in denial about what is going on in Iraq. The Democrats said that the decision to keep American forces there, for what they described as the longest tours of duty since World War II, will only bolster the Democratic position in the fight with the administration over Iraq policy.</p>
        <p>''This really hurts,'' said Senator Richard J. Durbin of Illinois, the No. 2 Democrat in the Senate, about the longer deployments. ''People understand this.''</p>
        <p>Democrats have had their own rough patches in the fight for the political high ground. Party leaders in the House and Senate vacillated this week over whether they would meet with the president at the White House next week to discuss the spending measure, even though some party strategists have emphasized that they must remain willing to talk with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>And some Democrats were painfully aware that if they did not accept the president's invitation, they would put Representative Nancy Pelosi, the House speaker, in the awkward position of having met with the Syrian president over the Easter recess while refusing to meet with her own.</p>
        <p>Democrats ultimately decided to make their way down Pennsylvania Avenue next Wednesday for a sit-down discussion with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>But it is unlikely that the meeting will produce a breakthrough given the hardening positions of both sides. The White House has said that Mr. Bush will refuse any war spending measure that sets a time certain for pulling United States forces out of Iraq. And Mr. Bush indicated Thursday that the bombing of the Iraqi Parliament building only strengthened his resolve, as he again made his case that a defeat in Iraq could lead to domestic terrorism.</p>
        <p>''There's a type of person that would walk in that building and kill innocent life, and that is the same type of person that is willing to come and kill innocent Americans,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Democrats said they intended to deliver to Mr. Bush a spending bill that contained a timetable for withdrawal, though they have yet to figure out how to split the difference between a House measure that would set a definitive 2008 withdrawal date and a Senate plan that would set only a goal but would require withdrawal to begin within 120 days.</p>
        <p>''We are not going to back down,'' said Senator Harry Reid, Democrat of Nevada, and the majority leader.</p>
        <p>Democrats appear very comfortable taking on Mr. Bush in this case. They said they had public opinion behind them. Senator Charles E. Schumer of New York said he believed that Democrats might have gained ground last week even though Mr. Bush had the field to himself while Congress was on its break.</p>
        <p>''All the verbal tricks, all the knee-capping, all the kinds of things that worked for him in the past when people were for the war in Iraq aren't working for him now,'' Mr. Schumer said.</p>
        <p>The image of soldiers scheduled to come home, but stuck in Iraq as a result of Democratic recalcitrance while money for their replacements was tied up in the legislative fight, was one of the administration's most powerful themes. But the administration-ordered extensions of their tours took out much of the steam.</p>
        <p>At the White House, the deputy spokeswoman, Dana Perino, said that the fact remained that delays in the spending measure were going to make training and personnel matters worse, and that Democrats were wrong to try to interfere with Pentagon decision-making.</p>
        <p>''Surely Democrats see the wisdom in letting the military make decisions about who gets deployed, for how long and when, rather than them calling the shots from the comfort of Capitol Hill,'' Ms. Perino said. Despite the intensifying exchanges, lawmakers on both sides said they anticipated that the spending measure would eventually be worked out. But the political climate may get worse before it gets better.</p>
        <p>''We just have to go through this unfortunate dance first,'' said Senator Susan Collins, Republican of Maine.</p>
        <p>THE REACH OF WAR: CONGRESSIONAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
