<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 17-Year Nightmare of Identity Theft Finally Results in Criminal Charges</title>
    <meta content="13idtheft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/us/13idtheft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Identity Fraud</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">rogge, yorck a</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">dahlstrom, david b</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Identity Fraud</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identity Fraud</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0DC133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 17-Year Nightmare of Identity Theft Finally Results in Criminal Charges</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A 17-Year Nightmare of Identity Theft Finally Results in Criminal Charges</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Los Angeles authorities file charges against German immigrant Yorck A Rogge for string of crimes committed over 17 years using identity of David B Dahlstrom of Salt Lake City; Rogge, currently in prison, is charged with 81 counts of identity theft and fraud; Dahlstrom has been trying to clear up bad credit allegedly left by Rogge; case illustrates tangled trail identity theft can leave; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For 17 years, David B. Dahlstrom, a locksmith in Salt Lake City, has not been entirely himself. That is because, the authorities here say, Yorck A. Rogge, a German immigrant in Los Angeles, has been him, too.</p>
        <p>The real Mr. Dahlstrom, 45, had lived a relatively uneventful life with his wife until Mr. Rogge entered the picture, prosecutors said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>David B. Dahlstrom has had difficulty getting credit and at one point was detained by police officers as the result of having his identity stolen in 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For 17 years, David B. Dahlstrom, a locksmith in Salt Lake City, has not been entirely himself. That is because, the authorities here say, Yorck A. Rogge, a German immigrant in Los Angeles, has been him, too.</p>
        <p>The real Mr. Dahlstrom, 45, had lived a relatively uneventful life with his wife until Mr. Rogge entered the picture, prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogge, 41, who was first arrested using Mr. Dahlstrom's name in 1990, has committed a string of crimes under it, the authorities said, and is in a state prison for violating parole after being charged with stealing a car and assaulting his girlfriend last year. Prosecutors in Los Angeles want to keep him there.</p>
        <p>The city attorney's office filed charges on Wednesday against Mr. Rogge, accusing him of 81 counts of identity theft and fraud.</p>
        <p>The case illustrates the tangled trail identity theft can leave, said Rocky Delgadillo, the city attorney, although he called this one ''extraordinary'' both for the duration of the fraud and the number of crimes traced to Mr. Rogge under his assumed name.</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Delgadillo said, Mr. Dahlstrom has had difficulty getting credit and at one point was detained by police officers serving an arrest warrant in his name.</p>
        <p>''This certainly demonstrates the kind of nightmare identity theft victims can suffer,'' said Mr. Delgadillo, whose office last year established a special unit of four prosecutors to investigate identity theft, a problem federal authorities say has grown considerably in the past decade.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dahlstrom said the ordeal had left him feeling ''violated and confused.''</p>
        <p>''Me and my wife have been stressed,'' he added, ''my credit has gone downhill. I cannot believe it happened to me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dahlstrom told the authorities that in 1985 he lost his wallet in Utah. The wallet contained his birth certificate, Social Security card and driver's license. Prosecutors said Mr. Rogge used Mr. Dahlstrom's identity in 1990, when he was arrested and convicted of driving under the influence of alcohol in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>From 1990 until last year, Mr. Rogge was convicted of a series of crimes using Mr. Dahlstrom's identity. Vandalism in 1994. Burglary in 1995. Leaving an accident scene in 2001. Making a bomb threat in 2004.</p>
        <p>For much of that time Mr. Rogge had a California driver's license in Mr. Dahlstrom's name. Prosecutors are trying to learn when it was first issued and how.</p>
        <p>Jerry Baik, a deputy city attorney, said defendants' records of previous arrests often lists aliases, but the police and prosecutors focusing on the crime of the moment rarely check the aliases against stolen identities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dahlstrom, meanwhile, first became aware his identity had been stolen when he was denied a credit card in 1997 because of what a creditor called ''fraudulent activity.'' In 1998, he received an insurance claim for an accident he was not involved in and another claim a few years after that.</p>
        <p>When he reported the trouble to the authorities in Utah they referred him to the police in Los Angeles, where the incidents occurred. The Los Angeles police, he said, cautioned him that unless he had the true name of a suspect little could be done.</p>
        <p>Problems mounted.</p>
        <p>Last year, the police in Utah told him there was a warrant for his arrest, and Mr. Dahlstrom called the Los Angeles city attorney's office pleading for help.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, there were some lucky breaks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogge's girlfriend, in a pique of anger, divulged his true name to a parole officer last year, who called Mr. Dahlstrom, who called the city attorney's office, starting a deeper investigation. Investigators determined the fingerprints of the two Mr. Dahlstroms did not match.</p>
        <p>From marriage license records, they established that Mr. Rogge was a German citizen, later confirmed by the German authorities, and investigators said it appeared he had entered the United States illegally.</p>
        <p>A check of criminal records showed the streak of crimes Mr. Rogge committed under Mr. Dahlstrom's name, the authorities said, while Mr. Dahlstrom has struggled to clear up the bad credit prosecutors say Mr. Rogge left him. Mr. Delgadillo said his office would issue documents to help Mr. Dahlstrom with creditors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baik said that Mr. Rogge, who was arrested in prison, had not been assigned a lawyer, pending his arraignment next week.</p>
        <p>If convicted on all the counts, he could be given a sentence totaling 31 years, but the maximum penalty is rarely given. The city attorney's office, which prosecutes misdemeanors, is considering turning the case over to the district attorney's office, which could file felony charges leading to a stiffer sentence.</p>
        <p>There may be yet another twist in the case.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors are trying to determine whether the Mr. Rogge in custody is the same Yorck Rogge who, according to an article in The Los Angeles Times at the time, was honored by a San Fernando Valley civic group in 1987 for helping chase a purse snatcher.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
