<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giving All for Her Country But Also Feeling the Pain</title>
    <meta content="13jane" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/arts/television/13jane.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giving All for Her Country But Also Feeling the Pain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giving All for Her Country but Also Feeling the Pain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>We know that it's easy to be seduced by a pretty face, but is it possible to be seduced by a sexy name? ''Painkiller Jane,'' a new series that starts tonight on SciFi, suggests that it is. Someone appears to have encountered the gritty comic book character, thought, ''Wouldn't that be a cool title for a TV series?'' and then decided to make one. The result is just what you'd expect: The name ends up being the best thing about the show.</p>
        <p>''Painkiller Jane'' is going for the tough-gal territory of ''Buffy the Vampire Slayer'' and ''Witchblade,'' and the actress in the title role, Kristanna Loken, certainly has please-don't-hurt-me credentials: She was the futuristic killing machine in ''Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you want to see the pretty lead actress, Kristanna Loken, cut up and otherwise abused by wounds she magically takes from others, SciFi’s new series is for you.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>We know that it's easy to be seduced by a pretty face, but is it possible to be seduced by a sexy name? ''Painkiller Jane,'' a new series that starts tonight on SciFi, suggests that it is. Someone appears to have encountered the gritty comic book character, thought, ''Wouldn't that be a cool title for a TV series?'' and then decided to make one. The result is just what you'd expect: The name ends up being the best thing about the show.</p>
        <p>''Painkiller Jane'' is going for the tough-gal territory of ''Buffy the Vampire Slayer'' and ''Witchblade,'' and the actress in the title role, Kristanna Loken, certainly has please-don't-hurt-me credentials: She was the futuristic killing machine in ''Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines.''</p>
        <p>Here she is on the side of good, playing a federal agent who is assigned to a secret unit that tracks ''neuros,'' people who wreak havoc through inexplicable special powers like being able to cause those near them to hallucinate or making corpses rise from their graves. Jane has a special power of her own: She magically heals from any gunshot, slash or other injury, although -- and here's what's supposed to be the quirky part -- she feels the pain they inflict.</p>
        <p>Thus the show rests on two pretty shopworn gimmicks, the instant healer and the specially powered who walk among us. (''Heroes'' anyone?) Decent scripts could make it work anyway, but the first two episodes at least don't bode well; the stories are flat, and the repartee between Jane and her teammates isn't zippy enough to amuse even the comic-book crowd.</p>
        <p>So the main reason to tune in ''Painkiller Jane'' is to see the lovely Ms. Loken cut up, riddled with bullets, thrown out of tall buildings and otherwise abused each week, suffering but then recovering. Misogynists and sadists, this is the show for you.</p>
        <p>Painkiller Jane  SciFi, tonight at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time.</p>
        <p>Gil Grant, executive producer; Kristanna Loken, co-executive producer. Based on the comic book created by Jimmy Palmiotti and Joe Quesada.</p>
        <p>WITH: Kristanna Loken (Jane Vasko, a k a Painkiller Jane), Rob Stewart (Andre McBride), Noah Danby (Connor King), Sean Owen Roberts (Riley Jensen), Stephen Lobo (Dr. Seth Carpenter), Nathaniel Deveaux (Joe Waterman), Alaina Huffman (Maureen Bowers).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
