<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sallie Mae Said to Talk To Suitors</title>
    <meta content="13deal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/business/13deal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sallie Mae</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blackstone Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Merced, Michael J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sallie Mae</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2DA133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sallie Mae Said to Talk To Suitors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sallie Mae Said to Talk to Suitors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and MICHAEL J. de la MERCED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; De La Merced, Michael J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sallie Mae is in talks to be bought out by private equity in possible deal worth $20 billion; discussions come as company is under scrutiny for its financial relationships with students; Blackstone Group is seen as potential bidder (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sallie Mae, the nation's largest lender to college students, is in talks to be bought out by private equity in what could be a deal for more than $20 billion, people briefed on the discussions said yesterday.</p>
        <p>A buyout, if completed, would be an impressive show of muscle-flexing by private equity firms, which have grown emboldened over the last two years by acquiring ever larger targets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nation’s largest lender to college students is in talks to be taken private in what could be a $20 billion deal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sallie Mae, the nation's largest lender to college students, is in talks to be bought out by private equity in what could be a deal for more than $20 billion, people briefed on the discussions said yesterday.</p>
        <p>A buyout, if completed, would be an impressive show of muscle-flexing by private equity firms, which have grown emboldened over the last two years by acquiring ever larger targets.</p>
        <p>Yet the discussions are taking place as the company has come under scrutiny by state and federal officials over the financial relationships between college officials and student loan companies. This week, Sallie Mae agreed to pay $2 million and to change its business practices to settle an investigation by the New York attorney general's office.</p>
        <p>One potential bidder is the Blackstone Group, the people briefed on the discussions said. Blackstone declined to comment. It could not be learned who the other potential bidders were, but one buyout group was thought to include a financial services firm.</p>
        <p>The negotiations appear to be at a late stage, but these people warned that numerous hurdles remain and it was unclear that a deal would be reached.</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae, officially the SLM Corporation, was created by Congress in 1972 to support a secondary market for student loans issued by private lenders, much the way Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac support the housing market. It was privatized in the 1990s, becoming fully independent as a publicly traded company by 2004. Now institutional investors like the Vanguard Group, not the government, own the company.</p>
        <p>Now its next stage may be as a private company. Sallie Mae declined to comment. While the price -- Sallie Mae has a market value of $16.7 billion -- would be well in the range of other recent buyouts, the company is still an unusual target for private equity.</p>
        <p>The financial services industry has been mostly been bypassed by the recent wave of buyouts because those companies usually have capital requirements that prevent them from taking on the required debt. Sallie Mae presents other difficulties by dint of the federally subsidized loans that constitute the majority of its $142 billion portfolio.</p>
        <p>But private equity has shown an increasing boldness over the last year, having several times shattered records for the largest leveraged buyout.</p>
        <p>Last year, a group led by Cerberus Capital Management, a private equity and hedge fund firm, bought a 51 percent stake in the General Motors' financing arm in a complex deal that is potentially worth about $14 billion. At the time of the transaction, the General Motors Acceptance Corporation held about $254 billion in loans on its balance sheet.</p>
        <p>In the student loan market, Sallie Mae dwarfs competitors like the Student Loan Corporation, a unit of Citigroup; Nelnet and First Marblehead. Last year, Sallie Mae, based in Reston, Va., reported net income of $1.2 billion, and the company has about 12,000 employees. It is being advised currently by UBS.</p>
        <p>Over the last four years, Sallie Mae has grown through a steady stream of acquisitions, especially debt collectors that give the company a growing second revenue stream. Another notable purchase was its acquisition last June of UPromise, one of the most prominent managers of the college savings plans known as 529s.</p>
        <p>And though it leads its sector, several analysts see Sallie Mae as undervalued. Its shares have fallen about 20 percent in the last six months, closing yesterday at $40.75.</p>
        <p>In a research note published Wednesday, Bradley Ball, an analyst with Citigroup, described the company's settlement with New York as a huge plus.</p>
        <p>''We believe SLM should benefit as competitors' unscrupulous practices are prohibited,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>But a deal would invite further scrutiny of Sallie Mae, given that most of its loans are federally subsidized. Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts and the chairman of the Senate Education Committee, is conducting his own investigation into lenders' practices. Mr. Kennedy's inquiry is focused on Student Loan Xpress, a Sallie Mae competitor, but may broaden to encompass other companies as well.</p>
        <p>Representative George Miller, Democrat of California and chairman of the House Education and Labor Committee, is running his own inquiry into the student loan industry. Moreover, profits at lenders like Sallie Mae may come under pressure from new legislation. In January, the House passed a bill that would cut interest rates on federally subsidized student loans in half.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
