<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Matter The Message, It's Delivered With Dazzle</title>
    <meta content="13aile" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/arts/dance/13aile.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ailey, Alvin, American Dance Theater</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Matter The Message, It's Delivered With Dazzle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Matter the Message, It’s Delivered With Dazzle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSLYN SULCAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sulcas, Roslyn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is apparently not much, as far as dance technique goes, that the youthful members of Ailey II cannot do. This junior division of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, directed by Sylvia Waters since its inception in 1974, opened a two-week season on Wednesday night at the Ailey Citigroup Theater, the in-house auditorium at the company's sparkling Midtown headquarters.</p>
        <p>The 255-seat black box theater provided a clubby, buzzing atmosphere for the troupe's first season in New York City, even if it occasionally felt as if it could barely contain the dancers' high-energy, emotive presentation. The Ailey II dancers can jump improbably high and land improbably softly, pour their bodies like cream into backbends and lifts, ripple their torsos and turn like tops. Unfortunately the choreographers who work with them appear so dazzled by their technical prowess that they tend to highlight what the dancers can do rather than draw anything unexpected from them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The dancers provided a high-energy, emotive presentation, but sadly, the choreographers didn’t draw anything unexpected from them at the opening of the company’s new headquarters on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is apparently not much, as far as dance technique goes, that the youthful members of Ailey II cannot do. This junior division of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, directed by Sylvia Waters since its inception in 1974, opened a two-week season on Wednesday night at the Ailey Citigroup Theater, the in-house auditorium at the company's sparkling Midtown headquarters.</p>
        <p>The 255-seat black box theater provided a clubby, buzzing atmosphere for the troupe's first season in New York City, even if it occasionally felt as if it could barely contain the dancers' high-energy, emotive presentation. The Ailey II dancers can jump improbably high and land improbably softly, pour their bodies like cream into backbends and lifts, ripple their torsos and turn like tops. Unfortunately the choreographers who work with them appear so dazzled by their technical prowess that they tend to highlight what the dancers can do rather than draw anything unexpected from them.</p>
        <p>The exception on the opening night program (two other programs will follow) was Robert Battle's 1995 solo, ''Takademe,'' set to Sheila Chandra's percussive vocalizing. The rhythmic sounds are those that accompany Indian Kathak dance, and Mr. Battle uses their complexity and propulsiveness as an inspiration for a highly kinetic, demandingly coordinated dance that incorporates sudden scissoring jumps, low stamping, a contracting torso and fluttering hands -- often all at the same time. Yannick Lebrun met the challenges of Mr. Battle's compelling physical illogic with wit, style and clarity.</p>
        <p>The other three works on the program were all created for Ailey II last year (although Jessica Lang's ''Splendid Isolation II'' is a reworking of an earlier piece), testament to Ms. Waters's quietly consistent pursuit of new choreography. All appeared to have Messages. In ''Celestial Landscape,'' by Darrell Grand Moultrie, a vaguely liturgical, insistently pounding score by Karl Jenkins set eight dancers in shimmering body tights leaping, falling and catching one another to spectacular effect but little variation. A second movement to a slower choral song saw a man convulsing on the floor as the group slowly backed away. By the end any malaise had clearly been vanquished as a final burst of swirling, spectacular movement brought cheers from the audience.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lang's ''Splendid Isolation II'' has a far more somber tone and eschews the obvious virtuosity of the dancers. A woman (the eloquent Alicia Lundgren) in a long white skirt that spreads over most of the stage is partnered by an anguished man (Tyrell V. Rolle), with a shadowy quartet that echoes their movement. The piece is set to mournful music by Trio Mediaeval and Mahler's Symphony No. 5, and clearly something dramatic is going on. Mr. Rolle pulls the skirt over his body like a shroud, then intensely clasps Ms. Lundgren's hands, only to have her finally vanish, leaving him holding just the fabric. It all seems to mean something -- but what?</p>
        <p>Meaning was, if anything, overly clear in Abdel R. Salaam's ''Axis,'' memorably described in the program as a ''choreoprayer for ecological balance and planetary healing.'' Balanchine said that there were no sisters-in-law in ballet; neither is there any way to suggest ecological balance in contemporary dance. Mr. Salaam makes vibrant movement that infuses modern dance with African and Caribbean forms to rousing effect. His visual imagination is often arresting, and the dancers perform with passion. But men in masks spraying aerosols into the air, and women in white as glaciers? No, no, no.</p>
        <p>Ailey II performances continue through April 22 at Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Manhattan; (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
