<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Increasing Board Size, Toyota Names First American Director</title>
    <meta content="13toyota" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/business/worldbusiness/13toyota.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Press, James E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fackler, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Increasing Board Size, Toyota Names First American Director</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Toyota Promotes an American to Its Board</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN FACKLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fackler, Martin</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Toyota Motor Corporation announces that it will elevate North American operations president James E Press to be first non-Japanese member of its board of directors; increases number or board members from 25 to 30; changes are subject to shareholder approval; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Toyota announced a management shuffle on Thursday that would elevate the president of its North American operations, James E. Press, to be the first non-Japanese to sit on the automaker's board.</p>
        <p>The move comes amid concerns at Toyota over political resentment in the United States, where Japanese carmakers have prospered while the American producers struggle. It also reflects the efforts of Toyota, a solidly Japanese company, to become more international these days, as it produces and sells more vehicles overseas than in Japan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A management reshuffling would make James Press, the director of North American operations, the highest ranking non-Japanese in the company’s history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Toyota announced a management shuffle on Thursday that would elevate the president of its North American operations, James E. Press, to be the first non-Japanese to sit on the automaker's board.</p>
        <p>The move comes amid concerns at Toyota over political resentment in the United States, where Japanese carmakers have prospered while the American producers struggle. It also reflects the efforts of Toyota, a solidly Japanese company, to become more international these days, as it produces and sells more vehicles overseas than in Japan.</p>
        <p>The changes announced on Thursday would increase the number of board members to 30 from 25. Mr. Press, 60, was among nine new directors appointed. Four members retired, including the executive vice president, Yoshimi Inaba, a popular executive who had led Toyota's important China operations for two years.</p>
        <p>The changes are subject to approval by a meeting of shareholders in June, the company said.</p>
        <p>In addition to his new board seat, Mr. Press was promoted to senior managing director, an executive post in the Japanese parent company just two rungs below Toyota's president, Katsuaki Watanabe. Mr. Press is also the first non-Japanese to advance to this level in Toyota's 72-year history, the company said.</p>
        <p>His promotion came after years of discussion at Toyota about whether to name Americans, Europeans and other non-Japanese to its board. In the last few years, sales outside Japan have far outstripped those at home, but the makeup of the board did not reflect that.</p>
        <p>About four years ago, Toyota created the senior managing director post as a first step toward giving more authority to non-Japanese, short of board seats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Press is to join a board with 29 other members, most of whom have spent their entire careers at Toyota.</p>
        <p>He joined Toyota from Ford in 1970, when the Japanese automaker sold just over 200,000 cars in the United States, all imported from Japan. Last year, it was the third-largest seller of autos in the United States, behind General Motors and Ford.</p>
        <p>Mr. Press rose through the ranks of the company's North American sales subsidiary, where he was known for close ties with dealers. He took over as president of Toyota's North American operations last year after his predecessor, a Japanese executive, resigned after being named in a sexual-harassment lawsuit. The suit was settled, and the executive later retired.</p>
        <p>If any American executive was to be named to the board, the most likely candidate was Mr. Press, senior Toyota executives have said. They characterized him as having the best understanding of any American executive of the company's corporate culture, which stresses a long-term view, employee involvement, adherence to Toyota's manufacturing process and continuous improvement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Press has taken a more visible role in the American operations over the last year. Last month, he testified to Congress alongside executives from Detroit automakers, with legislation under consideration that would raise fuel-economy standards to as much as 40 miles a gallon, from the current 27.5. And in February, he spoke to the Economic Club of Chicago, where he stressed the company's interest in the environment.</p>
        <p>Toyota has built market share in the United States with fuel-efficient vehicles like the Camry and Corolla sedans at a time when the American producers have been closing factories and laying off workers. Its success has prompted some Toyota executives to express concern about possible trade problems with Washington.</p>
        <p>While Toyota has not been singled out, some in Congress criticize Japan, saying it undervalues its currency, the yen, to help drive down the prices of its autos. Four House Democrats recently wrote to Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr., saying the yen's value had increased Japanese auto exports to the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
