<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Call Girl to Kant Girl In a Flash of White Panties</title>
    <meta content="13hana" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/movies/13hana.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanai, Sachiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitsuru, Meike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuroda, Emi</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Glamorous Life of Sachiko Hanai, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Glamorous Life of Sachiko Hanai, The (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Call Girl to Kant Girl In a Flash of White Panties</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Call Girl to Kant Girl in a Flash of White Panties</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews film The Glamorous Life of Sachiko Hanai, directed by Meike Mitsuru; Emi Kuroda stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The overripe morsel who gets batted around in the Japanese absurdithon ''The Glamorous Life of Sachiko Hanai'' looks like she was conjured up by a teenage boy in dangerous hormonal overdrive. As gently plumped as a freshly cooked hot dog and about as intelligent, Sachiko Hanai (Emi Kuroda) works as a prostitute servicing men who tend to yell for their mothers at inappropriate moments. It's a living or something like it, though mostly it's just a suitable setup for the ensuing clutter of soft-core political parody, hard-core narrative nonsense, breezy sexism, junky visuals and penny-ante surrealism.</p>
        <p>One night, a stray bullet lodges in the middle of Sachiko's forehead, instantly transforming her into a genius -- a super-randy, superagreeable genius that is, one who can expound on Kant's ''Critique of Pure Reason'' while bouncing about in her birthday suit. You see, the bullet in Sachiko's noggin -- as some crudely rendered cartoons helpfully illustrate -- has triggered hitherto untapped mental powers, turning her into a brainiac.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The overripe morsel who gets batted around in the Japanese absurdithon “The Glamorous Life of Sachiko Hanai” looks like she was conjured up by a teenage boy in dangerous hormonal overdrive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The overripe morsel who gets batted around in the Japanese absurdithon ''The Glamorous Life of Sachiko Hanai'' looks like she was conjured up by a teenage boy in dangerous hormonal overdrive. As gently plumped as a freshly cooked hot dog and about as intelligent, Sachiko Hanai (Emi Kuroda) works as a prostitute servicing men who tend to yell for their mothers at inappropriate moments. It's a living or something like it, though mostly it's just a suitable setup for the ensuing clutter of soft-core political parody, hard-core narrative nonsense, breezy sexism, junky visuals and penny-ante surrealism.</p>
        <p>One night, a stray bullet lodges in the middle of Sachiko's forehead, instantly transforming her into a genius -- a super-randy, superagreeable genius that is, one who can expound on Kant's ''Critique of Pure Reason'' while bouncing about in her birthday suit. You see, the bullet in Sachiko's noggin -- as some crudely rendered cartoons helpfully illustrate -- has triggered hitherto untapped mental powers, turning her into a brainiac.</p>
        <p>Now able to devour a philosophy tome in a single sitting, her white panties flashing, Sachiko has basically morphed into Superslut, with her amazing powers now located equally above the neck and below the navel. In other words, she is somewhat more human than a blowup doll, though still as hot to trot as a Shetland in the Sahara.</p>
        <p>Directed, in a manner of speaking, by Meike Mitsuru, ''The Glamorous Life of Sachiko Hanai'' apparently started out as just another soft-core item, or what the Japanese call a pink film, but evolved into something more ambitious, sort of. Certainly it doesn't look or play out like the typical American pay-TV fodder.</p>
        <p>Although our plucky star spends much of her onscreen time undressed (not so her male partners), the film differs from pornography in one crucial respect: It doesn't seem to have been created for the usual instrumental purpose. Or maybe it's just me. In lieu of erotic and visual pleasure, ''The Glamorous Life'' instead offers regularly timed bouts of pro-forma coitus, a North Korean spy and some smutty weirdness involving a clone of the current President Bush's trigger finger. Don't ask because I won't tell.</p>
        <p>The Glamorous Life of Sachiko Hanai  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Directed by Meike Mitsuru; written (in Japanese, with English subtitles) by Nakano Takao; director of photography, Ito Hiroshi; edited by Kaneko Naoki; music by Kishioka Taro; produced by Kinugawa Makahito, Morita Kazuto and Masuko Kyouichi; released by Palm Pictures. At the Cinema Village, 22 East 12th Street, Greenwich Village. Running time: 90 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Emi Kuroda (Sachiko Hanai), Ito Takeshi (Kim), Hotaru Yukijiro (Professor Saeki) and Matsue Tetsuaki (Mamoru).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
