<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Murder Trial to Begin in Illinois, 14 Years After 7 Died</title>
    <meta content="13chicken" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/us/13chicken.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070414T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Palatine (Ill)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brown's Chicken and Pasta (Palatine, Ill, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sander, Libby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luna, Juan A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Degorski, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Illinois</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1DC133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Murder Trial to Begin in Illinois, 14 Years After 7 Died</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Murder Trial to Begin in Illinois, 14 Years After 7 Died</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIBBY SANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sander, Libby</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trial begins in case of Juan A Luna Jr, one of two men accused in 1993 robbery and killing of seven people at Brown's Chicken and Pasta restaurant in Palatine, Ill; killings were unsolved for years before Luna and James Degorski were arrested; Degorski will be tried separately; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years after the 1993 robbery and killing of seven people at a fast-food restaurant about 30 miles northwest of here, thousands of leads failed to bring investigators the break needed to solve one of the most gruesome crimes in Illinois history.</p>
        <p>It was not until 2002 that the authorities announced they had arrested two men in the infamous Brown's Chicken Massacre, so called because the victims were shot or stabbed and left inside two walk-in refrigerators at Brown's Chicken and Pasta restaurant in the quiet, middle-class village of Palatine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Opening statements are expected at the trial of one of the accused in the infamous Brown’s Chicken Massacre.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years after the 1993 robbery and killing of seven people at a fast-food restaurant about 30 miles northwest of here, thousands of leads failed to bring investigators the break needed to solve one of the most gruesome crimes in Illinois history.</p>
        <p>It was not until 2002 that the authorities announced they had arrested two men in the infamous Brown's Chicken Massacre, so called because the victims were shot or stabbed and left inside two walk-in refrigerators at Brown's Chicken and Pasta restaurant in the quiet, middle-class village of Palatine.</p>
        <p>On Friday, more than 14 years after the killings, opening statements are expected at the trial of one of the accused, Juan A. Luna Jr., in Cook County Criminal Court here.</p>
        <p>Those 14 years have tested the patience of the victims' families, of investigators and of Palatine's residents.</p>
        <p>''Everybody feels like they want it to be over,'' said Mayor Rita Mullins, who was finishing her first term when the slayings occurred. ''They probably will never find the answer to 'why' -- why did this happen, why did it happen in Palatine -- but the answer will be as to 'who.'''</p>
        <p>During all the years the case was unsolved, Ms. Mullins said, ''people did look from side to side, wondering who could have done this. It was the fear of the unknown.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Luna was 18 on Jan. 8, 1993, when, prosecutors say, he and 20-year-old James Degorski walked into Brown's around 9 p.m., intending to rob it after it closed. The two shared a chicken dinner, then slipped on latex gloves and herded the couple who owned Brown's and five employees to the rear of the restaurant, then into the two refrigeration units, the authorities say. Less than $2,000 was taken, they say.</p>
        <p>Relatives notified the police when employees failed to arrive home on time. Five victims were found in one walk-in cooler at the restaurant; two were in another. Some had been shot several times; the throat of one was slit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Luna, who had worked at the restaurant until a few months before the slayings, was one of 300 current and former employees interviewed and cleared not long after the killings.</p>
        <p>But in 2002, a former girlfriend of Mr. Degorski came forward with details of the crime that investigators have said only someone linked directly to it could have known. The woman told investigators she waited nine years because Mr. Degorski had threatened to kill her if she revealed what he told her about that night.</p>
        <p>Mr. Degorski and Mr. Luna were arrested in May 2002. Both pleaded not guilty; if convicted, however, they could face the death penalty. Both have been held without bail in Cook County Jail. Mr. Degorski will be tried after Mr. Luna.</p>
        <p>Among the evidence prosecutors are expected to present at Mr. Luna's trial is a videotaped confession he gave shortly after his arrest, a confession that he has since claimed was coerced. They are also likely to present DNA tests that they say link the remains of the suspects' partly eaten chicken dinner, retrieved from a trash can, to saliva samples gotten from the men a few weeks before their arrests.</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers have indicated they may try to discredit the DNA analysis by arguing that the test results were not conclusive and that the chicken dinner was mishandled.</p>
        <p>Judge Vincent M. Gaughan has barred lawyers from speaking to the news media outside the courtroom. Neither Mr. Luna's lead lawyer, Clarence L. Burch, nor the Cook County state's attorney, Richard A. Devine, who is prosecuting the case himself, would grant an interview for this article.</p>
        <p>A confession and forensic evidence often help prosecutors in cases in which the crime occurred many years earlier, said Leonard L. Cavise, a professor of criminal law at DePaul University College of Law, so Mr. Luna's statement and the DNA test results could present major hurdles for his legal team.</p>
        <p>The Brown's Chicken franchise never reopened, and the building was torn down in 2001. There was talk for a time of erecting a memorial to the victims, but the idea faded, and now the corner is a parking lot for a Eurofresh Market.</p>
        <p>Some victims' families have said they are grateful that the case is nearing completion, however painful it is to recall the details after so many years. Many have requested privacy as the trial begins, declining to speak to reporters.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Shilling, a daughter of the restaurant's owners, Richard and Lynn Ehlenfeldt, said she and her two sisters planned to attend the trial.</p>
        <p>''My sisters and I, as well as the families of our mother and father, have patiently waited for this trial and justice for more than 14 years,'' Ms. Shilling, a Wisconsin state representative from La Crosse, said in a statement. ''All of us expect that it will be an emotional and painful experience as we again relive the grief and anguish all of us have experienced.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 14, 2007, Saturday  A picture caption yesterday with an article about the trial of one man accused of killing seven people at a fast-food restaurant in Palatine, Ill., in 1993 misstated the date the picture was taken and referred incorrectly to the date the bodies were found. The picture was taken on Jan. 9, 1993, not Jan. 8. The bodies were found on Jan. 9, not two days earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 14, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A picture caption yesterday with an article about the trial of one man accused of killing seven people at a fast-food restaurant in Palatine, Ill., in 1993 misstated the date the picture was taken and referred incorrectly to the date the bodies were found. The picture was taken on Jan. 9, 1993, not Jan. 8. The bodies were found on Jan. 9, not two days earlier.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
