<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Insists It's Trying to Free New Jersey Man Jailed in Ethiopia</title>
    <meta content="13ethiopia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/world/africa/13ethiopia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Somalia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ethiopia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gettleman, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">connors, will</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meshal, Amir Mohamed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Ethiopia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Insists It's Trying to Free New Jersey Man Jailed in Ethiopia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Insists It’s Trying to Free New Jersey Man Jailed in Ethiopia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY GETTLEMAN and WILL CONNORS; Jeffrey Gettleman reported from Nairobi, and Will Connors from Addis Ababa, Ethiopia. Raymond Bonner contributed reporting from London, Mark Mazzetti from Washington, and David W. Chen from Trenton.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">connors, will; Gettleman, Jeffrey</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American officials say they are working for release of Amir Mohamed Meshal, American jailed in Ethiopia on suspicion of terrorist activities; Meshal went to Somalia in Dec to help Islamist movement; he was captured after Ethiopian forces helped Somalia's interim government defeat Islamists; human rights groups cite Meshal case as evidence that Ethiopian and American governments are running secret detention program, charge American officials strenuously deny (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American officials said Thursday that they were working assiduously for the release of Amir Mohamed Meshal, an American who had been jailed in Ethiopia on suspicion of terrorist activities, and that they hoped he would be freed very soon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meshal went to Somalia in December to help the Islamist movement and was captured after Ethiopian forces helped Somalia's interim government defeat the Islamists. American officials said the F.B.I. had determined that no charges should be brought against him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>American officials said that they were working for the release of Amir Mohamed Meshal, an American who had been jailed in Ethiopia on suspicion of terrorist activities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American officials said Thursday that they were working assiduously for the release of Amir Mohamed Meshal, an American who had been jailed in Ethiopia on suspicion of terrorist activities, and that they hoped he would be freed very soon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meshal went to Somalia in December to help the Islamist movement and was captured after Ethiopian forces helped Somalia's interim government defeat the Islamists. American officials said the F.B.I. had determined that no charges should be brought against him.</p>
        <p>''He's clean,'' said an American official who spoke on the condition of anonymity, citing the diplomatic negotiations over Mr. Meshal's release. Earlier on Thursday, American officials said that they hoped he would be freed before a court hearing for several suspects on Friday in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia's capital. That looked unlikely on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>Ethiopian officials declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Human rights groups have cited the Meshal case as evidence that the Ethiopian and American governments are running a secret detention program. American officials have strenuously denied that.</p>
        <p>Ethiopia acknowledged Tuesday that it was holding 41 terrorism suspects from 17 countries who had been arrested in Somalia. American intelligence officers have interviewed many of them, but American officials have denied any role in detaining or transporting them.</p>
        <p>Members of Mr. Meshal's family in Tinton Falls, N.J., said that they had heard from several contacts in Ethiopia that he would be released soon, but that they had received no official confirmation. But when they get it, said Mr. Meshal's father, Mohamed Meshal, he will ''bring all his brothers and dear friends to the airport, just meet and greet.''</p>
        <p>The younger Mr. Meshal has had quite a journey. The eldest of five children of Egyptian immigrants, he grew up in Tinton Falls and went to Monmouth Regional High School. He dropped out of Brookdale Community College, then went to Egypt to do telemarketing, and Dubai, where he was a tour guide.</p>
        <p>He arrived in Somalia as Ethiopian troops massed on the border. Islamist clerics were urging Muslims from overseas to come to Somalia to fight a holy war against Ethiopia, which has a long Christian identity.</p>
        <p>After the Ethiopians routed the Islamist forces, many of the Islamist leaders and a cadre of fighters fled south, toward Kenya.</p>
        <p>In late January, Kenyan authorities caught Mr. Meshal trying to enter the country illegally. He was put in a Kenyan jail, where the F.B.I. agents interrogated him.</p>
        <p>Officials in Washington said that they hoped Mr. Meshal would be released in a few days. They said that unlike Daniel Joseph Maldonado, another American captured after fleeing the battlefield in Somalia and later charged by the F.B.I., Mr. Meshal was not expected to be charged.</p>
        <p>''The F.B.I. determined after they interrogated him in Kenya that they were not interested in him,'' said an American official in Washington, speaking on condition of anonymity because he is not authorized to comment publicly on the matter.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Meshal was questioned in Kenya, American officials told his family that he was going home.</p>
        <p>But instead of being freed, Mr. Meshal, with 62 other suspects, was deported, without judicial hearings, to Somalia. Most members of that group were flown to Ethiopia, where they were imprisoned.</p>
        <p>American diplomats in Ethiopia have been pushing for Mr. Meshal's release, said the embassy's spokeswoman, Tina Malone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meshal's father said he would not plan a homecoming yet. ''The first time around when he was let go, it was a disaster for us,'' he said. ''We want to be 100 percent sure.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
