<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: April 13 - April 19</title>
    <meta content="13theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070419T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDF133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="15054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: April 13 - April 19</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ALL THE WRONG REASONS: A TRUE STORY OF NEO-NAZIS, DRUG SMUGGLING AND UNDYING LOVE' In previews; opens on Sunday. John Fugelsang is the son of an ex-nun and a former Franciscan brother. He tells his story in this solo show (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 460-5475.</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN FIESTA' Previews start tomorrow. Opens on April 26. Steven Tomlinson's new play, directed by Mark Brokaw, is about an avid collector of ceramic dinnerware whose family disapproves of his same-sex marriage (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 353-0303.</p>
        <p>'CORAM BOY' Previews start on Monday. Opens on May 2. An adaptation of Jamila Gavin's novel about two orphans is the latest National Theater hit to move from London to Broadway (2:30). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'DIXIE'S TUPPERWARE PARTY' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on May 10. Dixie Wingate has left her Alabama trailer park to sell Tupperware in New York in this irreverent comedy. Ars Nova, 511 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' In previews; opens on May 6. The grandes dames Angela Lansbury and Marian Seldes play retired tennis players in this new Terrence McNally comedy. Michael Blakemore directs. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'FROST/NIXON' In previews; opens on April 22. Frank Langella plays Richard M. Nixon in this acclaimed London transfer about the famous post-Watergate interview. With Michael Sheen. (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' In previews; opens on April 29. Laura Bell Bundy plays the smiling, ditsy sorority girl who takes Harvard Law by storm in this musical adaptation. Jerry Mitchell directs (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' In previews; opens on May 3. The Tony winners Michael Cerveris and Donna Murphy star in a musical about the relationship between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya (with songs by Weill). Harold Prince directs (2:30). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'110 IN THE SHADE' Previews start today. Opens on May 9. Audra McDonald stars in the Roundabout's revival of the musical version of N. Richard Nash's ''Rainmaker.'' Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'REALISM' and 'JUMP!' The first play opens on Thursday; the second on April 26. The Exchange, formerly known as the Jean Cocteau Rep, presents in repertory these new works by emerging British writers (1:30 each). Kirk Theater, 420 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'TRANSFIGURES' In previews; opens on Monday. Created from sources that include the writings of Joan of Arc, scientific journals and Post-it notes from the desks of corporate secretaries, this new show examines the Jerusalem Syndrome (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' Lincoln Center Theater's brave, gorgeous, sprawling and ultimately exhilarating production of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about intellectuals errant in 19th-century Russia. A testament to the seductive powers of narrative theater, directed with hot and cool canniness by Jack O'Brien and featuring a starry cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Martha Plimpton, Josh Hamilton and Ethan Hawke, among others) in a tasty assortment of roles. Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:45). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOWARD KATZ' The subject of Patrick Marber's comedy of unhappiness about a rabid talent agent, starring a baleful Alfred Molina and directed by Doug Hughes, is nothing more nor less than your standard-issue midlife crisis. This familiar topic gets the better of all the talented people here trying to make it seem fresh (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' Kevin Spacey gives a bizarre, beat-the-clock performance, as lively as a frog on a hot plate, as James Tyrone in this off-kilter revival of Eugene O'Neill's last play. Mercifully, he does not block the view of Eve Best, who maps the contradictory levels of Tyrone's strapping love interest with clarity and intelligence (2:50). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'PRELUDE TO A KISS' Craig Lucas's broken-hearted romantic comedy from 1990 receives a first-rate remounting, courtesy of the Roundabout Theater Company. Alan Tudyk and Annie Parisse play a young couple whose marriage founders shortly after the bride receives a kiss from an elderly stranger (John Mahoney). The kiss awakens all three to an unsettling awareness of love's frailty and, paradoxically, of its durability too (2:00). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE ACCOMPLICES' Bernard Weinraub, a former reporter for The New York Times, has chosen a worthy subject for his first play: In 1940, the young Zionist Peter Bergson was determined to persuade the United States government to open its arms to Jewish refugees fleeing the Nazis. Unfortunately, this production takes a hagiographic approach to its protagonist, emphasizing his heroism at the expense of more complex characterization. (2:00). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (David Ng)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'BLACKBIRD'  David Harrower's stunning new drama looks back at a sexual relationship -- between a 40-year-old man and a 12-year-old girl -- that transforms, cripples and paralyzes. Jeff Daniels and Alison Pill, both extraordinary, peel their characters down to their barest souls. Joe Mantello is the masterly director(1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DARK AT THE TOP OF THE STAIRS' Jack Cummings III directs a respectable if reverential revival of William Inge's last major play. Seeking to access the poetry in Inge's homely tale of troubled lives in the Midwest in the 1920s, he can't quite hide its fundamentally prosaic qualities. Still, this Transport Group production gives audiences a chance to encounter a rarely seen drama from Broadway's heyday (2:35). Connelly Theater, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'DYING CITY' Christopher Shinn's crafty and unsettling play about grief and violence, set in the shadow of the Iraq war. Directed by James Macdonald and fiercely acted by Pablo Schreiber and Rebecca Brooksher, this quiet, transfixing production turns passive aggression into a theatrical dynamic (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-7600. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'EXITS AND ENTRANCES'  Athol Fugard casts a tender glance back at an actor whose dedication to theater helped spark his own in this warm if insubstantial stage memoir. Morlan Higgins capably excavates the emotional core of a role that might have seemed generic, playing an aging gay actor reckoning with the end of an up-and-down career. William Dennis Hurley plays the Fugard stand-in (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'JACK GOES BOATING' Bob Glaudini's gentle comedy about pothead losers in love is a reminder of how engrossing uneventful lives can be in the hands of the right actors. Peter DuBois directs the easygoing ensemble, brilliantly led by Philip Seymour Hoffman (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'KING HEDLEY II' The Signature Theater Company concludes its season dedicated to August Wilson with a gritty, strongly cast revival of this play set in a violence-ravaged Pittsburgh in the 1980s. Russell Hornsby gives a galvanizing performance in the title role, as a man struggling to live down the errors of his past and plant the seeds for a promising new life (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MARIE ANTOINETTE: THE COLOR OF FLESH' Joe Gross's intriguing play features impeccable performances by Amanda Jones, Samantha Ives and Jonathan Kells Phillips as the three corners of a triangle of love and friendship caught up in the French Revolution. It's no ordinary triangle: Ms. Jones plays Marie Antoinette, and Ms. Ives the real portraitist who often painted her (1:30). The 45th Street Theater, 354 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 254-9533. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'THE NIBROC TRILOGY' ''Last Train to Nibroc,'' ''See Rock City'' and ''Gulf View Drive'' make no mention of 19th-century Russian intellectuals but they do signal the arrival of a talented American playwright, Arlene Hutton. Set in Kentucky and Florida, between the beginning of World War II and the early 1950s, the plays track the life of a young couple whose individual ambitions conflict; they also clash with the goals of a changing American society. Straightforward and heartfelt, but never treacly, the works stand out in a cold, postmodern universe. Try ''See Rock City'' if you have time for only one (1:25, 1:30 and 1:55). 78th Street Theater Lab, 236 West 78th Street, (212) 352-3101. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'OUR LEADING LADY' Kate Mulgrew stars as Laura Keene, who was starring in ''Our American Cousin'' on the night Lincoln was shot, in Charles Busch's uneven new comedy. An occasionally lively but mostly lumpen tribute to the glamour and grit of the theatrical life of a past era (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SERENDIB' David Zellnik's play about a group of scientists observing monkeys in Sri Lanka tackles questions about masculinity and social dominance within a framework that is too cute by half. That said, Mr. Zellnik seems to have more on his mind than many young playwrights (1:55). Ensemble Studio Theater, 549 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 247-4982. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'SOME MEN' Terrence McNally's hit-and-miss comedy about gay life is a parade of cleanly drawn types, zippy one-liners and sentimental set pieces, woven into a pageant of the ages à la ''Cavalcade,'' Noël Coward's generations-spanning tribute to the British stiff upper lip. Trip Cullman directs the agile, appealing cast (2:00). Second Stage, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'WAKE UP MR. SLEEPY! YOUR UNCONSCIOUS MIND IS DEAD!' Richard Foreman's latest film-theater hybrid is a memorial service, of sorts, for the intuitive self, killed by a surface-worshiping world. It is also a dazzling exercise in reality shifting that is as invigorating as it is mournful (1:05). Ontological Theater at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). B</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'ESSENTIAL SELF-DEFENSE' Adam Rapp's new play is a quirky love story about a wholesome but anxious girl (the charming Heather Goldenhersh) and an automaton with a beating heart and a big vocabulary (Paul Sparks, impressively affectless). Dark, zany, entirely mannered and mostly empty (2:15). Peter Jay Sharp Theater, Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'LOS ANGELES' Julian Sheppard's play about a gamin lost in a Hollywood of aimlessness and empty sex is as thin as the slip dress she keeps wearing and, presumably, taking off (1:20). Flea Theater, 41 White Street, between Broadway and Church Street, TriBeCa, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'MY TRIP TO AL-QAEDA' Lawrence Wright, author of a deeply researched book about the rise of Islamic terrorism, conducts a theatrical seminar about the events leading to the horror of 9/11. He combines a linear narrative of the development of Al Qaeda with reminiscences about the experience of writing the book. Absorbing, and chilling too (1:30). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PROMETHEUS BOUND' With a splendid performance by David Oyelowo, this is a smart revival of Aeschylus' 2,500-year-old play, rich in poetic imagery. It still has things to say about the abuse of power by an autocratic ruler who vindictively runs roughshod over anyone who disagrees with him (1:20). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>'TALL GRASS' Brian Harris's three short plays, black farces all, are not nearly as slight as any sound-bite synopsis would have them seem. Here Mr. Harris, a former stock analyst, explores the alliances formed between love and brutality in scenarios in which the tension builds to culminating shock (1:30). The Beckett Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'TEA AND SYMPATHY' The specter of the Ted Haggard scandal hangs over the Keen Company's revival of Robert Anderson's 1953 play about life in a psychologically stifling boys' boarding school. Girded by Jonathan Silverstein's skillful, understated direction, the play attains an unexpected timeliness as it evolves into a story about the dangers of sexual repression (2:00). Clurman Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes tomorrow. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AFTER THE WEDDING' (R, 119 minutes, in Danish) A modern creation with a classic theme involving haves and have-nots, bloodlines and family ties. The canned realism of the Danish director Susanne Bier is strictly Dogme-lite, but the spiky, screen-filling performances of her two male leads, Mads Mikkelsen and Rolf Lassgard, are really something to see. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'AIR GUITAR NATION' (R, 82 minutes) Alexandra Lipsitz's breezy competition documentary follows pantomiming would-be rockers as they compete for the right to represent their country in a global championship based in Oulou, Finland. The movement, such as it is, aims to unite a war-torn planet in musical fantasy and to rawwwwwwk!  -- but not necessarily in that order. Stylistically, it's nothing special, but the film's droll humor and wild performances are hard to resist. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'BOY CULTURE' (No rating, 88 minutes) Q. Allan Brocka's absorbing drama follows an emotionally repressed gay hustler (Derek Magyar) as he rebels against the obsessions of his culture -- grooming, cruising, working out -- and a powerful attraction to his roommate. Only when he takes on a reclusive and much older client is he forced to pay attention to a story other than his own. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'DEAD SILENCE' (R, 90 minutes) In this new film from the makers of the ''Saw'' series, a young man (Ryan Kwanten) whose wife was murdered by a demonic ventriloquist's dummy returns to his hometown to unravel the roots of a century-old curse. The film's playfully self-aware touches (like a grand old theater named the Guignol) distract from its leaden pacing, three too many final twists and various behavioral idiocies. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'FIREHOUSE DOG' (PG, 111 minutes) When a pampered Hollywood pooch trades his movie-star lifestyle for a rundown firehouse, it's not long before he is saving a father-son relationship and tracking down a serial arsonist. Yet the movie's wittiest moment -- a canine parody of Dudley Moore's first glimpse of Bo Derek in ''10'' -- will be appreciated only by parents, and in trying to straddle both age groups, ''Firehouse Dog'' proves decidedly less nimble than its furry star. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'FIRST SNOW' (R, 101 minutes) Guy Pearce, in his ''Memento'' mode, is a fast-talking salesman in this moody little thriller, which asks metaphysical questions about fate, death and fortunetelling. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'GRINDHOUSE' (R, 180 minutes) A double feature, complete with fake previews for schlocky exploitation pictures, that pays nostalgic tribute to disreputable traditions of moviemaking and moviegoing. Robert Rodriguez contributes ''Planet Terror,'' a purposely incoherent zombie gross-out flick that flaunts is own badness the way Rose McGowan (as a go-go dancer named Cherry Darling) shows off her weaponized prosthetic leg. For his part, Quentin Tarantino, more of a connoisseur than his collaborator (and a much better filmmaker), turns out a brutal, talky and satisfying car-chase revenge movie in ''Death Proof,'' starring Kurt Russell. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE HILLS HAVE EYES 2' (R, 89 minutes) Wes Craven's 1977 film, ''The Hills Have Eyes,'' in which suburbanites battled mutant cannibals, was a pulpy parable of the thin line separating civilization from savagery. Last year's remake was basically the same movie with glossier production values and a less satirical, more bludgeoning approach to violence. This follow-up, in which National Guard trainees are trapped on a former atomic test site and are stalked by flesh-eating freaks headquartered in a warrenlike mountain hideout, is essentially a catalog of transgressive images, lighted and edited like a heavy-metal video. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HOAX' (R, 115 minutes) A first-rate performance by Richard Gere drives this true story of Clifford Irving (Mr. Gere), who claimed to be the authorized biographer of Howard Hughes. Shadowed by the paranoia of its period (the early '70s), this movie, crisply directed by Lasse Hallstrom from an excellent script by William Weaver, is less a morality play than the entertaining portrait of a literary gambler. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece, independent to the bone. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST MIMZY' (PG, 94 minutes) This overstuffed yet warmhearted sci-fi drama follows a pair of wide-eyed siblings as they solve the riddle of a box from the future. Despite leaden direction (by the New Line Cinema honcho Robert Shaye) and a story crammed with pseudoscientific flotsam -- including palm reading, levitation and telepathy -- this wholesome entertainment doesn't talk down. Nevertheless, a film gazing this far into the future shouldn't be quite so unwilling to look beyond the frame. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE LOOKOUT' (R, 99 minutes) This directorial debut by the veteran screenwriter Scott Frank (''Out of Sight'') is a variation of an old, old story, about a nobody (a brain-damaged janitor played by Joseph Gordon-Levitt) who falls in with crooks who make him feel like somebody. Although the movie's no masterpiece -- the final stretch feels forced and unconvincing -- there's a lot to like here. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'MEET THE ROBINSONS' (G, 93 minutes) Actually, if you see them coming, run in the other direction. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAGE TURNER' (No rating, 85 minutes, in French) A pretty young thing slithers into the bosom of a bourgeois family like an asp in this shivery little thriller from the French filmmaker Denis Dercourt. Not Chabrol, but not bad, either. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PRIDE' (PG, 104 minutes) The Zimbabwean-born filmmaker Sunu Gonera's directorial debut, ''Pride,'' about a swim coach (Terrence Howard, star of ''Hustle &amp; Flow'') leading an urban recreational center's swim team to a championship, about 1971, is a silk ascot wrapped around an ear of corn. But when sinewy young idealists glide through water to the tune of ''I'll Take You There,'' the heart still swells. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'REIGN OVER ME' (R, 124 minutes) Mike Binder's comic drama of post-9/11 grief is wildly uneven -- by turns insightful and grindingly mawkish. Don Cheadle and Adam Sandler are two college buddies who reunite, somewhat improbably, some years after the attacks that robbed one of them of his family. The actors rise above the material, particularly in the longer, looser scenes that allow their contrasting temperaments -- Mr. Cheadle's tense understatement and Mr. Sandler's shaggy emoting -- to find a workable syncopation. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE TV SET' (R, 87 minutes) Jake Kasdan's knowing satire of network television sends up the neuroses of writers and the ruthlessness of executives with minimal exaggeration. Nothing in this story of a writer (David Duchovny) pursuing his dream project seems implausible, which is less a limitation on the movie's comedy than it is its source. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WHOLE NEW THING' (No rating, 92 minutes) This minutely observed family drama, which tracks the growing pains of a precocious 13-year-old boy in rural Nova Scotia, is the rare film in which the actors playing parents and child feel biologically connected. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>BEST OF 2006 (Tonight through Thursday) The BAMcinématek offers New York cinephiles the opportunity to catch up with some of last year's best films as determined by IndieWIRE's critics' poll. Tonight there's an advance screening of Julia Loktev's much-praised New York independent film ''Day Night Day Night'' (which will open commercially on May 9). Tomorrow brings the East Coast premiere of ''Il Caimano,'' a political satire by one of Italy's most accomplished active filmmakers, Nanni Moretti (''The Son's Room''), in which an underemployed filmmaker (played by Mr. Moretti's favorite alter ego, Silvio Orlando) agrees to make a flattering biography of Silvio Berlusconi, then Italy's prime minister. Robinson Devor's ''Police Beat,'' on Sunday, is one of the most beautiful and mysterious independent films in recent memory. It's a lyrical account of a Senegalese immigrant who works as a bicycle patrolman in Seattle. ''Climates'' (Tuesday), from the Turkish filmmaker Nuri Bilge Ceylan, is a worthy successor to his 2002 ''Distant,'' with Mr. Ceylan himself interpreting the central role of an egocentric academic whose relationship with an art director is slowly, and largely silently, falling apart. In ''Time to Leave'' (Wednesday), the French filmmaker François Ozon (''Swimming Pool'') looks at the last days of a gay fashion photographer (Melvil Poupaud) dying of cancer. On Thursday there's a preview of Mr. Devor's new feature, ''Zoo,'' a sympathetic portrait of a man who died after having sex with a horse. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $10. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>JUBILO (Tonight) Will Rogers's earliest surviving feature film (1919), about a drifter who finds a home on an Oklahoma ranch, gets a rare screening in a print preserved by the Museum of Modern Art. Ben Model provides piano accompaniment. Museum of Modern Art, Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>WEST OF THE TRACKS (Wednesday and Thursday) The Chinese documentary filmmaker Wang Bing took three years to capture this sweeping, nine-hour documentary about the transformations worked by encroaching capitalism on an industrial city, Shenyang, in northeastern China. As the aging, unprofitable factories are closed down by a distant government, it gradually becomes clear to the local workers that they have been forgotten in China's rush to riches. The film's three parts -- ''Rust,'' ''Remnants'' and ''Rails'' -- will be shown in rotation through April 24, beginning tonight with ''Rust'' and tomorrow with ''Remnants.'' ''Rails'' will be shown next Friday. Anthology Film Archives, 32-34 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, anthologyfilmarchives.org; $8. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ART BRUT (Tuesday and Wednesday) Rock 'n' roll needs to celebrate as well as ridicule its own mythology, and Art Brut, sarcastically but exuberantly singing about the thrill of plugging in and making a ruckus -- ''Formed a band, we formed a band/Look at us, we formed a band!'' -- is one of the rare groups that can do both. Tuesday at 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. Wednesday at 8 p.m., Studio B, 259 Banker Street, between Meserole Avenue and Calyer Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 389-1880, clubstudiob.com; $12. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOSEPH ARTHUR (Thursday) Romance, despair and the struggle for faith intermingle in Mr. Arthur's haunting songs, which can float in a gorgeous acoustic reverie or flare up in electrified anger. At 9 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* ROSANNE CASH AND ELVIS COSTELLO (Tonight) Rosanne Cash has been a frequent guest at the Rubin Museum of Art, a cozy gallery of Himalayan works in the former Barneys store in Chelsea; she was the first artist to perform in the museum's 144-seat theater three years ago, and has been there five times since. Tonight she is joined by Elvis Costello for an acoustic show on the enigmatic theme of ''Magic Numbers.'' At 7, 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CUTE IS WHAT WE AIM FOR (Thursday) At some point between Dashboard Confessional and Fall Out Boy, emo's polarity flipped: instead of grand gestures of sincerity, the hallmark of the genre became a verbose, smirky self-awareness. Cute Is What We Aim For, from Buffalo, tries hard to sound witty and effete, but the band falls as short on that front (''Are you perspiring from the irony/Or sweating to these lyrics?'') as it does with its sluggish riffs. With Circa Survive, As Tall as Lions and Envy on the Coast. At 7:30 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* ROKY ERICKSON AND THE EXPLOSIVES (Tonight and Sunday) One of the godfathers of psychedelic rock, who howled like a werewolf over the flutter of an electric jug in his 1960s band the 13th Floor Elevators, Roky Erickson is also one of the most notorious casualties of that era. He spent years in a mental hospital and, despite genuine gifts as a songwriter, has struggled ever since to reclaim his career. At 59, in what his representatives say is his best mental health in many years, he makes what is believed to be his New York debut. Tonight at 9, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; Sunday at 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com. Both sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE GOSSIP (Tomorrow) Based in Portland, Ore., but with roots in Arkansas, this trio of two women and one man plays a bare but potent blues-punk, dotting anthems of female empowerment with earthy ''oohs.'' With Chinese Stars and First Nation. At 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PATTY GRIFFIN (Thursday) Patty Griffin may be best known as the songwriter of the Dixie Chicks' ''Let Him Fly'' and ''Truth No. 2.'' But on her own she is more cathartic, with songs that plunge into love as mysticism, desire and faith. Her songs may twang, but they can also cut deep. With Terremoto. At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; $29 and $39. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>GUSTER (Tonight and tomorrow night) Guster, a band from Boston, has followed the Dave Matthews Band's playbook for building an audience: touring constantly and singing unabashedly earnest folk-rock songs about the painful uncertainties of friendship, love and growing up. With Mason Jennings tonight and the Format tomorrow. At 8, Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; $39 (sold out tomorrow). (Pareles)</p>
        <p>BUDDY GUY (Tonight) The blues arrive in burst after burst of adrenaline when Mr. Guy plays his songs, full of gut-level belting and speedy guitar curlicues. He makes nearly every excess sound heartfelt. With Danielia Cotton. At 8, B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $48. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>HOT CHIP (Thursday) With wobbly electronic rhythms and a strong command of the drippy, semi-ironic disco ballad, this English group plays wistful but still snarky dance music. Get too lost in the beats and you'll miss gags like the oh-so-art-rock countdown of nonsense words in descending size (''S-E-X-I-N-G, C-A-S-I-O, P-O-K-E''). With Tussle. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ISLEY BROTHERS (Tonight) The Isley Brothers' career spans virtually the entire history of soul music, from their gospel-heated rave-ups of the late '50s and early '60s (''Shout!,'' ''Nobody but Me'') through the slithery funk of the '70s (''It's Your Thing,'' ''That Lady''), all the way to their recent collaborations with R. Kelly. Throughout, the libido has remained as intact as Ronald Isley's falsetto. Opening the show is Sharon Jones, the queen of an active local scene that recreates, spiritedly but not too pedantically, the musky sound of Stax/Volt '60s soul. At 8, United Palace Theater, 4140 Broadway, at 175th Street, Washington Heights, (212) 307-7171, concertstonight.com; $39.50 to $69.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JANDEK (Tomorrow) A singer, guitarist and occasional keyboardist from Texas, Jandek is also one of the great sphinxes of contemporary American music. Since the late '70s he has released dozens of strange, challenging albums -- his music is a creaky, nightmarish variation of folk-rock -- and maintained an almost total void in place of a public persona. (For years, no one was even sure what he looked like.) Recently he has begun to tour a little, and tomorrow, in a show presented by Tonic, he plays with two veteran underground musicians, the guitarist Tim Foljahn (playing bass) and the drummer Jim White. At 8 p.m., Abrons Arts Center, Henry Street Settlement, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 598-0400, henrystreet.org; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NORAH JONES (Wednesday) For those who have missed her occasional unannounced gigs at small, no-cover Manhattan bars, in which she wears disguises and does everything from punk to country, Ms. Jones plays a fully official concert at a big, conspicuous place, leading her band in the music that made her famous: gentle, comforting soul-jazz. Opening the show is M. Ward, a gifted singer and guitarist better known for his work as a sideman (Cat Power, Bright Eyes) than for his tasteful and beguiling songs. At 8 p.m., Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $39.50 to $60. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* SALIF KEITA (Thursday) Salif Keita, from Mali, has long been celebrated for a cosmopolitan ear and a voice that can melt hearts, but lately his work has been even more entrancing than usual. His latest album, ''M'Bemba'' (Decca), has songs of love and tribute to ancestors, its acoustic guitars joined by instruments from Hawaii, the Caribbean and even medieval Europe. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $41 in advance, $45 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KLAXONS, BONDE DO ROLE (Tonight) Klaxons' eerie rave-punk is punctuated by the peal of air-raid sirens and paranoid, shouted lyrics that allude to William S. Burroughs and Thomas Pynchon. How this British band manages to cram in such fear and loathing and still make exhilarating, danceable grooves is what makes it fascinating. With Bonde do Role, a raucous Brazilian trio that makes silly but contagiously high-energy pastiches of electronics and fist-pumping hard rock, à la the early Beastie Boys . At 10, Studio B, 259 Banker Street, between Meserole Avenue and Calyer Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 389-1880, clubstudiob.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* THE LOCUST, CATTLE DECAPITATION, DAUGHTERS (Tonight and tomorrow night) If noise-rock had superheroes, the Locust would surely be among them. Not only does this long-running San Diego band have a supreme control of its screamy hurricane of sound -- delivered in quick blasts of guitar, keyboards and indecipherable squeals -- but the group also dresses in skintight insect costumes from head to toe, all the way up to the black mesh over their eyes. (Perfect for Halloween merchandising!) It plays with Cattle Decapitation, a ''deathgrind'' metal band once affiliated with the Locust, and Daughters, a noisy band from Providence, R.I. Tonight at 6:30, Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $15. Tomorrow night at 7, Europa, 98-104 Meserole Avenue, at Manhattan Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 383-5723, europaclub.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LOSER'S LOUNGE TRIBUTE TO HALL AND OATES (Tonight and tomorrow night) As Nick Lowe said, you've got to be cruel to be kind. Joe McGinty's enduring Loser's Lounge series, now 14, both honors and skewers pop greats with cleverly over-the-top performances, and turns its attention here to Hall and Oates, whose mega-selling soul-pop ranged from the sublime (''She's Gone'') to the farcical (''Portable Radio''). At 7 and 9:30, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LURA (Tomorrow) A young Cape Verdean singer who was born in Portugal, Lura specializes in bubbly, lilting acoustic songs that are quicker and more danceable -- but no less sensuous -- than the morna tunes popularized by Cesaria Evora. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, worldmusicinstitute.org or symphonyspace.org; $27; $15 for students. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PLAIN WHITE T'S (Tuesday) Trite is a strong word, but when it comes to ''Hate (I Really Don't Like You),'' this Chicago power-pop band's irritatingly bland recent radio hit (''Hate is a strong word/But I really, really, really don't like you''), it may not be strong enough. With Boys Night Out, Lovedrug, and Dear and the Headlights. At 8 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $16 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RJD2 (Tonight) As a D.J. and producer, RJD2 -- born R. J. Krohn -- has made a mark in underground hip-hop with productions and remixes for Aceyalone, Aesop Rock and El-P, as well as his collaboration with the rapper Blueprint in Soul Position. He likes crisp funk drum breaks overlaid with brooding chords for a mixture of heft and introspection. With Busdriver and Happy Chichester. At 6, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>RODRIGO Y GABRIELA (Monday) Once thrash-metal bandmates in Mexico, this guitar duo discovered what the Gipsy Kings have long known: Europeans and Americans go crazy for virtuosic acoustic renditions of their favorite '70s rock ballads. The Gipsy Kings did it with ''Hotel California,'' and Rodrigo y Gabriela's repertory includes a lush ''Stairway to Heaven.'' With Krystle Warren. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Kenny Wayne Shepherd (Wednesday) A 29-year-old blues guitarist inspired equally by the Allman Brothers and Muddy Waters, Mr. Shepherd recently released ''10 Days Out (Blues From the Backroads)'' (Reprise), a CD-DVD package documenting his work with various blues greats, including B. B. King, Clarence (Gatemouth) Brown, Honeyboy Edwards and Etta Baker. Since working on it, several of his collaborators have died, but for this tour he is joined by Hubert Sumlin, Bryan Lee and Buddy Flett. At 8 p.m., Gramercy Theater, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PATTI SMITH (Wednesday) Her first flash of rock 'n' roll brilliance, and maybe still her best, was a cover: Them's ''Gloria,'' transformed from garage-rock swagger into an erotic rhapsody. So Patti Smith's new album, ''Twelve'' (Columbia), with versions of songs by the Rolling Stones, Nirvana, Jimi Hendrix and others, is especially promising. She offers a preview at the Hiro Ballroom. At 7 p.m., 371 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>UMPHREY'S McGEE (Tonight) One of the few jam bands to gain critical respect in the rock world, Umphrey's McGee, from South Bend, Ind., seamlessly incorporates the irregular meters and gnarled guitar patterns of classic progressive rock into the spoonful-of-sugar textures more common in its milieu, a feat of reconciliation that impresses the connoisseurs and keeps all others on their feet. At 9, Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171, nokiatheatrenyc.com; $26.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>UNCLE MONK (Monday) There is life after the Ramones, but who knew that its sound would be bluegrass? Tom Erdelyi, better known as Tommy Ramone, the band's first drummer (and only surviving original member), plays a mean mandolin in this new acoustic duo, singing tautly written songs about the comforts and subtle politics of home life. With Copper Kettle. At 7:30 p.m., Parkside Lounge, 317 East Houston Street, between Clinton and Attorney Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 673-6270, parksidelounge.com. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>RASHIED ALI QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Rashied Ali has led a substantial career in the jazz avant-garde over the past 40 years, beginning with his role in the late-period work of John Coltrane. His drumming drives this hard-bop band, featuring the trumpeter Jumaane Smith and the tenor saxophonist Lawrence Clark. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>J. D. ALLEN TRIO (Tonight) J. D. Allen, a harmonically adventurous tenor saxophonist, enjoys strong support from Gregg August on bass and Rudy Royston on drums. At 8:30 and 10, the River Room, Riverbank State Park, Riverside Drive at 145th Street, Hamilton Heights, (212) 491-1500, theriverroomofharlem.com; cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETER APFELBAUM AND NEW YORK HIEROGLYPHICS (Thursday) Peter Apfelbaum, a multireedist and pianist, celebrates the 30th anniversary of this adventurous African-inspired band, with collaborators including Abdoulaye Diabate on kora, Peck Allmond on trumpet and Charles Burnham on violin. At 10 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, near Metropolitan Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934, zebuloncafeconcert.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE BERESFORD / MICHAEL BATES (Wednesday) Mr. Beresford, a multi-instrumentalist long ensconced in British free-improvisational circles, teams up with the trumpeter Nate Wooley and the drummer Harris Eisenstadt. Then Mr. Bates, a bassist, leads Outside Sources, with Russ Johnson on trumpet, Tony Malaby on tenor saxophone and Jeff Davis on drums. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BOSSABRASIL FESTIVAL (Tuesday through Thursday) On Tuesday and Wednesday this festival showcases the pianist Cesar Camargo Mariano and the guitarist Romero Lubambo in a duo, and the jazz-pop singer Leny Andrade with the Cuban saxophonist and clarinetist Paquito d'Rivera. Thursday's lineup includes the guitarist Dori Caymmi and the singer known as Joyce, with a trio led by the American pianist Kenny Werner. (Through April 21.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AVISHAI COHEN / HIROMI'S SONICBLOOM (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Cohen is a bassist whose new album, ''As Is '' (Half Note), documents a recent run here with his groove-oriented band. The pianist Hiromi Uehara also has a new release: ''Time Control'' (Telarc), an audacious jolt of fusion with the core group featured here. (Through April 22.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $25 at tables, $15 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SHANE ENDSLEY BAND (Thursday) Shane Endsley, an adventurous yet lyrical trumpeter, leads a modernistic ensemble stocked with peers like the drummer Rudy Royston and the guitarist Mike Gamble. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>E.S.T. / MATTHEW SHIPP (Tomorrow) The initials stand for Esbjorn Svensson Trio, a Swedish jazz-crossover group with an energetic new album called ''Tuesday Wonderland''; taking its lead from Esbjorn Svensson's piano, the ensemble favors somber harmonies and skittering rhythms. Mr. Shipp, in an opening solo piano set, will most likely suggest a darker ideal. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $25 in advance, $30 tomorrow. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANAT FORT (Tonight) Ms. Fort is a prepossessing young pianist with an auspicious new debut album. She performs her own music with her working trio, the bassist Gary Wang and the drummer Roland Schneider. At 10:30, BAMCafé, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JÜRGEN FRIEDRICH TRIO (Tuesday) ''Seismo'' (Pirouet), a recent album by the German pianist Jürgen Friedrich, proposes a daring and articulate strain of post-bop abstraction. As on the recording, Mr. Friedrich performs here with the support of an American rhythm team, the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Tony Moreno. At 10 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL FRISELL (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) This weekend Mr. Frisell, the guitarist, leads his rubbery trio with the bassist Tony Scherr and the drummer Kenny Wollesen. Next week he welcomes some other familiar colleagues: the clarinetist Don Byron, the trumpeter Ron Miles and the violinist Jenny Scheinman. (Through April 22.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>VINCENT HERRING AND THE EARTH JAZZ AGENTS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Vincent Herring, an alto saxophonist with a tart and bluesy command, presents a driving hard-bop band featuring the pianist Anthony Wonsey. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $28. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>INGRID JENSEN QUARTET (Sunday) A fiery post-bop trumpeter with a book of sharp, original tunes, Ingrid Jensen performs here with the pianist Enrique Haneine, the bassist Carlo DeRosa and the drummer Alison Miller. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KALAPARUSHA (Tomorrow) Kalaparusha Ahra Difda, a multireedist formerly known as Maurice McIntyre, is a founding member of the Association for the Advancement of Creative Musicians, and has kept that organization's commitment to sonic and spiritual exploration. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Sista's Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766, sistasplace.org; cover, $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BIRÉLI LAGRÈNE AND GYPSY JAZZ (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Lagrène, a French gypsy guitarist, recently released a double album placing his rhythmically fleet playing in both a solo setting and at the helm of a big band. Here he traffics in the ebullient style of Django Reinhardt, his most famous forebear. (Through April 22.) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHRIS LIGHTCAP'S BIGMOUTH (Thursday) This ensemble employs compositional forms as a springboard; Chris Lightcap, a bassist, has creative cohorts in the tenor saxophonists Tony Malaby and Matt Renzi, the pianist James Carney and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL MAYS TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Bill Mays, a harmonically astute pianist, focuses on popular movie themes in this engagement with the bassist Rufus Reid and the drummer John Riley. At 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $25, with a $15 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CHARLES MINGUS 85TH BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION (Tuesday through Thursday) Several of the most exuberant repertory bands in the city operate with a common inspiration, the bassist and composer Charles Mingus, and all of them will appear at Jazz at Lincoln Center over the next week. A bruising big band called the Mingus Dynasty holds court on Tuesday, while the more chamberlike Mingus Orchestra performs on Wednesday and Thursday. (Through April 22.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WES MONTGOMERY TRIBUTE ALL-STARS (Tonight through Sunday night) Peter Bernstein occupies the hot seat in this salute to the guitarist Wes Montgomery, but he has plenty of company, including the trumpeter Jeremy Pelt, the saxophonist Eric Alexander and the drummer Ray Appleton, a Montgomery alumnus. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30; $25 on Sunday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE MORENO SEXTET (Thursday) The versatile young guitarist Mike Moreno has a new album, ''Between the Lines'' (World Culture Music), that establishes his graces as a composer. His sonorous band includes the saxophonists John Ellis and Marcus Strickland and the drummer Kendrick Scott. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM NEWSOME (Wednesday) Mr. Newsome, a soprano saxophonist, teams up with the pianist Lucian Ban to create a contemporary jazz informed by Romanian folk music. Their band includes Cristian Soleanu and Alex Harding on saxophones, Arthur Balogh on bass and Willard Dyson on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AARON PARKS QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Aaron Parks, the precocious pianist in Terence Blanchard's working band, leads his own quartet with Mike Moreno on guitar, Matt Brewer on bass and Marcus Gilmore on drums. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SONNY ROLLINS (Tonight) Last year this tenor saxophonist released ''Sonny, Please'' (Doxy), his best studio recording in more than a decade. Performing his only area concert this year, he leads a trusted band, and presumably will offer searching solos, songbook obscurities and an unsinkable calypso. At 8 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, One Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; $20 to $78. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SUN RA ARKESTRA/NUBLU ORCHESTRA (Tonight and Monday) The Sun Ra Arkestra, led by the alto saxophonist Marshall Allen, carries on the boisterous avant-gardism of its cosmic namesake with a ragtag, rhythmic brio. The Nublu Orchestra, conducted by the sagacious Butch Morris, creates a whorl of timbres in the service of groove. The two bands share a bill tonight; Mr. Morris and company perform alone at Nublu on Monday. Tonight at 7:30, Paul Robeson Theater, 40 Greene Avenue, near Adelphi Street, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 783-9794, ticketweb .com; $15. Nublu Orchestra plays on Monday at 10 p.m. and midnight, Nublu, 62 Avenue C, near Fifth Street, East Village, (212) 979-9925, nublu.net; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* GONZALO RUBALCABA QUINTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Gonzalo Rubalcaba is an astonishing pianist technically, and he plays with a dramatic flourish and rhythmic depth evocative of his native Cuba. He has superb partners here: the trumpeter Michael Rodriguez, the saxophonist Yosvany Terry, the bassist Matt Brewer and the drummer Francisco Mela. (Through April 22.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SLAVIC SOUL PARTY (Tomorrow and Tuesday) The percussionist Matt Moran leads this Balkan brass band, which has a spirited new album called ''Teknochek Collision'' (Barbès). At 10 p.m. tomorrow, 9 p.m. on Tuesday, Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SPIDER'S WEB (Tonight) The pianist Ross Lossing, the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Jeff Williams make up this ensemble, which strives for the flexibility and intricacy implied by its name. At 8:30, Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $10; $6 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAIN AND THE EBONIX (Thursday) Jeff (Tain) Watts, one of the most dazzlingly propulsive drummers to emerge in the last 25 years, marks the release of ''Folk Songs'' (Dark Key Music), a new album with this band featuring Christian McBride on bass, David Kikowski on piano and Marcus Strickland on saxophones. At 9:30 p.m., the Cutting Room, 19 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 691-1900, thecuttingroomnyc.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* TODO TANGO (Tonight and tomorrow night) The Argentinean bassist Pablo Aslan, a prominent figure in the burgeoning jazz-tango subculture, is a featured guest at this concert; it also happens to be the final Jazz at Lincoln Center performance by the Afro-Latin Jazz Orchestra. At 8, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DAVID TORN (Tuesday) Mr. Torn is an inventive guitarist and producer whose new album, ''Prezens'' (ECM), suggests a texturally slippery approach to group improvisation. That has something to do with the alto saxophonist Tim Berne, the keyboardist Craig Taborn and the drummer Tom Rainey, who appear here; but it's also an expression of his gift for organizing sound. At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; cover, $20, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* VISION TONIC (Sunday, Tuesday and Wednesday) In response to the sudden closing of Tonic (see John Zorn, below), the Vision Festival has absorbed a few new bookings for an off-season series one block to the east. Sunday's schedule includes a group led by the harpist Zeena Parkins, while Tuesday's will include a rare performance by the Scandinavian trio called the Thing. On Wednesday the alto saxophonist Oliver Lake will perform with the multi-instrumentalist Eugene Chadbourne. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Clemente Soto Vélez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, at Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 696-6681, visionfestival.org; cover, $10, and a one-drink minimum per set. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOHN ZORN IMPROV (Tonight) Noise is the currency at a John Zorn improv party, which can feature any number of audacious and open-minded musicians. Usually the action has a jubilant tinge, but this happens to be the final night of programming at Tonic, an avant-garde hub that Mr. Zorn helped establish nearly a decade ago. At 7:30 and 9:30, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; donation, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>* 'ANDREA CHÉNIER' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) Ben Heppner, arguably the leading Wagnerian tenor of our day, continues his bold explorations of far-flung repertory with the title role of Giordano's swashbuckling verismo opera, in the Metropolitan Opera's revival of Nicolas Joël's 1996 production. Mr. Heppner may lack the vocal colorings and idiomatic expressivity of the heroic Italian tenors who excelled in this touchstone role, that of a poet with libertarian fervor during the French Revolution. But in his honest and compelling portrayal he sings with burnished sound, vigor and lyrical sensitivity. The rich-voiced soprano Violeta Urmana sings Maddalena for the final performance on Wednesday night, but the popular soprano Aprile Millo takes over the role tomorrow. The stentorian baritone Juan Pons sings Gérard. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $42 to $220 tomorrow, $15 to $175 for Wednesday. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'CURLEW RIVER' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Britten called his one-act opera ''Curlew River'' a church parable. Inspired by a Japanese Noh play, the work takes the form of a sacred ritual, with a procession of monks enacting a mystery play about a madwoman who crosses a river with a ferryman in search of her abducted son. The Japan Society offers a staging of this haunting and seldom-seen work, a co-production with L'Opéra de Rouen/Haute-Normandie. Directed by Yoshi Oida, it stars the tenor Michael Bennett as the madwoman, with musical direction by David Stern. At 7:30, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258, japansociety.org; $52; $45 for members. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'FLAVIO' (Tomorrow) Candy pink and candy green set the tone for Chas Rader-Shieber's antic production of an opera that consists of arias nestled side by side, bright and sweet as a box of fondants: much of a good thing, leaving a reasonably pleasant aftertaste. On the first night of the City Opera revival, the singers seemed to be fighting to find their pitches: making company debuts are Katherine Rohrer, a light mezzo with a nice tone who didn't quite find her feet on the first note; Gerald Thompson, a promising but sometimes wild countertenor; and the conductor William Lacey, who led a strong, lithe performance. David Walker did a fine job as the foppish, foolish king of the title. At 1:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'GIULIO CESARE' (Tonight and Tuesday) The auditorium of the Metropolitan Opera may be too big for Handel. But the cast that has been assembled for the company's revival of ''Giulio Cesare'' is so exceptional that the lack of intimacy does not matter. With a score of astounding richness and variety, the opera emerges as an affecting and psychologically astute masterpiece. With his alluring voice, the countertenor David Daniels excels in the daunting title role. The soprano Ruth Ann Swenson makes a vocally exquisite Cleopatra. Patricia Bardon, a rich-toned Irish mezzo-soprano, brings noble bearing and lyrical elegance to the role of Cornelia. Harry Bicket elicits a surprisingly stylish account of the score from the orchestra. The downside is John Copley's tacky production. At 7:30, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $15 to $205. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'MADAMA BUTTERFLY' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) East-West relations go south in Puccini's famous melodrama. Shu-Ying Li sings Cio-Cio-San, and Christopher Jackson is Lieutenant Pinkerton in this New York City Opera production. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; sold out tomorrow;$25 to $115 for Wednesday. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'TURANDOT' (Tomorrow, Monday and Thursday) For spectacle and big music, the Franco Zeffirelli production of Puccini's final opera, at the Met, is hard to beat. For compelling leads, you might have to look elsewhere: Andrea Gruber sounded wobbly and thin on the first night of this revival, and Richard Margison effortful, though he marshaled his forces for ''Nessun dorma.'' Only Hei-Kyung Hong's Liù, with her reliably floating pianos, was really worth the price of admission. But spectacle and size are evidently enough to keep tickets selling briskly for this one. Marco Armiliato conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Monday and Thursday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out tomorrow and Thursday; $175 tickets remain for Monday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'DIE ZAUBERFLÖTE' (Tonight and tomorrow night) The last two performances of this new look at the Mozart favorite by the South African director William Kentridge and the Belgian opera house La Monnaie. At 7:30, Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $40 to $125. (Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMERICAN SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Sunday) Franz Schreker's much-discussed and little-heard opera ''Der Ferne Klang'' is taken up by the enterprising Leon Botstein in this concert performance. At 3 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $27 to $55. (Holland)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Sunday and Tuesday) Nicholas Maw is one of the Chamber Music Society's 2006-7 ''season composers.'' Here the society presents his ''Roman Canticle,'' a setting of Robert Browning's poem ''Two in the Campagna,'' for mezzo-soprano, flute, viola and harp. Angelika Kirchschlager, the mezzo-soprano originally scheduled to perform the work, has been replaced by Peggy Kriha Dye, a soprano. The program also includes Charles Martin Loeffler's ''Quatre Poems'' for voice, viola and piano; Dvorak's Piano Trio in E minor; and Mendelssohn's String Quintet No. 1. Sunday at 5 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; $28 to $50. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NELSON FREIRE (Thursday) New York audiences experience Mr. Freire's pianism only in glimpses, but this Brazilian returns to the Metropolitan Museum of Art with Bach, Beethoven and Chopin standards, Debussy's ''Children's Corner Suite'' and excerpts from Albéniz's ''Iberia.'' At 8 p.m., (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $50. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* OSVALDO GOLIJOV/DAWN UPSHAW YOUNG ARTISTS CONCERT (Tomorrow and Sunday) To foster collaboration between singers and composers, the soprano Dawn Upshaw, through the auspices of Carnegie Hall's Weill Music Institute, has presented joint workshops with leading composers, notably John Harbison in 2004 and Osvaldo Golijov this season. A roster of young composers, paired with young singers, has been collaborating in these workshops for some months, under the guidance of Mr. Golijov and Ms. Upshaw. The resulting works will be presented this weekend in two very affordable programs. Needless to say, each piece will be receiving its world premiere. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 3 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $15. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>KALICHSTEIN-LAREDO-ROBINSON TRIO (Sunday) This venerable piano trio is celebrating its 30th anniversary since making its debut in 1977 at the White House for President Jimmy Carter's inauguration. On Sunday it performs Leon Kirchner's Trio No. 2 and is joined by the violist Pinchas Zukerman for Mozart's Piano Quartet in E flat (K. 493), and by the double bassist Harold Robinson for Schubert's ''Trout'' Quintet. At 2 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $23 to $75. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* OLIVER KNUSSEN (Tonight) This British composer has a significant body of bracing and inventive scores to his credit. But in the last decade or so he has had a woeful record of meeting deadlines for commissioned pieces. An ambitious new work for the pianist Peter Serkin and a large chamber ensemble was supposed to have had its long-awaited premiere tonight at Zankel Hall. Alas, Mr. Knussen was not able to complete the score. In its place he will offer his ''Requiem -- Songs for Sue,'' a New York premiere. The program, featuring Mr. Serkin, the soprano Susan Narucki and the Zankel Band, boosted here to the size of a chamber orchestra, still looks enticing, with works by Messiaen, Magnus Lindberg and Julian Anderson. And Mr. Knussen is an accomplished conductor, which has been one of the problems, actually: his conducting has taken time from his composing. At 7:30, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 and $35. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* KARITA MATTILA (Wednesday) She's been called the leading lyric soprano of her generation -- though that was before she took on ''Fidelio'' and ''Salome'' -- and praised for her lied interpretations, particularly of Finnish song, represented by one set on this thoughtful and wide-ranging concert. The other pieces are Barber's ''Hermit Songs,'' a set of Wolf songs and Turina's ''Poema en Forma de Canciones.'' Martin Katz is the pianist. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to $84. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NETHERLANDS BACH SOCIETY (Wednesday) The Netherlands Bach Society, a period-instrument ensemble founded in 1921, says it is the oldest early-music group still performing in that country. On Wednesday Jos Van Veldhoven, its artistic director, leads the ensemble and soloists -- including the sopranos Dorothee Mields and Johanette Zomer, the alto Matthew White, the tenor Charles Daniels and the bass Peter Harvey -- in Bach's monumental Mass in B minor. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $50. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Today and tomorrow) Sakari Oramo conducts the orchestra in Sibelius's Sixth Symphony. Lisa Batiashvili is the soloist for Shostakovich's First Violin Concerto. Today at 11 a.m., tomorrow at 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $24 to $79. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* ORPHEUS CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Tomorrow) A new piece by Ingram Marshall is a good reason to go to a concert. Perhaps the only reason Mr. Marshall is not better known is that he's not played more, and the Cheswatyr New Music Initiative, which teamed up with Orpheus and WNYC to commission ''Orphic Memories,'' is doing its bit to change that by ensuring that this piece is played on the orchestra's tour and broadcast. As for the music: think Romantic sensibility and lushness filtered through an electronics sensibility. The conductorless ensemble is adding to the program Gil Shaham in the Beethoven Violin Concerto, as well as Mendelssohn's Sinfonia No. 10. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $30 to $88. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* POCKET CONCERTOS (Tomorrow) Miller Theater presents the second installment of its innovative Pocket Concertos series, a three-year project commissioning 12 composers to write 12 concertos. The lineup tomorrow features ''Spin 5,'' a five-movement violin piece by Charles Wuorinen performed by Jennifer Koh; ''People Mountain People Sea,'' a cello work by Huang Ruo performed by Jian Wang; Anthony Davis's ''You Have the Right to Remain Silent,'' for clarinet, performed by J. D. Parran; and Sebastian Currier's Piano Concerto, with Emma Tahmizian. Brad Lubman leads the Perspectives Ensemble. At 8 p.m., Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $25; $15 for students. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>CHRISTOPHE ROUSSET (Thursday) Call it ''Family Ties'': the concert by this master harpsichordist features music by Louis Couperin and his nephew, the better-known François, and by Johann Sebastian Bach and one of his most famous sons, Carl Philipp Emanuel. François's harpsichord music represents an acme of the French style; Mr. Rousset will play a linked group of five pieces, or ordre, from the last of his four books of collected harpsichord works. From the Bachs, the offerings are the French Suite No. 3 by the father, and the third of the seminal ''Württemberg'' sonatas by the son. At 7:30 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $40. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* UBS VERBIER FESTIVAL CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Thursday) This chamber orchestra, whose members are chosen from the best current members and alumni of the UBS Verbier Festival Orchestra, will perform Mozart concertos with the first-rate violinist Maxim Vengerov as soloist and conductor. The program includes the Violin Concertos Nos. 2 and 4 (K. 211 and 218), with Mr. Vengerov's own cadenzas, and the Sinfonia Concertante in E flat (K. 364), with the violist Lawrence Power -- repertory this group recently recorded for a new disc on EMI. The concert also includes Shostakovich's Chamber Symphony. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $30 to $98. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>YOUNG CONCERT ARTISTS IRENE DIAMOND CONCERT (Wednesday) Young Concert Artists discovers talented instrumentalists, singers and composers through yearly auditions; the organization then presents them in concerts and assists in managing their careers. The group's annual Irene Diamond Concert spotlights two pianists and a flutist. Chu-Fang Huang plays Grieg's Piano Concerto in A minor; Dora Seres plays Mozart's Flute Concerto in G; and Gleb Ivanov performs Prokofiev's Piano Concerto No. 3. Scott Yoo, an alumnus of the group, conducts the Orchestra of St. Luke's. At 7:30 p.m., Rose Theater, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 307-6656, yca.org; $15 to 35. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AILEY II (Tonight through Sunday; Wednesday and Thursday) Alvin Ailey created a second, or junior, company in 1974, almost casually, as a way of working on new choreography. Ailey II is now a world-class troupe, filled with dancers who are not only good but also capable of performing with a youthful hunger for their art, as well as with a reverence for dance that is a part of the mission of the company director, Sylvia Waters, whom Ailey himself chose to direct that first group. Now Ailey II is coming home, performing in the black-box theater that is part of the Ailey headquarters: newer, grander and more gleaming than Ailey ever envisioned. The repertory will include new dances by Abdel Salaam, Darrell Grand Moultrie and Jessica Lang, along with Ailey's ''Streams'' and a chunk of Ailey highlights. (Through April 22.) Tonight and Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8; tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, alvinailey.org; $40; $10 student rush tickets available. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>'THE A.W.A.R.D. SHOW!' (Sunday) The latest in a series of performances produced by Neta Pulvermacher displays new choreography by Ashleigh Leite, Kyle Abraham, Sara Jull and Jennie MaryTai Liu. Discussions with the choreographers follow the dancing. At 7 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; free. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>* LES BALLETS GRANDIVA (Monday and Tuesday) The lads -- or lasses? -- in this all-male ballet troupe will present the world premiere of Brian Reeder's ''They Who Wore White Flowers,'' the local premiere of Victor Trevino's ''Grand Tarantelle'' and their own versions of war-horse classical ballet delicacies like the pas de deux from ''Spartacus.'' At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-4551, symphonyspace.org; $21 and $26; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LES BALLETS JAZZ DE MONTREAL (Tuesday through Thursday) A Canadian company that refuses to adhere to strict definitions of either ballet or jazz dances its way through two new works: one inspired by Brazilian music and dance, the other set to both Vivaldi arias and folk songs from Quebec. Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $40. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>KIMBERLY BARTOSIK AND JENNIFER ALLEN (Thursday) Ms. Allen's ''Open'' explores the joys and terrors of childhood. Ms. Bartosik's ''Ecsteriority I'' is a meditation on distance and closeness, set in a debris-filled landscape. (Through April 21.) At 8 p.m., the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, thekitchen.org; $10. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* DANCE AT DNA: TAMI STRONACH DANCE AND 'OB.JECT.OB.JECT' (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) In the new piece ''Pinchas the Fish-People and the Great Flood,'' Ms. Stronach reconfigures a myth, telling the story from the perspective of mermaids. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m. ''OB.ject.ob.JECT'' focuses on dances by women, among them Jody Oberfelder, Preeti Vasudevan and Hana Van Der Kolk, as well as solos choreographed by Melinda Allen, Tiffany Rhynard, Andrea Woods and Tina Vasquez, and performed by Inspirit/Christal Brown. (Through April 22.) Thursday at 8 p.m. This beehive dance organization is also host to ''Works in Progress,'' in which choreographers show excerpts from new pieces for audience commentary. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, dnadance.org; $17 (Stronach); $20 (''OB.ject'') and $10 (suggested donation for ''Works in Progress''). (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* DANCE PARTY (Tomorrow) In a shared program, Larry Keigwin and his company will present ''Bolero,'' a new work for 80 performers about the challenges of life in New York City, with Chris Elam and his Misnomer Dance Theater dancing Mr. Elam's new ''future perfect,'' which focuses on belonging and fulfillment. At 8 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 279-4200, www.skirballcenter.nyu.edu; $20 and $30. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* EIFMAN BALLET OF ST. PETERSBURG (Tonight through Sunday; Wednesday and Thursday) Boris Eifman, one of Russia's most flamboyantly theatrical choreographers, presents an opening gala tonight, with excerpts from six of his ballets and the world premiere of ''Cassandra,'' by the young choreographer Nikita Dmitrievsky. Next week the group will also perform ''Red Giselle'' and the New York premiere of Mr. Eifman's ''Seagull,'' based on Chekhov's classic play. Tonight and Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, Saturday at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $35 to $100. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* GENDER BENDER: THREE WEEKS OF SEXUAL CONFUSION IN DANCE (Tonight, and tomorrow and Thursday nights) This festival continues with performances by Les Ballets Grandiva (see above) tonight and tomorrow, ending next week with a program by Monica Bill Barnes and nicholasleichterdance. Ms. Barnes's modern-dance choreography is known for its theatricality and knowing humor. Nicholas Leichter explores race and sex with provocative pairings of dancers in work that draws from traditional and street dance styles. At 8:30, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $17 to $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>GREEN SPACE BLOOMS: DANCE IN QUEENS (Tonight through Sunday night) This program features a performance each night by Valerie Green and her Dance Entropy, with the guest companies and musicians Mariko Tanabe Danse and Anand Patole (tonight); Gloria McLean/Lifedance and Laurie Hockman (tomorrow) and Diane Vivona/DV Dance and Balkan Music (Sunday). At 8, Green Space Studio, 37-24 24th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 956-3037, greenspacestudio.com; $20; $15 for students, dancers and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* LAR LUBOVITCH DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday through Thursday) Known for the rich flow of his modern-dance choreography, Mr. Lubovitch and his eloquent dancers will present two programs, which include ''Little Rhapsodies,'' with Rasta Thomas, a guest dancer, and Pedja Muzijevic, who will play the Schumann piano score and the music for ''Dvorak Serenade in E.'' The Limón Dance Company will be a guest in Mr. Lubovitch's ''Recordare,'' in programming that also includes his ''Love Stories.'' The performances on Tuesday and Wednesday include ''Love Stories,'' ''Little Rhapsodies'' and ''Dvorak Serenade in E.'' ''Recordare'' replaces ''Love Stories'' on Thursday. (Through April 21.) At 8 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 279-4200, www.skirballcenter.nyu.edu; $35; $20 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BARBARA MAHLER (Thursday). ''There's No Place Like Home'' features choreography distinguished by tight focus and strong physicality. (Through April 22.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $15. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK THEATER BALLET: 'DANCE ON A SHOESTRING' (Tonight and tomorrow night) This company and its students will perform hourlong programs of new works, classics and revivals. At 7, Dance Gallery, 30 East 31st Street, Manhattan, (212) 679-0401, nytb.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* THE NOTHING FESTIVAL (Wednesday and Thursday) Tere O'Connor, the organizer of this two-week festival, asked several choreographers and groups to create new works out of nothing, dances with no stories, no music and no outside sources. This week's participants are Douglas Dunn, Hijack, Sam Kim and Dean Moss. (Through April 21.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $20 and $12. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>PALISSIMO (Tonight through Sunday) Injuries to two cast members forced the postponement of ''Le Petit Mort/Now It's Time to Say Goodbye,'' by Pavel Zustiak. Mr. Zustiak's company is back in business now with a new work that ponders death and confrontations with mortality. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 4 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 4 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101, ps122.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>QUEENS THEATER ASIAN CULTURAL FESTIVAL (Thursday) The festival opens with American debut performances by the Pasha Dance Company of Korea, directed by Hwang Mi-sook. At 8 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718) 760-0064, queenstheatre.org; $28; $26 for 65+; $20 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>PILAR RIOJA (Today and tomorrow) The doyenne of Spanish dance in New York City will present a program that includes two new works: a stylized flamenco dance called ''Muero Porque No Muero'' (''I die because I can't die''), to music by Surinach, and ''Bamberas,'' whose title refers to a form of folk music that fuses flamenco with traditional Andalusian song to the beat of fandangos. (Through April 22.) Today at 11 a.m. and 8 p.m., tomorrow at 8 p.m., Repertorio Español Gramercy Arts Theater, 138 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 225-9920, repertorio.org; $30 to $50. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>AYNSLEY VANDENBROUCKE MOVEMENT GROUP (Wednesday and Thursday) ''And How Should I Begin?,'' a dance of connections and missed connections, takes its inspiration from T. S. Eliot's ''Love Song of J. Alfred Prufrock,'' but the choreographer says you don't need to know the poem to understand the dance. (Through April 21.) At 8 p.m., Baryshnikov Arts Center, 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $15. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Museum of Natural History: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. Having delved into pearls, diamonds and amber, the museum applies its time-tested show-and-tell formula to the premier precious natural material, gold. This astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples -- larded with fascinating facts and tales -- ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure, Bangladesh dowry rituals and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it, but that gold ingots have a brute force all their own. You are certain to emerge with mind boggled and eyes dazzled. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* Chelsea Art Museum: 'DANGEROUS BEAUTY,' through April 21. A somewhat timely update of a well-worn idea, this show of contemporary works in a variety of mediums by 18 artists examines the beauty myth in art, advertising and the fashion industry. Eloquent but blunt imagery of anorexic girls, chiseled male beefcake and close-ups of surgically deformed faces predominates, reminding us of the violent extremes to which some people will go in pursuit of society's ideal of beauty and a designer body. The rest of the show -- often pointing an accusatory finger at skinny models, cosmetic labels and the mass media -- feels familiar in its critique, but the basic premise about the ideology of beauty in our culture is beyond argument. 556 West 22nd Street, (212) 255-0719, chelseaartmuseum.org. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>FRICK COLLECTION: 'GEORGE STUBBS (1724-1806): A CELEBRATION,' through May 27. One of the finest horse painters ever, Stubbs knew his subjects from head to hoof and skin to bones. He painted other mammals too: dogs, lions, tigers, oxen, monkeys and humans. This intimate show of 17 Stubbs paintings from English collections reveals his admirable range, although the people he portrayed in two large, late canvases, elegiac celebrations of farm workers raking and reaping grain, have the stiffness of figures on a candy box. His horses are his true monuments. 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'HENRI CARTIER-BRESSON'S SCRAPBOOK: PHOTOGRAPHS, 1932-46,' through April 29. Arrived by way of the Fondation Henri Cartier-Bresson in Paris, this show has more than 300 of the prints the photographer glued into an album and toted to New York for curators at the Museum of Modern Art to cull. Captured by the Nazis, he had been presumed dead when the Modern planned his retrospective. Then he turned up alive -- the ''posthumous'' exhibition opened, with him in attendance, in 1947. The current exhibition reconstructs as best as possible the layout of the scrapbook as Cartier-Bresson originally organized the pictures. It surveys the revolutionary work he shot in Spain, Italy, Mexico, Britain and France. His taste for uncanny detail linked him to Surrealism and Surrealist wit, but unlike many Surrealists, he remained committed to human values. Boys mug at his camera. Prostitutes swan. Their gazes equalize them with us. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN SOCIETY: 'Awakenings: Zen Figure Painting in Medieval Japan,' through June 17. Japan Society has a history of producing exquisite shows of Buddhist art. And this one, with four dozen paintings of Buddhists gods and saints hung in shrinelike alcoves, is transporting. And it covers an unusually broad swath of geography, bringing together 13th- to 16th-century hanging scrolls not only from Japan but also from China, where Zen Buddhism, called Chan in Chinese, originated. 333 East 47th Street, (212) 832-1155, japansociety.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* metropolitan museum of art: 'Venice and the Islamic World, 828-1797,' through July 8. At its peak in the Renaissance, Venice, the Most Serene, was a giant, clamorous Costco-on-the-Rialto. All the necessities, and most of the luxuries, of life flowed into and through it, with many items arriving from Islamic Africa and the Near East. With classic Met largesse, this exhibition suggests the spectacle of two different cultures meeting in one fantastic city, in which commerce and love of beauty, those great levelers, unite them in a fruitful bond. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* El Museo del Barrio: 'The Disappeared (Los Desaparecidos),' through June 17. The most potent show of contemporary political art of the season, and one of the most moving shows of any kind in the city right now. The title refers to a peculiarly chilling form of violence associated with political upheavals in Latin America over the past 40 years, and now becoming more common in Iraq. 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, (212) 831-7272, elmuseo .org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Museum of Modern Art: JEFF WALL, through May 14. This majestic show makes a great case for Mr. Wall as the most complete, if traditional, of the untraditional artists who emerged from the turmoil of Conceptual Art. His often immense color transparencies mounted on light boxes are enthralling vehicles, intent on giving pleasure while making a point or two about society, art, history, visual perception, the human animal or all of the above. An imposing blend of painting, street photography and movies, they blur reality and artifice, narrative and form, detail and the big statement. You can't stop looking at them. (212) 708-9400, moma.org (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Lorna Simpson,' through May 6. This tight, refined and impassioned survey covers more than 20 years of Lorna Simpson's career, from her photo-and-text meditations on race and sexism in the 1980s, to her more recent short films, which unite American history and personal history in forceful and lyrical ways. It would be easy to put some of this work on a shelf as ''identity art,'' but with an African-American woman holding one of the highest offices in the United States government, an African-American man running for president, and the nation embroiled in what some people view as an ethnic war, this art is entirely of the moment. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* 'PAINTINGS, FLAGS &amp; IRON: HAITIAN ART FROM THE LAST FIFTY YEARS' This splendid exhibition offers total immersion in the originality and continued vitality of Haiti's self-taught artists. Works by well-known painters like Hector Hyppolite, Toussaint Auguste and Rigaud Benoit range across religion, history and everyday themes. They include still lifes, landscapes and Pierre Joseph Valcin's enthralling rendering of a maternity ward. The forged and welded sculptures of Georges Liautaud and Gabriel Bien-Aimé are on a par with Bill Traylor's antic silhouette drawings. And there are no words for the extravagantly sequined and beaded flags depicting Voodoo spirits and saints, except fabulous. Edward Thorp Gallery, 210 11th Avenue, at 25th Street, (212) 691-6565, through April 21. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Lamar Peterson Best known for his fanciful, Pop-inflected paintings of African-American suburban life, this young painter smashes that subject to smithereens in his new work, a promising advancement that is already yielding rewards. Fredericks &amp; Freiser, 536 West 24th Street, (212) 633-6555, fredericksfreisergallery.com, through April 28. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>'Gifts of the Forest: Native Traditions in Wood and Bark' Drawn from the collections of the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center in Connecticut, this show celebrates the trees of the rich forests that once covered the Northeast, yielding essential materials to the Pequot and other Eastern Woodland cultures. The objects run from ancient woodworking tools to contemporary objects that carry on tribal traditions, like the simple and beautiful wooden flute made in 1999 by Hawk Henires (Nipmuc) and adorned with an elegantly carved bird motif. Many things here were made in the 19th and 20th centuries: handsome woven baskets, carved bowls and spoons, decorated cradle boards for carrying babies, birch bark canoe models, an elegant birch-bark hamper whose sides bear a stylized tree motif. UBS Art Gallery, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, between 51st and 52nd Streets, (212) 713-2885, through April 27. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* 'THOMAS STRUTH: Making Time' Through the 1990s, the German photographer Thomas Struth became an art world celebrity for his outsize, absorbing portraits of crowds interacting with artwork in the world's great museums. As a follow-up, he is presenting the American premiere of two new series of pictures of audiences beholding single masterpieces in the Museo Nacional del Prado in Madrid, and the State Hermitage Museum in St. Petersburg, Russia. The show, which cannily allows us to look safely at others looking at art, is one of the most visually sumptuous and thought-probing in the city. Marian Goodman Gallery, 24 West 57th Street, (212) 977-7160, through April 28. (Genocchio)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* KRISTIN BAKER: SURGE AND SHADOW In these clever, ambitious mergers of Pop, Minimalism and Abstract Expressionism, abstract painting takes another turn for the spectacular, aided by the freshly white-on-white Deitch space. Cataclysmic compositions and an all-plastic, labor-intensive process strike the eye with a dazzling newness, but the eye adjusts and is eventually bored. A series of smaller studies evades the prescribed soullessness. Deitch Projects, 18 Wooster Street, near Grand Street, SoHo, (212) 343-7300; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'Early Chinese Buddhist Sculpture,' Asia Week is over, but its essence lingers on in this exhibition of beautiful carved stone figures of Buddhas and bodhisattvas dating from the Northern Wei to Tang periods in China. This is the type of work that elicited rapturous responses when shown in London and Washington a few seasons back. Throckmorton Fine Art, 145 East 57th Street, third floor, (212) 223-1059; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* ANYA KIELAR: 'LADY' The traditions of photomontage, collage and assemblage are sliced, diced and reconfigured here with surgical precision, feminist wit and a terrific sense of light, dark and color. The works range from two to three dimensions, with the best -- mysterious boxed collages that cross Hannah Hoch with Kembra Phaler -- landing squarely in between. Daniel Reich Gallery, 537A West 23rd Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-4949, danielreichgallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MOMA: Armando ReverÓn  Unless you spotted his single smoke-puff of a painting at MoMA months ago, Armando Reverón probably means nothing to you. Why should he? The artist, who died in 1954, spent most of his life in a shack by the sea in his native Venezuela. Many of his contemporaries dismissed him as nuts. His white-on-white pictures are practically unphotographable. But chances are that if you visit this retrospective, you'll find yourself thinking about him a lot. His art and his story are like few others, and so is the museum's inspired installation: a single, long corridor with cabinetlike rooms of paintings on either side and, at the very end, against a sea-green wall, a life-size doll with giant bat wings floating overhead. (212) 708-9400, moma.org; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>WILHELM SASNAL A truncated, slightly altered version of a Polish film from the 1960s provides the frame or caption for often drab, studiously incomplete paintings that reciprocate with hints of cinematic light or depictions of movie screens. A genuine sense of postwar Communist bloc deprivation is evoked, without giving the viewer much to work with. Anton Kern Gallery, 532 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 367-9663; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'David Shapiro: Rock Iraq,' A while back, David Shapiro filled a gallery with the empty containers of all the consumer products he had bought and used over two years. His current Pierogi solo takes up less space: it's an 8-by-8-foot tabletop model of an imaginary benefit concert. The exact cause espoused isn't stated. But with no musicians present, and corporate logos plastering the concert hall walls, emptiness and waste are the unmistakable themes. Pierogi, 177 North Ninth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-2144, pierogi2000.com; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ALL THE WRONG REASONS: A TRUE STORY OF NEO-NAZIS, DRUG SMUGGLING AND UNDYING LOVE' In previews; opens on Sunday. John Fugelsang is the son of an ex-nun and a former Franciscan brother. He tells his story in this solo show (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 460-5475.</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN FIESTA' Previews start tomorrow. Opens on April 26. Steven Tomlinson's new play, directed by Mark Brokaw, is about an avid collector of ceramic dinnerware whose family disapproves of his same-sex marriage (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 353-0303.</p>
        <p>'CORAM BOY' Previews start on Monday. Opens on May 2. An adaptation of Jamila Gavin's novel about two orphans is the latest National Theater hit to move from London to Broadway (2:30). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'DIXIE'S TUPPERWARE PARTY' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on May 10. Dixie Wingate has left her Alabama trailer park to sell Tupperware in New York in this irreverent comedy. Ars Nova, 511 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'DEUCE' In previews; opens on May 6. The grandes dames Angela Lansbury and Marian Seldes play retired tennis players in this new Terrence McNally comedy. Michael Blakemore directs. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'FROST/NIXON' In previews; opens on April 22. Frank Langella plays Richard M. Nixon in this acclaimed London transfer about the famous post-Watergate interview. With Michael Sheen. (1:40). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'LEGALLY BLONDE' In previews; opens on April 29. Laura Bell Bundy plays the smiling, ditsy sorority girl who takes Harvard Law by storm in this musical adaptation. Jerry Mitchell directs (2:20). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, at 47th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LOVEMUSIK' In previews; opens on May 3. The Tony winners Michael Cerveris and Donna Murphy star in a musical about the relationship between Kurt Weill and Lotte Lenya (with songs by Weill). Harold Prince directs (2:30). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'110 IN THE SHADE' Previews start today. Opens on May 9. Audra McDonald stars in the Roundabout's revival of the musical version of N. Richard Nash's ''Rainmaker.'' Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'REALISM' and 'JUMP!' The first play opens on Thursday; the second on April 26. The Exchange, formerly known as the Jean Cocteau Rep, presents in repertory these new works by emerging British writers (1:30 each). Kirk Theater, 420 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'TRANSFIGURES' In previews; opens on Monday. Created from sources that include the writings of Joan of Arc, scientific journals and Post-it notes from the desks of corporate secretaries, this new show examines the Jerusalem Syndrome (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'THE COAST OF UTOPIA' Lincoln Center Theater's brave, gorgeous, sprawling and ultimately exhilarating production of Tom Stoppard's trilogy about intellectuals errant in 19th-century Russia. A testament to the seductive powers of narrative theater, directed with hot and cool canniness by Jack O'Brien and featuring a starry cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Jennifer Ehle, Martha Plimpton, Josh Hamilton and Ethan Hawke, among others) in a tasty assortment of roles. Vivian Beaumont Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'COMPANY' Fire, beckoning and dangerous, flickers beneath the frost of John Doyle's elegant, unexpectedly stirring revival of Stephen Sondheim and George Furth's era-defining musical from 1970, starring a compellingly understated Raúl Esparza. Like Mr. Doyle's ''Sweeney Todd,'' this production finds new clarity of feeling in Sondheim by melding the roles of performers and musicians (2:20). Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CURTAINS' This musical comedy about a musical-comedy murder -- featuring songs by John Kander and Fred Ebb and a book by Rupert Holmes -- lies on the stage like a promisingly gaudy string of firecrackers, waiting in vain for a match. The good news is that David Hyde Pierce, playing a diffident Boston detective, steps into full-fledged Broadway stardom. Scott Ellis directs a talent-packed cast that includes Debra Monk and Karen Ziemba. (2:45). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920s stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, it has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'GREY GARDENS' Christine Ebersole is absolutely glorious as the middle-aged, time-warped debutante called Little Edie Beale in this uneven musical adaptation of the notorious 1975 documentary of the same title. She and the wonderful Mary Louise Wilson (as her bedridden mother), in the performances of their careers, make ''Grey Gardens'' an experience no passionate theatergoer should miss (2:40). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOWARD KATZ' The subject of Patrick Marber's comedy of unhappiness about a rabid talent agent, starring a baleful Alfred Molina and directed by Doug Hughes, is nothing more nor less than your standard-issue midlife crisis. This familiar topic gets the better of all the talented people here trying to make it seem fresh (1:30). Laura Pels Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'JOURNEY'S END' A splendid revival of R. C. Sherriff's 1928 drama of life in the trenches during World War I. Acutely staged (by David Grindley) and acted by a fine ensemble led by Hugh Dancy and Boyd Gaines, this production offers an exemplary presentation of that theatrical rarity, an uncompromising, clear-eyed play about war and the experience of day-to-day combat. An essential ticket (2:40). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARY POPPINS' This handsome, homily-packed, mechanically ingenious and rather tedious musical, adapted from the P. L. Travers stories and the 1964 film, is ultimately less concerned with inexplicable magic than with practical psychology. Ashley Brown, who sings prettily as the family-mending nanny, looks like Joan Crawford trying to be nice and sounds like Dr. Phil. Directed by Richard Eyre and Matthew Bourne (2:30). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LES MISÉRABLES' This premature revival, a slightly scaled-down version of the well-groomed behemoth that closed only three years ago, appears to be functioning in a state of mild sedation. Appealingly sung and freshly orchestrated, this fast-moving adaptation of Victor Hugo's novel isn't sloppy or blurry. But its pulse rate stays well below normal (2:55). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A MOON FOR THE MISBEGOTTEN' Kevin Spacey gives a bizarre, beat-the-clock performance, as lively as a frog on a hot plate, as James Tyrone in this off-kilter revival of Eugene O'Neill's last play. Mercifully, he does not block the view of Eve Best, who maps the contradictory levels of Tyrone's strapping love interest with clarity and intelligence (2:50). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'PRELUDE TO A KISS' Craig Lucas's broken-hearted romantic comedy from 1990 receives a first-rate remounting, courtesy of the Roundabout Theater Company. Alan Tudyk and Annie Parisse play a young couple whose marriage founders shortly after the bride receives a kiss from an elderly stranger (John Mahoney). The kiss awakens all three to an unsettling awareness of love's frailty and, paradoxically, of its durability too (2:00). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' Duncan Sheik and Steven Sater's bold adaptation of the Frank Wedekind play is the freshest and most exciting new musical Broadway has seen in some time. Set in 19th-century Germany but with a ravishing rock score, it exposes the splintered emotional lives of adolescents just discovering the joys and sorrows of sex. Performed with brio by a great cast, with supple direction by Michael Mayer and inventive choreography by Bill T. Jones (2:00). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'TALK RADIO' The most lacerating portrait of a human meltdown this side of a Francis Bacon painting. Playing an abrasive radio talk show host with a God complex, the astounding Liev Schreiber seems to fill the air as inescapably as weather in Robert Falls's gut-grabbing revival of Eric Bogosian's 1987 play (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE ACCOMPLICES' Bernard Weinraub, a former reporter for The New York Times, has chosen a worthy subject for his first play: In 1940, the young Zionist Peter Bergson was determined to persuade the United States government to open its arms to Jewish refugees fleeing the Nazis. Unfortunately, this production takes a hagiographic approach to its protagonist, emphasizing his heroism at the expense of more complex characterization. (2:00). Acorn Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (David Ng)</p>
        <p>'BILL W. AND DR. BOB' This insightful new play about the founders of Alcoholics Anonymous subtly makes the claim that the recovery movement was born as a series of accidents. Patrick Husted is excellent as Bob Smith, Bill Wilson's partner in combating addictions (2:15). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Ginia Bellafante)</p>
        <p>* 'BLACKBIRD'  David Harrower's stunning new drama looks back at a sexual relationship -- between a 40-year-old man and a 12-year-old girl -- that transforms, cripples and paralyzes. Jeff Daniels and Alison Pill, both extraordinary, peel their characters down to their barest souls. Joe Mantello is the masterly director(1:30). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage I, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DARK AT THE TOP OF THE STAIRS' Jack Cummings III directs a respectable if reverential revival of William Inge's last major play. Seeking to access the poetry in Inge's homely tale of troubled lives in the Midwest in the 1920s, he can't quite hide its fundamentally prosaic qualities. Still, this Transport Group production gives audiences a chance to encounter a rarely seen drama from Broadway's heyday (2:35). Connelly Theater, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'DYING CITY' Christopher Shinn's crafty and unsettling play about grief and violence, set in the shadow of the Iraq war. Directed by James Macdonald and fiercely acted by Pablo Schreiber and Rebecca Brooksher, this quiet, transfixing production turns passive aggression into a theatrical dynamic (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-7600. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'EXITS AND ENTRANCES'  Athol Fugard casts a tender glance back at an actor whose dedication to theater helped spark his own in this warm if insubstantial stage memoir. Morlan Higgins capably excavates the emotional core of a role that might have seemed generic, playing an aging gay actor reckoning with the end of an up-and-down career. William Dennis Hurley plays the Fugard stand-in (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'IN THE HEIGHTS' Lin-Manuel Miranda's joyous songs paint a vibrant portrait of daily life in Washington Heights in this flawed but enjoyable show. Essentially a valentine to the barrio -- conflict of a violent or desperate kind is banished from the picture -- the musical contains a host of funny performances and brings the zesty sound of Latin pop to the stage. (2:10). 37 Arts, 450 West 37th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'JACK GOES BOATING' Bob Glaudini's gentle comedy about pothead losers in love is a reminder of how engrossing uneventful lives can be in the hands of the right actors. Peter DuBois directs the easygoing ensemble, brilliantly led by Philip Seymour Hoffman (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'KING HEDLEY II' The Signature Theater Company concludes its season dedicated to August Wilson with a gritty, strongly cast revival of this play set in a violence-ravaged Pittsburgh in the 1980s. Russell Hornsby gives a galvanizing performance in the title role, as a man struggling to live down the errors of his past and plant the seeds for a promising new life (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MARIE ANTOINETTE: THE COLOR OF FLESH' Joe Gross's intriguing play features impeccable performances by Amanda Jones, Samantha Ives and Jonathan Kells Phillips as the three corners of a triangle of love and friendship caught up in the French Revolution. It's no ordinary triangle: Ms. Jones plays Marie Antoinette, and Ms. Ives the real portraitist who often painted her (1:30). The 45th Street Theater, 354 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 254-9533. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'THE NIBROC TRILOGY' ''Last Train to Nibroc,'' ''See Rock City'' and ''Gulf View Drive'' make no mention of 19th-century Russian intellectuals but they do signal the arrival of a talented American playwright, Arlene Hutton. Set in Kentucky and Florida, between the beginning of World War II and the early 1950s, the plays track the life of a young couple whose individual ambitions conflict; they also clash with the goals of a changing American society. Straightforward and heartfelt, but never treacly, the works stand out in a cold, postmodern universe. Try ''See Rock City'' if you have time for only one (1:25, 1:30 and 1:55). 78th Street Theater Lab, 236 West 78th Street, (212) 352-3101. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'OUR LEADING LADY' Kate Mulgrew stars as Laura Keene, who was starring in ''Our American Cousin'' on the night Lincoln was shot, in Charles Busch's uneven new comedy. An occasionally lively but mostly lumpen tribute to the glamour and grit of the theatrical life of a past era (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SERENDIB' David Zellnik's play about a group of scientists observing monkeys in Sri Lanka tackles questions about masculinity and social dominance within a framework that is too cute by half. That said, Mr. Zellnik seems to have more on his mind than many young playwrights (1:55). Ensemble Studio Theater, 549 West 52nd Street, Clinton, (212) 247-4982. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'SOME MEN' Terrence McNally's hit-and-miss comedy about gay life is a parade of cleanly drawn types, zippy one-liners and sentimental set pieces, woven into a pageant of the ages à la ''Cavalcade,'' Noël Coward's generations-spanning tribute to the British stiff upper lip. Trip Cullman directs the agile, appealing cast (2:00). Second Stage, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SPALDING GRAY: STORIES LEFT TO TELL' A disarming collage of selections from the monologues and journals of Mr. Gray, the ultimate stand-up solipsist, who died in 2004. Directed by Lucy Sexton, and read by five performers, none of whom resemble Mr. Gray, with an affection that shrewdly stops short of hero worship (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'WAKE UP MR. SLEEPY! YOUR UNCONSCIOUS MIND IS DEAD!' Richard Foreman's latest film-theater hybrid is a memorial service, of sorts, for the intuitive self, killed by a surface-worshiping world. It is also a dazzling exercise in reality shifting that is as invigorating as it is mournful (1:05). Ontological Theater at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' Singing CliffsNotes for Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel (2:40). B</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  The biomusical that walks like a man (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' ''A Chorus Line'' with pimples (1:45). Circle in the Square, 254 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'ESSENTIAL SELF-DEFENSE' Adam Rapp's new play is a quirky love story about a wholesome but anxious girl (the charming Heather Goldenhersh) and an automaton with a beating heart and a big vocabulary (Paul Sparks, impressively affectless). Dark, zany, entirely mannered and mostly empty (2:15). Peter Jay Sharp Theater, Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'LOS ANGELES' Julian Sheppard's play about a gamin lost in a Hollywood of aimlessness and empty sex is as thin as the slip dress she keeps wearing and, presumably, taking off (1:20). Flea Theater, 41 White Street, between Broadway and Church Street, TriBeCa, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'MY TRIP TO AL-QAEDA' Lawrence Wright, author of a deeply researched book about the rise of Islamic terrorism, conducts a theatrical seminar about the events leading to the horror of 9/11. He combines a linear narrative of the development of Al Qaeda with reminiscences about the experience of writing the book. Absorbing, and chilling too (1:30). Culture Project, 55 Mercer Street, at Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PROMETHEUS BOUND' With a splendid performance by David Oyelowo, this is a smart revival of Aeschylus' 2,500-year-old play, rich in poetic imagery. It still has things to say about the abuse of power by an autocratic ruler who vindictively runs roughshod over anyone who disagrees with him (1:20). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closes tomorrow. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>'TALL GRASS' Brian Harris's three short plays, black farces all, are not nearly as slight as any sound-bite synopsis would have them seem. Here Mr. Harris, a former stock analyst, explores the alliances formed between love and brutality in scenarios in which the tension builds to culminating shock (1:30). The Beckett Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes on Sunday. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>'TEA AND SYMPATHY' The specter of the Ted Haggard scandal hangs over the Keen Company's revival of Robert Anderson's 1953 play about life in a psychologically stifling boys' boarding school. Girded by Jonathan Silverstein's skillful, understated direction, the play attains an unexpected timeliness as it evolves into a story about the dangers of sexual repression (2:00). Clurman Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closes tomorrow. (Bellafante)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AFTER THE WEDDING' (R, 119 minutes, in Danish) A modern creation with a classic theme involving haves and have-nots, bloodlines and family ties. The canned realism of the Danish director Susanne Bier is strictly Dogme-lite, but the spiky, screen-filling performances of her two male leads, Mads Mikkelsen and Rolf Lassgard, are really something to see. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'AIR GUITAR NATION' (R, 82 minutes) Alexandra Lipsitz's breezy competition documentary follows pantomiming would-be rockers as they compete for the right to represent their country in a global championship based in Oulou, Finland. The movement, such as it is, aims to unite a war-torn planet in musical fantasy and to rawwwwwwk!  -- but not necessarily in that order. Stylistically, it's nothing special, but the film's droll humor and wild performances are hard to resist. (Matt Zoller Seitz)</p>
        <p>'Blades of Glory' (PG-13, 93 minutes) In this fast, light, frequently funny comedy about a male figure-skating team, Will Ferrell and Jon Heder stake an early claim to being the comedy couple of the year. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'BOY CULTURE' (No rating, 88 minutes) Q. Allan Brocka's absorbing drama follows an emotionally repressed gay hustler (Derek Magyar) as he rebels against the obsessions of his culture -- grooming, cruising, working out -- and a powerful attraction to his roommate. Only when he takes on a reclusive and much older client is he forced to pay attention to a story other than his own. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'DEAD SILENCE' (R, 90 minutes) In this new film from the makers of the ''Saw'' series, a young man (Ryan Kwanten) whose wife was murdered by a demonic ventriloquist's dummy returns to his hometown to unravel the roots of a century-old curse. The film's playfully self-aware touches (like a grand old theater named the Guignol) distract from its leaden pacing, three too many final twists and various behavioral idiocies. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'FIREHOUSE DOG' (PG, 111 minutes) When a pampered Hollywood pooch trades his movie-star lifestyle for a rundown firehouse, it's not long before he is saving a father-son relationship and tracking down a serial arsonist. Yet the movie's wittiest moment -- a canine parody of Dudley Moore's first glimpse of Bo Derek in ''10'' -- will be appreciated only by parents, and in trying to straddle both age groups, ''Firehouse Dog'' proves decidedly less nimble than its furry star. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'FIRST SNOW' (R, 101 minutes) Guy Pearce, in his ''Memento'' mode, is a fast-talking salesman in this moody little thriller, which asks metaphysical questions about fate, death and fortunetelling. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'GRINDHOUSE' (R, 180 minutes) A double feature, complete with fake previews for schlocky exploitation pictures, that pays nostalgic tribute to disreputable traditions of moviemaking and moviegoing. Robert Rodriguez contributes ''Planet Terror,'' a purposely incoherent zombie gross-out flick that flaunts is own badness the way Rose McGowan (as a go-go dancer named Cherry Darling) shows off her weaponized prosthetic leg. For his part, Quentin Tarantino, more of a connoisseur than his collaborator (and a much better filmmaker), turns out a brutal, talky and satisfying car-chase revenge movie in ''Death Proof,'' starring Kurt Russell. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE HILLS HAVE EYES 2' (R, 89 minutes) Wes Craven's 1977 film, ''The Hills Have Eyes,'' in which suburbanites battled mutant cannibals, was a pulpy parable of the thin line separating civilization from savagery. Last year's remake was basically the same movie with glossier production values and a less satirical, more bludgeoning approach to violence. This follow-up, in which National Guard trainees are trapped on a former atomic test site and are stalked by flesh-eating freaks headquartered in a warrenlike mountain hideout, is essentially a catalog of transgressive images, lighted and edited like a heavy-metal video. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HOAX' (R, 115 minutes) A first-rate performance by Richard Gere drives this true story of Clifford Irving (Mr. Gere), who claimed to be the authorized biographer of Howard Hughes. Shadowed by the paranoia of its period (the early '70s), this movie, crisply directed by Lasse Hallstrom from an excellent script by William Weaver, is less a morality play than the entertaining portrait of a literary gambler. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'KILLER OF SHEEP' (No rating, 83 minutes) Largely hidden from view for three decades, Charles Burnett's lyrical film about a working-class family living in a broken-down home in a bombed-out stretch of Los Angeles is an American masterpiece, independent to the bone. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAST MIMZY' (PG, 94 minutes) This overstuffed yet warmhearted sci-fi drama follows a pair of wide-eyed siblings as they solve the riddle of a box from the future. Despite leaden direction (by the New Line Cinema honcho Robert Shaye) and a story crammed with pseudoscientific flotsam -- including palm reading, levitation and telepathy -- this wholesome entertainment doesn't talk down. Nevertheless, a film gazing this far into the future shouldn't be quite so unwilling to look beyond the frame. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'THE LOOKOUT' (R, 99 minutes) This directorial debut by the veteran screenwriter Scott Frank (''Out of Sight'') is a variation of an old, old story, about a nobody (a brain-damaged janitor played by Joseph Gordon-Levitt) who falls in with crooks who make him feel like somebody. Although the movie's no masterpiece -- the final stretch feels forced and unconvincing -- there's a lot to like here. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'MEET THE ROBINSONS' (G, 93 minutes) Actually, if you see them coming, run in the other direction. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PAGE TURNER' (No rating, 85 minutes, in French) A pretty young thing slithers into the bosom of a bourgeois family like an asp in this shivery little thriller from the French filmmaker Denis Dercourt. Not Chabrol, but not bad, either. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'PRIDE' (PG, 104 minutes) The Zimbabwean-born filmmaker Sunu Gonera's directorial debut, ''Pride,'' about a swim coach (Terrence Howard, star of ''Hustle &amp; Flow'') leading an urban recreational center's swim team to a championship, about 1971, is a silk ascot wrapped around an ear of corn. But when sinewy young idealists glide through water to the tune of ''I'll Take You There,'' the heart still swells. (Seitz)</p>
        <p>'REIGN OVER ME' (R, 124 minutes) Mike Binder's comic drama of post-9/11 grief is wildly uneven -- by turns insightful and grindingly mawkish. Don Cheadle and Adam Sandler are two college buddies who reunite, somewhat improbably, some years after the attacks that robbed one of them of his family. The actors rise above the material, particularly in the longer, looser scenes that allow their contrasting temperaments -- Mr. Cheadle's tense understatement and Mr. Sandler's shaggy emoting -- to find a workable syncopation. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE TV SET' (R, 87 minutes) Jake Kasdan's knowing satire of network television sends up the neuroses of writers and the ruthlessness of executives with minimal exaggeration. Nothing in this story of a writer (David Duchovny) pursuing his dream project seems implausible, which is less a limitation on the movie's comedy than it is its source. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WHOLE NEW THING' (No rating, 92 minutes) This minutely observed family drama, which tracks the growing pains of a precocious 13-year-old boy in rural Nova Scotia, is the rare film in which the actors playing parents and child feel biologically connected. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>BEST OF 2006 (Tonight through Thursday) The BAMcinématek offers New York cinephiles the opportunity to catch up with some of last year's best films as determined by IndieWIRE's critics' poll. Tonight there's an advance screening of Julia Loktev's much-praised New York independent film ''Day Night Day Night'' (which will open commercially on May 9). Tomorrow brings the East Coast premiere of ''Il Caimano,'' a political satire by one of Italy's most accomplished active filmmakers, Nanni Moretti (''The Son's Room''), in which an underemployed filmmaker (played by Mr. Moretti's favorite alter ego, Silvio Orlando) agrees to make a flattering biography of Silvio Berlusconi, then Italy's prime minister. Robinson Devor's ''Police Beat,'' on Sunday, is one of the most beautiful and mysterious independent films in recent memory. It's a lyrical account of a Senegalese immigrant who works as a bicycle patrolman in Seattle. ''Climates'' (Tuesday), from the Turkish filmmaker Nuri Bilge Ceylan, is a worthy successor to his 2002 ''Distant,'' with Mr. Ceylan himself interpreting the central role of an egocentric academic whose relationship with an art director is slowly, and largely silently, falling apart. In ''Time to Leave'' (Wednesday), the French filmmaker François Ozon (''Swimming Pool'') looks at the last days of a gay fashion photographer (Melvil Poupaud) dying of cancer. On Thursday there's a preview of Mr. Devor's new feature, ''Zoo,'' a sympathetic portrait of a man who died after having sex with a horse. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $10. (Dave Kehr)</p>
        <p>JUBILO (Tonight) Will Rogers's earliest surviving feature film (1919), about a drifter who finds a home on an Oklahoma ranch, gets a rare screening in a print preserved by the Museum of Modern Art. Ben Model provides piano accompaniment. Museum of Modern Art, Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, (212) 708-9400, moma.org; $10. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>WEST OF THE TRACKS (Wednesday and Thursday) The Chinese documentary filmmaker Wang Bing took three years to capture this sweeping, nine-hour documentary about the transformations worked by encroaching capitalism on an industrial city, Shenyang, in northeastern China. As the aging, unprofitable factories are closed down by a distant government, it gradually becomes clear to the local workers that they have been forgotten in China's rush to riches. The film's three parts -- ''Rust,'' ''Remnants'' and ''Rails'' -- will be shown in rotation through April 24, beginning tonight with ''Rust'' and tomorrow with ''Remnants.'' ''Rails'' will be shown next Friday. Anthology Film Archives, 32-34 Second Avenue, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 505-5181, anthologyfilmarchives.org; $8. (Kehr)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ART BRUT (Tuesday and Wednesday) Rock 'n' roll needs to celebrate as well as ridicule its own mythology, and Art Brut, sarcastically but exuberantly singing about the thrill of plugging in and making a ruckus -- ''Formed a band, we formed a band/Look at us, we formed a band!'' -- is one of the rare groups that can do both. Tuesday at 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. Wednesday at 8 p.m., Studio B, 259 Banker Street, between Meserole Avenue and Calyer Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 389-1880, clubstudiob.com; $12. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOSEPH ARTHUR (Thursday) Romance, despair and the struggle for faith intermingle in Mr. Arthur's haunting songs, which can float in a gorgeous acoustic reverie or flare up in electrified anger. At 9 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* ROSANNE CASH AND ELVIS COSTELLO (Tonight) Rosanne Cash has been a frequent guest at the Rubin Museum of Art, a cozy gallery of Himalayan works in the former Barneys store in Chelsea; she was the first artist to perform in the museum's 144-seat theater three years ago, and has been there five times since. Tonight she is joined by Elvis Costello for an acoustic show on the enigmatic theme of ''Magic Numbers.'' At 7, 150 West 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CUTE IS WHAT WE AIM FOR (Thursday) At some point between Dashboard Confessional and Fall Out Boy, emo's polarity flipped: instead of grand gestures of sincerity, the hallmark of the genre became a verbose, smirky self-awareness. Cute Is What We Aim For, from Buffalo, tries hard to sound witty and effete, but the band falls as short on that front (''Are you perspiring from the irony/Or sweating to these lyrics?'') as it does with its sluggish riffs. With Circa Survive, As Tall as Lions and Envy on the Coast. At 7:30 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* ROKY ERICKSON AND THE EXPLOSIVES (Tonight and Sunday) One of the godfathers of psychedelic rock, who howled like a werewolf over the flutter of an electric jug in his 1960s band the 13th Floor Elevators, Roky Erickson is also one of the most notorious casualties of that era. He spent years in a mental hospital and, despite genuine gifts as a songwriter, has struggled ever since to reclaim his career. At 59, in what his representatives say is his best mental health in many years, he makes what is believed to be his New York debut. Tonight at 9, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; Sunday at 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com. Both sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE GOSSIP (Tomorrow) Based in Portland, Ore., but with roots in Arkansas, this trio of two women and one man plays a bare but potent blues-punk, dotting anthems of female empowerment with earthy ''oohs.'' With Chinese Stars and First Nation. At 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3132, knittingfactory.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PATTY GRIFFIN (Thursday) Patty Griffin may be best known as the songwriter of the Dixie Chicks' ''Let Him Fly'' and ''Truth No. 2.'' But on her own she is more cathartic, with songs that plunge into love as mysticism, desire and faith. Her songs may twang, but they can also cut deep. With Terremoto. At 8 p.m., Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; $29 and $39. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>GUSTER (Tonight and tomorrow night) Guster, a band from Boston, has followed the Dave Matthews Band's playbook for building an audience: touring constantly and singing unabashedly earnest folk-rock songs about the painful uncertainties of friendship, love and growing up. With Mason Jennings tonight and the Format tomorrow. At 8, Beacon Theater, 2124 Broadway, at 74th Street, (212) 307-7171, beacontheatrenyc.com; $39 (sold out tomorrow). (Pareles)</p>
        <p>BUDDY GUY (Tonight) The blues arrive in burst after burst of adrenaline when Mr. Guy plays his songs, full of gut-level belting and speedy guitar curlicues. He makes nearly every excess sound heartfelt. With Danielia Cotton. At 8, B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $48. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>HOT CHIP (Thursday) With wobbly electronic rhythms and a strong command of the drippy, semi-ironic disco ballad, this English group plays wistful but still snarky dance music. Get too lost in the beats and you'll miss gags like the oh-so-art-rock countdown of nonsense words in descending size (''S-E-X-I-N-G, C-A-S-I-O, P-O-K-E''). With Tussle. At 6:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ISLEY BROTHERS (Tonight) The Isley Brothers' career spans virtually the entire history of soul music, from their gospel-heated rave-ups of the late '50s and early '60s (''Shout!,'' ''Nobody but Me'') through the slithery funk of the '70s (''It's Your Thing,'' ''That Lady''), all the way to their recent collaborations with R. Kelly. Throughout, the libido has remained as intact as Ronald Isley's falsetto. Opening the show is Sharon Jones, the queen of an active local scene that recreates, spiritedly but not too pedantically, the musky sound of Stax/Volt '60s soul. At 8, United Palace Theater, 4140 Broadway, at 175th Street, Washington Heights, (212) 307-7171, concertstonight.com; $39.50 to $69.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* JANDEK (Tomorrow) A singer, guitarist and occasional keyboardist from Texas, Jandek is also one of the great sphinxes of contemporary American music. Since the late '70s he has released dozens of strange, challenging albums -- his music is a creaky, nightmarish variation of folk-rock -- and maintained an almost total void in place of a public persona. (For years, no one was even sure what he looked like.) Recently he has begun to tour a little, and tomorrow, in a show presented by Tonic, he plays with two veteran underground musicians, the guitarist Tim Foljahn (playing bass) and the drummer Jim White. At 8 p.m., Abrons Arts Center, Henry Street Settlement, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 598-0400, henrystreet.org; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NORAH JONES (Wednesday) For those who have missed her occasional unannounced gigs at small, no-cover Manhattan bars, in which she wears disguises and does everything from punk to country, Ms. Jones plays a fully official concert at a big, conspicuous place, leading her band in the music that made her famous: gentle, comforting soul-jazz. Opening the show is M. Ward, a gifted singer and guitarist better known for his work as a sideman (Cat Power, Bright Eyes) than for his tasteful and beguiling songs. At 8 p.m., Theater at Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $39.50 to $60. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* SALIF KEITA (Thursday) Salif Keita, from Mali, has long been celebrated for a cosmopolitan ear and a voice that can melt hearts, but lately his work has been even more entrancing than usual. His latest album, ''M'Bemba'' (Decca), has songs of love and tribute to ancestors, its acoustic guitars joined by instruments from Hawaii, the Caribbean and even medieval Europe. At 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club &amp; Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144, bbkingblues.com; $41 in advance, $45 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* KLAXONS, BONDE DO ROLE (Tonight) Klaxons' eerie rave-punk is punctuated by the peal of air-raid sirens and paranoid, shouted lyrics that allude to William S. Burroughs and Thomas Pynchon. How this British band manages to cram in such fear and loathing and still make exhilarating, danceable grooves is what makes it fascinating. With Bonde do Role, a raucous Brazilian trio that makes silly but contagiously high-energy pastiches of electronics and fist-pumping hard rock, à la the early Beastie Boys . At 10, Studio B, 259 Banker Street, between Meserole Avenue and Calyer Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 389-1880, clubstudiob.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* THE LOCUST, CATTLE DECAPITATION, DAUGHTERS (Tonight and tomorrow night) If noise-rock had superheroes, the Locust would surely be among them. Not only does this long-running San Diego band have a supreme control of its screamy hurricane of sound -- delivered in quick blasts of guitar, keyboards and indecipherable squeals -- but the group also dresses in skintight insect costumes from head to toe, all the way up to the black mesh over their eyes. (Perfect for Halloween merchandising!) It plays with Cattle Decapitation, a ''deathgrind'' metal band once affiliated with the Locust, and Daughters, a noisy band from Providence, R.I. Tonight at 6:30, Rebel, 251 West 30th Street, Manhattan, (212) 695-2747, rebelnyc.com; $15. Tomorrow night at 7, Europa, 98-104 Meserole Avenue, at Manhattan Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 383-5723, europaclub.com; $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LOSER'S LOUNGE TRIBUTE TO HALL AND OATES (Tonight and tomorrow night) As Nick Lowe said, you've got to be cruel to be kind. Joe McGinty's enduring Loser's Lounge series, now 14, both honors and skewers pop greats with cleverly over-the-top performances, and turns its attention here to Hall and Oates, whose mega-selling soul-pop ranged from the sublime (''She's Gone'') to the farcical (''Portable Radio''). At 7 and 9:30, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LURA (Tomorrow) A young Cape Verdean singer who was born in Portugal, Lura specializes in bubbly, lilting acoustic songs that are quicker and more danceable -- but no less sensuous -- than the morna tunes popularized by Cesaria Evora. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, worldmusicinstitute.org or symphonyspace.org; $27; $15 for students. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PLAIN WHITE T'S (Tuesday) Trite is a strong word, but when it comes to ''Hate (I Really Don't Like You),'' this Chicago power-pop band's irritatingly bland recent radio hit (''Hate is a strong word/But I really, really, really don't like you''), it may not be strong enough. With Boys Night Out, Lovedrug, and Dear and the Headlights. At 8 p.m., Fillmore New York at Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $16 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>RJD2 (Tonight) As a D.J. and producer, RJD2 -- born R. J. Krohn -- has made a mark in underground hip-hop with productions and remixes for Aceyalone, Aesop Rock and El-P, as well as his collaboration with the rapper Blueprint in Soul Position. He likes crisp funk drum breaks overlaid with brooding chords for a mixture of heft and introspection. With Busdriver and Happy Chichester. At 6, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $20. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>RODRIGO Y GABRIELA (Monday) Once thrash-metal bandmates in Mexico, this guitar duo discovered what the Gipsy Kings have long known: Europeans and Americans go crazy for virtuosic acoustic renditions of their favorite '70s rock ballads. The Gipsy Kings did it with ''Hotel California,'' and Rodrigo y Gabriela's repertory includes a lush ''Stairway to Heaven.'' With Krystle Warren. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Kenny Wayne Shepherd (Wednesday) A 29-year-old blues guitarist inspired equally by the Allman Brothers and Muddy Waters, Mr. Shepherd recently released ''10 Days Out (Blues From the Backroads)'' (Reprise), a CD-DVD package documenting his work with various blues greats, including B. B. King, Clarence (Gatemouth) Brown, Honeyboy Edwards and Etta Baker. Since working on it, several of his collaborators have died, but for this tour he is joined by Hubert Sumlin, Bryan Lee and Buddy Flett. At 8 p.m., Gramercy Theater, 127 East 23rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PATTI SMITH (Wednesday) Her first flash of rock 'n' roll brilliance, and maybe still her best, was a cover: Them's ''Gloria,'' transformed from garage-rock swagger into an erotic rhapsody. So Patti Smith's new album, ''Twelve'' (Columbia), with versions of songs by the Rolling Stones, Nirvana, Jimi Hendrix and others, is especially promising. She offers a preview at the Hiro Ballroom. At 7 p.m., 371 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>UMPHREY'S McGEE (Tonight) One of the few jam bands to gain critical respect in the rock world, Umphrey's McGee, from South Bend, Ind., seamlessly incorporates the irregular meters and gnarled guitar patterns of classic progressive rock into the spoonful-of-sugar textures more common in its milieu, a feat of reconciliation that impresses the connoisseurs and keeps all others on their feet. At 9, Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171, nokiatheatrenyc.com; $26.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>UNCLE MONK (Monday) There is life after the Ramones, but who knew that its sound would be bluegrass? Tom Erdelyi, better known as Tommy Ramone, the band's first drummer (and only surviving original member), plays a mean mandolin in this new acoustic duo, singing tautly written songs about the comforts and subtle politics of home life. With Copper Kettle. At 7:30 p.m., Parkside Lounge, 317 East Houston Street, between Clinton and Attorney Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 673-6270, parksidelounge.com. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>RASHIED ALI QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Rashied Ali has led a substantial career in the jazz avant-garde over the past 40 years, beginning with his role in the late-period work of John Coltrane. His drumming drives this hard-bop band, featuring the trumpeter Jumaane Smith and the tenor saxophonist Lawrence Clark. At 8, 10 and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>J. D. ALLEN TRIO (Tonight) J. D. Allen, a harmonically adventurous tenor saxophonist, enjoys strong support from Gregg August on bass and Rudy Royston on drums. At 8:30 and 10, the River Room, Riverbank State Park, Riverside Drive at 145th Street, Hamilton Heights, (212) 491-1500, theriverroomofharlem.com; cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETER APFELBAUM AND NEW YORK HIEROGLYPHICS (Thursday) Peter Apfelbaum, a multireedist and pianist, celebrates the 30th anniversary of this adventurous African-inspired band, with collaborators including Abdoulaye Diabate on kora, Peck Allmond on trumpet and Charles Burnham on violin. At 10 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, near Metropolitan Avenue, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934, zebuloncafeconcert.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE BERESFORD / MICHAEL BATES (Wednesday) Mr. Beresford, a multi-instrumentalist long ensconced in British free-improvisational circles, teams up with the trumpeter Nate Wooley and the drummer Harris Eisenstadt. Then Mr. Bates, a bassist, leads Outside Sources, with Russ Johnson on trumpet, Tony Malaby on tenor saxophone and Jeff Davis on drums. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BOSSABRASIL FESTIVAL (Tuesday through Thursday) On Tuesday and Wednesday this festival showcases the pianist Cesar Camargo Mariano and the guitarist Romero Lubambo in a duo, and the jazz-pop singer Leny Andrade with the Cuban saxophonist and clarinetist Paquito d'Rivera. Thursday's lineup includes the guitarist Dori Caymmi and the singer known as Joyce, with a trio led by the American pianist Kenny Werner. (Through April 21.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AVISHAI COHEN / HIROMI'S SONICBLOOM (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Cohen is a bassist whose new album, ''As Is '' (Half Note), documents a recent run here with his groove-oriented band. The pianist Hiromi Uehara also has a new release: ''Time Control'' (Telarc), an audacious jolt of fusion with the core group featured here. (Through April 22.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $25 at tables, $15 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SHANE ENDSLEY BAND (Thursday) Shane Endsley, an adventurous yet lyrical trumpeter, leads a modernistic ensemble stocked with peers like the drummer Rudy Royston and the guitarist Mike Gamble. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>E.S.T. / MATTHEW SHIPP (Tomorrow) The initials stand for Esbjorn Svensson Trio, a Swedish jazz-crossover group with an energetic new album called ''Tuesday Wonderland''; taking its lead from Esbjorn Svensson's piano, the ensemble favors somber harmonies and skittering rhythms. Mr. Shipp, in an opening solo piano set, will most likely suggest a darker ideal. At 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $25 in advance, $30 tomorrow. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANAT FORT (Tonight) Ms. Fort is a prepossessing young pianist with an auspicious new debut album. She performs her own music with her working trio, the bassist Gary Wang and the drummer Roland Schneider. At 10:30, BAMCafé, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JÜRGEN FRIEDRICH TRIO (Tuesday) ''Seismo'' (Pirouet), a recent album by the German pianist Jürgen Friedrich, proposes a daring and articulate strain of post-bop abstraction. As on the recording, Mr. Friedrich performs here with the support of an American rhythm team, the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Tony Moreno. At 10 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL FRISELL (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) This weekend Mr. Frisell, the guitarist, leads his rubbery trio with the bassist Tony Scherr and the drummer Kenny Wollesen. Next week he welcomes some other familiar colleagues: the clarinetist Don Byron, the trumpeter Ron Miles and the violinist Jenny Scheinman. (Through April 22.) At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>VINCENT HERRING AND THE EARTH JAZZ AGENTS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Vincent Herring, an alto saxophonist with a tart and bluesy command, presents a driving hard-bop band featuring the pianist Anthony Wonsey. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $28. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>INGRID JENSEN QUARTET (Sunday) A fiery post-bop trumpeter with a book of sharp, original tunes, Ingrid Jensen performs here with the pianist Enrique Haneine, the bassist Carlo DeRosa and the drummer Alison Miller. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KALAPARUSHA (Tomorrow) Kalaparusha Ahra Difda, a multireedist formerly known as Maurice McIntyre, is a founding member of the Association for the Advancement of Creative Musicians, and has kept that organization's commitment to sonic and spiritual exploration. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Sista's Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766, sistasplace.org; cover, $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BIRÉLI LAGRÈNE AND GYPSY JAZZ (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Lagrène, a French gypsy guitarist, recently released a double album placing his rhythmically fleet playing in both a solo setting and at the helm of a big band. Here he traffics in the ebullient style of Django Reinhardt, his most famous forebear. (Through April 22.) At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHRIS LIGHTCAP'S BIGMOUTH (Thursday) This ensemble employs compositional forms as a springboard; Chris Lightcap, a bassist, has creative cohorts in the tenor saxophonists Tony Malaby and Matt Renzi, the pianist James Carney and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319, corneliastreetcafe.com; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL MAYS TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Bill Mays, a harmonically astute pianist, focuses on popular movie themes in this engagement with the bassist Rufus Reid and the drummer John Riley. At 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119, kitano.com; cover, $25, with a $15 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CHARLES MINGUS 85TH BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION (Tuesday through Thursday) Several of the most exuberant repertory bands in the city operate with a common inspiration, the bassist and composer Charles Mingus, and all of them will appear at Jazz at Lincoln Center over the next week. A bruising big band called the Mingus Dynasty holds court on Tuesday, while the more chamberlike Mingus Orchestra performs on Wednesday and Thursday. (Through April 22.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WES MONTGOMERY TRIBUTE ALL-STARS (Tonight through Sunday night) Peter Bernstein occupies the hot seat in this salute to the guitarist Wes Montgomery, but he has plenty of company, including the trumpeter Jeremy Pelt, the saxophonist Eric Alexander and the drummer Ray Appleton, a Montgomery alumnus. At 7:30 and 9:30, with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $30; $25 on Sunday. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MIKE MORENO SEXTET (Thursday) The versatile young guitarist Mike Moreno has a new album, ''Between the Lines'' (World Culture Music), that establishes his graces as a composer. His sonorous band includes the saxophonists John Ellis and Marcus Strickland and the drummer Kendrick Scott. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SAM NEWSOME (Wednesday) Mr. Newsome, a soprano saxophonist, teams up with the pianist Lucian Ban to create a contemporary jazz informed by Romanian folk music. Their band includes Cristian Soleanu and Alex Harding on saxophones, Arthur Balogh on bass and Willard Dyson on drums. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $12; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>AARON PARKS QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Aaron Parks, the precocious pianist in Terence Blanchard's working band, leads his own quartet with Mike Moreno on guitar, Matt Brewer on bass and Marcus Gilmore on drums. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SONNY ROLLINS (Tonight) Last year this tenor saxophonist released ''Sonny, Please'' (Doxy), his best studio recording in more than a decade. Performing his only area concert this year, he leads a trusted band, and presumably will offer searching solos, songbook obscurities and an unsinkable calypso. At 8 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, One Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722, njpac.org; $20 to $78. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SUN RA ARKESTRA/NUBLU ORCHESTRA (Tonight and Monday) The Sun Ra Arkestra, led by the alto saxophonist Marshall Allen, carries on the boisterous avant-gardism of its cosmic namesake with a ragtag, rhythmic brio. The Nublu Orchestra, conducted by the sagacious Butch Morris, creates a whorl of timbres in the service of groove. The two bands share a bill tonight; Mr. Morris and company perform alone at Nublu on Monday. Tonight at 7:30, Paul Robeson Theater, 40 Greene Avenue, near Adelphi Street, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 783-9794, ticketweb .com; $15. Nublu Orchestra plays on Monday at 10 p.m. and midnight, Nublu, 62 Avenue C, near Fifth Street, East Village, (212) 979-9925, nublu.net; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* GONZALO RUBALCABA QUINTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Gonzalo Rubalcaba is an astonishing pianist technically, and he plays with a dramatic flourish and rhythmic depth evocative of his native Cuba. He has superb partners here: the trumpeter Michael Rodriguez, the saxophonist Yosvany Terry, the bassist Matt Brewer and the drummer Francisco Mela. (Through April 22.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SLAVIC SOUL PARTY (Tomorrow and Tuesday) The percussionist Matt Moran leads this Balkan brass band, which has a spirited new album called ''Teknochek Collision'' (Barbès). At 10 p.m. tomorrow, 9 p.m. on Tuesday, Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SPIDER'S WEB (Tonight) The pianist Ross Lossing, the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Jeff Williams make up this ensemble, which strives for the flexibility and intricacy implied by its name. At 8:30, Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $10; $6 for students. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TAIN AND THE EBONIX (Thursday) Jeff (Tain) Watts, one of the most dazzlingly propulsive drummers to emerge in the last 25 years, marks the release of ''Folk Songs'' (Dark Key Music), a new album with this band featuring Christian McBride on bass, David Kikowski on piano and Marcus Strickland on saxophones. At 9:30 p.m., the Cutting Room, 19 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 691-1900, thecuttingroomnyc.com; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* TODO TANGO (Tonight and tomorrow night) The Argentinean bassist Pablo Aslan, a prominent figure in the burgeoning jazz-tango subculture, is a featured guest at this concert; it also happens to be the final Jazz at Lincoln Center performance by the Afro-Latin Jazz Orchestra. At 8, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* DAVID TORN (Tuesday) Mr. Torn is an inventive guitarist and producer whose new album, ''Prezens'' (ECM), suggests a texturally slippery approach to group improvisation. That has something to do with the alto saxophonist Tim Berne, the keyboardist Craig Taborn and the drummer Tom Rainey, who appear here; but it's also an expression of his gift for organizing sound. At 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 967-7555, joespub.com; cover, $20, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* VISION TONIC (Sunday, Tuesday and Wednesday) In response to the sudden closing of Tonic (see John Zorn, below), the Vision Festival has absorbed a few new bookings for an off-season series one block to the east. Sunday's schedule includes a group led by the harpist Zeena Parkins, while Tuesday's will include a rare performance by the Scandinavian trio called the Thing. On Wednesday the alto saxophonist Oliver Lake will perform with the multi-instrumentalist Eugene Chadbourne. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Clemente Soto Vélez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, at Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 696-6681, visionfestival.org; cover, $10, and a one-drink minimum per set. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOHN ZORN IMPROV (Tonight) Noise is the currency at a John Zorn improv party, which can feature any number of audacious and open-minded musicians. Usually the action has a jubilant tinge, but this happens to be the final night of programming at Tonic, an avant-garde hub that Mr. Zorn helped establish nearly a decade ago. At 7:30 and 9:30, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; donation, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>* 'ANDREA CHÉNIER' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) Ben Heppner, arguably the leading Wagnerian tenor of our day, continues his bold explorations of far-flung repertory with the title role of Giordano's swashbuckling verismo opera, in the Metropolitan Opera's revival of Nicolas Joël's 1996 production. Mr. Heppner may lack the vocal colorings and idiomatic expressivity of the heroic Italian tenors who excelled in this touchstone role, that of a poet with libertarian fervor during the French Revolution. But in his honest and compelling portrayal he sings with burnished sound, vigor and lyrical sensitivity. The rich-voiced soprano Violeta Urmana sings Maddalena for the final performance on Wednesday night, but the popular soprano Aprile Millo takes over the role tomorrow. The stentorian baritone Juan Pons sings Gérard. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $42 to $220 tomorrow, $15 to $175 for Wednesday. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'CURLEW RIVER' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Britten called his one-act opera ''Curlew River'' a church parable. Inspired by a Japanese Noh play, the work takes the form of a sacred ritual, with a procession of monks enacting a mystery play about a madwoman who crosses a river with a ferryman in search of her abducted son. The Japan Society offers a staging of this haunting and seldom-seen work, a co-production with L'Opéra de Rouen/Haute-Normandie. Directed by Yoshi Oida, it stars the tenor Michael Bennett as the madwoman, with musical direction by David Stern. At 7:30, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258, japansociety.org; $52; $45 for members. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'FLAVIO' (Tomorrow) Candy pink and candy green set the tone for Chas Rader-Shieber's antic production of an opera that consists of arias nestled side by side, bright and sweet as a box of fondants: much of a good thing, leaving a reasonably pleasant aftertaste. On the first night of the City Opera revival, the singers seemed to be fighting to find their pitches: making company debuts are Katherine Rohrer, a light mezzo with a nice tone who didn't quite find her feet on the first note; Gerald Thompson, a promising but sometimes wild countertenor; and the conductor William Lacey, who led a strong, lithe performance. David Walker did a fine job as the foppish, foolish king of the title. At 1:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; $25 to $125. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'GIULIO CESARE' (Tonight and Tuesday) The auditorium of the Metropolitan Opera may be too big for Handel. But the cast that has been assembled for the company's revival of ''Giulio Cesare'' is so exceptional that the lack of intimacy does not matter. With a score of astounding richness and variety, the opera emerges as an affecting and psychologically astute masterpiece. With his alluring voice, the countertenor David Daniels excels in the daunting title role. The soprano Ruth Ann Swenson makes a vocally exquisite Cleopatra. Patricia Bardon, a rich-toned Irish mezzo-soprano, brings noble bearing and lyrical elegance to the role of Cornelia. Harry Bicket elicits a surprisingly stylish account of the score from the orchestra. The downside is John Copley's tacky production. At 7:30, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; $15 to $205. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'MADAMA BUTTERFLY' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) East-West relations go south in Puccini's famous melodrama. Shu-Ying Li sings Cio-Cio-San, and Christopher Jackson is Lieutenant Pinkerton in this New York City Opera production. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nycopera.com; sold out tomorrow;$25 to $115 for Wednesday. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'TURANDOT' (Tomorrow, Monday and Thursday) For spectacle and big music, the Franco Zeffirelli production of Puccini's final opera, at the Met, is hard to beat. For compelling leads, you might have to look elsewhere: Andrea Gruber sounded wobbly and thin on the first night of this revival, and Richard Margison effortful, though he marshaled his forces for ''Nessun dorma.'' Only Hei-Kyung Hong's Liù, with her reliably floating pianos, was really worth the price of admission. But spectacle and size are evidently enough to keep tickets selling briskly for this one. Marco Armiliato conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Monday and Thursday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000, metopera.org; sold out tomorrow and Thursday; $175 tickets remain for Monday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'DIE ZAUBERFLÖTE' (Tonight and tomorrow night) The last two performances of this new look at the Mozart favorite by the South African director William Kentridge and the Belgian opera house La Monnaie. At 7:30, Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100, bam.org; $40 to $125. (Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMERICAN SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Sunday) Franz Schreker's much-discussed and little-heard opera ''Der Ferne Klang'' is taken up by the enterprising Leon Botstein in this concert performance. At 3 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $27 to $55. (Holland)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Sunday and Tuesday) Nicholas Maw is one of the Chamber Music Society's 2006-7 ''season composers.'' Here the society presents his ''Roman Canticle,'' a setting of Robert Browning's poem ''Two in the Campagna,'' for mezzo-soprano, flute, viola and harp. Angelika Kirchschlager, the mezzo-soprano originally scheduled to perform the work, has been replaced by Peggy Kriha Dye, a soprano. The program also includes Charles Martin Loeffler's ''Quatre Poems'' for voice, viola and piano; Dvorak's Piano Trio in E minor; and Mendelssohn's String Quintet No. 1. Sunday at 5 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788, chambermusicsociety.org; $28 to $50. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NELSON FREIRE (Thursday) New York audiences experience Mr. Freire's pianism only in glimpses, but this Brazilian returns to the Metropolitan Museum of Art with Bach, Beethoven and Chopin standards, Debussy's ''Children's Corner Suite'' and excerpts from Albéniz's ''Iberia.'' At 8 p.m., (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $50. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* OSVALDO GOLIJOV/DAWN UPSHAW YOUNG ARTISTS CONCERT (Tomorrow and Sunday) To foster collaboration between singers and composers, the soprano Dawn Upshaw, through the auspices of Carnegie Hall's Weill Music Institute, has presented joint workshops with leading composers, notably John Harbison in 2004 and Osvaldo Golijov this season. A roster of young composers, paired with young singers, has been collaborating in these workshops for some months, under the guidance of Mr. Golijov and Ms. Upshaw. The resulting works will be presented this weekend in two very affordable programs. Needless to say, each piece will be receiving its world premiere. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 3 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $15. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>KALICHSTEIN-LAREDO-ROBINSON TRIO (Sunday) This venerable piano trio is celebrating its 30th anniversary since making its debut in 1977 at the White House for President Jimmy Carter's inauguration. On Sunday it performs Leon Kirchner's Trio No. 2 and is joined by the violist Pinchas Zukerman for Mozart's Piano Quartet in E flat (K. 493), and by the double bassist Harold Robinson for Schubert's ''Trout'' Quintet. At 2 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $23 to $75. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* OLIVER KNUSSEN (Tonight) This British composer has a significant body of bracing and inventive scores to his credit. But in the last decade or so he has had a woeful record of meeting deadlines for commissioned pieces. An ambitious new work for the pianist Peter Serkin and a large chamber ensemble was supposed to have had its long-awaited premiere tonight at Zankel Hall. Alas, Mr. Knussen was not able to complete the score. In its place he will offer his ''Requiem -- Songs for Sue,'' a New York premiere. The program, featuring Mr. Serkin, the soprano Susan Narucki and the Zankel Band, boosted here to the size of a chamber orchestra, still looks enticing, with works by Messiaen, Magnus Lindberg and Julian Anderson. And Mr. Knussen is an accomplished conductor, which has been one of the problems, actually: his conducting has taken time from his composing. At 7:30, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 and $35. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* KARITA MATTILA (Wednesday) She's been called the leading lyric soprano of her generation -- though that was before she took on ''Fidelio'' and ''Salome'' -- and praised for her lied interpretations, particularly of Finnish song, represented by one set on this thoughtful and wide-ranging concert. The other pieces are Barber's ''Hermit Songs,'' a set of Wolf songs and Turina's ''Poema en Forma de Canciones.'' Martin Katz is the pianist. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $25 to $84. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>NETHERLANDS BACH SOCIETY (Wednesday) The Netherlands Bach Society, a period-instrument ensemble founded in 1921, says it is the oldest early-music group still performing in that country. On Wednesday Jos Van Veldhoven, its artistic director, leads the ensemble and soloists -- including the sopranos Dorothee Mields and Johanette Zomer, the alto Matthew White, the tenor Charles Daniels and the bass Peter Harvey -- in Bach's monumental Mass in B minor. At 8 p.m., Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949, metmuseum.org; $50. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Today and tomorrow) Sakari Oramo conducts the orchestra in Sibelius's Sixth Symphony. Lisa Batiashvili is the soloist for Shostakovich's First Violin Concerto. Today at 11 a.m., tomorrow at 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500, nyphil.org; $24 to $79. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* ORPHEUS CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Tomorrow) A new piece by Ingram Marshall is a good reason to go to a concert. Perhaps the only reason Mr. Marshall is not better known is that he's not played more, and the Cheswatyr New Music Initiative, which teamed up with Orpheus and WNYC to commission ''Orphic Memories,'' is doing its bit to change that by ensuring that this piece is played on the orchestra's tour and broadcast. As for the music: think Romantic sensibility and lushness filtered through an electronics sensibility. The conductorless ensemble is adding to the program Gil Shaham in the Beethoven Violin Concerto, as well as Mendelssohn's Sinfonia No. 10. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $30 to $88. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* POCKET CONCERTOS (Tomorrow) Miller Theater presents the second installment of its innovative Pocket Concertos series, a three-year project commissioning 12 composers to write 12 concertos. The lineup tomorrow features ''Spin 5,'' a five-movement violin piece by Charles Wuorinen performed by Jennifer Koh; ''People Mountain People Sea,'' a cello work by Huang Ruo performed by Jian Wang; Anthony Davis's ''You Have the Right to Remain Silent,'' for clarinet, performed by J. D. Parran; and Sebastian Currier's Piano Concerto, with Emma Tahmizian. Brad Lubman leads the Perspectives Ensemble. At 8 p.m., Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799, millertheater.com; $25; $15 for students. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>CHRISTOPHE ROUSSET (Thursday) Call it ''Family Ties'': the concert by this master harpsichordist features music by Louis Couperin and his nephew, the better-known François, and by Johann Sebastian Bach and one of his most famous sons, Carl Philipp Emanuel. François's harpsichord music represents an acme of the French style; Mr. Rousset will play a linked group of five pieces, or ordre, from the last of his four books of collected harpsichord works. From the Bachs, the offerings are the French Suite No. 3 by the father, and the third of the seminal ''Württemberg'' sonatas by the son. At 7:30 p.m., Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $40. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* UBS VERBIER FESTIVAL CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Thursday) This chamber orchestra, whose members are chosen from the best current members and alumni of the UBS Verbier Festival Orchestra, will perform Mozart concertos with the first-rate violinist Maxim Vengerov as soloist and conductor. The program includes the Violin Concertos Nos. 2 and 4 (K. 211 and 218), with Mr. Vengerov's own cadenzas, and the Sinfonia Concertante in E flat (K. 364), with the violist Lawrence Power -- repertory this group recently recorded for a new disc on EMI. The concert also includes Shostakovich's Chamber Symphony. At 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800, carnegiehall.org; $30 to $98. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>YOUNG CONCERT ARTISTS IRENE DIAMOND CONCERT (Wednesday) Young Concert Artists discovers talented instrumentalists, singers and composers through yearly auditions; the organization then presents them in concerts and assists in managing their careers. The group's annual Irene Diamond Concert spotlights two pianists and a flutist. Chu-Fang Huang plays Grieg's Piano Concerto in A minor; Dora Seres plays Mozart's Flute Concerto in G; and Gleb Ivanov performs Prokofiev's Piano Concerto No. 3. Scott Yoo, an alumnus of the group, conducts the Orchestra of St. Luke's. At 7:30 p.m., Rose Theater, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 307-6656, yca.org; $15 to 35. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AILEY II (Tonight through Sunday; Wednesday and Thursday) Alvin Ailey created a second, or junior, company in 1974, almost casually, as a way of working on new choreography. Ailey II is now a world-class troupe, filled with dancers who are not only good but also capable of performing with a youthful hunger for their art, as well as with a reverence for dance that is a part of the mission of the company director, Sylvia Waters, whom Ailey himself chose to direct that first group. Now Ailey II is coming home, performing in the black-box theater that is part of the Ailey headquarters: newer, grander and more gleaming than Ailey ever envisioned. The repertory will include new dances by Abdel Salaam, Darrell Grand Moultrie and Jessica Lang, along with Ailey's ''Streams'' and a chunk of Ailey highlights. (Through April 22.) Tonight and Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8; tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m., Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444, alvinailey.org; $40; $10 student rush tickets available. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>'THE A.W.A.R.D. SHOW!' (Sunday) The latest in a series of performances produced by Neta Pulvermacher displays new choreography by Ashleigh Leite, Kyle Abraham, Sara Jull and Jennie MaryTai Liu. Discussions with the choreographers follow the dancing. At 7 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479, joyce.org; free. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>* LES BALLETS GRANDIVA (Monday and Tuesday) The lads -- or lasses? -- in this all-male ballet troupe will present the world premiere of Brian Reeder's ''They Who Wore White Flowers,'' the local premiere of Victor Trevino's ''Grand Tarantelle'' and their own versions of war-horse classical ballet delicacies like the pas de deux from ''Spartacus.'' At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-4551, symphonyspace.org; $21 and $26; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LES BALLETS JAZZ DE MONTREAL (Tuesday through Thursday) A Canadian company that refuses to adhere to strict definitions of either ballet or jazz dances its way through two new works: one inspired by Brazilian music and dance, the other set to both Vivaldi arias and folk songs from Quebec. Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $40. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>KIMBERLY BARTOSIK AND JENNIFER ALLEN (Thursday) Ms. Allen's ''Open'' explores the joys and terrors of childhood. Ms. Bartosik's ''Ecsteriority I'' is a meditation on distance and closeness, set in a debris-filled landscape. (Through April 21.) At 8 p.m., the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, thekitchen.org; $10. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* DANCE AT DNA: TAMI STRONACH DANCE AND 'OB.JECT.OB.JECT' (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) In the new piece ''Pinchas the Fish-People and the Great Flood,'' Ms. Stronach reconfigures a myth, telling the story from the perspective of mermaids. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m. ''OB.ject.ob.JECT'' focuses on dances by women, among them Jody Oberfelder, Preeti Vasudevan and Hana Van Der Kolk, as well as solos choreographed by Melinda Allen, Tiffany Rhynard, Andrea Woods and Tina Vasquez, and performed by Inspirit/Christal Brown. (Through April 22.) Thursday at 8 p.m. This beehive dance organization is also host to ''Works in Progress,'' in which choreographers show excerpts from new pieces for audience commentary. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, (212) 279-4200, dnadance.org; $17 (Stronach); $20 (''OB.ject'') and $10 (suggested donation for ''Works in Progress''). (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* DANCE PARTY (Tomorrow) In a shared program, Larry Keigwin and his company will present ''Bolero,'' a new work for 80 performers about the challenges of life in New York City, with Chris Elam and his Misnomer Dance Theater dancing Mr. Elam's new ''future perfect,'' which focuses on belonging and fulfillment. At 8 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 279-4200, www.skirballcenter.nyu.edu; $20 and $30. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* EIFMAN BALLET OF ST. PETERSBURG (Tonight through Sunday; Wednesday and Thursday) Boris Eifman, one of Russia's most flamboyantly theatrical choreographers, presents an opening gala tonight, with excerpts from six of his ballets and the world premiere of ''Cassandra,'' by the young choreographer Nikita Dmitrievsky. Next week the group will also perform ''Red Giselle'' and the New York premiere of Mr. Eifman's ''Seagull,'' based on Chekhov's classic play. Tonight and Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, Saturday at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, nycitycenter.org; $35 to $100. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* GENDER BENDER: THREE WEEKS OF SEXUAL CONFUSION IN DANCE (Tonight, and tomorrow and Thursday nights) This festival continues with performances by Les Ballets Grandiva (see above) tonight and tomorrow, ending next week with a program by Monica Bill Barnes and nicholasleichterdance. Ms. Barnes's modern-dance choreography is known for its theatricality and knowing humor. Nicholas Leichter explores race and sex with provocative pairings of dancers in work that draws from traditional and street dance styles. At 8:30, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org; $17 to $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>GREEN SPACE BLOOMS: DANCE IN QUEENS (Tonight through Sunday night) This program features a performance each night by Valerie Green and her Dance Entropy, with the guest companies and musicians Mariko Tanabe Danse and Anand Patole (tonight); Gloria McLean/Lifedance and Laurie Hockman (tomorrow) and Diane Vivona/DV Dance and Balkan Music (Sunday). At 8, Green Space Studio, 37-24 24th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 956-3037, greenspacestudio.com; $20; $15 for students, dancers and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* LAR LUBOVITCH DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday through Thursday) Known for the rich flow of his modern-dance choreography, Mr. Lubovitch and his eloquent dancers will present two programs, which include ''Little Rhapsodies,'' with Rasta Thomas, a guest dancer, and Pedja Muzijevic, who will play the Schumann piano score and the music for ''Dvorak Serenade in E.'' The Limón Dance Company will be a guest in Mr. Lubovitch's ''Recordare,'' in programming that also includes his ''Love Stories.'' The performances on Tuesday and Wednesday include ''Love Stories,'' ''Little Rhapsodies'' and ''Dvorak Serenade in E.'' ''Recordare'' replaces ''Love Stories'' on Thursday. (Through April 21.) At 8 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 279-4200, www.skirballcenter.nyu.edu; $35; $20 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BARBARA MAHLER (Thursday). ''There's No Place Like Home'' features choreography distinguished by tight focus and strong physicality. (Through April 22.) At 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194, danspaceproject.org; $15. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK THEATER BALLET: 'DANCE ON A SHOESTRING' (Tonight and tomorrow night) This company and its students will perform hourlong programs of new works, classics and revivals. At 7, Dance Gallery, 30 East 31st Street, Manhattan, (212) 679-0401, nytb.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* THE NOTHING FESTIVAL (Wednesday and Thursday) Tere O'Connor, the organizer of this two-week festival, asked several choreographers and groups to create new works out of nothing, dances with no stories, no music and no outside sources. This week's participants are Douglas Dunn, Hijack, Sam Kim and Dean Moss. (Through April 21.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org; $20 and $12. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>PALISSIMO (Tonight through Sunday) Injuries to two cast members forced the postponement of ''Le Petit Mort/Now It's Time to Say Goodbye,'' by Pavel Zustiak. Mr. Zustiak's company is back in business now with a new work that ponders death and confrontations with mortality. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 4 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 4 p.m., Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101, ps122.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>QUEENS THEATER ASIAN CULTURAL FESTIVAL (Thursday) The festival opens with American debut performances by the Pasha Dance Company of Korea, directed by Hwang Mi-sook. At 8 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718) 760-0064, queenstheatre.org; $28; $26 for 65+; $20 for students. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>PILAR RIOJA (Today and tomorrow) The doyenne of Spanish dance in New York City will present a program that includes two new works: a stylized flamenco dance called ''Muero Porque No Muero'' (''I die because I can't die''), to music by Surinach, and ''Bamberas,'' whose title refers to a form of folk music that fuses flamenco with traditional Andalusian song to the beat of fandangos. (Through April 22.) Today at 11 a.m. and 8 p.m., tomorrow at 8 p.m., Repertorio Español Gramercy Arts Theater, 138 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 225-9920, repertorio.org; $30 to $50. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>AYNSLEY VANDENBROUCKE MOVEMENT GROUP (Wednesday and Thursday) ''And How Should I Begin?,'' a dance of connections and missed connections, takes its inspiration from T. S. Eliot's ''Love Song of J. Alfred Prufrock,'' but the choreographer says you don't need to know the poem to understand the dance. (Through April 21.) At 8 p.m., Baryshnikov Arts Center, 450 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (212) 868-4444, smarttix.com; $15. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* American Museum of Natural History: 'GOLD,' through Aug. 19. Having delved into pearls, diamonds and amber, the museum applies its time-tested show-and-tell formula to the premier precious natural material, gold. This astounding array of art, artifacts and natural samples -- larded with fascinating facts and tales -- ranges from prehistoric times to the present. Stops along the way include pre-Columbian empires, sunken treasure, Bangladesh dowry rituals and the moon landing. It turns out that gold comes from the earth in forms as beautiful as anything man has thought to do with it, but that gold ingots have a brute force all their own. You are certain to emerge with mind boggled and eyes dazzled. Central Park West and 79th Street, (212) 769-5100, amnh.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* Chelsea Art Museum: 'DANGEROUS BEAUTY,' through April 21. A somewhat timely update of a well-worn idea, this show of contemporary works in a variety of mediums by 18 artists examines the beauty myth in art, advertising and the fashion industry. Eloquent but blunt imagery of anorexic girls, chiseled male beefcake and close-ups of surgically deformed faces predominates, reminding us of the violent extremes to which some people will go in pursuit of society's ideal of beauty and a designer body. The rest of the show -- often pointing an accusatory finger at skinny models, cosmetic labels and the mass media -- feels familiar in its critique, but the basic premise about the ideology of beauty in our culture is beyond argument. 556 West 22nd Street, (212) 255-0719, chelseaartmuseum.org. (Benjamin Genocchio)</p>
        <p>FRICK COLLECTION: 'GEORGE STUBBS (1724-1806): A CELEBRATION,' through May 27. One of the finest horse painters ever, Stubbs knew his subjects from head to hoof and skin to bones. He painted other mammals too: dogs, lions, tigers, oxen, monkeys and humans. This intimate show of 17 Stubbs paintings from English collections reveals his admirable range, although the people he portrayed in two large, late canvases, elegiac celebrations of farm workers raking and reaping grain, have the stiffness of figures on a candy box. His horses are his true monuments. 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, frick.org. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'HENRI CARTIER-BRESSON'S SCRAPBOOK: PHOTOGRAPHS, 1932-46,' through April 29. Arrived by way of the Fondation Henri Cartier-Bresson in Paris, this show has more than 300 of the prints the photographer glued into an album and toted to New York for curators at the Museum of Modern Art to cull. Captured by the Nazis, he had been presumed dead when the Modern planned his retrospective. Then he turned up alive -- the ''posthumous'' exhibition opened, with him in attendance, in 1947. The current exhibition reconstructs as best as possible the layout of the scrapbook as Cartier-Bresson originally organized the pictures. It surveys the revolutionary work he shot in Spain, Italy, Mexico, Britain and France. His taste for uncanny detail linked him to Surrealism and Surrealist wit, but unlike many Surrealists, he remained committed to human values. Boys mug at his camera. Prostitutes swan. Their gazes equalize them with us. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, icp.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* JAPAN SOCIETY: 'Awakenings: Zen Figure Painting in Medieval Japan,' through June 17. Japan Society has a history of producing exquisite shows of Buddhist art. And this one, with four dozen paintings of Buddhists gods and saints hung in shrinelike alcoves, is transporting. And it covers an unusually broad swath of geography, bringing together 13th- to 16th-century hanging scrolls not only from Japan but also from China, where Zen Buddhism, called Chan in Chinese, originated. 333 East 47th Street, (212) 832-1155, japansociety.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* metropolitan museum of art: 'Venice and the Islamic World, 828-1797,' through July 8. At its peak in the Renaissance, Venice, the Most Serene, was a giant, clamorous Costco-on-the-Rialto. All the necessities, and most of the luxuries, of life flowed into and through it, with many items arriving from Islamic Africa and the Near East. With classic Met largesse, this exhibition suggests the spectacle of two different cultures meeting in one fantastic city, in which commerce and love of beauty, those great levelers, unite them in a fruitful bond. (212) 535-7710, metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* El Museo del Barrio: 'The Disappeared (Los Desaparecidos),' through June 17. The most potent show of contemporary political art of the season, and one of the most moving shows of any kind in the city right now. The title refers to a peculiarly chilling form of violence associated with political upheavals in Latin America over the past 40 years, and now becoming more common in Iraq. 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, (212) 831-7272, elmuseo .org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Museum of Modern Art: JEFF WALL, through May 14. This majestic show makes a great case for Mr. Wall as the most complete, if traditional, of the untraditional artists who emerged from the turmoil of Conceptual Art. His often immense color transparencies mounted on light boxes are enthralling vehicles, intent on giving pleasure while making a point or two about society, art, history, visual perception, the human animal or all of the above. An imposing blend of painting, street photography and movies, they blur reality and artifice, narrative and form, detail and the big statement. You can't stop looking at them. (212) 708-9400, moma.org (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Lorna Simpson,' through May 6. This tight, refined and impassioned survey covers more than 20 years of Lorna Simpson's career, from her photo-and-text meditations on race and sexism in the 1980s, to her more recent short films, which unite American history and personal history in forceful and lyrical ways. It would be easy to put some of this work on a shelf as ''identity art,'' but with an African-American woman holding one of the highest offices in the United States government, an African-American man running for president, and the nation embroiled in what some people view as an ethnic war, this art is entirely of the moment. (212) 570-3676, whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* 'PAINTINGS, FLAGS &amp; IRON: HAITIAN ART FROM THE LAST FIFTY YEARS' This splendid exhibition offers total immersion in the originality and continued vitality of Haiti's self-taught artists. Works by well-known painters like Hector Hyppolite, Toussaint Auguste and Rigaud Benoit range across religion, history and everyday themes. They include still lifes, landscapes and Pierre Joseph Valcin's enthralling rendering of a maternity ward. The forged and welded sculptures of Georges Liautaud and Gabriel Bien-Aimé are on a par with Bill Traylor's antic silhouette drawings. And there are no words for the extravagantly sequined and beaded flags depicting Voodoo spirits and saints, except fabulous. Edward Thorp Gallery, 210 11th Avenue, at 25th Street, (212) 691-6565, through April 21. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Lamar Peterson Best known for his fanciful, Pop-inflected paintings of African-American suburban life, this young painter smashes that subject to smithereens in his new work, a promising advancement that is already yielding rewards. Fredericks &amp; Freiser, 536 West 24th Street, (212) 633-6555, fredericksfreisergallery.com, through April 28. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Other</p>
        <p>'Gifts of the Forest: Native Traditions in Wood and Bark' Drawn from the collections of the Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center in Connecticut, this show celebrates the trees of the rich forests that once covered the Northeast, yielding essential materials to the Pequot and other Eastern Woodland cultures. The objects run from ancient woodworking tools to contemporary objects that carry on tribal traditions, like the simple and beautiful wooden flute made in 1999 by Hawk Henires (Nipmuc) and adorned with an elegantly carved bird motif. Many things here were made in the 19th and 20th centuries: handsome woven baskets, carved bowls and spoons, decorated cradle boards for carrying babies, birch bark canoe models, an elegant birch-bark hamper whose sides bear a stylized tree motif. UBS Art Gallery, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, between 51st and 52nd Streets, (212) 713-2885, through April 27. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* 'THOMAS STRUTH: Making Time' Through the 1990s, the German photographer Thomas Struth became an art world celebrity for his outsize, absorbing portraits of crowds interacting with artwork in the world's great museums. As a follow-up, he is presenting the American premiere of two new series of pictures of audiences beholding single masterpieces in the Museo Nacional del Prado in Madrid, and the State Hermitage Museum in St. Petersburg, Russia. The show, which cannily allows us to look safely at others looking at art, is one of the most visually sumptuous and thought-probing in the city. Marian Goodman Gallery, 24 West 57th Street, (212) 977-7160, through April 28. (Genocchio)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* KRISTIN BAKER: SURGE AND SHADOW In these clever, ambitious mergers of Pop, Minimalism and Abstract Expressionism, abstract painting takes another turn for the spectacular, aided by the freshly white-on-white Deitch space. Cataclysmic compositions and an all-plastic, labor-intensive process strike the eye with a dazzling newness, but the eye adjusts and is eventually bored. A series of smaller studies evades the prescribed soullessness. Deitch Projects, 18 Wooster Street, near Grand Street, SoHo, (212) 343-7300; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'Early Chinese Buddhist Sculpture,' Asia Week is over, but its essence lingers on in this exhibition of beautiful carved stone figures of Buddhas and bodhisattvas dating from the Northern Wei to Tang periods in China. This is the type of work that elicited rapturous responses when shown in London and Washington a few seasons back. Throckmorton Fine Art, 145 East 57th Street, third floor, (212) 223-1059; closes tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* ANYA KIELAR: 'LADY' The traditions of photomontage, collage and assemblage are sliced, diced and reconfigured here with surgical precision, feminist wit and a terrific sense of light, dark and color. The works range from two to three dimensions, with the best -- mysterious boxed collages that cross Hannah Hoch with Kembra Phaler -- landing squarely in between. Daniel Reich Gallery, 537A West 23rd Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-4949, danielreichgallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MOMA: Armando ReverÓn  Unless you spotted his single smoke-puff of a painting at MoMA months ago, Armando Reverón probably means nothing to you. Why should he? The artist, who died in 1954, spent most of his life in a shack by the sea in his native Venezuela. Many of his contemporaries dismissed him as nuts. His white-on-white pictures are practically unphotographable. But chances are that if you visit this retrospective, you'll find yourself thinking about him a lot. His art and his story are like few others, and so is the museum's inspired installation: a single, long corridor with cabinetlike rooms of paintings on either side and, at the very end, against a sea-green wall, a life-size doll with giant bat wings floating overhead. (212) 708-9400, moma.org; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>WILHELM SASNAL A truncated, slightly altered version of a Polish film from the 1960s provides the frame or caption for often drab, studiously incomplete paintings that reciprocate with hints of cinematic light or depictions of movie screens. A genuine sense of postwar Communist bloc deprivation is evoked, without giving the viewer much to work with. Anton Kern Gallery, 532 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 367-9663; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* 'David Shapiro: Rock Iraq,' A while back, David Shapiro filled a gallery with the empty containers of all the consumer products he had bought and used over two years. His current Pierogi solo takes up less space: it's an 8-by-8-foot tabletop model of an imaginary benefit concert. The exact cause espoused isn't stated. But with no musicians present, and corporate logos plastering the concert hall walls, emptiness and waste are the unmistakable themes. Pierogi, 177 North Ninth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-2144, pierogi2000.com; closes on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 19, 2007, Thursday  A film series entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday, about the three-part Chinese documentary ''West of Tracks'' at Anthology Film Archives, misstated the opening dates for the first two parts, ''Rust'' and ''Remnants.'' ''Rust'' opened yesterday and ''Remnants'' opens today; they did not open last Friday and Saturday. (As the article noted, part three, ''Rails,'' opens tomorrow.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 19, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A film series entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday, about the three-part Chinese documentary ''West of Tracks'' at Anthology Film Archives, misstated the opening dates for the first two parts, ''Rust'' and ''Remnants.'' ''Rust'' opened yesterday and ''Remnants'' opens today; they did not open last Friday and Saturday. (As the article noted, part three, ''Rails,'' opens tomorrow.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
