<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paris Believes in Tears (And Love and Real Estate)</title>
    <meta content="13priv" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/movies/13priv.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Resnais, Alain</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morante, Laura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Lambert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dussollier, Andre</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Private Fears in Public Places (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Resnais, Alain</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Private Fears in Public Places (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paris Believes in Tears (And Love and Real Estate)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Paris Believes in Tears (and Love and Real Estate)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews film Private Fears in Public Places, directed by Alain Resnais; Laura Morante, Lambert Wilson and Andre Dussollier star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Things happen in Alain Resnais's ''Private Fears in Public Places,'' much as they do in life. There is a breakup, a brief encounter, an awkward rejection. There are hot tears and heavy sighs. But because this is an Alain Resnais film, things happen with elegant camera moves and syncopated editing, and they happen to characters in near-geometric alignment: six heavenly bodies as seen through a mighty telescope.</p>
        <p>The six include the quarrelsome lovers, Nicole and Dan (Laura Morante and Lambert Wilson); the real estate broker, Thierry (André Dussollier), who's trying to find them a new apartment in the tough Parisian market; and the sad-sack bartender, Lionel (Pierre Arditi), who faithfully tops off Dan's drinks. Thierry has an assistant, Charlotte (Sabine Azéma), with whom he appears infatuated, and a much-younger sister, Gaëlle (Isabelle Carré), who sits in cafes with a red flower pinned to her lapel, waiting for the next SWM to pull up a chair. For her part, Charlotte spends evenings caring for Lionel's ailing, verbally abusive, unnamed father. Here, death bangs at the door as noisily as desire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Things happen in “Private Fears in Public Places,” much as they do in life. But because this is an Alain Resnais film, things happen in near-geometric alignment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Things happen in Alain Resnais's ''Private Fears in Public Places,'' much as they do in life. There is a breakup, a brief encounter, an awkward rejection. There are hot tears and heavy sighs. But because this is an Alain Resnais film, things happen with elegant camera moves and syncopated editing, and they happen to characters in near-geometric alignment: six heavenly bodies as seen through a mighty telescope.</p>
        <p>The six include the quarrelsome lovers, Nicole and Dan (Laura Morante and Lambert Wilson); the real estate broker, Thierry (André Dussollier), who's trying to find them a new apartment in the tough Parisian market; and the sad-sack bartender, Lionel (Pierre Arditi), who faithfully tops off Dan's drinks. Thierry has an assistant, Charlotte (Sabine Azéma), with whom he appears infatuated, and a much-younger sister, Gaëlle (Isabelle Carré), who sits in cafes with a red flower pinned to her lapel, waiting for the next SWM to pull up a chair. For her part, Charlotte spends evenings caring for Lionel's ailing, verbally abusive, unnamed father. Here, death bangs at the door as noisily as desire.</p>
        <p>It's all rather complicated, kind of like life, though mostly like a stage play. ''Private Fears in Public Places'' was written by Jean-Michel Ribes and is based on the play of the same title by Alan Ayckbourn, who wrote a cycle of plays that Mr. Resnais turned into the 1993 films ''Smoking'' and ''No Smoking.'' Once again there are various characters in various formations, conspicuously artificial sets and a suffusion of feeling, though this time the sentiment feels heavy rather than playful. Everyone except Gaëlle, who looks about 35, seems firmly in middle age or on its far side. (Mr. Resnais's tendency to soften the focus whenever he films his older actresses in close-up only underscores the obvious and not with the kindness he perhaps intends.)</p>
        <p>There is no plot to speak of, just scenes organized around emotional encounters and rituals. There are appointments, misunderstandings and romantic lulls, along with some wince-worthy bump-and-grind videos. The lovers quarrel, the broker shows his apartments and the bartender whips up drinks and advice. There are tears, yes, but no hysterics. The mood is polite, discreet, hushed, resolutely adult, even when the characters fall down drunk. Mr. Resnais's narrative techniques are similarly refined. The edits are as smooth as the fluid camerawork, and many scenes connect through dissolves overlaid with the image of the ceaselessly falling snow. It doesn't snow often in Paris, but it snows throughout ''Private Fears in Public Places,'' adding to the overall air of gentle, twinkling unreality.</p>
        <p>At several points in the film Mr. Resnais places the camera directly above his sets and points down, so we (and he) can watch the actors move about as if we were perched on a catwalk. As with the manufactured sets and all the overtly staged exits and entrances, this elevated point of view evokes the theater while remaining steadfastly cinematic. Seen from above, these stagy rooms also look like a warren, an image that brings to mind Mr. Resnais's ''Mon Oncle d'Amérique'' (1980). In that film characters sprout the heads of rats, twitchy whiskers and all, and one fleetingly transforms into an actual rat running in a mazelike home, a crude metamorphosis that betrays a cynical, ungenerous view of the human condition.</p>
        <p>''Private Fears in Public Places'' hasn't a trace of cynicism. Its characters are not lab rats or types; they are people, somewhat blurred around the edges but nonetheless alive. They work and frolic, laugh and weep, alone and with others. All are playing self-conscious roles -- son, colleague, sibling and lover -- that at once define and restrict them. Despite the obvious personal and social perks, the private love and the public profile, playing the same role for too long can, the film suggests, take a toll. That much at least seems true from the creased, crumpled face of Lionel, who for too many years has performed the part of the dutiful son, faithfully caring for the invalid father who has become as much his warden as his ward.</p>
        <p>In the early 1960s Mr. Resnais's ''Last Year at Marienbad'' inspired head-scratching among critics and audiences, attracting the kind of attention in the press now usually reserved for celebrity scandals and box-office receipts. These days, difficult films -- it seems important to add that difficult is not a pejorative -- rarely elicit anything but yawns and condescension. ''Private Fears in Public Places'' is far from difficult and that, it is also worth noting, is not a criticism. The film is accessible, pleasant, dreamy, a touch goofy and melancholic. Its modernist gestures are little more than stylistic tics, but there's an image of snow falling on two clasped hands that is almost rapturous. The role of the artist remains, for Mr. Resnais, the role of a lifetime.</p>
        <p>Private Fears in Public Places  Opens today in Manhattan and on Video on Demand.</p>
        <p>Directed by Alain Resnais; written (in French, with English subtitles) by Jean-Michel Ribes, based on the play by Alan Ayckbourn; director of photography, Eric Gautier; edited by Hervé de Luze; music by Mark Snow; production designers, Jacques Saulnier, Jean-Michel Ducourty and Solange Zeitoun; produced by Bruno Pésery; released by IFC First Take. Running time: 120 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Sabine Azéma (Charlotte), Isabelle Carré (Gaëlle), Laura Morante (Nicole), Pierre Arditi (Lionel), André Dussollier (Thierry), Claude Rich (Arthur) and Lambert Wilson (Dan).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
