<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Duke Case: What Was Learned?</title>
    <meta content="l13duke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Duke Case: What Was Learned?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Duke Prosecutor Throws Out Case Against Players'' and ''NBC News Drops Imus Show Over Racial Remark'' (front page, April 12):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Duke Prosecutor Throws Out Case Against Players'' and ''NBC News Drops Imus Show Over Racial Remark'' (front page, April 12):</p>
        <p>Overlooked in the public outcry over these two incidents is their common denominator.</p>
        <p>Not only does each case show the adverse effect on innocent young people of the irresponsible behavior of supposed adults; more broadly, each illustrates the costs of our sometimes mindless devotion to the principle of free expression.</p>
        <p>Defenders of provocative speech often defend it as mere words. But as these two episodes demonstrate, words have consequences, whether uttered by a reprehensible shock jock, a renegade district attorney or a reckless accuser.</p>
        <p>As valuable as free expression is, it must not be allowed to trump the right of all our citizens, especially the most vulnerable, to dignity and equal treatment.</p>
        <p>As Justice Robert Jackson once observed: ''The choice is not between order and liberty. It is between liberty with order and anarchy without either.''</p>
        <p>Gerard J. Fitzpatrick  Collegeville, Pa., April 12, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a professor of politics at Ursinus College.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Michael B. Nifong, the Durham County district attorney, wasn't the only one who rushed to judgment. The president of Duke University acted precipitously, as if the charges were equivalent to guilt, and the media's constant focus on race and economic issues reinforced the image of guilt, as if that was the only possible outcome.</p>
        <p>Whatever happened to innocent until proven guilty? And why did it take more than a year to come to that conclusion?</p>
        <p>Lenore H. Forsted  Wynnewood, Pa., April 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>With all charges in the Duke lacrosse case now dropped, one glaring flaw in our legal system lingers. In instances of alleged sex crimes, the accuser's identity remains confidential.</p>
        <p>This is a sound policy; it allows victims to come forward without fear of shame or public scrutiny often associated with such crimes. But one accused of a sex crime receives no such anonymity. And this is wrong. One should stand trial before the masses are allowed speculation of one's guilt.</p>
        <p>Like many, at first I condemned the Duke lacrosse players. Though now exonerated, these men will toil with the lasting effects of such serious allegations, and they should not have to.</p>
        <p>As millions join me in apologizing to these men, let us learn from our mistakes. In protecting the anonymity of the accuser and the accused, we will adhere to the most fundamental principle of our legal system: the presumption of innocence.</p>
        <p>William Stephens  Raleigh, N.C., April 12, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a sophomore at North Carolina State University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>So, presumed guilty by fashionable black-white, rich-poor, athlete-nonathlete stereotypes, Duke's lacrosse players turn out to be innocent victims.</p>
        <p>I saw and despised Senator Joseph R. McCarthy. But McCarthyism never gained a tenth the oppressive mind control of today's academic and media political correctness.</p>
        <p>Charles Fred  Maspeth, Queens, April 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The defense attorneys also pilloried the press for piling on early in the Duke rape case investigation. The Times should examine its reporting in this case and report to us, its loyal readers, as to how it contributed or did not contribute to this miscarriage of justice.</p>
        <p>Henry Belch  Fairfax, Va., April 12, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
