<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Face of the L.P.G.A. Tour Is Changing</title>
    <meta content="13golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/sports/13golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ladies Professional Golf Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ochoa, Lorena</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sorenstam, Annika</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6DB133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Face of the L.P.G.A. Tour Is Changing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Face of the L.P.G.A. Tour Is Changing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Annika Sorenstam and Michelle Wie spent last season facing new and uncomfortable realities.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, the top player in women's golf, ceded player of the year honors for the first time in six years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Annika Sorenstam was supplanted in 2006 as player of the year by Lorena Ochoa, who can remove Sorenstam from the No. 1 ranking with a victory at the Ginn Open this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Annika Sorenstam and Michelle Wie spent last season facing new and uncomfortable realities.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, the top player in women's golf, ceded player of the year honors for the first time in six years.</p>
        <p>Wie, the top draw in women's golf, skidded to last-place finishes against the men while failing to capture her first L.P.G.A. Tour victory.</p>
        <p>Deep into the start of a new year, they share one more thread: neither is healthy enough to compete.</p>
        <p>On the morning that Sorenstam was to begin perhaps her final defense of her No. 1 ranking, she withdrew yesterday from the Ginn Open in Reunion, Fla., with a ruptured disk and a bulging disk.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, 36, is expected to be out of action for at least a month.</p>
        <p>''I've been playing with quite a bit of pain for the past several weeks,'' she said yesterday in a statement. ''I couldn't take it much more and decided it was time to see someone after the pro-am yesterday.''</p>
        <p>Sorenstam had an appointment scheduled with a neurosurgeon yesterday.</p>
        <p>Even before her withdrawal from the tournament, Sorenstam had seen a shifting landscape on the L.P.G.A. Tour in ways large and small.</p>
        <p>Last year, she was supplanted as player of the year by Lorena Ochoa, who can remove Sorenstam from the No. 1 ranking with a victory at the Ginn Open. Ochoa shot a six-under-par 66 yesterday to share the first-round lead with Laura Davies.</p>
        <p>When the L.P.G.A. printed its 2007 media guide, Ochoa was on the cover with Seon Hwa Lee, last year's rookie of the year, and Julieta Granada, who won $1 million at last year's ADT Championship.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, whose picture used to dominate L.P.G.A. covers, did not even get an inside flap.</p>
        <p>''The Tour is wide open now,'' Sherri Turner, an L.P.G.A. player, said after her round yesterday.</p>
        <p>Wie, 17, was supposed to be a part of the competitive conversation, but her injuries have been confounding. Last summer, she left the PGA Tour's John Deere Classic on a stretcher after a bout with heat exhaustion.</p>
        <p>In January, she arrived at the PGA's Sony Open sporting a bandage on her right wrist. She shot 78-76 and missed the cut by 14 shots.</p>
        <p>A month later, Wie injured her left wrist during a fall while she was running, forcing her to miss the Kraft Nabisco Championship, the L.P.G.A.'s first major of the year. She has not competed since.</p>
        <p>Even in Wie's absence, some have questioned her approach to being a professional. She finished the 2006 season with last-place finishes on the European Tour and the PGA Tour, and a 17th-place finish in a field of 20 at the L.P.G.A.'s Samsung World Championship.</p>
        <p>David Leadbetter, her swing coach, has said critics underestimate Wie's resiliency. Others still wonder if she is taking the correct approach.</p>
        <p>''I would rather her set her goal to be the best player on the L.P.G.A. Tour than setting her goal to make the cut on the PGA Tour,'' Nancy Lopez said Wednesday during a news conference at the Ginn Open. ''She's just such a great player and super person. It's just I would like to see her out here trying to beat the women on the L.P.G.A. Tour, because she's so talented.</p>
        <p>''Then, when she gets bored of beating all of us here, she should try the men's tour. Right now, I think she should be out here developing her game and getting comfortable with that.''</p>
        <p>Wie's spokesman, Jesse Derris, said in an e-mail message yesterday that there was no update on Wie's status.</p>
        <p>''We have not announced her first tournament back as of yet, and will not do so until she is ready to go,'' Derris said.</p>
        <p>In the interim, other young players have filled in where Wie was once projected. Two years ago, Paula Creamer won an L.P.G.A. event four days before her high school graduation. She has won two more L.P.G.A. events since.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Morgan Pressel became the youngest woman, at 18 years 10 months 9 days, to win an L.P.G.A. major.</p>
        <p>Asked about beating Wie to a major, Pressel said: ''She's still a little younger than I am, so she still has a little bit of time. It's unfortunate that she has an injured wrist. It won't be too long before we see her again.''</p>
        <p>By the time Sorenstam and Wie return, the landscape they once knew may still be evolving. New faces may have emerged and new realities may have set in.</p>
        <p>Of course, Sorenstam and Wie may still have something in common: both of them could be chasing Ochoa.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
