<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Little Luxe on the Jersey Shore</title>
    <meta content="13boutique" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/travel/escapes/13boutique.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tutelian, Louise</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Little Luxe on the Jersey Shore</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Little Luxe on the Jersey Shore</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUISE TUTELIAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tutelian, Louise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on three new luxury boutique hotels along Jersey Shore; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEOPARD-PATTERNED rugs accent the chocolate and lipstick-red lobby of the Virginia Hotel. The crystal chandeliers look like huge fuzzy dandelions. Frank Sinatra croons ''Satin Doll'' as guests sip cocktails and nibble fruit and cheese. Directly off the lobby in the hotel's dining room, the Ebbitt Room, guests dine on entrees like roasted rack of lamb with caramelized fennel and aged balsamic vinegar.</p>
        <p>Most of the Virginia's 24 rooms are only about 12 by 12 feet, but packed with plush amenities: terry robes, Bulgari toiletries, hand-pressed Belgian linen sheets. Their sea foam and silver color scheme is both stylish and soothing. Doors close with the satisfying thunk of solid brass hardware. A mirrored petite armoire in each room houses snacks like Terra Frites and chocolate Moose Munch (for a fee), and is topped by flat-screen TV and CD/DVD player -- the Virginia offers use of DVDs from ''Easy Rider'' to ''As Good as It Gets.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until recently, “boutique hotel” and “Jersey Shore” were two phrases rarely heard in the same sentence. But some hotels here have recently transformed themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEOPARD-PATTERNED rugs accent the chocolate and lipstick-red lobby of the Virginia Hotel. The crystal chandeliers look like huge fuzzy dandelions. Frank Sinatra croons ''Satin Doll'' as guests sip cocktails and nibble fruit and cheese. Directly off the lobby in the hotel's dining room, the Ebbitt Room, guests dine on entrees like roasted rack of lamb with caramelized fennel and aged balsamic vinegar.</p>
        <p>Most of the Virginia's 24 rooms are only about 12 by 12 feet, but packed with plush amenities: terry robes, Bulgari toiletries, hand-pressed Belgian linen sheets. Their sea foam and silver color scheme is both stylish and soothing. Doors close with the satisfying thunk of solid brass hardware. A mirrored petite armoire in each room houses snacks like Terra Frites and chocolate Moose Munch (for a fee), and is topped by flat-screen TV and CD/DVD player -- the Virginia offers use of DVDs from ''Easy Rider'' to ''As Good as It Gets.''</p>
        <p>It's just what you'd expect from a place that bills itself as a boutique hotel: sophistication, intimacy, cleanliness and good service, with a minimum of flash and glitter.</p>
        <p>Yet Curtis Bashaw, a managing partner of the company that owns the Virginia, seems to hear nothing but amazement in the comments of new arrivals in the lobby, with its carpet custom-woven with the hotel's signature red V.</p>
        <p>''If I've heard it once,'' Mr. Bashaw said, ''I've heard it a million times: 'Boy, I can't believe this place is in New Jersey.' ''</p>
        <p>The Virginia is in Cape May, housed in a Victorian inn built in 1879. Outside, it looks much like the kind of place where you'd expect ornate antiques, lace curtains, creaky steps and communal breakfasts. But inside, it exudes an unexpected stylish vibe.</p>
        <p>Until recently, ''boutique hotel'' and ''Jersey Shore'' were two phrases rarely heard in the same sentence. Hotels in shore towns from Cape May north to Monmouth County tended to fall into a few distinct categories: the homey B&amp;B in the genteel old summer colony, the casino high-rise in Atlantic City, the flat-roofed stucco motel wedged in amid bungalows and boardwalk.</p>
        <p>But in the last few years, as property values have skyrocketed on the shore, with big new houses and condos replacing old seaside cottages, a few hotels have begun transforming themselves to attract travelers in search of a touch of class and a scent of sea spray.</p>
        <p>They have been a long time coming. The boutique hotel trend has been around for decades. In 1984, Ian Schrager and Steve Rubell attracted a lot of attention when they turned the dowdy Executive Hotel in Manhattan into the ultra-chic Morgans. A boutique hotel is typically long on amenities, design and service. It usually has no more than 100 rooms and often far fewer. The lobby is meant to emulate a living room; the guest rooms, bedrooms in an elegant private home.</p>
        <p>RICHARD PERNICIARO, director of the Center for Regional and Business Research at Atlantic Cape Community College, thinks he knows why the template has finally hit the Jersey beaches. ''To be different and to command more money is the key,'' he said. ''The thinking is 'I have to create something upscale to justify the huge investment in land and property.' ''</p>
        <p>The hotelier also needs to offer a place sufficiently self-contained and intriguing to attract guests year round.</p>
        <p>On Long Beach Island, two hours south of Manhattan, two flags with block letters reading ''OPEN'' flapped in a stiff breeze at the Daddy O, the newest Jersey Shore boutique hotel, on a cold day in March. The Sea Horse Motel down the block was still closed tighter than a clamshell for the off-season. Across the street, shrink-wrapped cabin cruisers were perched high and dry.</p>
        <p>But at the Daddy O, mellow sounds of recorded Brazilian jazz filled the air, and the lobby was warmly decorated with brown and ivory leather chairs, oversize ottomans and side tables stained in a soft silver wash.</p>
        <p>The bisque marble floor in the public areas of the Daddy O are edged in chocolate brown, and walls are covered in glittering beige paper peppered with crushed Murano glass, sparkling even in a winter sun. On the second and third floors, 22 guest rooms are small but sleek, with mahogany trim and furniture and faux mink pillows and throws. There are flat-screen TVs, two kinds of halogen reading lamps and marble bathrooms with rainfall shower heads.</p>
        <p>The Daddy O was a worn-out 80-year-old hotel and restaurant when Marty Grims, a Philadelphia restaurateur who owns the Plantation on Long Beach Island, and four partners purchased it in 2005. ''We bought the property for the value of the land,'' he said. ''That was $4.5 million with the liquor license, and we spent another $5.5 million gutting and renovating it.''</p>
        <p>He knew the effect he wanted. ''Custom millwork, polished stainless-steel hardware, these were things you wouldn't find at a typical shore motel,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Daddy O opened last August to praise from longtime Long Beach Island vacationers like Barbara Sunderlin, a Macy's personal shopper from Fort Washington, Pa. ''It blew me away,'' said Ms. Sunderlin, a guest that first month. ''From the shower heads to the TV to the sheets, I felt like I was more in New York than at the shore.''</p>
        <p>Delighting a certain kind of customer -- and luring customers back -- is good business if a hotel is to survive year-round in a shore town. The boutique hotels, said Rummy Pandit, assistant dean and director of hospitality management at Rutgers School of Business in Camden, N.J., are courting ''30-somethings on a weekend away from young kids, people who are retired or near retirement and are fairly affluent -- the kind of people who have stayed in B&amp;Bs and want a more upscale experience.''</p>
        <p>Terri and Scott Sommer of Northport, N.Y., who stayed at the Virginia in late February, fit that profile. Heading down to the pocket-size lobby bar for a cocktail in front of the fireplace, they explained their choice. ''We didn't want a bed-and-breakfast -- we like more privacy than that,'' said Mr. Sommer, who is semiretired from the medical supply business. His wife added that the service and upgraded amenities at the Virginia were just right.</p>
        <p>''For us it was the best balance,'' she said, ''more privacy than a B&amp;B, but not the anonymity of a big hotel.''</p>
        <p>Developers with deep pockets are looking at the shore differently, too. Mr. Bashaw's company, Cape Advisors., which owns the Virginia, has purchased the aging Holiday Inn and Howard Johnson hotels on the Boardwalk in Atlantic City and plans to combine them and transform them into what is being described as an independent 337-room boutique hotel, the first noncasino luxury hotel in Atlantic City. ''Boutique doesn't have to mean small,'' Mr. Bashaw said. In his lexicon, the term means ''non-cookie-cutter.''</p>
        <p>But to the lovers of boutique hotels as they are usually understood, a more authentic model might be the one followed by Sark and Dido Krikorian, owners of the Blue Bay Inn in Atlantic Highlands, N.J. The town overlooks Raritan Bay at the northern tip of the Jersey Shore and is close to Sandy Hook, a narrow peninsula of beaches and salt marshes.</p>
        <p>Sensing the time was right for more visitors to discover Atlantic Highlands, their hometown, the Krikorians bought Honest Paul's Tavern, a rundown bar in foreclosure, and three adjacent lots for less than $1 million in 2000. Mr. Krikorian, a residential builder, and his wife were both in their 60s and thought the purchase was a perfect second act.</p>
        <p>''My husband said: 'You know what would be fun? We'll build a bed-and-breakfast and hire someone to run it,' '' Mrs. Krikorian said. It didn't quite turn out that way. They gutted the bar and spent $4 million designing and decorating from the ground up in a European style. The Blue Bay opened in September 2004. The inn, on a pleasant though modest block, is an unexpected and cosmopolitan addition to a street that also holds a marine supply store, a print shop and a brick elementary school. Its cream facade is subtly silvered with its name in brushed steel, and guests enter through a charming courtyard. Each of the 27 guest rooms is individually designed, in color schemes from beige to pumpkin to violet. Beds are piled high with pillows, and plush upholstered club chairs and ottomans add swaths of color. Bathrooms feature inlaid European tiles. The hallways serve as an art gallery, with all the works for sale.</p>
        <p>John Majors, a genial accountant from St. Petersburg, Fla., said he had been surprised to find the Blue Bay in such an unassuming town -- even though Atlantic Highlands is close enough to Manhattan to have a view of the skyline. The Blue Bay is ''convenient, well-appointed and comfortable,'' he said. He heard about it from a Wall Street colleague and quickly booked a suite for a three-week stay this spring. He'll be taking the ferry to Lower Manhattan to attend to a project he's working on.</p>
        <p>All of the boutique hotel owners have also benefited from the growing popularity of Jersey Shore weddings and anniversary parties, which bring crowds of guests in the shoulder seasons of spring and fall.</p>
        <p>Marty Grims of the Daddy O sees another potential market -- in the classic shore tradition. At his hotel, he said, guests can find ''a luxury hotel with its own restaurant, a half a block from the beach.'' That should be perfect, he thinks, for summer vacationers who are well off but still find themselves priced out of buying million-dollar houses at the shore -- or who just don't want the hassle of owning a second home.</p>
        <p>''A mortgage can cost $7,000 a month, and you're paying it all through the winter,'' Mr. Grims said. ''This way, you can book all four weekends in August and only pay $2,300 -- with none of the headaches.''</p>
        <p>BOUTIQUE LODGINGS</p>
        <p>Sand in Your Shoes, Fine Linens on Your Bed</p>
        <p>THESE new hotels on the Jersey Shore are open year-round, with rates varying by season and room; two- or three-night stays are sometimes required. All the marble, glass, silk and leather in the interior design makes them less than child-friendly -- but they're not intended to be.</p>
        <p>The Blue Bay Inn (51 First Avenue, Atlantic Highlands; 732-708-9600; www.bluebayinn) is a block from the 40-minute Seastreak ferry to Manhattan. The Southwestern-style Copper Canyon restaurant serves lunch on weekdays and dinner daily except Sunday, and the inn's jazz lounge is open on weekends. Spa treatments may be arranged. Rooms are $159 to $299, Continental breakfast included.</p>
        <p>Daddy O Hotel (4401 Long Beach Boulevard, Brant Beach; 609-494-1300; www.daddyohotel.com) is half a block from the beach. The Daddy O restaurant serves lunch and dinner daily. In the summer, a shop sells wine, liquor and take-out food. There is a roof deck, and beach badges, towels and chairs are provided in season. Rooms are $115 to $375, including Continental breakfast in summer.</p>
        <p>The Virginia Hotel (25 Jackson Street, Cape May; 609-884-5700; www.virginiahotel.com), a half-block from the beach and close to shops, offers valet parking and limited room service. The Ebbitt Room on the lobby level serves dinner nightly from April through December and small plates in other months. Rooms are $100 to $475, including a Continental breakfast. Guests must be at least 12 years old.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
