<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Lonely Place, Saved by Puppies</title>
    <meta content="13dog" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/movies/13dog.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839861"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shannon, Molly</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Year of the Dog (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">White, Mike</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Shannon, Molly</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Year of the Dog (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E3DE133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Lonely Place, Saved by Puppies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Lonely Place, Saved by Puppies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews film Year of the Dog, directed by Mike White; Molly Shannon stars; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The wily and resourceful young screenwriter Mike White writes movies that seem as if they were cooked up by the skinny, self-consciously awkward guy who always ends up alone in a corner at the office holiday party. As it happens, Mr. White, who sometimes acts in the films he and others write, is a skinny, seemingly self-aware guy, though given his résumé -- ''Chuck &amp; Buck,'' ''The Good Girl,'' ''School of Rock'' and ''Nacho Libre'' -- it's a safe bet he doesn't often play the wallflower, at least in Hollywood.</p>
        <p>''Year of the Dog'' is exactly the kind of story you would expect Mr. White to make for his directing debut. It's funny ha-ha but firmly in touch with its downer side, which means it's also funny in a kind of existential way. It stars the comic Molly Shannon as a woman who discovers her true self through a love of animals, though not that kind of love. She's not Catherine the Great, just Peggy the Good. It's a film about what it means to devote yourself to something other than your fears and desires, to shed that hard, durable shell called selfishness. It is, rather remarkably, an inquiry into empathy as a state of grace. And if that sounds too rarefied for laughs, rest assured, it's also about a stone-cold beautiful freak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Year of the Dog” is funny ha-ha but firmly in touch with its downer side, which means it’s also funny in a kind of existential way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The wily and resourceful young screenwriter Mike White writes movies that seem as if they were cooked up by the skinny, self-consciously awkward guy who always ends up alone in a corner at the office holiday party. As it happens, Mr. White, who sometimes acts in the films he and others write, is a skinny, seemingly self-aware guy, though given his résumé -- ''Chuck &amp; Buck,'' ''The Good Girl,'' ''School of Rock'' and ''Nacho Libre'' -- it's a safe bet he doesn't often play the wallflower, at least in Hollywood.</p>
        <p>''Year of the Dog'' is exactly the kind of story you would expect Mr. White to make for his directing debut. It's funny ha-ha but firmly in touch with its downer side, which means it's also funny in a kind of existential way. It stars the comic Molly Shannon as a woman who discovers her true self through a love of animals, though not that kind of love. She's not Catherine the Great, just Peggy the Good. It's a film about what it means to devote yourself to something other than your fears and desires, to shed that hard, durable shell called selfishness. It is, rather remarkably, an inquiry into empathy as a state of grace. And if that sounds too rarefied for laughs, rest assured, it's also about a stone-cold beautiful freak.</p>
        <p>That freak would be Peggy, who seems like a punch line in waiting. Unmarried and just north of 40, she lives with her sole companion, a sturdy little beagle named Pencil, in a tidy little house someplace in Southern California. She works as an assistant to some kind of numbers cruncher, Robin (the divine Josh Pais), on an office floor filled with cubicles that, from just the right angle, look remarkably like feedlot pens. It's drab but pleasant enough, and anyway Peggy doesn't seem to mind or notice. Every morning she brings a big pink box of doughnuts for everyone in the office to share, then soaks in the joy. At lunch she listens to her office mate Layla (Regina King) plot her love life with the cunning of Sun Tzu.</p>
        <p>We are, during the opening of ''Year of the Dog,'' in seriously overtilled territory, somewhere between Alexander Payne and Todd Solondz. Mr. White lays out the narrow parameters of Peggy's life with an aggressive lack of visual flair in a style that might be termed, to bend a phrase from Gloria Grahame, Late Nothing. His most obvious choice, one that feels like a misguided shortcut, is to arrange objects and people symmetrically -- including Tom McCarthy and Laura Dern as Peggy's obsessively matched brother and sister-in-law -- inside the frame like displayed goods. It's a standard-issue comedy strategy, fine for Barry Sonnenfeld-level laughs, but it also suggests that there's nothing beneath these overly clean, tidy lines and, by extension, nothing much beneath Peggy, either.</p>
        <p>This being a Mike White film, I was keeping my fingers crossed for more. One of the most talented screenwriters enlivening the commercial mainstream, Mr. White is a standard-bearer for freaks and geeks. (He worked on the critically revered television show of the same name.) He boldly let his own freak flag fly in the 2000 pathology-driven comedy ''Chuck &amp; Buck,'' in which, as a childlike man (Buck) who romantically stalks an old friend, he slithers under your skin, delivering an off-putting performance that deliberately risks turning a creepy story into an unlikable one. ''Year of the Dog'' limns less dangerous territory, but one of its modest glories is that here too Mr. White takes some appreciable chances with our sympathies, notably through a leading character who has more in common with Buck than might at first appear.</p>
        <p>It takes a while, but Mr. White does peel away his film's surface banality. What gets everything moving, including his somewhat sneakily or perhaps cautiously articulated intellectual interests (this is, after all, a studio-bankrolled comedy), is Pencil's untimely death, which tears a hole in Peggy's world and eventually her psyche. For Peggy, a woman who greets her beloved four-legged friend with a toothy smile that rivals the sun for warmth (Pencil shines right back), this isn't the death of some adopted stray, one in a line of carelessly loved dumb beasts. It is a shock to the system, a life-altering tragedy, a terrible end that becomes -- movingly, through one odd story kink after another -- a radical new beginning.</p>
        <p>Reader, she becomes a vegan. She also advocates and donates, destroys a couple of fur coats and takes her young niece and baby nephew to an animal sanctuary where rescued horses, cows, pigs and chickens roam about breathing fresh air with the green grass below and the blue sky above. Into the void left by Pencil she crams a couple and then a couple hundred and then thousands of abused and abandoned creatures, both by petition and by adoption, transforming into a kind of Angelina Jolie of the animal kingdom. She also finds what she hopes may be her Brad Pitt in the form of a pasty lump who volunteers at the A.S.P.C.A., ignoring or ignorant of the warning embedded in his name: Newt (Peter Sarsgaard, superb).</p>
        <p>In other words Peggy becomes, at last, a fleshed-out character worth spending time with, not because she's funny (she is) or nice (not always) or sympathetic (not necessarily). Instead it is precisely because she isn't especially pleasant to be around, because she makes some wrong and, depending on your worldview and palate, some suspect choices -- fermented soybean, for starters -- that she and the film finally start to hum, whistle and work. After the story settles in, Ms. Shannon, who remains best known for her tenure on ''Saturday Night Live,'' fits Mr. White's anti-intuitive purposes admirably, in large part because so much of the performance willfully goes against the grain, pushing at us with naked, frenzied need that can feel embarrassing and, at times, almost grotesque.</p>
        <p>In its broad outline, ''Year of the Dog'' is the story of a woman who goes slightly bonkers and becomes an animal-rights advocate, not because she's bonkers, but because the love of animals is where she finally finds her peace of mind, sense of self, grace. It's also about the creation of conscience, about what makes us human and why, a surprisingly little-told story in contemporary American cinema.</p>
        <p>You can learn a lot from our movies, like how to hold a gun and blow someone's head off. It's more unusual to watch a film in which the central struggle is how to be happy and sane. There's a touch of the saint in Peggy, true, but what makes me love her is that she's ridiculously, beautifully human.</p>
        <p>''Year of the Dog'' is Rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). Bring hankies.</p>
        <p>Year of the Dog  Opens today in New York and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Mike White; director of photography, Tim Orr; edited by Dody Dorn; music by Christophe Beck; production designer, Daniel Bradford; produced by Mr. White, Ben LeClair and Dede Gardner; released by Paramount Vantage. Running time: 97 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Molly Shannon (Peggy), Laura Dern (Bret), Regina King (Layla), Tom McCarthy (Pier), Josh Pais (Robin), John C. Reilly (Al) and Peter Sarsgaard (Newt).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
