<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rent Board Statistics Show Ups, Downs and Betweens</title>
    <meta content="13rent" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/nyregion/13rent.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EFDC133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rent Board Statistics Show Ups, Downs and Betweens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rent Board Statistics Show Ups, Downs and Betweens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANNY SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, Janny</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rent Guidelines Board, embarking once again upon the annual drama of deciding the size of the allowable rent increases for rent-stabilized apartments, reviewed yesterday a hodgepodge of statistics -- some of them contradictory -- intended to shed light on how much New Yorkers can afford to pay.</p>
        <p>At a meeting in Lower Manhattan, the board received its staff's yearly study of ''income and affordability,'' one of several reports it will consider before June 22, when it will decide the rent increases that landlords can claim for the city's one million rent-stabilized apartments. The report found unemployment down, wages up and gross city product growing; but it also found the household income of tenants in rent-stabilized apartments shrinking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rent Guidelines Board, embarking once again upon the annual drama of deciding the size of the allowable rent increases for rent-stabilized apartments, reviewed yesterday a hodgepodge of statistics  some of them contradictory  intended to shed light on how much New Yorkers can afford to pay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rent Guidelines Board, embarking once again upon the annual drama of deciding the size of the allowable rent increases for rent-stabilized apartments, reviewed yesterday a hodgepodge of statistics -- some of them contradictory -- intended to shed light on how much New Yorkers can afford to pay.</p>
        <p>At a meeting in Lower Manhattan, the board received its staff's yearly study of ''income and affordability,'' one of several reports it will consider before June 22, when it will decide the rent increases that landlords can claim for the city's one million rent-stabilized apartments. The report found unemployment down, wages up and gross city product growing; but it also found the household income of tenants in rent-stabilized apartments shrinking.</p>
        <p>Evictions were up by almost 8 percent in 2006, according to housing court statistics in the report. The number of homeless families moving into permanent housing was down, and fewer people on public assistance were being placed in jobs. At the same time, overall homelessness levels were down in 2005 and 2006, though they started to rise in late 2006, the report found.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to just make plain old sense of it,'' said Betty Phillips Adams, a longtime advocate for low-income housing who is one of the five public members on the nine-member board. It appeared to her, she said, that while the rents in stabilized apartments had been going up, the income of residents in those apartments was going down.</p>
        <p>But Magda L. Cruz, a real estate lawyer who is one of the board's two members appointed to represent building owners, said, ''All the indicators seem to be very, very positive.'' And she said to Ms. Adams, ''I'm taking the same data that you're looking at and seeing a much rosier picture.''</p>
        <p>When a member of the board's staff judiciously declined to draw conclusions from the data and suggested instead that the numbers spoke for themselves, Marvin Markus, the chairman, said, ''We give diplomacy classes for that.''</p>
        <p>The report, which examines housing affordability and tenant income in the New York City rental market, found that the city's economy grew in 2006 for the third straight year and that the gross city product (the total value of goods and services produced) grew by 3.7 percent. Unemployment dropped for the third year in a row, labor force participation rose slightly, and overall real wages for workers grew by 0.8 percent in 2005, the latest year for which there were statistics.</p>
        <p>But the report also found that income levels for tenants in rent-stabilized apartments dropped by 8.6 percent between 2001 and 2004, the latest figures that were used, and that nearly 23 percent of all renter households had incomes below the poverty line. Between 2002 and 2005, the median monthly contract rent for all tenants, excluding fuel and utility payments, rose by 20 percent.</p>
        <p>While the median ratio of gross rent to income in 2005 was 31.2 percent, nearly 29 percent of rental households spent more than half of their household income on rent. And while the total number of people on public assistance dropped between June 2005 and June 2006 for the second consecutive year, the number of new applications rose in the first four months of the 2007 fiscal year. Job placements among recipients of public assistance declined, and the number of food stamp recipients grew.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cruz asked the board's staff to find out what percentage of people on public assistance live in rent-stabilized apartments, as opposed to public housing.</p>
        <p>And Adriene L. Holder, a Legal Aid Society lawyer and one of the two board members appointed to represent tenants, said that the city's economy might appear robust but that many people working multiple jobs earned so little that they still qualified for food stamps and legal services.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
