<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sabres Give Islanders Rude Welcome to Playoffs</title>
    <meta content="13islanders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/sports/hockey/13islanders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Campbell, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E5D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sabres Give Islanders Rude Welcome to Playoffs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sabres Give Islanders Rude Welcome to Playoffs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO, April 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Islanders were a desperate team. They had to win their last four games -- including a shootout over the Devils on the last day of the regular season -- just to reach the postseason.</p>
        <p>Their reward for qualifying for the final playoff spot in the Eastern Conference was a first-round matchup with the Buffalo Sabres, who finished with the N.H.L.'s best record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Led by defenseman Brian Campbell’s two goals, the Sabres used their superior speed to earn an easy victory over the Islanders Thursday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Islanders were a desperate team. They had to win their last four games -- including a shootout over the Devils on the last day of the regular season -- just to reach the postseason.</p>
        <p>Their reward for qualifying for the final playoff spot in the Eastern Conference was a first-round matchup with the Buffalo Sabres, who finished with the N.H.L.'s best record.</p>
        <p>At HSBC Arena on Thursday, the Sabres used their superior speed to earn an easy 4-1 victory, outshooting the Islanders by 35-21.</p>
        <p>Defenseman Brian Campbell scored two goals for Buffalo, the first and second of his playoff career, bracketing a pair by Chris Drury.</p>
        <p>Drury's second goal put Buffalo ahead, 3-1, less than two minutes into the third period. A penalty to the Islanders' Randy Robitaille had expired seconds earlier when Dainius Zubrus found Drury alone to the right of Islanders goalkeeper Wade Dubielewicz. Drury's one-time blast sneaked between Dubielewicz and the short-side post.</p>
        <p>Drury's 37th career playoff goal broke open what had been a tight-checking game.</p>
        <p>Buffalo jumped to a 1-0 lead halfway through the first period on a one-timer by Campbell. On the play, center Tim Connolly took a breakout pass in Buffalo's zone and streaked up the left side before feathering a pass to Campbell at the top of the right face-off circle. Campbell's slap shot beat Dubielewicz low.</p>
        <p>The speedy Sabres came out and controlled play in the first period, outshooting the Islanders by 11-1. But Dubielewicz made several big saves to keep the score 1-0, including denying Zubrus on a breakaway.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz, 28, had spent most of the season in the minors before being called up to fill in when Rick DiPietro sustained a concussion.</p>
        <p>He saw action in his third game of the season in a loss to the Sabres on March 30 after Mike Dunham gave up five goals. But Dubielewicz would play the next five games for the Islanders, going 4-1 and helping lead the team to its first playoff berth since 2004.</p>
        <p>''When Dubielewicz came in, he brought that belief back to our team,'' Coach Ted Nolan said. ''I think we felt sorry for ourselves a little bit when Ricky went down.''</p>
        <p>But the Islanders will need more than belief to beat Buffalo.</p>
        <p>And they may get it. DiPietro, out since March 25, has been cleared to practice with the team again Friday.</p>
        <p>DiPietro did not put a timetable on when he would return to play.</p>
        <p>When asked if he could play in Game 2 of the series Saturday night, he said: ''Your guess is as good as mine. We'll see how I feel tomorrow. This is obviously the first practice in a while, and we'll take it from there.</p>
        <p>''It's a weird feeling. You're still a part of the team, but you're not part of the everyday grind, getting dressed for practice, being around the guys in the locker room. So it's going to be nice to be back.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
