<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Needing Quality Victory, Wrong Nets Show Up</title>
    <meta content="13nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E5D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Needing Quality Victory, Wrong Nets Show Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, April 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As masters of deception, the Nets put forth a very predictable performance against the Cleveland Cavaliers on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>They played defense for a half, following a gutsy game with one in which they barely showed up. They again swung from a team apparently heading in the right direction to one simply passing time until summer vacation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As masters of deception, the Nets put forth a very predictable performance against the Cleveland Cavaliers on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>They played defense for a half, following a gutsy game with one in which they barely showed up. They again swung from a team apparently heading in the right direction to one simply passing time until summer vacation.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers put together an unstoppable third quarter to cruise to a 94-76 victory over the Nets at Quicken Loans Arena.</p>
        <p>The Nets (37-41) will be, at best, a .500 team this season and, with four games remaining, they are two games behind the Washington Wizards for the sixth seed in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>The Nets have won six of nine games, but that is just one of the many deceiving things about this team. Their three defeats have come against the Detroit Pistons, the Chicago Bulls and the Cavaliers, the teams with the three best records in the East. Except for two victories over the injury-depleted Wizards, the Nets did not defeat a team above .500 during that nine-game stretch.</p>
        <p>The Nets are holding firm to their stance that they do not need confidence-boosting victories against elite competition in order to have a successful run in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if that's a concern, but it's definitely something that we have to look at and acknowledge,'' Nets forward Bostjan Nachbar said. ''At the end of the day right now, we're just trying to make the playoffs. We don't care if we win against the good teams or the bad teams. The important thing is that we get those wins that are going to get us into the playoffs, and when the playoffs start that's when we're going to start focusing on beating good teams.''</p>
        <p>On Thursday night, the Nets showed they were no match for great individual talent. LeBron James scored 35 points, imposing his will in the paint. Vince Carter led the Nets with 26 points, but small forward Richard Jefferson's line was most telling of the Nets' inconsistency.</p>
        <p>Jefferson finished with only 5 points and shot 2 of 13 from the field, a game after posting a season-high 35 points. Jefferson also missed two fast-break dunk attempts.</p>
        <p>''Rough night,'' he said. ''It happens.''</p>
        <p>The Nets, who could qualify for the playoffs as early as Friday night when they play the Knicks, have often shrugged off poor games this season, a luxury they will not have once the playoffs arrive. They need either two victories, two Indiana Pacers defeats, or a victory and a Pacers loss to clinch a playoff berth.</p>
        <p>Other than their victory against the struggling Wizards on Tuesday, the Nets' last road victory against a winning team was Jan. 29, when they beat the Utah Jazz on a buzzer-beating 3-pointer by Carter.</p>
        <p>Thursday night's game provided the Nets their final opportunity for a quality road victory before the playoffs. Their final two road games are against the Pacers and the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''We're a below .500 team,'' Jefferson said. ''That, most of the time, means you struggle against teams that are above .500. It doesn't mean we should just sail it in or just quit.''</p>
        <p>Thursday night's game was about over for the Nets after the Cavaliers' tour de force in the third quarter. They made 14 of 17 shots in the third, led by James's 6 of 7, to open up a 21-point lead entering the fourth.</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers (47-32) are caught in a bizarre playoff-positioning situation. They have the same record as the Bulls, the fellow Central Division team they are battling for the No. 2 seed. Because the three division winners are guaranteed one of the top four seeds, the Cavaliers would be seeded fifth if they do not finish with a better record than the Bulls, who hold the tie breaker over Cleveland.</p>
        <p>The fifth-seeded team's path to the conference finals would be decidedly tougher than that of the No. 2 seed.</p>
        <p>The No. 5 team would probably have the play the Miami Heat, the defending champions, in the first round. A victory in that series would probably set up a second-round meeting with Detroit, which has clinched the Central Division.</p>
        <p>Cavaliers center Zydrunas Ilgauskas said he did not think the system was fair.</p>
        <p>''You play so many games, so you should be seeded by your record,'' he said. ''You win your division, you get a banner, you get a T-shirt, that's about as good as you get.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
