<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parise Wastes Little Time in Firing Up the Devils</title>
    <meta content="13devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/sports/hockey/13devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Lightning</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E5D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="605" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parise Wastes Little Time in Firing Up the Devils</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Parise Wastes Little Time in Firing Up the Devils</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils may not have much offensive firepower but they do have Zach Parise. With 31 goals during the regular season, tops on the Devils, he is the type of player a team can lean on. That's exactly what the Devils did Thursday in an imperfect 5-3 victory over Tampa Bay in their Eastern Conference quarterfinals opener.</p>
        <p>The Devils could not contain Tampa Bay's potent pair of Martin St. Louis and Vincent Lecavalier and, getting hit with six penalties, they spent much of the game shorthanded. But two goals from the 22-year-old Parise, including one that snapped a 3-3 tie moments after Lecavalier scored, lifted New Jersey to the victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Zach Parise is the type of player a team can lean on, and he proved that Thursday night by scoring two goals to lead the Devils to a victory in the series opener.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils may not have much offensive firepower but they do have Zach Parise. With 31 goals during the regular season, tops on the Devils, he is the type of player a team can lean on. That's exactly what the Devils did Thursday in an imperfect 5-3 victory over Tampa Bay in their Eastern Conference quarterfinals opener.</p>
        <p>The Devils could not contain Tampa Bay's potent pair of Martin St. Louis and Vincent Lecavalier and, getting hit with six penalties, they spent much of the game shorthanded. But two goals from the 22-year-old Parise, including one that snapped a 3-3 tie moments after Lecavalier scored, lifted New Jersey to the victory.</p>
        <p>''This was a preview of what the Devils have with this kid,'' said the Devils' veteran Scott Gomez. ''He's got the flair for the big time. It just keeps getting better. He's non-stop, always soaking in information. He's a hard worker and he likes the spotlight. He's a special one, there's no doubt about it.''</p>
        <p>Parise's first goal came 7 minutes 43 seconds into the first period and it gave the Devils a 1-0 lead. Less than five minutes later, they scored again. This time, it was the captain, Patrik Elias, who took a pass from Gomez and slipped a slap shot from just beyond the right circle past goaltender Johan Holmqvist, who was making his first N.H.L. playoff start.</p>
        <p>After goals by St. Louis and the Devils' Brian Rafalski, Lecavalier struck twice. The second of his two goals, which came at 2:51 of the third period, tied the game at 3-3 and shifted momentum in Tampa Bay's favor. But Parise came through, scoring just 1:03 later.</p>
        <p>''We've been playing tight games all year,'' Parise said. ''We've done really well when we've had that pressure. There was no panic at all, and I think that shows a lot of the experience we have on the bench.''</p>
        <p>Brian Gionta sealed the victory for the Devils with a goal with just 1:22 left.</p>
        <p>The best-of-seven series continues Saturday at the Meadowlands.</p>
        <p>''Zach has proven what everyone said coming in, that he can be a top-echelon player,'' the Devils' Jamie Langenbrunner said. ''The confidence he played with throughout the season has carried over to the playoffs and that's great to see. It couldn't happen to a better kid.''</p>
        <p>Though the Devils struck first in the series, Thursday's game isn't one they're going to want to use as a blueprint for the rest of the playoffs. Getting into a shootout with Tampa Bay might not be a good idea for a team that scored the fewest goals during the regular season among all the playoff teams.</p>
        <p>''They're good offensively,'' said Devils goalie Martin Brodeur, who turned back 23 shots. ''I don't know what adjustments we're going to make, but we'll definitely look at tapes and see how they exposed us a little bit in our defensive zone and try to be better.''</p>
        <p>It would help to not give Tampa Bay so many power-play opportunities. Parise was among those who picked up a penalty, getting hit with a slashing call while the Devils were clinging to a 4-3 lead.</p>
        <p>''We took too many penalties, there's no question,'' Devils coach Lou Lamoriello said. ''A couple of them were not good penalties. They were the kind of penalties you can't take in this type of series, especially with the type of explosiveness they have.''</p>
        <p>The Devils put on a good show Thursday night, but with 14,495 fans inside Continental Arena, the game was not sold out.</p>
        <p>''The people who were here were outstanding, and that helps tremendously,'' Lamoriello said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
