<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off the Air: The Light Goes Out for Don Imus</title>
    <meta content="13imus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/business/13imus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Msnbc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Imus, Don</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonves, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Jacques</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">MSNBC</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off the Air: The Light Goes Out for Don Imus</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Off the Air: The Light Goes Out for Don Imus</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER and JACQUES STEINBERG; Tina Kelley contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill; Steinberg, Jacques</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>CBS cancels Don Imus's radio program after weeklong controversy over racial and sexual insults made on air; move comes one day after MSNBC cable network cancels television simulcast; pressure had mounted from black leaders and women's groups for references to Rutgers University's women's basketball team as 'nappy-headed hos'; CBS chief executive Leslie Moonves comments; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CBS brought a weeklong confrontation over a racial and sexual insult by the radio host Don Imus to an end yesterday when it canceled the ''Imus in the Morning'' program, effective immediately.</p>
        <p>The move came a day after the cable television network MSNBC, a General Electric unit that has simulcast Mr. Imus's radio program for the last 10 years, removed the show from its morning lineup. The two moves, taken together, mean that Mr. Imus, who has been broadcasting the program for more than 30 years, no longer has a home on either national radio or television.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>CBS yielded to pressure when it canceled “Imus in the Morning,” ending a program that had been broadcasting for more than 30 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CBS brought a weeklong confrontation over a racial and sexual insult by the radio host Don Imus to an end yesterday when it canceled the ''Imus in the Morning'' program, effective immediately.</p>
        <p>The move came a day after the cable television network MSNBC, a General Electric unit that has simulcast Mr. Imus's radio program for the last 10 years, removed the show from its morning lineup. The two moves, taken together, mean that Mr. Imus, who has been broadcasting the program for more than 30 years, no longer has a home on either national radio or television.</p>
        <p>It is possible, though, that he could re-emerge on satellite radio.</p>
        <p>Mr. Imus received the news at home in a telephone call. Many of his listeners learned of it during the afternoon radio show ''Mike and the Mad Dog,'' which announced it on WFAN, the CBS-owned New York station that also carried Mr. Imus's program.</p>
        <p>The CBS chief executive, Leslie Moonves, met yesterday afternoon with the Rev. Al Sharpton and the Rev. Jesse Jackson, leaders in what became a national movement to remove Mr. Imus from the air in the wake of his comments disparaging members of the Rutgers women's basketball team. On April 4, Mr. Imus referred on the air to the Rutgers athletes as ''nappy-headed hos.''</p>
        <p>Both CBS and MSNBC had been under pressure from black leaders and women's groups, then advertisers began abandoning the Imus program and its networks this week, pulling out the financial underpinnings from the show.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Mr. Moonves said: ''Those who have spoken with us the last few days represent people of good will from all segments of our society -- all races, economic groups, men and women alike. In our meetings with concerned groups, there has been much discussion of the effect language like this has on our young people, particularly young women of color trying to make their way in this society.''</p>
        <p>He went on to say, ''That consideration has weighed most heavily on our minds as we made our decision, as have the many e-mails, phone calls and personal discussions we have had with our colleagues across the CBS Corporation and our many other constituencies.''</p>
        <p>The CBS decision came hours before Mr. Imus and the Rutgers basketball team met at the New Jersey governor's mansion in Princeton. The Rutgers group at the meeting included some parents, university adminstrators, and the Rev. DeForest Soaries of the First Baptist Church in Somerset, N.J., where the Rutgers head coach, C. Vivian Stringer, is a parishioner.</p>
        <p>At 10:50 p.m., after three hours, Mr. Imus left without commenting. The Rutgers group stayed about an hour longer. Ms. Stringer spoke for the group before leaving.</p>
        <p>''It was a very productive meeting,'' she said. ''Players, coaches, parents, administrators, the pastor, and Mr. Imus were able to really dialogue. I'm extremely proud of our 10 young basketball players.''</p>
        <p>Asked if Mr. Imus apologized, Ms. Stringer declined to answer. ''We've said as much as we can say tonight.''</p>
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine, who had offered the mansion as a meeting site, was injured in an traffic accident and did not take part.</p>
        <p>Neither of Mr. Imus's employers, however, was willing to wait to see if the meeting would produce anything like a rapprochement.</p>
        <p>CBS and NBC originally announced a two-week suspension for Mr. Imus that was to begin on Monday, but the protests increased as the week went on. They gained momentum first from a news conference by the Rutgers team and then by the recounting of previous episodes when Mr. Imus and his supporting cast engaged in racially charged banter.</p>
        <p>Executives at NBC said the discomfort of staff members and concerns about the network's reputation had influenced the decision to cut ties with Mr. Imus. But it was paying only a license fee to carry the show. CBS Radio and WFAN produced the show and contracted with Mr. Imus as its star.</p>
        <p>CBS also manages Westwood One, the syndicator that has sold the Imus show to other stations around the country. Mr. Imus, 66, was among the most recognizable voices on radio, and commanded a salary estimated at $10 million a year.</p>
        <p>With his longtime base gone, Mr. Imus may well try to turn to satellite radio. But before he can entertain such a possibility, he would presumably have to reach some accommodation with CBS. He recently signed a five-year contract extension.</p>
        <p>Even then, it seems unlikely that he would match his current salary in a fledgling medium with a fraction of the audience of conventional radio, particularly as the two main satellite companies -- Sirius and XM -- try to cut costs in pursuit of a merger. Moreover, with Congress and the Federal Communications Commission reviewing that proposed deal, they may be reluctant to take on a tainted figure like Mr. Imus, who would stir controversy among the regulators who must approve the merger.</p>
        <p>That said, the chief executive of Sirius, Mel Karmazin, is a longtime friend of Mr. Imus and was for many years his boss at Infinity Broadcasting, which later merged with CBS. A Sirius spokesman did not immediately return a call last night seeking comment. An XM spokesman said he had no comment.</p>
        <p>The CBS action on Mr. Imus came on an extraordinary day. For four and a half hours yesterday morning, he turned his radio program into a live fund-raiser for three charities -- two benefiting children with cancer, and the other related to sudden infant death syndrome -- an endeavor he has undertaken each of the last 18 years.</p>
        <p>Among the guests were children and parents who had been beneficiaries of his efforts -- particularly the Imus Cattle Ranch for Kids With Cancer, a program that the host founded at his New Mexico ranch along with his wife, Deirdre.</p>
        <p>Through the broadcast, though, Mr. Imus continually referred to the perilous predicament he was in.</p>
        <p>He strongly suggested, for example, that he believed that his long career on conventional radio, at least, was drawing to a close, which gave the broadcast something of a funereal atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''This may or not be our final radiothon,'' he said, just before 6 a.m. ''But let's say for the sake of being safe that it is.''</p>
        <p>At several points, he lashed out at the ''hypocrisy'' in media coverage of the fallout from his remark.</p>
        <p>He also expressed bitterness that MSNBC had ''pulled the plug'' on televising his program less than 12 hours before the fund-raiser was to begin. ''They got their pound of flesh,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Imus also acknowledged that, ultimately, he alone was to blame for his predicament. ''I said a stupid, idiotic thing that hurt these kids,'' he said of the Rutgers players. ''If I hadn't have said it, we wouldn't be here.''</p>
        <p>As he left his studio in Secaucus, N.J., at midmorning yesterday, the house band he hired for the fund-raiser, led by Levon Helm, serenaded him with ''Hail to the Chief.''</p>
        <p>The radiothon, which continued throughout the day and was to conclude at 10 a.m. Friday, had brought pledges in excess of $1.6 million by 6 p.m. yesterday. In a sign that the attention swirling around Mr. Imus might have actually helped the fund-raiser, donations were running substantially higher than at the same point in previous years, WFAN said.</p>
        <p>In a memo sent to CBS employees announcing Mr. Imus's dismissal, Mr. Moonves said: ''This is about a lot more than Imus. As has been widely pointed out, Imus has been visited by presidents, senators, important authors and journalists from across the political spectrum. He has flourished in a culture that permits a certain level of objectionable expression that hurts and demeans a wide range of people. In taking him off the air, I believe we take an important and necessary step not just in solving a unique problem, but in changing that culture, which extends far beyond the walls of our company.''</p>
        <p>With Mr. Imus now gone from their lineup, CBS Radio and WFAN were under pressure yesterday to find someone to replace him. At least temporarily, WFAN planned to install ''Mike and the Mad Dog,'' a sports talk show, in the morning hours that Mr. Imus had occupied, according to a company executive.</p>
        <p>But the prospect of such added responsibilities did not stop the two hosts -- Mike Francesa and Christopher Russo (the ''Mad Dog'') -- from blistering their employer, CBS Radio, for cutting ties to Mr. Imus in the midst of the fund-raiser.</p>
        <p>''They should know better,'' Mr. Russo said on the air. ''A sophomore in college handles this better.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
