<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dow Fires 2, Citing Talks On a Buyout</title>
    <meta content="13chemical" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/business/13chemical.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dow Chemical Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reinhard, J Pedro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kreinberg, Romeo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liveris, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Dow Chemical Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E5D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dow Fires 2, Citing Talks On a Buyout</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dow Chemical Fires 2, Citing Talks on a Buyout</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH; Michael J. de la Merced contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H; Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Chemical Company fires executives J Pedro Reinhard and Romeo Kreinberg saying they held unauthorized talks with JPMorgan Chase involving potential $52 billion buyout; firings come two days after chief executive Andrew Liveris publicly denies report that company was for sale (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last four months, two senior executives of the Dow Chemical Company held a series of secret meetings with investment bankers and prospective investors about selling the company in a leveraged buyout that would have been worth more than $52 billion.</p>
        <p>There was only one problem: Dow Chemical was never for sale and neither executive, one of whom was on the company's board, had told the company they were trying to put it into play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two senior executives were fired for holding a series of secret meetings about selling the company in a leveraged buyout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the last four months, two senior executives of the Dow Chemical Company held a series of secret meetings with investment bankers and prospective investors about selling the company in a leveraged buyout that would have been worth more than $52 billion.</p>
        <p>There was only one problem: Dow Chemical was never for sale and neither executive, one of whom was on the company's board, had told the company they were trying to put it into play.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Dow Chemical, which had been the subject of a rash of buyout rumors, fired the two executives -- J. Pedro Reinhard, a director and senior adviser to management, and Romeo Kreinberg, an executive vice president -- saying they were ''engaged in business activity that was highly inappropriate'' involving ''unauthorized discussions with third parties about the potential acquisition of the company.''</p>
        <p>The two men did not return calls for comment, but Mr. Kreinberg told The Associated Press that Dow's accusations had no substance.</p>
        <p>The investigation of the director and the dismissals have faint echoes of the situation at Hewlett-Packard last year, when apparently unauthorized news leaks from the board led to a internal investigation of directors and to upheaval at the company.</p>
        <p>The firings also come at a time when deal making is rampant, and many executives and companies have succumbed to the allure of being bought out.</p>
        <p>It is uncertain whether the two executives had hoped simply to put Dow Chemical in play or had sought to be part of the management of an acquired company.</p>
        <p>The move by Dow Chemical came just two days after its chief executive, Andrew Liveris, publicly denied a report in a British newspaper that it was in talks about a sale.</p>
        <p>Frank J. Mitsch, an analyst with BB&amp;T Capital Markets who has covered Dow Chemical for years, said: ''I've never seen anything like this in chemical land: Liveris making all these denials, while unbeknownst to him, two of his own heavy-hitters are holding talks.''</p>
        <p>Shares of Dow Chemical jumped nearly 5 percent on Monday after the report on a possible buyout, only to fall 2 percent on Tuesday's denials, Yesterday, the shares rose 2 percent.</p>
        <p>How Mr. Reinhard, a Dow executive for more than three decades and once considered a contender for the chief executive job, and Mr. Kreinberg, who ran the company's most profitable business, plastics, engaged in covert negotiations over the fate of the company is likely to become a much talked about tale on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>People involved in the discussion said that both men engaged in talks with JPMorgan Chase about the prospect of a buyout and encouraged the bank to seek possible bidders.</p>
        <p>JPMorgan worked on the project for at least a month, running numbers on the business based on public filings and eventually reaching out to several private equity firms including Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company and the Blackstone Group, these people said. The firms held meetings and briefly crunched some numbers, but their interest soon cooled.</p>
        <p>JPMorgan was never formally retained by Dow Chemical to pursue a sale, and it is unclear whether Mr. Reinhard and Mr. Kreinberg represented themselves to the bank as authorized to engage in such preliminary discussions.</p>
        <p>Yet the private talks soon became public on Feb 25, when The Sunday Express reported that three private equity firms -- Kohlberg Kravis, Blackstone and the Carlyle Group -- were ready to bid $54 billion for Dow.</p>
        <p>The report set off a firestorm at Dow Chemical's headquarters in Midland, Mich.</p>
        <p>Mr. Liveris called JPMorgan's chief executive, James Dimon, to find out what was happening, people involved in the discussions said. When Mr. Dimon learned that Mr. Liveris was not interested in a buyout, it stopped work on the project.</p>
        <p>An executive from Blackstone called Mr. Liveris to tell him that the firm was not involved with a buyout proposal.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, however, The Sunday Express ran another report of a possible buyout, this one specifying that Dow Chemical was about to be bought for $50 billion, with much of the money coming from the Middle East, in particular Oman. The company had had enough.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Dow, which usually does not comment publicly on deal speculation, issued a statement denying that it was in play. And on Tuesday, the chief executive, Mr. Liveris, appeared on CNBC to reiterate the denial. Dow also decided that it was time it found out exactly why the talk persisted.</p>
        <p>''This was becoming too disruptive,'' Christopher R. Huntley, a Dow spokesman, said. ''It was unsettling for our employees and for local communities, and the share price volatility was not good for shareholders.''</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Huntley, high-level executives and directors started calling their contacts in the financial world, trying to trace the rumor to its source. One of them struck gold:</p>
        <p>''Someone in a position to know pointed at Romeo and Pedro,'' Mr. Huntley said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reinhard and Mr. Kreinberg did not return repeated phone calls. In a brief conversation with The Associated Press, Mr. Kreinberg said: ''The behavior of the company is very unusual, and the accusations have absolutely no substance and are highly damaging to my reputation after 30 years of employment.''</p>
        <p>Representatives for JPMorgan, Kohlberg Kravis Roberts and Blackstone all declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reinhard will remain on the board until a vote by shareholders, the company said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reinhard is no stranger to deal making, As chief financial officer, he helped engineer a number of the company's deals, notably the $11.6 billion acquisition of Union Carbide in 1999.</p>
        <p>Yet the next year, he was passed over to be the successor to the chief executive, William Stavropoulos, in favor of Michael D. Parker.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Reinhard, 55, and Mr. Kreinberg, 61, spent their entire careers at Dow Chemical and both are natives of Latin America: Mr. Reinhard is from Brazil and Mr. Kreinberg is from Argentina.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kreinberg is a director of Oman Petrochemical Industries, a joint venture Dow formed with the government of Oman and the Oman Oil Company. Mr. Huntley would not say whether the source said the two men had said they were talking with corporate authorization.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
