<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Equality Elusive Under New Jersey Civil Union Law</title>
    <meta content="13civil" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/13/nyregion/13civil.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5D9133FF930A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Equality Elusive Under New Jersey Civil Union Law</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2 Months After New Jersey’s Civil Union Law, Problems Finding True Equality</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nickie Brazier called U.P.S., where she is a driver, to add Heather Aurand to her health insurance the day after their Feb. 22 civil union in New Jersey, knowing it would save them $340 a month. But U.P.S. said no. ''They said it was because we're not married,'' Ms. Brazier recalled.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kevin Slavin was able to sign his partner up for the health plan at the hospital where he specializes in pediatric infectious diseases but soon learned that both men's benefits would be treated as taxable income -- not the case for his married coworkers -- and that his partner could not collect his pension if Dr. Slavin died.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Questions are being raised about whether civil unions for same-sex couples adequately fulfill the promise of the State Supreme Court ruling that led to the arrangements.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nickie Brazier called U.P.S., where she is a driver, to add Heather Aurand to her health insurance the day after their Feb. 22 civil union in New Jersey, knowing it would save them $340 a month. But U.P.S. said no. ''They said it was because we're not married,'' Ms. Brazier recalled.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kevin Slavin was able to sign his partner up for the health plan at the hospital where he specializes in pediatric infectious diseases but soon learned that both men's benefits would be treated as taxable income -- not the case for his married coworkers -- and that his partner could not collect his pension if Dr. Slavin died.</p>
        <p>Merissa Muench of Mount Olive, N.J., said her employer of seven years, a medical sterilization office where she is a technician, told her the company did not cover civil union partners.</p>
        <p>''It just irks me that a guy they just hired, his wife -- bing! -- has health insurance,'' said Ms. Muench, 30, who declined to name her employer for fear of being fired. ''What else does the gay American community have to do to prove that we're worth it just as much as you guys?''</p>
        <p>Nearly two months after New Jersey became the third state to approve civil unions for same-sex couples, many are finding that all partnerships are not created equal, raising questions about whether the new arrangement adequately fulfills the promise of the State Supreme Court ruling that led to it.</p>
        <p>In October, the court declared that the state's Constitution ''guarantees that every statutory right and benefit conferred to heterosexual couples through civil marriage must be made available to committed same-sex couples,'' leaving it to the Legislature to decide how to do it. Lawmakers rejected the option of same-sex marriage, but pledged that ''civil union couples shall have all of the same benefits, protections and responsibilities under law'' that married couples have.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, residents who work for companies headquartered in other states, and those whose insurers are based outside New Jersey, have found it difficult if not impossible to sign their partners up for health insurance. Unions and employers whose self-insured plans are federally regulated have also denied coverage in some cases. Staff members in doctors' offices and emergency rooms have questioned partners' role in decision-making. Confusion abounds over the interplay of state and federal laws governing taxes, inheritance and property.</p>
        <p>Then there are cases like that of the lesbian who was told that she was likely to be denied coverage for a mammogram after she added her partner to her insurance. The insurance company changed the employee's designation to male since there was no spot on its forms for ''civil union spouse.''</p>
        <p>Some 229 couples obtained civil unions in New Jersey in the first month they were available. Gay-rights advocates say they have collected two dozen discrimination complaints, laying the groundwork for a legal challenge to the civil union law that would essentially re-petition the Supreme Court for same-sex marriage. The highest courts in Connecticut, which established civil unions in 2005, and California, where domestic partnerships offer benefits and protections like those provided by civil unions, are already considering similar cases.</p>
        <p>''How can you call it equal protection when you have to go through hell maybe to get your civil union recognized?'' asked Steven Goldstein, chairman of Garden State Equality, a gay-rights group. ''Why should gay couples have to take those steps? That's not equal protection under the law. That's why we're fighting for marriage equality.''</p>
        <p>As Thomas H. Prol, co-chairman of the New Jersey Bar Association's committee on gay issues, put it, ''The word's starting to spread that civil unions aren't working in the real world.''</p>
        <p>State officials attribute many of the problems to unfamiliarity with the civil union law's provisions and its interaction with dozens of state statutes governing matters like adoption, workers' compensation and hospitalization. They said it was far too early to judge the law a failure, and said they would work with couples and companies to resolve problems.</p>
        <p>''This is uncharted territory, and we're talking about an area of undeveloped law,'' said J. Frank Vespa-Papaleo, director of the New Jersey Division on Civil Rights. Told about some of the couples' experiences, he suggested that employers whose health insurance plans were governed by federal laws, for example, should provide civil union couples with the option of signing up with a comparable plan for the same fees.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Wilfredo Caraballo, a Democrat from Essex County who was a lead sponsor of the civil union law, said he was ''frustrated because the intent of the bill is not being met.''</p>
        <p>''We've got a real problem, and the problem is the feds do govern some areas,'' Mr. Caraballo said. ''The truth is there's nothing any of us can do about the federal law. To the extent we can make the law stronger on the state level, I assure you we're trying it.''</p>
        <p>Nathaniel Persily, a law professor at the University of Pennsylvania who has published a study of same-sex marriage and public opinion, said ''these kinds of difficulties were inevitable'' when New Jersey created a parallel institution, noting, ''Whenever there's a sort of spotty civil innovation, it takes civil society some time to catch up.''</p>
        <p>''The state has not sent the clearest signal,'' Professor Persily added. ''The fact that they are given different status under law brings up the possibility that private companies will also treat them differently.''</p>
        <p>In some cases, though, companies have adjusted quickly after receiving complaints from couples or inquiries from their lawyers, or from reporters.</p>
        <p>Timothy Zimmer, a computer programmer who works in Newark for a Massachusetts company he declined to name, said his insurance company, United Healthcare, had told him that his partner would not be covered even if they got a civil union.</p>
        <p>''First, the NJ civil union is not deemed to be a marriage under NJ law,'' the insurer wrote in an e-mail message to him. ''Therefore there is no 'spouse' as defined in the MA plan. The MA law recognizes marriages between members of the same sex only for marriages performed in MA between MA residents. Since the NJ members are not 'married' under either NJ or MA law, there is no 'spouse' eligible for coverage as a dependent.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zimmer, 52, said in an interview last week, ''Apparently the civil union law gave us all the rights of marriage, except the ones we really need.''</p>
        <p>After being contacted by The New York Times, a spokesman for United Healthcare said Monday night that the company had reviewed a bulletin on civil unions from the New Jersey Department of Banking and Insurance, consulted the employer, and decided that civil union partners in New Jersey were the legal equivalent of spouses.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of nice if they do say yes,'' Mr. Zimmer said Tuesday. ''I'm used to the no.'' He was still awaiting word yesterday.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Cookie Van Pelt of Jackson, N.J., who works for Sam's Club, said she was told that her partner, Jean Farr, could not be covered because ''their medical benefits fall under federal law, and they won't change for us.'' But John Simley, a spokesman for Wal-Mart, which operates Sam's Club, said the company allowed employees to choose between a self-insured health plan, which is federally regulated, and a health-maintenance organization that covers civil union partners.</p>
        <p>Such self-insured plans, which are financed by employers rather than purchased from a state-regulated insurer, have caused problems for couples. Since they are governed by the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974, a federal law, insurers and employers often presume that the plans are also subject to the 1996 federal Defense of Marriage Act, which defines marriage as between a man and a woman.</p>
        <p>Sharon Mayhak said she was denied coverage by her partner's employer, which has a self-insured plan, so she remains without insurance despite bad arthritis. (She refused to name the company.)</p>
        <p>''The thing is my partner really likes her job, we are in our 50s, and this is not a good time to look for work,'' Ms. Mayhak said a few weeks after she and her partner of 37 years were joined in a civil union. ''We were told this is supposed to be equal in every way, and this is not equal.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Brazier, the U.P.S. driver -- who gave birth to twins five weeks ago and also has a 2-year-old son -- remains in limbo amid mixed messages from her employer and her union. Norman Black, a spokesman for United Parcel Service, said that the company had offered benefits to domestic partners of its nonunion workers since 2004, but that hourly workers like Ms. Brazier were covered by the Teamsters under a self-insured plan.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Ms. Brazier's union local said its lawyers were looking into whether it could do anything to push U.P.S. to provide partner benefits for its members.</p>
        <p>''It's been a strain,'' said Ms. Aurand, Ms. Brazier's partner. ''We didn't know all the loopholes -- we were sure they'd let us go on.'' But gay-rights advocates said federal law did not prohibit self-insured companies from providing benefits to same-sex couples. A 2006 report by the Human Rights Campaign Foundation found that more than half the Fortune 500 companies, most of which have self-insured plans, offered benefits to domestic partners.</p>
        <p>''It's the employer's own choice to decide who's a beneficiary, and the federal government doesn't prevent employers from doing the right thing,'' said Michele Granda , a staff lawyer with the Boston-based Gay and Lesbian Advocates and Defenders. ''Those employers are purposefully choosing to discriminate against their employees.''</p>
        <p>While health insurance has caused the bulk of the problems so far in New Jersey, civil union couples are also beginning to grapple with the complex interactions of state and federal laws regarding other matters. Civil union partners filing taxes jointly in New Jersey have to file federal tax returns as if they were single, then calculate what they would owe on a joint federal return to figure their state credits and deductions, said Stephen J. Hyland, a lawyer and writer of ''New Jersey Domestic Partners: A Legal Guide.''</p>
        <p>''Civil union couples will most likely be treated as if they are single for purposes of qualifying for Medicaid, which can jeopardize the couple's home if one partner needs nursing home care,'' Mr. Hyland said.</p>
        <p>Bankruptcy is governed by federal law, although state law determines how married and civil union couples hold title to their property.</p>
        <p>Couples who drew up the equivalent of prenuptial agreements before registering as domestic partners may need to update the agreements before getting a civil union, which offers more legal protections, said Felice Londa, a lawyer in Elizabeth, N.J.</p>
        <p>Then there are more immediate, if mundane, matters, like Ms. Londa's frustration while shopping for dresses with her partner of eight years for their May 6 ceremony.</p>
        <p>''We said we're going to have a civil union, and one said, 'Oh, is that some kind of business dinner?' '' she recalled the saleswoman saying. ''Nobody gets it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
