<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whirlwind Before Draft</title>
    <meta content="24meetings" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/football/24meetings.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whirlwind Before Draft</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Whirlwind Before the N.F.L. Draft</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THAYER EVANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Evans, Thayer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After flying more than 5,000 miles over six days last week to visit five N.F.L. teams, the former Arkansas left tackle Tony Ugoh learned something.</p>
        <p>''A lot of flying will wear anybody out,'' said Ugoh, 23, who is listed as 6 feet 5 inches and 305 pounds. ''I handled it, but I thought it'd be a lot easier. You lose a lot of energy flying.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The time between the N.F.L. scouting combine and the draft is critical for teams hoping to screen prospective draft choices, and for players hoping to sell themselves to potential employers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After flying more than 5,000 miles over six days last week to visit five N.F.L. teams, the former Arkansas left tackle Tony Ugoh learned something.</p>
        <p>''A lot of flying will wear anybody out,'' said Ugoh, 23, who is listed as 6 feet 5 inches and 305 pounds. ''I handled it, but I thought it'd be a lot easier. You lose a lot of energy flying.''</p>
        <p>Ugoh also expended a lot of energy visiting the Baltimore Ravens, the Giants, the Kansas City Chiefs, the San Francisco 49ers and the Oakland Raiders in one week. But the journey provided little insight into where he will be selected in the N.F.L. draft this weekend.</p>
        <p>The N.F.L. may seem dormant between the scouting combine in late February and the draft in late April, but those are critical weeks -- for teams hoping to screen prospective draft choices, and for players hoping to sell themselves to potential employers. Players projected to be picked near the top of the draft may visit only a few teams; players like Ugoh, who may be drafted by any number of teams, try to acquaint themselves with as many as possible.</p>
        <p>The visits are arranged and paid for by the teams, which are allowed to meet with a player only once and for no longer than a day, the league spokesman Greg Aiello said. Visits may not include any physical activity, he said, and teams can meet with as many as 30 draft-eligible players. That limit, however, does not apply to players who attended college or high school in the same metropolitan area, or players whose parents reside nearby.</p>
        <p>The process is similar to fraternity rush: Each party can interrogate the other, but the organization ultimately decides who can join. Ugoh and his peers will find out the results this weekend at Radio City Music Hall.</p>
        <p>''No team really wants to show their hand,'' Ugoh said about the signals that he received during his many team visits last week. ''Some of what the teams say about wanting you may be sincere, but some may be a compliment thing.''</p>
        <p>Ugoh is projected to be picked late in the first round or early in the second round. His trip began April 15, a Sunday, with a flight to Baltimore from Bentonville, Ark., and a glimpse of how cut-throat the N.F.L. can be. He had dinner with Ravens scouts and another prospect, then a scout took the two players to the Embassy Suites and told them to be in the lobby at 7:20 the next morning. Right after midnight, the lights in the players' room were off.</p>
        <p>Ugoh said that he set his cellphone alarm for 6:15 a.m., but he slept through it. He awoke at 6:55, only after hearing the other player open the door to leave. ''He was like, 'Nice ring tone,' '' Ugoh said. ''He started giggling and pretty much walked right out of the room. I thought it was kind of messed up that he was going to let me oversleep.''</p>
        <p>Ugoh rushed to the lobby just in time; he did not say another word to the other prospect.</p>
        <p>''That showed me how competitive it is,'' he said. ''I guess we were in direct competition and I didn't know. I wouldn't have figured so. I guess it's every man for himself.''</p>
        <p>Ugoh's flight to New York on April 16 was delayed because of weather conditions, so he took the train to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The night before his visit with the Giants, Ugoh ate dinner that Monday night with his agent, Alan Herman, devouring a 16-ounce T-bone steak, mashed potatoes and broccoli. The next day, April 17, Ugoh shopped at a store for big and tall men, where Herman spent hundreds of dollars on XXXL tall shirts for Ugoh to wear for the rest of his trip. They then met with an accountant, Rosario Ruffino, to discuss Ugoh's financial plan.</p>
        <p>''All we have to do is fill in the numbers once you get drafted,'' Ruffino told Ugoh in Herman's office in Midtown.</p>
        <p>Ugoh was among 20 players who attended a dinner and met with Giants Coach Tom Coughlin and General Manager Jerry Reese that Tuesday night at the Hilton hotel in Hasbrouck Heights, N.J., not far from Giants Stadium. Ugoh is considered a possible draft choice for the Giants because David Diehl has little experience at left tackle, with only two career starts; he is a former guard/right tackle. The Giants have the 20th overall pick and the 19th pick in the second round.</p>
        <p>''I heard Coach Coughlin could be kind of harsh or whatever, but I think he's just really straightforward,'' Ugoh said. ''That's a good thing.''</p>
        <p>During a dinner of fried chicken, barbecue ribs, carrots, potatoes, salad and cheesecake, Ugoh received a white Giants cap and talked with the offensive line coach Pat Flaherty. The next morning, last Wednesday, Ugoh wore a blue short-sleeve shirt, which he purchased the day before to color coordinate with his 8:15 a.m. visit with the Giants.</p>
        <p>After a tour of the team's facilities, Ugoh had individual meetings with a variety of Giants personnel. While with Flaherty, he was asked to diagram on a dry-erase board the responsibility of each offensive lineman for the play known as 4 Counter, the best running play for Arkansas last season. In the 4 Counter, the running back takes a step in one direction, then goes the other way.</p>
        <p>''That stuff is my strong point,'' Ugoh said.</p>
        <p>He flew out of Newark on Wednesday. The next morning, in Kansas City, Mo., Ugoh rose at 6:15 a.m. and put on a red short-sleeve shirt for his visit with the Chiefs, who have the 23rd overall pick. After breakfast at the team's facilities, he was one of 19 players who took a drug test and had his dimensions measured. It took nearly three hours.</p>
        <p>The next stop was San Francisco. After breakfast Friday at the 49ers' headquarters, Ugoh met with a psychologist, whom he previously met at the Senior Bowl in January. Football was not discussed in the hour-long session, he said. ''We talked about relationships with girls, family members and stuff like that,'' Ugoh said. ''She remembered that I like to cook pasta.''</p>
        <p>Ugoh then met for an hour with the offensive line coach George Warhop, who gave him tips on how to improve his vertical steps and how to balance his weight better when changing directions. They also watched tape of a recent 49ers minicamp.</p>
        <p>After a physical examination and lunch, Ugoh waited in the lobby of the 49ers' headquarters for an official from the Oakland Raiders to pick him up. He left San Francisco without having spoken to Coach Mike Nolan or the vice president for player personnel, Scot McCloughan. The 49ers have the 11th pick in the first round and the 10th pick in the second.</p>
        <p>''That was weird,'' Ugoh said. ''They said they were interested.''</p>
        <p>For his visit with Oakland, Ugoh first saw a team doctor for another physical exam. He then traveled another 30 minutes to the Raiders' headquarters and was taken to the team's Hall of Fame room; he was given a small suitcase filled with a jumpsuit, shirts and an Oakland draft-day cap.</p>
        <p>After answering personality questions (in writing), Ugoh met the offensive coordinator Greg Knapp. The assistant offensive line coach James Cregg then reviewed Ugoh's performance in the first quarter of the game Arkansas played against Louisiana State last season.</p>
        <p>A Raiders official then picked up Ugoh to take him to his hotel. On the way out, he met the Raiders' owner, the 77-year-old Al Davis. ''Is this who I think it is?'' Davis said, according to Ugoh. ''Tony Ugoh from Arkansas, right?''</p>
        <p>As Ugoh recalled it: ''I said, 'Yes sir.' I said, 'You're from Brooklyn, right?' He was like, 'Yep, I'm the king of Brooklyn.' We just started laughing.''</p>
        <p>Ugoh and Davis met again later that day. He said Davis told him that the Raiders were ''real interested'' in him. Oakland has the No. 1 pick in the draft as well as the first selection of the second round.</p>
        <p>''He was amazing,'' Ugoh said of Davis. ''He had a great personality and was real fun to talk to.''</p>
        <p>With his visits finished, he flew back to Arkansas on Saturday. He moved out of his apartment over the weekend and is living with his parents this week in Houston.</p>
        <p>Ugoh knows how uncertain draft day can be. But he said that his mind kept drifting back to one team, the Giants. ''They showed me the most love,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ugoh will know Saturday if that was true or not.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
