<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Bronx, a Team Perhaps Thrown Into Panic</title>
    <meta content="24chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/baseball/24chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Torre, Joe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hughes, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rivera, Mariano</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pavano, Carl</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFDD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Bronx, a Team Perhaps Thrown Into Panic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Bronx, a Team Perhaps Thrown Into Panic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's too soon for the Yankees to panic, but I think they need to panic. They need to do something, and panic seems to be as good a something as anything.</p>
        <p>They might have done just that yesterday. Brian Cashman and Joe Torre, cool and calm characters both, are not usually given to panic. But with their pitching in disarray, they may be in the most perilous position of their lengthy Yankees tenures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees have an advantage in that it’s early, and they have a lot of time to correct their pitching problems. But they also have a lot time to intensify their problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's too soon for the Yankees to panic, but I think they need to panic. They need to do something, and panic seems to be as good a something as anything.</p>
        <p>They might have done just that yesterday. Brian Cashman and Joe Torre, cool and calm characters both, are not usually given to panic. But with their pitching in disarray, they may be in the most perilous position of their lengthy Yankees tenures.</p>
        <p>It appeared that they were prepared to be patient and ride out the injuries that will have two starting pitchers on the disabled list, down from four last week, even after Chien-Ming Wang pitches tonight. But yesterday, they scheduled Phil Hughes, their No. 1 pitching prospect, to pitch Thursday night against Toronto at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had planned to leave Hughes, their No. 1 draft choice in 2004, with their top minor league team all season, but you know about the best-laid plans of mice and general managers.</p>
        <p>Amid their pitching problems, the Yankees have an advantage in that it's early, and they have a lot of time to correct and overcome their problems. The disadvantage is that it's early, and the Yankees have a lot of time to intensify and escalate their problems.</p>
        <p>Though the Red Sox' three-game sweep last weekend dropped the Yankees four games behind in the standings, where it remained after last night's games, it should not be compared with the Yankees' five-game sweep of the Red Sox in Boston last August. That shocking event plunged the Red Sox six and a half games behind the Yankees, and the Yankees continued to expand the bulge between them.</p>
        <p>In that series, the Yankees beat Josh Beckett, Curt Schilling and David Wells. In this latest series, the Red Sox beat Jeff Karstens and Chase Wright. By the time the teams play in Boston again, on June 1, the Red Sox probably won't have Karstens and Wright to kick around.</p>
        <p>But boy, was the Yankees' pitching bad in Boston.</p>
        <p>''We're relying on kids to get us through it,'' Cashman said yesterday in a telephone interview. ''I'm proud of how they're taking it out there and not letting it affect them.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees would have been in a dire position if they had played Kansas City, but their decimated pitching staff was no match for the Red Sox. What was really troubling was that the veteran relievers didn't do their jobs.</p>
        <p>It was bad enough that Karstens gave up seven runs in four and a third innings Saturday and that the Red Sox hit four consecutive home runs against Wright on Sunday. But in Friday's game, which Andy Pettitte left in the seventh with the Yankees leading, 5-2, Mike Myers gave up a run, Luis Vizcaíno two and -- egad -- Mariano Rivera two, and Sunday's game turned on a three-run homer against Scott Proctor.</p>
        <p>''It's the domino effect,'' Cashman said of the bullpen's failure. ''We're not getting innings from the starting rotation, and that affects the bullpen. We're looking forward to getting back on line and getting consistent quality starts. It will take some time, but that's the plan.''</p>
        <p>Not all of the bullpen failures can be attributed to overwork. Rivera, for example, had had four days off when he lost to the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>It would be foolish and premature to speculate on the impending demise of Rivera as the game's premier closer, but it will be intriguing to watch Jonathan Papelbon of Boston to see if he is ready to take the orb and scepter from Rivera and supplant him as the closer who clinches championships.</p>
        <p>Papelbon, a 26-year-old right-hander, relieved in four of Boston's last five games before last night, including the last two against the Yankees, securing saves in each game while allowing one hit and no runs in four innings. No one has said anything about his overuse.</p>
        <p>That was the kind of performance that the Yankees used to get routinely from Rivera. They may yet get a retro Rivera, but they will hold their collective breath and cross their fingers when Rivera enters his first game against the Red Sox at Yankee Stadium this weekend.</p>
        <p>As for the Yankees' problems, Cashman preferred to look on the bright side, noting that Wang is due back tonight and that Mike Mussina may be ready for a minor league rehabilitation start as early as Friday. Then there is the $40 million enigma named Carl Pavano.</p>
        <p>''Pavano threw on flat ground in Boston,'' Cashman said. ''He will continue to throw on flat ground in Tampa Bay. We'll take it one step at a time.''</p>
        <p>There is no other way the Yankees can take it with Pavano. One step at a time is better than one injury at a time, which is how they had to take it with him last year.</p>
        <p>During the telephone conversation, Cashman was asked if it was time to panic, then quickly told ''only kidding.''</p>
        <p>''My humor is gone a little bit,'' he replied.</p>
        <p>Then came the Hughes announcement. If it is a panic move, it may be one of several. The first? Torre's decision to bring Rivera into the Boston game Friday night with one out in the eighth inning.</p>
        <p>Torre had said in spring training that he would restrict Rivera to three-out saves. But to stick to that plan, Torre has to trust his other relievers. He has long shown a lack of trust in them (he has used Pettitte twice in relief this season), and he did again in that instance. Incredibly, the calm, cool Torre panicked in the 15th game of the season.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
