<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gonzales's Testimony Satisfied At Least One Person, His Boss</title>
    <meta content="24gonzales" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/washington/24gonzales.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gonzales, Alberto R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE3DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gonzales's Testimony Satisfied At Least One Person, His Boss</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Least the Boss Was Satisfied by Gonzales’s Answers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG and NEIL A. LEWIS; David Johnston contributed reporting.</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush said Monday that the Congressional testimony of Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales last week, roundly panned by members of both parties, had ''increased my confidence in his ability to do the job.''</p>
        <p>Speaking during a short question-and-answer session in the Oval Office, Mr. Bush said of Mr. Gonzales's performance before the Senate Judiciary Committee, ''The attorney general went up and gave a very candid assessment, and answered every question he could possibly answer, honestly answer.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush said that the attorney general’s testimony last week had increased his confidence in him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush said Monday that the Congressional testimony of Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales last week, roundly panned by members of both parties, had ''increased my confidence in his ability to do the job.''</p>
        <p>Speaking during a short question-and-answer session in the Oval Office, Mr. Bush said of Mr. Gonzales's performance before the Senate Judiciary Committee, ''The attorney general went up and gave a very candid assessment, and answered every question he could possibly answer, honestly answer.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has repeatedly asserted his confidence in Mr. Gonzales, a longtime adviser, as criticism has mounted over the dismissals of eight United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>But his statement on Monday was his first direct comment about Mr. Gonzales since the attorney general appeared before the committee, and it was at considerable odds with an overwhelmingly critical assessment of his testimony by members of both parties. It indicated that Mr. Bush, at least for now, has concluded his attorney general can weather the challenge to his leadership at the Justice Department, barring any evidence of wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>That challenge had seemed all the more daunting as of Sunday, when Senator Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, the ranking Republican on the committee whom both sides view as a barometer of support for Mr. Gonzales, appeared on ''Fox News Sunday'' and said, ''The attorney general's testimony was very, very damaging to his own credibility,'' and that his continued tenure was ''bad for the Department of Justice.''</p>
        <p>Asked to comment on Mr. Bush's assessment of Mr. Gonzales's testimony on Monday, Mr. Specter said in a telephone interview, ''I'm not going to get involved in evaluating the president's decision to retain the attorney general.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Specter added, ''I will continue to work with the attorney general as long as he has that position.''</p>
        <p>Several other Republican senators who have been critical of Mr. Gonzales, including Jeff Sessions of Alabama, John E. Sununu of New Hampshire and Tom Coburn of Oklahoma, did not respond to requests for comment on Monday.</p>
        <p>With many lawmakers working in their home districts, it was unclear whether their unresponsiveness was a result of busy schedules or a concerted effort to avoid a running, tit-for-tat debate with the White House over Mr. Gonzales's future.</p>
        <p>One senior Republican Congressional aide at work in Washington on Monday, who requested anonymity to speak candidly, called Mr. Bush's statement that his confidence in Mr. Gonzales had grown after his testimony ''curious''; another senior Republican aide asked, ''Was he watching the same hearing as everyone else?''</p>
        <p>White House officials were confronted Monday with questions about whether Mr. Bush's statements of confidence would ultimately be followed by a resignation, with reporters recalling that Mr. Bush had pledged support for Donald H. Rumsfeld shortly before his ouster as defense secretary. ''He's staying,'' the White House spokeswoman, Dana Perino, said of Mr. Gonzales in one such exchange on Monday morning.</p>
        <p>Later, asked if Mr. Bush had seen all the testimony, Ms. Perino said the president had been traveling but had received updates from aides and had seen some of it on television news reports.</p>
        <p>Pressure to push Mr. Gonzales out is likely to continue. Although Mr. Gonzales has sought to maintain the impression that the country's legal business is going on without interruption, several Justice Department officials say that the attorney general and his advisers have been greatly distracted by the uproar.</p>
        <p>Some administration allies had even voiced optimism last week that Mr. Gonzales would resign and spare Mr. Bush the discomfort of standing by him as support erodes even within his own party.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a news briefing on Monday after announcing an initiative to fight identity theft, Mr. Gonzales indicated he had no such plan.</p>
        <p>''I will stay as long as I can be effective, and I can be effective,'' Mr. Gonzales said in response to questions about his plans.</p>
        <p>He said he ''can't just be focused on the U.S. attorneys situation.''</p>
        <p>''I've also got to be focused on what's important for the American people,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzales said he needed to spend time on his priorities, like combating terrorism, drug abuse and the danger to children from the Internet.</p>
        <p>Emphasizing the point, the White House released a statement late Monday commending Mr. Gonzales and the Federal Trade Commission chairwoman, Deborah Platt Majoras, for their work on identity theft.</p>
        <p>Asked how he knew he was still effective, Mr. Gonzales responded: ''I think a cabinet secretary or the head of an agency every day should wake up and ask themselves that question: Am I still effective in this position? I think that's a question that all of us should ask, every day.''</p>
        <p>''And as long as I think that I can be effective,'' he said, ''and the president believes that I should continue to be at the head of the Department of Justice, I'll continue serving as the attorney general.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzales added, ''I've already indicated that I've made mistakes, and I accept responsibility for that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has said all along that he would leave it to Mr. Gonzales to regain his credibility with Congress. And Mr. Gonzales's testimony was viewed within both parties as a sort of screen test of whether he could remain in his job.</p>
        <p>Members of the Senate committee expressed exasperation as Mr. Gonzales invoked a faulty memory more than 50 times when pressed about his involvement in the removal of the United States attorneys, saying he could not say how the idea of dismissing them originated or remember the details of a late November meeting with senior staff members at which the plan for the dismissals was discussed -- and which he had attended, according to administration documents.</p>
        <p>''If the attorney general's hearing performance increased the president's confidence in his ability to lead the Justice Department, then he's setting the bar fairly low,'' said Senator Patrick J. Leahy, Democrat of Vermont and chairman of the Judiciary Committee, in a statement on Monday.</p>
        <p>He repeated his suspicions that the White House had removed the prosecutors because of partisan concerns that they were either not doing enough to prosecute Democrats on voter fraud charges or going too far in pressing corruption charges against Republicans. The White House denies those accusations.</p>
        <p>In defending Mr. Gonzales, Mr. Bush said the Justice Department was fully within its rights to replace the prosecutors, who serve at the pleasure of the president. And, he and other officials said, after releasing thousands of internal documents and submitting to questioning in the Senate, no evidence of illegality on Mr. Gonzales's part had surfaced.</p>
        <p>''The attorney general broke no law, did no wrongdoing,'' Mr. Bush said. ''And some senators didn't like his explanation, but he answered as honestly as he could. This is an honest, honorable man, in whom I have confidence.''</p>
        <p>Dan Bartlett, the White House counselor, said in an interview that as far as the White House was concerned, the public was not paying much attention to the debate over Mr. Gonzales and that there was ''a disconnect'' between what he termed Washington's fascination with the issue and the public's interest in it.</p>
        <p>''There's no traction with the public because there is no serious allegation of wrongdoing,'' Mr. Bartlett said.</p>
        <p>And, if Mr. Gonzales were to step down,officials argued, it would wrongly lead the public to conclude that he had done something wrong.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
