<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Old Captain For Knicks Going Fishing</title>
    <meta content="24araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/basketball/24araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Orleans Hornets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Orleans Hornets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reed, Willis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Araton, Harvey</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Old Captain For Knicks Going Fishing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Old Knick Captain Is Ready to Go Fishing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It didn't feel like fate phoning, only the New Orleans Hornets. Not initially, not until Gale Reed told her husband, Willis, ''You could go home.''</p>
        <p>''I am home,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>First and foremost, Willis Reed, still the most important catch the Knicks ever made, was always a gentleman. He is retiring as the Hornets’ vice president in June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It didn't feel like fate phoning, only the New Orleans Hornets. Not initially, not until Gale Reed told her husband, Willis, ''You could go home.''</p>
        <p>''I am home,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It was 2003, early summer, and Willis Reed was winding down a basketball career in its fifth decade in a quiet, administrative role for the Knicks, back at Madison Square Garden -- which, in a truth-serum moment, he might admit was the only place he ever wanted to work.</p>
        <p>But the atmosphere wasn't what Reed remembered from the only championship days the franchise has known, with the team deteriorating under the ownership of James L. Dolan and Reed's wife advising him that home is where the heart is, not necessarily where the retired jersey hangs.</p>
        <p>She told him she had spoken to his mother about the offer. ''She'd love to have you back in Louisiana,'' Gale Reed said.</p>
        <p>Reed took the job as the Hornets' vice president for basketball operations. His ailing mother got to enjoy the proximity of her only child for those summer months and into fall. In October, weeks before her 80th birthday, Inell Reed died.</p>
        <p>''I got to spend those last few weeks, and that was a blessing,'' Reed said.</p>
        <p>Was it meant to be for him to make that move, finish up in his native state? Seemed to Reed to be the case, at least until the late summer of 2005, until a wakeup call named Katrina.</p>
        <p>Given the scope of human suffering after a calamitous hurricane, the relocation of a professional basketball franchise is not worth discussing. But it was, for Reed, another personal reminder that life is less about plans than it is about events.</p>
        <p>''You just never know,'' he said in a telephone interview from Oklahoma City, where the Hornets played most of their home games the past two seasons and where Reed is concluding his basketball life this spring.</p>
        <p>Stuff happens, for better or worse and occasionally both. Play with the hand you're dealt, Reed learned at the peak of his athletic prowess when he dribbled left at the free-throw line, tripped over the foot of the Lakers' Wilt Chamberlain and crashed to the Garden floor, writhing in pain.</p>
        <p>It was May 4, 1970, Game 5 of a deadlocked N.B.A. finals. Out of the game with a torn thigh muscle went Reed, with Coach Red Holzman's Knicks trailing by 10, soon by 16. The Knicks stormed back in the second half to win it for their center, their captain, No. 19 in your retired numbers program.</p>
        <p>''When I look back on that season, I think about how Red preached to us how we needed to win every night to get home-court advantage,'' Reed said. ''If we hadn't, and I had gotten injured in Game 5 on the road, there is no way we come back to win that game without the Garden fans.''</p>
        <p>Without the rally, who knows what would have come of the inspirational and historic moment we call Willis Limping Onto The Court?</p>
        <p>One urgent entrance on a leg medicated for the occasion and two opening jump shots signaled a Game 7 rout and defined the man. It produced the memory that Reed said he would cherish most.</p>
        <p>And least? ''Well, you can guess that one,'' he said to someone he knew recalled another unforgettable Garden walk by Reed, out of the building, into the night, after being fired as the coach by the corporate caretaker of the day, Sonny Werblin, 14 games into 1978-79 season.</p>
        <p>Here is where a young tabloid sports journalist, a Knicks fan growing up, intersected with the arc of a legend's postplaying career. He reported from Seattle that Reed, perplexed by rumors about his job security, had commented that the team needed clarity, how it would benefit everyone to know if he was in or he was out.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the back page failed to convey Reed's intentions, or his tone. It was not a challenge; Reed had issued a plea. In a telephone interview at the time, the reporter shared this opinion with Werblin. Days later, Werblin fired Reed, saying at a news conference reintroducing Holzman that he did not accept ultimatums from employees.</p>
        <p>Reed had made the playoffs and won a round in his first season with a team in transition -- Hall of Fame credentials by current standards. He was 6-8 at the time of his dismissal. Would he ever have been as great a coach as he was a warrior? A moot question and not the one I was hoping he would answer.</p>
        <p>People close to Reed had told me long ago that he believed my story gave Werblin the ammunition he was looking for. It was impossible to know if he held a grudge. First and foremost, Reed was always a gentleman, even during more down times with the Nets. He was always a friendly face with a giant paw of a hand outstretched.</p>
        <p>Under such conditions, the time never seemed right to raise the subject, to risk reopening the wound. Not until the other day, with Reed in deep reflection about the winding river we ride.</p>
        <p>''You know what, Sonny had come in wanting to make changes,'' he said. ''He fired other people and he wanted to fire me. So if it didn't happen that day, it would've happened the next week or the next month. I had no control over those circumstances.''</p>
        <p>Once again, stuff happens. Maybe the only part of a professional career that anyone really controls is the time to say, I quit. Asked why now, with the Hornets headed back to New Orleans next season, Reed said he had told them in 2003 that he wanted to retire at 65, which he will turn in June. He had built a house in northwestern Louisiana, near Grambling, where he went to college. He loves the outdoors, and his property has oak trees and squirrels and a couple of streams.</p>
        <p>''Call me in Louisiana,'' he said, ''and my wife will tell you I've gone fishing.''</p>
        <p>Farewell to the captain, still the most important catch the Knicks ever made.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
