<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Killing and Suicide in Houston Is Third Such Shooting in 4 Days</title>
    <meta content="24houston" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/us/24houston.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Houston (Tex)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Balleza, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">thurm, david h</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Houston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Houston (Tex)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DF143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Killing and Suicide in Houston Is Third Such Shooting in 4 Days</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Killing and Suicide in Houston Is Third Such Shooting in 4 Days</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN BALLEZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Balleza, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, April 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David H Thurm, facing eviction from Houston apartment complex, shoots and wounds neighbor and kills apartment manager before killing himself; shooting is third in Houston in four days in which gunman shot someone before committing suicide; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 48-year-old man who was facing eviction from a fashionable apartment complex here shot and killed the manager of the complex on Monday before killing himself.</p>
        <p>The shooting was the third since Friday in which a gunman opened fire on someone else in Houston before committing suicide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A man who was facing eviction from a fashionable apartment complex killed the manager of the complex and then himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 48-year-old man who was facing eviction from a fashionable apartment complex here shot and killed the manager of the complex on Monday before killing himself.</p>
        <p>The shooting was the third since Friday in which a gunman opened fire on someone else in Houston before committing suicide.</p>
        <p>On Friday, a contract employee at the Johnson Space Center killed a supervisor after receiving a critical evaluation and shot himself to death.</p>
        <p>That night, at an apartment complex in northwestern Houston, neighbors reported hearing a couple argue. The police said the gunman, Marco Soto, 33, apparently shot his girlfriend, Maria Aguilar, 40, several times before shooting himself.</p>
        <p>In the shooting on Monday, the police said that shortly after 1 p.m., the man, David H. Thurm, knocked on a neighbor's door and shot through the door, hitting the neighbor two times in the chest before reloading and going to the management office. There, Mr. Thurm opened fire and killed a manager, a spokesman for the police, Victor Senties, said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thurm then struggled with a courier who was in the office before stepping outside and turning the gun on himself. The police said they believed that papers seeking Mr. Thurm's eviction were being drawn up at the time of the shooting.</p>
        <p>The space center shooting also began shortly after 1 p.m. The police said the gunman, William A. Phillips Jr., 60, apparently feared losing his position after a poor review.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillips had received an e-mail message from his employer, Jacobs Engineering of Pasadena, Calif., a subcontractor for the space agency, that cited missed meetings among other problems. He apparently printed out the message two days before buying a handgun, the police said. A copy of the message was found in his lunch bag after the shootings.</p>
        <p>On Friday, he went to lunch with his NASA supervisor, David Beverly, 62, and another man, a spokesman for the agency, James Hartsfield, said. After lunch, Mr. Phillips entered Mr. Beverly's office and shot him twice, Mr. Hartsfield said.</p>
        <p>Another employee, Fran Crenshaw, was in the office during the shooting. Mr. Beverly and Ms. Crenshaw moved a desk against the door. Mr. Phillips returned, pushed into the office and shot Mr. Beverly at least two more times before restraining Ms. Crenshaw with duct tape, Mr. Hartsfield said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
