<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Pays For Driving In Manhattan?</title>
    <meta content="24nyc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/nyregion/24nyc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E5DE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Pays For Driving In Manhattan?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Who Pays for Driving in Manhattan?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To pursue the future, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg had to return to the past. Consciously or not, he went as far back as the first century. In the process, he discovered that it was possible to wow an audience with lines that have been around for 2,000 years.</p>
        <p>History loomed large as the mayor presented his blueprint for an ''environmentally sustainable'' New York over the next quarter century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To pursue the future, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg had to return to the past. Consciously or not, he went as far back as the first century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To pursue the future, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg had to return to the past. Consciously or not, he went as far back as the first century. In the process, he discovered that it was possible to wow an audience with lines that have been around for 2,000 years.</p>
        <p>History loomed large as the mayor presented his blueprint for an ''environmentally sustainable'' New York over the next quarter century.</p>
        <p>As expected, he has both caught grief and heard hosannas for his most contentious proposal: a charge of $8 for cars and $21 for commercial trucks that enter Manhattan below 86th Street during weekday business hours. It's the vaporizer solution: a way to break up congestion, all that traffic choking Manhattan streets.</p>
        <p>For decades, little has modified driving habits that pretty much everyone agrees are wasteful and unhealthful. Many people drive into Manhattan because they prefer to, not because they necessarily have to. Some don't even mind traffic jams. In the age of cellphones and BlackBerries, the car can double as an office during a crawl through Midtown.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg's goal is to nudge these drivers into subways and buses, or force them to pay for refusing to change their ways.</p>
        <p>Some critics have invoked the sort of language typically hauled out for attacks on the billionaire mayor. Two of their favorite phrases are ''Manhattan-centric'' and ''elitist.''</p>
        <p>They are right about the Manhattan-centric part. Until the center of New York commerce moves to another borough, what else could any plan be?</p>
        <p>But elitist? The suggestion seems to be that everyone living south of 86th Street rides in limos and taxicabs. If so, who are all those people we see getting on subway trains and buses every day in Manhattan? And who are all those supposedly poor people driving in from other boroughs who somehow can afford to pay as much as $30 in Midtown garage fees?</p>
        <p>Anticipating criticism, Mr. Bloomberg asked his Sunday audience at the American Museum of Natural History -- granted, a friendly audience -- to travel back in time.</p>
        <p>Where, he asked them, would they have stood in the 1850s on plans for Central Park? Or in the 1890s on a proposal to extend the subways to empty stretches of northern Manhattan? Or in the 1930s on the ''megaproject'' called Rockefeller Center?</p>
        <p>The mayor didn't say so (he didn't have to), but all those projects might well have been shot down had they come along today.</p>
        <p>Central Park's creation displaced 1,600 shantytown residents and led to the demolition of a black settlement known as Seneca Village. Want to bet that if Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux unrolled their park plans today, they would be denounced as elitists -- racist elitists, at that? Rockefeller Center and the subway extension would probably also have gone nowhere in today's climate of ''don't just do something, stand there.''</p>
        <p>Not that there aren't questions about the mayor's proposal.</p>
        <p>For instance, why does the ''congestion pricing'' zone stretch as far north as 86th Street? Previous incarnations of this long-discussed concept put the northern border at 60th Street.</p>
        <p>Are there no ways to make the plan more palatable to New Yorkers living outside Manhattan? A suggestion raised yesterday in a Daily News column by Samuel I. Schwartz, a transportation consultant, is to eliminate existing tolls ''where they don't belong'' -- say, on bridges connecting Queens and the Bronx.</p>
        <p>ALSO, how can we be sure that the city and state will keep providing hundreds of millions of dollars a year for mass transit improvements that City Hall acknowledges are essential for this plan to work? For that matter, there is no guarantee that the $8 and $21 will go exclusively to mass transit, as promised. Think of the state lottery. That money supposedly goes to education. In reality, it is lumped together with other state revenue. You could just as easily say that it pays for prisons and welfare.</p>
        <p>But first comes the question of New Yorkers' will to act. That was the point of the mayor's traipse through history. And whether or not he meant to, he borrowed from Hillel the Elder, a Jewish sage of 2,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>''If I am not for myself, who will be?'' Hillel said. ''If I am only for myself, what am I? And if not now, when?'' Mr. Bloomberg's formulation went this way: ''If we don't act now, when? And if we don't act, who will?''</p>
        <p>That echo across two millenniums earned him the biggest applause of the day.</p>
        <p>NYC E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
