<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scholars and Officials Alike Gather in Schlesinger Tribute</title>
    <meta content="24schlesinger" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scholars and Officials Alike Gather in Schlesinger Tribute</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr. was remembered yesterday as a pre-eminent historian, a lifelong liberal and a father who danced with his daughter and watched Sergeant Bilko with a son.</p>
        <p>At a memorial service in the Great Hall at Cooper Union, in Lower Manhattan, historians, diplomats and a former president mingled with surviving New Frontiersmen of the Kennedy White House to recall the lasting contributions of Mr. Schlesinger, who died on Feb. 28 at the age of 89. The event filled the 900-seat Great Hall, where, as several speakers noted, Abraham Lincoln defined his presidential candidacy in 1860.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr. was remembered yesterday as a pre-eminent historian, a lifelong liberal and a father who danced with his daughter and watched Sergeant Bilko with a son.</p>
        <p>At a memorial service in the Great Hall at Cooper Union, in Lower Manhattan, historians, diplomats and a former president mingled with surviving New Frontiersmen of the Kennedy White House to recall the lasting contributions of Mr. Schlesinger, who died on Feb. 28 at the age of 89. The event filled the 900-seat Great Hall, where, as several speakers noted, Abraham Lincoln defined his presidential candidacy in 1860.</p>
        <p>Among the speakers was the Princeton historian Sean Wilentz, who called Mr. Schlesinger ''the most formidable American historian of his generation.''</p>
        <p>''A great scholar,'' Professor Wilentz said, ''can set the standard about a key period of history. Arthur did so, amazingly, for three: the age of Jackson, the age of Franklin Delano Roosevelt and the thousand days of John Fitzgerald Kennedy.''</p>
        <p>William J. vanden Heuvel, who was an aide to Robert F. Kennedy at the Justice Department, said of Mr. Schlesinger: ''His strength, his optimism, his leadership refreshed the liberal soul in bad times and held it to its highest standards in good. He was an unrepentant New Dealer to the final day of his life. 'The people' mattered. It was their welfare that government was about.''</p>
        <p>His oldest son, Stephen, recalled that Mr. Schlesinger had drawn the children into political luncheons but had also played tennis and watched Sergeant Bilko with him on the old television comedy ''The Phil Silvers Show.'' And the historian's daughter, Christina Schlesinger, said, ''He wasn't called 'the dancing professor' for nothing.''</p>
        <p>Former President Bill Clinton said Mr. Schlesinger's writing had gained from his experience in the arena of politics, which gave him a ''feel for the difficulty of the political enterprise.''</p>
        <p>Senator Edward M. Kennedy said, ''He believed very deeply that a knowledge of history was essential to temper and civilize the use of power.''</p>
        <p>''Arthur,'' Mr. Kennedy said, ''was a beloved friend for decades who wrote history with unsurpassed eloquence and shaped history with unsurpassed wisdom and scholarship.''</p>
        <p>Theodore Sorensen, a Schlesinger colleague on President John F. Kennedy's White House staff, recalled that when Mr. Schlesinger denounced multiculturalism in 1991 in his book ''The Disuniting of America,'' liberals asked, ''What are we going to do with Arthur?'' Now, Mr. Sorensen said, they ask, ''What are we going to do without Arthur?''</p>
        <p>In her talk, Christina Schlesinger said that to the end, her father argued that James Buchanan, occupant of the White House just before the Civil War, was a worse president than George W. Bush. But that, she said, ''was on a good day'' for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Schlesinger numbered some Republicans as well as Democrats among his friends. Another speaker was former Secretary of State Henry A. Kissinger, who said he was always indebted to Mr. Schlesinger. Mr. Kissinger said that in 1955, when he was a new instructor at Harvard, Mr. Schlesinger, by then a tenured professor, took a memo that Mr. Kissinger had written on nuclear strategy and, unbeknown to him, sent it to the journal Foreign Affairs, which had Mr. Kissinger turn it into his first published article.</p>
        <p>He called Mr. Schlesinger ''a solicitous friend'' who never let their later political differences affect their ties.</p>
        <p>The British historian Hugh Thomas called Mr. Schlesinger ''a liberal who laughed,'' and others recalled those moments.</p>
        <p>Wearing a bow tie in tribute to Mr. Schlesinger's unswerving style in neckwear, Mr. Kennedy spoke of the time in 1962 when, during his first run for the Senate, a Harvard law professor, Mark A. DeWolfe Howe, denounced him as having no qualification beyond ambition.</p>
        <p>''Relax, Mark,'' Mr. Schlesinger said, ''Ted's a candidate for the United States Senate, not the faculty of Harvard Law School.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton recalled that Mr. Schlesinger had asked him to write a biography of Lincoln for a series Mr. Schlesinger edited. When Mr. Clinton protested that he had just signed a big contract to do his own memoir, Mr. Schlesinger replied, ''Lincoln is a better story, and it's shorter.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
