<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Shared World View And Its High Costs</title>
    <meta content="24kaku" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/books/24kaku.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Nixon and Kissinger (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E3D6173EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Shared World View And Its High Costs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nixon and Kissinger</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nixon and Kissinger  Partners in Power  By Robert Dallek  Illustrated. 740 pages. HarperCollins. $32.50.</p>
        <p>The current war in Iraq is mentioned only once in Robert Dallek's engrossing new book, ''Nixon and Kissinger,'' and yet the reader cannot help regarding his account of the Nixon White House and its handling of the Vietnam War as a kind of parable about the presidency of George W. Bush and its determination to stay the course in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One cannot help regarding his account of the Nixon White House and its handling of the Vietnam War as a kind of parable about the presidency of George W. Bush and its determination to stay the course in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nixon and Kissinger  Partners in Power  By Robert Dallek  Illustrated. 740 pages. HarperCollins. $32.50.</p>
        <p>The current war in Iraq is mentioned only once in Robert Dallek's engrossing new book, ''Nixon and Kissinger,'' and yet the reader cannot help regarding his account of the Nixon White House and its handling of the Vietnam War as a kind of parable about the presidency of George W. Bush and its determination to stay the course in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Dallek seems to have taken up the much-written-about subject of Richard M. Nixon and his national security adviser (and later secretary of state) Henry A. Kissinger with just this sort of subtext in mind, for he ends his preface with this observation: ''Arguments about the wisdom of the war in Iraq and how to end U.S. involvement there, relations with China and Russia, what to do about enduring Mideast tensions between Israelis and Arabs, and the advantages and disadvantages of an imperial presidency can, I believe, be usefully considered in the context of a fresh look at Nixon and Kissinger and the power they wielded for good and ill.''</p>
        <p>Though much of the Nixon White House's copious tape and paper trail has been available for years and books by insiders like H. R. Haldeman, Nixon's chief of staff, have minutely chronicled the Jacobean atmosphere that thrived in that embattled White House, Mr. Dallek has shrewdly drawn upon recently declassified archives, including transcripts of Mr. Kissinger's phone calls and the papers of Alexander M. Haig Jr., Mr. Kissinger's deputy on the National Security Council and later Nixon's chief of staff.</p>
        <p>And while his book leans heavily at times on the work of earlier authors -- most notably Richard Reeves's gripping 2001 account of the Nixon presidency (''President Nixon: Alone in the White House''), Walter Isaacson's incisive 1992 biography of Mr. Kissinger (''Kissinger'') and David Greenberg's fascinating 2003 deconstruction of Nixon's image (''Nixon's Shadow'') -- he has succeeded in drawing a compelling portrait of the two men while analyzing the momentous consequences their foreign policy decisions had on America and the world.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Dallek has done, and done remarkably deftly, in this volume is focus on the relationship between the two men, and the ways in which their personal traits -- their drive, their paranoia and their hunger for power and control -- affected their performance in office and informed their foreign policy decisions. Each was given to impugning the other's emotional stability: President Nixon would ask his aide John Ehrlichman to talk to Mr. Kissinger about getting therapy, while Mr. Kissinger would frequently refer to his boss as ''that madman,'' ''our drunken friend'' and ''the meatball mind.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, the two men had more than a little in common, including tumultuous childhoods that left them painfully insecure and a self-serving grandiosity that made them feel they could rationalize dubious means to achieve their ends.</p>
        <p>Both men saw themselves as foreign policy realists, yet their missteps would be compared by analysts and pundits to the missteps made by neoconservative ideologues in the Bush administration. In both cases, there was a drive to expand executive power. In both cases there was a distrust of the foreign policy elite, which led to policy-making outside the usual channels and a circumvention of experts at the State Department and the C.I.A. In both cases there was a growing isolation at the White House as increasingly unpopular wars ground on. And in both cases there were huge ambitions to recast world affairs.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Dallek argues that the Nixon-Kissinger ''reach for distinction'' had its positive effects, spurring the opening to China and détente with the Soviet Union, he forcefully makes the point that their ambition and arrogance ''skewed their judgments and produced terrible decisions in dealings with Vietnam, India-Pakistan, and Chile.'' Nixon's determination to run foreign policy out of the White House meant that Congress and State Department analysts were often cut out of the loop on important decisions. Nixon, for instance, ordered the massive bombing campaign against Hanoi and Haiphong in December 1972, while Congress was in recess for the Christmas break, telling Mr. Kissinger that ''one of the beauties of doing it now'' is ''we don't have the problem of having to consult with Congress.''</p>
        <p>Despite growing antiwar sentiment and the president's own declining poll numbers, despite warnings from commanders on the ground that ''the war had become a bottomless pit,'' Nixon and Mr. Kissinger, Mr. Dallek says, ''clung to the conviction that they could use military pressure to force the North Vietnamese into an agreement that would deliver an autonomous South Vietnam -- peace with honor.'' They blamed the press for presenting a pessimistic view of the war and insisted that ''Vietnamization'' was working, while Nixon continued to assert that an American withdrawal from Vietnam would shred the country's credibility -- that it would suffer ''a blow from which it will never recover.''</p>
        <p>Worse, the Nixon administration continued the war -- and expanded it into Cambodia, which destabilized that nation, brought the Khmer Rouge to power and led to the annihilation of some two million people under their rule -- when it had ample evidence that the war was unwinnable. In fact, as early as 1966, Mr. Dallek writes, two visits to Vietnam left Mr. Kissinger ''convinced that a U.S. military victory was out of reach.'' Their determination to ''stay the course'' until Saigon could supposedly stand on its own, Mr. Dallek argues, was in part ''the product of political cynicism'':</p>
        <p>''The domestic political consequences of a collapse were a primary consideration. They hung back from leaving Vietnam until the 1972 elections were behind them. As Kissinger had warned Haldeman when Nixon considered ending U.S. involvement by the close of 1971, turmoil in South Vietnam in 1972 might play havoc with Nixon's return to the White House.''</p>
        <p>The ceasefire the United States finally reached with North Vietnam in 1973 was not appreciably different from one that could have been reached four years earlier -- and came at a cost of thousands more American lives, countless Vietnamese deaths, the expansion of the war into Cambodia and Laos, and an increasingly divided nation at home.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Dallek points out, Nixon would try to use his initiatives with China and the Soviet Union to distract attention from the failures in Vietnam -- just as, later, he would try to use them to distract attention from his growing problems with Watergate.</p>
        <p>''Nixon's use of foreign affairs to overcome impeachment threats in 1973-1974 are a disturbing part of the administration's history,'' Mr. Dallek writes. ''Its impact on foreign policy deserves particular consideration, as does the more extensive use of international relations to serve domestic political goals throughout Nixon's presidency. Nixon's competence to lead the country during his impeachment crisis also requires the closest possible scrutiny.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Kissinger would later recall that by October 1973, ''Nixon no longer had the time or nervous energy to give consistent leadership,'' the secretary of state would continue to promote the fiction that the president was in charge during the Yom Kippur War. Mr. Dallek suggests that Mr. Kissinger ''would have done well to atleast consult with other cabinet members about suspending the president's authority under the Constitution's 25th Amendment''; such a move, he writes, would ''have signaled Kissinger's greater concern with the national well-being than with Nixon's survival.'' But ''as the inner workings of Nixon's presidency amply demonstrate, Kissinger was as much the partisan supporter of a highly imperfect administration as he was its foreign policy expert serving the national security.''</p>
        <p>After leaving office in disgrace in 1974, Nixon would spend the remainder of his life trying to rehabilitate his reputation -- and, to a large degree, would succeed. At his funeral in 1994, he was praised for his doggedness and political savvy, and eulogized as a visionary foreign policy maker who helped end the cold war.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kissinger has continued to write a succession of books, spinning his own reputation and his record in the Nixon administration. Last year Tony Snow, the White House press secretary, said that Mr. Kissinger had been quietly advising President Bush, supporting ''the overall thrust and direction of the administration policy'' in Iraq.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
