<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Breast Cancer Not Linked To Abortion, Study Says</title>
    <meta content="24canc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/health/24canc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Breast Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pregnancy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4D6173EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Breast Cancer Not Linked To Abortion, Study Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Breast Cancer Not Linked to Abortion, Study Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS BAKALAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bakalar, Nicholas</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is no association between abortion and an increased risk for breast cancer, scientists reported yesterday in a large study.</p>
        <p>There has been considerable debate over whether abortion, induced or spontaneous, is linked to breast cancer -- a debate that may intensify with last week's 5-4 Supreme Court ruling, which suggested that an abortion procedure could be banned if it posed a risk to a woman's health.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The study tracked women prospectively to see if those who reported having abortions were more likely to develop breast cancer in the future and found that they were not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is no association between abortion and an increased risk for breast cancer, scientists reported yesterday in a large study.</p>
        <p>There has been considerable debate over whether abortion, induced or spontaneous, is linked to breast cancer -- a debate that may intensify with last week's 5-4 Supreme Court ruling, which suggested that an abortion procedure could be banned if it posed a risk to a woman's health.</p>
        <p>The possibility of such a link has been suggested by some retrospective studies -- that is, studies that looked for a history of abortion in women who had already been given a diagnosis of breast cancer.</p>
        <p>But such studies are subject to error caused by inaccurate reporting. Because of personal sensitivities and the stigma associated with the operation, healthy women may be reluctant to reveal that they have had an abortion, while those with breast cancer, seeking a cause for their illness, are more likely to report one.</p>
        <p>This study, published in The Archives of Internal Medicine, tracked women prospectively to see if those who reported having abortions were more likely to develop breast cancer in the future. They were not.</p>
        <p>''There are still some states that require women to be informed about the risk of breast cancer if they get an abortion,'' said Karin Michels, the lead author and an associate professor of epidemiology at Harvard. ''I think that may not be justified based on the current evidence.''</p>
        <p>Researchers studied 105,716 women enrolled in a study designed to examine associations between lifestyle and disease. The women were 29 to 46 years old at the beginning of the study in 1993, and 93 percent were premenopausal.</p>
        <p>Initially, the women responded to a questionnaire about abortion, with 16,118 saying that they had had one or more induced abortions and 21,753 reporting one or more spontaneous abortions. The researchers collected data on breast cancer risk factors beginning in 1989, updating them every other year through 2003. There were 1,458 newly diagnosed cases of breast cancer during the study period.</p>
        <p>The scientists found no difference in breast cancer incidence between the women who had had spontaneous or induced abortions and those who had not. Breast cancer incidence did not differ among women who had had an induced or spontaneous abortion before or after their first birth, or who had had no abortion at all.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the authors write, it is well established that a full-term pregnancy before age 35 does reduce the long-term risk for breast cancer. So it might be said that a pregnant woman who aborts increases her risk for breast cancer compared with what it would be if she carried the pregnancy to full term.</p>
        <p>Joel Brind, a professor of biology and endocrinology at Baruch College in Manhattan, found fault with the ways in which the study reported the data. Rather than reporting all of the abortions, he said, the researchers should have analyzed only those that occurred earliest in the study, allowing enough time after the abortion for breast cancer to develop.</p>
        <p>''I see no reason why this study would change my opinion that having an abortion increases the risk about 30 percent over not having gotten pregnant in the first place,'' Dr. Brind said. ''I believe also that this particular study, were the data properly handled and reported, would have come up with a result in agreement with that.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Michels said that most of the abortions occurred more than 10 years before the breast cancer diagnosis, and that analyzing only the earliest abortions made no difference in the results. But she acknowledged that Dr. Brind raised a crucial issue.</p>
        <p>''In analyzing data,'' she said, ''we have to be careful what we are comparing and take account of whether a woman who has had an induced abortion misses out on the potential benefit she would have had if she had a full-term pregnancy.</p>
        <p>''We did analyze the data keeping this issue in mind,'' Dr. Michels said, ''and we did not find that an incomplete pregnancy deprives a woman of the protection a full-term pregnancy would have conferred.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
