<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Northeaster's Wake Come Appeals for U.S. Disaster Aid</title>
    <meta content="24fema" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/nyregion/24fema.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Emergency Management Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1DF143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Northeaster's Wake Come Appeals for U.S. Disaster Aid</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Northeaster’s Wake Come Appeals for U.S. Disaster Aid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <dateline>BOUND BROOK, N.J., April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As residents and business owners pulled soggy wallboard and ruined furniture out into the sun on Monday, state and federal officials in New Jersey and New York toured towns hardest hit by last week's northeaster to try to determine whether federal aid would be available to them.</p>
        <p>Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey said that New Jersey had suffered $180 million in damage to private and public property in what he called the second-worst rainstorm in the state's history. To underscore the extent of the damage, he came here to the train station, which has been closed since heavy rains swelled the Raritan River last week and put many streets under water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey said that New Jersey had suffered $180 million in damage in what he called the second-worst rainstorm in the state’s history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As residents and business owners pulled soggy wallboard and ruined furniture out into the sun on Monday, state and federal officials in New Jersey and New York toured towns hardest hit by last week's northeaster to try to determine whether federal aid would be available to them.</p>
        <p>Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey said that New Jersey had suffered $180 million in damage to private and public property in what he called the second-worst rainstorm in the state's history. To underscore the extent of the damage, he came here to the train station, which has been closed since heavy rains swelled the Raritan River last week and put many streets under water.</p>
        <p>R. David Paulison, administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, who accompanied Mr. Codey, said that he had wanted to see the destruction for himself to make a comprehensive case to President Bush about the damage. And he assured officials that the request would be considered in ''days, not weeks.''</p>
        <p>Last week Mr. Codey asked President Bush to declare several regions of New Jersey -- including parts of Bergen, Burlington, Essex, Hudson, Middlesex, Morris, Passaic, Somerset and Union Counties -- disaster areas to qualify for federal aid .</p>
        <p>Accompanied by the state's two United States senators, Frank R. Lautenberg and Robert Menendez, and Representative Mike Ferguson, Mr. Codey recounted the flood's toll: 40,000 people without power, 3,000 evacuated from their homes, and 1,400 residents forced to flee to shelters. In addition, three deaths were attributed to the heavy rains.</p>
        <p>He warned that ''the biggest challenge lies ahead of us,'' and urged people affected by the flooding to call 211 or to sign on to 222.nj211.org.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lautenberg said he planned to speak to the Senate Appropriations Committee about the need for $30 million to speed on a flood prevention program, but he said the president's budget included only $10 million..</p>
        <p>In response to appeals from merchants, who unlike homeowners do not receive federal emergency funds, Mr. Codey raised the possibility of a bond issue to buy out businesses that have been damaged by multiple floods.</p>
        <p>In New York, Mr. Paulison began his tour of the flood-ravaged areas on Monday in Mamaroneck, in Westchester County, where he met with Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, homeowners and the minister of the First Baptist Church, which was heavily damaged by floodwaters.</p>
        <p>The county executive, Andrew J. Spano, Representative Nita M. Lowey and Senator Clinton said they planned to start a charity for flood victims while they awaited word on whether 12 counties in New York State -- including Westchester, Nassau, Suffolk and all of New York City -- would be declared a disaster area.</p>
        <p>Preliminary assessments indicated that New York State sustained about $36 million in storm damage.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, Philip Mikan, of the state Department of Emergency Management and Homeland Security, said additional days were needed before an official estimate of damages could be made.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
