<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</title>
    <meta content="24dvd" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/movies/homevideo/24dvd.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Critics Choice"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Welles, Orson</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Renoir, Jean</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D6173EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Choice: New DVD's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New DVDs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jane Eyre</p>
        <p>Without Orson Welles, Twentieth Century Fox's 1944 version of ''Jane Eyre'' would probably join the other literary adaptations Fox is releasing on DVD this week -- ''Anna Karenina'' (1948), and a double bill of the 1935 and 1952 versions of ''Les Misérables'' -- somewhere on a back shelf in high school libraries, to be shown whenever an English teacher feels like taking an afternoon off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orson Welles dominates the 1944 version of “Jane Eyre” and a low-priced, high-quality Jean Renoir collection brings the director’s lesser-known work to the forefront.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jane Eyre</p>
        <p>Without Orson Welles, Twentieth Century Fox's 1944 version of ''Jane Eyre'' would probably join the other literary adaptations Fox is releasing on DVD this week -- ''Anna Karenina'' (1948), and a double bill of the 1935 and 1952 versions of ''Les Misérables'' -- somewhere on a back shelf in high school libraries, to be shown whenever an English teacher feels like taking an afternoon off.</p>
        <p>But with Welles as the stormy Mr. Rochester, this movie becomes something different: something suffused with his personality and legend. Although this ''Jane Eyre'' is signed by the director Robert Stevenson, and Welles never made any authorial claims to it, generations of Welles scholars have found his fingerprints all over the film. Mr. Stevenson was a competent and at times superior craftsman, but the forced perspectives, exaggerated camera angles and meticulous attention to sound cannot be found in many of his other movies, like ''Mary Poppins'' (1964), to cite but one perhaps unfair example.</p>
        <p>By the time Welles appeared in this film, he had already adapted this Brontë novel twice for radio: in 1938 for ''The Mercury Theater on the Air'' and in 1940 for ''The Campbell Playhouse.'' (Only the Campbell version survives.) And the screenplay, attributed to John Houseman, Aldous Huxley and Mr. Stevenson, is structured like a radio program, with a central narrator -- Joan Fontaine as Jane -- reading long expository passages from the book and actors stepping in to interpret crucial scenes.</p>
        <p>Add to that a score by Welles's regular collaborator Bernard Herrmann; a central set designed by the architect William Pereira that bears a powerful resemblance to Charles Foster Kane's digs; and the presence of Mercury players like Agnes Moorehead and Erskine Sanford, and the case for ''Jane Eyre'' as a Welles film in disguise seems all but closed.</p>
        <p>Welles gave ''Jane Eyre'' everything, it seems, except his genius. His first Hollywood film after his RKO contract came to a calamitous end, it is the work of someone playing it safe and sitting on his best instincts. Ms. Fontaine, effortlessly able to enlist the audience's deepest sympathy when working for Alfred Hitchcock (''Rebecca'') or Max Ophuls (''Letter From an Unknown Woman''), here seems merely meek and recessive. And who wouldn't be, confronted by a Welles fitted out with elevator shoes and one of the worst rubber noses in his large collection?</p>
        <p>As critics at the time pointed out, Welles seems to be playing Emily Brontë's thundering Heathcliff rather than her sister Charlotte's downtrodden Rochester, completely overpowering poor Jane. Mr. Stevenson -- or Welles, or the cinematographer George Barnes, or whoever was calling the shots -- tries to make it up to Ms. Fontaine by framing her in tight, tremulous close-ups, and much of the movie consists of her looking beseechingly into the camera, pleading for an understanding that never comes.</p>
        <p>Still this well-produced disc has much to recommend it, including two world-class villains, played by Ms. Moorehead and the incomparably snide Henry Daniell, and a startling appearance by an unbilled, very young Elizabeth Taylor, her perfect adult face perched on a tiny body, as Jane's one childhood friend.</p>
        <p>There are two commentary tracks, one by Joseph McBride (a Welles biographer) and Margaret O'Brien, the former child star who appears in the film as Rochester's coquettish ward, and another by the film historians Nick Redman, Steven Smith and Julie Kirgo.</p>
        <p>An isolated music track lets Mr. Herrmann's string-based score, one of his most emotionally wide-ranging, stand on its own. (Fox Home Video, $19.98, not rated.)</p>
        <p>Jean Renoir  3-Disc Collector's Edition</p>
        <p>This is certainly the DVD bargain of the year so far: five features and two shorts by Jean Renoir, one of the movies' genuine masters, presented in first-class restorations for the preposterous list price of $29.98 (much less from discount sellers). As Lionsgate did with its recent set of early Hitchcock films, it has leased the definitive versions of these titles from Canal Plus, the French rights holder, fitted them out with subtitles and offered them to the unwashed American masses for a fraction of the price the individual discs go for in France.</p>
        <p>Lesser-known work from the Renoir canon, these films are drawn principally from the very beginning of his career and the very end. ''Whirlpool of Fate'' (known less melodramatically in French as ''La Fille de l'Eau'') is his first solo film (he was co-director of one before this), released in 1925 as a vehicle for his wife at the time, a pouty Gloria Swanson imitator named Catherine Hessling.</p>
        <p>Fittingly, the first shot of the first true Renoir film is of flowing water; it was an image to which he would repeatedly return, as if unconsciously, symbolizing the continuity of life and movement beyond the edges of his films' frame. Renoir followed ''Whirlpool of Fate'' with a large-budget production of ''Nana,'' the Zola novel set in a 19th-century Paris in which the theater merges with prostitution, and the city's biggest star (Ms. Hessling again) is also its most notorious courtesan. And so was born Renoir's second-most-characteristic theme: the notion of life as theater, as a continuous performance in which the greatest risk lies in stepping out of character.</p>
        <p>Disc 2 contains two experimental shorts, ''Charleston Parade'' (1927) and ''The Little Match Girl'' (1928), as well as Renoir's only real epic, ''La Marseillaise'' (1938), a populist (or, more accurately, Popular Front) account of the French Revolution that was financed by public subscription.</p>
        <p>Disc 3 skips to the later years, with the 1959 television production ''Le Testament du Docteur Cordelier'' (here called ''The Doctor's Horrible Experiment''), a free-handed interpretation of ''Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde'' starring the mime Jean-Louis Barrault (''Children of Paradise'').</p>
        <p>The final film is the deceptively casual ''Elusive Corporal'' (1962), a surprisingly lighthearted return to the setting of ''La Grande Illusion,'' a German prisoner-of-war camp (though it is World War II rather than World War I). Jean-Pierre Cassel, who died last week, plays the French officer whose repeated attempts to escape give him the same symbolic standing as Renoir's beloved water imagery. He is that which can't be contained -- life, sexuality, the passing of time -- and in the film's last scene, he stands alone and contemplates the Seine. (Not rated.)</p>
        <p>Also Out Today</p>
        <p>PLANET EARTH: THE COMPLETE BBC SERIES -- David Attenborough narrates an 11-part BBC tour of the world in a box set that includes 90 minutes not shown on American television. (BBC Warner, $79.98, not rated.)</p>
        <p>NIGHT AT THE MUSEUM -- Ben Stiller is a night guard at a museum much like the American Museum of Natural History, where the exhibitions come to life after hours. With Dick Van Dyke, Mickey Rooney and Robin Williams; directed by Shawn Levy. (Fox, $29.98, PG.)</p>
        <p>THE QUEEN -- Helen Mirren's Oscar-winning performance as the long-suffering Elizabeth II, as directed by Stephen Frears. (Miramax, $29.99, PG-13.)</p>
        <p>Dave Kehr  Critics Choice</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
