<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Composers Near and Far, Speaking a Language of Now</title>
    <meta content="24juil" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/arts/music/24juil.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Juilliard Ensemble</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6D6173EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="404" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Composers Near and Far, Speaking a Language of Now</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Composers Near and Far, Speaking a Language of Now</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Contemporary composition dropped in on the New Juilliard Ensemble for one of its regular check-ups on Friday, and Joel Sachs's young musicians played music by five far-flung composers at Alice Tully Hall. Represented (in order of appearance) were Finland, Iceland, Ireland, Tajikistan and the United States.</p>
        <p>Musical hearts still seem to be beating with regularity, although not one of these pieces was really compatible with any of its neighbors on the program. The hard-nosed, post-Schoenberg atonality so much in fashion during the two decades after World War II was pursued by only one of Friday's composers, Farangis Nurulla-Khoja, who came to Canada from Tajikistan by way of Sweden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five far-flung composers at Alice Tully Hall on Friday performed contemporary works that all seemed to be exercises in instrumental hedonism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Contemporary composition dropped in on the New Juilliard Ensemble for one of its regular check-ups on Friday, and Joel Sachs's young musicians played music by five far-flung composers at Alice Tully Hall. Represented (in order of appearance) were Finland, Iceland, Ireland, Tajikistan and the United States.</p>
        <p>Musical hearts still seem to be beating with regularity, although not one of these pieces was really compatible with any of its neighbors on the program. The hard-nosed, post-Schoenberg atonality so much in fashion during the two decades after World War II was pursued by only one of Friday's composers, Farangis Nurulla-Khoja, who came to Canada from Tajikistan by way of Sweden.</p>
        <p>His work, ''La Devinette d'Arlequin,'' seemed less the riddle of its title than a busy, marchlike exercise in calculated harshness -- an impression multiplied by the instrumental hedonism pursued by most everyone else on Friday.</p>
        <p>Seppo Pohjola's ''Liebelei'' (literally, ''Flirtation'' in German) was one basis for comparison: its rumbling and persistent bass line operated underneath successions of chirping winds and slow chords. With its deep rising scale passages, ''Liebelei'' behaved much like an old-fashioned chaconne.</p>
        <p>Snorri Sigfus Birgisson's ''Drift of Melancholy'' offered luscious orchestrations to three settings of poems by Mary Jo Salter. Charlotte Dobbs sang them with an attractive young soprano voice, but given vocal lines of considerable blandness, she found herself swamped by the sheer luxury of Mr. Birgisson's strings, winds, harp and mallet percussion. Could it be that the Finnish Mr. Pohjola and the Icelander Mr. Birgisson are just cold-weather souls dreaming of lusher vegetation?</p>
        <p>Raymond J. Lustig's ''Trashed: Images From a Sunken City'' remembers the plight of New Orleans with a generous mini-encyclopedia of American musical culture, high and low. Fragments of jazz float intermittently by, and there is a brief, hymnlike episode for strings; deafening eruptions of drums and percussion rise up.</p>
        <p>None of these pieces drew from the past in the time-honored ways, but Gerald Barry's ''Lisbon'' seemed, historically speaking, more freestanding than most. Sheltered from the classical tradition and fortified by exposure to Irish folklore, ''Lisbon'' is happily oblivious to the niceties of the avant-garde. It begins with brisk melody in unison, gives the bass drum a few whacks, and indulges in long, stuck-in-the-record-groove repetitions. Think of folk music that has had a few too many.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sachs assembled this collection of music and conducted it with his customary enterprise. Benjamin Smith was the pianist in ''Lisbon.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
