<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woman Says Church Aide Pressured Her Into Sex at 15</title>
    <meta content="24church" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/nyregion/24church.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woman Says Church Aide Pressured Her Into Sex at 15</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Woman Says Church Aide Pressured Her Into Sex at 15</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He was 25, and she was 15. He was the director of the church youth ministry; she was a faithful member. He singled her out for special attention and told her that it was ''God's plan'' that they have sex, she testified in court on Monday.</p>
        <p>The testimony was the first time the girl, now 23, publicly told her story of how she was controlled and abused by Matthew Maiello, now 33, when he was the director of the rock Mass and of the youth ministry at St. Raphael's Roman Catholic Church in East Meadow in the late 1990s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Matthew Maiello, who has served time for statutory rape, singled her out for special attention and told her that it was “God’s plan” that they have sex, she testified in court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He was 25, and she was 15. He was the director of the church youth ministry; she was a faithful member. He singled her out for special attention and told her that it was ''God's plan'' that they have sex, she testified in court on Monday.</p>
        <p>The testimony was the first time the girl, now 23, publicly told her story of how she was controlled and abused by Matthew Maiello, now 33, when he was the director of the rock Mass and of the youth ministry at St. Raphael's Roman Catholic Church in East Meadow in the late 1990s.</p>
        <p>In 2003, Mr. Maiello pleaded guilty to the statutory rape of her and three other teenagers and served two years in prison. Now she and another victim are suing him; the parish; its pastor, the Rev. Thomas Haggerty; and the Diocese of Rockville Centre.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maiello beat down her defenses by saying that he loved her and invoking God, the woman testified in a multimillion-dollar civil suit in State Supreme Court here. But Mr. Maiello also warned that he had Mafia connections and threatened to kill her and hurt her family if she told on him, she said.</p>
        <p>When she resisted sex, Mr. Maiello told her it was all right because they were going to marry, she said. But then he pressured her into repeated group sex with a 15-year-old boy and even videotaped some encounters, she said.</p>
        <p>''It was very overwhelming,'' she testified, when Mr. Maiello started pressuring her. Before then she had only kissed and held hands with a boyfriend, she said. She looked like a young adolescent in a photo from that year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maiello had sex with her many days a week, as often as four times a day, on gym mats, in closets and on pews, she testified.</p>
        <p>''I didn't like what he was doing,'' she testified, recalling physical pain and bleeding from certain acts. ''It made me feel disgusting and dirty,'' she said. ''I felt like he prostituted me.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Maiello ''told me if I loved him and wanted to make him happy, I had to do this,'' she testified. ''He told me it was God's plan, that God brought us together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maiello praised her singing and rewarded her with favored roles in youth shows, she said.</p>
        <p>But he was also violent and ''controlled everything I did'' so that ''I was like a puppet,'' she said. He isolated her from friends and forced her to abandon her dream of becoming a pediatrician to devote more time to him, she said. He dictated what clothes she wore and exactly how she shampooed and required her to take his neckties home to memorize his smell, she said. Now the scent of his cologne causes disturbing flashbacks ''and my heart pounds,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maiello gave her marijuana and beer, which she said she had never used before. ''It stripped my inhibitions from me,'' she said.</p>
        <p>His routine was to signal her on a beeper, then she rode her bike to St. Raphael's, parked it by the convent and went down to his basement office. Despite many visits and a rule that he not be alone with a youth, no one checked on them, she said.</p>
        <p>Through most of her testimony, the woman was somber and spoke firmly. But she broke down a few times. One of her lawyers, Ben Rubinowitz, showed a poster-size photo of a dark blue couch with a floral print in Mr. Maiello's office and asked, ''Is this the couch you lost your virginity on?'' As she said yes, her face reddened and contorted and she buried her head in her clenched hands, sobbing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maiello was so charming that he insinuated himself ''as a member of my family,'' she testified. When her mother developed breast cancer, her father consulted with Mr. Maiello first, then together they told the daughter. She testified that Mr. Maiello treated her to ''Jesus Christ, Superstar'' on Broadway, but made her leave early so they could have sex and still get home on time.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Maiello left the church to teach at a Catholic high school, he stayed in touch and turned her SAT preparation into a sex game, she testified. Wrong answers were penalized by stripping and having sex, she said. He dressed her in red lingerie and a Catholic school girl's uniform, she said.</p>
        <p>Eventually she reported Mr. Maiello to the police, resulting in his prosecution.</p>
        <p>The abuse has caused her to suffer depression and suicidal urges and impaired family and romantic relationships, she said. She has tried to become a teacher but cannot because of anxieties over child abuse, she said.</p>
        <p>''I don't trust anyone,'' she testified. She also said, ''I don't believe in God any more.'' The abuse occupies her mind every day and causes harrowing nightmares, she said. The night before, she woke up in a sweat from a nightmare in which Mr. Maiello ''was in a car and trying to shoot me,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The woman said she wished it would all go away. ''Most of all, I want to say my life is my own,'' she testified.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
