<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In U.S. Absence, States Take Lead in Student Loan Cases</title>
    <meta content="24loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/education/24loans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Missouri</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillon, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In U.S. Absence, States Take Lead in Student Loan Cases</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In U.S. Absence, States Take Lead in Student Loan Cases</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dillon, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State attorneys general nationwide are stepping up their scrutiny of college lending practices in absence of federal enforcement action, following pattern that experts say has prevailed in some other major consumer investigations in recent years; Illinois and Missouri announce concessions by universities (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State attorneys general around the country are stepping up their scrutiny of college lending practices in the absence of federal enforcement action, following a pattern that experts say has prevailed in some other major consumer investigations in recent years.</p>
        <p>Yesterday the attorneys general of Illinois and Missouri announced that as a result of investigations into lending practices at three major universities in those states, the universities had agreed to adopt a code of conduct to guide their relations with student lenders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attorneys general around the country are stepping up their scrutiny of college lending practices in the absence of federal enforcement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State attorneys general around the country are stepping up their scrutiny of college lending practices in the absence of federal enforcement action, following a pattern that experts say has prevailed in some other major consumer investigations in recent years.</p>
        <p>Yesterday the attorneys general of Illinois and Missouri announced that as a result of investigations into lending practices at three major universities in those states, the universities had agreed to adopt a code of conduct to guide their relations with student lenders.</p>
        <p>The code will be modeled on one developed by Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo of New York, who has been looking into student loan practices for months and who said in an interview that similar investigative efforts were snowballing around the country.</p>
        <p>''I think we've reached a tipping point,'' Mr. Cuomo said.</p>
        <p>The state-by-state regulatory action, so far limited largely to efforts by Democrats, comes at a time of little progress in the development of federal rules on lenders' dealings with colleges. A bid by the Education Department to negotiate such rules collapsed on Friday in disagreement among representatives of colleges, banks and other groups.</p>
        <p>Education Secretary Margaret Spellings, aides say, now plans to form a task force that will recommend federal rules, which would govern lender gifts to colleges and university officials, how colleges refer students to lenders and how to prevent lenders' misuse of a national student data system.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Spellings is in danger of being overtaken both by Congress, which is considering new legislation, and by the attorneys general.</p>
        <p>In announcing the new agreements in their states, the Illinois and Missouri attorneys general said Mr. Cuomo had shared with them information derived from New York's inquiry. And Mr. Cuomo said he was sharing information with the attorneys general of ''dozens of other states.''</p>
        <p>James E. Tierney, a former Maine attorney general who is director of the National State Attorney General program at Columbia University, said that in coming months the country would most likely see an increasing number of states investigating lending practices at the nation's thousands of universities.</p>
        <p>Professor Tierney said the actions by attorneys general had precedent in some major past cases. Among them is the one that led to an agreement last year by the Ameriquest Mortgage Company, accused of predatory lending practices, to pay $325 million and make changes to its policies. The agreement settled investigations by attorneys general in more than two dozen states.</p>
        <p>In addition to the attorneys general in New York, Missouri and Illinois, those in California, Connecticut, Minnesota and Ohio have announced in recent days that they are investigating student lending practices. Last week 40 attorneys general, or their aides, participated in a conference call with Mr. Cuomo, arranged by the National Association of Attorneys General to discuss the student lending issue, said Angelita Plemmer, a spokeswoman for the association.</p>
        <p>Nebraska's attorney general reached a settlement with the Nebraska-based lender Nelnet last week, based on his review of the company's own internal inquiry. But Mr. Cuomo says he is continuing his Nelnet investigation.</p>
        <p>Yesterday the spotlight was on Illinois and Missouri. Attorney General Lisa Madigan of Illinois announced that she had reached settlements with DeVry University and the Career Education Corporation, two for-profit higher education providers based in her state. Both universities agreed to abide by a code of conduct that prohibits student loan companies from paying colleges for loan volume and bars university officials from receiving payments from lenders.</p>
        <p>DeVry, with 50,000 students at 84 campuses, will return to students the $88,122 that it received from Citibank after the university put that lender on its preferred lending list for students seeking private loans, which are not guaranteed by the federal government. DeVry no longer maintains a relationship with Citibank as a preferred lender.</p>
        <p>Career Education, with about 90,000 students on 80 campuses in the United States and overseas as well as online, received a total of $21,200 from Wachovia and Sallie Mae, both of which were on its preferred lender list. The company has agreed to donate the money to a fund that will inform the public about student loans, Attorney General Madigan said.</p>
        <p>In Missouri, Attorney General Jeremiah W. Nixon said that an investigation of Washington University in St. Louis had found that the university signed an agreement in April 2005 with Education Finance Partners, a lender based in California, that included a revenue-sharing provision. The university ended the agreement with the lender in March 2006 and never received any money.</p>
        <p>The university denied any wrongdoing but agreed to abide in the future by a code of conduct, according to a settlement document signed yesterday by Mr. Nixon and a vice chancellor at Washington University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
