<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine, Condition Upgraded, Leaves Intensive Care</title>
    <meta content="24corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/nyregion/24corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine, Condition Upgraded, Leaves Intensive Care</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gov. Corzine Is Moved From Intensive Care</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI and LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David; Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 10 days in critical condition with severe chest injuries he suffered in a car crash, Gov. Jon S. Corzine was moved out of intensive care late Monday afternoon and upgraded to stable condition, his doctors at Cooper University Hospital here said.</p>
        <p>The doctors and Mr. Corzine's aides said he was alert, sitting up in bed and able to chat with friends, staff members and doctors about issues ranging from the schedule for his rehabilitation, which is expected to take months, to the war in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey will remain in the hospital for at least a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 10 days in critical condition with severe chest injuries he suffered in a car crash, Gov. Jon S. Corzine was moved out of intensive care late Monday afternoon and upgraded to stable condition, his doctors at Cooper University Hospital here said.</p>
        <p>The doctors and Mr. Corzine's aides said he was alert, sitting up in bed and able to chat with friends, staff members and doctors about issues ranging from the schedule for his rehabilitation, which is expected to take months, to the war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>But he remains on heavy pain medication -- now delivered orally and through a skin patch rather than intravenously -- he fatigues easily and he will remain in the hospital for at least another week, according to Dr. Steven E. Ross, head of the trauma division at the hospital.</p>
        <p>''I would suggest that he's not going to go back to being governor if he's on sufficient medications to make him groggy,'' Dr. Ross said at a news conference, noting that he, like other doctors, advises patients on such narcotics not to drive or operate heavy machinery because the drugs can impair judgment.</p>
        <p>Tom Shea, the governor's chief of staff, said Mr. Corzine would not resume his official duties until some time after he is released from the hospital. Richard J. Codey, a fellow Democrat who is president of the State Senate, has been acting governor since the April 12 accident when the Chevrolet Suburban Mr. Corzine was riding in, moving at 91 miles per hour with emergency lights flashing, collided with another car and then slammed into a guardrail on the Garden State Parkway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea said that Mr. Corzine did not appear to remember details of the crash, in which he fractured his sternum, 11 ribs and left thigh bone, or of his first week in intensive care, during which he underwent three operations on his leg and relied on a ventilator to breathe.</p>
        <p>But over the last day, said Mr. Shea, the governor asked about the state budget, a proposal to sell the New Jersey Turnpike and other political issues, appearing eager to get back to work.</p>
        <p>In giving an upbeat assessment of the progress that Mr. Corzine, 60, has made, his doctors said he was making a speedier recovery than would be expected even of a younger person and was suffering much less pain than they would have anticipated for someone with such extensive injuries.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ross said that Mr. Corzine had his first good night's sleep Sunday, since day and night often merge in intensive care units, where bright lights are left on.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Dr. Ross said, the governor resumed eating a regular diet, asking for a cheeseburger and a chocolate milk shake (which were promptly delivered).</p>
        <p>With the removal of a feeding tube and a tube that connected Mr. Corzine to a mechanical ventilator, he can now speak. But Mr. Shea and Dr. Ross said they had not pressed him to say much.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea said that Mr. Corzine was not available for questions from reporters, because the governor was not yet ready to talk to people who would ''parse his every word and try to beat him over the head with it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine was described as reading newspapers, watching television and inquiring about New Jersey professional basketball and hockey teams in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea said that Mr. Corzine was sitting up in bed with his arms clasped behind his head and was in surprisingly good spirits.</p>
        <p>''He is not as grouchy as you would expect him to be,'' Mr. Shea said. ''He is fairly even-keeled.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ross said that the doctors and nurses had not detected any evidence that Mr. Corzine had become depressed after the accident and while in the intensive care unit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine is receiving antibiotics to treat a possible infection of his trachea, or windpipe. His doctors were concerned that the breathing tube had irritated the inner lining of his respiratory system and that he had been coughing up thick sputum.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine has not had a significant fever, and his white blood cell count has given no indication of serious infection, the doctors reported.</p>
        <p>''He is still coughing, but the antibiotics are doing their job,'' Dr. Ross said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert F. Ostrum, Cooper's head of orthopedics and the surgeon who operated on Mr. Corzine's broken left femur, or thigh bone, said that the wound was healing well and did ''not hurt that much.'' The governor can bend his left knee 30 degrees, ''which is impressive,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The doctors said it was too early to tell when Mr. Corzine would regain his strength, which in part will determine his fitness to return to work and the approach to his rehabilitation schedule. He tires easily, which Dr. Ross said is normal for someone in his condition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea said it had not been determined whether Mr. Corzine would go from the hospital to an inpatient rehabilitation center or receive therapy at Drumthwacket, the governor's official residence, in Princeton.</p>
        <p>For now, though, Mr. Corzine cannot even get himself out of bed to sit in a chair, something Dr. Ostrum said would be a milestone. The doctors said they hoped Mr. Corzine could sit upright for an hour or two later this week. ''That would be a big deal,'' Dr. Ostrum said.</p>
        <p>When he gains enough strength to walk, Mr. Corzine is expected to use forearm crutches because standard crutches could be painful and possibly aggravate his injured ribs, Dr. Ostrum said.</p>
        <p>Given the long rehabilitation ahead for Mr. Corzine and the demands of the governorship, Dr. Ross said his patient had to be careful that undue stress did not undermine his recovery.</p>
        <p>''It could if we let him go back too soon,'' Dr. Ross said. ''It is our goal to assure that he is ready for that stress at the time he goes back. That is our advice.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
