<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Obama, in Foreign Policy Speech, Urges U.S. Leadership</title>
    <meta content="24obama" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/us/politics/24obama.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HEADING TOWARD 2008"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obama, Barack (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zeleny, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">International Monetary Fund</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE4DF143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Obama, in Foreign Policy Speech, Urges U.S. Leadership</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Obama Outlines His Foreign Policy Views</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF ZELENY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zeleny, Jeff</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic presidential hopeful Sen Barack Obama, in speech to Chicago Council on Global Affairs, presents himself as candidate 'who can speak directly' to world; outlines his approach to foreign policy, vowing to double foreign aid, expand and modernize military, and rebuild fractured alliances; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Presenting himself as a presidential candidate ''who can speak directly to the world,'' Senator Barack Obama on Monday outlined his approach to foreign policy, vowing to double foreign aid, expand and modernize the military, and rebuild fractured alliances.</p>
        <p>In a speech before the Chicago Council on Global Affairs, Mr. Obama combined a harsh critique of the Bush administration with a call for the United States to resist the temptation to turn inward. A robust engagement in world affairs, he said, will help reduce the threat of terrorism and repair what he characterized as the nation's bruised image across the globe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The senator said that America must repair its standing in the world and resist the temptation to turn inward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Presenting himself as a presidential candidate ''who can speak directly to the world,'' Senator Barack Obama on Monday outlined his approach to foreign policy, vowing to double foreign aid, expand and modernize the military, and rebuild fractured alliances.</p>
        <p>In a speech before the Chicago Council on Global Affairs, Mr. Obama combined a harsh critique of the Bush administration with a call for the United States to resist the temptation to turn inward. A robust engagement in world affairs, he said, will help reduce the threat of terrorism and repair what he characterized as the nation's bruised image across the globe.</p>
        <p>''America cannot meet the threats of this century alone, but the world cannot meet them without America,'' Mr. Obama said. ''We must neither retreat from the world nor try to bully it into submission -- we must lead the world, by deed and example.''</p>
        <p>It was the first of several policy speeches that Mr. Obama, Democrat of Illinois, is to deliver in coming weeks as he works to define his candidacy with specific proposals to pursue if elected. He likened today's challenges to those facing the United States after World War II, saying that building a similar pattern of diplomatic and economic alliances could strengthen the nation's hand.</p>
        <p>As a first-term senator, Mr. Obama faces the challenge of convincing voters that he has the experience necessary to lead the nation in wartime. He renewed his call for most American combat brigades to be withdrawn from Iraq by March 31, 2008, but he spoke more broadly of what he described as a need for the United States to use its influence around the world in ways that extend beyond the use of force.</p>
        <p>His foreign policy, he said, would more closely resemble the ''burden sharing'' the first President Bush employed during the Persian Gulf war than the current administration's approach.</p>
        <p>''No president should ever hesitate to use force -- unilaterally if necessary -- to protect ourselves and our vital interests when we are attacked or imminently threatened,'' Mr. Obama said. ''But when we use force in situations other than self-defense, we should make every effort to garner the clear support and participation of others.''</p>
        <p>In the opening three months of the race, Mr. Obama has solidified his role as one of the leading contenders for the Democratic nomination, raising more money than any of his rivals for the primary campaign and drawing tens of thousands of admirers to rallies across the nation. But Mr. Obama is also striving to expand his appeal beyond that of a best-selling author and political celebrity as he tackles questions of substance and policy.</p>
        <p>''This election offers us the chance to turn the page and open a new chapter in American leadership,'' Mr. Obama said. ''This is going to require a new spirit, not of bluster and bombast, but of quiet confidence and sober intelligence, a spirit of care and renewed competence.''</p>
        <p>Lisa Miller, a spokeswoman for the Republican National Committee, dismissed the criticism.</p>
        <p>''Senator Obama started his career with a tone of hope but has quickly turned to one of blame,'' Ms. Miller said. ''Obama has no foreign policy experience, therefore has no record of having done anything -- wrong or otherwise.''</p>
        <p>In his 40-minute address, Mr. Obama did not dwell on his own biography, including his father's family from Africa, or that he spent part of his childhood living abroad. But his speech was punctuated with examples of his global travels and the underlying subtext that his world view was shaped differently from other candidates in the presidential race.</p>
        <p>If elected, he said, he would double foreign aid to $50 billion by 2012, which would be the final year of his first term.</p>
        <p>''I know that many Americans are skeptical about the value of foreign aid today,'' Mr. Obama said. ''A relatively small investment in these fragile states up front can be one of the most effective ways to prevent the terror and strife that is far more costly both in lives and treasure to the United States down the road.''</p>
        <p>The United States also must build a 21st-century military, Mr. Obama said, in addition to ''showing wisdom in how we deploy it.'' He called for expanding ground forces, adding 65,000 soldiers to the Army and 27,000 to the Marines. Less than 1 percent of the military can speak foreign languages like Arabic, Mandarin or Korean, he said, calling for additional training and recruitment to address the problem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama said he would lead an effort to secure nuclear stockpiles and materials across the world within four years.</p>
        <p>To prevent countries from building weapons programs, Mr. Obama endorsed the concept of an international nuclear fuel bank, proposed last year by former Senator Sam Nunn, who now advises the Nuclear Threat Initiative. As president, Mr. Obama said he would provide $50 million to get the fuel bank started and urge Russia and other countries to join.</p>
        <p>''The American moment has not passed,'' Mr. Obama said. ''The American moment is here. And like generations before us, we will seize that moment and begin the world anew.''</p>
        <p>HEADING TOWARD 2008</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
