<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers to Face Sabres. That's Buffalo, Right?</title>
    <meta content="24rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/hockey/24rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Weekes, Kevin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jagr, Jaromir</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Shanahan, Brendan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0DF143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers to Face Sabres. That's Buffalo, Right?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers to Face Sabres. That’s Buffalo, Right?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Rangers staged a practice finally knowing who their second-round playoff opponent would be, they had to dig deep into their memories to begin preparing for Buffalo. They have not played the Sabres since Dec. 1.</p>
        <p>A bizarre gap in the N.H.L. schedule has created an Eastern Conference semifinal series between strangers. Introductions may be necessary when the teams play Game 1 on Wednesday night in Buffalo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A bizarre gap in the N.H.L. schedule has created an Eastern Conference semifinal series between strangers. The Rangers play the Sabres in Game 1 on Wednesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Rangers staged a practice finally knowing who their second-round playoff opponent would be, they had to dig deep into their memories to begin preparing for Buffalo. They have not played the Sabres since Dec. 1.</p>
        <p>A bizarre gap in the N.H.L. schedule has created an Eastern Conference semifinal series between strangers. Introductions may be necessary when the teams play Game 1 on Wednesday night in Buffalo.</p>
        <p>In their four meetings this season, the Rangers were 0-1-3.</p>
        <p>''I don't remember the games,'' Rangers goalie Henrik Lundqvist said. ''But when the playoffs start, it's almost like you play a different team. Even though you didn't win, it doesn't matter when you step into the playoffs. It's almost like two new teams.''</p>
        <p>Because of the way the season progressed, this series will feature one new team. The Rangers of late April look little like the team that lost four times to Buffalo in their first 26 games of the season.</p>
        <p>The Sabres charged to the front of the standings in October, tying an N.H.L. record by winning their first 10 games. The Rangers sputtered through the first half, hitting the stride that carried them to the playoffs in February.</p>
        <p>The Sabres finished the regular season with the best record in the N.H.L. The Rangers' late surge made them the No. 6 seed in the conference.</p>
        <p>The Rangers are more than happy to hoist the underdog flag again for this series. They waved it heartily before playing Atlanta in the first round, which they turned into a four-game sweep. But they are also showing signs of confidence.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if they're the cream of the crop right now,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said of the Sabres. ''They're certainly one of eight teams left, and a good one. I'm not going to suggest I don't want to give them credit, but we're where we are because we belong here, too.</p>
        <p>''One thing I will say is we are a different team than we were three months ago. Buffalo is what they are. Maybe we're a little less familiar to them than they are to us. They are a good team. I'm not going to take anything away from them, but I'm not going to pump their tires, either.''</p>
        <p>The Sabres had only a slightly tougher time with their first-round opponent than the Rangers did, eliminating the Islanders in five games.</p>
        <p>The regular-season meetings between the Rangers and the Sabres have an ancient-history feel. In the first meeting, on Oct. 14, the Rangers battled a snowstorm, arrived in Buffalo the day of the game and lost, 7-4. Their next two meetings, Nov. 5 and Nov. 26, went to overtime. Their meeting Dec. 1 was decided in a shootout.</p>
        <p>In three of the four games, the backup goalie Kevin Weekes made the start. Lundqvist appeared only in a 3-2 loss in overtime Nov. 26 at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>The experience was enough for the Rangers to appreciate the Sabres' speed and firepower. In their first two meetings, the Rangers allowed two-goal leads to evaporate.</p>
        <p>''They're really good at creating chances.'' Lundqvist said. ''You have to manage the puck against them because every time you lose the puck, they just go. If you're not playing smart, you can have three-on-ones and probably four-on-ones because they come so hard.''</p>
        <p>Before the Rangers adopted their current style -- with forwards backchecking as a matter of habit and an all-around commitment to defense -- they left opponents frequent opportunities for game-breaking rushes.</p>
        <p>''I think we played a wide-open game early in the season, and you cannot play a wide-open game against Buffalo,'' Rangers forward Jaromir Jagr said. ''You cannot leave a big gap between forwards and defense because you have to pass the puck through the three forwards, and that is very dangerous because you get odd-man rushes.''</p>
        <p>The Sabres led the league with 308 goals in the regular season, 20 more than the Ottawa Senators, who had the second-highest total. The Rangers allowed 216 goals, the second-lowest total in the Eastern Conference, behind only the Devils.</p>
        <p>Part of the Rangers' defensive tactic is to spend more time on offense. Atlanta had so much trouble scoring in the first round because the Rangers dominated possession.</p>
        <p>''You have to expect you're going to feel pressure,'' forward Brendan Shanahan said. ''You're going to be under pressure from these guys because of the style they play. It's a matter of dealing with it and turning some attack on them as well.</p>
        <p>''You just can't spend the whole series defending.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers may, however, spend part of the series reacquainting themselves.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
