<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Candidates in France Focus on Centrist Voters</title>
    <meta content="24france" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/world/europe/24france.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bayrou, Francois</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Royal, Segolene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Royal, Segolene</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E6DF143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Candidates in France Focus on Centrist Voters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Candidates in France Focus on Centrist Voters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>French presidential campaign enters new phase as winners of first round, Nicolas Sarkozy on right and Segolene Royal on left, start battle for 6.8 million voters who chose centrist Francois Bayrou, with more than 18 percent of vote; Sarkozy and Royal together garnered 57 percent of vote; Bayrou declines to endorse either for now; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The French presidential race is on -- for the vote of the center.</p>
        <p>The campaign entered a new phase on Monday, as the winners of the first round, Nicolas Sarkozy on the right and Ségolène Royal on the left, began a battle for the 6.8 million voters who chose the path down the middle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nicolas Sarkozy and Ségolène Royal are battling for France’s political center in the second round of the country’s presidential elections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The French presidential race is on -- for the vote of the center.</p>
        <p>The campaign entered a new phase on Monday, as the winners of the first round, Nicolas Sarkozy on the right and Ségolène Royal on the left, began a battle for the 6.8 million voters who chose the path down the middle.</p>
        <p>Taken together, the two winners scooped up 57 percent of the vote in the first round on Sunday. But François Bayrou, the legislator and farmer who heads the centrist Union for French Democracy, came in a strong third with more than 18 percent of the vote, and those votes are up for grabs.</p>
        <p>''The voters of the center control the election,'' said Stéphane Rozès, a director of the CSA polling institute. ''The challenge is not knowing where they will go.''</p>
        <p>At a rally in the city of Dijon, in eastern France, on Monday, Mr. Sarkozy set aside his law-and-order persona and portrayed himself as ''the candidate of openness'' whose message was for ''all the French people.''</p>
        <p>''Openness of spirit is being able to take into consideration the positions of others, the ability to think that others might be right,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Royal, who had rejected proposals from fellow Socialists to join forces with Mr. Bayrou before the first round, reached out to him across party lines to say she was ready for a dialogue.</p>
        <p>''It is my responsibility to make this overture,'' she said at a rally in the city of Valence, in southern France. ''I'm awaiting a response.''</p>
        <p>She added that she was ''launching an appeal beyond the left to all'' who denounced the system during the campaign.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bayrou said on Sunday night that he would not endorse either candidate at the moment.</p>
        <p>''If you listened carefully to what I said earlier, you'll see I want to keep my independence,'' he told reporters.</p>
        <p>He was upbeat in his concession speech on Sunday night, insisting that his message of conciliation instead of traditional party infighting had resonated among voters. ''There is finally a center in France, a large center, a strong center, an independent center capable of speaking and acting beyond previous borders,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bayrou's share of the vote this time was more than two-and-a-half times what he received in the first round of the presidential election in 2002, when he received less than seven percent. Instead of endorsing either candidate, he may prefer to position his party for the strongest showing possible for parliamentary elections, which come in June.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bayrou's party has had an odd history. Created in 1978 by Valéry Giscard d'Estaing during his presidency, it united Christian Democrats and liberals, and was meant to serve as an alternative to the Rally for the Republic party that Jacques Chirac founded two years earlier when he was running for mayor of Paris.</p>
        <p>Then in 2002, Mr. Chirac created the much larger Union for a Popular Movement, or UMP. He lured to his camp many of Mr. Bayrou's deputies in Parliament and severely weakened his party in the process.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chirac's former prime minister, Jean-Pierre Raffarin, and the current foreign minister, Philippe Douste-Blazy, were once members of Mr. Bayrou's party. It typically has voted with the governing UMP in Parliament.</p>
        <p>In the campaign, Mr. Bayrou, trying to break the classic left-right party divide in politics, offered to worked with the big Socialist and UMP parties. He even floated the idea of selecting a member of one of those parties as his prime minister. Both camps rejected the idea.</p>
        <p>Then Michel Rocard, a former Socialist prime minister, proposed an alliance with Mr. Bayrou before the first round as the most efficient way to defeat Mr. Sarkozy. Both Mr. Bayrou and Ms. Royal said no.</p>
        <p>Ms. Royal is expected to win over the bulk of the eleven percent of the voters who chose one of six leftist candidates. Likewise, Mr. Sarkozy can generally count on the 12 percent of the vote that went to the extreme-right candidates Jean-Marie Le Pen and Philippe de Villiers.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Royal, who trailed Mr. Sarkozy by nearly six percentage points in Sunday's contest, needs a substantial swath of the center to win.</p>
        <p>''She can only become president with the help of Bayrou voters,'' said Bernard Kouchner, a Socialist former minister who had encouraged Ms. Royal to align with Mr. Bayrou before the first round. ''A way has to be found to join with Bayrou. But I see very little chance that this historic moment will be seized. Sarkozy will win unless Royal opens up this game a little bit.''</p>
        <p>According to a CSA poll conducted after the results of the first round came out, slightly more of Mr. Bayrou's voters will support Ms. Royal than Mr. Sarkozy in the second round on May 6 (45 percent compared with 39 percent). The remaining 16 percent said they would not vote.</p>
        <p>But the Bayrou vote is the volatile chemical of the election, and pollsters come to the race with humility. The IFOP polling organization, for example, reached the conclusion that 54 percent of Mr. Bayrou's voters would swing to Mr. Sarkozy, and 46 percent to Ms. Royal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bayrou's camp knows its potential power. ''We own them,'' said a Bayrou aide, referring to Mr. Sarkozy and Ms. Royal. The aide spoke on condition of anonymity because Mr. Bayrou had not yet announced his intentions.</p>
        <p>But Marielle de Sarnez, Mr. Bayrou's campaign director, made clear that Mr. Bayrou would not compromise his core values for promises by either candidate. ''One thing is sure,'' she was quoted as saying Monday in the daily Le Parisien. ''We are not for sale!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
