<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Little Bits of Paper Make a Big Gift</title>
    <meta content="24stamp" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/business/24stamp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stamps (Postal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Doctors Without Borders</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gross, William H</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1DE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Little Bits of Paper Make a Big Gift</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Little Bits of Paper Make a Big Gift</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY MATTHEW HEALEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yachts and fine art are often the hobbies for wealthy money managers. For Warren E. Buffett, it's bridge.</p>
        <p>But for William Gross, manager of the bond powerhouse Pimco, his passion for the last 15 years has been collecting stamps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>William Gross, manager of the bond powerhouse Pimco, will donate the proceeds from an auction of his rare stamp collection to Doctors Without Borders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yachts and fine art are often the hobbies for wealthy money managers. For Warren E. Buffett, it's bridge.</p>
        <p>But for William Gross, manager of the bond powerhouse Pimco, his passion for the last 15 years has been collecting stamps.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Gross plans to auction off his collection of classic British stamps and donate the entire proceeds, estimated at $4 million to $5 million, to Doctors Without Borders, the humanitarian charity with operations in more than 70 countries around the world. Shreves Philatelic Galleries, based in New York and Dallas, will conduct the sale on June 11.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Gross said his decision to sell his British collection was based both on his feeling that the market for stamps of that country had reached a high point, and the desire of him and his wife, Sue, to make a significant contribution to a humanitarian cause.</p>
        <p>Dr. Darin Portnoy, the president of the United States section of Doctors Without Borders, said the proceeds of Mr. Gross's collection could be one of the largest donations in the 36-year history of the organization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gross, 63, became an avid collector of rare stamps about 15 years ago when he determined that exceptional high-end collectibles could increase in value at a rate comparable to other investments.</p>
        <p>He has since amassed a collection of mostly classic, 19th-century stamps of the United States and other countries, including Britain, France, Switzerland and Scandinavia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gross described his strategy for investing in stamps as being ''to protect myself and educate myself as much as possible with historic auction catalogs,'' tracking and comparing values over time to learn which items had done well.</p>
        <p>One of his formative experiences as a young man was trying to sell mint sheets of 3-cent stamps his mother had bought as an investment for his college education, only to find that they had not appreciated at all.</p>
        <p>His British collection includes some glamorous items: a block of 18 of the Penny Black, the world's first postage stamp issued in 1840, that is one of the largest outside of museums; a rare 1904 six-pence stamp intended only for government use that is estimated to be worth $250,000 and an envelope -- which philatelists call a cover -- bearing the world's first three postage stamps: a Penny Black, a Two-Penny Blue issued at the same time and a Penny Red, issued a year later.</p>
        <p>Specialists in 19th-century philately covet such multicolor frankings, and this item is estimated to be worth as much as half a million dollars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gross's collecting became well known a year and a half ago, when he bought the unique plate-number block of four airmail stamps with an inverted biplane in the center, known as the Inverted Jenny, for nearly $3 million and promptly swapped it for a relatively nondescript, used one-cent blue stamp, which completed Mr. Gross's collection of United States stamps and made him the first person ever to own one of every United States stamp issued.</p>
        <p>The one-cent stamp, from 1868, has an experimental security grill pressed into the back, known as a Z-grill, and is one of only two known and the only one in private hands.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gross displayed his United States collection to the public last May at the Washington 2006 international stamp exhibition.</p>
        <p>While he said he intends to keep and continue adding to his American collection, Mr. Gross said his British collection, which he conceded still had a few empty spaces, would provide a ''good source of funding for charity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
