<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debating Abortion Without Evasions</title>
    <meta content="l24abortion" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EEDE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debating Abortion Without Evasions</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Postures in Public, Facts in the Womb'' (column, April 22):</p>
        <p>David Brooks writes, ''In the beginning there is the womb and the creature inside.'' Sounds as if ''the womb'' is sitting over there in the corner, minding its own business, unattached to a person!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Postures in Public, Facts in the Womb'' (column, April 22):</p>
        <p>David Brooks writes, ''In the beginning there is the womb and the creature inside.'' Sounds as if ''the womb'' is sitting over there in the corner, minding its own business, unattached to a person!</p>
        <p>In fact, ''in the beginning'' there is a woman. It is her body we are talking about. It is her decision to take on the dangers of pregnancy and the future obligations of parenthood; that is the real beginning of this story.</p>
        <p>Sorry, Mr. Brooks. Neither you, nor the Supreme Court, nor any other person can decree when ''the beginning'' starts. Because in the end, the choice about what to do with any pregnancy belongs to the person ''the womb'' belongs to. A woman.</p>
        <p>Kate Permut  Scarborough, N.Y., April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Until the final paragraph, David Brooks makes a marvelous case for ending legalized abortion. But then, strangely, in the last paragraph he argues for abortion being available for ''the first four or five months.''</p>
        <p>If everything preceding his suggestion is true (and I believe that it is), I cannot see how he can reach this rather strange (although he regards it as ''sensible'') recommendation.</p>
        <p>Daniel H. Pilon  Solon Springs, Wis., April 23, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As David Brooks shows, the crux of the abortion problem is while one side can't say ''fetus,'' the other side can't say ''mother.'' Those of us living in the real world have had to face torturous decisions weighing the lives of both, equally valued, equally loved.</p>
        <p>No five black-robed men can give us the answer.</p>
        <p>Agatha Moorad  Lake Oswego, Ore., April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In describing in great detail the growth of the fetus in the womb, David Brooks does not mention either the health of the mother or the possibility that the fetus may not be following this normal growth pattern.</p>
        <p>Similarly, when he calls for parental consent for minors to have an abortion, he does not mention the possibility that the girl's father or other family member may be responsible for the pregnancy, or that the girl may be beaten within an inch of her life if she tells her parents.</p>
        <p>Jean A. Starks  Kingston, N.J., April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>David Brooks deserves credit for detailing the personhood of unborn children. Yet I wonder why, in his estimation, a fetus deserves legal protection at six months but not at four. Is it because he or she can see? Smile? Any criterion chosen would be arbitrary.</p>
        <p>To answer his question, the continuous process of human life begins at conception. While our instinct is to protect those who look like us, we should err on the side of life and protect even those ''small biological clumps'' that can grow into friends and relatives if given only the chance.</p>
        <p>Timothy P. Wymore  Madison, Wis., April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It is amazing how seldom contraception is mentioned by those who oppose abortion. Women need to be in control of their own fertility.</p>
        <p>No woman likes having an abortion. It is a desperate act, a last resort when birth control has not been used or has failed. The best way to reduce abortion is to make contraception readily available.</p>
        <p>Joyce Lockard  Beaverton, Ore., April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''A Sharp Turn for the Supreme Court on Abortion'' (letters, April 20):</p>
        <p>I am a rheumatologist caring for a patient whose lupus nephritis is flaring. Her creatinine is rising as her platelet count falls, and she has failed to improve with pulse methylprednisolone and intravenous cyclophosphamide. I am contemplating using rituximab. I would like to refer this case to the United States Supreme Court for its guidance.</p>
        <p>Richard Zweig, M.D.  Santa Rosa, Calif., April 20, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
