<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking Landmark Status, and Hoping to Lose a Label of Unrest</title>
    <meta content="24journal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/nyregion/24journal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070426T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CROWN HEIGHTS JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Landmarks Preservation Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7DC143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking Landmark Status, and Hoping to Lose a Label of Unrest</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seeking Landmark Status, and Hoping to Lose a Label of Unrest</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WILSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bass player's widow looked down Dean Street and remembered her neighbors by the work they did: a teacher, a letter carrier, a doctor, another jazz man. A subway conductor, a church lady. Across the street, there is a mansion, once a doctor's home.</p>
        <p>''That's a gorgeous house,'' said the woman, Audrey Williams, 69. Her husband, Tommy Williams, who played with the likes of Quincy Jones, was one of several musicians on the street. ''Cedar Walton lived a couple of blocks up. Then another doctor down the block.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The city’s Landmarks Preservation Commission is expected to designate a long swath of 472 buildings in Crown Heights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The bass player's widow looked down Dean Street and remembered her neighbors by the work they did: a teacher, a letter carrier, a doctor, another jazz man. A subway conductor, a church lady. Across the street, there is a mansion, once a doctor's home.</p>
        <p>''That's a gorgeous house,'' said the woman, Audrey Williams, 69. Her husband, Tommy Williams, who played with the likes of Quincy Jones, was one of several musicians on the street. ''Cedar Walton lived a couple of blocks up. Then another doctor down the block.''</p>
        <p>The name of the neighborhood came along only in the 20th century, after several lesser labels -- St. Marks, Brower Park, Grant Square -- for the inner Brooklyn sweep of farmland, mansions, brownstones and carriage houses had faded. The new name invoked a promise of grandeur that the neighborhood's architects strived to deliver with bell towers and movie palaces, terra-cotta and bronze.</p>
        <p>Crown Heights. The images that clung to that name changed horribly in August 1991, when a Hasidic motorist fatally struck a black boy on the sidewalk. The accident led to days of violence and chaos in which a Hasidic student was killed. The neighborhood with the grand name joined a grim fraternity of American areas, like Watts and, eight months later, South Central Los Angeles, that would be known for a riot.</p>
        <p>But in a meeting this morning, the city's Landmarks Preservation Commission is expected to designate a long swath of 472 buildings as landmarks. The designation, in effect, freezes the look of the area. Any significant changes to the facades of those buildings must meet commission approval.</p>
        <p>It is a designation more widely associated with Manhattan's stately blocks, but it is appearing more throughout the boroughs. Today's Crown Heights vote is the first of a series in the neighborhood that, when completed, would apply to about 1,800 mostly middle-class, black-owned homes and buildings landmarks, second only to Park Slope.</p>
        <p>''It has a vibrant community and a vibrant historic housing stock,'' said the commission chairman, Robert B. Tierney. ''It has an eclectic array of architectural styles.''</p>
        <p>The area that will be voted on today does not include the portion where the unrest occurred. A day spent in it suggested a community cleaved from the tense days of August 1991, by both time and space, years and blocks. It sits on the opposite side of Eastern Parkway, a physical, cultural and psychological boundary from the southern section.</p>
        <p>''Not that we're trying to say we're not part of that,'' said Denise Brown, of the neighborhood association. ''But there's two distinct neighborhoods in Crown Heights.''</p>
        <p>The spine of the landmark area is Dean Street, where rows of brownstones on the same side of the street were designed like a palindrome, producing the pattern: ABBBCCBBBA. The effect is much more complex and ornate than a uniform row. Elsewhere in the neighborhood, on Prospect Place, there are houses that look like little Swiss chalets, a row of white, two-story homes with roofs made to appear primitive, with stone slabs. The lobby of 97 Brooklyn Avenue, a large apartment building, is designed like a medieval castle, complete with electric ''flames'' in a large fireplace.</p>
        <p>''These two girls moved here and took a picture near the fireplace,'' said Jean Segers, 64, a neighbor, chuckling. ''With a glass of wine, like it was their apartment.''</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, the beauty of the architecture owes much to a lack of money in the 1970s and 1980s, when -- as in much of Brooklyn and the city -- drugs and poverty and crime drove out the movies and the so-called doctors row. No one had the cash to make bad choices.</p>
        <p>''People didn't paint the outside all kinds of funky colors and do crazy things,'' Ms. Brown said. ''They couldn't afford to.''</p>
        <p>Old meets new. Outside a longtime hardware store on Nostrand Avenue, where young newcomers buy tools for renovation, a knot of men watched a complicated version of checkers, with extra rules. Imhotep's, a vegan restaurant and store down Nostrand, serves soy barbecue and okra. An old neighborhood bar, where the average age on Thursday afternoon was above 50, advertises a gay dance party on weekends. There is a restaurant, Secrets, that features jazz nights. ''I've passed,'' said the bassist's widow, Mrs. Williams, ''but I haven't been in.''</p>
        <p>Walter Clark, a 60-year-old Vietnam veteran, peered in garbage cans with his one good eye. ''I pick up bottles and cans and stuff. I couldn't punch a clock,'' he said. He applauded the landmark status: ''The inside changes, but not the outside.''</p>
        <p>Signs of new money are seemingly on every block, where workers carried sheets of plywood and tools into vacant brownstones. Many of the new faces of Crown Heights North are white ones, according to those who have lived here longest.</p>
        <p>A white woman who gave her name only as Noreen said she had lived here 52 years, since she was 5. When she felt hostility from her black neighbors after the assassination of Martin Luther King Jr., she responded brassily, ''I didn't shoot the man.''</p>
        <p>Now, she greets the newcomers with the same mixture of welcome and wariness of many New Yorkers who see higher rents coming behind them. ''Last year, we saw a lot of Caucasians coming back,'' she said. ''My friend said, 'Your cousins are coming,' and I said, 'Yeah, but I never went anywhere.' ''</p>
        <p>The friend could have been referring to Nicholas DiFonzo, 27, white and lanky, a music writer, painter and waiter, who shares a floor of a brownstone with roommates. ''It's got a pretty homey feel to it,'' he said. ''It's got a community I'm obviously not a part of, for obvious reasons. One, I just moved here. And ethnic differences.'' But, he added, ''Everybody's cool.''</p>
        <p>It is a New York rule that the newest tenants in a neighborhood may immediately begin citing the way things used to be; Mr. DiFonzo is no exception. ''It's a weird cocktail of emotions you get from that,'' he said of the influx, still slight, of white tenants. ''This is the edge of the gentrification. You can almost see it. Every other day, there's a sign in the door that says, 'We will buy your house for cash.' ''</p>
        <p>CROWN HEIGHTS JOURNAL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 26, 2007, Thursday  An architect's rendering of planned renovations to the New-York Historical Society building that were approved on Tuesday by the Landmarks Preservation Commission. The rendering published yesterday, showing a 40-foot entrance portal sheathed in glass, was an earlier, unapproved version.</p>
        <p>Drawing (Drawing by Platt Byard Dovell White Architects)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 26, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An architect's rendering of planned renovations to the New-York Historical Society building that were approved on Tuesday by the Landmarks Preservation Commission. The rendering published yesterday, showing a 40-foot entrance portal sheathed in glass, was an earlier, unapproved version.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;Drawing (Drawing by Platt Byard Dovell White Architects)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
