<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Difficult Annual Times Meeting for Sulzbergers</title>
    <meta content="24times" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/business/media/24times.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842629"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Times</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan Stanley</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sulzberger, Arthur Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Difficult Annual Times Meeting for Sulzbergers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Difficult Annual Times Meeting for Sulzbergers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LANDON THOMAS Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Times Company annual shareholder meeting traditionally has been a tame affair, where the Sulzberger family, which owns a controlling interest in the company, applauds the achievements of its journalists and, in turn, basks in the applause of investors.</p>
        <p>But times have changed. With the company's stock performance lagging, along with much of the newspaper industry, the chairman and publisher, Arthur Sulzberger Jr., and his family are bracing for a contentious meeting today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With The New York Times Company’s stock performance lagging, the Sulzberger family is bracing for a contentious meeting today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York Times Company annual shareholder meeting traditionally has been a tame affair, where the Sulzberger family, which owns a controlling interest in the company, applauds the achievements of its journalists and, in turn, basks in the applause of investors.</p>
        <p>But times have changed. With the company's stock performance lagging, along with much of the newspaper industry, the chairman and publisher, Arthur Sulzberger Jr., and his family are bracing for a contentious meeting today.</p>
        <p>Last year, dissident investors, led by Hassan Elmasry, a senior portfolio manager at Morgan Stanley Investment Management, withheld 30 percent of their votes for the election of Class A directors, as a sign of their frustration with the company's dual ownership structure and performance.</p>
        <p>This year, the company and its critics have both lobbied hard. According to people who have spoken with Mr. Sulzberger, the family and the company are prepared for the possibility that the vote withheld might exceed 50 percent.</p>
        <p>The vote is largely symbolic: under the dual ownership structure, the family owns 89 percent of Class B shares and elects 70 percent of the board, or 9 of 13 directors. But such an outcome could put additional pressure on family members and independent directors to take more aggressive steps in addressing the dissidents' concerns.</p>
        <p>So far none of the nonfamily directors of the Times Company have stepped down since the battle began and they have told Mr. Sulzberger that they have no plans to resign. Still, the uncomfortable glare of public scrutiny upon them is not expected to diminish soon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sulzberger has said repeatedly that the company would not change the longstanding dual class structure that gives the family control, maintaining that it preserves the independence of the newspaper and protects the company in dire economic times.</p>
        <p>In a speech prepared for the annual meeting today, Mr. Sulzberger plans to say, ''only the trustees of the Ochs/Sulzberger family have the ability to change that and we are unanimous in our commitment to retain it.''</p>
        <p>In his first public response to his unhappy investors, Mr. Sulzberger defended the Times Company's recent investments, including the net $500 million it has spent on its new headquarters as well as his holding of chairman and publisher titles.</p>
        <p>He is expected to describe the current industry climate as ''the most dramatic transformation in our long and distinguished history,'' and acknowledge that despite strong growth in the company's digital businesses, the print side continues to decline.</p>
        <p>He also plans to credit his grandfather, Arthur Hays Sulzberger, for putting a two-class structure in place, ''to get us through times like this.'' But ''all of us -- my family and you, our shareholders -- have felt the pain of this disruption,'' the prepared text states.</p>
        <p>Whatever the outcome of the meeting, it is unlikely to appease the critics, led by Mr. Elmasry, whose portfolio includes a 7 percent stake in The Times.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Sulzberger and Mr. Elmasry declined to comment for this article.</p>
        <p>Some other large Class A investors -- in particular T. Rowe Price, which owns 15 percent, and Private Capital Management, with 9.3 percent -- also withheld their votes last year. They have not made their intentions for this year's meeting clear.</p>
        <p>Brian C. Rogers, chairman of T. Rowe Price did not return calls seeking comment. Bruce S. Sherman of Private Capital declined to comment. Howard P. Milstein, the chief executive of Emigrant Bank, bought a 4.3 percent stake in the company; he has told Mr. Sulzberger that he would support him.</p>
        <p>Representatives of Mr. Elmasry have said that he would not attend today's meeting.</p>
        <p>The campaign has grown heated, with both sides making their cases to two corporate advisory firms. The results have been mixed: Institutional Shareholder Services issued a report advising investors to withhold their vote, while Proxy Governance said that investors should vote for the Times directors. A third advisory service, Glass-Lewis, which does not meet with investors, has recommended that investors withhold their votes.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Sulzberger received support when Donald E. Graham, the chairman and chief executive of the Washington Post Company, urged investors to support the Times Company. Writing in the opinion pages of The Wall Street Journal, Mr. Graham argued that an elimination of the two-class structure would result ''in a line of buyers eager to purchase the company'' and said that a new owner might not maintain the same news standards.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the dispute over the capital structure is a more fundamental tension between the interests of the Sulzberger family, which sees itself as the guardian of The Times newspaper, and its institutional investors, who argue that the company's dual class structure prevents the company from being fully accountable to all shareholders.</p>
        <p>''This is a governance issue,'' said Charles M. Elson of the University of Delaware. ''If you own 100 percent, you do whatever you want. Once you enter the public, your obligations change.''</p>
        <p>For advice on its governance practices, the Times Company's board has hired Martin Lipton, a lawyer with experience in advising directors. For public relations counsel, the board has hired Paul Verbinnen, president of Sard Verbinnen.</p>
        <p>Separately, extended family members themselves had a regularly scheduled meeting on Friday at the Times Company's headquarters, where they met with executives on the news and business sides of The Times. Over the weekend they gathered in a more informal setting at a conference center in Connecticut to discuss family business, where, according to one person present, there was little discussion about the controversy.</p>
        <p>''The family's identity is caught up in being a steward of The New York Times,'' said Alex S. Jones, a co-author of ''The Trust,'' a book on the Ochs-Sulzberger family. ''They would not give up that stewardship for any reason that I could imagine.''</p>
        <p>The vehicle for this stewardship is a 1997 trust, which controls the majority of the non-traded Class B stock and which includes Mr. Sulzberger, five of his cousins, a fifth-generation family member and Mr. Sulzberger's brother in law, Eric M. A. Lax. (Four trustees also serve as directors elected by Class B shareholders.)</p>
        <p>It is the trust, not the board, that has the power to declassify the shares, and it would take at least a 6-to-2 vote to do that.</p>
        <p>In his meeting with the full board in February, Mr. Elmasry made a broad critique of past investments, including the acquisition of About.com, a Web information service that the Times Company bought in 2005 for $410 million, which he deemed ''speculative,'' and the company's new headquarters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sulzberger, in his speech, is expected to defend About.com's expanding margins, saying they increased to 38 percent in 2006 from 27 percent in 2005, and its contributions to the paper's digital properties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Elmasry also asked the board to separate the chairman and publisher titles that Mr. Sulzberger now holds, according to people briefed on the meeting. Mr. Elmasry did not say which job Mr. Sulzberger should give up.</p>
        <p>While the board has the power to ask Mr. Sulzberger to step down as chairman, it does not have the authority to appoint the publisher. Throughout the history of The Times, the title of publisher has been held by a family member.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sulzberger, according to the prepared text of his speech, is expected to say that his two titles allow him to ''balance the financial and journalistic needs of this institution.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Elmasry's complaint stems from a view that, starting in the late 1990s, attempts by management to diversify into areas like cable television took focus away from the newspaper's core brand.</p>
        <p>''The New York Times had some wonderful years financially and also in terms of how the stock market saw the company,'' said Andy Brown, a predecessor of Mr. Elmasry at Morgan Stanley's fund unit who bought the original stake in the Times Company in 1996 and who now runs his own fund company. ''You could argue that this was the result of financial discipline, but you could also argue that management was emboldened by this success to make all these acquisitions.''</p>
        <p>Other Class A investors have also questioned the board and management. In February, T. Rowe Price had a conference call with all board members, except for Mr. Sulzberger and Janet L. Robinson, the company's chief executive, who did not attend at T. Rowe Price's request. Ms. Robinson also met with Mr. Sherman of Private Capital in March.</p>
        <p>Analysts also argue that the transition of advertising to the Internet has hurt all publishing companies.</p>
        <p>The Times Company has already reacted to a number of the issues that Mr. Elmasry has raised during his campaign. For example, Mr. Sulzberger and Michael Golden, vice chairman and publisher of The International Herald Tribune, have said they will not accept stock-based compensation for 2006 and 2007.</p>
        <p>Additionally, the company has agreed to sell its television stations, raised its dividend and formalized a rotation process ensuring that in the coming years Class A shareholders will be able to vote for directors on the compensation, audit and nominating committees. As part of the plan, the eight independent directors who are not part of the family or management will now be subject to shareholder vote at least once every three years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
