<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Right Office, Trust and Candor</title>
    <meta content="24tside" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/health/24tside.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1D6173EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Right Office, Trust and Candor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Right Office, Trust and Candor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cues that a family medicine or pediatric practice is welcoming to adolescents can be discerned well before the first visit. Some practices set aside office hours for teenagers. Some have a different waiting area, with bigger chairs, age-appropriate reading material -- and no toddler toys.</p>
        <p>But specialists in adolescent medicine say that even without such accommodations, the right attitude goes a long way. ''Everyone in the practice, from the front-office person to the physician, should like to work with teenagers,'' said Dr. Robert T. Brown, immediate past president of the Society for Adolescent Medicine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cues that a family medicine or pediatric practice is welcoming to adolescents can be discerned well before the first visit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cues that a family medicine or pediatric practice is welcoming to adolescents can be discerned well before the first visit. Some practices set aside office hours for teenagers. Some have a different waiting area, with bigger chairs, age-appropriate reading material -- and no toddler toys.</p>
        <p>But specialists in adolescent medicine say that even without such accommodations, the right attitude goes a long way. ''Everyone in the practice, from the front-office person to the physician, should like to work with teenagers,'' said Dr. Robert T. Brown, immediate past president of the Society for Adolescent Medicine.</p>
        <p>''If the front-office person doesn't like it, the patient can be alienated right away,'' Dr. Brown said. That front-office person has to be able to go, 'Hah! That's a teenager and I love 'em anyway.' ''</p>
        <p>Experts say office visits should begin to change when the patient is 11 to 13, with the doctor spending time in the examining room alone with the patient. Until then, the physician usually converses largely with the parent or guardian.</p>
        <p>Doctors need to explain how that dynamic will shift, and why.</p>
        <p>''It's called 'setting the stage,' it takes five to seven minutes, and you do it once,'' said Dr. Kenneth R. Ginsburg, who lectures and writes about treating adolescents. ''If you do it right, then you can have a different environment where the kid understands the power of a health professional, and the parents see you as an ally.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ginsburg tells the patient and the parents that they will be setting up what is, in effect, a social contract, based on candor, trust and confidentiality. State laws vary, but if a patient says something in confidence, the doctor will generally disclose it only if there is reason to think the patient or someone else is in danger of abuse or other serious harm.</p>
        <p>Parents need to be assured, Dr. Ginsburg said, ''that we're not trying to take over their role.''</p>
        <p>''The challenge for doctors,'' he went on, ''is to get parents to understand that we do this fully in support of the same goals for their child that they have.''</p>
        <p>As a child becomes a teenager, the parent, doctor and patient relationship is bound to change, and that may be uncomfortable for everyone. But the old relationship may no longer serve the changing health needs of an adolescent.</p>
        <p>Dr. John Santelli, chairman of the department of population and family health at Columbia University, says parents have to look for doctors who will readily address issues like sexuality and drug use.</p>
        <p>''If the doctor won't see my son or daughter independently, I'd wonder,'' Dr. Santelli said. ''If they're not talking about these issues, I'd wonder. The kids themselves are too embarrassed, too reticent to raise them. They don't even realize these are medical issues. So it's essential that the doctor does.''</p>
        <p>To find doctors skilled in caring for adolescents, who can diagnose causes for fainting and depression, discuss gynecological issues and sports injuries, parents have a variety of sources.</p>
        <p>Word of mouth counts for a lot. Parents can also call the nearest children's or teaching hospital, which may have an adolescent clinic.</p>
        <p>Parents seeking referrals can contact organizations of health professionals who treat adolescents. Those with Internet referral services include the Society for Adolescent Medicine (www.adolescenthealth.org), the North American Society for Pediatric and Adolescent Gynecology (www.naspag.org/contact.html) and the American Academy of Pediatrics (www.aap.org).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
