<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Pilot's Heart Attack? Lightning? I Can Cope</title>
    <meta content="24flier" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/business/24flier.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FREQUENT FLIER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Frequent Flier</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Aviation Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EEDF143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Pilot's Heart Attack? Lightning? I Can Cope</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Pilot’s Heart Attack? Lightning? I Can Cope</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tara-Nicholle Nelson as told to Joan Raymond.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I want to set the record straight: I don't like to fly. And that's a problem, given the fact that I have to do a lot of business travel. I dread it so much that last year, I didn't even get on a plane to go to an event. In anyone's book, that's really bad for your bottom line.</p>
        <p>I'm more than just the run-of-the-mill, sweaty-palmed nervous flier. I was the real-deal claustrophobic who always had to sit in the front row, aisle seat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How to confront a fear of flying, deal with it and get on with business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I want to set the record straight: I don't like to fly. And that's a problem, given the fact that I have to do a lot of business travel. I dread it so much that last year, I didn't even get on a plane to go to an event. In anyone's book, that's really bad for your bottom line.</p>
        <p>I'm more than just the run-of-the-mill, sweaty-palmed nervous flier. I was the real-deal claustrophobic who always had to sit in the front row, aisle seat.</p>
        <p>Claustrophobia is often defined as ''fear of small or tight spaces.'' But it also includes the fear of having no escape routes. Small, tight spaces and no escape route sounds like air travel to me. Deep down inside, I realize that my fears are illogical. I pride myself on being a logical person.</p>
        <p>So, a few months ago, I decided to research the science of flying. I'm kind of a Web nerd, so I knew that I could find the information. I wanted to confront my fears, deal with them, and get on with business. And I did, using the Federal Aviation Administration's Web site, Howstuffworks.com and others. I even took a free online self-help course at Fearofflyinghelp.com.</p>
        <p>I'm an organized person by nature, so I made a list of my issues and took them on, one by one. The first: What if the plane gets struck by lightning? I found out that planes get hit by lightning all the time, but are equipped to take a hit with very little effect. I'm breathing easy. Lightning is something I can check off my list.</p>
        <p>My second issue focused on the pilot's health. What if he or she has a heart attack while piloting the plane? I learned that pilots take physicals every six months. Good. Check. (However, a small part of me wishes they would take them every week.)</p>
        <p>The structure of the plane always concerned me. Fortunately, I discovered that wings don't break into tiny little pieces for no reason. And engines are quite secure in their well-constructed compartments. Check and check.</p>
        <p>You can impress your friends with this tidbit of knowledge I picked up: Even without engines, commercial airliners are built to glide to safety rather than to plummet. I'm very happy about that. Gliding is always preferable to plummeting.</p>
        <p>Turbulence was another big problem. In those cases, I imagined the pilot behind that locked door wrestling with the controls. Nope. I learned that turbulence is predictable, unavoidable, no cause for distress and usually less jolting in the air than it is on the road. And the pilot doesn't wrestle with anything, let alone the controls. Except in the movies, of course. Check.</p>
        <p>This exercise has given me a lot of confidence. I still need an aisle seat, but I'll take one anywhere, not just the front row. Now, I always fly on my favorite airline. I get a lot of legroom, so I don't feel confined. Best of all, I get a personal TV, which serves as a distraction, keeping me calm. So far so good. But all bets are off if I switch channels and stumble across ''Snakes on a Plane.''</p>
        <p>FREQUENT FLIER E-mail: joan.raymond@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: joan.raymond@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
