<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wiping Out A Parasite, Not a Spirit Of Adventure</title>
    <meta content="24case" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/health/24case.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842515"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Cases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Parasites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parasites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parasites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5D6173EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wiping Out A Parasite, Not a Spirit Of Adventure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wiping Out a Parasite, Not a Spirit of Adventure</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE PANOSIAN DUNAVAN, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunavan, Claire Panosian (Dr)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Keith Aronowitz first noticed the crater on his elbow after returning from Bolivia. For a week or two, he simply ignored it. Then his friends began to worry.</p>
        <p>''A buddy saw the hole in my arm,'' recalled Mr. Aronowitz, a photographer and video editor, ''and said: 'Hey, you better see a doctor. That doesn't look right.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Keith Aronowitz first noticed the crater on his elbow after returning from Bolivia. For a week or two, he simply ignored it. Then his friends began to worry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Keith Aronowitz first noticed the crater on his elbow after returning from Bolivia. For a week or two, he simply ignored it. Then his friends began to worry.</p>
        <p>''A buddy saw the hole in my arm,'' recalled Mr. Aronowitz, a photographer and video editor, ''and said: 'Hey, you better see a doctor. That doesn't look right.' ''</p>
        <p>O.K., he decided, I'll see a dermatologist, and maybe I'll even help her with the diagnosis. At the back of his mind, he was thinking of a recent National Geographic article. In it, the author also contracted a weird skin infection in South America. And it all started, the writer stated, with the bite of a sand fly.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Aronowitz arrived at Madidi National Park -- the same Amazon outpost visited by the National Geographic author -- he, too, was bombarded by sand flies. Soon, their pesky bites left him covered in itchy bumps. Then came the elbow ulcer.</p>
        <p>In Los Angeles, however, his doctor simply shrugged her shoulders when he proffered these clues. Instead, she handed him an all-purpose cream and glided off.</p>
        <p>Another two months passed. The hole in Mr. Aronowitz's elbow got bigger, deeper and juicier. That's when he found me.</p>
        <p>I'm a tropical medicine specialist who has seen plenty of exotic skin infections over the years. You could say my interest dates back to childhood. Growing up, I was always fascinated by the shallow scar on the cheek of my grandfather, a native of southern Turkey. ''How'd you get it?'' I asked him, touching the papery depression. ''Oh, where I was born, everyone had this,'' he replied. ''First a fly bit you, then you got a sore. After a while it healed and never came back.''</p>
        <p>Years later, as an infectious diseases trainee, I suddenly grasped my grandfather's diagnosis. What he had was a classic case of ''Old World'' cutaneous leishmaniasis, also known as ''Oriental sore,'' ''Baghdad boil'' and ''Aleppo evil.'' I then spent two years studying immune responses to the common Middle Eastern blight.</p>
        <p>First, the bite of the sand fly transmits the single-cell parasites. Then warrior lymphocytes flood the dermis, causing other cells sheltering the invading microbes to self-destruct. As the battle plays out and the good guys prevail, patients' skin lesions slowly morph from volcanic nodules to thick-rimmed ulcers to patchy, irregular scars.</p>
        <p>But certain cases of leishmaniasis acquired in South America are not so easily vanquished. After hearing Mr. Aronowitz's story, I felt a little queasy. The region he visited harbors particularly nasty strains of leishmania that sometimes evade the immune system, later spreading like cancer to the nose, mouth and throat.</p>
        <p>It was bad enough that my new patient had a ragged, crusty defect on his elbow. What if the parasite started in on his face? This was no longer a watch-and-wait situation -- it was time to treat. Or try, at least.</p>
        <p>My first choice was an antifungal drug that counters leishmania. Although the medicine bothered his stomach, Mr. Aronowitz faithfully downed the pills for two or three months. But when he stopped them, his elbow got itchy and red, and before long the sore was back.</p>
        <p>Intravenous pentamidine -- once a mainstay for AIDS patients with Pneumocystis pneumonia -- was my next ploy. It bought my patient another year.</p>
        <p>Now I was down to heavy-metal therapy. That's right: the elephant gun for leishmaniasis is a toxic drug made from the chemical antimony.</p>
        <p>Everything about the drug, Pentostam, is laborious. To procure it, I had to reach out to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta and fill out piles of paperwork. Meanwhile, Mr. Aronowitz was outfitted with a semipermanent IV to receive the drug. A high price to pay for a few days in the rain forest.</p>
        <p>Finally, it was showtime. Day after day for a month, the man with a hole in his elbow visited our hospital's infusion center, patiently enduring ever-worsening aches and pains while the parasite poison coursed through his veins. He also underwent weekly blood tests and EKGs to make sure his kidneys, liver and heart remained healthy throughout the treatment.</p>
        <p>Thankfully, this drug, Pentostam, was the charm; it cured Mr. Aronowitz's infection with no lasting side effects. Four years later, his elbow is as smooth as silk.</p>
        <p>Epilogue: Last spring, Mr. Aronowitz returned to the Amazon. This year, he recently told me, he's planning another trip, to shoot a documentary about shamans.</p>
        <p>He is philosophical about the danger.</p>
        <p>''I don't know why, but I've always been fascinated by the wild, green romanticism of it,'' he said. ''Sure there are insects and animals there. Maybe that's why I like it.''</p>
        <p>Since we're friends, I can be frank. I'll take my insects and parasites under the microscope.</p>
        <p>CASES Claire Panosian Dunavan is a professor of medicine and infectious diseases at the University of California, Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Claire Panosian Dunavan is a professor of medicine and infectious diseases at the University of California, Los Angeles.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
