<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Report Says the Backup Samples From Landis Test Positive</title>
    <meta content="24landis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/othersports/24landis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Testosterone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tour de France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Testosterone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Landis, Floyd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E2DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Report Says the Backup Samples From Landis Test Positive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Report Says the Backup Samples From Landis Test Positive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macur, Juliet</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tests on seven backup urine samples taken from Floyd Landis at the 2006 Tour de France have revealed traces of synthetic testosterone, according to a report yesterday by L'Équipe, the French sports newspaper.</p>
        <p>Landis, who won last year's Tour but tested positive for doping in the race, and his lawyers did not confirm or deny the report in a teleconference yesterday, saying they expected to receive the full results of those tests shortly from the French lab that conducted the testing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tests on seven backup urine samples taken from Floyd Landis at the 2006 Tour de France have revealed traces of synthetic testosterone, according to a report Monday by a French newspaper.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tests on seven backup urine samples taken from Floyd Landis at the 2006 Tour de France have revealed traces of synthetic testosterone, according to a report yesterday by L'Équipe, the French sports newspaper.</p>
        <p>Landis, who won last year's Tour but tested positive for doping in the race, and his lawyers did not confirm or deny the report in a teleconference yesterday, saying they expected to receive the full results of those tests shortly from the French lab that conducted the testing.</p>
        <p>The samples taken during the Tour had been deemed negative last year, but the French lab conducted a more sophisticated test on each sample this time, to determine the presence of man-made testosterone. The new round of testing was done at the request of the United States Anti-Doping Agency.</p>
        <p>''First of all, I won the Tour fair and square,'' Landis said on the teleconference yesterday afternoon. He added that he was disappointed, but not surprised, that the results were leaked to the French newspaper. He blamed the French lab or the United States Anti-Doping Agency for revealing the results prematurely.</p>
        <p>Michael Henson, Landis's spokesman, criticized the French lab's testing methods. ''There were errors in the scientific methods, and our observers were aware of that from the time they hit the ground in Paris,'' Henson said. ''They don't have a grasp of the basic tenets of the science that they were dealing with.''</p>
        <p>Henson said that Landis was tested twice randomly in the first week of the Tour, then six more times when he was wearing the yellow jersey as the race's leader.</p>
        <p>The new test results were the latest phase of the case involving Landis, 31, and his failed doping test from the race. Despite a chronic hip injury, he won the Tour after an improbable comeback in the Alps in Stage 17. But his feel-good story was cut short.</p>
        <p>A day after the race ended, a urine sample he provided after Stage 17 tested positive for a ratio of testosterone to epitestosterone of 11 to 1, nearly three times the maximum set under World Anti-Doping Agency rules. Synthetic testosterone was also found in his urine samples. Landis quickly professed his innocence.</p>
        <p>In September, the United States Anti-Doping Agency charged Landis with a doping violation and Landis appealed, blaming the French lab that conducted the testing for the mistake. A hearing in front of a three-person arbitration panel is scheduled to begin May 14. If Landis loses the appeal, he could take the case to the Court of Arbitration for Sport. The court's decision would be final. If Landis loses that appeal, he faces a two-year ban from cycling and the loss of his Tour title.</p>
        <p>If the L'Équipe report is accurate, the seven additional positives may provide extra evidence for the United States Anti-Doping Agency in its case against Landis. International antidoping rules say that those seven positives cannot constitute a doping violation on their own. But those results can confirm another positive test, according to a ruling by the American Arbitration Association panel that gave the United States Anti-Doping Agency the approval to test those samples.</p>
        <p>Travis Tygart, USADA's senior managing director and general counsel, declined to comment on the case because it was the agency's policy not to discuss continuing cases.</p>
        <p>Don Catlin, the former head of the U.C.L.A. antidoping lab who now runs his own antidoping research facility, said that initial tests of urine samples could produce negative results because none of the tests fail the screening for a high ratio of testosterone to epitestosterone. If a sample comes back below the threshold of four to one, he said, there is nothing to trigger the more sophisticated carbon isotope ratio test. That test examines the atomic makeup of testosterone in the urine and can determine if it is natural or synthetic.</p>
        <p>Landis's lawyers said that they were frustrated by USADA's insistence on having the samples tested at the French lab, which had tested Landis's initial samples from the Tour. They had asked for the testing to be moved to another lab, but their request was denied, said Maurice Suh, one of Landis's lawyers. It was just a handful of the many complaints about the process that Landis and his lawyers detailed Monday.</p>
        <p>Lance Armstrong, who won the Tour de France seven times and was a teammate of Landis's on the United States Postal Service team, has criticized the French lab and its testing process. The lab had retroactively tested urine samples from the 1999 Tour that were linked to Armstrong and found traces of the blood-booster EPO in them. Those results were also leaked to L'Équipe.</p>
        <p>Like Landis, Armstrong has vehemently denied ever taking performance-enhancing drugs. Both have complained about the leaking of test results from the French lab.</p>
        <p>''I have never been supportive of that lab,'' Armstrong said yesterday in a telephone interview. ''If you can't maintain a level of confidentiality around the stuff that is truly a serious issue, then the lab needs to not be a certified lab.''</p>
        <p>''But I think it's become very personal for both sides there,'' he said. ''They've been very outspoken, and Floyd's been very outspoken. There's some bad blood between the two.''</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
