<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Officers Of Apple Await Suit</title>
    <meta content="24apple" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/technology/24apple.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Apple Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Officers Of Apple Await Suit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Officers of Apple Await Suit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF and ERIC DASH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two former Apple executives expect to be sued this week by the Securities and Exchange Commission over the company's backdating of employee stock options, several people involved in negotiations between the former executives and the government said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The move against the two would be the first fruit of separate investigations into Apple's options practices by the commission and the Justice Department. The investigations, into events more than five years ago, have cast a cloud over the company even at the height of its iPod-driven renaissance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two former executives expect to be sued this week by the S.E.C. over the company’s backdating of employee stock options.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two former Apple executives expect to be sued this week by the Securities and Exchange Commission over the company's backdating of employee stock options, several people involved in negotiations between the former executives and the government said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The move against the two would be the first fruit of separate investigations into Apple's options practices by the commission and the Justice Department. The investigations, into events more than five years ago, have cast a cloud over the company even at the height of its iPod-driven renaissance.</p>
        <p>After its own investigation late last year, Apple acknowledged improper dating of options grants to Steven P. Jobs, its chief executive, and others. It cited ''serious concerns'' about the actions of two unnamed former officials, but absolved Mr. Jobs of any responsibility.</p>
        <p>One of the executives facing S.E.C. action is Nancy R. Heinen, Apple's former general counsel and a longtime confidant of Mr. Jobs. Her lawyer said she would contest the accusations, which involve options grants to Mr. Jobs and others in 2001.</p>
        <p>''We have a very good defense,'' said the lawyer, Cristina Arguedas. The expected lawsuit against Ms. Heinen was reported yesterday in The San Jose Mercury News.</p>
        <p>The other executive, Fred D. Anderson, the company's former chief financial officer, is preparing to enter into a settlement with the S.E.C. over the dating of an option grant to senior officials in January 2001, according to a person close to the settlement negotiations.</p>
        <p>The settlement terms are said to include a payment of about $3.5 million, an amount representing his personal gains from the options and a small civil penalty.</p>
        <p>Significantly, as part of the agreement, Mr. Anderson will not be required to give up his role as a director of several public companies, the person close to the negotiations said. He is currently chairman of the audit committee of eBay and a managing director at Elevation Partners, a venture capital firm.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Anderson said he would not comment, pending a decision by the S.E.C. to file a lawsuit. A commission spokesman also declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson joined Apple in 1996 and left as chief financial officer in 2004 to join Elevation Partners. He stepped down from the Apple board last October in the course of the internal investigation of options practices. Ms. Heinen, who followed Mr. Jobs to Apple from Next Software in 1997, left the company last spring.</p>
        <p>It is not clear whether the two prospective S.E.C. civil lawsuits will be the extent of the commission's action against Apple or its executives over the backdating activities. Nor is it clear when an investigation by the United States attorney's office in San Francisco will come to a conclusion. A spokesman for the office had no comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>But Apple's stock rose $2.54, to $93.51, yesterday after an article in The Mercury News on Sunday, citing unidentified sources, said evidence suggested that Mr. Jobs was unlikely to face civil or criminal charges.</p>
        <p>Apple said it was continuing to cooperate with the investigations.</p>
        <p>Of the two executives facing imminent S.E.C. action, Ms. Heinen is confronting the more serious charges. The S.E.C. lawsuit is expected to accuse her of having played in role in picking false dates for two options grants -- an October 2001 date for a grant to Mr. Jobs, and the January 2001 date for the grant to the company's top executives, which included both Mr. Anderson and Ms. Heinen.</p>
        <p>The case against Mr. Anderson involves only the January 2001 grant, and does not assert that he picked the falsely recorded date, but notes that as chief financial officer he was copied on e-mail messages that discussed the dating, according to a person close to the negotiations.</p>
        <p>Apple is the most prominent of a number of technology companies that have been caught up in both civil and criminal investigations over the recording of inaccurate stock option grant dates.</p>
        <p>During the dot-com era, the practice of backdating stock grants to a lower stock price, increasing their value when exercised, was common in Silicon Valley. When he returned to Apple in 1997, Mr. Jobs issued a significant number of options grants to employees in an effort to hold on to scarce talent during the boom times.</p>
        <p>In December, after a six-month investigation of ''irregularities'' in its options practices, Apple said 6,427 grants from 1997 to 2002 had been backdated, including a large grant to Mr. Jobs. That grant, approved in December 2001, was ultimately reported to have been made at an Apple board meeting that October -- a session that never took place. The stock price rose in the interim.</p>
        <p>The minutes of the supposed meeting have been attributed to Wendy Howell, who worked in Apple's legal department and has since left the company. But who might have authorized or known of the fabrication is in dispute.</p>
        <p>Ms. Howell's lawyer, Thomas F. Carlucci, said yesterday that his client ''had no personal reason whatsoever, financial or otherwise, to prepare the subject documents.'' He emphasized that ''Ms. Howell was a line attorney at Apple who prepared documents at the request of her superiors'' and that ''at no time did she act alone, or without direction from Apple management.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Heinen's lawyer, Ms. Arguedas, said yesterday that her client had not given Ms. Howell any instructions in connection with the falsified minutes.</p>
        <p>The other grant that figures in the S.E.C. lawsuits, made to senior executives, was dated Jan. 17, 2001, but is said to have received final approval some weeks later. That grant was made by Mr. Jobs as chief executive and chairman.</p>
        <p>Ms. Arguedas said Ms. Heinen had no incriminating information about Mr. Jobs. ''He knew about this in the sense that the board knew everything about this,'' she said. ''We don't think it's incriminating because we don't think anything wrong happened here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
