<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In New Rochelle, a Push Not to Let a Melee Derail Growth in the Thriving Downtown</title>
    <meta content="24newroc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/nyregion/24newroc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1321" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In New Rochelle, a Push Not to Let a Melee Derail Growth in the Thriving Downtown</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In New Rochelle, a Push Not to Let a Melee Derail Growth in the Thriving Downtown</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE, N.Y., April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever since 200 police officers were called in to break up a melee of unruly teenagers this month at New Roc City, the slick youth-oriented entertainment complex here, city officials as well as developers busy redesigning the once-moribund downtown have cast the episode as an anomaly.</p>
        <p>Yet New Roc's management company moved quickly to establish new rules in hopes of ensuring that it remains a one-time occurrence, adding as many as 10 police officers at the complex during peak times. And anyone under 18 will be barred from the place -- excluding the 16-screen multiplex -- after 6 p.m. on weekends unless accompanied by a parent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever since 200 police officers were called in to break up a group of violent teenagers earlier this month, city officials have cast the episode as an anomaly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ever since 200 police officers were called in to break up a melee of unruly teenagers this month at New Roc City, the slick youth-oriented entertainment complex here, city officials as well as developers busy redesigning the once-moribund downtown have cast the episode as an anomaly.</p>
        <p>Yet New Roc's management company moved quickly to establish new rules in hopes of ensuring that it remains a one-time occurrence, adding as many as 10 police officers at the complex during peak times. And anyone under 18 will be barred from the place -- excluding the 16-screen multiplex -- after 6 p.m. on weekends unless accompanied by a parent.</p>
        <p>The aggressive response has rankled teenagers and parents, who fear it will crimp the social life of young people in southern Westchester County -- who, by police accounts, were not to blame for the episode -- or lead them toward riskier activities, like under-age drinking.</p>
        <p>''My guess is they'll find that it will backfire,'' said Ellen Dupuy d'Angeac, a mother of three who has lived in New Rochelle for five years. ''You have to make rules about behavior, not about age. Sixteen- and 17-year-olds don't want their parents hanging out with them on a Saturday night, and their parents don't want to hang out with them either.''</p>
        <p>And Amy E. Jackson, a member of a citizens' advisory committee on development here who also has three children, said: ''So what are they going to do now? Are they going to hang out in people's basements or in the woods?''</p>
        <p>But Joseph V. Apicella, executive vice president of Cappelli Enterprises, the developer that built and manages New Roc City, said the chief concern was safety.</p>
        <p>''It reminds me of when we were in our classroom and someone would act out, and our entire class would get punished as a result,'' he said. ''It's unfortunate, but we want it to be safe and family-oriented, and we want it to be a place where people can be happy.''</p>
        <p>New Roc City, which opened in 1999, is a popular destination for Westchester's young people, with glow-in-the-dark miniature golf, video games, bowling, go-carts and ice skating. On April 8, it was already packed when hundreds of young people, most from New York City, began pouring off Metro-North trains in the early evening, the police said.</p>
        <p>Turned away from the packed complex, after having been turned away earlier in the day from the auto show at the Javits Convention Center in Manhattan, the crowd grew restive, the police said. Shots were fired. A teenager was stabbed. Nearly 200 police officers were summoned from nearby communities, and six teenagers were arrested on charges including inciting to riot, disorderly conduct, assault and resisting arrest.</p>
        <p>And New Rochelle, a sprawling suburb with a diverse population and a newly booming downtown where finishing touches are being put on a Trump high-rise and more ambitious development plans are under review, became the unlikely scene of a melee.</p>
        <p>Cappelli Enterprises, which has a proposal pending before the city for a 1.2 million-square-foot residential, retail, hotel and office complex called Le Count Square, is paying for the added police presence, hiring off-duty officers here. New Roc's managers said they would enforce the new rules -- including a minimum purchase of $10 for anyone under 18 entering the fun house, ice skating arena or speedway -- with discretion. For example, well-behaved minors at the center in the afternoon will not be asked to leave at 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>If approved, Le Count Square will rise across from New Roc City, which is a pool shot away from Trump Plaza, the 40-story retail and condominium tower in which Cappelli is a partner with Donald J. Trump. A number of other developers have also joined the building boom: In all, about 800 units of housing are under construction downtown, with almost 1,000 more in the planning stage.</p>
        <p>''We are about to invest another half-billion dollars, and we can't be penny-wise and pound-foolish,'' Mr. Apicella said of the new rules at New Roc City. ''If it means that some of the fun house operations will lose some money, that's the price we have to pay to ensure the overall well-being of the downtown revitalization. That's the philosophy.''</p>
        <p>Even before the melee, there was talk of turning New Roc City into more of a retail center. The New Rochelle mayor, Noam Bramson, and Mr. Apicella said the original plan for the land that became New Roc City called for retail, but the market was too weak in the 1990s to attract it. Large national retailers would mean more lucrative rents and more sales tax revenues for the city. The melee made that shift all the more attractive, Mayor Bramson said.</p>
        <p>''Anytime an episode of this nature occurs, it necessarily impacts the thinking of everyone involved in public life,'' Mayor Bramson said. ''So it does perhaps lend some degree of additional efforts to make that happen. Entertainment is an important part of a complete and vital downtown, and it's not our desire to eliminate entertainment uses, but to have a better mix.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Apicella said that the speedway, ice arena and fun house -- run by independent operators -- comprise more than 300,000 square feet of potential retail space. Cappelli Enterprises, which is among the county's largest developers, would buy out the existing leases if the right businesses came along, he said. So far, no major retailer has signed.</p>
        <p>Some residents say the new restrictions are inconvenient, but necessary. ''It's a lesser of two evils,'' said Kenneth Daniels, an engineer who was visiting New Roc City last week with his 13-year-old daughter, Kayla. ''It's better than having this all shut down. This is putting New Rochelle back on the map.''</p>
        <p>Through much of the 20th century, New Rochelle was a budding suburb, celebrated for its handsome houses and smart business district, which at one time was the county's retail epicenter.</p>
        <p>Its proximity to Manhattan was highlighted in George M. Cohan's 1906 musical, ''Forty-Five Minutes From Broadway.'' A decade later, it was where Norman Rockwell began painting idealized pictures of small-town life. And in the 1960s, it was the place Rob and Laura Petrie called home on ''The Dick Van Dyke Show.''</p>
        <p>Lapped by Long Island Sound, the residential areas have stayed strong. But the downtown suffered a series of blows in the 1970s as a number of prominent stores closed or moved, including Arnold Constable, W. T. Grant and Bloomingdale's. Many residents turned their backs on the downtown, and by the early 1990s, there were at least 30 vacancies.</p>
        <p>In some sense, the melee at New Roc City was a reflection of the entertainment complex's own success, with its reputation for razzle-dazzle reaching beyond Westchester's borders. The police say that on April 8 young people in New York City used their cellphones to text message one another about meeting up at New Roc.</p>
        <p>''There's a real phenomenon with technology here,'' said Anthony D. Murphy, the city's deputy police commissioner. ''Cellphones and text messaging can create a large presence anywhere. It's a combination of bad coincidences: You had overcrowding, and you throw in a few hooligans. But what I witnessed for the most part were a lot of frightened teenagers who wanted to go home.''</p>
        <p>City officials seem determined not to let New Roc City threaten the progress of development downtown, especially since it was New Roc itself that helped spur so much of it. With the announcement of the new rules, Mayor Bramson urged residents and city employees to join him at the movies at New Roc on the Saturday after the melee.</p>
        <p>''There were hundreds of people who came from throughout the city and demonstrated that we're not going to define ourselves by a single episode, and we're not going to be scared to enjoy the facilities within our community,'' he said in a phone interview afterward. ''New Rochelle really demonstrated its character in the aftermath of this event.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
