<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>$8 Fee for Cars? Bravo, or Fuhgeddaboutit!</title>
    <meta content="l24traffic" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EEDE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>$8 Fee for Cars? Bravo, or Fuhgeddaboutit!</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bloomberg Draws a 25-Year Blueprint for a Greener City'' (news article, April 23):</p>
        <p>I applaud and admire Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg for his leadership in proposing an $8-a-day congestion fee for drivers in New York. It's about time that government in this country, whether on a national, state or local level, took the initiative by preparing us all for proactive, perhaps drastic, measures to protect our environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bloomberg Draws a 25-Year Blueprint for a Greener City'' (news article, April 23):</p>
        <p>I applaud and admire Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg for his leadership in proposing an $8-a-day congestion fee for drivers in New York. It's about time that government in this country, whether on a national, state or local level, took the initiative by preparing us all for proactive, perhaps drastic, measures to protect our environment.</p>
        <p>Brave, progressive reform like this is what we all must adapt to sooner than later, so bravo to Mr. Bloomberg for taking this important step.</p>
        <p>Chris Sharp  Brooklyn, April 23, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Much as I applaud Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's sincere concern about the environment and much as I applaud many of his other proposals, this proposal is tantamount to a regressive tax. The wealthy will be able to afford this tax, but the poor will not.</p>
        <p>In addition, if trucking and delivery services increase their charges to cover the congestion fee, this will also be felt by the poor and by those on fixed incomes disproportionate to the wealthy.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the fee should be leveled only on luxury vehicles and on cars with a sticker price of more than $20,000. And Town Cars and limousines.</p>
        <p>Nina Keneally  Stratford, Conn., April 23, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a longtime yellow-taxi driver, I congratulate the mayor on this forward-looking plan that includes far more than a surcharge.</p>
        <p>The plan envisions a greener, more mass-transit-friendly New York City, a city that just might be showing the way for the cities of the world to follow.</p>
        <p>The plan envisions a New York in which finally the transportation infrastructure will be more modern, more efficient, cleaner and safer.</p>
        <p>Eugene Weixel  New York, April 23, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's Earth Day announcement indicating his support for a congestion tax will probably prove to be one of the most important in New York's history. Individually owned cars are one of the leading causes of poor health in the metropolitan area, taking a toll not just in terms of accidents, but also in terms of noise pollution and air pollution.</p>
        <p>What's more, nondrivers have to pay hefty fees in the form of medical care, road repairs, higher mass transit fees, longer cab rides and higher retail prices in stores (those delivery trucks can't get through).</p>
        <p>A congestion tax will clean the air, fatten our wallets and decongest our lungs.</p>
        <p>Peter Muennig, M.D.  New York, April 23, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an assistant professor at the Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>If the average New Yorker can afford $8 to drive in Manhattan to fight congestion, the rich can do without their obscene stretch limos, and cabs should be barred from operating on any street or avenue on which a bus line runs or on any street or avenue on which there is subway service, below 125th Street.</p>
        <p>Let's be democratic.</p>
        <p>The city should require the installation of E-ZPass or OnStar-type trackers on every vehicle and divide the entire city into zones about one mile square.</p>
        <p>As you drive, the tracker records how many zone lines you have crossed, and like E-ZPass, your credit card is billed 50 cents each time you cross a zone.</p>
        <p>Why should Manhattan bill Queens and Brooklyn, unless Queens and Brooklyn and the Bronx can bill Nassau and Suffolk?</p>
        <p>But let's start with the rich.</p>
        <p>Sheldon  Bunin  Jackson Heights, Queens  April 23, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
