<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rival Offer Could Derail ABN Merger</title>
    <meta content="24bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/business/24bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">ABN AMRO Holding NV</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Barclays Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bank of America Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1262" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rival Offer Could Derail ABN Merger</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rival Offer Could Derail ABN Merger</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA WERDIGIER</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABN Amro agreed Monday to be acquired by Barclays of Britain for 67 billion euros (nearly $91 billion), creating one of the world's largest banks in a carefully constructed deal that reduces, but does not eliminate, the chance of another suitor coming in with a higher bid to buy and break up the bank.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro, the largest Dutch bank, said it had arranged to sell LaSalle Bank, its attractive American business, to Bank of America for $21 billion in cash. LaSalle's appeal had drawn the Royal Bank of Scotland Group and two other European financial companies to prepare a counteroffer for ABN Amro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The deal with Barclays reduces, but does not eliminate, the chance of another suitor coming in with a higher bid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABN Amro agreed Monday to be acquired by Barclays of Britain for 67 billion euros (nearly $91 billion), creating one of the world's largest banks in a carefully constructed deal that reduces, but does not eliminate, the chance of another suitor coming in with a higher bid to buy and break up the bank.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro, the largest Dutch bank, said it had arranged to sell LaSalle Bank, its attractive American business, to Bank of America for $21 billion in cash. LaSalle's appeal had drawn the Royal Bank of Scotland Group and two other European financial companies to prepare a counteroffer for ABN Amro.</p>
        <p>In fact, the Royal Bank of Scotland and its partners, Banco Santander Central Hispano and Fortis of Belgium, were scheduled to meet with ABN Amro executives in Amsterdam on Monday. The meeting was canceled after the European bidders learned about the LaSalle agreement, but they have still requested information about the deal, and analysts do not rule out a rival bid.</p>
        <p>The combination of ABN Amro and Barclays, which has increased investors' expectations of other cross-border mergers, would create one of the world's largest banks by total assets, about $3.1 trillion, even after LaSalle is sold, according to Bloomberg data. It will have operations in a wide geographical area, including Brazil and South Africa, with 217,000 employees and 47 million customers.</p>
        <p>Barclays agreed to pay 3.225 of its shares for each ABN Amro share, an offer worth 36.25 euros each. That is 33 percent above ABN Amro's share price on March 16, the day before the two banks said they were in takeover talks.</p>
        <p>Barclays, which traces its roots back 300 years to the banker James Barclay, agreed to locate the combined bank's headquarters in Amsterdam, rather than London. John Varley, the Barclays chief executive who will run the merged bank, will move there from London. The holding company of the new group will be called Barclays.</p>
        <p>The banks said their combination would save 3.5 billion euros a year ($4.75 billion) by 2010, including the elimination of 23,600 jobs, or 10 percent of their current work forces.</p>
        <p>As ABN Amro and Barclays executives were explaining the sealed agreement to analysts and journalists at meetings at Barclays headquarters here, the Royal Bank of Scotland and its partners told ABN Amro that it wanted information about the circumstances in which the LaSalle sale to Bank of America could be terminated.</p>
        <p>For the group to make a worthwhile counteroffer at this late stage, LaSalle would still have to be part of the ABN group.</p>
        <p>A London-based activist fund, the Children's Investment Fund, which set takeover talks in motion with its demands early this year to either put ABN Amro up for sale or break it up, expressed its own misgivings on Monday about the LaSalle sale.</p>
        <p>''We are concerned the pre-agreed sale of LaSalle Bank unfairly hinders the Royal Bank of Scotland consortium,'' the fund, which owns less than 3 percent of ABN Amro, said in a statement. It asked the Dutch company to fully disclose all details of the LaSalle sale.</p>
        <p>Bank of America is eligible for a $200 million breakup fee if the LaSalle sale is called off ''under certain limited circumstances,'' ABN Amro and Barclays said, declining to give further details.</p>
        <p>In Amsterdam on Monday, shares of ABN Amro fell 1.43 percent to 35.77 euros, indicating stockholders' skepticism about getting a higher offer for their shares. Barclays dropped 2.27 percent in London, to £7.33.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro's chief executive, Rijkman W. J. Groenink, emphasized that Barclays was his preferred partner and that he did not see any financial logic in a split-up of the bank. But he said he was willing to listen to what the Royal Bank of Scotland and its partners had to offer.</p>
        <p>''The Barclays combination is the preferred option for us,'' Mr. Groenink said. ''It has always been the ambition of ABN to build rather than break.''</p>
        <p>Even though the sale of LaSalle Bank, which would turn Bank of America into the largest in Chicago, allowed Barclays to offer more to ABN Amro shareholders, the consortium led by the Royal Bank of Scotland would still be able to offer a higher price for ABN Amro, said Euan Stirling, an investment director at Standard Life Investments in London.</p>
        <p>It could afford to make a higher offer because it can essentially split the acquisition bill three ways and generate greater cost savings, analysts have said. After such an acquisition, the consortium would break up ABN, with each member owning a different part of ABN's business.</p>
        <p>Joost de Graaf, a fund manager at Kempen Capital Management in Amsterdam, which owns both ABN Amro and Barclays shares, said, ''A counterbid is still in the cards, and if they come forward with a bid for 40 euros without any large strings attached, it will be really difficult for ABN not to talk to them.''</p>
        <p>Aside from LaSalle, the Royal Bank of Scotland is interested in the investment banking business. Santander, Spain's largest bank, is considering the Brazilian and Italian operations of ABN.</p>
        <p>Fortis, based in Brussels and Utrecht, in the Netherlands, would keep the Dutch operations as well as the private equity and private banking arms.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro and Barclays hurried to reach an agreement over the weekend to pre-empt n offer by their rivals to break up the bank after the period of exclusive talks ended on Friday.</p>
        <p>Since their talks began, gossip about somewhat similar cross-border deals has picked up.</p>
        <p>Rumors that Société Générale of France was in talks with UniCredito of Italy sent Société Générale shares up about 12 percent last week. After the markets closed on Friday, the banks denied that they were in talks. On Monday, Société Générale fell back 3 percent.</p>
        <p>UniCredito said, however, that ''in the context of regular exploratory activity of strategic growth opportunities, there are contacts,'' and analysts still think that a deal is possible.</p>
        <p>In Frankfurt on Monday, shares of Deutsche Bank rose modestly, contrary to the movement of many other bank shares, after Merrill Lynch raised its recommendation on Deutsche Bank. German analysts see a good chance that the bank is looking for a merger partner.</p>
        <p>European banks are under pressure to grow through acquisitions and compete with larger American rivals, avoiding becoming takeover targets. Barclays itself has been rumored to be a target for huge companies like Citigroup.</p>
        <p>The number and value of cross-border transactions has increased to around 30 percent of all deals from less than 20 percent in the early 1990s, according to the European Central Bank.</p>
        <p>Some of the most notable were Santander's purchase of Abbey National in 2004, and a similar acquisition by Danske Bank. Yet, cross-border deals in Europe remain the exception rather than the rule because of the difficulties in combining companies with different languages, cultures and jurisdictions.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro was regarded for years as a takeover target because of its relatively low share price. But rival banks were deterred by its mixture of businesses, which was unattractive to any single bidder. Mr. Groenink has been under pressure to increase the share price, and investors criticized failed acquisition attempts and the bank's lack of focus.</p>
        <p>In the agreement announced Monday, ABN Amro was advised by Lehman Brothers, Morgan Stanley, Rothschild and UBS. Goldman Sachs provided a fairness opinion to the supervisory board.</p>
        <p>Barclays was advised by Credit Suisse, Deutsche Bank, Lazard and JPMorgan Cazenove. Barclays and ABN Amro also used their own investment banks to advise on the deal.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch is advising the Royal Bank of Scotland Group.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
