<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Long Arms And Passport, Rookie Finds a Role</title>
    <meta content="24bulls" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/basketball/24bulls.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bulls</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Deng, Luol</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wade, Dwyane</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE7DE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Long Arms And Passport, Rookie Finds a Role</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Long Arms and Passport, Rookie Finds a Role</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>DEERFIELD, Ill., April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thabo Sefolosha and Luol Deng were bouncing the ball to each other and shooting with their feet, playing on an imaginary soccer field instead of the Chicago Bulls' practice court.</p>
        <p>''We get tired of making jump shots, so we try to kick it in,'' Deng, the Bulls' third-year small forward, said Monday with a smile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chicago’s Thabo Sefolosha, a rookie guard and the first player from Switzerland to play in the N.B.A., gamely guarded Miami’s Dwyane Wade during their first-round game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thabo Sefolosha and Luol Deng were bouncing the ball to each other and shooting with their feet, playing on an imaginary soccer field instead of the Chicago Bulls' practice court.</p>
        <p>''We get tired of making jump shots, so we try to kick it in,'' Deng, the Bulls' third-year small forward, said Monday with a smile.</p>
        <p>On the patch of grass between their townhouses in suburban Chicago, Sefolosha and Deng often kick around a real soccer ball. Once again, the 22-year-old teammates share a bond as European-raised basketball players with African heritages.</p>
        <p>Deng was born in Sudan, fled to Egypt with his diplomat father, and grew up in soccer-crazy London. He played one year of basketball at Duke and has become a mentor to Sefolosha, a rookie guard and the first player from Switzerland to play in the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>''We have a lot in common,'' Deng said. ''He is familiar with a lot of stuff in Africa and Europe, and there are a lot of things to talk about.''</p>
        <p>They boast about their favorite soccer clubs (Arsenal for Deng, Barcelona for Sefolosha), but they talk mostly about basketball. The two enjoyed breakout games in the Bulls' first-round Game 1 victory against the Miami Heat, Deng scoring 33 points and Sefolosha coming off the bench and gamely guarding Dwyane Wade.</p>
        <p>''The Game Chose Me'' is tattooed around a crowned basketball on Sefolosha's left biceps, a ready answer for those who wonder how -- coming from a country whose best-known athlete is the tennis star Roger Federer -- he made it to the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>''Basketball is so small there,'' Sefolosha said. ''My parents did not play basketball. Why basketball? I don't know.''</p>
        <p>Sefolosha's father, Patrick, is a musician and poet from South Africa. He moved to Switzerland in 1984 to escape apartheid because he was married to Sefolosha's mother, Christine, an artist from Switzerland who is white.</p>
        <p>The couple, now divorced, have two sons, Kgomotso and Thabo (pronounced TAH-bow, which means ''the one who brings joy,'' in Sotho, a South African dialect). The brothers first played basketball when a neighbor in their hometown, Vevey, invited them to his club. Thabo, then 11, was hooked.</p>
        <p>He and his brother excelled on the local club team, and they started watching the N.B.A. on videotapes their coaches made. Sefolosha's favorite team in the '90s? ''The Bulls,'' he answered without hesitation.</p>
        <p>By the time Sefolosha was 17, he played in Switzerland's professional league (where Kgomotso plays now). Sefolosha advanced to play three seasons in the premier French league and one season in Italy's A-league, where the Bulls scout Ivica Dukan discovered him. Sefolosha was drafted No. 13 last year by Philadelphia, but the Bulls traded their 16th pick for his rights on draft night.</p>
        <p>When he arrived in Chicago, he already spoke English fluently. Deng suggested he move into the empty townhouse next door, and Sefolosha began the process of assimilation into the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>''He's a pretty cerebral guy,'' Bulls Coach Scott Skiles said. ''He really tries to study the game, and he knows what he can or can't do.''</p>
        <p>Skiles would not say whether he would give Sefolosha extended minutes again in Game 2 on Tuesday; Sefolosha played 18 minutes in the opener because Kirk Hinrich had foul trouble. ''I don't want Thabo to feel like if things don't go well in Game 2, that's it,'' Skiles said.</p>
        <p>Sefolosha said that his strategy against Wade was simple: He tried to force him left (Wade has an injured left shoulder), or ''just try to stay in front of him because he's so fast, give him space.'' Wade scored 21 points in Game 1 but shot 3 for 9 in the first half.</p>
        <p>Sefolosha also gave Lakers guard Kobe Bryant fits with his 6-foot-7 frame and 7-foot wingspan in the Bulls' 94-89 victory in December. Bryant shot 6 for 19 and scored 19 points, more than 12 below his season average.</p>
        <p>''You face the best players of the world. It's fun and challenging, and I love that,'' Sefolosha said.</p>
        <p>Skiles said: ''He does a good job of giving the impression that he's unfazed. He's had his ups and downs with regard to that.''</p>
        <p>''But,'' Skiles added, Sefolosha is ''not going to get too high or too low.''</p>
        <p>Sefolosha says that his home country has fostered his even temper. ''I love Switzerland; people are laid-back and easy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His determination to forge a career in the N.B.A. has a dual purpose. If Sefolosha works in a foreign country, he is exempt from fulfilling his six-month army duty, which he says will expire when he is 27.</p>
        <p>He is, however, eager to return for a working holiday. Sefolosha will hold his inaugural basketball camp for 250 children in Switzerland this summer, modeled after the camp Deng holds in London.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to come to his camp, and he's going to come to mine,'' Sefolosha said. ''We can really have a good friendship being that close.''</p>
        <p>If not on the basketball court, they know where to find each other.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The league fined Bulls guard Kirk Hinrich $25,000 for flinging his mouthguard into the stands in frustration during the third quarter of the Bulls' 96-91 victory against the Heat in Game 1. Hinrich was angry at being called for his fourth personal foul. He was assessed a technical for the incident.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
