<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Projections Show Troubles Still Loom for Benefit Plans</title>
    <meta content="24benefit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/washington/24benefit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842580"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7DE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Projections Show Troubles Still Loom for Benefit Plans</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Projections Show Troubles Still Loom for Benefit Plans</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS and ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert; Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush Administration says rising medical costs and looming retirement of baby boom generation are set to overwhelm Medicare program by 2019; says Social Security trust fund is on track to run out of reserves by 2041; new estimates are similar to 2006 projections, but have become significantly more ominous over last six years; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two seemingly inexorable forces, rising medical costs and the looming retirement of the baby boom generation, are set to overwhelm the Medicare program by 2019, the Bush administration reported Monday.</p>
        <p>The Social Security trust fund, which finances the government's giant retirement program, is on track to run out of reserves by 2041 -- less dire than the outlook for Medicare but still not sustainable without raising taxes or cutting benefits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rising medical costs and the retirement of baby boomers are set to overwhelm the Medicare program by 2019, the Bush administration reported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two seemingly inexorable forces, rising medical costs and the looming retirement of the baby boom generation, are set to overwhelm the Medicare program by 2019, the Bush administration reported Monday.</p>
        <p>The Social Security trust fund, which finances the government's giant retirement program, is on track to run out of reserves by 2041 -- less dire than the outlook for Medicare but still not sustainable without raising taxes or cutting benefits.</p>
        <p>The new estimates, prepared by the trustees of the federal government's main entitlement programs for the elderly and the disabled, are broadly similar to projections from last year, but have become significantly more ominous over the last six years.</p>
        <p>''Without change, rising costs will drive government spending to unprecedented levels, consume nearly all projected federal revenues and threaten America's future prosperity,'' said Henry M. Paulson Jr., secretary of the Treasury and a trustee of the Social Security and Medicare trust funds.</p>
        <p>But Congressional Democrats retorted that President Bush had squandered valuable time after his re-election in 2004 by pushing for an overhaul of Social Security that would have allowed people to channel payroll tax contributions to private investment accounts. That proposal got nowhere in Congress, and Mr. Bush effectively dropped his effort last year.</p>
        <p>''Instead of peddling an ill-conceived Social Security privatization plan that has already been overwhelmingly rejected by the American people, the administration should turn its attention to strengthening Medicare,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson said he had little hope of reaching agreement with Democratic leaders in Congress.</p>
        <p>''There was a time when I was a bit more optimistic than I am today,'' Mr. Paulson said Monday. ''I'm getting a little tired of playing solitaire.''</p>
        <p>Though Medicare spending has climbed more slowly than expected in some areas, particularly the new prescription drug benefit, the trustees reiterated their dire warnings about the financial outlook for both Medicare and Social Security.</p>
        <p>The trustees said that Medicare's problems were more immediate and more difficult to solve. Medicare costs are propelled upward by increases in prices for medical care and by an imminent explosion in the number of retirees as 76 million members of the baby boom generation become eligible for benefits.</p>
        <p>Spending on Medicare hit $408 billion last year, about 3.1 percent of the nation's gross domestic product, and was the biggest federal program after the Department of Defense.</p>
        <p>The new report projects that Medicare's share of the total economy will double to more than 6.5 percent of the gross domestic product by 2030.</p>
        <p>For the first time, the trustees issued a formal ''warning'' about Medicare's increasing reliance on general tax revenues, rather than payroll taxes and premiums specifically earmarked for the program.</p>
        <p>This finding requires President Bush to submit proposed solutions to Congress early next year.</p>
        <p>In February, Mr. Bush proposed to cut the growth of Medicare by $65.6 billion over the next five years. Under those proposals, more and more Medicare beneficiaries would have to pay higher premiums for coverage of prescription drugs and doctors' services, and Medicare would trim payments to most types of health care providers.</p>
        <p>Administration officials as well as the program's independent trustees said Medicare's actual outlook over the next decade was probably worse than the official projections.</p>
        <p>That is because the projections assume that Medicare will follow current law and sharply reduce payments to doctors. As a practical matter, Congress has blocked those reductions for the last four years and is likely to continue doing so to prevent physicians from refusing to take Medicare patients.</p>
        <p>John L. Palmer, one of two independent trustees of Medicare and Social Security, estimated that Medicare spending would be as much as $400 billion higher over the next 10 years if Congress blocks the reductions in payments to physicians.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, the senior Republican on the Senate Finance Committee, said Democrats were ignoring the urgent fiscal problems that lie just ahead.</p>
        <p>The Democrats' budget blueprint, passed in different form by the House and the Senate, ''doesn't do anything to address entitlement spending'' and simply assumes $15 billion in savings by cutting payments to certain health care providers, Mr. Grassley said.</p>
        <p>There were a few bright spots in the report.</p>
        <p>Spending from Medicare's Hospital Insurance Trust Fund was lower than expected last year because of ''an abrupt decrease in the number of hospital admissions.'' After increasing about 2 percent a year for some years, the number of admissions appeared to decline by 4 percent last year, to 13.1 million, the trustees said.</p>
        <p>Michael O. Leavitt, the secretary of health and humans services, said it was possible that the new drug benefit for Medicare recipients could have improved their health and reduced the need for hospital care.</p>
        <p>But an analysis of the data by Medicare actuaries says the sharp decline in hospital admissions ''is believed to be a one-time random fluctuation.''</p>
        <p>The trustees said their new estimate of the cost of Medicare's prescription drug benefit over the next decade was ''significantly lower'' than the estimate they made a year ago. They described this as an ''extraordinary change,'' reflecting several factors.</p>
        <p>Private insurers, which administer the drug benefit, are submitting lower bids to the government, in the expectation that they can increase the use of low-cost generic drugs and control the use of brand-name medicines, the trustees said.</p>
        <p>David Sloane, director of government relations at AARP, the lobby for older Americans, said Medicare's problems could not be solved without addressing those of the overall health care system.</p>
        <p>''Medicare's insolvency is a symptom of the disease, which is escalating costs throughout our health care system,'' Mr. Sloane said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
