<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scrushy to Pay $81 Million To Settle S.E.C. Lawsuit</title>
    <meta content="24healths" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/business/24healths.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">HealthSouth Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Scrushy, Richard M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E3DE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scrushy to Pay $81 Million To Settle S.E.C. Lawsuit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Scrushy to Pay $81 Million to Settle S.E.C. Lawsuit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KYLE WHITMIRE</byline>
      <dateline>BIRMINGHAM, Ala., April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former chief executive of HealthSouth, Richard M. Scrushy, reached a settlement with the Securities and Exchange Commission on Monday, agreeing to pay more than $81 million. The amount represents the forfeiture of $77.5 million and $3.5 million in fines.</p>
        <p>The settlement also prohibits Mr. Scrushy from serving as an officer or director of a publicly traded company for at least five years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former chief executive of HealthSouth agreed to pay more than $81 million to settle a case over accounting fraud.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The former chief executive of HealthSouth, Richard M. Scrushy, reached a settlement with the Securities and Exchange Commission on Monday, agreeing to pay more than $81 million. The amount represents the forfeiture of $77.5 million and $3.5 million in fines.</p>
        <p>The settlement also prohibits Mr. Scrushy from serving as an officer or director of a publicly traded company for at least five years.</p>
        <p>The agreement is the latest development in a case that began in March 2003, after an S.E.C. lawsuit and a subsequent F.B.I. raid uncovered accounting fraud at HealthSouth, the chain of rehabilitation hospitals founded by Mr. Scrushy.</p>
        <p>The sting of the settlement for Mr. Scrushy might not be as bad as it appears. In another order filed on Monday, Federal District Judge Inge P. Johnson said the settlements and judgments in three other civil cases could count as a $71.5 million credit toward Mr. Scrushy's disgorgement to the S.E.C. In effect, the agreement with the S.E.C. will cost Mr. Scrushy an additional $9.5 million.</p>
        <p>In January 2006, an Alabama Circuit Court judge ordered Mr. Scrushy to pay back more than $52 million of bonuses and interest as part of a derivatives lawsuit. A similar action last year in Delaware cost him another $17 million, and he paid $1.5 million to settle a lawsuit with HealthSouth employees who lost pension investments as a result of the accounting scandal.</p>
        <p>According to an S.E.C. lawyer, Jack Worland, the settlement was not the largest the commission has reached with an executive, but it was still substantial.</p>
        <p>''Without having looked at the numbers,'' Mr. Worland said, ''we would have to guess that it is probably within the top five.''</p>
        <p>As part of the settlement, Mr. Scrushy neither admitted nor denied accusations that he was responsible for the fraud.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C.'s civil lawsuit had been placed on hold, pending a criminal case against Mr. Scrushy. In that 2005 trial, a federal jury in Birmingham acquitted Mr. Scrushy of all charges that he had participated in the fraud.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. lawsuit has been in mediation since November 2005, but the parties began to negotiate seriously in December, S.E.C. officials said.</p>
        <p>''For a while we were very far apart,'' Mr. Worland said on Monday. ''I guess Mr. Scrushy had to resolve some of the uncertainties in his life.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Scrushy was found guilty last year by a federal jury in Montgomery, Ala., of bribing the governor of Alabama at the time, Don Siegelman. The judge has not set a sentencing date, and Mr. Scrushy intends to appeal.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. had also included HealthSouth as a defendant in the lawsuit, but the company settled in 2005 for $100 million. The company had no comment on Mr. Scrushy's latest settlement.</p>
        <p>Even with the settlement, Mr. Scrushy's legal woes continue. A class-action lawsuit by shareholders and bondholders is still pending in federal court, in addition to a derivative action in state court.</p>
        <p>''As part of the S.E.C. rules in the settlement today, we cannot comment on this case,'' Mr. Scrushy's lawyer, Arthur W. Leach, said. ''However, we will continue to vigorously defend Mr. Scrushy against the various civil suits in federal and state court.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
