<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raptors' Mitchell Finds That a Little Quality Time Is the Key</title>
    <meta content="24raptors" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/basketball/24raptors.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, Sam</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6DE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raptors' Mitchell Finds That a Little Quality Time Is the Key</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Raptors’ Mitchell Finds That a Little Quality Time Is the Key</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twirling a toothpick in his mouth, Raptors Coach Sam Mitchell competed against T. J. Ford, his starting point guard, in a 3-point shooting competition after practice Monday afternoon. After grimacing and growling following his game-ending miss, a grinning Mitchell ambled toward reporters.</p>
        <p>It was difficult to tell that Toronto was a little more than 24 hours from Game 2 in its first-round N.B.A. playoffs series against the Nets. The Nets, after all, had stolen the home-court advantage from the young Raptors with a victory in Game 1 of this best-of-seven series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Raptors Coach Sam Mitchell’s smile and his moxie have helped him orchestrate the biggest turnaround in the N.B.A.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Twirling a toothpick in his mouth, Raptors Coach Sam Mitchell competed against T. J. Ford, his starting point guard, in a 3-point shooting competition after practice Monday afternoon. After grimacing and growling following his game-ending miss, a grinning Mitchell ambled toward reporters.</p>
        <p>It was difficult to tell that Toronto was a little more than 24 hours from Game 2 in its first-round N.B.A. playoffs series against the Nets. The Nets, after all, had stolen the home-court advantage from the young Raptors with a victory in Game 1 of this best-of-seven series.</p>
        <p>Yet Mitchell's attitude should not come as a surprise. All season, his smile and moxie have helped him orchestrate the biggest turnaround in the N.B.A. and become one of the leading candidates for the coach of the year award, which will be announced Tuesday.</p>
        <p>In a Sports Illustrated poll of 248 N.B.A. players last year, Mitchell was voted the league's worst coach. Around the same time, the Raptors hired Bryan Colangelo as their new president.</p>
        <p>New executives often hire new coaches, and Colangelo had every reason to fire Mitchell, who was leading the Raptors to a 27-55 record.</p>
        <p>But Mitchell kept his job and led the Raptors to 47 victories, their first Atlantic Division title and their first playoff appearance since 2002. On Monday, he put his situation in perspective.</p>
        <p>''I don't have an aunt or an uncle, never met my grandparents,'' he said. ''My brother died at 24. I've been through a lot tougher things in life.''</p>
        <p>He shied away from taking credit for the team's accomplishments.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day, I go downstairs and I pull up my stats for the season,'' Mitchell said. ''I don't have one rebound. I don't have one assist. I didn't score 1 point. I didn't turn it over, either. I'm not oversimplifying what we do, but at the end of the day, the players got to make the plays.''</p>
        <p>Mitchell, who retired in 2002 after 13 seasons as a player, spoke of his hands-on approach with players. Instead of obsessing over game tape, he said, he would rather see his assistants work with players on the court.</p>
        <p>That distaste for endless film study stands as a contrast to the Nets' Lawrence Frank, who has built his reputation on a tireless work ethic in the office and the film room.</p>
        <p>Mitchell, whose contract expires at the end of the season, said that managing egos was the most difficult part of his job.</p>
        <p>''You got to instill discipline,'' he said. ''You got to make sure guys play the way they're supposed to play. You got to make sure guys are where they're supposed to be.''</p>
        <p>Mitchell said that his best coaching move of the season was probably listening to Ford's advice late in games against the Los Angeles Clippers and the Portland Trail Blazers last December. Ford made the winning plays in each of those games.</p>
        <p>Ford said: ''Being here, being able to talk to him, being an extension of him, I feel comfortable asking him questions, and he feels comfortable getting on me when I'm not doing what I'm supposed to do. I really admire that because I know he wants me to get better. He knows the talent that I have.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
