<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AstraZeneca Acquires a Biotech Company</title>
    <meta content="24drug" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/business/24drug.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">AstraZeneca</org>
        <org class="online_producer">MedImmune Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1DE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AstraZeneca Acquires a Biotech Company</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">AstraZeneca Acquires a Biotech Company</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AstraZeneca said yesterday it had agreed to acquire MedImmune for $15.6 billion, in perhaps the most emphatic sign yet of the push by big drug makers into biotechnology.</p>
        <p>The all-cash deal for MedImmune, worth $58 a share, appears to be the largest purchase ever of an American biotechnology company, according to Recombinant Capital, a company that tracks such transactions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The $15.6 billion deal to acquire MedImmune is perhaps the most emphatic sign yet of the push by big drug makers into biotechnology.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AstraZeneca said yesterday it had agreed to acquire MedImmune for $15.6 billion, in perhaps the most emphatic sign yet of the push by big drug makers into biotechnology.</p>
        <p>The all-cash deal for MedImmune, worth $58 a share, appears to be the largest purchase ever of an American biotechnology company, according to Recombinant Capital, a company that tracks such transactions.</p>
        <p>For AstraZeneca, based in London, the acquisition would help bolster its product pipeline after some recent setbacks, and would supplement its portfolio with biologic drugs -- protein-based therapies that are made in cultures of living cells.</p>
        <p>''We have taken very decisive action to significantly accelerate delivery of this biologics strategy,'' David Brennan, an American who was promoted to chief executive of AstraZeneca in 2006 and has engineered a flurry of acquisitions and product licenses.</p>
        <p>Big pharmaceutical companies have been eager either to license products from biotechnology companies or to buy companies outright to replenish depleted product pipelines.</p>
        <p>There is another motive, too: because biotechnology protein drugs are far more complex than typical pills, which are simple chemicals, they have been largely insulated from the generic competition that can wipe out sales of a blockbuster drug almost overnight.</p>
        <p>The deal will also move AstraZeneca into vaccines, a former pharmaceutical industry backwater that is now being viewed as attractive because of rising vaccine prices. The drug giants Pfizer and Novartis also moved into the vaccine business through acquisitions last year.</p>
        <p>MedImmune, based in Gaithersburg, Md., is one of the largest companies in the biotechnology industry and was one of the earliest to become profitable. MedImmune posted revenues last year of $1.3 billion, mainly from Synagis, a drug to prevent a respiratory infection in infants, and had net earnings of $48.7 million.</p>
        <p>The company is perhaps best known, though, for FluMist, a nasal spray flu vaccine that so far has not lived up to expectations. The company is hoping that will change after next month, when it hopes to win approval for FluMist to be used in children younger than 5, a group likely to be needle-phobic.</p>
        <p>MedImmune is also entitled to royalties on sales of Merck's new cervical cancer vaccine and on a similar one being developed by GlaxoSmithKline.</p>
        <p>MedImmune's stock rose nearly 18 percent, to $56.57. AstraZeneca shares fell 4 percent, to £28.32.</p>
        <p>MedImmune, which had been under shareholder pressure to put itself on the block, announced on April 12 that it would consider doing so after months of resisting the idea. Carl C. Icahn, who had reported in February owning a little over 1 percent, threatened to start a proxy fight to force the sale of the company because of its ''lackluster'' performance.</p>
        <p>Even before that, Matrix Asset Advisors, a money management firm in New York that owns about 0.7 percent of MedImmune's shares, had been agitating for a sale, saying that a pharmaceutical company would attach more value to MedImmune than the public markets were.</p>
        <p>That proved to be prescient. The $58 a share AstraZeneca will pay represents a 21 percent premium over MedImmune's closing price on Friday and is 53 percent higher than MedImmune's closing price the day before it announced that it would put itself on the block.</p>
        <p>Premiums of 50 percent or more are no longer unusual for such deals, and there can be bidding wars for biotech companies, as in this case. The average premium on big biotechnology acquisitions in 2006 was 60 percent, twice the average of the deals in 2003 to 2005, according to Ernst &amp; Young.</p>
        <p>Even so, based on MedImmune's sales and prospects, some analysts said AstraZeneca was paying far more than deals last year in which Novartis bought Chiron and Merck of Germany acquired Serono.</p>
        <p>Brian Lian, an analyst with CIBC World Markets, called the MedImmune price ''extraordinary,'' saying that it was ''difficult to rationalize.''</p>
        <p>But AstraZeneca said the deal would add to its cash earnings per share, excluding amortization, by 2009 and that it could achieve $500 million a year in cost savings. It said it did not expect big layoffs at MedImmune and would try to retain that company's management and employees. David M. Mott, chief executive of MedImmune, will become a senior executive at AstraZeneca.</p>
        <p>AstraZeneca is dependent on a few drugs for most of its sales growth, including the anti-cholesterol pill Crestor, Nexium for stomach acid and Seroquel for schizophrenia.</p>
        <p>But it has suffered several setbacks over the last couple of years, including the failure in clinical trials of potential blockbusters -- licensed from biotechnology companies -- to treat stroke and atherosclerosis. It also dropped work on Exanta, a blood thinner, and Galida, for diabetes. Its heart drug Toprol-XL is losing patent protection.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
