<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Checker Cabs Could Fly: Hop In, the Meter's Running</title>
    <meta content="24road" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/business/24road.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE ROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Road</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">DayJet Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EEDF143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Checker Cabs Could Fly: Hop In, the Meter's Running</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">If Checker Cabs Could Fly: Hop in, the Meter’s Running</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE idea of cheap little jets that resembled sport utility vehicles and could be produced by the thousands seemed far-fetched -- and some even said preposterous -- when the two pioneers in the field, Eclipse Aviation, in Albuquerque, and Adam Aircraft, near Denver, were gearing up for production six years ago.</p>
        <p>Edward E. Iacobucci was an early believer. He had worked for I.B.M. for 11 years before founding a software company, Citrix Systems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>DayJet plans to begin flying the nation’s first on-demand, per seat air taxi service in June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE idea of cheap little jets that resembled sport utility vehicles and could be produced by the thousands seemed far-fetched -- and some even said preposterous -- when the two pioneers in the field, Eclipse Aviation, in Albuquerque, and Adam Aircraft, near Denver, were gearing up for production six years ago.</p>
        <p>Edward E. Iacobucci was an early believer. He had worked for I.B.M. for 11 years before founding a software company, Citrix Systems.</p>
        <p>He was retired in 2001, when he ran into Vern Raburn, a former Microsoft executive and founder of Eclipse who was developing a little five-passenger jet with a price tag of $875,000.</p>
        <p>''What really interested me more than this notion of 'an airplane in every garage' that some people were talking about was the notion that you can mass produce these things at such a low price,'' Mr. Iacobucci said. ''Vern told me he wanted to be the Henry Ford of aviation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Iacobucci, now 53, gave this some thought and decided that if Mr. Raburn could be Henry Ford, he could be Checker Cab.</p>
        <p>That was the beginning of DayJet, a company based in Delray Beach, Fla., that recently took delivery of its first three Eclipse 500 jets. The company plans to begin flying the nation's first on-demand, per seat air taxi service in June. DayJet, with $68 million in equity capital, has so far ordered 239 Eclipse 500 jets (each one selling for $1.5 million).</p>
        <p>Competitors who are considering getting into the air taxi business will be watching carefully. DayJet plans to operate at first in a few regional markets in Florida. By fall, DayJet expects to be flying between 10 secondary airports with 35 jets, and by the end of the year, it expects to have as many as 15 routes and 50 aircraft.</p>
        <p>The keys to the business are ''on-demand'' and ''per seat.'' Air taxis, Mr. Iacobucci said, will open a new market in business aviation, mostly to people who now drive on business trips of 300 or so miles. It is also hoping to attract business travelers who now fly from, say, Gainesville, Fla., to Pensacola, Fla., on commercial airlines that route them through a hub like Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Skeptics insist that you can't make money running an airplane on demand like a taxi because of the economics and the enormously complicated logistics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Iacobucci acknowledges that it is very complicated logistically.</p>
        <p>''We are providing a service that never existed before,'' he said, ''so you get into all sorts of things like value networks and viral marketing that help us identify not just the city but which combination of cities works best'' to find on-demand passengers. ''You have to balance demand and supply in a world where you don't know what demand is.''</p>
        <p>I nodded and made notes. Somewhere deep, I had a sinking feeling similar to those I vaguely recalled from college economics courses.</p>
        <p>How does this work? I asked.</p>
        <p>''Think of it as a time arbitrage system,'' he said.</p>
        <p>I tried.</p>
        <p>''The value of a leg from A to B, well, you can quote that in a myriad of ways that involve how you value your time,'' he said. ''If it takes an hour to fly from Boca to Gainesville, and I as a customer say, 'I can't leave any earlier today than 9 a.m. and have to be there by 10:30' that's going to be an expensive ticket, maybe close to $4 a mile, because chances are I am not going to get enough other people to converge with you.</p>
        <p>''But our technology lets people game the system, until they find the point -- say, try 9:30 or try 7:30 a.m. -- where they feel comfortable with the price matching the value received.''</p>
        <p>How much does it cost? It depends.</p>
        <p>It costs about $600 each way to fly between Florida cities, through Atlanta. It costs about the same to fly directly from Fort Lauderdale to Tallahassee, he said. But there's only one flight a day. ''Our price for Fort Lauderdale to Tallahassee may not beat that every time, but it can range from between $300 and $1,000 each way, depending on your value of your time,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In general, Mr. Iacobucci said, fares will average about the same as unrestricted coach fares on commercial airlines.</p>
        <p>I was still hanging in there.</p>
        <p>''Every reservation that comes in,'' he said, ''is an opportunity to find a better solution, which is the essence of complexity science.''</p>
        <p>By definition, an air taxi cannot be on a schedule, he went on, adding: ''The minute you nail something down and build a schedule, you're eliminating options. Don't make a decision until you have to. That is what it is all about.''</p>
        <p>I thought I would show that part to my wife and my editor, both of whom think I should plan ahead better. The phrase ''time arbitrage'' will be most useful.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, I'm test-flying one of Mr. Iacobucci's taxis next month. I'll let you know how I fare.</p>
        <p>ON THE ROAD Email: jsharkey@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Email: jsharkey@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
