<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Modernity Drills Through Rock Toward an Alpine Hamlet</title>
    <meta content="24austria" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/world/europe/24austria.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="KAISERTAL JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tyrol (Austria)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alps Mountains</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Austria</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Alps Mountains</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6DF143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Modernity Drills Through Rock Toward an Alpine Hamlet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Modernity Drills Through Rock Toward an Alpine Hamlet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>THE KAISERTAL, Austria, April 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Austria's Kaisertal is one of last inhabited valleys in Tyrolean Alps not connected by road to outside world; 2,690-foot tunnel to be completed in 2008 will alter lives of valley's 30 residents, who now come and go on foot; Kaisertal residents generally welcome tunnel; critics say tunnel will spoil pristine valley; photos, maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Years from now, if Sarah Leitner ever wants to regale her children with stories about her daily walk to school, she will not have to embellish, even a little: this plucky 8-year-old must hike a mountain to get to her home in this remote Alpine valley.</p>
        <p>True, there are 300 wooden steps winding up the steep slope. And her mother, Ursula, waits for her at the top, in a rusty, mud-spattered car that bears no license plates because it never sees a regular road.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the 30 people who live in the Kaisertal, Austria, there has always been only one way in and one way out: on foot. Yet next March, that isolation will come to an end.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Years from now, if Sarah Leitner ever wants to regale her children with stories about her daily walk to school, she will not have to embellish, even a little: this plucky 8-year-old must hike a mountain to get to her home in this remote Alpine valley.</p>
        <p>True, there are 300 wooden steps winding up the steep slope. And her mother, Ursula, waits for her at the top, in a rusty, mud-spattered car that bears no license plates because it never sees a regular road.</p>
        <p>The Leitners live in the Kaisertal, one of the last inhabited valleys in the Alps not connected by road to the outside world. In this isolated mountain settlement, food and fuel are carried in on an aerial ropeway. Its few vehicles were winched up the stairs many years ago, and are now stranded there, in an Arcadian landscape of fields and farmhouses, circled by jagged, snow-capped peaks.</p>
        <p>For the 30 people who live in the Kaisertal, there has always been one way in and one way out: on foot.</p>
        <p>Next March, however, work will be completed on a 2,690-foot tunnel through the mountain, and the valley's splendid isolation will come to an abrupt end. It cannot end fast enough for Sarah Leitner.</p>
        <p>''I'll be really glad when the road comes,'' she said the other day, trudging up the steps, her backpack bobbing like a buoy in a choppy sea. ''Finally, my friends will be able to come visit me.''</p>
        <p>The decision to build the tunnel was made after decades of dispute over whether to make the valley more accessible, and it is still arousing complex emotions among people in this gentle land of gingerbread houses and onion-domed churches near the German border.</p>
        <p>Residents of the Kaisertal generally welcome the connection, citing the ease of shopping, going to a doctor or seeing a movie, without having to put on hiking boots and go on a wilderness walk.</p>
        <p>But nature lovers who savor such pursuits say the tunnel will bring taxis and tourists, followed by real estate development -- spoiling one of the last truly pristine valleys in the Tyrolean Alps.</p>
        <p>To prevent that, Ebbs, the town that includes the Kaisertal, plans to limit access to residents, emergency vehicles and service people. It will issue them a plastic card, with an encoded chip, that will open a gate at the mouth of the tunnel, next to the town.</p>
        <p>Over time, however, critics predict that the limitations on access will be relaxed, particularly as the economic incentives of opening up the valley to outside traffic become more tantalizing.</p>
        <p>''This region is an El Dorado for people who live in Bavaria; they can drive here in an hour,'' said Norbert Wolf, an environmentalist who has campaigned against the tunnel for years. ''I'm very skeptical that this tunnel will only be used by the people who live there.''</p>
        <p>Today, the 30 residents subsist on farming and running small guesthouses, which also sell beer and apple strudel to passing hikers. The valley's population was once about 70, but it has dwindled as residents, particularly young ones, have left for opportunities in the outside world.</p>
        <p>Josef Ritzer, the mayor of Ebbs, said the remainder would eventually have packed up, too. Showing visitors around the other day, he pointed to an abandoned Alpine house, clinging stubbornly to a hillside.</p>
        <p>''Without the tunnel, the rest of the valley will end up like that,'' Mr. Ritzer said. ''We want people to stay, but to do that, we have to give them the same opportunities as people in the town.''</p>
        <p>The project is budgeted at nearly $9 million, of which the province of Tyrol is kicking in roughly three-quarters. Austria specializes in highly engineered tunnels, and this one has its own marvels, including a 180-degree curve in the middle.</p>
        <p>Workers are blasting a path through a ridge to connect the tunnel to a dirt road in the valley. Their jackhammers echo noisily off the mountains, something not lost on the project's critics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf does not dispute that the residents needed something more convenient than a winding staircase. His solution would have been to replace the aerial ropeway -- a rickety contraption -- with a modern gondola that could have carried people as well as provisions.</p>
        <p>He noted that other places thrive while banning private cars. The glamorous Swiss ski resort Zermatt, for example, requires visitors to park outside town and take a train or taxi the rest of the way.</p>
        <p>In the Kaisertal, however, people have simpler desires. Ursula Leitner said she would like to be able to carry her groceries home, rather than putting them on the ropeway. She would like to go the annual ball in Ebbs without having to hike down with her shoes and gown in a bag.</p>
        <p>More important, the family could get prompt access to medical treatment. Last fall, Sarah became violently ill with a stomach virus and had to hike down to a doctor. A group of walkers, not understanding the girl's distress, poked fun at her as she and her parents hurried past.</p>
        <p>There are longer-term drawbacks to life in the Kaisertal. Young people struggle to find spouses willing to move here. Failed relationships are common. Loneliness hangs in the thin mountain air.</p>
        <p>Yet there is also romance and idealism to living in this Alpine version of Walden Pond. Neighbors take care of one another. Each Monday, they gather at one of the guesthouses to play cards.</p>
        <p>It's like one big family, though, as Josef Schwaighofer, 43, the owner of the guesthouse, notes, ''None of the families is related.'' Pausing, he adds with a twinkle, ''that we know of.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwaighofer, who grew up here, has never considered leaving. But he said fewer and fewer people appreciate the valley's slow rhythm of life. For them, the tunnel is an escape hatch. ''They want to get into town quickly,'' he said with a hint of sadness. ''Life today is getting faster and faster.''</p>
        <p>KAISERTAL JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
