<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Shortage of Pitchers Forces the Yankees to Turn to a Prized Prospect</title>
    <meta content="24pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/baseball/24pins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hughes, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Shortage of Pitchers Forces the Yankees to Turn to a Prized Prospect</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Shortage of Pitchers Forces the Yankees to Turn to a Prized Prospect</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla., April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees did not plan it this way. But then, they did not expect to lose so many starting pitchers to injuries, either. So Phil Hughes, the 20-year-old right-hander who may be the best pitching prospect in all of minor league baseball, will make his Yankees debut Thursday.</p>
        <p>''My exact goal, and I talked openly about it, was that hopefully we'd be able to keep him down all year,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said. ''But reality kicks in when you play a season. We have a team need and we need a starter. Right now, we're thinking about one start.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phil Hughes, the 20-year-old right-hander who may be the best pitching prospect in all of minor league baseball, will make his Yankees debut on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees did not plan it this way. But then, they did not expect to lose so many starting pitchers to injuries, either. So Phil Hughes, the 20-year-old right-hander who may be the best pitching prospect in all of minor league baseball, will make his Yankees debut Thursday.</p>
        <p>''My exact goal, and I talked openly about it, was that hopefully we'd be able to keep him down all year,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said. ''But reality kicks in when you play a season. We have a team need and we need a starter. Right now, we're thinking about one start.''</p>
        <p>Hughes would be the youngest pitcher to start for the Yankees since 18-year-old José Rijo in 1984, according to the Elias Sports Bureau.</p>
        <p>The Yankees could have left Chase Wright in the rotation to face the Boston Red Sox again Friday. But Wright allowed homers to four batters in a row Sunday night, and the Yankees returned him to Class AA Trenton on Monday.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' principal owner, George Steinbrenner, was displeased that the Yankees were swept in Boston, and he told that to Manager Joe Torre when Torre called him Monday.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, he wasn't happy about the weekend,'' Torre said. ''But that was the extent of it.''</p>
        <p>If Steinbrenner was behind Hughes's promotion, Cashman and Torre did not say. Torre spoke with Cashman on Sunday about the need for a new starter, and Cashman said that he consulted Monday with Dave Miley, the manager at Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre; Dave Eiland, the Class AAA pitching coach; Nardi Contreras, the minor league pitching coordinator; and Mark Newman, the senior vice president for baseball operations.</p>
        <p>''Right now, he's the best pitcher at Triple A,'' Cashman said. ''That's the bottom line.''</p>
        <p>Hughes was scheduled to start here Tuesday, but the Yankees decided to back him up two days to face Toronto at Yankee Stadium. Jeff Karstens will start the series opener against Boston on Friday, when Mike Mussina will test his strained left hamstring for Trenton.</p>
        <p>If Mussina comes through that start healthy, Cashman and Torre said, his next start would be in Texas against the Rangers on May 3. In theory, that would bump Hughes out of the rotation, because Cashman said that Karstens was still ahead of him on the depth chart.</p>
        <p>But Torre did not dismiss the idea that Hughes could stay longer. Carl Pavano, another starter, is on the disabled list with a forearm strain and has not been cleared to throw off a mound.</p>
        <p>''I think we have to be realistic; we have people up here,'' Torre said. ''But he's up here and he's going to pitch Thursday, and if we're comfortable and we see that he's comfortable, we'll see what we do. Especially with Pavano down at this point in time, if we think it's the right thing for him -- and, of course, for us -- we're certainly going to look at it.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees badly need innings from their starters. According to Elias, Yankees starters had averaged 4.9 innings per outing through Sunday, ranking last in the majors.</p>
        <p>They are not likely to receive a lengthy outing from Hughes. The Yankees have tried to be careful with Hughes's workload, restricting his innings in the second half last season. Hughes has pitched only 2531/3 innings in the minors, including a career-high 146 last season.</p>
        <p>Cashman said that Torre would not be asked to restrict Hughes's innings, but he added that Torre was ''not going to stretch him out.'' Torre said that he would see how hard Hughes has to compete to determine how long he pitches.</p>
        <p>''A lot of it is going to depend on how comfortable he is to watch,'' Torre said. ''Is he going to get in trouble every inning? I think sometimes pitch counts don't tell you the whole story. You may wear yourself out after 70 or 80 if you have to deal with pressure every inning.''</p>
        <p>Hughes had one good start and one bad start for Scranton this season before firing six scoreless innings last Wednesday at Syracuse, allowing two hits and striking out 10.</p>
        <p>Hughes told reporters that he threw 14 changeups, the most he had ever thrown in a game, rounding out his fastball/curveball repertory.</p>
        <p>''Everybody has been clamoring for him since last year, as far as fans and the media, anyway,'' Eiland told The Scranton Times-Tribune on Monday. ''If he pitches the way he pitched the last time in Syracuse, he's not going to have any problems.''</p>
        <p>Hughes was the Yankees' No. 1 draft pick in 2004 and went 12-6 with a 2.16 earned run average between Trenton and Class A Tampa and Trenton last season. He entered this season ranked by Baseball America as the top pitching prospect in the minors, and he is 2-1 with a 3.94 E.R.A. at Scranton, with 17 strikeouts and 4 walks in 16 innings.</p>
        <p>''There's certainly a lot of hype,'' Cashman said. ''I'm more looking forward to having him and everyone else help us through a difficult time. I'll probably be more excited when we get our full complement of guys back.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
