<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer's Campaign Reforms Stall as G.O.P. Senators Resist</title>
    <meta content="24finance" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/nyregion/24finance.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer's Campaign Reforms Stall as G.O.P. Senators Resist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spitzer’s Campaign Reforms Stall as G.O.P. Senators Resist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer's bid to overhaul New York's campaign finance laws, including sharply lowering limits on contributions, disintegrated Monday as the Senate Republicans suggested that his proposals were undemocratic and would be advantageous to wealthy candidates -- like the governor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer bristled at the Senate's objections and said he would begin traveling the state to attack senators in their districts, using the issue of campaign finance reform as part of his effort to wrest control of the Senate from Republicans. The development promised to reignite the political battle between Mr. Spitzer and Republicans that had cooled when they reached a budget deal at the end of March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senate Republicans suggested that Gov. Eliot Spitzer’s proposals were undemocratic and would be advantageous to wealthy candidates  like the governor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer's bid to overhaul New York's campaign finance laws, including sharply lowering limits on contributions, disintegrated Monday as the Senate Republicans suggested that his proposals were undemocratic and would be advantageous to wealthy candidates -- like the governor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer bristled at the Senate's objections and said he would begin traveling the state to attack senators in their districts, using the issue of campaign finance reform as part of his effort to wrest control of the Senate from Republicans. The development promised to reignite the political battle between Mr. Spitzer and Republicans that had cooled when they reached a budget deal at the end of March.</p>
        <p>''The reason we are not here today with a proposal that can become law is very simple,'' the governor said at a news conference with representatives from a number of government watchdog groups, including Common Cause and the League of Women Voters. ''The Republican members of the State Senate were not willing to break their addiction to the free flow of money.''</p>
        <p>The governor's staff said the talks had stalled over the Senate's unwillingness to ban donations through limited liability companies, which allow the rich to avoid contribution limits easily, and to bar corporations from using their subsidiaries to skirt contribution limits. Such means were routinely used by donors last year.</p>
        <p>Joseph L. Bruno, the Senate majority leader, would not say what specifically had caused the breakdown, but he railed against Mr. Spitzer's plan.</p>
        <p>''The governor's proposals would favor the wealthy and be an elitist kind of approach,'' Mr. Bruno said. ''Frankly, the governor, when he ran for A.G., pretty much financed his own campaign, and how many people can do that in this life?'' Mr. Bruno was referring to a controversial loan Mr. Spitzer received from his father, a wealthy real estate developer, during his first run for attorney general in 1994.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer and his aides were incredulous about the claim, since they said their proposed legislation would have what they called a ''millionaires' amendment.'' Under the proposal, if candidates gave more than 20 times the contribution limit to themselves, their opponents would be allowed to receive donations of twice the limit from all of their contributors.</p>
        <p>The governor had made campaign finance reform one of the top priorities of his administration and had negotiated the issue with legislative leaders for months. He moved unilaterally to lower contribution limits to his own campaign shortly after coming into office, although he has appeared at fund-raisers for the state party, which has higher limits.</p>
        <p>His failure to sway the Legislature on campaign finance could be viewed as his latest lesson in the intractable way of doing business in Albany. On the other hand, after a bruising fight over the state budget, the governor seemed energized by the prospect of taking on the Senate.</p>
        <p>From the Senate's perspective, protecting its financial pipeline is important, as New York becomes increasingly Democratic and at a time when Republicans are out of the governor's office for the first time in a dozen years.</p>
        <p>''I think they don't want to cut off their supply,'' said Liam Arbetman, a research associate with Common Cause New York. His analysis of campaign records showed that the Senate Republican Campaign Committee took in half a million dollars from limited liability companies last year, he said.</p>
        <p>Over all, New York has some of the least restrictive campaign finance laws.</p>
        <p>Statewide candidates can receive donations from individuals of more than $50,000 -- that is the highest level among the 37 states that limit contributions, according to the National Conference of State Legislatures.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer said he proposed to reduce contribution limits 25 to 80 percent, including a reduction in contributions for statewide candidates to $15,000 from $55,800, or to $7,500 if there is no primary. He also wanted a $50,000 limit on contributions to so-called housekeeping accounts maintained by the political parties that can be used for everything from voter outreach to office supplies.</p>
        <p>He said he also would have limited the contributions of political action committees to $350,000 -- ''arguably not far enough,'' he said, but far less than many are giving now.</p>
        <p>Finally, he proposed adding a fifth member to the Board of Elections to break deadlocks over enforcement issues. The panel, with two Democrats and two Republicans, often splits its vote.</p>
        <p>Despite the governor's assertions, it was not clear late Monday that the issue of campaign finance reform was as neatly split down party lines as Mr. Spitzer suggested. The governor said late in the afternoon that he had been assured by Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, the Legislature's top Democrat, that the Assembly supported his full proposal.</p>
        <p>Throughout the day, though, Mr. Silver was noncommittal, and he was meeting with his members about the matter into the early evening. Earlier in the day, Mr. Silver said he had not made a recommendation to Assembly Democrats, though the issue has been under consideration for months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver also appeared to echo some of Mr. Bruno's sentiments.</p>
        <p>''What's compounded a lot of the issues to my members is the sudden emergence of very wealthy people as governors and mayors and candidates,'' Mr. Silver said. ''Those are another set of concerns that come to the issue of unilateral disarmament.''</p>
        <p>After 7 p.m., his office issued a statement of support for the governor's plan, even as he continued to discuss it with his members.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno, for his part, said the governor's continuing threats to change the balance of power in the Senate were making it hard to negotiate.</p>
        <p>''It certainly makes it more difficult when the governor is in a campaign mode,'' Mr. Bruno said. ''He never stops with the politics of it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
