<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rodriguez's Record Can't Improve Yankees'</title>
    <meta content="24yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/baseball/24yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Devil Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Tampa Bay Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Devil Rays</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Igawa, Kei</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hughes, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EFDD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rodriguez's Record Can't Improve Yankees'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rodriguez’s Record Can’t Improve Yankees’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla., April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez smashed two more home runs on Monday and already has 14 this season. No player in baseball history has hit so many in the first 18 games. No player has ever hit more in April. Rodriguez is batting .400, about as hot as a hitter can be, yet the Yankees are reeling.</p>
        <p>They lost for the fourth game in a row Monday, 10-8 to the Tampa Bay Devil Rays at Tropicana Field, because their starter had another dismal outing. Kei Igawa lasted just four and a third innings, allowing seven earned runs on eight hits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yankees starter Kei Igawa allowed seven runs over four and a third innings while Alex Rodriguez homered twice, making him the first player to hit 14 in the first 18 games of a season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez smashed two more home runs on Monday and already has 14 this season. No player in baseball history has hit so many in the first 18 games. No player has ever hit more in April. Rodriguez is batting .400, about as hot as a hitter can be, yet the Yankees are reeling.</p>
        <p>They lost for the fourth game in a row Monday, 10-8 to the Tampa Bay Devil Rays at Tropicana Field, because their starter had another dismal outing. Kei Igawa lasted just four and a third innings, allowing seven earned runs on eight hits.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' starters have failed to last five innings in half of their games. The rotation is averaging the fewest innings per start of any staff in the majors. The bullpen is exhausted, and the offense cannot keep up.</p>
        <p>''Our team should not lose four games in a row,'' center fielder Johnny Damon said. ''It happens, but we are supposed to be better than this. We do need our starters to help out our bullpen a bit more. It seems like those guys are up every single night.''</p>
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang returns on Tuesday, Andy Pettitte goes on Wednesday and the top prospect Phil Hughes makes his major league debut on Thursday. Perhaps Pettitte can persuade Roger Clemens to speed up his workouts and report to the Bronx. The Yankees need all the sturdy arms they can find.</p>
        <p>''The whole game was not good at all,'' Igawa said through his translator, and that was an understatement. Every half-inning, by both teams, included at least one base runner. As Manager Joe Torre noted, the Yankees scored in five consecutive innings, yet trailed by the end of every one.</p>
        <p>It was not the way the Yankees wanted to follow up their lost weekend in Boston, where the Red Sox swept them for the first time at Fenway Park since 1990.</p>
        <p>''We need a win in the worst way,'' Rodriguez said. ''But just hard work and grinding through it and supporting your teammates is the most important thing. The key is not to get discouraged.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez, who consumed so much attention for his various struggles last season, is now the least of the Yankees' worries. He was 4 for 5, scoring four runs and driving in three. He has 34 runs batted in, one shy of Juan González's April record, set in 1998. He has tied Albert Pujols's April home-run record, set last year, with 14.</p>
        <p>According to Trent McCotter of the Society for American Baseball Research, the last player to hit 14 home runs over 18 games in a single season was Sammy Sosa in 2001. The last player before Sosa was Barry Bonds, earlier that season.</p>
        <p>Sosa and Bonds combined for 137 home runs in 2001, with Bonds setting the single-season record of 73. No wonder, then, that Rodriguez's feats are turning his teammates into fans.</p>
        <p>''The guy's on fire, and I hope he keeps it up,'' Damon said. ''The whole team is rallying around him. We can't wait until the next time he comes up.''</p>
        <p>Ken Griffey Jr., Rodriguez's former teammate in Seattle, once explained the difference between baseball and basketball with three words: ''I bat third.'' In other words, even the best hitter can help his team only once every nine trips to the plate. In basketball, a team can feed its star the ball over and over.</p>
        <p>If only Rodriguez could have hit with the bases loaded in the sixth and eighth innings on Monday, the Yankees might have won. Instead, Melky Cabrera came up in those spots, grounding into a force out to end the sixth and striking out swinging at a shoulder-high fastball to end the eighth.</p>
        <p>Cabrera is hitting .197 with no extra-base hits, but he is likely to stay on the roster when Wang is activated from the disabled list on Tuesday. The reserve Kevin Thompson seems headed back to Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre. ''If he stays in the strike zone, he's fine,'' Torre said of Cabrera. ''It looks to me like he's trying to make too big of an impact. Sometimes he just gets a big swing.''</p>
        <p>Cabrera did have one hit, which was more than Hideki Matsui, who had missed 15 days with a strained hamstring. In his first game back, Matsui walked twice and drove in a run with a sacrifice fly. He also flied out, and popped out to end the game.</p>
        <p>The game was broadcast back to Japan, on television and radio, with Matsui's return the main draw and Igawa the undercard. This was Igawa's first start against the Devil Rays, whose third baseman, Akinori Iwamura, hit .291 against Igawa when they faced each other in Japan.</p>
        <p>He did better this time, walking in the second to touch off a four-run rally, and adding a single and a double against Igawa, who said he could not locate his inside fastball. The double chased Igawa with one out in the fifth, and when Iwamura scored, Igawa's earned run average had swollen to 7.84 in four starts. ''His last two starts were good,'' Torre said. ''He should have been on a roll.''</p>
        <p>A procession of five relievers followed Igawa, whose inconsistency makes the Yankees even more desperate for Wang's return. Mike Mussina is about a week away, and the Yankees are finding that the waiting is the hardest part.</p>
        <p>''We certainly look forward to getting those guys back,'' Torre said. ''But it would be nice to win a game in the meantime.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Carl Pavano said he continued to feel a grabbing sensation in his right forearm when he threw. He played catch Monday and has still not been cleared for mound work. ''I got after it a little more today, but there's definitely something more to work through, that's for sure,'' Pavano said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
