<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Upscale Snacks, Famous Clients, and a Health Dept. Warning</title>
    <meta content="24resto" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/nyregion/24resto.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842622"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Waverly Inn &amp; Garden</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Vanity Fair</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Graydon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Upscale Snacks, Famous Clients, and a Health Dept. Warning</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Upscale Snacks, Famous Clients, and a Health Dept. Warning</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC KONIGSBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Konigsberg, Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just like ''Jeopardy!,'' shooting free throws and parenthood, running a restaurant is one of those things that looks much easier on TV. That would be one conclusion to draw, anyway, given Graydon Carter's recent experience with the Waverly Inn and Garden.</p>
        <p>The multitasking Mr. Carter's day job, of course, is editor of Vanity Fair magazine. On the side, he has also spread his wings by writing books, producing and consulting on movies ( ''The Kid Stays in the Picture,'' ''A Beautiful Mind''), and even acting in them (who could forget his star turn in the 2004 remake of ''Alfie''?).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The restaurant of Vanity Fair editor Graydon Carter was cited for nine different violations, including “mouse activity.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just like ''Jeopardy!,'' shooting free throws and parenthood, running a restaurant is one of those things that looks much easier on TV. That would be one conclusion to draw, anyway, given Graydon Carter's recent experience with the Waverly Inn and Garden.</p>
        <p>The multitasking Mr. Carter's day job, of course, is editor of Vanity Fair magazine. On the side, he has also spread his wings by writing books, producing and consulting on movies ( ''The Kid Stays in the Picture,'' ''A Beautiful Mind''), and even acting in them (who could forget his star turn in the 2004 remake of ''Alfie''?).</p>
        <p>Then, late last year, Mr. Carter and some partners opened the Waverly Inn in the West Village to a limited clientele, a sort of neighborhood snack bar for movie stars, fashion designers and people who wear Belgian loafers. Serving things like truffled macaroni and cheese in a charmingly disheveled town house may be just another form of content providing. And by all accounts, tables at the Waverly Inn, 16 Bank Street at Waverly Place, are packed.</p>
        <p>But on March 28, the restaurant failed an inspection with the city's health department, with a total of 38 violation points. It takes a minimum of 28 points to fail. The restaurant was cited for nine different violations, including ''mildew buildup'' inside an ice machine; ''facility conditions conducive to the existence of pest life'' (this had to do with debris and old equipment on the basement floor); and the absence of a sign at the bar instructing employees to wash their hands. And the restaurant was reprimanded for not having adequate warning signs regarding first aid for choking patrons and the effects of alcohol on pregnancy.</p>
        <p>Also: ''Mouse activity present in that approximately 20 fresh mice excreta observed on floor under flavor syrup storage racks in basement.''</p>
        <p>The violations were not significant enough to order a shutdown of the restaurant, said a department spokesman, Geoffrey Cowley. ''Once the restaurant score hits 75 points, the protocol is to determine whether a shutdown is in order,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As it was, the Waverly Inn was reinspected by the city on Thursday, and passed this time, with a score of 22 points. One violation was the storage of a used cutting knife ''between a food preparation table and a wall.'' And there was less mouse activity this time. ''The restaurant is full of signs now,'' Mr. Carter said by telephone yesterday, acknowledging that dealing with the city's health code was not something he gave much thought to when he first decided to open his own restaurant. ''I think this is probably part of the game, the kind of thing that all restaurants have to go through. They don't have health inspections at magazine offices. They probably should.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carter said the restaurant had worked to address its mouse problem. ''Maybe you'll see the Waverly cat there at some point,'' he said. ''Then we get a children's book out of it down the road.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carter was quick to defend the hygienic standards of his chef, John DeLucie. ''John keeps a very clean kitchen,'' he said. He went on to praise the health department's recent crackdown on restaurant conditions following the release of widely viewed video footage of a pack of rats swarming through a Taco Bell/KFC in Greenwich Village in late February.</p>
        <p>''You appreciate health inspectors when you're eating in restaurants,'' he said. ''I mean, I eat there,'' he said of the Waverly Inn. ''I like clean food and that sort of thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
