<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pedicab Limit Withstands Mayor's Veto</title>
    <meta content="24council" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/nyregion/24council.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7DD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pedicab Limit Withstands Mayor's Veto</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pedicab Limit Withstands Mayor’s Veto</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City's freewheeling pedicab industry will be regulated for the first time after a City Council vote yesterday to override a mayoral veto.</p>
        <p>The Council also voted to ban the use of metal bats in high school baseball games when it overrode a second mayoral veto. The pedicab bill becomes law in mid-June, the bat bill on Sept. 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Council also voted to ban metal bats in high school baseball games when it overrode a second mayoral veto.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City's freewheeling pedicab industry will be regulated for the first time after a City Council vote yesterday to override a mayoral veto.</p>
        <p>The Council also voted to ban the use of metal bats in high school baseball games when it overrode a second mayoral veto. The pedicab bill becomes law in mid-June, the bat bill on Sept. 1.</p>
        <p>Dozens of pedicab drivers sat in the balcony of the Council chamber yesterday, frequently cheering Council members who supported the veto by Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and hissing or booing members who spoke in favor of the bill. The strongest point of contention among drivers was a provision in the bill that caps at 325 the number of pedicabs that can operate in the city.</p>
        <p>On several occasions, the City Council speaker, Christine C. Quinn, and the public advocate, Betsy Gotbaum, who presided at the meeting, threatened to clear the chamber.</p>
        <p>Ms. Quinn and other supporters of the bill argued that the pedicabs operate largely without insurance and create a traffic hazard, particularly in the Times Square area during theater hours.</p>
        <p>The proliferation of pedicabs in the theater district has been an irritant to theater and hotel owners, who say the pedicabs cause congestion, and to taxi drivers, who say their permits from the city give them exclusive rights to people who hail cabs. The number of permits for taxicabs and horse-drawn carriages is limited.</p>
        <p>''If you're going to use our streets to make money, then the city has to have some way to regulate your activity,'' Ms. Quinn said. She said it was important to bring this relatively new industry to a level of oversight similar to that imposed on taxis and tour buses.</p>
        <p>The pedicab drivers and their advocates have contended that the regulations are too onerous, specifically the limit on the number of vehicles, and have said that the restriction would most likely put about 175 drivers out of work.</p>
        <p>When Mayor Bloomberg vetoed the bill in March, he said that the free market should dictate the number of pedicabs on the city's streets.</p>
        <p>Two-thirds of the 51 Council members' votes, or 34, are needed to override a veto. The Council voted 37 to 6 to override it with two abstentions. Six members were absent.</p>
        <p>To impose its ban on metal bats, the Council voted 41 to 4 in favor of overriding the mayor's veto.</p>
        <p>That bill's sponsor, Councilman James S. Oddo, a Republican from Staten Island, has maintained that baseballs move at a higher speed when hit with aluminum bats, which were first introduced in the early 1970s, and pose a greater risk of injury to students playing baseball.</p>
        <p>Mayor Bloomberg, in vetoing the bill earlier this month, said that it was far from certain that aluminum bats were more dangerous than the wooden ones. And, in the end, he said, ''I don't think it's the city's business to regulate that.''</p>
        <p>The handful of Council members who opposed overriding the veto said that there was no credible evidence that aluminum bats were more dangerous than wooden ones. ''There are no statistics to show that it's a problem,'' said Tony Avella, a Queens Democrat. ''You should not pass legislation on the basis of not having the facts.''</p>
        <p>Councilman Oddo said he was gratified by the vote in support of the ban and criticized the bat manufacturers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oddo said that the bat makers had spent more than $200,000 to lobby Council members to support the mayor's veto. ''This is about money,'' Mr. Oddo said. He said that if the aluminum bat manufacturers had a choice between the safety of young people and making money, ''I believe they would choose to make money.''</p>
        <p>After the vote, a coalition of aluminum bat makers, coaches and others calling themselves Don't Take My Bat Away, held a press conference on the steps of City Hall. The group said it would go to federal court this week to seek ''an immediate and permanent injunction of the new law.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
