<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maine Has Last Word in Solving Rockies</title>
    <meta content="24mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/sports/baseball/24mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Colorado Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Colorado Rockies</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDD143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maine Has Last Word in Solving Rockies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Maine Has Last Word in Solving Rockies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Maine exuded confidence even before the Mets faced the Colorado Rockies at Shea Stadium last night. While listening to his iPod in the clubhouse, Maine worked on a crossword puzzle -- in blue ink.</p>
        <p>Maine could have been an answer to his own puzzle if the clue had been a five-letter word for a pitcher in a groove. He baffled the Rockies for seven and two-thirds innings as the Mets cruised to a 6-1 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Maine baffled the Rockies for seven and two-thirds innings, scattering seven hits and allowing one run as the Mets cruised to a victory Monday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Maine exuded confidence even before the Mets faced the Colorado Rockies at Shea Stadium last night. While listening to his iPod in the clubhouse, Maine worked on a crossword puzzle -- in blue ink.</p>
        <p>Maine could have been an answer to his own puzzle if the clue had been a five-letter word for a pitcher in a groove. He baffled the Rockies for seven and two-thirds innings as the Mets cruised to a 6-1 victory.</p>
        <p>Maine threw strikes early in the count, and his fastball, changeup and slider danced across the plate. It was a familiar story line. Maine (3-0) has been dominant all season, allowing a combined 15 hits and 5 earned runs over his four starts.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to throw three pitches for strikes,'' Maine said when asked about his blazing start. ''That's just my game plan.''</p>
        <p>The plan worked remarkably well once again. In his previous start, Maine held the Florida Marlins without a hit through six innings. He did not flirt with a no-hitter last night; Matt Holiday singled in the second inning. But he consistently threw in the low 90s, allowing one run and seven hits while striking out five batters and walking two.</p>
        <p>Maine, in his second season with the Mets, left the game to a standing ovation from the 32,154 fans.</p>
        <p>''The fans here are great,'' said Maine, the only Mets starter without a loss. ''They see someone go out there working hard and they respect that. And I appreciate that, too.''</p>
        <p>After the game, Maine looked relaxed, as if he had just completed one of his daily crossword or sudoku puzzles. He said he liked puzzles because they kept him calm and helped pass the time.</p>
        <p>On a warm night, Maine also received some help from his teammates, who gave him an early cushion. With runners on first and second in the second inning, José Valentín drilled an 84-mile-an-hour pitch from Rockies starter Taylor Buchholz, who was making his first start of the season. He took a mighty swing, knocking the ball over the right-field wall for a three-run homer.</p>
        <p>''I hit him pretty good with a changeup that just hung in the strike zone,'' Valentín said. ''Put a sweet swing on it and hit it out of the park. When you hit the ball like that, there's good feelings.''</p>
        <p>There were more good feelings in the fourth inning, when Moises Alou scored on Valentín's sacrifice fly to center field to give the Mets a 4-0 lead. Valentín finished with four runs batted in, and Alou went 3 for 3.</p>
        <p>The defense chipped in, too. Carlos Beltrán saved at least a run with a leaping catch in the second inning. With runners at first and second, Yorvit Torrealba sent a fly ball to deep center field.</p>
        <p>''As soon as he hit it, I thought it was going out,'' Beltrán said.</p>
        <p>But the ball stayed in the park, and Beltrán made a one-handed catch at the warning track before hitting the wall.</p>
        <p>Beltrán was a victim of his own medicine in the fifth inning, when center fielder Steve Finley jumped at the wall to rob him of extra bases, possibly a two-run homer. It was one of the lone bright spots for the Rockies, who cut the lead to 4-1 on Holliday's single in the sixth inning.</p>
        <p>But that was Maine's only costly mistake. Holliday, who leads the majors with a .400 average, had three singles against Maine.</p>
        <p>In the seventh inning, the Mets (12-6) padded their lead when Carlos Delgado hit his first home run of the season. Earlier, Delgado was hit on the left hand by Buchholz in the fifth inning, and it appeared as if he might have to take a seat. He remained in the game, though his pinky was sore after the game.</p>
        <p>Delgado's two-run homer against the right-handed reliever Bob Keppel gave the Mets a 6-1 lead and put a smile on his face after the game.</p>
        <p>''It feels nice,'' Delgado said. ''For a little while, I wasn't swinging that good, putting too much body into my swing. It's nice to let your hands work.''</p>
        <p>But the news was not all good for the Mets.</p>
        <p>David Wright, who was 0 for 11 in a three-game series against the Atlanta Braves this past weekend, went 0 for 3 to drop his average to .261. He also struck out twice.</p>
        <p>And Ambiorix Burgos loaded the bases with three walks in the ninth inning before inducing a popout in foul territory to end the game.</p>
        <p>But yesterday's game will be remembered for all that went right. And Maine was the main reason for the Mets' success.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The right-handed reliever Duaner Sánchez, who had surgery April 10 for a hairline fracture in his right shoulder, said before yesterday's game that he would pitch again this season. Sánchez said that he was not in any pain but he did not know when he would receive clearance to resume baseball activities.  José Reyes stole two bases to increase his major league-leading total to 12.  Julio Franco, who did not play yesterday, marked the 25th anniversary of his major league debut, which took place with the Philadelphia Phillies on April 23, 1982. ''It's not too many times you see that come by,'' Franco said of his longevity.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
