<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Product Tips You Can Use, by Way of Cellphone</title>
    <meta content="24adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/24/business/media/24adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Philips Electronics</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E4DE143EF937A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Product Tips You Can Use, by Way of Cellphone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Product Tips You Can Use, by Way of Cellphone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARLENE LUKOVITZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM time to time, Philips Electronics has used its ''sense and simplicity'' campaign to clear away marketing that bothers consumers. Last year it paid Hearst $2 million to remove the subscription cards from four of its magazines for a month, and several times it has bought up blocks of commercials on television shows and used them to give air time back to the programmers (like CBS's ''60 Minutes'' and NBC's evening news).</p>
        <p>Now Philips is using the same campaign to showcase a free service it is offering to cellphone users. The service, Philips Simplicity Concierge, lets people send text messages to seek information about popular destinations in major cities -- restaurants in Boston, for instance, or spas in London -- and get a Yellow Pages-style listing of five options, including phone numbers for making reservations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new service by Philips Electronics lets people send text messages to seek information about popular destinations in major cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM time to time, Philips Electronics has used its ''sense and simplicity'' campaign to clear away marketing that bothers consumers. Last year it paid Hearst $2 million to remove the subscription cards from four of its magazines for a month, and several times it has bought up blocks of commercials on television shows and used them to give air time back to the programmers (like CBS's ''60 Minutes'' and NBC's evening news).</p>
        <p>Now Philips is using the same campaign to showcase a free service it is offering to cellphone users. The service, Philips Simplicity Concierge, lets people send text messages to seek information about popular destinations in major cities -- restaurants in Boston, for instance, or spas in London -- and get a Yellow Pages-style listing of five options, including phone numbers for making reservations.</p>
        <p>The recommendations made by the service, which will be available on the Internet and by cellphone through the end of the year, are being drawn from the content of Condé Nast Web sites. Under the arrangement, Philips is paying $5 million to the Condé Nast Media Group, a unit of Condé Nast Publications that handles marketing and sales for the company's magazines and Web sites.</p>
        <p>''When you're traveling and pressed for time, and haven't had an opportunity to look for resources, you want a trusted source to give you a recommendation,'' said Eric Plaskonos, director of brand communication at Philips.</p>
        <p>Philips, a part of Royal Philips Electronics, makes phones as well as many other consumer products. But the ''sense and simplicity'' campaign is a conceptual one: the focus is not on pitching the company's consumer products directly, but on promoting the idea of clutter reduction for people's lives.</p>
        <p>''People are pretty passionate when you simplify things for them, and that's rich territory for getting people to spend more time with the brand,'' said Martha Cleary, vice president and group account director for Philips's media agency, Carat USA, part of the Aegis Group.</p>
        <p>The most unusual element of this stage of the campaign is its heavy reliance on cellphones, which are just starting to emerge as a tool for marketers and for e-commerce.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Philips is using the concierge service to experiment with wireless e-commerce. In addition to text recommendations, users with Web-enabled phones get a screen message with a link to a Philips area of Amazon.com, where they are encouraged to buy products.</p>
        <p>''Our intent is to show people that this technology can work for you and help you,'' Mr. Plaskonos said. ''Eventually, our hope is that this will transfer to mobile purchasing, through sites like Amazon, of products that they need for gifting purposes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Plaskonos said that the e-commerce feature was still ''a little bit out there in terms of consumer behavior'' and that Amazon has not seen a lot of sales from it yet. ''But we're interested in seeing if this is something that people will begin to pick up on,'' he added.</p>
        <p>For Condé Nast, which has its own branded mobile sites and cellphone shopping services, the Philips program is expected to yield further insights into how its content translates to the mobile arena.</p>
        <p>Richard Beckman, president of the Condé Nast Media Group, said he was eager to see how many consumers would use the concierge service. The companies will keep track of which information categories prove the most popular and will fine-tune the service accordingly.</p>
        <p>To get travel tips by cellphone, users must send a text message to 82222 and enter an information category and city abbreviation. The Philips concierge then sends them back a list of five recommended establishments. A request for New York City restaurants, for example, steers people to August, Babbo, Balthazar, Barney Greengrass and BLT Steak.</p>
        <p>The concierge service is being introduced through advertising supplements running in the May and June issues of Condé Nast Traveler, Golf, Gourmet, House &amp; Garden, Self, Vanity Fair and Wired, plus one May and one June issue of the weekly New Yorker. Depending on which magazines generate the most traffic, Philips will also run ads in some later issues.</p>
        <p>Ads for the service will also run through June 30 on the eight publications' Web sites, including Concierge.com (Condé Nast Traveler's site) and Epicurious.com, which features recipes and other content from Gourmet and Bon Appétit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Plaskonos of Philips said that the ''sense and simplicity'' campaign has already helped link the Philips brand to the concept of simplicity in the minds of many consumers. First came a 2005 sponsorship of a ''60 Minutes'' episode in which Philips gave back all the national commercial time so that the show could broadcast longer news segments.</p>
        <p>Last year there were other examples, like a 98-page supplement to Gourmet magazine that showcased literary writing about food, issues of Business 2.0, Fortune, People and Time that let readers flip straight from the cover to the table of contents, and periods of free access to paid areas of the Web sites NYTimes.com, ESPN.com and WSJ.com.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the best-known example was the Philips sole sponsorship that reduced commercials on NBC's Dec. 4, 2006 ''Nightly News With Brian Williams'' broadcast from seven minutes to just over one minute. That newscast saw an 8 percent ratings lift and generated 9,400 grateful e-mail messages over three days.</p>
        <p>Other marketers have taken note. Pfizer was the sole sponsor of the first three Monday evening editions of ''ABC World News With Charles Gibson'' this month, and CVS made a similar arrangement with ABC for the broadcast of the show last night.</p>
        <p>The North American division of Philips has committed about 25 percent of its 2007 advertising budget to the ''sense and simplicity'' campaign, about the same percentage as in 2006, Mr. Plaskonos said. According to TNS Media Intelligence, Philips's ad spending in the United States was $105.3 million last year.</p>
        <p>The campaign for the concierge service reflects some lessons learned from the sponsorships. ''One of our takeaways was that people are interested in turning other people on to shortcuts or solutions for simplifying problems in their lives,'' said Mr. Plaskonos.</p>
        <p>ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
