<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Uses Recess to Fill Envoy Post And 2 Others</title>
    <meta content="05bush" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/washington/05bush.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Swift Boat Veterans for Truth</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Fox, Sam</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Biggs, Andrew G</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Baucus, Max</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dudley, Susan E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE1DA163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Uses Recess to Fill Envoy Post And 2 Others</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Uses Recess to Fill Envoy Post and 2 Others</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>FORT IRWIN, Calif., April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pes Bush uses Conmgressional recess to push through three appointments that are opposed by Democrats; names Sam Fox as ambassador to Belgium; Fox donated $50,000 to group Swift Boat Beterans for Truth that opposed Sen John Kerry during 2004 presidential campaign and attacked Kerry's record in Vietnam War;</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush used the Congressional recess on Wednesday to push through his choice to be ambassador to Belgium and to fill two domestic policy positions, provoking Democratic ire with all three appointments.</p>
        <p>The ambassadorship will be filled by Sam Fox, a major Republican donor who had withdrawn his name for the job in late March when it became clear that Democrats on the Foreign Relations Committee were lining up against him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush used the Congressional recess to push through three appointees who will serve without Senate confirmation through 2008.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush used the Congressional recess on Wednesday to push through his choice to be ambassador to Belgium and to fill two domestic policy positions, provoking Democratic ire with all three appointments.</p>
        <p>The ambassadorship will be filled by Sam Fox, a major Republican donor who had withdrawn his name for the job in late March when it became clear that Democrats on the Foreign Relations Committee were lining up against him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox donated $50,000 to the group Swift Boat Veterans for Truth that opposed Senator John Kerry during his 2004 presidential campaign. The group attacked Mr. Kerry's record in the Vietnam War with advertising that included unsubstantiated accusations that he had not earned his war medals.</p>
        <p>''It's sad but not surprising that this White House would abuse the power of the presidency to reward a donor over the objections of the Senate,'' Mr. Kerry said Wednesday in a statement. ''Unfortunately, when this White House can't win the game, they just change the rules, and America loses.''</p>
        <p>Recess appointments let a president install people into jobs requiring Senate confirmation when Congress is out of session. In the current cases, the appointees can stay in place without Senate confirmation through 2008.</p>
        <p>The White House announced the appointments as Mr. Bush visited an Army training base here and called upon Congress to drop a push by Democrats to attach timetables for withdrawal of American combat troops from Iraq to approval for emergency war spending. Though Mr. Bush and the new Democratic leadership in Congress pledged just three months ago that they would work cooperatively, they are now on a collision course over the role of Congress in foreign policy and the administration's dismissal of eight United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>In another of the appointments on Wednesday, Mr. Bush named Andrew Biggs, a champion of privatization, as the deputy commissioner of the Social Security Administration. Senator Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana and the chairman of the Senate Finance Committee, had said in February that he would not take up Mr. Biggs's nomination, made in 2006, because of his stand on Social Security.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baucus said on Wednesday, ''Prospects for getting real Social Security reform anytime soon just took a big hit with this recess appointment.''</p>
        <p>Democrats also complained about the appointment of Susan E. Dudley as administrator of the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs at the Office of Management and Budget, a powerful position that involves review of regulations from major federal agencies.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dudley has written that government regulation is not warranted ''in the absence of a significant market failure,'' alarming consumer and environmental groups. Mr. Bush nominated her in August and again in January, with Democrats vowing to block confirmation.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, these are politically provocative acts,'' said Sarah Feinberg, a spokeswoman for the Democratic caucus in the House, referring to the three appointments.</p>
        <p>Tony Fratto, a White House spokesman, said that all of the appointees were qualified and that Democrats were to blame for forcing the president to resort to recess appointments. ''We understand and respect the Senate's process for confirming nominees,'' he said. ''It's unfortunate that partisan politics sometimes gets in the way of cooperation.''</p>
        <p>In a fourth recess appointment on Wednesday, Mr. Bush named Carol Waller Pope, a Democrat, to be a member of the Federal Labor Relations Authority. Ms. Pope was first appointed to the three-member board in 2000 and served until her term expired last year. Democrats and unions had urged the president to renominate her because otherwise the board had only two members, both Republicans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush used his visit to the training site to renew his criticism of Democrats for their legislation tying future war spending to timetables for withdrawal.</p>
        <p>Listing what he said was evidence of progress in Iraq, he said, ''Just as the strategy is starting to make inroads, a narrow majority in the Congress passed legislation they knew all along I would not accept.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
