<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Under the Spanish Moss, A River Runs Blood Red</title>
    <meta content="05reap" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/movies/05reap.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hopkins, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swank, Hilary</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Reaping, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Warner Brothers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Swank, Hilary</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Reaping, The (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E0DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Under the Spanish Moss, A River Runs Blood Red</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Under the Spanish Moss, a River Runs Blood Red</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews film The Reaping, directed by Stephen Hopkins; Hilary Swank stars (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tagline for the inane horror flick ''The Reaping'' asks, ''What hath God wrought?''</p>
        <p>The question really should be addressed to Warner Brothers, the studio releasing this schlock-o-rama, and all those clever little gnomes in Hollywood who keep trying to squeeze boffo opening weekends from even the lamest horror premise. The only remotely notable thing about this particular jumble of boos, bangs and door creaks, swaying Spanish moss, creeping blond kids and swelling décolletage, creatively presented from various angles in various contexts, is that it tries to wed the horror trend with the heated-up God market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The only remotely notable thing about this particular jumble of boos, bangs and door creaks is that it tries to wed the horror trend with the heated-up God market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tagline for the inane horror flick ''The Reaping'' asks, ''What hath God wrought?''</p>
        <p>The question really should be addressed to Warner Brothers, the studio releasing this schlock-o-rama, and all those clever little gnomes in Hollywood who keep trying to squeeze boffo opening weekends from even the lamest horror premise. The only remotely notable thing about this particular jumble of boos, bangs and door creaks, swaying Spanish moss, creeping blond kids and swelling décolletage, creatively presented from various angles in various contexts, is that it tries to wed the horror trend with the heated-up God market.</p>
        <p>That décolletage, alternately swelling and heaving, belongs to Hilary Swank, who as Katherine Winter, a faith-bound minister turned science-crazed miracle-buster, travels the world debunking signs of grace. Katherine turns feasts into fish, wine into H2O and her findings into a lesson plan for her students at Louisiana State University, where she works side-by-side with the crucifix wearing-and-fondling Ben (Idris Elba). When the film opens, the miracle-busters are investigating an event in Santiago, Chile, where the mumbling, mesmerized faithful have taken to adoring the decades-old corpse of a priest that, for one worshiper, is literally finger-licking good. Sure enough, Katherine discovers it isn't the waxy corpse that's making the faithful twitch and howl, but rather fumes from a local oil refinery. Case closed.</p>
        <p>Not so the movie, which goes on and on, largely due to a smiling stranger, Doug Blackwell (David Morrissey), who brings Katherine news of strange doings in a secluded bayou town called Haven. Armed with their lab equipment, computers and his-and-hers faith and doubt, the miracle-busters plunge first into a river that has recently turned the color of blood and then into a fast-rising tide of nonsense involving motorcycle toughs and Satanic love, shaky accents and sweaty sheets. There's a strange girl who used to live in the village of the damned and a fat man parading a white suit and bluster redolent of Burl Ives. There are falling frogs, buzzing flies, crawling lice and really mad cows. Alas, there are also five other plagues.</p>
        <p>To judge from the landscape shots, the director Stephen Hopkins would have done better shooting a cable show for National Geographic. He frames his star almost as attractively, which is smart because the always-game Ms. Swank has little to do here but look pretty. But there's nothing to be done with the screenplay by Carey W. Hayes and Chad Hayes (''House of Wax''), which, at least in its onscreen manifestation, bags and sags without finding a core reason for being.</p>
        <p>The invocations of God and the Devil are especially unfortunate, because they're at once opportunistic and pusillanimous, and because they serve to remind you, again and again, that you're watching this hooey, not ''Rosemary's Baby.'' The allusion to Hurricane Katrina, on the other hand, is just tacky.</p>
        <p>''The Reaping'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). Discreet sex, overt blood and some way-ugly boils.</p>
        <p>The Reaping</p>
        <p>Opens today nationwide.</p>
        <p>Directed by Stephen Hopkins; written by Carey W. Hayes and Chad Hayes, based on a story by Brian Rousso; director of photography, Peter Levy; edited by Colby Parker Jr.; music by John Frizzell; production designer, Graham Walker; produced by Joel Silver, Robert Zemeckis, Susan Downey and Herbert W. Gains; released by Warner Brothers Pictures. Running time: 96 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Hilary Swank (Katherine), David Morrissey (Doug), Idris Elba (Ben), AnnaSophia Robb (Loren McConnell) and Stephen Rea (Father Costigan).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
