<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marbury Lights It Up As Knicks' Hopes Dim</title>
    <meta content="05knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/sports/basketball/05knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Philadelphia 76ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia 76ers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2D9163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marbury Lights It Up As Knicks' Hopes Dim</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Marbury Lights It Up for the Fading Knicks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest devastating blow to the Knicks' season -- and the blows are coming in rapid progression now -- came in the form of a remarkable lean-in jumper and a powerful block at the final buzzer.</p>
        <p>The Knicks produced another drama-filled evening at Madison Square Garden last night, going from 10 points down to 9 points up, then nearly erasing a 7-point deficit in the final seconds. But the night ended as most of them recently have, with a deflating loss and a sense that their season will soon be over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stephon Marbury led the Knicks with 30 points  28 in the second half  but could not deliver the victory despite some uncanny scoring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The latest devastating blow to the Knicks' season -- and the blows are coming in rapid progression now -- came in the form of a remarkable lean-in jumper and a powerful block at the final buzzer.</p>
        <p>The Knicks produced another drama-filled evening at Madison Square Garden last night, going from 10 points down to 9 points up, then nearly erasing a 7-point deficit in the final seconds. But the night ended as most of them recently have, with a deflating loss and a sense that their season will soon be over.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia's Andre Iguodala punctuated a 92-90 victory with a flying block of Stephon Marbury's 3-point attempt on the game's final play. The Knicks (31-43) lost their third straight game, their ninth in their last 11, and missed a chance to pick up a game on the eighth-place Orlando Magic (34-41), which lost to Toronto.</p>
        <p>The Knicks are a season-high 12 games below .500. They remain mathematically, and improbably, alive for a playoff berth, but their elimination seems inevitable. Knicks Coach Isiah Thomas seemed to sense as much as he grimly faced the news media after the game.</p>
        <p>''This is definitely a missed opportunity,'' he said. ''We just got to suck it up and go to practice tomorrow and keep working.''</p>
        <p>Thomas had spent the previous few days lamenting referees' treatment of Marbury, a gesture that cost him $50,000. But Thomas waved off the suggestion that Marbury might have been fouled on the final play, and Marbury said flatly: ''It doesn't matter. The game's over.''</p>
        <p>Marbury scored 30 points, but he had little help and was on the bench resting when the Knicks let most of a 9-point lead slip away late in the fourth quarter. Marbury lay down near the bench and afterward had ice taped to his lower back. Thomas said there were ''a lot of things going on with him physically. He's pretty beat up.''</p>
        <p>Marbury insisted that he was fine.</p>
        <p>In a wild final minute, the 76ers nearly let a 7-point lead vanish. The Knicks had gone more than five minutes without a field goal when Marbury heaved an off-balance 3-pointer over Rodney Carney. It appeared to be falling short when the 76ers' Steven Hunter leaped and caught the ball for a goaltending call. Nate Robinson followed with a layup, and the Knicks were down by 90-88 with 31.3 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Then came the backbreaking shot. Andre Miller, well guarded by the lanky Renaldo Balkman 18 feet from the basket, leaned in and around Balkman and pushed up a shot that somehow found the net, giving the 76ers a 4-point lead with 7.4 seconds left.</p>
        <p>''It was great defense, and he hit it,'' said Balkman, who had 17 points and 16 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Mardy Collins said: ''He just made a tough shot. We thought he traveled, but they didn't call it.''</p>
        <p>After Marbury made a layup, the Knicks were forced to foul and they sent Kyle Korver -- a 92 percent free-throw shooter -- to the line with 2.3 seconds left. Incredibly, Korver missed both free throws, giving the Knicks the ball with 1.1 seconds left. The best they could manage was Marbury's deep 3-pointer, with Carney and Iguodala defending.</p>
        <p>Marbury missed his first six field-goal attempts of the night as the Knicks fell behind by 10. He single-handedly got them back in the game, scoring 20 points and making all seven of his shots in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>But the good times did not last. Marbury, perhaps pushing too hard, missed four driving layups in the fourth quarter trying to power through the lane. The Knicks' late meltdown also included offensive fouls on Eddy Curry and Collins and turnovers by Marbury and Jared Jeffries.</p>
        <p>Curry had a mixed night. He finished with 14 points and 11 rebounds but had 7 turnovers and scored only 1 point in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Iguodala led the 76ers with 18 points, many of them on spectacular dunks in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Isiah Thomas repeatedly declined to comment on his $50,000 fine from the N.B.A. ''I don't have a reaction,'' he said. ''My focus is on tonight's game.'' Thomas was fined Tuesday for comments he made about officiating after Saturday's loss to the Hornets in Oklahoma City. He complained that referees did not afford the same respect to Stephon Marbury as they did to other stars in the league. Marbury was more forthcoming. ''It feels good knowing that he said something,'' Marbury told reporters at the morning shoot-around, adding, ''It was time for someone to say something.'' Marbury added: ''When I go to the basket, they're telling me the same thing: I'm initiating contact, because I'm stronger than most guards. I'm tired of hearing that.''  David Lee was in uniform, but Thomas said he was only available for emergency duty.  Jamal Crawford has been running on an underwater treadmill and taking flat-footed shots. If all goes well, the next step would be running on land. Crawford, who is recovering from surgery on his right ankle, said he expected to be re-evaluated next week.  The Knicks used their 18th starting lineup as the rookie Mardy Collins, a Philadelphia native, made the first start of his N.B.A. career.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
