<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grandma Would Be Tickled Purple</title>
    <meta content="05online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/fashion/05online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Eggs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DE163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grandma Would Be Tickled Purple</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Grandma Would Be Tickled Purple</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE pickled egg is not for everyone. Yet, in the interest of full disclosure, I would like to reveal the simple recipe for my family's favorite (and unusual) Easter delicacy.</p>
        <p>Peel a dozen hard-boiled eggs and immerse them in a bath of beet juice for several hours (or days) until they turn dark purple. Slice and serve.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hunt for just the right “Easter vase” to display pickled eggs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE pickled egg is not for everyone. Yet, in the interest of full disclosure, I would like to reveal the simple recipe for my family's favorite (and unusual) Easter delicacy.</p>
        <p>Peel a dozen hard-boiled eggs and immerse them in a bath of beet juice for several hours (or days) until they turn dark purple. Slice and serve.</p>
        <p>I should mention that this is actually my grandmother's recipe. And that she did not like to cook. And that her pickled eggs tasted kind of metallic from the canned beet juice she used.</p>
        <p>She would have laughed incredulously at some of the more elaborate recipes I found online last week, versions that called for fancy ingredients such as cider vinegar and brown sugar (at Cooks.com), or 12 whole cloves and sliced fresh ginger (at Allrecipes.com).</p>
        <p>One question is: Why would anyone eat a second one of my grandmother's pickled eggs (the purple-tinged yolks also lent an otherworldly appearance to a plateful of food) much less clamor for them year after year? Another is: Why would I suddenly wake up one spring morning, 15 years after she had died, with an urge to introduce them to my own children on Easter?</p>
        <p>While some people may settle for the easy answer and say I was beset by nostalgia for childhood, my mother dismissed that suggestion last week. ''It was the way she served them,'' said my mother, who lives in Arizona, during a phone consultation in which we were discussing the correct proportion of beet juice to eggs.</p>
        <p>No one could resist the presentation. My grandmother, who loved pretty things like hand-painted teacups and pearl circle pins, always decanted the eggs that were floating in their beet juice into a big purple-tinted footed glass vase -- or was it a decanter? Every year she completed the assembly process at home, popped a piece of plastic wrap over the top and rode over to our house in the passenger's seat of the car, the beet-juice concoction perched precariously on her lap. Had my grandfather ever slammed on the brakes, she would have been dyed purple from head to toe.</p>
        <p>''Remember the big purple-colored thing?'' I asked my mother.</p>
        <p>''It looked so pretty in the middle of the table, better than a centerpiece of flowers,'' my mother said.</p>
        <p>After my grandmother died, her teacups went to my aunt. A pearl ring went to my mother, who gave it to me. And her recipe for pickled eggs? Well, that's in the public domain now.</p>
        <p>''But what happened to the purple, footed thing?'' I asked.</p>
        <p>My mother didn't know. And this is when I started hoping the Internet could help me find a replacement.</p>
        <p>With Easter looming, I went online to look for a big, purple-colored foot thing at sites like Westportstyle.com (which had a purple, footed glass vase for $52.50 that was very pretty but unfortunately the wrong shape).</p>
        <p>Bluestemmissouricrafts.com had a purple glass vase in a wire holder (for $56) and someone in Saukville was selling a ''16-inch Amethyst Purple Glass VASE JAR'' on the Milwaukee area Craigslist.org for $20 (no photo was available).</p>
        <p>But none that I saw resembled the one I remembered.</p>
        <p>Now, I know that among those who study unusual family rituals, my desire for a purple-tinted footed thing would be just a footnote in the pantheon of idiosyncratic ways people celebrate Easter nowadays.</p>
        <p>With the customs associated with the holiday expanding far beyond such simple activities as hunting for eggs and wearing fashionable bonnets, Target.com is selling an ''Egg Tree'' described as a 19-inch tabletop decoration ($13.49).</p>
        <p>Orientaltrading.com has ''Easter Egg Head Boppers,'' for $4.95 a dozen, and I wouldn't put it past some family to wear those bopper antennas at the table on Sunday.</p>
        <p>In fact, Easter is even moving onto other holidays' turf. No longer are decorated cookies just for Christmas; at www.deandeluca, iced cookies shaped like Easter eggs, baby chicks and flowers are $45 for 19.</p>
        <p>I only wish that the childhood tradition I wanted to recapture involved something like, say, watching Charles M. Schulz's classic ''It's the Easter Beagle, Charlie Brown,'' because then I simply could purchase the DVD version from Kmart.com for $16.99 instead of having to call my mother back and badger her to try to remember more details about the footed thing and where it might have come from.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to have to subject you to professional hypnosis,'' I said.</p>
        <p>''O.K., wait a minute, let me think,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She paused. ''Why, you know what it was? It was a big oversized brandy snifter, not a vase.''</p>
        <p>Back online, I found that Galasource.com had a jumbo 23 1/2-inch-tall brandy snifter for $155, but the shape was a little too squat and it was made of clear glass. Glassware4gellin.com had a snifter that was the right shape (11 inches tall with a 6-inch opening, and 4 inches across the bottom) for $22.75, but it was also clear, as well as temporarily out of stock. Grilllovers.com even had a giant acrylic ice bucket shaped like a brandy snifter, for $149.99 (''Larger-than-life, giant stemware has many uses besides impressing party guests.'')</p>
        <p>With a sinking feeling, I realized this might be as close as I could come. But then how will I serve the pickled eggs?</p>
        <p>''One last idea,'' my mother said. ''Did you try typing vase plus brandy snifter?''</p>
        <p>''Hang on,'' I said.</p>
        <p>Onscreen popped a picture of ''AMETHYST VASE BRANDY SNIFTER STYLE, Item Number: 10490,'' for sale for $69.95 at Tias.com.</p>
        <p>It was awfully close. But not quite tall enough.</p>
        <p>''I might have a picture of your grandmother's from one Easter when everybody was at the table,'' my mother said.</p>
        <p>She promised to look for it.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, I may tinker with that pickled-egg recipe. A little fresh dill and onion couldn't hurt.</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail: Slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
