<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>C-Class, One for Comfort, One for Sport</title>
    <meta content="NUGGETMercedesCClass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E0DB173FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="293" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>C-Class, One for Comfort, One for Sport</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY W. PETERS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: 2008 Mercedes-Benz C-Class, sport and luxury models.</p>
        <p>Is it real? Yes. In fact, this was the second time Mercedes has unveiled the new C-Class at an auto show. The first time was at the Geneva Auto Show earlier this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: 2008 Mercedes-Benz C-Class, sport and luxury models.</p>
        <p>Is it real? Yes. In fact, this was the second time Mercedes has unveiled the new C-Class at an auto show. The first time was at the Geneva Auto Show earlier this year.</p>
        <p>What's the point? The C-Class, the closest thing Mercedes has to a sedan for the masses, hasn't been significantly redesigned since 2000. Mercedes needed a fresh look for its top-selling vehicle worldwide, which has to compete with recently redesigned models of the BMW 3 Series and the Lexus IS.</p>
        <p>What they said: "The battle for market share in the entry class remains fierce," said Ernst Lieb, president and chief executive officer of Mercedes-Benz USA.</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: The C-Class is Mercedes's bridge vehicle. It's the vehicle they hope to use to attract buyers who will eventually move on to bigger, more expensive models.</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? Mercedes will offer two V-6 engines, a 3.0-liter 228-horsepower version for the C300; and a 3.5-liter 268-horsepower version for the C350.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? As the entry-level Mercedes, the C-Class is on par with models from Audi, BMW and Lexus in its segment. Prices will start at around $32,000 and reach up near $40,000. It will be available in the United States in August.</p>
        <p>How's it look? Mercedes has essentially made two separate cars with its new C-Class. It will sell sport and luxury versions of the vehicle, two styles that are quite distinct and aimed at two very different demographic groups. The sport version is, well, sportier. It lacks the signature three-point Mercedes hood ornament and has the grille of a coupe. The luxury version looks a bit more like a classic sedan, hood ornament included.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
