<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Show of Force Expected For Arnie's Army at First Tee</title>
    <meta content="05anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/sports/golf/05anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Palmer, Arnold</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1D9163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Show of Force Expected For Arnie's Army at First Tee</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Show of Force for Arnie’s Army at Augusta’s First Tee</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For one brief shining moment at 7:45 this morning, the Masters will be the Masters again when Arnold Palmer hits the ceremonial opening tee shot with the same whiplash swing that popularized golf and the Masters half a century ago.</p>
        <p>His ball won't go as far and probably not as straight as it did when he was winning the Masters every other year from 1958 to 1964, but who cares? Arnold Palmer will be on the first tee at Augusta National again, and that's enough for anyone who remembers seeing him here when real soldiers at nearby Fort Gordon were the original enlistees in Arnie's Army.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arnold Palmer will be on the first tee at Augusta again, and that’s enough for anyone who remembers seeing him when real soldiers at nearby Fort Gordon were the original enlistees in Arnie’s Army.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For one brief shining moment at 7:45 this morning, the Masters will be the Masters again when Arnold Palmer hits the ceremonial opening tee shot with the same whiplash swing that popularized golf and the Masters half a century ago.</p>
        <p>His ball won't go as far and probably not as straight as it did when he was winning the Masters every other year from 1958 to 1964, but who cares? Arnold Palmer will be on the first tee at Augusta National again, and that's enough for anyone who remembers seeing him here when real soldiers at nearby Fort Gordon were the original enlistees in Arnie's Army.</p>
        <p>''When I first played here in the '50s, they started doing the scoreboards as you see them,'' he recalled Tuesday at a news conference announcing his role as the honorary starter. ''The first people to do those scoreboards were soldiers from Fort Gordon; they took their week off to do the work as volunteers. They said, 'We are soldiers in Arnie's Army.' And it spread.</p>
        <p>''Then finally after spreading as much as it did throughout the game of golf and in tournaments that I was playing in, everybody was carrying signs. And the PGA Tour and Augusta National jointly said, 'Hey, no more signs,' because it was getting obnoxious. There were so many signs and the people were holding them up. And in only a couple of years, it stopped.''</p>
        <p>But the enlistments in Arnie's Army have never stopped, and dozens more will be sworn in this morning when the 77-year-old Palmer marches onto the first tee.</p>
        <p>The tradition of an honorary starter at the Masters began in 1963 with two prominent early pros, Fred McLeod and Jock Hutchison, then it continued with Gene Sarazen, Byron Nelson, Ken Venturi and Sam Snead. For the past four years there was no honorary starter, but now there's Palmer.</p>
        <p>''I think the time has come,'' he said. ''My competitive golf is done. Maybe I might play some friendly competitions, but as far as competitions like the Masters or playing the Tour in any way, shape or form is not a reality anymore.''</p>
        <p>Would he do any ''arm-twisting'' to get Jack Nicklaus, who won a record six Masters, and Gary Player, a three-time winner, to hit future ceremonial tee shots in what would be a nostalgic reunion of what was once golf's Big Three?</p>
        <p>''To let them join me,'' he said with a laugh, ''or to tell them to stay away.''</p>
        <p>Ever the competitor, Palmer was smiling more and more as he talked. Especially when he was reminded that Player, 71, planned to play in what would be his 51st Masters next year, surpassing Palmer's record of 50 appearances, achieved in consecutive years from 1955 to 2004.</p>
        <p>''Gary just wants to do one better, and that's fine, I'm for him,'' Palmer said with that familiar smile. ''But he can't touch my record. He hasn't even come close to it. He missed a year.'' (Player did not play in the Masters in 1973.) Palmer fondly remembered his first Masters in 1955 as a rookie pro when he was paired in the first round with Sarazen, then 53 and the golfer who is remembered most for his legendary double-eagle 2 at the par-5 15th hole en route to winning the second Masters in 1935.</p>
        <p>''That was one of the great thrills of my life,'' Palmer said. ''Gene was a very quick player. When I would hit a putt, if it didn't go in the hole, he just waited until I got my ball out of the way so he could putt. If mine went in, he was putting while mine was still in the hole.''</p>
        <p>On the 15th fairway, Palmer asked Sarazen to show him the spot from which Sarazen hit a 4-wood into the cup.</p>
        <p>''He pointed out pretty much where it was,'' Palmer said. ''But you also have to remember that the tee, when he made the double eagle, was over by the trees on the left side. It's no longer even in sight now. He was right where these guys are driving it today.''</p>
        <p>Yes, ''these guys,'' primarily Tiger Woods and Phil Mickelson, who have won five of the past six Masters, much like Palmer and Nicklaus won seven of nine from 1958 to 1966.</p>
        <p>''There's certainly a parallel there,'' Palmer said. ''It's not as long as Jack and I were, but it's certainly got a definite relation to what has happened. And you could go back before Jack and myself and you could look at Hogan and Nelson and Snead and Demaret and people like that, they switched it back and forth.''</p>
        <p>Woods and Mickelson might someday be honorary starters at the Masters, but it won't be any easier for them to accept that role than it was for Palmer, who also won two British Opens and one United States Open.</p>
        <p>''You realize it's over, and it's been my life for over 50 years,'' he said. ''It's a hard pill to swallow. I'll sit at home and watch on television from time to time,'' referring to even the best of today's touring pros, ''and think, 'You know, I could have done that better.' ''</p>
        <p>And most of the time, he would have.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
