<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets Have Rare Rout, But Lose The Crowd</title>
    <meta content="05nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838209"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Atlanta Hawks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2D9163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets Have Rare Rout, But Lose The Crowd</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With 12 minutes remaining Wednesday night, Continental Arena was already nearly empty, quiet and hollow. The life had been sucked out of the building, but for good reason.</p>
        <p>The Nets soundly defeated the Atlanta Hawks, 101-86, to move a game and a half ahead of the Orlando Magic for seventh place in the Eastern Conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With 12 minutes remaining Wednesday night, Continental Arena was already nearly empty, quiet and hollow. The life had been sucked out of the building, but for good reason.</p>
        <p>The Nets soundly defeated the Atlanta Hawks, 101-86, to move a game and a half ahead of the Orlando Magic for seventh place in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>The Nets (35-39) probably would not mind such uneventful nights if it means they will limp into the playoffs. Should they get there, the Nets certainly would hope for more raucous support.</p>
        <p>The Nets are five victories away from securing a playoff spot, and that number could be smaller depending on what some of the teams trailing them -- the Magic, the Indiana Pacers and the Knicks -- do.</p>
        <p>''We know what's at stake,'' said Nets point guard Jason Kidd, who had 9 points and 10 assists. ''We feel like we're taking care of business. We've had trouble with teams that don't have good records. We've lost a lot of close games to those teams. Right now, we can't take anybody lightly.''</p>
        <p>The Nets have an outside shot to catch the Washington Wizards (39-35) for the sixth spot in the East. They have two games remaining against the Wizards, whose star player, Gilbert Arenas, left Wednesday night's loss to the Charlotte Bobcats with a sprained left knee.</p>
        <p>Forward Bostjan Nachbar led the Nets with 26 points, including a career-high seven 3-pointers. He and Vince Carter, who scored 24 points, were the catalysts of 20-2 run to end the first half that allowed the Nets to blow the game open.</p>
        <p>The rhythm the Nets were in Wednesday night was quite evident during a fourth-quarter possession. The rookie point guard Marcus Williams, dribbling just outside the top of the 3-point arc, swung a one-handed pass to Carter, who was on the right block. Carter dumped the ball off to Nachbar, who was streaking down the middle of the lane. He delivered a behind-the-back pass to Josh Boone, who threw down a two-handed dunk. That gave the Nets an 80-60 lead with 11 minutes 34 seconds remaining in the game.</p>
        <p>''I think the team looks much more mature now as the season's going to an end,'' Nachbar said. ''We don't have a lot of ups and downs anymore, especially in the second half. We're controlling the game pretty much throughout.''</p>
        <p>After falling behind by 5 points with just under five minutes remaining in the first half, the Nets went on their run and punctuated it with a pair of heady defensive plays.</p>
        <p>With 2.9 seconds remaining in the half, Hawks forward Solomon Jones jumped toward the rim with two hands, but Nachbar got in his way and forced Jones to miss the dunk. Hawks forward Marvin Williams got the rebound and went up for a dunk of his own, but Carter blocked him from behind to preserve the Nets' 52-39 halftime lead.</p>
        <p>Those two plays were indicative of the defense the Nets needed to have their way. The Nets held the Hawks to 1 of 8 shooting in the final five minutes of the first half.</p>
        <p>''We just had to step up our defensive intensity, first and foremost,'' said Carter, who scored only 4 points in the second half but had 6 assists (8 for the game). ''I think we executed frequently on offense. We moved the ball and found the open man.''</p>
        <p>The Hawks were battered because their star player, swingman Joe Johnson, has been out for about a month with an injured right calf. Regardless of who the Hawks had on the court, they have the third worst record in the East and are a team the Nets should expect to beat.</p>
        <p>One of the Nets' downfalls this season has been losing games to lesser opponents, including a home loss to the Hawks in early February. With the regular season near its end, the Nets can no longer afford to give away games, especially with coming games against the Chicago Bulls, the Wizards and the Cleveland Cavaliers.</p>
        <p>''Things change daily,'' Nets Coach Lawrence Frank said. ''As we go from here on out, every team we play is either in the playoffs or fighting to get in the playoffs. All we can be concerned about is our own play.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
