<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sweeping the Cardinals Looks as Easy as 1-2-3</title>
    <meta content="05mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/sports/baseball/05mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Maine, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1D9163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sweeping the Cardinals Looks as Easy as 1-2-3</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sweeping the Cardinals Looks as Easy as 1-2-3</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fans at Busch Stadium sat huddled far too long on this blustery 41-degree night, and when Carlos Beltrán's second home run in as many at-bats disappeared into the right-field stands in the seventh inning Wednesday night, they finally had an excuse to flee. They were fed up with how thoroughly the Mets had dismantled the Cardinals throughout this series, and the 10-0 demolition that completed their three-game sweep stuck with the theme.</p>
        <p>The Mets had ruined the pomp and circumstances of opening night, the World Series ring ceremony on Tuesday and Braden Looper's first major league start Wednesday night. While outscoring the Cardinals, 20-2, the Mets played crisp defense and received fantastic pitching, things that the Cardinals were in short supply of.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pitcher John Maine took a perfect game into the fifth inning before departing after allowing one hit and two walks in seven innings Wednesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The fans at Busch Stadium sat huddled far too long on this blustery 41-degree night, and when Carlos Beltrán's second home run in as many at-bats disappeared into the right-field stands in the seventh inning Wednesday night, they finally had an excuse to flee. They were fed up with how thoroughly the Mets had dismantled the Cardinals throughout this series, and the 10-0 demolition that completed their three-game sweep stuck with the theme.</p>
        <p>The Mets had ruined the pomp and circumstances of opening night, the World Series ring ceremony on Tuesday and Braden Looper's first major league start Wednesday night. While outscoring the Cardinals, 20-2, the Mets played crisp defense and received fantastic pitching, things that the Cardinals were in short supply of.</p>
        <p>''If we had a blueprint, that's how you'd like to do it,'' Manager Willie Randolph said.</p>
        <p>The latest strong starting-pitching performance came from John Maine, who took a perfect game into the fifth before departing after allowing one hit and two walks while striking out six in seven innings. Afterward, closer Billy Wagner sought out Maine and told his fellow Virginian, ''Way to represent.''</p>
        <p>The Cardinals, meanwhile, lost even though Looper, starting for the first time after 572 relief appearances, performed better than any other Cardinals pitcher this series. Perhaps that is why they are 0-3. The bullpen allowed seven runs after Looper left, including a solo homer to José Reyes, although two of the runs were unearned because the Cardinals committed an outfield error for the third consecutive game. Just one Cardinal reached second base.</p>
        <p>''They're not playing the best baseball right now, but it's definitely a confidence booster when you come into St. Louis and sweep the world champions,'' David Wright said.</p>
        <p>The last time the Mets won their first three games on the road was in 1994, in Chicago, but they have not started a season 4-0 since 1985. Not even last season, when they won eight of their first nine games on their way to a 16-8 April. That hot start gave the Mets the momentum they needed to roll through the East Division. But their early schedule is decidedly tougher this season -- or so it seemed, until the Cardinals imploded -- with the retooled Atlanta Braves up next and another strong division opponent, the Philadelphia Phillies, awaiting them at Shea Stadium for Monday's home opener. With this leg out of the way, the Mets can focus on disrupting the Braves' home opener Friday, when they will march into Turner Field as the division champions.</p>
        <p>Maine spent most of spring training tinkering with his slider and developing a changeup, which he hoped would offset his fastball's tendency to rise. Needing only 41 pitches to retire the first 12 Cardinals, Maine was confident throwing both pitches at any point in the count, but mostly as a strikeout pitch.</p>
        <p>In the fourth, Maine struck out Chris Duncan on a fading changeup. In the fifth, after Scott Rolen's leadoff single snapped his perfect game, Maine caught Preston Wilson flailing at a 2-2 slider in the dirt, then came back to retire Yadier Molina on a lineout to third and Aaron Miles on an inning-ending fly out.</p>
        <p>''We've got the kind of hitters where we've got to get something, and we got one rally the whole game,'' Cardinals Manager Tony La Russa said. ''That's not making enough happen.''</p>
        <p>For Maine, it was just a continuation of his recent dominance against the Cardinals. He shut them out through five and a third innings in Game 6 of last year's National League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>''It's a good start, but it's already behind me,'' Maine said. ''In five more days, I have another start.''</p>
        <p>Looper, the former Mets closer, whose two seasons in New York were marked by meltdowns in big games, was just as giddy at the prospect of pitching against his former team. Converted to a starter after Jeff Weaver, Jeff Suppan and Jason Marquis signed elsewhere, Looper shut down the Mets through five innings with his rediscovered cutter and a sinker that bore over the inside corner against left-handed hitters. He had allowed four hits -- all singles -- before Paul Lo Duca ripped a one-out single, his third hit of the night, into center field. Beltrán took two quick strikes and then pounced on a fat up-and-in fastball, launching it a few rows deep into the right-field stands.</p>
        <p>''The first couple of innings, he was throwing hard,'' Beltrán said of Looper. ''Then he got a little bit tired, and he started leaving the ball over the middle of the plate.''</p>
        <p>As Looper started wearing down, Beltrán was warming up. When he came up the next inning against Josh Hancock, he watched one pitch sail by for ball one, then clobbered the next deep into the right-field stands, sending fans scattering. They never came back.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Willie Randolph will wear Jackie Robinson's No. 42 for the Mets' April 15 game against Washington as part of Major League Baseball's celebration of the 60th anniversary of Robinson's breaking the major league color barrier. For a boy growing up in Brooklyn who became the first African-American manager in New York, there is no greater honor. ''I said I'd have to fight whoever to get to wear No. 42,'' Randolph said. ''Anything associated with Jackie Robinson is an honor for me, and it will be a very special day to wear his No. 42.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
