<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mommy and Daddy's Little Life Coach</title>
    <meta content="05advice" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/fashion/05advice.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3DE163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mommy and Daddy's Little Life Coach</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mommy and Daddy’s Little Life Coach</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE ROSENBLOOM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbloom, Stephanie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Helen Barahal was deciding whether to sell an East Harlem apartment she was renting to tenants, she asked her son, Marcus, for advice.</p>
        <p>''I knew that the neighborhood wasn't that good at the time, but it was going to change,'' Marcus said. ''I told her to hold on to it because I knew we would make more from the rent instead of selling it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nature and pervasiveness of child-to-parent advice has reached new proportions as many parents are treating their offspring as worldly equals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Helen Barahal was deciding whether to sell an East Harlem apartment she was renting to tenants, she asked her son, Marcus, for advice.</p>
        <p>''I knew that the neighborhood wasn't that good at the time, but it was going to change,'' Marcus said. ''I told her to hold on to it because I knew we would make more from the rent instead of selling it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Barahal heeded his advice and has kept the apartment (worth about $100,000 when she bought it in 2000), which is now being bought for four times as much.</p>
        <p>It was a ''Marcus-approved sale,'' Ms. Barahal said.</p>
        <p>Marcus is 11.</p>
        <p>But age, as they say, is just a number. Ms. Barahal's broker, Jeffrey Gardere of the Corcoran Group (who happens to have a doctorate in psychology), said that Ms. Barahal, like many parents nowadays, does not simply listen to her child. ''She relies on what he has to say,'' Mr. Gardere said.</p>
        <p>Parents have long depended on their children to be in-house experts on fashion, technology and pop culture, to introduce them to fresh music, purge their closets of ghastly apparel (''mom jeans'') and troubleshoot household electronics. And generations of parents have encouraged their children to weigh in on family decisions like choosing a winter vacation spot or a replacement for the belly-up goldfish.</p>
        <p>But the nature and pervasiveness of child-to-parent advice has reached new proportions for a variety of reasons. Many parents -- who have shed their status as old fogy untouchables and become pals with their progeny -- are treating their offspring as worldly equals. They think of their computer-savvy, plugged-in children as confidants, and so they look to them for advice on life decisions, as well as major purchases: cars, computers, vacation packages, real estate, home décor.</p>
        <p>An article in the Journal of Business Research for April says today's children ''encounter decision-making at an earlier age,'' are ''taking on greater roles and responsibilities in family purchases'' and are influencing their parents' buying decisions far beyond areas where children are the ''primary product users.''</p>
        <p>Sandi Mendelson, a chief executive at Hilsinger-Mendelson, a literary public relations firm, said she seeks advice from her daughter, Karah Preiss, 17, because, ''I just respect how she looks at the world.''</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of trust,'' said Ms. Mendelson, who lives in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Karah -- who figured out which television the family should buy and turned her mother onto the band Coldplay -- also obliges her mother's publishing-executive friends when they want to pick her brain about what's in and what's out. She said she enjoys weighing in, as well as hanging out with her mother and her mother's friends.</p>
        <p>''It's not a sort of 'You're so lame, Mom' situation at all,'' Karah said. ''I don't ever feel like I'm stuck in the parent-child stereotype, where I'm, like, rolling my eyes.''</p>
        <p>Susan Linn, a psychologist at Judge Baker Children's Center and Harvard Medical School and the author of ''Consuming Kids: The Hostile Takeover of Childhood'' (New Press, 2004), suggested a few explanations for the boom in adolescent advice.</p>
        <p>One cause is the increase in single parent families. In 2003 about 28 percent of children lived with only a father or a mother, up from about 12 percent in 1970, according to the Census Bureau. Because single parents bear the burden of raising children alone, they are more stressed, Dr. Linn said, so the parent-child dynamic tends to be more negotiable.</p>
        <p>''It's just the two of us,'' said Dr. Betsy Kavaler, a single parent, who lives with her daughter, Sonia Brozak, 11, in Manhattan. ''That makes her more like a partner in some ways than a child.''</p>
        <p>Sonia has spoken to a contractor about renovations to their apartment when Dr. Kavaler, a urologist, is at work; has chosen vacations for her and her mother prompted by her art and history studies; has even decided which middle school would be the best to attend.</p>
        <p>''It's so different than when we were growing up,'' said Dr. Kavaler, who participates in numerous activities with Sonia and her friends.</p>
        <p>''Now it's 'What do the kids want?' '' Dr. Kavaler said. ''My father would say, 'Who cares what the kids want?' ''</p>
        <p>(Of course, in places like ancient Egypt, where Tutankhamen became King Tut at 8 or 9, they had to care.)</p>
        <p>Sonia, for one, likes to contribute her two cents. ''It's nice because I feel like I'm not being spoken down to,'' she said. ''Ninety-five percent of the time I feel most kids are spoken down to.''</p>
        <p>Jodi Seidler, the creator of Makinglemonade.com, a Web site for single parents, said her son, Sam, who turned 17 this week, ''advises me about everything,'' including her leap back into the dating pool.</p>
        <p>''He said 'Well, Mom, why don't you go online?' '' said Ms. Seidler, who lives in Santa Monica, Calif., and has since been on the dating Web sites eHarmony, Matchmaker and JDate. She has given Sam information about promising prospective dates and listened to his response, not only because she wants his advice, but also because she wants ''to see who he is and what he thinks.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Seidler said that Sam often reassures her that when the time is right, Mr. Right will appear. (''It's so Zen,'' she said.) Routinely levelheaded advice from a child, however, has its downside.</p>
        <p>''That's what makes it hard,'' Ms. Seidler said. ''When your own child is more sophisticated or intuitive or sensitive or funny than the men that are out there.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Linn said another reason for the ratcheting up of adolescent advice is today's incessant marketing. Besides filling children's heads with information about products and brands, giving children ''the trappings of maturity,'' it sells everyone on the notion that children are smarter now than in previous generations, Dr. Linn said.</p>
        <p>In reality, though, the prefrontal cortex of the brain, which plays a significant role in judgment, ''doesn't fully develop until the 20s,'' she said. (She estimates that children influence about $600 billion in adult spending a year, and almost $17 billion a year is spent directly marketing to children, even for adult goods like cars.)</p>
        <p>The advice trend is also driven, Dr. Linn said, by the increased access to information children have because of the Internet, as well as by Peter Pan parents, who may think they can stay young and relevant by swapping advice with teenagers.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reasons, is being a resource for parents a burden for children? Are they growing up too soon? And when they do grow up, will they think they are the equals of older co-workers and managers from the get-go?</p>
        <p>That all depends, psychologists say, on the child, the decisions the child is making and the family situation. Giving children too much power can make them feel unsafe. But inviting children to help choose which board game to play or which DVD to rent may help them learn to participate in group decision making.</p>
        <p>Dan Kindlon, who teaches child psychology at Harvard and wrote ''Alpha Girls: Understanding the New American Girl and How She Is Changing the World'' (Rodale Books, 2006), said that as long as children believe they can rely on their parents and that there are boundaries -- like curfews or limits on Internet time -- seeking advice from one's child can be a win-win situation.</p>
        <p>By giving advice to their parents, teenagers learn to give back and to practice being independent thinking adults, said Dr. Kindlon, who is a father of teenagers. ''They feel like they're contributing in a meaningful way,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the notion that children today are wiser than previous generations, that they are ''getting older younger,'' Dr. Linn said, is really a ''commercially constructed phenomenon that is resulting in kids' sort of skipping over a whole part of childhood.''</p>
        <p>''We're robbing kids of childhood in some ways,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The image of the American teenager as the young but sober purveyor of advice on love, money and life is only reinforced in films (''Clueless'' is a prime example) and television series (''Friday Night Lights,'' ''Gilmore Girls'' and ''Desperate Housewives,'' to name a few).</p>
        <p>In a new movie, ''The TV Set,'' to be released tomorrow, Sigourney Weaver plays Lenny, a television executive, who keeps a finger on the pulse of the network's crucial demographic by having her teenage daughter, Bethany, evaluate every pilot. (When she says she loves the network's reality series ''Slut Wars,'' Lenny just knows it will be a hit.)</p>
        <p>In real life, Ms. Weaver said she does not rely on her daughter, Charlotte Simpson, 16, for career advice, though if she had to make a ''life decision,'' she said by phone, ''I would.''</p>
        <p>''My daughter and her friends, they seem much more confident and wiser than I felt at that age,'' Ms. Weaver said. ''I felt like the ultimate geek of all time. They seem very comfortable in their skins.''</p>
        <p>Of course, adolescents have always grappled with weighty decisions. Dr. Kindlon pointed out that when all Americans lived on farms, children had real responsibilities. ''We've just extended adolescence so long in our culture, we kind of forget how much responsibility teenagers used to get,'' Dr. Kindlon said. He paused and then wondered aloud, ''How old was King Tut?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
