<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Side Declines to Gamble, And the Other Finishes Strong</title>
    <meta content="05card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/crosswords/bridge/05card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Side Declines to Gamble, And the Other Finishes Strong</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Side Declines to Gamble, and the Other Finishes Strong</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alder, Phillip</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Heitzman Jr. of Suffern, N.Y., and Jonathan Weinstein of Evanston, Ill., finished second in the Lebhar Imp Pairs at the Spring North American Championships in St. Louis last month, 17 imps behind Boye Brogeland from Norway and Ishmael Del'Monte from Australia. Heitzman and Weinstein scored well on the diagramed deal.</p>
        <p>The first decision was South's: Should he open one no-trump to show his balanced hand with 15-17 points, or should he begin with one club because he has two unguarded suits and a pair of four-card majors?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Heitzman Jr. of Suffern, N.Y., and Jonathan Weinstein of Evanston, Ill., finished second in the Lebhar Imp Pairs at the Spring North American Championships.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert Heitzman Jr. of Suffern, N.Y., and Jonathan Weinstein of Evanston, Ill., finished second in the Lebhar Imp Pairs at the Spring North American Championships in St. Louis last month, 17 imps behind Boye Brogeland from Norway and Ishmael Del'Monte from Australia. Heitzman and Weinstein scored well on the diagramed deal.</p>
        <p>The first decision was South's: Should he open one no-trump to show his balanced hand with 15-17 points, or should he begin with one club because he has two unguarded suits and a pair of four-card majors?</p>
        <p>Weinstein decided on one club. After West overcalled one spade, and Heitzman made a negative double promising four hearts (or five in a hand too weak to respond two hearts), East should have advanced with one no-trump. It would not have been without risk, but more points are lost with pusillanimous passes than with brazen bids. Holding nine high-card points, he should have made some show of strength.</p>
        <p>Here South would still have rebid two hearts, but then maybe West would have contested with three diamonds, a contract that would make with an overtrick.</p>
        <p>After East passed and South rebid two hearts, West might have gambled with a takeout double, but that would have been aggressive opposite a partner who had passed twice.</p>
        <p>Against two hearts West, a professional player, led the diamond king and continued with a low diamond to his partner's ace. East shifted to the spade six, declarer rising with his ace and cashing two top trumps to get the bad news about the 4-1 break.</p>
        <p>Now South led his club eight, which West fatally failed to cover with the ten.</p>
        <p>East took the club eight with his king and returned his second spade, West winning with the ten to give this end position:</p>
        <p>South could afford to lose only one more trick. If West had led the spade king, declarer would have ruffed on the board. East would have overruffed and returned his remaining trump, but South would have won in his hand, cashed the spade queen and played a club to dummy's jack. East would not have passed throughout with the club queen as well.</p>
        <p>Instead West tried his spade jack, East ruffing after declarer pitched a club from the board. Now East led a diamond, which allowed a pretty ending. South discarded a club from his hand, ruffed on the board, played a heart to his queen and cashed the final trump. West threw in the towel, being caught in a black-suit show-up squeeze.</p>
        <p>Making two hearts was worth 4.9 international match points. Going down one would have resulted in a fractional loss.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
