<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Irish Inquiry Faults Handling of Day of Attacks in 1974</title>
    <meta content="05irish" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/world/europe/05irish.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northern Ireland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ireland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dublin (Ireland)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Monaghan (Ireland)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quinn, Eamon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland/Dublin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Northern Ireland</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EEDC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="430" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Irish Inquiry Faults Handling of Day of Attacks in 1974</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Irish Inquiry Faults Handling of Day of Attacks in 1974</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EAMON QUINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Quinn, Eamon</byline>
      <dateline>DUBLIN, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Irish government commission of inquiry issues report critical of police for their handling of investigation of 1974 coordinated bombings in Dublin and Monaghan which killed 33 adults and children; report notes police lost files and documentation, but says police are not solely responsible for shortcomings in inquiry; victims' representatives claim British authorities in Northern Ireland and Irish police in Dublin quickly identified presumed bombers and traced them to unionist areas of Northern Ireland, then quickly wound down their inquiry (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although the decades of violent conflict over Northern Ireland have ended, an official report issued here on Wednesday demonstrated how the past still haunts the landscape.</p>
        <p>The report addressed the deadliest day of the conflict -- May 17, 1974, when 33 adults and children were killed in coordinated bombings in Dublin and Monaghan, Ireland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The report criticized the police for losing files and documentation, saying documentation had been handled in a way that was “manifestly inappropriate.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although the decades of violent conflict over Northern Ireland have ended, an official report issued here on Wednesday demonstrated how the past still haunts the landscape.</p>
        <p>The report addressed the deadliest day of the conflict -- May 17, 1974, when 33 adults and children were killed in coordinated bombings in Dublin and Monaghan, Ireland.</p>
        <p>After decades of dead-end investigations, the official Irish government commission of inquiry, consisting of a sole member, Patrick McEntee, a senior criminal prosecuting lawyer, was asked by the Irish government to find out why the Irish police had quickly wound down their inquiry into the bombings.</p>
        <p>In his report, he criticized the police for losing files and documentation, saying documentation had been handled in a way that was ''manifestly inappropriate.'' But he said it would be ''unfair and unjust'' to say the police were ''solely responsible for the shortcomings'' in the inquiry.</p>
        <p>The toll of 33 dead was the worst in three decades of violence between republicans, who wanted Northern Ireland to unite with Ireland, and unionists, who wanted it to remain a British province. More than 3,700 people were killed in the conflict, which ended with an accord in 1998.</p>
        <p>Representatives of the victims say the British authorities in Northern Ireland and the Irish police in Dublin quickly identified the presumed bombers and traced them to unionist areas of Northern Ireland. But within weeks of the bombings, the investigation in Dublin ended. None ever started in Belfast.</p>
        <p>''It was shameful,'' said Dermot Walsh, a professor of law at the University of Limerick, who said he suspected that the Irish government had been frightened that any hint of British military collusion in the bombings would give a propaganda coup to the Irish Republican Army.</p>
        <p>At 5:30 p.m. on the day of the bombings, Bernadette McNally, 16, was waiting for the workday to end so she could leave her job selling shoes on Talbot Street in Dublin, she said Wednesday in an interview.</p>
        <p>''A late customer came in looking for -- and I will always remember -- a pair of brown sandals,'' she said. ''There was then a big flash, and it was like a violent wind. I was thrown to the floor.''</p>
        <p>The second of three car bombs in Dublin had gone off, killing 13 people, including the customer shopping for sandals and May McKenna, who lived upstairs. A fourth exploded in Monaghan, 75 miles away.</p>
        <p>Ms. McNally said she remained angry at the authorities who, she said, ''hushed up'' the violence. They should find out who gave the orders that day in May, she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
