<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberty Trades Hammon for No. 2 Pick</title>
    <meta content="05wnba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/sports/basketball/05wnba.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Liberty</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Women's National Basketball Association</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hammon, Becky</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5D9163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="438" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberty Trades Hammon for No. 2 Pick</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Liberty Trades Hammon for No. 2 Pick in the Draft</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The W.N.B.A. president, Donna Orender, wearing a broad smile, walked to the lectern yesterday and announced that Liberty point guard Becky Hammon had been traded to the San Antonio Silver Stars for the draft rights to center Jessica Davenport.</p>
        <p>''Wow!'' Orender said after making the announcement at the W.N.B.A. draft, held in Cleveland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Liberty point guard Becky Hammon, who had been the face of the franchise for several years, was traded to the San Antonio Silver Stars for the draft rights to center Jessica Davenport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The W.N.B.A. president, Donna Orender, wearing a broad smile, walked to the lectern yesterday and announced that Liberty point guard Becky Hammon had been traded to the San Antonio Silver Stars for the draft rights to center Jessica Davenport.</p>
        <p>''Wow!'' Orender said after making the announcement at the W.N.B.A. draft, held in Cleveland.</p>
        <p>Only seven minutes earlier, the Liberty had drafted Tiffany Jackson, a forward from Texas, with the fifth pick. Before Liberty fans could digest the vision of a Hammon-to-Jackson scoring punch, the team traded for Davenport, who was selected second over all by the Silver Stars.</p>
        <p>Hammon, a three-time All-Star, had been the face of the franchise for several years. But the Liberty, which was 11-23 last season, has been in a rebuilding mode and was aiming to bolster its front court. Davenport and Jackson add instant youth and credibility.</p>
        <p>''I think this is a big day for the Liberty,'' Coach Pat Coyle said on a conference call with reporters. ''We're just delighted with our picks.''</p>
        <p>There was another trade at the top of the draft board as the Phoenix Mercury took point guard Lindsey Harding of Duke with the No. 1 pick and then sent her to the Minnesota Lynx for Tangela Smith, a nine-year veteran. It was the first time in the 11-year history of the draft that the top two picks were traded.</p>
        <p>The other players in the top five were Armintie Price of Mississippi, who went to the Chicago Sky at No. 3, and Noelle Quinn of U.C.L.A., who went fourth to Minnesota.</p>
        <p>The Liberty also selected guard Shay Doron of Maryland in the second round and forward Martina Weber of Iona in the third.</p>
        <p>In the trade for the 6-foot-5 Davenport, the Liberty sent its second-round pick next year to the Silver Stars for San Antonio's first-round pick.</p>
        <p>Davenport, a three-time Big Ten player of the year from Ohio State, averaged 20 points and 9.6 rebounds this season. Her college career ended with a whimper, when 13th-seeded Marist beat the fourth-seeded Buckeyes in the first round of the N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
        <p>''New York is the Mecca of basketball,'' Davenport said. ''So just to be able to go there and play ball, I'm going to be excited.''</p>
        <p>The 6-3 Jackson averaged 16.8 points and 9 rebounds in her senior season as Texas missed its second straight N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
        <p>Hammon was playing in Spain when the trade unfolded.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Tickets for Liberty games this season, which begins at home May 20 against Chicago, went on sale yesterday. They can be purchased at Ticketmaster.com and nyliberty.com or by calling (877) 962-2849.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
