<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Obama Shows His Strength in a Fund-Raising Feat on Par With Clinton</title>
    <meta content="05obama" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/us/politics/05obama.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zeleny, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Healy, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obama, Barack (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7DA163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Obama Shows His Strength in a Fund-Raising Feat on Par With Clinton</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Obama Shows His Strength in a Fund-Raising Feat on Par With Clinton</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF ZELENY and PATRICK HEALY; Jeff Zeleny reported from Des Moines, and Patrick Healy from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zeleny, Jeff; Healy, Patrick</byline>
      <dateline>DES MOINES, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen Barack Obama's campaign says fundraising in first three months exceeded goals set when he entered race in Jan; reports raising $25 million, with donations from 100,000 people, half of whom contributed through Internet and thousands of whom gave $25; figures show Obama standing toe to toe with Sen Hillary Rodham Clinton, whose campaign raised $26 million; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If there was any doubt that Senator Barack Obama could stand toe to toe with Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, at least in raising money, the matter was settled on Wednesday as Mr. Obama's presidential campaign announced raising $25 million in the first three months of the year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama's total for the first fund-raising period of the 2008 presidential race was close to Mrs. Clinton's. She reported Sunday that she had raised $26 million, but declined to provide a breakdown of contributions for the primary season versus the general election. Mr. Obama said $23.5 million of the money he raised was for the primary season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Obama campaign announced it had raised $25 million only days after Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton said her campaign had raised $26 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If there was any doubt that Senator Barack Obama could stand toe to toe with Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, at least in raising money, the matter was settled on Wednesday as Mr. Obama's presidential campaign announced raising $25 million in the first three months of the year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama's total for the first fund-raising period of the 2008 presidential race was close to Mrs. Clinton's. She reported Sunday that she had raised $26 million, but declined to provide a breakdown of contributions for the primary season versus the general election. Mr. Obama said $23.5 million of the money he raised was for the primary season.</p>
        <p>''It's been a truly historic response,'' Mr. Obama said in an e-mail message to supporters, ''a measure of just how hungry people are to turn the page on this era of small and destructive politics and repair our American community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama, who arrived in Iowa on Wednesday evening for a campaign trip, was the last major candidate to disclose his figures for the first quarter of this year, purposefully keeping his tally under wraps for a dramatic unveiling designed to show his breadth of support. He said he had received donations from 100,000 people, half of whom contributed through the Internet, including thousands who gave $25.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton and former President Bill Clinton spent Wednesday at their home in Chappaqua, N.Y., at a previously scheduled retreat with top aides. A Clinton campaign official said they had reached their fund-raising goals for the first quarter and emphasized that both Clintons would pursue donors even more vigorously over the next three months.</p>
        <p>The Obama campaign said fund-raising had exceeded goals that were set when Mr. Obama entered the race in January. Over the last 11 weeks, campaign officials said, event attendance often doubled expectations and low-dollar contributions have poured in. Last Saturday, the final day of the quarter, officials said the campaign had raised $500,000 on its Web site alone.</p>
        <p>''There is a freshness and enthusiasm out there that certainly does not guarantee future financial success,'' David Plouffe, the Obama campaign manager, said in an interview. ''But it's a tremendous asset to have.''</p>
        <p>The Obama campaign reported raising $6.9 million using the Internet, compared with $4.2 million by the Clinton campaign. While raising money on Web sites provides a far cheaper -- and faster -- alternative to direct mail and fund-raising events, it remains difficult to gauge whether online success translates into electoral success, as Howard Dean illustrated in the last Democratic presidential race.</p>
        <p>Still, several Clinton donors privately wondered whether Mrs. Clinton was having trouble converting contributors from her two Senate races into donors for her presidential bid. She began this race with a database of more than 250,000 donors, and received money from 50,000 contributors in the first quarter. Mr. Obama said he began his national campaign with a far smaller database, but attracted 100,000 contributors.</p>
        <p>Fred P. Hochberg, a Democratic fund-raiser in New York who is helping Mrs. Clinton, said it was far too soon to tell if the gap in donors was troubling.</p>
        <p>''You've really got to wait and see,'' Mr. Hochberg said. ''Who knows what his Internet operation was like compared to hers? And 50,000 people is a lot of donors. They both have a lot of donors.''</p>
        <p>The Clinton campaign declined to provide a breakdown of Mrs. Clinton's separate fund-raising totals for the primary campaign account and the general election account. Candidates are allowed to receive up to $4,600 per donor -- $2,300 for the primary season and $2,300 for the general election.</p>
        <p>Both the Clinton campaign and the Obama campaign declined to disclose how much money they had in the bank. All the figures will be made public by April 15, when reports must be filed with the Federal Election Commission.</p>
        <p>Penny Pritzker, finance chairwoman for the Obama campaign, met with major fund-raisers at a breakfast Wednesday morning in midtown Manhattan and later spoke to fund-raisers across the country on a conference call. One topic of discussion, according to participants, was what some supporters said was a need to refocus attention from Mr. Obama's fund-raising toward a series of policy speeches he intends to make in the next quarter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama, a longtime advocate of public financing and campaign finance overhaul, is seldom eager to talk about his fund-raising. While his campaign trumpeted the news on Wednesday, requests for interviews with the candidate were denied.</p>
        <p>''The average citizen cares not one whit about this,'' David Axelrod, the campaign's chief strategist said in an interview. ''Nonetheless, as a new candidate starting up from scratch, given the capacities of some of the other campaigns, we knew that this was a test of whether we were real or not and whether we had the capacity to hang in there for the long term.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
