<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italians Win Yukos Units, But Gazprom Is to Benefit</title>
    <meta content="05yukos" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/business/worldbusiness/05yukos.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eni</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enel Spa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yukos (Russian Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kramer, Andrew E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Moscow (Russia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Yukos</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Gazprom</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EEDB163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italians Win Yukos Units, But Gazprom Is to Benefit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Italians Win Yukos Units, but Gazprom Is to Benefit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW E. KRAMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kramer, Andrew E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Italian energy companies Eni and Enel win auction for assets of bankrupt Yukos oil company, then promptly announces they will sell most of assets to state-owned Russian gas giant Gazprom; two companies bid $5.83 billion for 20 percent of Gazprom Neft, held by Yukos, and for companies that hold natural gas field licenses in Russian Arctic; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two Italian energy companies won an auction Wednesday for assets of the bankrupt Yukos oil company, then promptly announced they would sell most of the assets to the state-owned Russian gas giant Gazprom.</p>
        <p>The two Italian companies, Eni and Enel, which have been courting Gazprom on a range of deals, bid $5.83 billion for the 20 percent of Gazprom's oil subsidiary, Gazprom Neft, held by Yukos, and for companies that hold natural gas field licenses in the Russian Arctic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The two Italian energy companies who won the Yukos auction announced they would sell most of the assets to the state-owned Russian gas giant Gazprom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two Italian energy companies won an auction Wednesday for assets of the bankrupt Yukos oil company, then promptly announced they would sell most of the assets to the state-owned Russian gas giant Gazprom.</p>
        <p>The two Italian companies, Eni and Enel, which have been courting Gazprom on a range of deals, bid $5.83 billion for the 20 percent of Gazprom's oil subsidiary, Gazprom Neft, held by Yukos, and for companies that hold natural gas field licenses in the Russian Arctic.</p>
        <p>Their joint venture, EniNeftegaz, which is 60 percent owned by Eni and 40 percent by Enel, bid against companies affiliated with Rosneft and Novatek, an independent Russian gas producer.</p>
        <p>The sale was the second of a half-dozen or so auctions planned this spring to dispose of the assets of Yukos, once Russia's largest private company. Yukos was declared bankrupt last August.</p>
        <p>In the first sale, Rosneft, the state oil company, won 9.4 percent of its own stock that had been held by Yukos, paying about 10 percent less than the market price for the shares on the London Stock Exchange. Oil analysts say most of the assets will end up with Russia's two state companies, Gazprom and Rosneft.</p>
        <p>EniNeftegaz had earlier signed an option agreement giving Gazprom rights to buy the entire stake in Gazprom Neft and 51 percent of the other companies. After the auction Wednesday, Gazprom's deputy director for exports, Aleksandr I. Medvedev, said Gazprom would exercise the option.</p>
        <p>An agreement signed last November between Eni and Gazprom broadly promised the Italian company access to upstream Russian gas assets in exchange for investment opportunities for Gazprom in the retail side of the natural gas business in Europe.</p>
        <p>''This transaction, which is in the context of a fruitful and ongoing relationship between Italy and Russia, underlines the value of our strategic partnership with Gazprom,'' Paolo Scaroni, the chief executive of Eni, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Gazprom has struck similar deals with BASF and E.On, the German energy companies, and President Vladimir V. Putin has called such agreements a model for foreign investment in Russia's state-dominated energy sector.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the auction Tuesday, Prime Minister Romano Prodi of Italy spoke on the telephone with Mr. Putin. The pair discussed cultural programs and ''trade and economic'' cooperation, according to the Kremlin press service, which did not say if the auction was mentioned.</p>
        <p>At the auction, Eni and Enel representatives raised small paper tickets to bid as an auctioneer called out the prices.</p>
        <p>The outcome, however, appeared determined in the earlier negotiations of Eni, Gazprom and the Russian government, Kaha Kiknavelidze, an oil and gas analyst for UBS, said in a telephone interview from London. ''Naturally, a Gazprom-endorsed entity is a favorite,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiknavelidze said that Gazprom is understood to have been offered assets outside Russia, possibly in Europe or North Africa, in exchange for the former Yukos property obtained by Eni and Enel.</p>
        <p>As in the Rosneft sale, Mr. Kiknavelidze and other energy analysts said the gas fields went for well below market rates. Gazprom has agreed to pay $3.7 billion for the Gazprom Neft shares, meaning the Italian companies paid a net $2.14 billion for the fields. The fields hold an estimated five billion barrels of oil equivalent, according to the Eni statement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
