<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Photographing the Light in Places That May Soon Be Lost</title>
    <meta content="05dome" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/arts/design/05dome.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Photographing the Light in Places That May Soon Be Lost</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Photographing the Light in Places That May Soon Be Lost</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shattuck, Kathryn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>But for the occasional modern accouterment -- a microwave in Belgium, a row of 2005 calendars in Spain -- Bert Teunissen's photographs of Europeans at home could have been captured in the remote corners of the continent a century or two ago. Weathered faces gaze out from surroundings patinaed through generations of use. Fireplaces the size of caves radiate heat across stone-slab floors. Hams and sausages age on hooks dangling from massive wooden beams. A dog wiles away a lazy lifetime at its owner's feet.</p>
        <p>And then there is the light, dissipated by homespun lace or entering windows unobstructed, that slices through the haze of years like a freshly sharpened knife.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bert Teunissen’s photographs of Europeans at home could have been captured in the remote corners of the continent a century or two ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>But for the occasional modern accouterment -- a microwave in Belgium, a row of 2005 calendars in Spain -- Bert Teunissen's photographs of Europeans at home could have been captured in the remote corners of the continent a century or two ago. Weathered faces gaze out from surroundings patinaed through generations of use. Fireplaces the size of caves radiate heat across stone-slab floors. Hams and sausages age on hooks dangling from massive wooden beams. A dog wiles away a lazy lifetime at its owner's feet.</p>
        <p>And then there is the light, dissipated by homespun lace or entering windows unobstructed, that slices through the haze of years like a freshly sharpened knife.</p>
        <p>''At first I thought it was quite obvious to compare the work of a Dutch photographer to a Dutch painter,'' Mr. Teunissen said of his initial dismay at reviews that likened his portraits to the still lifes painted by Vermeer and de Hoogh. But once he more closely examined the Dutch masterpieces painted some 300 years earlier and their particular radiance, he too was struck by a certain similarity.</p>
        <p>''It was only then that I understood that the kind of light I used in those pictures is the same kind of light as painters used in those paintings,'' he said in a telephone interview from his home in Huizen, about 15 miles east of Amsterdam. ''It's old and antique light, the kind you rarely see anymore.''</p>
        <p>Thirty of Mr. Teunissen's portraits are on view at the Aperture Gallery in Chelsea through May 10, when a companion book, ''Domestic Landscapes,'' will be published in the United States by Aperture. His Web site, bertteunissen.com, has several hundred more, including images from a 2003 project in Japan. Spanning 10 countries and 10 years and counting, his collection serves to archive a way of life that is, he said, ''fated to disappear as a consequence not only of architectural standardization but also of social displacement and shifts in public opinion about life and how it should be lived.''</p>
        <p>''Domestic Landscapes'' began as a quest for the special light and atmospheres that were familiar to Mr. Teunissen, now 47, as a boy, and that he longed for after his childhood dwelling in the rural Netherlands was razed when he was 8 and replaced by a modern house that never quite felt like home.</p>
        <p>It metamorphosed into an effort to preserve memories of a lifestyle fast becoming obsolete. Of the more than 350 structures Mr. Teunissen has photographed, he estimated that about 90 percent no longer exist.</p>
        <p>A commercial photographer whose work for companies like G Star Jeans veers toward the cool and kinetic, Mr. Teunissen came upon his first interior in ''Domestic Landscapes'' by accident, as he cycled through the hamlet of Castelnau in southwestern France.</p>
        <p>There he found his way to the home of a white-haired woman who sat at a wooden table, its top painted in brown and white checks. Behind her a deer head was mounted above a stone fireplace adorned with a short toile curtain. Shelves of bottles and painted dishware hung beneath a heavy beamed ceiling.</p>
        <p>''I was immediately bewitched by the atmosphere,'' he said. ''The light that fell through the windows seemed extremely familiar to me.''</p>
        <p>Almost a year later, on an assignment to capture what he called a ''Sunday afternoon feeling'' for a gin advertisement, he took a similar image some 700 miles away in his birthplace of Ruurlo.</p>
        <p>''It started occurring to me that there had been an atmospheric similarity,'' he said. ''The places in my photographs had something in common that had to do with some kind of architectural consistency.''</p>
        <p>''But it was not just about nice old places that gave me a nostalgic feeling and reminded me of my old family home,'' he continued. ''It also became clear that this had to do with a way of living, a way of building, a way of using the house, that I understood was disappearing.''</p>
        <p>He began to investigate remote regions of Europe where actual daylight had been an important aspect in the way people lived and used a house in the years before electricity.</p>
        <p>Through mayors, fire stations and tour guides, he asked for introductions into people's homes, after which he set up his camera, using only natural light to illuminate his subjects in the rooms they used most.</p>
        <p>Many of the dwellings in ''Domestic Landscapes'' have been lived in by the same families across centuries, their occupants some of the last purveyors of ancient culinary and agricultural traditions.</p>
        <p>But while most of his subjects were elderly, he occasionally stumbled across younger people who honored the more self-sufficient ways of their ancestors. An image taken in the Spanish village of Monterroso shows a tub of fresh meat on the floor before an old couple and their middle-aged son, who abandoned a successful career in Switzerland to return home and revive traditional methods of raising and slaughtering livestock.</p>
        <p>''Ironically, the Europeans portrayed by Teunissen are members of a generation whose work on the foundations of the European Union has ushered in the demise of their own way of life,'' Saskia Asser, a curator at the Huis Marseille Museum for Photography in Amsterdam, wrote in an essay for the exhibition. ''Age-old trades and crafts are disappearing as farming and agriculture are industrialized. Moreover, strict European Union regulations passed down from Brussels make life for the small farmer or food producer untenable.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Teunissen witnessed the effects of these regulations in northern Portugal, where assorted pubs and taverns had been shuttered because they did not meet the latest European Union standards, which he said required them to have two built-in toilets and stainless steel worktops.</p>
        <p>''Since the provincial government was dependent on European subsidies to finance the construction of a much-needed new road, the mostly elderly innkeepers were forced to either comply, which they simply could not afford to do, or close down,'' he wrote in an essay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Teunissen will soon begin photographing in Eastern Europe and Russia, and hopes someday to venture to the United States, he said.</p>
        <p>But always there is the pressure of time.</p>
        <p>''Those people belong there,'' he said. ''That's what you feel when you look at the pictures. They kind of made each other, the people and the places, they became a single unit together.</p>
        <p>''All you can do now is cross the country and hope that you still find places that have been left alone, and left in peace.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
