<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Symbol From a Golden Age Of Football Is Lost</title>
    <meta content="05rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/sports/ncaafootball/05rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Grambling State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Robinson, Eddie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2D9163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Symbol From a Golden Age Of Football Is Lost</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Coach Who Symbolized a Golden Age of Football</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everybody knew the end was near for Eddie Robinson: James Harris and Doug Williams, Robinson's cornerstone quarterbacks at Grambling State University; the sprawling Grambling family; the news media that covered Robinson's historic moments. We all knew. His health had been in steady decline for months.</p>
        <p>Still, when we learned that Coach Rob had died, the news came as a blow. An icon was gone, a legend was dead, another era of college football had ended.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eddie Robinson was a symbol of the virtues associated with being “Coach”: dedicated and stubborn, firm and dictatorial. Yet always a gentleman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everybody knew the end was near for Eddie Robinson: James Harris and Doug Williams, Robinson's cornerstone quarterbacks at Grambling State University; the sprawling Grambling family; the news media that covered Robinson's historic moments. We all knew. His health had been in steady decline for months.</p>
        <p>Still, when we learned that Coach Rob had died, the news came as a blow. An icon was gone, a legend was dead, another era of college football had ended.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't surprised,'' said Harris, the Jacksonville Jaguars' vice president of player personnel, ''but any time you lose someone as close to you and as important to you as Coach Rob, it hurts. He was as great a person as there's ever been.''</p>
        <p>Harris added: ''He represented what America stands for: developing young people, touching lives, preparing young men for life. He had no equal.''</p>
        <p>Eddie Robinson was more than a coach and more than a legend. As the head football coach at Grambling from 1941 to 1997, Robinson, who died Tuesday at the age of 88, was an enduring symbol. A symbol of the golden age of football at historically black colleges and universities. Mostly, he was a symbol of the virtues associated with being ''Coach'': dedicated and stubborn, firm and dictatorial. Yet always a gentleman.</p>
        <p>My road with Robinson goes back to 1968 when I played my first college football game for Morgan State against his Grambling Tigers in Yankee Stadium. The game was part of Robinson's vision to take black college football out of small, on-campus stadiums and showcase it in larger venues.</p>
        <p>That afternoon in New York, more than 62,000 fans flocked to Yankee Stadium to watch Morgan defeat Grambling, 9-7. This was a world of intercollegiate athletics few outside the circle knew existed, a world of high-stepping bands and hard-hitting football at a time when many of the best black athletes were concentrated in black colleges.</p>
        <p>Morgan won that afternoon, though we would never again come close to beating an Eddie Robinson-coached team.</p>
        <p>Robinson was an every-person's coach. You might not have known him or met him in person, but trust me, if you ever had a coach you cared about, who made you angry, who could make you feel lower than low or higher than high, you knew Eddie Robinson. He could talk trash with the best, tell tall tales with the best and inspire with the best.</p>
        <p>When Harris was a high school senior in Monroe, La., Robinson told him that if he came to Grambling he'd make him a pro.</p>
        <p>''I had thought about going to school up North to be on TV, to have the opportunity to represent my neighborhood,'' Harris once said. ''That was appealing -- the idea of paving the way for other kids. But it got hard to say no to Coach Robinson.</p>
        <p>''Coach came by my house one night. He had been to New York to do a show with Howard Cosell. Grambling had a lot of players in the N.F.L. and Cosell asked Coach Robinson point-blank: 'You've produced so many N.F.L. players. Why can't you produce a quarterback?' And that stuck with him. He got off the plane in Monroe. Came straight to my house. He told me that if I came to Grambling, in four years I'd be ready for the N.F.L. He told me that he knew I could play quarterback. He said, 'Howard Cosell challenged me and I'm here to let you know I think you can do it.' ''</p>
        <p>Harris had an outstanding career at Grambling. As a three-year starter, he led Grambling to a combined 24-5-1 record. But after being drafted by the Buffalo Bills in 1969 in the eighth round, Harris was so disappointed that he contemplated not reporting to camp. Robinson again provided the historical perspective, challenging Harris. He told Harris that he had to report to camp.</p>
        <p>''He thought I could play quarterback in the N.F.L.,'' Harris said. ''He knew I could make it. If I didn't go, the other guys coming along, it would take this much time for the next guy to get a chance and the next guy. But if I go and make it, it may give other guys an opportunity to play, or some young kid growing up will see me play and then they would want to play.''</p>
        <p>Harris reported to camp and went on to become the first African-American to build an extended career as an N.F.L. quarterback.</p>
        <p>Nearly 20 years earlier, Robinson had given Tank Younger a similar pep talk after he was drafted in 1949, becoming the first player to be drafted by the N.F.L. from a historically black college.</p>
        <p>During an interview in his office at Grambling several years ago, Robinson recalled how he had told Younger that his being drafted represented a great opportunity for black college football. ''If you fail,'' he said, ''it's no telling when another player will get an opportunity. They'll say, 'We took the best you had and he failed.' ''</p>
        <p>Robinson was hired as the Grambling head coach in 1941 and retired in 1997. His tenure at Grambling extended from an era when the great black athlete routinely attended a historically black college to an era of integration when black coaches were forced to dig deeper to find diamonds in the rough.</p>
        <p>Robinson's passing on Tuesday marks the end of an era. At the same time, Robinson's legacy should challenge a generation of young coaches at historically black colleges and universities to revitalize their mission, to define a new role and give renewed purpose to the institution that Robinson represented with such vigor.</p>
        <p>He leaves an incredible standard: one school, one football program, thousands of former players who are much better for having had him in their lives.</p>
        <p>There will never be another.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
