<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woods Versus Field, and Nicklaus's 18 Majors</title>
    <meta content="05golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/sports/golf/05golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Augusta National Golf Club</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Singh, Vijay</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1D9163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woods Versus Field, and Nicklaus's 18 Majors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Woods Versus the Field, and Nicklaus’s 18 Majors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was midnight on the eve of the final round of the 1997 Masters, and Tiger Woods could not sleep.</p>
        <p>Woods, playing in his first major championship as a professional, owned a nine-shot lead over Costantino Rocca, but he could not shake the thought of Greg Norman blowing a six-shot lead a year earlier. Woods looked across the room and saw his father, Earl, who was also having trouble finding rest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 71st Masters began today, and Tiger Woods remains the benchmark at Augusta.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was midnight on the eve of the final round of the 1997 Masters, and Tiger Woods could not sleep.</p>
        <p>Woods, playing in his first major championship as a professional, owned a nine-shot lead over Costantino Rocca, but he could not shake the thought of Greg Norman blowing a six-shot lead a year earlier. Woods looked across the room and saw his father, Earl, who was also having trouble finding rest.</p>
        <p>Woods recalled his father's advice. ''He said: 'You know what? Just go to sleep. You know it's going to be the most important round of your life, but you can handle it. Just go out there and do what you do. Just get in your own little world and go out there and just thrash 'em.' ''</p>
        <p>On the eve of the 71st Masters, Woods has not stopped. There are reminders of his dominance all across the golf world, but his footsteps are largest here.</p>
        <p>In the Augusta National pro shop, just around the corner from the caddie shack, DVD copies of Woods's first victory at Augusta are displayed in short stacks in the middle of the room.</p>
        <p>In the Augusta National media center, directly across from the first fairway, television highlights of Woods's feats play on an endless loop.</p>
        <p>The Golf Channel has spent the week interspersing its Masters coverage with memories of Woods -- drives skirting tree tops, chip shots dancing on greens, fists pumping in the afternoon.</p>
        <p>''If I have a great rest of my career,'' Phil Mickelson said Tuesday, ''and I go out and win 20 more tournaments and 7 more majors to get to 50 wins and 10 majors, which would be an awesome career, I still won't get to where he's at today. So I don't try to compare myself against him. What I like to do is to try to win as many tournaments and as many majors that I can. And with him in the field, it just gives it more credibility, whatever it is I am able to accomplish.''</p>
        <p>Woods is chasing his third consecutive major title, fifth green jacket and 13th major victory over all. When he steps onto the first tee at 1:52 p.m. Eastern on Thursday, with Paul Casey of England and Aaron Baddeley of Australia, he will be at the nexus of the Masters story line whether he shoots 64 or 74.</p>
        <p>Mickelson is the defending champion, and Vijay Singh has as many victories as Woods this season (2), but only Woods is competing against 96 other players and the specter of Jack Nicklaus's 18 professional majors.</p>
        <p>''Tiger is the benchmark, and that's no disrespect to anyone else,'' said David Leadbetter, the swing instructor with six players in the field. ''It's more of a story when he doesn't win. It's like one big match play tournament -- Tiger against the field.''</p>
        <p>Ernie Els added: ''A lot of other guys have had talent, breakthrough talent, but never really showed it the way Tiger has. He's really come through more than I think a lot of people have expected. But he's showed a lot of dedication through the last 10 years.''</p>
        <p>Woods's commitment at the Masters has manifested itself in many ways. When he had to wake up at dusk to complete a rain-delayed round at the 2002 Masters, which he eventually won, he woke up even earlier -- around 4 a.m. -- to get in a run.</p>
        <p>On the PGA Tour, his good friend Charles Howell III has borrowed some of his workout tips. On the L.P.G.A. Tour, his good friend Annika Sorenstam has borrowed one of his clubs.</p>
        <p>Golfers around the world have tried to copy Woods, trying to duplicate the physical and mental state he brings to a golf tournament.</p>
        <p>''I honestly don't think about it when I'm playing,'' Geoff Ogilvy said. ''It's just that when you sit down after the week and, 'Wow, he won another one.' It's good for us because it makes us try to get better. It's kind of fun playing now. If he's not already, he's getting pretty close to being the best of all time. He's just a better player. I just have to figure out how he does it and do something.''</p>
        <p>Rocco Mediate, who is not in the field, said that Woods had sacrificed much to become the world's best golfer. He added that many players might not be willing to give up the sleep and put in the hours on the range and in the gym that Woods does.</p>
        <p>But Woods is not all work. On Tuesday night, he attended the annual Masters champions' dinner, where Mickelson served brisket, barbecue ribs, fried chicken, smoked sausage and vanilla ice cream to the winners of green jackets.</p>
        <p>''It's fun to hear the stories,'' Woods said. ''But when it's time to play, you put all of that aside and go get the job done.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
