<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Infiniti Concept That's Soon to Be Reality</title>
    <meta content="NUGGET--Infiniti--EX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838226"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0DB173FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="267" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Infiniti Concept That's Soon to Be Reality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK KURCZEWSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: Infiniti EX Concept design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? Ignore the Concept part of the Infiniti EX's name. Minus a few show-car touches like a liquid-crystal glass roof that varies from clear to frosted this is the Infiniti EX35 crossover that will go on sale later this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Introduced on Wednesday: Infiniti EX Concept design study</p>
        <p>Is it real? Ignore the Concept part of the Infiniti EX's name. Minus a few show-car touches like a liquid-crystal glass roof that varies from clear to frosted this is the Infiniti EX35 crossover that will go on sale later this year.</p>
        <p>What's the point? Infiniti wants to slot a car-based crossover below its own FX35 and FX45 utility vehicles. The EX Concept, and the forthcoming EX35, will be sized and priced to do just that.</p>
        <p>What they said: In perhaps the biggest bit of non-news at the New York auto show, Mark Igo, vice president and general manager of Infiniti, admitted that the EX Concept is "the foundation for a new luxury crossover, the EX35."</p>
        <p>What they didn't say: The EX Concept has some clever new technology, including parking assist and lane departure warning systems, that use cameras to eliminate blind spots or warn the driver when the car is shifting lanes. Of the liquid-crystal glass roof, Infiniti would only say that it "offers a hint of future tech."</p>
        <p>What makes it tick? The EX Concept is motivated by a V-6 engine driving all four wheels.</p>
        <p>How much, how soon? Infiniti didn't commit to a price, but surely it will fall below the $37,000 base price of the larger FX35. The EX35 will arrive late in 2007.</p>
        <p>How's it look? As yet another in a growing line of luxury crossover vehicles, the Infiniti EX Concept deserves special mention for its elegant design. Infiniti says it's coupelike. No way but it's still a good looking machine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
