<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Wal-Mart, Lessons in Self-Help; A New Program to Offer White-Collar Perks To Chain's Workers</title>
    <meta content="05improve" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/business/05improve.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbaro, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Fitness and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEFDA163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1353" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Wal-Mart, Lessons in Self-Help; A New Program to Offer White-Collar Perks To Chain's Workers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Wal-Mart, Lessons in Self-Help</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BARBARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barbaro, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wal-Mart Stores in last year has quietly introduced ambitious program in US--in equal parts self-help class, corporate retreat and tent revival--that tries to turn its 1.3 million workers into model for its 200 million customers on issues ranging from personal health to environment; program, to be announced, tests assumption, if not conventional wisdom, that environmentalism and fitness are luxuries of well-off, inaccessible to vast number of nation's working class because of hectic schedules, stretched budgets and bad habits; it thrusts Wal-Mart far deeper into workers' personal lives than company has ever reached before; specific programs detailed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Employees at a Wal-Mart near Saratoga, Fla., have started an aerobics class twice a week in their break room. Wal-Mart workers in Denver are reimbursed for taking public transportation to and from work. And the staff at a Sam's Club in Indianapolis now takes a daily walk around the perimeter of the store.</p>
        <p>The chain that promises ''always low prices'' seems to be adding the mantra of nonstop self-improvement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wal-Mart has quietly introduced an ambitious self-help project to make its workers more productive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Employees at a Wal-Mart near Saratoga, Fla., have started an aerobics class twice a week in their break room. Wal-Mart workers in Denver are reimbursed for taking public transportation to and from work. And the staff at a Sam's Club in Indianapolis now takes a daily walk around the perimeter of the store.</p>
        <p>The chain that promises ''always low prices'' seems to be adding the mantra of nonstop self-improvement.</p>
        <p>In the last year, Wal-Mart has quietly introduced an ambitious program in the United States -- in equal parts self-help class, corporate retreat and tent revival -- that tries to turn its 1.3 million workers into a model for its 200 million customers on issues ranging from personal health to the environment.</p>
        <p>The program, to be announced today, tests the assumption, if not conventional wisdom, that environmentalism and fitness are luxuries of the well-off, inaccessible to a vast number of the nation's working class because of hectic schedules, stretched budgets and bad habits.</p>
        <p>At the same time, it thrusts Wal-Mart, the nation's largest employer, far deeper into workers' personal lives than the company -- and perhaps any retailer -- has ever reached before.</p>
        <p>In extensive workshops held nationwide, the company is teaching its employees the benefits of carpooling to work with three colleagues (for a savings of $400 a year on gas), quitting cigarette smoking ($1,500 a year) and turning off a television ($40 a year in electricity, plus more time to spend with family).</p>
        <p>The program, called the personal sustainability project, is voluntary, but it is proving popular, with roughly 50 percent of employees in a dozen states signing up so far. The company may eventually extend the program to its workers around the world.</p>
        <p>For Wal-Mart, the payoff could be significant: if it succeeds, the initiative could improve employee morale, and therefore productivity; reduce health care spending on a work force with higher rates of heart disease and diabetes than the general public; and improve Wal-Mart's reputation with the image-conscious consumers it is courting with costlier merchandise.</p>
        <p>Over the next two years, Wal-Mart will ask all employees to adopt a pledge to improve their bodies, their families or their planet. And behind that seemingly New Age aspiration is an estimated $30 million commitment, making the program one of the most expensive of its kind.</p>
        <p>White-collar companies, like I.B.M. and Microsoft, have long sponsored fitness and lifestyle improvement programs, which are considered a simple perk by their largely middle-class employees. But companies with workers who are more likely to live paycheck to paycheck have generally scoffed at the cost, which makes Wal-Mart's investment so striking.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart, which is known for its rigid rules, is also giving the program an unusually democratic structure. The company is training -- and paying -- hundreds of employees to recruit their colleagues, holding off-site retreats for participants (a rarity for hourly workers) and tracking workers' progress in written reports that measure participation rates.</p>
        <p>During a workshop in Houston several weeks ago, Wal-Mart managers and hourly workers spent five hours at the zoo learning about environmental sustainability, a lesson that included tips on reducing carbon emissions and consuming healthier, more environmentally friendly food. By the end of the day, each employee had written down a pledge -- or, in the program's parlance, a personal sustainability practice.</p>
        <p>''I want to start recycling around my home,'' said Curtis Tipton, a manager.</p>
        <p>''Improve my physical health with food and exercise,'' said Ferne Oyster, who works in a grocery department.</p>
        <p>''Spend more quality time with my family,'' said Miriam Crosby, who runs a Wal-Mart in the area.</p>
        <p>This is a far cry from the mandatory, at times robotic Wal-Mart cheer (''Give me a 'W,' give me an 'A,' '' and so on) uttered every morning at the chain's 4,000 United States stores -- and that, organizers say, is the point.</p>
        <p>To succeed, the program must be personal, with each of Wal-Mart's employees tailoring it to his or her own life. Wal-Mart has left the initiative purposely vague, the better to encourage workers to decide how to improve themselves.</p>
        <p>The challenges for Wal-Mart are significant. Its workers earn, on average, less than $20,000 a year, which means that fitness and ecology are, by necessity, relatively low priorities. Wal-Mart attracts a transient work force, with frequent turnover making it difficult to train people over time. And a disproportionate number of its employees suffer from chronic diseases that stem in part from poor eating habits.</p>
        <p>''We need a Subway in there instead of a McDonald's,'' said Cheryl Victorian, a 39-year-old package receiver at a Wal-Mart near Houston who, pressed for time, frequently eats breakfast and lunch at the McDonald's in her store. Now 248 pounds, she said her goal is to get down to 195.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Wal-Mart's chief executive, H. Lee Scott Jr., said he was in talks with McDonald's about granting employees discounts on healthy menu items, like salads.</p>
        <p>About half of the Wal-Mart employees introduced to the personal sustainability project have agreed to participate, a figure much higher than the company had expected. Among the pledges the workers have made are to stop eating fast food, switch to nontoxic cleaning supplies, prepare two organic meals a week and stretch five mornings a week.</p>
        <p>Kim Nicholson, a 40-year-old employee at Sam's Club in Indianapolis, has lost 35 pounds since the program began and has organized a regular walk around her store (inside and outside).</p>
        <p>''The name of the game in retail is that we are juggling odd hours, raising families and the stress of the job,'' Ms. Nicholson said. ''It contributes to a lot of bad habits.'' She estimates, for example, that 40 out of the 110 employees at her store smoke cigarettes.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Nicholson, herself a smoker who weighs just under 200 pounds, said the personal sustainability project ''binds us all in a common cause.''</p>
        <p>She added, ''When you get a lot of people thinking about their health and the environment, it's powerful.''</p>
        <p>The self-improvement that Wal-Mart is evangelizing can be traced back to its broad environmental sustainability initiative. In the fall of 2005, Mr. Scott, the chief executive, vowed to reduce energy use in Wal-Mart's stores, improve the fuel efficiency of its trucks, minimize its use of packaging and pressure thousands of suppliers to follow its lead.</p>
        <p>But the company has wrestled with how to integrate its workers into the program. A year ago, executives enlisted the help of Adam Werbach, a prominent environmentalist and former president of the Sierra Club, who runs a consulting firm called Act Now Productions.</p>
        <p>At first, Mr. Werbach rebuffed Wal-Mart, assuming the project was a public relations stunt. But Mr. Werbach -- who, in the late 1990s, chastised environmentalists in speeches and essays for failing to reach average Americans -- said he realized that by ignoring Wal-Mart, ''I would be saying no to the one company that spoke to basically every American.''</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart, Mr. Werbach said, has the capacity to become ''the nation's largest environmental group.'' He and the staff of Act Now Productions developed the personal sustainability project with Wal-Mart ''to make environmentalism relevant to a broad audience.''</p>
        <p>Linda Dillman, the executive vice president for benefits and sustainability at Wal-Mart, said that the program harksback to ''what we did much better when we were a smaller company, which was give our associates information and let them solve problems.''</p>
        <p>Leslie Laney, a 33-year-old employee at Sam's Club in Brandon, Fla., decided to solve the trash problem in her store. After the personal sustainability project was introduced, Ms. Laney created a ''zero waste'' break room where workers use mugs instead of Styrofoam cups and set up bins to recycle aluminum cans and plastic bottles.</p>
        <p>Then she recruited co-workers to help clean up a wetland area behind a nearby elementary school, removing a tangle of overgrown vines. Their next plan is to turn the wetland into a classroom, with boardwalks that let students walk around and study the ecosystem.</p>
        <p>''This is not about becoming a tree-hugger,'' Ms. Laney said. ''It's about making one little change. It does not matter how big or small, but just doing one thing that makes a difference.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
