<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Officer Faces Charges Tied To a Shooting</title>
    <meta content="05cop" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/nyregion/05cop.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838115"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E5DB163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Officer Faces Charges Tied To a Shooting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Officer Faces Charges Tied to a Shooting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brick, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A police officer has been indicted on charges of evidence tampering and official misconduct in connection with the shooting of a fellow officer, according to court documents unsealed yesterday.</p>
        <p>The officer who was charged, Jacqueline Melendez Rivera, 37, was accused of covering for her husband, Jose Rivera, 31. Mr. Rivera has been charged with attempted murder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A police officer has been indicted on charges of evidence tampering and official misconduct in connection with the shooting of a fellow officer, according to court documents unsealed yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A police officer has been indicted on charges of evidence tampering and official misconduct in connection with the shooting of a fellow officer, according to court documents unsealed yesterday.</p>
        <p>The officer who was charged, Jacqueline Melendez Rivera, 37, was accused of covering for her husband, Jose Rivera, 31. Mr. Rivera has been charged with attempted murder.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors say that around 4 a.m. on Feb. 10, Mr. Rivera drove alongside a car carrying four undercover officers near Prospect Place and Sixth Avenue in Park Slope, Brooklyn, and yelled at and then shot at the officers.</p>
        <p>The officer who was driving, Andrew Suarez, was struck in the upper arm. His partners returned fire, then drove him to New York Methodist Hospital. He was released a few days later.</p>
        <p>The police found the gunman's car, a white Acura with bullet holes, more than a mile away, with Officer Rivera at the wheel. Prosecutors say Officer Rivera told detectives that she was moving the car because her husband had parked it illegally. The Riveras and their children live less than two blocks from the site of the shooting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rivera has been on parole since 2002 for an assault conviction connected to a shooting in 1996. He was arrested the day of Officer Suarez's shooting at the couple's home. He was arraigned yesterday in State Supreme Court in Brooklyn on charges of attempted murder and assault. Mr. Rivera pleaded not guilty and was ordered held without bail. His lawyer, Ezra C. Levy, did not return a call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Investigators questioned Officer Rivera, but law enforcement officials said they did not believe that she had been in the car during the shooting. She has been suspended from duty.</p>
        <p>Officer Rivera, a 13-year member of the Police Department and a military veteran, is seven months pregnant with her fourth child. She has said publicly that she had been unaware that her husband owned a gun and that an officer had been shot.</p>
        <p>The day of the shooting, Officer Rivera was arrested on charges of tampering with evidence, obstructing governmental administration and hindering prosecution. She was arraigned in Criminal Court and released on $50,000 bond.</p>
        <p>Officer Rivera testified before the grand jury weighing her case, said her lawyer, Jay H. Schwitzman. The grand jury declined to indict on charges of obstructing governmental administration or hindering prosecution.</p>
        <p>''She didn't know anybody was shot; she didn't know anybody was injured,'' Mr. Schwitzman said in a telephone interview. ''And as soon as she became aware of that, her cooperation was plentiful.''</p>
        <p>The most serious charge in the indictment, tampering with physical evidence, relates to the car, a law enforcement official said. That charge is a low-level felony, carrying a maximum penalty of four years in prison.</p>
        <p>Officer Rivera remains free on $50,000 bond. A date for her Supreme Court arraignment has not been set, a law enforcement official said.</p>
        <p>''She's staying strong,'' Mr. Schwitzman said, ''and I'm very glad that the grand jury listened to her.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
