<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>These Books, Possessed and Dangerous, Are for the Birds and Their Friends</title>
    <meta content="05game" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/technology/05game.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838116"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hand (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Square Enix</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vicious Cycle Software</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herold, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DB163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1197" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>These Books, Possessed and Dangerous, Are for the Birds and Their Friends</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">These Books, Possessed and Dangerous, Are for the Birds and Their Friends</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES HEROLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herold, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thes4</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Books are dangerous. At least that could be the moral of Final Fantasy Fables: Chocobo Tales, a quirky little game developed by h.a.n.d. for the Nintendo DS in which a possessed book tries to destroy the world.</p>
        <p>Tales starts with a bunch of young animals and children enjoying story time with an ancient, mysterious book. When read, the book develops a mouth, an eye and a nasty temper and immediately swallows up almost everyone in the neighborhood. Only a young chocobo chick and a couple of his friends are left behind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Books are dangerous. At least that could be the moral of Final Fantasy Fables: Chocobo Tales, a game in which a possessed book tries to destroy the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Books are dangerous. At least that could be the moral of Final Fantasy Fables: Chocobo Tales, a quirky little game developed by h.a.n.d. for the Nintendo DS in which a possessed book tries to destroy the world.</p>
        <p>Tales starts with a bunch of young animals and children enjoying story time with an ancient, mysterious book. When read, the book develops a mouth, an eye and a nasty temper and immediately swallows up almost everyone in the neighborhood. Only a young chocobo chick and a couple of his friends are left behind.</p>
        <p>The chocobo is a fictional large flightless bird common to the Final Fantasy game series. It is not a character in these games, just a beast of burden, so Tales is the equivalent of a movie about a talking baby camel from the people who made ''Lawrence of Arabia.''</p>
        <p>The chocobo discovers his friends have all been turned into playing cards who can be freed only if the chick enters one of the storybooks strewn about the neighborhood. Approach a book and the chocobo is sucked into the story. Each book contains a game that when won will free a friend or open up a blocked path.</p>
        <p>The story inside each book is a mishmash of traditional fairy tales like Mini Red Riding Hood and her experience with a glass slipper. Games are based on a book's story; for example, when a young boy finds a magic bean that grows into a beanstalk, the player must help him climb to the top by drawing leaves on the DS touch screen for him to bounce on.</p>
        <p>Each game has various difficulty settings, and winning on each setting will result in a freed friend, a useful item or a different story ending. Each story has two or three sometimes contradictory endings for the player to unlock. These endings affect the chick's world. For example, a story that ends with something being frozen will create an ice bridge across a lake that the chick needs to cross.</p>
        <p>Games are nicely varied. In one you must drag your chocobo through a pond and then onto flames that when doused reveal coins. In another, you must wend your way through an electrified maze. While some DS games feel a little gimmicky, Tales' minigames are so natural that I didn't even think about the fact that they could be played only on a touch screen.</p>
        <p>Besides the storybook minigames, Tales offers one more elaborate game used to battle the evil book's hypnotized minions. This is a card game in which opponents use playing cards with various attack and defense properties against one another.</p>
        <p>For each turn you must choose a card from three randomly dealt from a deck. Some cards are more powerful but require colored crystals generated during battle; if you play a card for which you don't have enough crystals, it won't do anything, so on some turns you might have a choice of three useless cards.</p>
        <p>While fun, the battles feel more like gambling than strategy, as you have to play cards too fast to really think about what you are doing, and your enemy's card often nullify your own. As in blackjack, there are decisions to be made, but luck is a huge component.</p>
        <p>There is some strategy involved in choosing your 15-card battle deck from the dozens of cards collected in your adventures. Unfortunately, Tales has a ridiculously cumbersome system in which you can't easily swap one card for another or compare two cards; even finding a particular card in your collection requires a tedious search. The designers would find it challenging to come up with a worse system.</p>
        <p>This flaw is surprising in a game that is otherwise beautifully designed, managing to turn a bunch of unrelated minigames into a cohesive whole and to use stories to make playing these games seem vital.</p>
        <p>Puzzle Quest, a puzzle/role published by D3Publisher, also uses story to elevate simple game play. But it builds its entire epic structure on the back of a single minigame.</p>
        <p>Puzzle Quest is built around a pattern-matching game, similar to Bejeweled, in which the player has to match three or more items in a grid by swapping two adjacent items. The game style is typical of so-called casual games like Tetris and Solitaire that are small and simple and can be played for 15 or 20 minutes when you're bored (although people will sometimes uncasually play them for hours).</p>
        <p>At first glance Puzzle Quest appears to be just another example of a casual game that throws in a little story to spice things up, like Got Game Entertainment's Mahjongg Artifacts, which has a story mode about a mah-jongg-playing archaeologist that in no way changes the fact that you are simply playing mah-jongg.</p>
        <p>But Puzzle Quest is something quite different; a turn-based role-playing game that has adapted a casual game style for its combat system.</p>
        <p>The player takes on the role of a knight investigating reports of undead creatures' attacking people in the kingdom. As he travels from town to town on a map of the territory, investigating these strange attacks, he must stop rampaging monsters and retrieve lost treasure.</p>
        <p>Each time the knight encounters a creature, like an orc or a skeleton, the map is replaced by an 8-by-8 grid filled with colorful icons. You and your opponent take turns matching these icons, which have different effects. Matching skulls damages your adversary, while matching gold coins gives the player money for upgrades. Matching colored disks builds up power reserves used to launch various spells to destroy icons or increase your attack power, with different colored reserves needed for different spells.</p>
        <p>Much of the game involves trying to build up the appropriate color reserves for your spells, although at times it is more important to pre-emptively match a color your enemy needs for a powerful attack spell.</p>
        <p>The game does an admirable job of adding some strategic depth and complexity to the casual game model without losing its pick-up-and-play nature.</p>
        <p>Puzzle Quest has all the trappings of a role-playing game. You can earn points to make your character more powerful, or use gold to buy weapons and acquire traveling companions that help you fight. You can capture monsters through one variation on the main game and learn their spells through a different variation.</p>
        <p>The game also shoots for an epic role-playing story, but the result is mind-numbingly dull. There is an occasional hint of mystery or an ethical choice to be made, but bland dialogue and personality-free characters tempt the player to press the skip button every time a conversation commences.</p>
        <p>So while the moral of Chocobo Tales could be that books are powerful and dangerous, the lesson of PuzzleQuest might be, if you're looking for a good story, read a book.</p>
        <p>FINAL FANTASY FABLES: CHOCOBO TALES  Developed by h.a.n.d. and published by Square Enix for Nintendo DS; for all ages; $29.99.</p>
        <p>PUZZLE QUEST: CHALLENGE OF THE WARLORDS  Developed by Vicious Cycle Software (for PlayStation Portable), 1st Playable Productions (for Nintendo DS) and Infinite Interactive (for both) and published by D3Publisher of America; for ages 10 and up; $29.99.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
