<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford Chief Sticking to His Road Map for Turnaround</title>
    <meta content="05ford" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/automobiles/05ford.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070406T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York International Auto Show</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maynard, Micheline</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mulally, Alan R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mulally, Alan R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EFDA163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford Chief Sticking to His Road Map for Turnaround</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ford Chief Sticking to His Road Map for Turnaround</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELINE MAYNARD; Nick Bunkley contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maynard, Micheline</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co's chief executive Alan R Mulally dismisses speculation by some analysts and industry executives that Ford would require third round of cuts on top of two already announced, address at New York International Auto Show; strategy calls for Ford to close 14 factories and to eliminate as many as 44,000 hourly and salaried jobs, or about third of its work force by 2008; Ford does not expect to make money in North America for two more years; Mulally introduces crossover vehicle called Flex; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company's sales continue to fall and no one is predicting a North American profit before 2009. But the chief executive insisted yesterday that he saw no need for deeper cuts beyond those slated in its recovery plan.</p>
        <p>Speaking at the New York International Auto Show as Ford introduced a crossover vehicle called the Flex, Alan R. Mulally dismissed speculation by some analysts and industry executives that Ford would require a third round of cuts on top of the two already announced as part of the program it calls the Way Forward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ford’s chief executive insisted that he saw no need for deeper cuts beyond those scheduled in the company’s recovery plan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company's sales continue to fall and no one is predicting a North American profit before 2009. But the chief executive insisted yesterday that he saw no need for deeper cuts beyond those slated in its recovery plan.</p>
        <p>Speaking at the New York International Auto Show as Ford introduced a crossover vehicle called the Flex, Alan R. Mulally dismissed speculation by some analysts and industry executives that Ford would require a third round of cuts on top of the two already announced as part of the program it calls the Way Forward.</p>
        <p>That strategy calls for Ford to close 14 factories and to eliminate as many as 44,000 hourly and salaried jobs -- or about a third of its work force by 2008. Ford, which lost $12.7 billion in 2006 including charges for its revamping, does not expect to earn money in North America for two more years.</p>
        <p>The plan, announced in January 2006, was expanded and speeded up in September.</p>
        <p>''With everything we know, we don't see any changes to the plan,'' Mr. Mulally said in a brief interview. ''This is the transformation. It's all in the plan to get there by 2009.''</p>
        <p>Even so, Mr. Mulally acknowledged that Ford had too many dealers, adding, ''When you have overcapacity, you need to consolidate to match capacity to demand.''</p>
        <p>There are about 4,600 Ford and Lincoln-Mercury dealers in the United States. Ford's next-closest competitor, the Toyota Motor Corporation, has 1,300 Toyota and Lexus dealers in the United States.</p>
        <p>Although Ford had said it expected its sales and market share to drop over the next two years, company officials acknowledged that sales fell faster in January and February than they had forecast. But yesterday, Mark Fields, the president of Ford's operations for the Americas, said Ford had hit its targets for unit sales, revenue from sales and other measurements in March, the first time this year that it has met its goals.</p>
        <p>For the first quarter, Ford's sales in the United States were down 13.2 percent from the first quarter of 2006, while its market share fell 2.3 percentage points, to 16.4 percent. Ford contends that some of the loss is because it is giving up unprofitable sales to rental car companies, which General Motors also is doing.</p>
        <p>Even so, sales of some of Ford's most popular vehicles have fallen this year, on top of steep declines in 2006. Sales of its Explorer sport utility are down 25.7 percent in the quarter compared with 2006, while the F-series pickup is down 14.1 percent.</p>
        <p>Ford officials say that part of the drop in F-series sales stems from a cut in production, leaving fewer choices at dealerships than truck buyers like to see when shopping.</p>
        <p>Further, they say Ford is seeing good performances from some of its newer models, like the Edge, a crossover vehicle introduced in December, and the Fusion sedan, introduced in October 2005.</p>
        <p>In 2008, those vehicles will be joined in showrooms by the boxy Flex, which bears a strong resemblance to two other models already on the road: the Scion xB, a small van sold by Toyota, and the cube-like Honda Element.</p>
        <p>In fact, the chocolate brown Flex on display at the Javits Convention Center yesterday had a white roof like that on a certain Toyota, the FJ Cruiser.</p>
        <p>Ford plans to put the Flex on sale in the summer of 2008 as a 2009 model. With a long hood and rectangular body, the Flex is ''a modern station wagon,'' said Ken Gross, a veteran automotive journalist.</p>
        <p>''Eighteen to 30-year-olds love this kind of stuff,'' Keith Crain, the publisher of Automotive News, said of the Flex's angular appearance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fields declared that the vehicle would make Ford ''the defining crossover company,'' just as it led the sport utility vehicle market in the 1990s, with the Explorer, Expedition and others. But Ford is late in expanding its offerings in the crossover market, which was created in 1995 when Toyota introduced the RAV-4.</p>
        <p>''It's not going to happen,'' Ron Pinelli, president of the Autodata Corporation, which tracks industry statistics, said of Mr. Fields's claim. ''Domestic manufacturers have been outclassed by imports'' in the crossover market. ''They did it first, and they did it better,'' Mr. Pinelli said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pinelli said Ford's new models were not selling in large enough numbers to make up for the loss in sales of its trucks and S.U.V.'s. He also said he was puzzled over which buyers might purchase Flex, given its retro appearance. ''Who is it really designed for?'' Mr. Pinelli asked.</p>
        <p>And where they might buy it was also open to question. Ford dealers expect the Flex to be available only in limited quantities, said Howard E. Kuperman, president of Phil's Ford Lincoln Mercury in Port Jervis, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Asked how he thought it would do, Mr. Kuperman replied, ''We car dealers can sell anything.''</p>
        <p>How many Ford dealers will be around by the time Flex reaches showrooms is not clear.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fields and Mr. Mulally said Ford was working to persuade dealers in some metropolitan areas to combine their dealerships. State franchise laws prevent carmakers from unilaterally closing dealerships, and financial advisers to Ford have estimated that it would cost the company several billion dollars to buy out hundreds of dealers.</p>
        <p>Said Mr. Mulally, ''There isn't enough money in the world to do something like that.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 6, 2007, Friday  An article in Business Day yesterday about the turnaround effort at the Ford Motor Company misstated the number and timing of plant closings under its restructuring plan. Ford will close 16 plants, not 14. And nine of those plants, not all 16, will close by 2008. The rest will close by 2012.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 6, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about the turnaround effort at the Ford Motor Company misstated the number and timing of plant closings under its restructuring plan. Ford will close 16 plants, not 14. And nine of those plants, not all 16, will close by 2008. The rest will close by 2012.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
