<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rethinking the Pots on an Old, Cracked Terrace</title>
    <meta content="05garden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/garden/05garden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E4DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rethinking the Pots on an Old, Cracked Terrace</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rethinking the Pots on an Old, Cracked Terrace</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raver, Anne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE was a little brown wren singing on the stone wall as I puttered around my motley collection of pots last weekend. It felt good to be dumping the old soil into the wheelbarrow and rinsing the pots with my garden hose.</p>
        <p>My tender plants -- elephant ears, aeoniums, echeverias, a bay and rosemary now in full bloom -- had sunned themselves all winter in an enclosed, south-facing porch. And as the day reached into the 60s, I had to suppress the urge to bring them all outside. Nighttime temperatures can still drop into the 30s in Maryland, which is way too cold for a tropical plant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Matching a plant’s color, shape and texture comes into play when choosing a container.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE was a little brown wren singing on the stone wall as I puttered around my motley collection of pots last weekend. It felt good to be dumping the old soil into the wheelbarrow and rinsing the pots with my garden hose.</p>
        <p>My tender plants -- elephant ears, aeoniums, echeverias, a bay and rosemary now in full bloom -- had sunned themselves all winter in an enclosed, south-facing porch. And as the day reached into the 60s, I had to suppress the urge to bring them all outside. Nighttime temperatures can still drop into the 30s in Maryland, which is way too cold for a tropical plant.</p>
        <p>My oxalis and begonias are all in bloom at the windows of my bedroom. When it is warm enough, I move them to a place I call the cow terrace, an old concrete slab about 20 feet wide that fans out from the stable doors in the old barnyard. The cows used to stand there, mooing, to be let into their stalls for milking.</p>
        <p>Those days are long gone. Blackberry vines and mulleins now grow through the cracks in the concrete. And I have set pots of herbs and succulents around the old metal chairs that I collected over the years at yard sales up and down the East Coast.</p>
        <p>I love this ruined terrace. Some friends advise me to jackhammer it out and plant a swath of soft grass right up to the stable doors. Others picture an elegant terrace, slightly raised, of brick or stone, laid over sand. But that would erase the history of the place.</p>
        <p>There is memory in such places, as J. B. Jackson, the cultural geographer, writes so eloquently in ''The Necessity for Ruins, and Other Topics.'' In its ad hoc, dilapidated way, this piece of concrete holds the story of my life: from my childhood, petting the old workhorse who once stood in this barnyard, to the chairs and the pots that I continue to collect in my perambulations as a gardener.</p>
        <p>And so, I have lived with this place pretty much the way it is, eating the blackberries when they ripen in July and growing big pots of basil and nasturtiums near the metal stairs that lead to my sunny loft in the old barn. Every year I add a few more pots.</p>
        <p>But this spring I have shifted my thoughts to Design, with a capital D, because of a new book, ''Pots in the Garden,'' by Ray Rogers, with photographs by Richard Hartlage, published in February by Timber Press.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogers is the plant geek -- he calls himself a plant missionary -- who walks off with all the blue ribbons from the Philadelphia Flower Show every year (315 over the past 18 years).</p>
        <p>I've actually watched this man go over one of his champion rex begonias with a pair of fingernail scissors. He learns everything there is to know about a plant, and has a good eye for matching plant to pot: how a rounded blue-green pot of fiery orange tulips, for instance, not only emphasizes the tulips' fat green leaves but also the shape of their bowl-like flowers. Or how a line of long toms -- 10-inch-tall narrow pots made for growing individual plants -- sets off the form and color of lewisias, delicate alpines that bloom in pure colors of yellow, white and pink.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogers has a lot to say about color, line, form and texture in a garden full of pots. So does Mr. Hartlage, whose gorgeous color pictures illustrate Mr. Rogers's every point. (And one of Mr. Hartlage's own creations, a giant hanging ball of seven different coleuses in contrasting colors and textures, exploded the boundaries of my conservative country mind.)</p>
        <p>And yet plenty of images in the book, which could have sprung from my own cracked terrace, were transformed by an artist's eye. One picture in particular teased my memory: handmade concrete troughs full of alpines -- some cascading, some cushiony green mounds, others fernlike or covered with yellow or purple blooms -- clustered in rows on square paving stones. It could have been some Roman ruins.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogers reminded me, as we talked on the phone, that it was the terrace garden built in the foundation of an old greenhouse once used for growing cut flowers at Wave Hill, a 19th-century estate turned public garden in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Another picture struck a deep chord: a spiky agave with creamy yellow leaves edged in dark green (Agave americana Mediopicta) set against a perfectly plain wall on a paved stone terrace. ''That picture is all about lines,'' Mr. Rogers said. It was taken at Chanticleer, another former estate now open to the public, in Wayne, Pa., west of Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Other images expressed the appeal of emptiness, as Mr. Rogers puts it: pots so beautiful they can stand alone, unplanted, as sculptures in the garden. Or how about an Indonesian bronze urn, filled to the brim with water, reflecting deep green ivy (another one of Mr. Hartlage's designs, for a garden in Nutley, N.J.).</p>
        <p>''That's a little bit of garden magic,'' Mr. Rogers said. ''It would have been easy to have left it empty, but filling it up to the brim was brilliant.''</p>
        <p>For those who love hot colors, Mr. Rogers encourages playing with the opposites on the color wheel: a wide pot of bright yellow narcissus, for instance, set between a pot of purple violas and a purplish-black cordyline, whose swordlike leaves emphasize the contrast.</p>
        <p>Above all, Mr. Rogers said, don't be afraid to experiment: ''Dive in headfirst. No guts, no glory.''</p>
        <p>So there I sat last weekend, in my creaky yard-sale chair, trying to match the ideals of those photos with my reality: a couple of chipped Guy Wolff pots; an antique milk crock that cracked in the February freeze; and a few purple and lime green pots with rolled edges that I once fell for at Simple Pleasures, a dangerously good shop in Providence, R.I.</p>
        <p>I'm fond of good junk, too: old ham boilers, an antique blue-and-yellow All soap bucket, a watering can made from a No. 10 tin can once filled with La Costeña jalapeños. Each one carries a memory apart from the salvias or the echeverias that occupied them at one point or another.</p>
        <p>I don't really want a picture-perfect garden on my old cow terrace. But this book has gotten under my skin. I'm going to jackhammer a hole in the concrete by an old post that could be perfect for a climbing rose just given to me by a friend. I'm going to take a pickax to some of the cracks, add a bit of sandy soil, and plant creeping thyme and sedums that can take the heat. And I'm going to add a few plants to my collection, like that Agave americana Mediopicta, which, with the right pot, will be a sculpture in itself.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
