<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cupid's Arrows and Southern Hip-Hop Beats</title>
    <meta content="05ball" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/arts/dance/05ball.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Joyce Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Adam, Julia</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Davis, Thaddeus</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cupid's Arrows and Southern Hip-Hop Beats</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cupid’s Arrows and Southern Hip-Hop Beats</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GIA KOURLAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kourlas, Gia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ballet Memphis is something of a little engine that could, to perhaps sum up the imaginative grit of Dorothy Gunther Pugh, who has presided over the group with equal dashes of elegance and temerity for 20 years. On Tuesday night both ingredients were on display in a program of New York premieres at her company's Joyce Theater debut.</p>
        <p>The first, by Trey McIntyre, is exceptional. When he's on his mark, Mr. McIntyre, the troupe's resident choreographer, embodies the breezy nature of a dreamer, albeit with his feet planted firmly on the ground. His joyful ''Naughty Boy!'' (2004), set to Mozart's Violin Concerto in G, focuses on the romantic antics of four couples and a Cupid, in the form of an especially enchanting Dawn Fay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Elegance and temerity were on display in a program of New York premieres at this company’s Joyce Theater debut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ballet Memphis is something of a little engine that could, to perhaps sum up the imaginative grit of Dorothy Gunther Pugh, who has presided over the group with equal dashes of elegance and temerity for 20 years. On Tuesday night both ingredients were on display in a program of New York premieres at her company's Joyce Theater debut.</p>
        <p>The first, by Trey McIntyre, is exceptional. When he's on his mark, Mr. McIntyre, the troupe's resident choreographer, embodies the breezy nature of a dreamer, albeit with his feet planted firmly on the ground. His joyful ''Naughty Boy!'' (2004), set to Mozart's Violin Concerto in G, focuses on the romantic antics of four couples and a Cupid, in the form of an especially enchanting Dawn Fay.</p>
        <p>''The Naughty Boy!'' begins with a curtain drawn across two-thirds of the stage and Cupid wearing a whimsical orange coonskin hat and a fitted plaid jacket. (Costume design is credited to Kirsty Munn and Liz Prince.) Suddenly colorful paper streamers fly through the air, paving the way for Ms. Fay to flee the stage, and she does, darting mischievously with a teasing smile.</p>
        <p>Mr. McIntyre can move groups through space with ease, as he does in ''The Naughty Boy!'' But in the second movement, when the curtain is drawn back to reveal the full stage and the work's main couple, Crystal Brothers and Travis Bradley, he offers even more in intricate partnering.</p>
        <p>Lifts, which show off Ms. Brothers's long feet and switchblade legs, are somehow both graceful and precarious; the dancers, for all their daring and attack, never surrender plasticity.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately Mr. McIntyre's work was the exception. In Julia Adam's ''Curtain of Green,'' to music by Philip Glass, steps are largely replaced by a bland accumulation of gestures. Based a story by Eudora Welty, the trio, for Ms. Fay, Steven McMahon and Kendall G. Britt Jr., is obscured by melodrama.</p>
        <p>The program's final work, Thaddeus Davis's ''Mercurial Balance,'' is a strange one. Created as a reflection of Memphis's hip-hop scene, the dance is anchored by its energetic compilation of music and the hokey ramblings of the spoken-word poets J'malo Torriel and Ed Brittenum of Brotha's Keepa. As a piece of dance-theater exploring love from male and female perspectives, it has problems in both the monotony of the choreography and the earnestness of the text.</p>
        <p>When the poets proclaim, ''Jekyll and Hyde vying for attention,'' they could be referring to the artistic disparity between ''The Naughty Boy!'' and ''Mercurial Balance.'' A section for one woman and two men displays little more than leg straddles in every conceivable direction. But the work gradually picks up steam, mainly thanks to an all-female section led by the inimitable Ms. Brothers, marvelously precise and committed to the material.</p>
        <p>It's not her fault she can't master hip-hop. She's way too much of a ballerina.</p>
        <p>Ballet Memphis performs through Sunday at the Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 242-0800 or joyce.org.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
