<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Sudden Dismissal, Julien Gives His Side</title>
    <meta content="05nhl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/sports/hockey/05nhl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6DA163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Sudden Dismissal, Julien Gives His Side</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Sudden Dismissal, Julien Speaks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Apparently, the Devils players were not the only ones stunned Monday when General Manager Lou Lamoriello fired Coach Claude Julien and then took over with the team in first place in the Atlantic Division and three games left in the regular season.</p>
        <p>Julien apparently never sensed the move coming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils players were not the only ones stunned Monday when General Manager Lou Lamoriello fired Coach Claude Julien and then took the team over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Apparently, the Devils players were not the only ones stunned Monday when General Manager Lou Lamoriello fired Coach Claude Julien and then took over with the team in first place in the Atlantic Division and three games left in the regular season.</p>
        <p>Julien apparently never sensed the move coming.</p>
        <p>''You don't ever come into work expecting to lose your job,'' Julien said in a conference call Wednesday after two days of silence.</p>
        <p>Instead, Lamoriello, who coached the Devils to a shootout victory Tuesday against Ottawa, will coach in the playoffs. Less than 14 months after he was fired as the coach of the Montreal Canadiens and less than 10 months after Lamoriello hired him, Julien, 46, is mulling his future, again. He remains with the organization, for now.</p>
        <p>''Last year was the first time in my whole coaching career I was let go, and I'd been coaching 13 years,'' Julien said, ''and, in my mind, I was hoping to go through another 13 years before I'd go through that again. Certainly, it is disappointing.''</p>
        <p>Lamoriello said Monday that he had not made a snap decision. Lamoriello said the Devils, despite amassing 102 points under Julien, did not appear to be focused for a lengthy playoff run.</p>
        <p>So Lamoriello summoned Julien to his office on Monday morning and fired him. Lamoriello informed the assistant coaches of the move, then told the players before canceling practice.</p>
        <p>''There's no doubt it hurts,'' Julien said. ''You don't want to be let go with three games left in the season.''</p>
        <p>Although Julien said that Lamoriello was ''nothing but fair with me,'' he did not sound as if he agreed with Lamoriello's reasoning. Despite a series of injuries, Julien had put together what appeared to be a successful season.''It's been a good year,'' Julien said. ''It's unfortunate this had to happen.''</p>
        <p>The Devils have been unable to add veterans because of costly and fruitless free-agent signings -- the departed Vladimir Malakhov, Dan McGillis and Alexander Mogilny among them -- that have limited their flexibility under the N.H.L. salary cap.</p>
        <p>Goaltender Martin Brodeur has had a brilliant season, posting 12 shutouts and tying Bernie Parent's single-season N.H.L. record by winning 47 games. But Brodeur, who turns 35 next month, has played more than 4,600 minutes this season, a career high.</p>
        <p>''This team here has had its share of challenges,'' Julien said.</p>
        <p>Julien said he had a great relationship with the players and with the assistant coaches.</p>
        <p>''I did my best,'' he said. Julien said he thought the Devils, who are in second in the Eastern Conference, have the potential to win the club's fourth Stanley Cup.''I've gone too far with this team to wish nothing but the best for them,'' Julien said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
