<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Novice's-Eye View Of Life and Sense in Theater</title>
    <meta content="05exit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/theater/reviews/05exit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fugard, Athol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hurley, William Dennis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Higgins, Morlan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Exits and Entrances (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Primary Stages Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Fugard, Athol</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Exits and Entrances (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Novice's-Eye View Of Life and Sense in Theater</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Novice’s-Eye View of Life and Sense in Theater</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood reviews Athol Fugard play Exits and Entrances, directed by Stephen Sachs; William Dennis Hurley and Morlan Higgins star; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Athol Fugard casts a misty-eyed glance back at the man who ignited his affection for the rough magic of theater in ''Exits and Entrances,'' his latest play, which opened last night at the 59E59 Theaters in a Primary Stages production.</p>
        <p>A heartfelt memoir of an Afrikaners actor who briefly crossed Mr. Fugard's path in the 1950s and '60s, when his career was still in embryo, this two-character play is not a major addition to this South African playwright's oeuvre. But in examining one source of the inspiration for his great achievement, it movingly speaks of theater's potential to shape lives in enduring ways, even as it acknowledges the evanescence of the art form.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Athol Fugard’s latest play movingly speaks of theater’s potential to shape lives in enduring ways, even as it acknowledges the evanescence of the art form.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Athol Fugard casts a misty-eyed glance back at the man who ignited his affection for the rough magic of theater in ''Exits and Entrances,'' his latest play, which opened last night at the 59E59 Theaters in a Primary Stages production.</p>
        <p>A heartfelt memoir of an Afrikaners actor who briefly crossed Mr. Fugard's path in the 1950s and '60s, when his career was still in embryo, this two-character play is not a major addition to this South African playwright's oeuvre. But in examining one source of the inspiration for his great achievement, it movingly speaks of theater's potential to shape lives in enduring ways, even as it acknowledges the evanescence of the art form.</p>
        <p>The play opens in 1956, backstage at a theater in Cape Town. On the bill is ''Oedipus Rex,'' the title role to be performed by André Huguenet (Morlan Higgins), a celebrated actor who has mounted the production in honor of his 30th year onstage. His powerful presence is extolled in an opening monologue delivered by the Playwright (William Dennis Hurley), looking back on their first encounter, when he was hired to play a small role in the production and act as André's assistant.</p>
        <p>Blustering in as curtain time approaches on opening night, André fills the dressing room with a flamboyant energy redolent of a fading theatrical era. The voice richly booms. Gestures sweep toward the sky. The act of donning a costume becomes a silent farce in three brief acts. As he and his assistant run lines before the curtain -- André has been editing and paraphrasing Sophocles, which gets under the aspiring writer's skin -- André breaks off to reflect on his own autobiography.</p>
        <p>''We have a lot in common,'' he observes, referring to, the fate-dogged king he is playing. ''Even though I didn't murder my father and sleep with my mother, the Gods appear to have also singled me out for special attention.''</p>
        <p>The grandiosity of course hides a heart singed by a lifelong sense of alienation. André grew up in a deeply religious family of no great means. As a gentle boy he was expected to pursue a religious vocation. But a furtive encounter with a legendary performance -- Anna Pavlova's ''Dying Swan'' -- seduced him into the world of dream-making.</p>
        <p>''She opened my eyes, my whole life, to possibilities I didn't know existed,'' he recalls. ''From her first glissade onstage I knew that I was looking at a world where I would be safe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Higgins, a Los Angeles actor making his New York debut, movingly imparts both the pride André takes in his achievement and the gnawing uncertainty that underlies it. André is a distinct portrait, but he is a type too: the gay man who has dedicated his life to art, reaping in the end a pile of press clippings and a lonely dotage with a sister. Mr. Higgins vividly brings alive the bedrock truth sometimes obscured by the role's generic contours.</p>
        <p>With a mixture of dry disdain and half-feigned pity, André leaps upon his young friend when he casually says, after the last performance of ''Oedipus,'' that André should go home satisfied. ''The stage is my real home,'' he grandly intones, adding that when acting, ''I know who I am, what I am, and why I am what I am.''</p>
        <p>Such declarations skirt cliché, and ''Exits and Entrances'' brings few fresh insights about the inner drives of actors or the sacrifices required to pursue a life in the theater. The psychology of performers has been explored more deeply -- and to more powerful theatrical effect -- in plays like ''A Life in the Theater'' by David Mamet and ''The Dresser'' by Ronald Harwood, to name but two. And I wish Mr. Fugard had not included a perfunctory passage in which André tearily bemoans a life that had to be lived in the closet.</p>
        <p>But he digs a little deeper in the second half as he juxtaposes the characters' strongly differentiated visions of theater's purpose, a conflict of no small significance in the context of their culture. For André it has always been an escape from the bruising burden of life, and he curtly upbraids the Playwright when he learns that his new play is about the suffering of the country's black population.</p>
        <p>''This world is ugly enough as it is, for heaven's sake,'' he says. ''People go to the theater to be elevated above its squalor.''</p>
        <p>The Playwright, played with a bright-eyed sincerity by Mr. Hurley, believes theater is a forum for a powerful encounter with the world's harsh truths, and perhaps a means of lessening them. Their argument grows heated (rather too monotonously, under the sometimes unsubtle direction of Stephen Sachs), and they are ready to part in anger when André implores his young friend to stay and share a final drink.</p>
        <p>The drink becomes a soliloquy. ''Exits and Entrances'' reaches a hushed climax with André discovering the true, bleak depths in that most overfamiliar of speeches, Hamlet's long meditation on being and nonbeing. André's means of escape becomes a terrifying reckoning with the anguish in his heart.</p>
        <p>Mr. Higgins performs it breathtakingly, revealing with harsh clarity how each phrase opens a new wound in the actor's exhausted soul. The pathos is almost unbearable. André is giving the last and greatest performance of his life offstage, to an audience of one.</p>
        <p>Exits and Entrances</p>
        <p>By Athol Fugard; directed by Stephen Sachs; sets by Charlie Corcoran; costumes by Shon Le Blanc; lighting by Brian Nason; sound by David B. Marling; production supervision by PRF Productions; production stage manager, Samone B. Weissman; associate artistic director, Michelle Bossy. Presented by Primary Stages, Casey Childs, executive producer; Andrew Leynse, artistic director; Elliot Fox, managing director; in association with Dasha Epstein and Jamie De Roy. At the 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, between Madison and Park Avenues; (212) 279-4200. Through April 29. Running time: 1 hour, 25 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Morlan Higgins (André) and William Dennis Hurley (the Playwright).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
