<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GARDEN Q. &amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="05qna" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/garden/05qna.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GARDEN Q. &amp; A.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Garden Q.&amp;A.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Land</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ideas for the Pondscape</p>
        <p>Q. We have the remains of a small farm pond and would like to landscape it with flowering perennials. Can you suggest a few that are hardy?</p>
        <p>A. A few is a wise idea. Massing is as effective at pond side as it is in a border, and plentiful moisture should help the plants achieve their full mass potential.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. We have the remains of a small farm pond and would like to landscape it with flowering perennials. Can you suggest a few that are hardy?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ideas for the Pondscape</p>
        <p>Q. We have the remains of a small farm pond and would like to landscape it with flowering perennials. Can you suggest a few that are hardy?</p>
        <p>A. A few is a wise idea. Massing is as effective at pond side as it is in a border, and plentiful moisture should help the plants achieve their full mass potential.</p>
        <p>For height, consider joe-pye weed (Eupatorium maculatum and E. pupureum). It makes substantial bushes about six feet tall before blooming, in muted pinks, from mid- to late summer.</p>
        <p>Or, you may prefer ironweed, Vernonia noveboracensis. It is as tall as the joe-pyes, or taller, and its purple flowers come later.</p>
        <p>For an earlier bloom and a lacier look, plant meadow rues, Thalictrum ssp. These four- to five-footers look like giant columbines until you see the airy umbels of tiny pink, white or yellow flowers.</p>
        <p>The dark green sword-shaped leaves of beardless iris contrast well with the plants above, and many are water lovers. Japanese varieties may grow four feet tall and bloom for weeks in midsummer. And you should do well with Siberians, which bloom before the Japanese, in a budget-busting array of colors.</p>
        <p>But whatever else you plant at the pond, be sure there is some blue flag, Iris versicolor, a fast-spreading native that flowers from late spring to early summer. Though it, too, comes in many colors, none are more beautiful than the original dark-veined true blue.</p>
        <p>Iris sources include Joe Pye Weed's Garden, jpwflowers.com (no phone); and Nicholls Gardens, (703) 754-9623 or nichollsgardens.com.</p>
        <p>After Winter, a Second Chance</p>
        <p>Q. I just found 100 crocus bulbs left over from last fall. They were in the unheated garage but they are still alive; I see little green shoots! Any tips on proper planting?</p>
        <p>A. Contritely and gratefully would be a good start. But don't feel too bad; letters like yours are a hardy spring perennial at Q.&amp;A.</p>
        <p>Just plant them now as you would have in fall. If they are going into a lawn, have some grass seed handy. Any opening in the turf is an opening for seeds, and if you do not supply them the weeds will be happy to oblige.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
