<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maybe She's Reappeared; Definitely She's a Mystery</title>
    <meta content="05masl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/books/05masl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Lippman, Laura</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">What the Dead Know (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maybe She's Reappeared; Definitely She's a Mystery</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Maybe She’s Reappeared; Definitely She’s a Mystery</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What the Dead Know  By Laura Lippman  376 pages. William Morrow. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Laura Lippman's ''What the Dead Know'' is an uncommonly clever impostor story, so cagily constructed that it easily fulfills the genre's two basic demands. First, Ms. Lippman is able to keep her reader guessing about the main character's disputed identity until the very end of this book. Second, when the revelation comes, it makes perfect sense, and it has been hiding in plain sight. This is not one of those mysteries with a denouement that feels tacked on, half baked or pulled out of thin air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The clues in this cagily constructed mystery are sprinkled amid the minutiae of a 1970s girlhood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What the Dead Know  By Laura Lippman  376 pages. William Morrow. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Laura Lippman's ''What the Dead Know'' is an uncommonly clever impostor story, so cagily constructed that it easily fulfills the genre's two basic demands. First, Ms. Lippman is able to keep her reader guessing about the main character's disputed identity until the very end of this book. Second, when the revelation comes, it makes perfect sense, and it has been hiding in plain sight. This is not one of those mysteries with a denouement that feels tacked on, half baked or pulled out of thin air.</p>
        <p>Here's the premise: A woman involved in a Baltimore highway accident comes forth with a bizarre revelation. Out of the blue she claims to be Heather Bethany, one of two adolescent sisters who were last seen at a mall in 1975. She knows a lot about Heather, and her claim is plausible, but there's also something about her that prompts incredulity. Ms. Lippman's well-drawn cast of supporting characters -- including a police officer, a social worker, a lawyer and a dapper retired detective who studied the case closely when the girls vanished -- are left to study her closely and try to figure out what game she's playing.</p>
        <p>It's fair to assume that Ms. Lippman would not be leading her readers through nearly 400 serpentine, carefully nuanced pages if Heather Bethany were Heather Bethany, pure and simple. It's a sure thing that something is amiss. But what? This book is so well larded with small, potentially troubling details that any of its characters might be hiding something. Starting with the so-called Heather: Ms. Lippman quickly lets the reader know that this woman has lived under a series of assumed names. She also lets it slip that the tricky part of being Heather is ''not knowing what she should know but remembering what she wouldn't know.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lippman usually writes installments of a series about Tess Monaghan, reporter turned detective. (Ms. Lippman is a former reporter for The Baltimore Sun.) These books are dependably solid, but the stand-alone ''What the Dead Know'' is in a different league. Even in comparison with her ''Every Secret Thing'' (2003), another stand-alone that overlaps slightly with this one in their plots about missing girls, the new book is exceptionally well executed.</p>
        <p>This time Ms. Lippman writes like a warmer-blooded American Ruth Rendell, keenly observant and giving a faintly spooky charge to every stray detail. Even as she expertly summons the minutiae of teenage girlhood circa 1975, it's gratifying to know that the contents of Heather's favorite purse will have something to do with Heather's destiny.</p>
        <p>''What the Dead Know'' takes its title from Ecclesiastes and is divided into several different time periods. The book starts in the present, flashes back to the disappearance and then reveals what happened to the parents of Heather and her sister, Sunny, after the girls went missing. This structure allows Ms. Lippman to dispense information sparingly, with the precision that is one of this book's most satisfying features.</p>
        <p>First we see the Bethany family as a unit. Then we learn that the mother, Miriam, is having an affair, and that the father, Dave, is a rigidly spiritual ex-hippie whose joyless quest for enlightenment hangs heavily over the rest of his family. Only later is it revealed that the girls were adopted (under highly fraught circumstances), so that even if a parent can identify Heather, there will be no corroborating DNA proof. And only later is it clear that one of the parents has died and will never learn the truth about the daughters' fate.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Ms. Lippman teases the reader with Heather's memories of a troubled sexual history. She seems to have been held prisoner. When she went to high school and played kissing games with classmates, she was the only teenager who secretly had an abusive husband at home. With information that sketchy, it's possible to jump to all the wrong conclusions, which is precisely what Ms. Lippman wants to encourage. The book's clues are indistinguishable from its red herrings until the final pages.</p>
        <p>For a novel steeped in such elaborate gamesmanship, ''What the Dead Know'' is unusually three-dimensional. Its characters are credibly and movingly drawn -- particularly Miriam, who has relocated and shape-shifted several different times since the disappearances, just as Heather claims to have done. Miriam winds up hiding in Mexico, driven there by the relentless publicity surrounding the Bethany case and not brought back to Baltimore until the book is ready for its aha! moment. Miriam returns as if from another planet, amazed at the doll-like, interchangeable young women on the covers of American celebrity magazines, creatures who contrast so sharply with her real, lost daughters.</p>
        <p>The sisters are equally well evoked, right down to the most seemingly mundane touches. In detailing their last known day together, Ms. Lippman presents a mall visit that is a superb feat of covert trickery. Their itinerary seems so banal, and yet it holds the key to their future. They look at clothes and dress patterns. They run into an oddball music teacher they know from school. They sneak into an R-rated movie, which happens to be ''Chinatown.'' They have the usual kind of petty, sisterly spat. Then they are grabbed by a policeman, and there's no one but Heather to explain what happened next. Thirty-two years later all the remaining witnesses are either incapacitated or dead.</p>
        <p>This presents a mystery writer's classic challenge to the reader: Here are the facts, now put them together. It's a cerebral tactic buried within a very human story, and that makes for an unusual combination. And ''What the Dead Know,'' like the best books in this tradition, is doubly satisfying. You read it once just to move breathlessly toward the finale. Then you revisit it to marvel at how well Ms. Lippman pulled the wool over your eyes.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
