<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>These Salons Forgo Beauty Sleep</title>
    <meta content="05skin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/fashion/05skin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SKIN DEEP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beauty Salons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty Salons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E4DE163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>These Salons Forgo Beauty Sleep</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">These Salons Forgo Beauty Sleep</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATASHA SINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Singer, Natasha</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT 6:30 p.m., when many hair salons around the country are beginning to close their doors for the night, the cocktail hour at the new Frédéric Fekkai salon in SoHo is just beginning.</p>
        <p>Up goes the volume on the electronic bossa nova of Bebel Gilberto. Out come the flutes of Simple Peche sparkling wine. And then the beauty night owls -- clients who schedule their treatments after dark -- start to arrive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some beauty salons are staying open past 10 p.m. and embracing late-night beauty with cocktail hours and music that seems more appropriate for a club.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT 6:30 p.m., when many hair salons around the country are beginning to close their doors for the night, the cocktail hour at the new Frédéric Fekkai salon in SoHo is just beginning.</p>
        <p>Up goes the volume on the electronic bossa nova of Bebel Gilberto. Out come the flutes of Simple Peche sparkling wine. And then the beauty night owls -- clients who schedule their treatments after dark -- start to arrive.</p>
        <p>''There are two types of beauty night owl,'' explained Melissa Maron, 25, a blond with creamy Vermeer skin who was having her hair teased and curled at Fekkai last Thursday at 7 p.m. ''There's the girl who gets a massage, a facial, a glass of wine, and heads home to bed, and there's the girl who gets her hair and nails done so she can go right out and show it off, which is what I like to do.''</p>
        <p>After the haircut, Ms. Maron, who works in product development at Victoria's Secret Beauty, planned to meet friends for tapas and then for drinks at GoldBar in Little Italy.</p>
        <p>''The great thing about a late hair appointment is you can go to the salon totally dressed to go out,'' she said.</p>
        <p>With the open layout and modernist furniture of a TriBeCa loft, the new Fekkai salon is designed to attract downtown hipsters who stay out late, wake up late and want their hair styled late -- or, at least until closing time at 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>But the beauty night shift is not just for 20-something clubgoers. A few salons and spas around the country are starting to offer later hours to accommodate people whose demanding jobs do not allow for haircuts, massages or manicures during lunch hour. Others do it periodically, to see if the longer hours are worthwhile.</p>
        <p>Some salons and spas are also using the later hours to recast themselves as social destinations with a cocktail-hour vibe, free after-hours drinks and snacks, and, in some cases, D.J.s.</p>
        <p>The result is an eclectic evening grooming scene in which executives coming from work intersect with young women in skinny jeans who are just beginning their night out.</p>
        <p>To accommodate both groups, Red Market Salon on Gansevoort Street serves coffee and wine. The loft-like space with exposed white-brick walls and bright-red styling chairs stays open until at least 11 p.m. and throws parties to showcase art.</p>
        <p>''We do get a young and trendy crowd who are getting their highlights done at 9:30 so they can meet their friends at clubs at 11:30,'' said Reynald Ricard, an owner of the salon. ''But most of the very late clients are lawyers, bankers and traders.''</p>
        <p>In addition to convenience, some clients prefer later appointments because salons can be less crowded and stylists more attentive in the evening. At 9 p.m. last Thursday, Megan French, a producer at Viacom, had the last hair appointment at the Paul Labrecque Salon and Spa inside the Reebok Sports Club/NY on the Upper West Side. Normally bustling during the day, the salon, which is open until 11 p.m. on weekdays, was quiet and almost peaceful.</p>
        <p>''At night here, there is never the constant phone ringing, or delivery guys arriving, or daughters chatting with mothers,'' Ms. French said. ''Maybe night treatments are becoming a trend because it's calmer when appointments aren't stacked one on top of another.''</p>
        <p>Others seek out night treatments for the social scene. At Fekkai, for example, the solid oak communal hairstyling stations are designed to encourage clients to talk to one another while they are getting highlights or a blow-out -- the beauty equivalent to the family-style dinner.</p>
        <p>''The salon, not the bar, has become a place to meet,'' said Fabrice Gili, creative director of the Fekkai SoHo salon. ''We have become a place to socialize like someone's apartment, a place to hang out, interact, relax and chill out, a place to start your evening.''</p>
        <p>Here are snapshots of the evening beauty scene in Manhattan last Friday.</p>
        <p>7 P.M., FRÉDÉRIC FEKKAI SOHO, 394 WEST BROADWAY -- Jodi Jordan, 22, a kindergarten teacher in Manhattan, was having her bangs trimmed while two friends in oversize sunglasses, stovepipe jeans and designer handbags looked on with studied nonchalance.</p>
        <p>''They play cool videos here,'' Ms. Jordan said. ''It's a hip place for young kids downtown and, after 5:30, they have Champagne.''</p>
        <p>One of the friends spun Ms. Jordan's chair to see a 360-degree view of the new haircut.</p>
        <p>''Let's see the whole look, diva,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Next stop for the threesome: a friend's band playing in the East Village.</p>
        <p>''That's what you get at night,'' said Mr. Gili after he had ministered to Ms. Jordan's hair. ''They are not in the going-back-to-work mood. They are ready to go out.''</p>
        <p>8 P.M., RED MARKET SALON, 32 GANSEVOORT STREET -- Krystal Mozell, a receptionist at a doctor's office in Manhattan, plopped onto a red vinyl couch to wait for a trim while other clients with foil-covered hair sat in belted robes, drinking glasses of red wine and chatting.</p>
        <p>''It's more relaxing to get your hair cut after work, especially at a place like this which is so social,'' said Ms. Mozell, 21. After the haircut, she planned to meet friends at a nearby lounge. ''Your hair looks great and fresh and you can use the good looks to go out to a club or something,'' she said.</p>
        <p>9 P.M., OKEANOS, 211 EAST 51ST STREET -- Russian hockey players and ballet dancers are regulars at this spa, which has a traditional Russian steam bath and treatments like platza, a rigorous massage involving birch branches. But after hours, American lawyers, bankers and hedge fund managers who work in the neighborhood frequent the place, too.</p>
        <p>In a bathrobe and flip-flops, Steven Rosenblatt, a lawyer in Manhattan, lounged in the lobby. He and Madina Axelrod, a colleague, were recovering from a session in the steam room -- with a vodka in one hand and a blini topped with salmon roe in the other.</p>
        <p>''People may have a prejudice that a sauna seems too epicurean, too luxurious or too self-indulgent,'' Mr. Rosenblatt said. ''But it's a sensational antidote to stress for lawyers and other people who need to decompress after work.''</p>
        <p>9:30 P.M., LA VIE ZEN SPA, 420 MADISON AVENUE -- In the same midtown neighborhood as Bear Stearns, and branches of Morgan Stanley, La Vie Zen, which opened last month, offers itself as an alternative to cold corporate environments. The spa, on the second floor of an office building, is steeped in Zen kitsch from the jade fobs on the changing room lockers to the Chinese Buddha and calligraphy in the waiting area.</p>
        <p>To accommodate after-work clients, the spa has started a monthly evening event called ''The Midnight Facial'' during which back scrubs, manicures and other treatments are available until 11.</p>
        <p>''We're in such a corporate, high-stress neighborhood, that we are already talking about staying open late once a week,'' said Bernice Luk, the spa's general manager.</p>
        <p>10 P.M., OSAKA HEALTH SPA, 37 WEST 46TH STREET -- Even from the sidewalk, the pagoda-like exterior with wooden-slatted doors and sloping roof signals that traditional Eastern treatments are the specialties here. Inside, on the third floor, there are stone-tiled hot and cold plunge baths, as well as a dry sauna and a steam room. Treatments include shiatsu massage, acupuncture, back-walking and herbal body scrubs.</p>
        <p>The spa is open until midnight Monday through Saturday. But the place was empty on Friday evening -- not because it was late, said Joseph Lee, the spa's consulting physician, but because it was too early.</p>
        <p>''We get Broadway actors, actresses and dancers who come in after their performances,'' Mr. Lee said. ''Acupressure is great for insomnia.''</p>
        <p>11 P.M., CLEO II SPA, 258 THIRD AVENUE -- This brightly lighted nail parlor is a well-known destination for New Yorkers beset by late-night manicure crises on the order of chipped polish and hangnails.</p>
        <p>Veronica Gray, a lawyer, and her friend, Alicia Simmons, a labor employment lawyer, were making their first visit. Sitting at adjacent manicure stations, the pair seemed giddy over the idea of late-night beauty treatments. They inspected each other's newly pedicured feet. They giggled.</p>
        <p>''Getting a manicure at eleven on a Friday night seems a little bit frivolous because you know you will mess it up by Sunday,'' said Ms. Gray, who had chosen a purple polish called Maniac Mauve. ''But it's fun and luxurious to kind of wash off the workweek with a beauty treatment.''</p>
        <p>Cleo II schedules the last appointments of the day at 11 for manicure-pedicures and 11:30 for manicures. But some clients arrive even later, according to Tenzin Tseyang, a manicurist.</p>
        <p>''There are even people who come begging for a manicure at midnight,'' Ms. Tseyang said. She eyed the clock above her manicure station. It was 11:30 p.m. ''And sometimes, even at midnight, we take them.''</p>
        <p>SKIN DEEP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
