<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Is Reviewing Request by Iran to Let Its Envoy Visit 5 Iranians Seized in a Raid in Iraq</title>
    <meta content="05iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/world/middleeast/05iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, William B Iv (Maj Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iran</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2DB163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Is Reviewing Request by Iran to Let Its Envoy Visit 5 Iranians Seized in a Raid in Iraq</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Is Reviewing Request by Iran to Let Its Envoy Visit 5 Iranians Seized in a Raid in Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG; Reporting was contributed by Alissa J. Rubin and Qais Mizher from Baghdad, Michael R. Gordon from Washington, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Kirkuk, Baquba and Falluja.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American officials are reviewing informal request from Iranian government for envoy to visit five Iranians who were imprisoned in Jan after American raid in northern Iraq; Iranian officials say men are diplomats; Bush administration has long accused Iran of giving weapons and money to Shiite militias in Iraq; Maj Gen William B Caldwell IV, military spokesman, refuses to say whether there is any connection between talks over five Iranians and negotiations over 16 Britons held by Iran; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American officials are reviewing an informal request from the Iranian government for an envoy to visit five Iranians who were imprisoned after an American raid in northern Iraq in January, an American military spokesman said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The spokesman, Maj. Gen. William B. Caldwell IV, said at a news conference that the request was ''being assessed at this time.'' He added that the Americans had conducted the raid to go after people suspected of carrying out illegal operations in Iraq. The general did not say when the Americans might approve or reject the request.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Americans had conducted the raid to go after people suspected of carrying out illegal operations in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American officials are reviewing an informal request from the Iranian government for an envoy to visit five Iranians who were imprisoned after an American raid in northern Iraq in January, an American military spokesman said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The spokesman, Maj. Gen. William B. Caldwell IV, said at a news conference that the request was ''being assessed at this time.'' He added that the Americans had conducted the raid to go after people suspected of carrying out illegal operations in Iraq. The general did not say when the Americans might approve or reject the request.</p>
        <p>He also said that the International Committee of the Red Cross had recently been allowed to visit a group of prisoners that included one of the five Iranians.</p>
        <p>General Caldwell's comments came in response to a reporter's question concerning a report on Wednesday from the Iranian state news agency that an envoy from the Iranian Embassy in Iraq would meet with the five detainees.</p>
        <p>Ali al-Dabbagh, a spokesman for the Iraqi government, said the five Iranians were a subject of discussion at a regional conference held last month in Baghdad that American and Iranian diplomats attended.</p>
        <p>General Caldwell's comments came as President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad of Iran said Wednesday that his country would free 15 British marines and sailors who had been held for nearly two weeks. The British detainees were seized by the Iranian military in the northern Persian Gulf on March 23 and were accused of having trespassed into Iran's territorial waters.</p>
        <p>General Caldwell did not say whether there was any connection between talks over the five Iranians and negotiations over the 15 British captives.</p>
        <p>The five Iranians imprisoned by the Americans were among six people detained in a raid on Jan. 11 in Erbil, the capital of the autonomous Kurdistan region. American attack helicopters and armored vehicles backed up the soldiers who carried out the raid, and 200 Kurdish soldiers surrounded the Americans in a tense standoff before letting them leave with their prisoners. One of the detainees was released that day.</p>
        <p>Iranian officials have said that the men are diplomats. Hoshyar Zebari, the Iraqi foreign minister and a Kurd, said in a telephone interview on Tuesday that although the men being held were not officially diplomats, they had nevertheless been acting as liaisons between Iraq and Iran.</p>
        <p>''It was not a clandestine operation,'' he said. ''They were known by us. They were under surveillance by regional security. They operated with the approval of the regional government and with the knowledge of the Iraqi government. We were in the process of formalizing that liaison office into a consulate. Then they would have diplomatic immunity.''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has long accused Iran of giving weapons and money to Shiite militias in Iraq, but it has increased its accusations in recent months. On Tuesday, an Iranian diplomat who was kidnapped more than eight weeks ago by men wearing uniforms from the Iraqi security forces was released to the Iranian Embassy. Mr. Zebari said that he had pushed hard to get the captors to free the diplomat, Jalal Sharafi, and that he was still working on the issue of the five Iranians held by the Americans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zebari said the liberation of Mr. Sharafi, the second secretary of the Iranian Embassy here, had nothing to do with the standoff over the 15 British marines and sailors.</p>
        <p>In other political wrangling, two members of Parliament who answer to Moktada al-Sadr, the radical Shiite cleric, were fired by Mr. Sadr for meeting with the Americans, a third legislator, Saleh al-Ajili, said Wednesday. American military officials say Mr. Sadr is in Iran, while Mr. Sadr's supporters say he is still in Iraq.</p>
        <p>After the elections for Parliament in late 2005, political blocs filled the seats with members they had selected. Recent legislation has given the blocs the right to replace members, Mr. Ajili said.</p>
        <p>He declined to give details of the meetings that the two fired legislators, Salam al-Maliki and Qusay Abdul Wahab, had with the Americans. Mr. Maliki is a former transportation minister. ''We have an order not to meet with anyone from the occupation authorities,'' Mr. Ajili said.</p>
        <p>In Washington, Gen. David H. Petraeus, commander of the American forces in Iraq, told a television interviewer on Wednesday that there had been some initial signs of progress in the plan to improve security in Baghdad, including a decline in sectarian killings. But he acknowledged that the militant group Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia had responded with ''sensational attacks'' in Tal Afar and Kirkuk. He made his comments on ''The NewsHour with Jim Lehrer.''</p>
        <p>He also suggested that the Congressional measures setting a deadline for withdrawing troops from Iraq might embolden the insurgents. ''I'm not sure that hard and fast deadlines are useful in the sense of providing the enemies out here just a time to which they have to hang tough, and then know that we would be going,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In Iraq, five employees of a power station were shot dead on Wednesday in an ambush west of Kirkuk, police officials said. In the Kut area, a concealed bomb killed two Iraqi soldiers. A former Iraqi Army colonel was shot dead in a restaurant in Falluja, and a civilian was killed by a sniper in Baghdad.</p>
        <p>Four Iraqi policemen were killed in an ambush in restive Diyala Province on Tuesday night, a police official said Wednesday. A civilian was killed and seven were wounded in an attack the same day in the town of Khalis. The bodies of four people, including a policeman, were found Wednesday in Baquba, the capital of Diyala. Three Iraqi Army soldiers were killed in the province in a bomb attack on Wednesday, and one civilian was killed. Another civilian was discovered dead on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>At least 22 shepherds and their sheep were seized Wednesday west of the city of Karbala by men in police uniforms. Police officials in Karbala denied any involvement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
