<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Money For Agency That Oversees State's Judges</title>
    <meta content="05courts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/nyregion/05courts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Commission on Judicial Conduct</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E7DA163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Money For Agency That Oversees State's Judges</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">More Money for Agency That Oversees State’s Judges</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York State's new budget will nearly double financing for the Commission on Judicial Conduct, the agency that investigates and disciplines judges throughout the state court system -- including the town and village courts that have recently come under strong criticism.</p>
        <p>The commission will receive an increase of $2 million under the budget the Legislature passed last weekend, bringing its annual spending to $4.8 million -- the largest budget in the agency's 30-year history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Commission on Judicial Conduct will receive an increase of $2 million under the budget the Legislature passed, bringing its annual spending to $4.8 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York State's new budget will nearly double financing for the Commission on Judicial Conduct, the agency that investigates and disciplines judges throughout the state court system -- including the town and village courts that have recently come under strong criticism.</p>
        <p>The commission will receive an increase of $2 million under the budget the Legislature passed last weekend, bringing its annual spending to $4.8 million -- the largest budget in the agency's 30-year history.</p>
        <p>Its pleas for more money drew unusual attention in Albany in recent months after a series of articles in The New York Times detailed the poor supervision of town and village justices.</p>
        <p>''The increase was necessary in light of the public disclosures,'' said Helene E. Weinstein, a Brooklyn Democrat who is chairwoman of the Assembly's Judiciary Committee.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers pushed for the money after Gov. Eliot Spitzer rejected a commission request for a $2.2 million increase and proposed adding just $22,000. But in recent weeks, aides to the governor agreed to support the larger increase.</p>
        <p>''We look forward to working with the agency to help them improve their efficiency and effectiveness moving forward,'' said Jeffrey Gordon, a spokesman for the Division of the Budget.</p>
        <p>State Senator John A. DeFrancisco, a Syracuse Republican who had pressed for the $2 million increase, said, ''It is basic to make sure that that commission has the tools to monitor the judiciary.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the commission's administrator, Robert H. Tembeckjian, said he had begun plans to double the size of its professional staff, increasing the number of lawyers and investigators to 34 from 17. The commission has said for years that most of its time and effort is spent investigating and disciplining town and village justices, who number about 2,000. Three-quarters of them are not lawyers. ''It means misconduct, where it occurs, will be dealt with more swiftly,'' Mr. Tembeckjian said. ''And the town and village justices will be subject to greater scrutiny by the commission.''</p>
        <p>The Times's series described the courts' troubled history, including justices who denied people basic protections like the right to a lawyer or a trial. Since 1978, the commission has disciplined justices who made racial and sexual comments from the bench, stole court funds and jailed people illegally. But in recent years, case backlogs have grown, and the commission said it lacked the resources to ensure that judges who had been punished had changed their behavior. Its staff has shrunk by more than half in the last two decades, with just two investigators for the western half of the state.</p>
        <p>Of the 640 judges in all New York courts who have been disciplined since 1978, 453 have been town and village justices. The most recent ruling came yesterday, with the censure of a justice in Tompkins County, William F. Burin of Lansing Town Court. The commission found that instead of promptly depositing court funds as required by law, Justice Burin had left sums as large as $10,000 around the court's office in a bank deposit bag for up to a month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
