<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Subdued by a Loss and a Cold Rain, Rutgers Fans Return to Earth</title>
    <meta content="05rutgers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/nyregion/05rutgers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEW BRUNSWICK JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDB163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Subdued by a Loss and a Cold Rain, Rutgers Fans Return to Earth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Subdued by a Loss and a Cold Rain, Rutgers Fans Return to Earth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Jonathan</byline>
      <dateline>NEW BRUNSWICK, N.J., April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Dorothy might say, ''Toto, we're still in New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>A day after the Rutgers University women's basketball team came back down to earth in a convincing defeat at the hands of the University of Tennessee in the N.C.A.A. final, the news trucks had departed, the students quietly returned to their studies, and a hard, cold rain fell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Feeling the sting of disappointment, a day after the school’s women’s basketball team lost in the N.C.A.A. finals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Dorothy might say, ''Toto, we're still in New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>A day after the Rutgers University women's basketball team came back down to earth in a convincing defeat at the hands of the University of Tennessee in the N.C.A.A. final, the news trucks had departed, the students quietly returned to their studies, and a hard, cold rain fell.</p>
        <p>''A dismal day,'' Cassandra DeMarshall, a junior from Mantua, muttered on Wednesday as she stared into the soaked street and read The Daily Targum, the student newspaper. ''I really thought they were going to take it.''</p>
        <p>And why not? After all, the women had defeated their longtime nemesis, the University of Connecticut, in the Big East tournament final, squeezed by the overwhelming favorite, Duke, in the third round and held a talented Louisiana State team to a mere 35 points in the semifinal game.</p>
        <p>Even Gov. Jon S. Corzine -- who traded in his blue vest for a red T-shirt and red crewneck sweater -- had caught the fever. He could be found jumping and shouting at several earlier games. But on Tuesday he attended a Passover Seder and could not make it to the final in Cleveland.</p>
        <p>A few games before the loss, the team's coach, C. Vivian Stringer, boldly declared, ''We are a team of destiny.''</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, that destiny was second place.</p>
        <p>For many at this sprawling university of 50,000 students here, a Rutgers victory would have meant much more than a simple championship. It would have been the first championship in a team sport since 1949. ''I think people would take us seriously,'' said Victoria Rollins, 22, a senior from Piscataway, who watched the game with several friends at the Olive Branch, a bar filled with Rutgers faithful.</p>
        <p>But on Wednesday, many fans kept their heads up. ''Nobody's upset about it,'' said Billy Skurka, 19, a freshman from Monroe Township, who sat at the student center and stared into a laptop computer. ''We're proud of how far they got. It was another pleasant surprise.''</p>
        <p>At 12:30 p.m. on Thursday, the bell will be rung in the Old Queens building. And at night the school will hold a rally at the Louis Brown Arena -- also known as the RAC -- in Piscataway.</p>
        <p>No one had predicted this run, just as no one had predicted the football team's Cinderella season, its most successful in 30 years. It was capped by the team's winning its first bowl game.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty amazing that Rutgers can go from a school that's a joke to one that maybe can win a championship,'' said Bill Cunningham, 25, a 2004 business school graduate, who remembered too well the bad old days of nearly empty stadiums and fan ennui.</p>
        <p>Carmela Pastena, who has worked at the school's business office for 24 years, said she witnessed something new on campus in the past few months.</p>
        <p>''I have never seen so much excitement that this year has brought,'' Ms. Pastena said. ''Between the football team and the basketball team, it's remarkable.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, there was much less frenzy along the Raritan River for the women's run at the championship than there had been for the football team. Several students said they missed the game entirely, or flipped back and forth between the game and ''American Idol,'' or simply had too much work to do.</p>
        <p>But for those who gathered in front of a television here or anywhere else around the state Tuesday night, the game was everything. As it spiraled out of control, those packed inside the Olive Branch grew quiet, bit nails and rubbed eyes. When one of several loose balls was scooped up by a Tennessee player, a fan wailed, ''Why didn't you get that?''</p>
        <p>After the defeat, announcers on WRSU-FM, the student station, tried to bolster the spirits of their crushed listeners by reminding them that all five of the team's starters would be returning next season, and after all, with what happened this year, the team would almost certainly be a Final Four contestant next year. Right?</p>
        <p>Even though Rutgers's run was portrayed as an underdog story, the basketball program is perhaps the most successful of the major sports at the university. For many years, it was just about the only sport that was not a laughingstock.</p>
        <p>In its 32-year existence, the women's basketball team has suffered through just four losing seasons. It can already boast of one championship -- in 1982, from the defunct A.I.A.W. -- the association in which the school played before the N.C.A.A. And it has qualified for the N.C.A.A. tournament 18 times.</p>
        <p>But that success has not exactly led to outbreaks of Scarlet Knight fever on campus. While attendance has climbed in the past several years, in the 2005-6 season the team averaged about 4,600 fans at the 8,000-seat Louis Brown Athletic Center compared with, say, Tennessee, which averages about 15,300 fans at its home games.</p>
        <p>Just before the game on Tuesday students eagerly signed a bedsheet in front of the student center wishing the team luck. One message said: "You all turn me on! Keep up the good work!"</p>
        <p>NEW BRUNSWICK JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
