<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CNN Replaces Its Morning News Anchor Team</title>
    <meta content="05cnn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/arts/television/05cnn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070407T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cable News Network</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CNN Replaces Its Morning News Anchor Team</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">CNN Replaces Its Morning News Anchor Team</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Disappointed with its ratings for its news program ''American Morning,'' CNN is replacing the anchor team of Soledad O'Brien and Miles O'Brien and installing the newly hired Kieran Chetry and the former CBS News correspondent John Roberts, the network announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>Jon Klein, the president of CNN's domestic operations, acknowledged in a news conference that the move was being made for ratings reasons. Citing small recent ratings gains by the morning show, Mr. Klein said: ''We want to be up more. We want to do better.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>CNN is replacing the anchor team of Soledad O’Brien and Miles O’Brien and installing the newly hired Kiran Chetry and the former CBS News correspondent John Roberts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Disappointed with its ratings for its news program ''American Morning,'' CNN is replacing the anchor team of Soledad O'Brien and Miles O'Brien and installing the newly hired Kieran Chetry and the former CBS News correspondent John Roberts, the network announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>Jon Klein, the president of CNN's domestic operations, acknowledged in a news conference that the move was being made for ratings reasons. Citing small recent ratings gains by the morning show, Mr. Klein said: ''We want to be up more. We want to do better.''</p>
        <p>Ratings for most morning news programs have been declining, although MSNBC has demonstrated strong gains for its simulcast of Don Imus's morning radio show.</p>
        <p>Mornings have been the only recent weak spot for CNN, Mr. Klein said. He said the network had posted gains for the rest of its schedule, especially among the audience group chiefly sought by news programs, viewers ages 25 to 54.</p>
        <p>The numbers back him up. Though CNN still trails Fox News Channel almost everywhere, several CNN programs have done well this quarter when compared with the same period last year. Lou Dobbs's newscast at 6 p.m., for example, is up 60 percent in that 25-to-54 age group. Wolf Blitzer's program ''The Situation Room'' has also had a strong first quarter, up 46 percent over last year.</p>
        <p>CNN, which has been dominated by Fox News Channel for years, was also promoting a victory for Mr. Blitzer over Fox in the 4 p.m. to 6 p.m. slot among that audience group, the first time CNN had such a victory over Fox since 2002.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein indicated that these successes had made him impatient to see progress in the morning. He played up the hard-news approach of ''American Morning,'' calling it ''the only real newscast in the morning.'' He said that with the presidential race heating up and interest in war news continuing, CNN had an opportunity to stand out.</p>
        <p>That was one reason to insert Mr. Roberts, he said. Mr. Roberts was a White House correspondent for CBS, among other assignments, including once serving as a co-anchor of the network's morning news broadcast, teamed with Meredith Vieira, now a co-host of ''Today'' on NBC.</p>
        <p>Ms. Chetry joined CNN two months ago, after leaving Fox News. ''You just have to look at her'' to know what a strong anchor she is, Mr. Klein said. ''She lights up the screen.''</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Brien, who is not related to Mr. O'Brien, was among the most prominent additions at CNN when she joined the network from NBC in 2003. She will become the anchor for an occasional program called ''CNN: Special Investigations Unit.'' Mr. O'Brien will also stay at CNN, as its chief technology and environment correspondent.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 7, 2007, Saturday  An article in The Arts on Thursday about CNN's new anchor team for its program ''American Morning'' misspelled the given name of one anchor. She is Kiran Chetry, not Kieran. The article also misstated the schedule for a new program with Soledad O'Brien, one of the morning anchors who is being replaced. The program, ''CNN: Special Investigations Unit,'' will be shown weekly, not occasionally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 7, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in The Arts on Thursday about CNN's new anchor team for its program ''American Morning'' misspelled the given name of one anchor. She is Kiran Chetry, not Kieran. The article also misstated the schedule for a new program with Soledad O'Brien, one of the morning anchors who is being replaced. The program, ''CNN: Special Investigations Unit,'' will be shown weekly, not occasionally.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
