<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Clothes Closet At the Mad Scientist's</title>
    <meta content="05CRITIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/fashion/05CRITIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CRITICAL SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DE163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Clothes Closet At the Mad Scientist's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Clothes Closet at the Mad Scientist’s</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Horacio Silva</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Silva, Horacio</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FITTINGLY for a store in a neighborhood that desperately needs a style lift, Hollander &amp; Lexer is named for two pioneering plastic surgeons from the early 1900s.</p>
        <p>''This used to be faux-rococo heaven for fake Marie Antoinettes,'' Hicham Benmira, one of the store's owners, said of this stretch of Atlantic Avenue. ''The men in this area were ready for an extreme makeover.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hollander &amp; Lexer in Brooklyn has a diverse mix of hipster labels and authentic workaday brands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FITTINGLY for a store in a neighborhood that desperately needs a style lift, Hollander &amp; Lexer is named for two pioneering plastic surgeons from the early 1900s.</p>
        <p>''This used to be faux-rococo heaven for fake Marie Antoinettes,'' Hicham Benmira, one of the store's owners, said of this stretch of Atlantic Avenue. ''The men in this area were ready for an extreme makeover.''</p>
        <p>Not that the scars are visible to the casual observer. Mr. Benmira and his partner, Brian Cousins, who also own Darr, a store across the street specializing in industrial-age furniture and found objects, are responsible for the most subtle of modifications. A barely legible sign, written in chalk on a small tin sandwich board, is the only indication that the place has been transformed into a men's clothing store to rival the cool women's boutiques in the area.</p>
        <p>Inside, though, the ''work'' approaches Jocelyn Wildenstein proportions. The black walls and Southern Gothic meets Victoriana aesthetic reflect Mr. Benmira's intention to create a sinister interior that resembles ''a twisted classroom at a perverse boarding school, with a little bit of a crazy scientist's home thrown in.''</p>
        <p>Which explains the antique laboratory glassware, portraits and furniture, including the upturned frame of an old hospital bed used as a hanging rack. A discarded teddy bear on a shelf appears to have been ravaged by a Rottweiler and serves as a metaphor for the store's brand of rough-hewn slightly creepy camp.</p>
        <p>So, too, does a cabinet of curiosities that displays Mr. Benmira's rusty eclecticism, from old Roman brass rings ($225 to $425) to Civil War era buttons ($35 for a string of them that can be worn as necklace) and African amulets ($65). It's an interesting assemblage, but I'm still at a loss as to who would want a desiccated sea urchin ($26).</p>
        <p>The clothing is equally diverse, a mix of hipster labels and authentic workaday brands like Filson. It's a formula that has been used by stores like Odin and Earnest Sewn -- and in truth most of the gear can also be found at Barneys Co-Op -- but it is a carefully considered approach, which seems to have been successfully exported to Brooklyn. If last weekend is any indication, the store is a magnet for local cardigan-wearing architects and art directors, or at least sensitive young guys who like to dress the part.</p>
        <p>NOT surprisingly, there is a lot of Steven Alan's unthreatening but on-trend men's wear. A cardigan ($220) pops up in different colors on several racks, and so do the label's lightweight cotton shirts ($175), with quirky signature detailing, like exposed seams and pockets on the inside. (I bought two.)</p>
        <p>The emerging New York label Engineered Garments also gets plenty of shelf space, including a chambray shirt ($190) tweaked with off-center pockets for obsessive-compulsive types who like their details askew. Other worthwhile finds include shirts by Nicholas K ($140) and a long-sleeve boat-neck top by Pleasure Principle ($145).</p>
        <p>I didn't care much for the outerwear, with the exception of a Caste seersucker jacket (well priced at $245) and an ultralight baby lamb aviator jacket by Brogden, the most expensive item in the store at $880.</p>
        <p>Much stronger is the selection of jeans -- by ubiquitous brands like Rag &amp; Bone and Paul Smith -- and casual pants, including a winning striped cotton pair by Unis ($175). The classic Filson pants ($175) may have old-school made in the U.S.A. cachet, but they are simply too bulky and itchy for summer.</p>
        <p>The center of the store is annoyingly dark (the lighting fixtures are great looking but awkwardly placed), and sorting through the racks is difficult. It's a pity, as there are some good items to be found, including What Comes Around Goes Around linen pants ($180) and vintage T-shirts by Helmet of the Wild ($78).</p>
        <p>Even in the bad light, it's impossible to miss the many man bags strewn around the place. Rogues Gallery rope-handle totes ($290) made from reconditioned sailcloth are prominently displayed. So are oversize tool bags by Billykirk, which are cool enough looking but too expensive to my mind at $395, especially as the Klein cotton tool bags on which they appear to be modeled sell for around $40 at Home Depot. A better buy is the company's waxed cotton take on an ammunition bag ($195).</p>
        <p>There is also a small butch-femme selection of books, including a Mike Disfarmer monograph and ''Casa Susanna,'' the Michel Hurst and Robert Swope visual chronicle of small-town New Jersey drag queens in the '60s. The books seem an afterthought and pale next to the cult grooming products, including Musgo Real cologne ($32) and Santa Maria Novella soap ($22 for a box of six), which are displayed in a 1930s mail sorter.</p>
        <p>If nothing else, the store disproves the notion that stylish shoes are as hard to find in Brooklyn as a restaurant open after 11 p.m. I bought a pair of smart brown Paul Smith lace-ups ($395) and was also tempted by a pair of tricked-out white leather high-tops by Double Identity ($220), as well as the selection of shoes by Cydwoq (from $225). And while I am aware that Jesus sandals, like the pair by Jutta Neumann ($250), will have many fashion disciples this summer, having been shown all over the European runways, I will not be one of them.</p>
        <p>This should not be a problem for Mr. Benmira, who wore a pair himself teamed with granola socks. Judging from his well-turned-out clientele, he is preaching to the converted.</p>
        <p>Hollander &amp; Lexer  358 Atlantic Avenue (between Bond and Hoyt Streets), Boerum Hill, Brooklyn; (718) 797-9190.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Southern Gothic boarding school meets 1930s demented scientist's laboratory.  SERVICE -- The male staff members are incredibly friendly and heavily mascaraed.  KEY ITEMS -- Nonthreatening shoes, noncommittal casual wear and nonemasculating man bags.  PRICES -- For the most part as modest as the store's unassuming facade.</p>
        <p>CRITICAL SHOPPER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
