<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greenwich Starts to Grapple With Racial Balance in Schools</title>
    <meta content="05greenwich" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/nyregion/05greenwich.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070407T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Greenwich (Conn)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0DA163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greenwich Starts to Grapple With Racial Balance in Schools</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wealthy Connecticut School District Starts to Grapple With Racial Imbalance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON LEIGH COWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowan, Alison Leigh</byline>
      <dateline>GREENWICH, Conn., April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than half a century after the landmark desegregation ruling in Brown v. Board of Education, this overwhelmingly white and wealthy town is beginning to confront the yawning racial imbalance in its cozy, well-groomed neighborhood schools.</p>
        <p>Every year since 2000, the Connecticut Department of Education has sent Greenwich -- along with other towns like West Hartford and, more recently, Fairfield and Groton -- warning letters citing specific schools in danger of violating state laws on racial balance by having student bodies far less diverse than their districts over all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Schools in the predominantly white and wealthy town have been in danger of violating state laws on racial balance since 2000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than half a century after the landmark desegregation ruling in Brown v. Board of Education, this overwhelmingly white and wealthy town is beginning to confront the yawning racial imbalance in its cozy, well-groomed neighborhood schools.</p>
        <p>Every year since 2000, the Connecticut Department of Education has sent Greenwich -- along with other towns like West Hartford and, more recently, Fairfield and Groton -- warning letters citing specific schools in danger of violating state laws on racial balance by having student bodies far less diverse than their districts over all.</p>
        <p>Those districts and a dozen others are bracing for another round of warnings after the Education Department reviews this year's list on Thursday. But little changes from year to year, and the state has rarely, if ever, followed through with sanctions like withholding money to force changes.</p>
        <p>Now, Greenwich's new superintendent -- who until last summer was the state education commissioner, responsible for enforcing the racial balance law -- has vowed to get serious about spreading minority students more equally among the district's 14 elementary and middle schools, rankling many parents for whom top-notch education without widespread busing was a major incentive to buy expensive homes here. The superintendent, Betty J. Sternberg, has convened a 44-person task force to tackle the problem, bluntly declaring, ''Our schools are becoming more segregated.''</p>
        <p>''There will always be people who love their neighborhood schools, and that's fine,'' Dr. Sternberg told teachers last month at the Old Greenwich School. But, she said, ''we're getting to be an increasingly segregated town,'' adding that she hoped residents, even without pressure from the state, would ''embrace the value of being educated in a diverse setting.''</p>
        <p>Few parents are openly criticizing the goal of diversity, but a group calling itself Concerned Citizens of Greenwich has run full-page advertisements in local newspapers asking that neighborhood schools not be made to suffer in the rush to bolster other schools.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sternberg said she had received a flood of e-mail messages, including many that took a ''hateful, bullying tone.'' In a recent essay in Greenwich Time, she cited one e-mail message from a parent who complained: ''The children are exposed to racial diversity in middle school and high school and in their extracurricular activities.  We don't want our elementary school-age children used to neutralize the makeup of another part of town.''</p>
        <p>Though Greenwich's population of 61,000 is 90 percent white, according to the census, nearly a quarter of the public schools' 8,800 students are black, Hispanic or Asian. Yet their representation in many elementary and middle schools is lopsided.</p>
        <p>At the Old Greenwich School, in a neighborhood on the east side of town near Stamford where modest fixer-uppers can fetch $1 million, school officials say the student body is roughly 95 percent white. On the west side of town near Port Chester, N.Y., an increasingly Hispanic area where there is a large housing project, the Hamilton Avenue School is 59 percent minority and the New Lebanon School is 53 percent minority, according to district officials; both are in violation of state law by being more than 25 percentage points off the district average in terms of racial mix.</p>
        <p>Two more schools, Julian Curtiss Elementary (39 percent minority) and Western Middle School (38 percent) are on the cusp and could be cited next year if demographic trends persist. (Old Greenwich, meanwhile, is likely to be found in ''impending'' violation for deviating by at least 15 points.)</p>
        <p>About 2,900 Greenwich children, most of them white, attend private schools.</p>
        <p>The state law mandates that a district must develop a plan to diversify any school more than 25 points off the district's average. Greenwich has committed to spend $29 million on a new building for Hamilton Avenue and has made it a magnet school in hopes of attracting white students from throughout the district.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Sternberg said such efforts -- along with past attempts to improve the heavily minority schools by reducing class sizes -- did little to address the looming issue of racial isolation in a district where test scores show a significant gap between racial groups. In both elementary and middle schools, the proportion of white students meeting state goals in reading is 40 percentage points higher than the proportion of black students and 25 points higher than Hispanics; the gaps in math are even larger.</p>
        <p>''It's laudable to put in resources, but where it fell short was it allowed the perpetuation of a separate but equal system, which the Supreme Court said is not O.K.,'' Dr. Sternberg said in an interview. ''Strong academic achievement is necessary for success but not sufficient, if kids can't really interact with each other.''</p>
        <p>Gary Orfield, a professor of education at the University of California, Los Angeles, who is among the nation's leading experts on school desegregation, criticized Connecticut's law as weak, saying its watch list was ''more like a warning system than a true enforcement process.''</p>
        <p>As in many other states, he said, the law does nothing to combat the larger disparities in diversity from one town to the next. ''In every region of the country we have segregation spreading, and most places aren't doing anything about it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Connecticut's attempts to make public schools reflect their communities at large goes back to about 1969, according to Karen Flanagan, a lawyer at the Department of Education. But even if it were strictly enforced, the law allows for many racially homogeneous schools: As long as Greenwich's minority enrollment stays below 25 percent, for example, schools could be all white without breaking the law.</p>
        <p>Likewise, Dr. Sternberg noted, towns with few minority residents like Darien, Avon and New Canaan could operate schools that are all white, while heavily black and Hispanic cities like New Haven and Bridgeport could have schools that are overwhelmingly minority without tripping over the state thresholds.</p>
        <p>''If you live in Darien, none of this applies to you,'' Dr. Sternberg said. ''It will never apply to them.''</p>
        <p>Besides Greenwich, the only other district Connecticut found in violation of the law last year was West Hartford, an affluent town also on the problem list since 2000. West Hartford administrators successfully argued seven years ago that two of their schools, now magnets, were ''unique,'' a designation that exempts them from having to file yearly action plans. But racial stratification in West Hartford's 11 elementary schools has worsened, and the district is expecting another sharp letter this week reminding it that two of its schools have too high a concentration of minority students and three are close to having too few.</p>
        <p>''The only real quick fix is a major redistricting of our entire elementary school system, and our board has said that's contrary to the philosophy of the neighborhood schools,'' said David P. Sklarz, West Hartford's superintendent. ''People move from other parts of Connecticut to West Hartford because they like the idea that their children can go to the neighborhood schools. There are sidewalks, crossing guards. It's a bit like going back in time.''</p>
        <p>Besides Greenwich and West Hartford, Fairfield and Groton each have a school that is expected to land them on this year's list of racially imbalanced schools. An additional 12 districts are in line to receive letters warning that schools they run are in impending danger of violating the law. They are: Manchester, Middletown, Norwich, Norwalk, Waterbury, Enfield, Shelton, Vernon, Danbury, Wallingford and two newcomers, Glastonbury and Hartford. Meriden, which had one school on last year's warning list, appears to have worked itself off the list this year.</p>
        <p>Districts that show no progress can theoretically lose state funding under the law, though neither Ms. Flanagan nor Dr. Sternberg, the former state commissioner, could recall this ever happening.</p>
        <p>Here in Greenwich, Dr. Sternberg has brought new urgency to the discussion, though she has promised no major changes until the task force issues recommendations in September. In the meantime, anxious parents have been turning out in droves for several public hearings that have addressed the topic.</p>
        <p>At the New Lebanon School, where the minority enrollment has more than doubled in the past decade, Gene Nyitray, the principal, acknowledged that his students' test scores needed improvement, but said parents liked that the school did not need buses and that Spanish was common in the hallways. A majority of parents, he said, ''don't view racial imbalance as a driving force. It's driven by the state.'' If change comes, he said, he hopes to preserve ''not just the feel, but the fact, that this is truly a neighborhood school.''</p>
        <p>At Hamilton Avenue, where nearly 40 percent of the students come from a home where English is not the dominant language and almost a third qualify for free or reduced-price lunches, the principal, Damaris Rau, said she felt the pinch whenever she saw the extras provided by deep-pocketed parent associations at other schools. ''It's also having parents knowing how to advocate for their schools,'' Dr. Rau explained. ''That doesn't happen on this side of town.''</p>
        <p>Hamilton Avenue has been struggling for the past two years without a gymnasium; on recent days, students were practicing juggling and spinning plates as part of an alternative program called ''circus arts.''</p>
        <p>But when its maze of modular buildings is replaced with the $29 million new school this fall, Hamilton Avenue students will have a television studio and free violin lessons in the younger grades. Classes have been limited to 15 students, down from 20, and Dr. Rau said she had 153 applications for next year from youngsters outside the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 7, 2007, Saturday  An article on Thursday about a new push to confront racial imbalance in the Greenwich, Conn., public schools misstated the content of fullpage advertisements placed recently in local newspapers by a group calling itself Concerned Citizens of Greenwich. The ads raised concerns about a proposal to spend $23 million rebuilding Glenville School, and offered a broader critique of a new task force considering topics including racial balance and redistricting. The ads did not ask that neighborhood schools ''not be made to suffer in the rush to bolster other schools.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 7, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about a new push to confront racial imbalance in the Greenwich, Conn., public schools misstated the content of fullpage advertisements placed recently in local newspapers by a group calling itself Concerned Citizens of Greenwich. The ads raised concerns about a proposal to spend $23 million rebuilding Glenville School, and offered a broader critique of a new task force considering topics including racial balance and redistricting. The ads did not ask that neighborhood schools ''not be made to suffer in the rush to bolster other schools.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
