<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mainstay Soprano Feels Snubbed by the Met</title>
    <meta content="05ruth" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/arts/music/05ruth.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Opera</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Swenson, Ruth Ann</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mainstay Soprano Feels Snubbed by the Met</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mainstay Soprano Feels Snubbed by the Met</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL J. WAKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wakin, Daniel J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ruth Ann Swenson, a mainstay soprano at the Metropolitan Opera, will take the stage tomorrow to begin a run of Handel's ''Giulio Cesare'' just six weeks after finishing chemotherapy for breast cancer.</p>
        <p>But her performances as a regal yet coquettish Cleopatra will be bittersweet, because the Met, for reasons unrelated to her illness, appears no longer to want her services after nearly two decades of regular performances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Metropolitan Opera appears no longer to want Ruth Ann Swenson’s services after nearly two decades of regular performances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ruth Ann Swenson, a mainstay soprano at the Metropolitan Opera, will take the stage tomorrow to begin a run of Handel's ''Giulio Cesare'' just six weeks after finishing chemotherapy for breast cancer.</p>
        <p>But her performances as a regal yet coquettish Cleopatra will be bittersweet, because the Met, for reasons unrelated to her illness, appears no longer to want her services after nearly two decades of regular performances.</p>
        <p>Ms. Swenson, known for her creamy sound and superb technique, has no more engagements there beyond a string of ''Traviata'' performances next season. Further, the Met has given one of the ''Giulio Cesare'' performances to her understudy, Danielle de Niese, described on the Met Web site as ''the young star of the recent celebrated Glyndebourne production.'' The site makes no reference to Ms. Swenson's merits. And next year four of her nine ''Traviata'' dates have been handed to another star, Renée Fleming.</p>
        <p>''It's hurtful,'' Ms. Swenson said. ''I'm a New Yorker. I've sung here for many, many years. I've had great success. I've never let them down.'' She added: ''It's so stressful to get up onstage and realize that the top guy doesn't like you, and there's nothing I can do about it. Nothing.''</p>
        <p>The top guy is Peter Gelb, the Met's first-year general manager, who has moved forcefully to put his stamp on the company by emphasizing the dramatic content of opera and working hard to push it before the public eye. Ms. Swenson, a coloratura soprano who has taken on heavier roles and is much liked in the profession, was hired by his predecessor, Joseph Volpe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gelb acknowledged some dissatisfaction with her past performances. But he disputed that her career at the Met was over.</p>
        <p>''She's singing beautifully,'' he said yesterday, a day after attending a dress rehearsal of ''Giulio Cesare.'' ''She not only survived this marathon opera but flourished in it. That's not just my opinion but the uniform consensus of the artistic staff and her colleagues.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gelb confirmed that the Met has not booked her for new engagements. ''That doesn't mean she wouldn't be singing at the Met again,'' he said. ''We try to balance our future seasons with new talent who have not sung at the Met. I would love to see her singing at the Met in the future as well. We also have to find the right repertoire.''</p>
        <p>He defended his decision to give Ms. de Niese another performance, saying she was a potential Met star. As for the ''Traviata'' performances, he said, ''Anytime we can get Renée Fleming to sing at the Metropolitan Opera is a good day for the Metropolitan Opera.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Swenson and her husband and vocal coach, David Burnakus, have other ideas about why Mr. Gelb seems to have lost interest.</p>
        <p>''I think I'm not skinny enough for him,'' the full-figured Ms. Swenson said. ''Excuse me, I'm not some giant person.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burnakus added that her age, 47, and lack of high-profile diva status also worked against her.</p>
        <p>Through much of the interview, the couple oscillated between bitterness, disappointment and cool acceptance over Ms. Swenson's relationship with the Met.</p>
        <p>''It's just life,'' Mr. Burnakus said. ''It's showbiz.''</p>
        <p>He also said Ms. Swenson was a casualty of a recent direction at many opera houses, and particularly at the Met under Mr. Gelb, to attract audiences by emphasizing the theatrical, to -- in Mr. Burnakus's view -- the music's detriment.</p>
        <p>Opera reviewers, while long enamored of Ms. Swenson's voice and musicianship, have at times faulted her for bland portrayals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gelb denied that age or weight influenced Ms. Swenson's position at the Met. ''These are individual conditions that have nothing to do with whether a singer is engaged,'' he said. ''I have to react to which singers are going to provide, in the right combination of repertoire and new productions, the greatest musical, theatrical experiences for our audiences. That ultimately is the bottom line for me as the head of this theater, and it would be irresponsible to react in any different way.''</p>
        <p>Certainly a singer's appearance has long been a factor in casting, as an impediment or an advantage. Deborah Voigt's weight, before her recent loss, may have cost her the role of Ariadne at the Royal Opera House in London nearly three years ago. Weight problems have led several sopranos to undergo surgery. The much-vaunted beauty of Anna Netrebko has not harmed her ascent.</p>
        <p>The tension between drama and music is as old as opera. Audiences can find it hard to accept a middle-aged matron in the role of a consumptive maiden, although experienced listeners can hear such portrayals in the voice. Appearance becomes even more crucial in a visually oriented age. Mr. Gelb, through his movie-theater simulcasting of Met productions, may be inadvertently emphasizing that tendency.</p>
        <p>The couple took pains to say that Ms. Swenson was not seeking publicity or sympathy by granting an interview, which she does infrequently. ''I have never been a P.R. animal,'' said Ms. Swenson, who grew up in Commack, N.Y., and spoke nervously, with a slight Long Island accent. Rather, she said, she felt that her return to the stage after cancer could inspire others. Ms. Swenson said that her treatment had been successful, and that doctors were highly optimistic.</p>
        <p>''No one's going to say that I have to give up and take it easy,'' Ms. Swenson said, finding common cause with Elizabeth Edwards and her husband, John Edwards, who decided to move forward with his presidential bid despite his wife's cancer. ''I totally comprehend where she's at. You can't crawl under the covers and lock yourself in a room, or you're sunk.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Swenson announced her breast cancer in October, shortly before having surgery. She cleared her calendar, with the goal of slowly working back into shape and singing Gounod's ''Faust'' again at the Met on March 12. At that performance she scaled back her movements to conserve stamina. The outpouring of support from the chorus and orchestra, she said, was overwhelming. She cried at her curtain call, something she never does. ''Talk about emotional,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Cleopatra, a role that helped make the young Beverly Sills a star, is daunting enough for any soprano. It includes eight arias and one duet. The Met production has five changes of voluminous, weighty costumes, and Ms. Swenson worries about them fitting properly after surgery. She is also still suffering the after-effects of chemotherapy: fatigue and numbness in her hands and feet. The treatment cost her the long strawberry-blond mane that was a trademark. ''I have peach fuzz,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She has engagements next season in Venice, San Francisco, Cincinnati and Dallas, and at the New York City Opera</p>
        <p>Ms. Swenson said she was aware that her words could burn bridges with Mr. Gelb. ''He doesn't like me anyway,'' she said, ''so what do I have to lose?''</p>
        <p>For his part Mr. Gelb said he was saddened. ''What I want the Met to focus on with her is the successes she can have here,'' he said. ''What I want for her is to hopefully think about the role that's coming up and having great success in it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
