<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Facing Reality About the War</title>
    <meta content="l05iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7DB163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Facing Reality About the War</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''What About Those Other Iraq Deadlines?'' (Op-Ed, April 4):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''What About Those Other Iraq Deadlines?'' (Op-Ed, April 4):</p>
        <p>Leon E. Panetta recites a litany of areas where the government of Iraq and its political leaders have not made the progress crucial to stabilizing Iraq.</p>
        <p>Mr. Panetta seems to see these failures as challenges to be met. But a more realistic view is to see these shortcomings as symptoms that reconciliation is not really possible.</p>
        <p>When an elected government cannot make progress on critical programs to bring peace and stability, one has to question whether there is any will to achieve those goals.</p>
        <p>Orin Hollander  Jamison, Pa., April 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I hope that the Bush administration listens to Leon E. Panetta's recommendations. As the mother of two Iraq war veterans and a friend to several others, I have been watching the current showdown between the president and Congress with a desperation most cannot fathom.</p>
        <p>There was never an exit strategy for the war in Iraq, and without setting benchmarks, we cede our national security to Iraqis.</p>
        <p>If and when President Bush vetoes the Congressional supplemental spending bill, he will be putting politics and pride before our troops, before our national security, before our very future.</p>
        <p>Worst of all, he'll be sentencing more and more of our troops to death because of his stubbornness and failure to grasp realities.</p>
        <p>Maura Satchell  Smyrna, Tenn., April 4, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a member of the Democratic National Veterans and Military Families Council.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Leon E. Panetta's article ought to be burned into the heads of the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>Deadlines and schedules are a fact of life. With the Iraqi government showing such neglect for its own deadlines and schedules, what else should the United States do but make clear that it will not sacrifice its blood and treasure forever?</p>
        <p>Setting a date for withdrawal is only reasonable.</p>
        <p>Victor Chen  New York, April 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''More Than a Feeling'' (editorial, April 4):</p>
        <p>The problem is not that critics of the Iraq war are too ''emotional,'' as President Bush charges. It is that his administration is devoid of emotion.</p>
        <p>The administration and its supporters have tried to pass off fake progress as success in a failing war, but they fail to take into consideration the very real human toll this war is taking.</p>
        <p>An Orwellian nightmare springs from leaders who base decisions only on a bottom line, and this administration is beginning to look more and more like one.</p>
        <p>Matt Lurrie  Forest Hills, Queens, April 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''More Than a Feeling,'' you say that ''President Bush and his advisers have made a lot of ridiculous charges about critics of the war in Iraq: they're unpatriotic, they want the terrorists to win, they don't support the troops, to cite just a few.''</p>
        <p>Fair enough. But the war critics have likewise made a lot of ridiculous charges about Mr. Bush and his team: that they purposely lied to start a war for personal reasons, that they are the real terrorists and so on. Such charges are a daily staple in the news media.</p>
        <p>You also say that war critics whose children are in Iraq are not too emotional to form valid judgments about the war.</p>
        <p>Fine, but then neither are Mr. Bush or Vice President Dick Cheney unqualified to make war decisions just because their own children are not fighting in Iraq, as many critics have charged.</p>
        <p>In short, there are plenty of ridiculous charges on both sides. Shouldn't you also highlight the absurd charges of the war critics when you condemn the absurd charges of war supporters?</p>
        <p>Mark R. Godburn  Sheffield, Mass., April 4, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The ''fantasy version of Iraq'' to which President Bush is ''clinging'' is that of those in the Project for the New American Century who dreamed up the policy of military domination of the Middle East as the way to ensure an oil supply. The dream has become a nightmare that has created a climate and resources for constant terrorism.</p>
        <p>The military operation in Iraq cannot be sustained and is a threat to the stability of oil-producing nations. We need to safeguard only the delivery channels of oil. The dollar and diplomacy, rather than the gun, will best ensure our share of oil.</p>
        <p>The latest reason advanced for staying in Iraq, that dire consequences will result on our departure, is also fantasy. There is no evidence to suggest that neighboring countries would war against each other. Rather, their interest is a brokered peace between Sunnis and Shiites to end a hostility there that the presence of foreign military worsens.</p>
        <p>Connell J. Maguire  Riviera Beach, Fla., April 4, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a retired Navy captain.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I drew two bits of information from ''McCain Wrong on Iraq Security, Merchants Say'' (front page, April 3). The obvious one is: so much for ''Straight Talk'' John McCain.</p>
        <p>The other, of more interest, is that it says something about the ''surge'' by showing what sort of effort would be needed to make Baghdad really safe -- not to mention Iraq as a whole.</p>
        <p>Robert Gelman  Ann Arbor, Mich., April 3, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The only thing missing from the photographs of Senator John McCain's ''stroll'' through the Shorja market in Baghdad was a banner overhead declaring ''Mission Accomplished.''</p>
        <p>Martin E. Cobern  Cheshire, Conn., April 3, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
