<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Met Shows Off Its Hits and Misses</title>
    <meta content="05gala" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/arts/music/05gala.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Opera</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Villazon, Rolando</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Netrebko, Anna</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4DC163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Met Shows Off Its Hits and Misses</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Met Shows Off Its Hits and Misses</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Metropolitan Opera's 40th-anniversary gala on Tuesday gave a reasonably accurate account of what life in the Met's Lincoln Center home has been and what it hasn't been. There were scenes from Puccini's ''Bohème,'' Massenet's ''Manon'' and Donizetti's ''Elisir d'Amore.'' The tenor Rolando Villazón and the soprano Anna Netrebko showed up in all three.</p>
        <p>Good things have happened in 40 years. James Levine has assembled an opera orchestra of remarkable refinement and flexibility. Given a size one and a half to two times that of a normal opera house, the acoustics are better than one might expect. The best singers find the Met an essential destination for their careers. The house has a stage crew of virtuoso efficiency. Sets and costumes are of the highest quality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This gala gave a reasonably accurate account of what life in the Met’s Lincoln Center home has been and what it hasn’t been.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Metropolitan Opera's 40th-anniversary gala on Tuesday gave a reasonably accurate account of what life in the Met's Lincoln Center home has been and what it hasn't been. There were scenes from Puccini's ''Bohème,'' Massenet's ''Manon'' and Donizetti's ''Elisir d'Amore.'' The tenor Rolando Villazón and the soprano Anna Netrebko showed up in all three.</p>
        <p>Good things have happened in 40 years. James Levine has assembled an opera orchestra of remarkable refinement and flexibility. Given a size one and a half to two times that of a normal opera house, the acoustics are better than one might expect. The best singers find the Met an essential destination for their careers. The house has a stage crew of virtuoso efficiency. Sets and costumes are of the highest quality.</p>
        <p>Looks are important here, and that applies to singers. Opera finds itself jostling for public attention and surrounded by the improbable attractiveness of movie stars and television personalities. So here on Tuesday was Ms. Netrebko, a beauty of some celebrity, and Mr. Villazón, with a frail appeal to melt any maternal heart.</p>
        <p>Ms. Netrebko seemed more at home on this big stage. There is a slightly metallic spine to her sound and it helps the voice carry easily in this hall. For better or worse the Met has bred a new kind of singer, one that can penetrate considerable distances and still remain clear and under control. As with the National Football League and its 300-pound linemen, a biological call has been sent out to nature, and nature has responded.</p>
        <p>But not always. Mr. Villazón has a very nice tenor voice, his fastness and looseness with phrasing and tempo notwithstanding. Standing, almost antlike, in the middle of Franco Zeffirelli's oversize set for ''La Bohème,'' however, he pushed uncomfortably. All the singers onstage pushed, fearing (with justification) that if they did not, they would vanish into the scenery. Puccini's subtle, almost chamber-music ensemble in Act I became a shouting match.</p>
        <p>The Zeffirelli scene was an uncomfortable reminder of the new Met's 1966 opening with Samuel Barber's ''Antony and Cleopatra.'' In both instances, medium-size operas were crushed by grandiose productions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villazón sounded lovely in Massenet's St. Sulpice scene, competing nicely with Jean-Pierre Ponnelle's vaulting church interior. Sheer size almost did in the Donizetti, with stage band, chorus and pit orchestra conducted by Bertrand de Billy often dangerously at odds. Mr. Villazón milked ''Una furtiva lagrima'' shamelessly but the audience loved it.</p>
        <p>Adina in ''L'Elisir'' let Ms. Netrebko do what she does well: sing out with strong, commanding technique. It is her singing, not what is behind it, that gets my attention. I found her Mimi in the Puccini and Manon in the Massenet somewhat impersonal, a collection of carefully gathered and well-considered details that never really reached this heart. You can have all of the parts and still not the whole.</p>
        <p>It was nice to find old hands like Samuel Ramey (Count des Grieux) and Paul Plishka (Benoit) onstage. Alessandro Corbelli (Dulcamara) and Monica Yunus (Gianetta) were particularly attractive in ''L'Elisir.'' Mariusz Kwiecien, Oren Gradus, Patrick Carfizzi and Glenn Alpert all did well. Listeners, most dressed to the hilt, had a good time and then went off to dinner upstairs.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
