<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Rivals Share Tangled Playoff Fates</title>
    <meta content="05rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/sports/hockey/05rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DA163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Rivals Share Tangled Playoff Fates</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New York Rivals Share Tangled Playoff Fates</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers will play their final regular-season home game Thursday night, against Montreal, without much thought about the intricate mathematics of the playoff race. What they know is that a victory is the solution. For the past six weeks, as they climbed into contention, the Rangers have known that only their results matter.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers' win-or-else blinders notwithstanding, the Rangers and the Islanders have become oddly entangled in the Eastern Conference playoff race. Now that the two bitter rivals have finished their season series, they can help each other make the playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers’ win-or-else blinders notwithstanding, the Rangers and the Islanders have become ludicrously entangled in the Eastern Conference playoff race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rangers will play their final regular-season home game Thursday night, against Montreal, without much thought about the intricate mathematics of the playoff race. What they know is that a victory is the solution. For the past six weeks, as they climbed into contention, the Rangers have known that only their results matter.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers' win-or-else blinders notwithstanding, the Rangers and the Islanders have become oddly entangled in the Eastern Conference playoff race. Now that the two bitter rivals have finished their season series, they can help each other make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Or, more bizarrely, the Islanders can guarantee the Rangers one of the remaining playoff spots Thursday night while the Rangers are simultaneously eliminating the Islanders. How do you think that would make Islanders fans feel?</p>
        <p>With 92 points and 41 victories in 80 games, the Rangers are in seventh place. The simplest way for them to clinch a playoff berth is by beating eighth-place Montreal. If the Rangers win, they are in. But if the Rangers get only 1 point against the Canadiens, by losing in overtime or a shootout, they can still clinch if the Islanders hold ninth-place Toronto to 1 point.</p>
        <p>And if the Islanders beat Toronto in regulation, the Rangers are in the playoffs no matter what they do against Montreal, because the Maple Leafs would be unable to match the Rangers' point total. If the Islanders win in regulation, and the Rangers lose to Montreal, the Canadiens would then grab the last remaining playoff spot, leaving the Islanders out of the postseason.</p>
        <p>With 86 points and 37 victories, the Islanders can reach the playoffs only if they win their remaining three games and Montreal earns 1 point or no points in its remaining two games.</p>
        <p>So while the Islanders can clinch a spot for the Rangers, the Rangers do not necessarily need the Islanders' help. But the Islanders have to have the assistance of Rangers, starting against Montreal, to keep their uphill quest alive.</p>
        <p>Of course, the Rangers could have clinched a berth and eliminated the Islanders by beating them Tuesday night, but they lost in a shootout, setting up the current tangle.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is, there's not a lot that we've done easy this year,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said. ''This is us. We're going to go out and work our tails off tomorrow night and get ourselves a victory and move on.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers have one game remaining after Montreal, at Pittsburgh on Saturday. But they would like nothing better than to settle their playoff fate at Madison Square Garden, in front of a crowd that watched the Rangers struggle for much of the season.</p>
        <p>After starting 10-11-3 in their first 24 home games, the Rangers have turned it around, going 10-4-2 in their past 16 home games, including 8-1-1 in their past 10. The last four home victories were by a combined score of 21-3.</p>
        <p>The Rangers will also get some reinforcements.</p>
        <p>Fedor Tyutin, the Rangers' steadiest defenseman this season, will return to the lineup after missing 16 games with a knee injury. And forward Marcel Hossa, who is also trying to return from a knee injury, might be back for Saturday's regular-season finale.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
