<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine Says He Will Seek Independent Audit of State's Troubled Pension Fund</title>
    <meta content="05pension" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/05/nyregion/05pension.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0DA163FF936A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine Says He Will Seek Independent Audit of State's Troubled Pension Fund</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Outside Audit Is Promised for New Jersey Pension Fund</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD G. JONES; Mary Williams Walsh contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Walsh, Mary Williams; Jones, Richard G</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine said on Wednesday that he would ask independent auditors to examine state financial records to determine how severely the pension fund for state and local workers has been jeopardized by underfunding.</p>
        <p>The governor's comments, which came during a news conference at the State House, were made in response to an article in The New York Times on Wednesday that described how New Jersey has diverted hundreds of millions of dollars that should have gone into the pension fund.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The audit would examine state financial records to determine how severely the pension fund for state and local workers has been jeopardized by underfunding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine said on Wednesday that he would ask independent auditors to examine state financial records to determine how severely the pension fund for state and local workers has been jeopardized by underfunding.</p>
        <p>The governor's comments, which came during a news conference at the State House, were made in response to an article in The New York Times on Wednesday that described how New Jersey has diverted hundreds of millions of dollars that should have gone into the pension fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine said the state government did not have auditors who were qualified to conduct a thorough examination of the fund, which, with reported assets of about $79 billion, is the nation's ninth-largest public-sector pension fund.</p>
        <p>''We do not have the expertise to do the actuarial assessment; we have to get an outside consultant,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The analysis of state pension records by The Times showed that the state recognized the pension fund's investment gains immediately, but delayed the reporting of losses, used money earmarked for pensions for other purposes like giving aid to poor school districts, and routinely exaggerated how much money it had contributed to the fund.</p>
        <p>In 2005, The Times found, the state reported in various accounts that it had contributed three different amounts into the pension fund for teachers. The actual figure was one of those amounts: zero.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine said on Wednesday that state officials had recently reviewed an audit that found the fund had a deficit of about $25 billion. But some experts have estimated that the shortfall is much larger.</p>
        <p>Whatever the figure is, the governor said, the shortfall must be closed.</p>
        <p>''The fact is we have a huge hole,'' said Mr. Corzine, who has warned of problems with the pension system since taking office 15 months ago. ''It has been created by a failure to deal with the issue, frankly, for the better part of a decade, and I consider it one of our greatest challenges.''</p>
        <p>Aside from the financial questions, Mr. Corzine acknowledged that the state was also reviewing the legal issues surrounding the diversion of money and the inaccurate reporting of contributions. Those practices could run afoul of pension management rules set forth by the Internal Revenue Service and the financial reporting rules of the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>Federal power to regulate state pension management is limited, however. Donald J. Segal, chairman of the American Academy of Actuaries' pension practice council, said yesterday that the group had put state pension funding onto the agenda for its next meeting after reading that New Jersey had repeatedly failed to finance its pension plan as required by state statute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segal said that he did not think New Jersey was the only place where such things had happened, and that the council wanted to discuss what could be done, in the absence of federal pension rules. One possibility, he said, would be to change professional standards, so that actuaries working for governments would be required to speak out if a government was failing to make its required contributions. Now, governmental actuaries cannot do so without breaking confidentiality agreements or risking dismissal.</p>
        <p>Officials with the state's Department of the Treasury have said that they have done nothing illegal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine said that regardless of what legal issues arise -- or penalties the state might face -- New Jersey must find new ways to fill the pension deficit. ''Whatever the outcome ultimately of someone reviewing this under federal I.R.S. regulations, we have a responsibility to close that gap,'' he said. ''We're trying to take steps on that.''</p>
        <p>The question of the solvency of state's pension fund is a result of years of questionable practices by Republican and Democratic legislators and former governors.</p>
        <p>State Senator Leonard Lance, the Republican minority leader from Hunterdon County who is a longtime advocate of greater transparency in the government's financial dealings, called for ''an immediate and public accounting.'' He called on the state treasurer, Bradley I. Abelow, and the head of the Division of Pensions and Benefits, Frederick J. Beaver, to appear before the Senate Budget and Appropriations Committee.</p>
        <p>''I am deeply disturbed, but not surprised, by media reports that have revealed the scope of the present deficit and potential long-term insolvency of the state's pension fund,'' Mr. Lance said.</p>
        <p>The Senate president, Richard J. Codey, who was Mr. Corzine's predecessor as interim governor for 18 months, noted that the state contributed more to the fund in 2006 -- about $1.1 billion -- than at any other time in recent years. That amount still fell short, however, of the required contributions for that year, $2.2 billion. Of that amount, $1.6 billion was to have been contributed by the state and the rest by local governments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey said he was confident that Mr. Corzine would begin to put the pension system back on track.</p>
        <p>''We're no different than a whole host of states that are out there,'' said Mr. Codey, a Democrat from Essex County. ''When I was governor we used to say a weekly novena that the stock market would go up'' -- and increase the fund's value -- ''but I don't think any retiree has to worry. We're nowhere near that point.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
