<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Citigroup Adds Hedge Fund and Its Leader</title>
    <meta content="14bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/business/14bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070417T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Old Lane Partners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pandit, Vikram S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramakrishnan, Guru</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EFDF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Citigroup Adds Hedge Fund and Its Leader</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Citigroup Adds Hedge Fund and Its Leader</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Citi7</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For nearly a year, Charles O. Prince III had been courting a former top Morgan Stanley investment banker. Yesterday, he got his man -- Vikram S. Pandit, who will head Citigroup's alternative investments group. But Mr. Prince may be paying a steep price.</p>
        <p>Citigroup said that Mr. Pandit would soon be running the division as part of a deal to buy Old Lane Partners -- the investment fund that Mr. Pandit helped found 13 months ago -- for a price that could exceed $800 million. While the terms were not disclosed, the apparent large premium for a hedge fund with a short and unimpressive track record has raised eyebrows from London to Greenwich, Conn., not to mention on Wall Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For nearly a year, Charles O. Prince III had been courting a former top Morgan Stanley investment banker. Yesterday, he got his man  Vikram S. Pandit, who will head Citigroup’s alternative investments group. But Mr. Prince may be paying a steep price.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For nearly a year, Charles O. Prince III had been courting a former top Morgan Stanley investment banker. Yesterday, he got his man -- Vikram S. Pandit, who will head Citigroup's alternative investments group. But Mr. Prince may be paying a steep price.</p>
        <p>Citigroup said that Mr. Pandit would soon be running the division as part of a deal to buy Old Lane Partners -- the investment fund that Mr. Pandit helped found 13 months ago -- for a price that could exceed $800 million. While the terms were not disclosed, the apparent large premium for a hedge fund with a short and unimpressive track record has raised eyebrows from London to Greenwich, Conn., not to mention on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Even with just a small stake, Mr. Pandit could personally reap several hundred million dollars. His 16 partners at Old Lane could net tens of millions of dollars more.</p>
        <p>''It's the equivalent of buying the New York Knicks to have dinner with Patrick Ewing,'' said Don Putnam, the founder of Grail Partners, a boutique merchant bank. ''Most of the Street will read this transaction for what it is: an institution that is desperately short of competent management bringing in someone from outside.''</p>
        <p>But Robert E. Rubin, the former Treasury secretary who is chairman of Citigroup's executive committee, brushed off the notion that the company was filling a talent gap. He said the search had nothing to do with bolstering Citigroup's succession plans.</p>
        <p>He even countered with his own sports analogy. ''It's like buying the 1927 New York Yankees,'' Mr. Rubin said, referring to a World Series team that included Babe Ruth and Lou Gehrig.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pandit, a 50-year-old banker with a Ph.D in engineering, said he was lured by the opportunity to build a business and take advantage of Citigroup's global network and giant balance sheet.</p>
        <p>When asked about any ambitions for one day taking over for Mr. Prince, the question was quickly dismissed: ''Let me be blunt: none,'' he said. ''I enjoy doing what we are doing. I want to enjoy doing it in a slightly different format than we did before.''</p>
        <p>The deal is expected to close in the third quarter of this year, and could slightly reduce earnings per share in the first year or two -- something that Mr. Prince has hoped to avoid.</p>
        <p>The agreement with Mr. Pandit comes as Mr. Prince is under pressure from investors to improve the bank's performance and rein in expenses. This week, he announced plans for a broad overhaul that will cut 17,000 jobs.</p>
        <p>Old Lane will operate as part of Citigroup's alternative investment group, the smallest of Citigroup's four major businesses. With hedge funds, private equity and real estate units, the division currently manages about $54.5 billion, including roughly $11 billion of Citigroup's own money. Old Lane has about $4.5 billion in assets under management and a fund focused on investments in India. Many decisions on integrating the businesses have not yet been made.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pandit will join Mr. Prince's senior management team, filling a spot that has been left open since Michael A. Carpenter left the bank in March 2006. Several of Mr. Pandit's Old Lane partners will take top leadership positions within the alternative investment group. John Havens, a former Morgan Stanley equities head, will serve as president of the entire division; Guru Ramakrishnan, a former top trader at Morgan Stanley, will run the Old Lane investment fund.</p>
        <p>Dean S. Barr, the head of the group's hedge fund investments, will remain in his post. Some had once considered him a contender to head the alternative investment group.</p>
        <p>Nearly two years ago, Mr. Pandit left Morgan Stanley after being passed over for a promotion that would have put him in line to succeed the chief executive then, Philip J. Purcell. At Citigroup, he may now get a second chance.</p>
        <p>Last year, the company hired PrinceGoldsmith, a boutique executive recruiting firm specializing in financial services, to conduct the search, along with one to identify a new financial chief. And with Mr. Rubin pulling for a strong leader to run the unit -- a potential earnings powerhouse but currently a laggard -- the process took several twists and turns.</p>
        <p>The search wound up, Mr. Rubin said, largely where it started. Early on in the process, Citigroup reached out to Mr. Pandit. He passed at the time.</p>
        <p>On Wall Street, of course, everything has a price.</p>
        <p>This time around, Mr. Pandit said, he was feeling ''very, very comfortable with the leadership team'' at Citigroup, which led him to agree to the deal.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 17, 2007, Tuesday  An article in Business Day on Saturday about Citigroup's acquisition of a hedge fund and the hiring of its leader, Vikram S. Pandit, misstated Mr. Pandit's educational background. He has a Ph.D. in finance, not in engineering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 17, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Saturday about Citigroup's acquisition of a hedge fund and the hiring of its leader, Vikram S. Pandit, misstated Mr. Pandit's educational background. He has a Ph.D. in finance, not in engineering.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
