<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Snap Judgments of Israel, More Than Words Can Say</title>
    <meta content="14date" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/arts/design/14date.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Jewish Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2D6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Snap Judgments of Israel, More Than Words Can Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Snap Judgments of Israel, More Than Words Can Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOLLAND COTTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotter, Holland</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jewish Museum is probably not the first place you would look for a tough but impartial critique of Arab-Israeli politics. And you don't find one in ''Dateline Israel: New Photography and Video Art,'' a survey of recent art that takes Israel as its subject.</p>
        <p>The all but total absence of Palestinians -- there's one; apparently others were invited but declined -- among the two dozen artists is an obvious problem, particularly as several non-Israelis from Europe and America are included. Beyond that, though, and despite some excellent work, there is the cautious, make-nice spirit of the show. It feels less like a critical report on pressing issues than a sightseeing tour with some tensions and bumps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jewish Museum is probably not the first place you would look for a tough but impartial critique of Arab-Israeli politics. And you don’t find one in “Dateline Israel.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Jewish Museum is probably not the first place you would look for a tough but impartial critique of Arab-Israeli politics. And you don't find one in ''Dateline Israel: New Photography and Video Art,'' a survey of recent art that takes Israel as its subject.</p>
        <p>The all but total absence of Palestinians -- there's one; apparently others were invited but declined -- among the two dozen artists is an obvious problem, particularly as several non-Israelis from Europe and America are included. Beyond that, though, and despite some excellent work, there is the cautious, make-nice spirit of the show. It feels less like a critical report on pressing issues than a sightseeing tour with some tensions and bumps.</p>
        <p>That said, it's a timely and intelligent tour as conducted by Susan Tumarkin Goodman, the Jewish Museum senior curator responsible for a series of one-per-decade surveys of new art from Israel. (The last was in 1997.) The non-Israeli voices she has added to this edition might be expected to bring an outsider perspective to the mix. Some do, some don't.</p>
        <p>A gold-tinted aerial view of Tel Aviv by the German-born photographer Wolfgang Tillmans starts the installation off with a splash of postcard color, but not much else. Wim Wenders's ''Jerusalem Seen From the Mount of Olives,'' a distant shot of the Dome of the Rock with a foreground view of a junk-strewn graveyard, at least comes with an idea: when the dead awaken at the end of time, trash is the first thing they'll see. But it's an easy idea, a generic consumerist dig.</p>
        <p>''Painting the Divide (Jerusalem),'' by the British artist Mark Wallinger, gets a little closer to what makes modern Israel distinctive as the vital but driven and conflicted place it is. In digital prints mounted as folding screens, Mr. Wallinger uses architectural forms to demonstrate the country's interlocked Jewish, Muslim and Christian strata, a fundamental integration beneath the splintering that makes the news.</p>
        <p>That splintering is the central fact of ''Wall,'' a film by the British artist Catherine Yass, which is basically a continuous, traveling close-up pan of the concrete security barrier that has separated Israel from the West Bank since the second intifada of 2000. Ms. Yass approaches the barrier with a kind of physical intimacy, like a devotee at the Western Wall, only to raise the question of whether the Israeli-built structure is protective or aggressive, freeing or imprisoning. (In the catalog, she makes a provocative comparison with Richard Serra's barrierlike sculptures.)</p>
        <p>Significantly, the show's lone Palestinian artist, Noel Jabbour, also photographs the security wall, but from afar, emphasizing not its height but its extent. In her three-panel picture, it snakes through villages and around olive groves and disappears over hills. It could extend to the horizon. There's no end in sight.</p>
        <p>Unlike Ms. Yass, Ms. Dabbour doesn't theatricalize her subject. She lets it stand as a hard sociopolitical fact, one she lives with every day. And it's tempting to say that if there is a single characteristic distinguishing the ''insider'' from the ''outsider'' eye, this kind of expressive neutrality might be it.</p>
        <p>But even apparently objective pictures deliver time-released dramas. In shots of beaches near Gaza and Tel Aviv by the Israeli artist Guy Raz, two lifeguard stands look pretty much alike -- until you notice that they fly different flags, one Israeli and the other Palestinian. Suddenly they become defensive watchtowers. And if you begin to sense that a picture-perfect ''typical'' Arab village in a photograph by Yaron Leshem feels somehow a little off, you would be right. The village is a simulation designed by the Israeli Army to train soldiers.</p>
        <p>Straightforward landscape shots by Igael Shemtov and Sharon Ya'ari become, on inspection, records of environmental damage. The portraits of ancient trees in Ori Gersht's beautiful ''Ghost-Olive'' series could be taken this way too, but also in other ways, as symbols of Israel and emblems of peace dissolving to dust before our eyes.</p>
        <p>Certain portraits aren't portraits at first. In a film by Boaz Arad and Miki Kratsman, crowds of men with bundles trudge by the stationary camera. Only after we learn, from a wall label, that they are Palestinian workers making their daily return home through a checkpoint do they become individuals with identities and histories.</p>
        <p>Studio portraits afford some of the show's most intriguing and perplexing moments. The Dutch artist Rineke Dijkstra photographed a young Israeli woman named Abigail twice, first in 1999 and then a year later, after she had joined the army. Is there a detectable change between the sitter wearing a halter top in the earlier picture and the one in uniform? Has she grown leaner and less dreamy, more confident, more guarded, tougher? And if so, is this good? Necessary?</p>
        <p>Informal portraits by the American photographer Gillian Laub, who has contributed work to The New York Times, are fleshed out with brief statements by the sitters. A young man named Yussie says that he returned to Jerusalem from the United States because his ''heart and soul are in Israel,'' though with his CD player and cool shades, he might be in America still.</p>
        <p>Ten-year-old Palestinian twin sisters speak fondly of Jewish neighbors. ''The Jews and Arabs fight, but we are the same,'' one says. ''They fight about nonsense.'' Twin Israeli teenagers, who recently joined the army, speak of their newfound commitment to their country, and of their fears for it. ''These aren't such good days for Israel,'' they say. ''The future is uncertain.''</p>
        <p>But these provocative, needling images are embedded in a soft news story, an exhibition that refrains from naming fears or the concrete reasons for fear. It sticks to package-tour generalities, skirting the difficult arguments and debates that the show's subject would seem to demand.</p>
        <p>Not all the work lacks urgency. Some of it acknowledges the dangers that shadow life and politics in the Middle East -- and, in turn, the world beyond. We find sharp rumblings of them in Michal Heiman's archival photographs of bloody body parts; in Orit Raff's pictures of Israeli baking ovens that trigger Holocaust associations; in Pavel Wolberg's shots of soldiers breaking up protests on the West Bank; and in a piece called ''Blinking'' by Motti Mizrachi composed of a year's worth of news photographs -- from the beginning of the 2000 intifada to the destruction of the twin towers -- digitally compressed into pretty, colorful, all-but abstract strips. Each strip is a document of a recent historical event that has been rendered nearly unseeable, unanalyzable, uncorrectible.</p>
        <p>Yael Bartana's ''Trembling Times'' hints at what a more exacting and stimulating show might have felt like. It is a video of cars on a highway near Tel Aviv, shot in 2001 on Israel's government-created annual Day of Remembrance for the war dead. On that day, at the sound of sirens, all Israelis are expected to stop and observe two minutes of memorial silence.</p>
        <p>The video doesn't explain any of this. We see cars suddenly slow to a crawl, then come to a standstill, as if confronted with an accident or a barrier. In its pacing the film is the visual equivalent of a dirge, but it is also a study in the ambivalent force of collective ritual, in this case a politically loaded one, imposed from above. The cars look robotic. Random traffic becomes, at a signal, automatically, a funeral procession. But a funeral for whom, for the dead of which wars, whose wars? Wars past, present or to come?</p>
        <p>About halfway though the six-minute video, drivers begin to emerge from the cars. They stand beside them, as if waiting for directions, demanding reasons for the delay, asking ''What's going on here, anyway?'' Or at least that's the question they should be asking. And the show should be asking it, too. It should be taking the risk of proposing bold and critical, if conditional, answers.</p>
        <p>''Dateline Israel: New Photography and Video Art'' is on view through Aug. 5 at the Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street; (212) 423-3271.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
