<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woman in Gang Assault Trial Says Man Started the Fight</title>
    <meta content="14assault" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/nyregion/14assault.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Greenwich Village (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E7DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woman in Gang Assault Trial Says Man Started the Fight</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Woman in Gang Assault Trial Says Man Started the Fight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the independent filmmaker told it, he made an innocuous remark, on the order of ''Hi, how're you doing?'' to a pretty woman walking by, and inexplicably found himself spat at, pummeled and stabbed by a pack of marauding lesbians. But one of the lesbians, who is charged with attempted murder, took the witness stand in a Manhattan courtroom yesterday and told a different version of the story, in which the man was a raunchy, cigarette-throwing aggressor.</p>
        <p>The filmmaker, Dwayne Buckle, 29, started the fight, said the defendant, Patreese Johnson, 19, by calling out, ''Let me get some of that,'' when Ms. Johnson and six friends passed by him last August as he sat on a fire hydrant outside a movie theater in Greenwich Village.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the women charged with attempted murder said the man who she attacked was a raunchy, cigarette-throwing aggressor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the independent filmmaker told it, he made an innocuous remark, on the order of ''Hi, how're you doing?'' to a pretty woman walking by, and inexplicably found himself spat at, pummeled and stabbed by a pack of marauding lesbians. But one of the lesbians, who is charged with attempted murder, took the witness stand in a Manhattan courtroom yesterday and told a different version of the story, in which the man was a raunchy, cigarette-throwing aggressor.</p>
        <p>The filmmaker, Dwayne Buckle, 29, started the fight, said the defendant, Patreese Johnson, 19, by calling out, ''Let me get some of that,'' when Ms. Johnson and six friends passed by him last August as he sat on a fire hydrant outside a movie theater in Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnson, 4-foot-11 and slight, wearing tortoise-shell glasses, said that at first she thought that Mr. Buckle, who ''looked like a bum,'' was thirsty and wanted some soda. She said she realized her mistake when ''he pointed to my lower area between my legs.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnson said she politely replied, ''No thank you, I'm not interested in that.''</p>
        <p>At that, she said, Mr. Buckle began calling the women a derogatory word for lesbians and boasted that he could have sex with them -- he used a cruder word -- and make them straight.</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnson said that she had been carrying a steak knife from her home because she lives in Newark and needed protection. She said she pulled her knife on that day only because Mr. Buckle had jumped on top of her friend Renata Hill, 25, one of three co-defendants charged with gang assault, and was throttling her. Ms. Johnson said she was afraid that her friend ''might die.''</p>
        <p>The other women on trial are Terrain Dandridge, 20, and Venice Brown, 19. All are from New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnson also said that she had given a statement to the police in which she said, ''I admit I did cut him one time for my own safety.'' But yesterday in State Supreme Court, she said she was not sure whether she had cut Mr. Buckle.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors have said the women recruited several men to help them attack Mr. Buckle, while defense lawyers say that the men were good Samaritans who stepped in on their own, and that one of them had stabbed Mr. Buckle.</p>
        <p>Christopher O'Hare, a police officer, said under cross-examination on Thursday that the police had looked for two male witnesses who were described as getting involved in the altercation at the very end.</p>
        <p>But, he told a defense lawyer, Kevin G. Roe, ''We've never been able to apprehend them.''</p>
        <p>In an interview with The New York Post from his hospital bed last August, Mr. Buckle, who has spent most of his career as a sound engineer, said he was the victim of ''a hate crime against a straight man.''</p>
        <p>But on Wednesday, on the first day of testimony in the trial, he stayed away from sexual politics and said he could not remember which of the women was the one he thought was pretty.</p>
        <p>He said he was outside the Independent Film Center in Greenwich Village, promoting his latest film, around 1:45 a.m. on Aug. 18 when the women walked by. Three of the seven have pleaded guilty to attempted assault and have been sentenced to six months in jail.</p>
        <p>He said he had called one of the woman an elephant and told another that she looked like a man. But apart from that, he said, he only passively defended himself by putting his hands in front of his face when the women started beating him.</p>
        <p>The defense contends that a blurry videotape made by a camera at the movie theater shows Mr. Johnson with his hands around the neck of a woman lying underneath him.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor, Sharon Laveson, introduced Ms. Johnson's steak knife into evidence by pulling it out of a box with a bright orange biohazard sticker on it. A detective and a police officer serving as witnesses examined it wearing latex gloves. But the detective said, under cross-examination by the defense, that he had not seen any blood on the knife when he retrieved it from under a car on the night of the stabbing.</p>
        <p>Why, then, was he wearing gloves to handle it on the witness stand, a defense lawyer asked. ''It's a precaution, sir,'' the detective replied.</p>
        <p>''What about germs?'' asked Justice Edward J. McLaughlin, as jurors doubled over laughing. ''You see any germs?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
