<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prokofiev's Take on Pushkin's Czar, Revealed at Last</title>
    <meta content="14godu" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/arts/music/14godu.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Princeton University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Prokofiev, Sergei</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2D6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prokofiev's Take on Pushkin's Czar, Revealed at Last</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Prokofiev’s Take on Pushkin’s Czar, Revealed at Last</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN SCHWEITZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schweitzer, Vivien</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON, N.J., April 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sergei Prokofiev and Vsevolod Meyerhold, the Russian stage director, scorned Modest Mussorgsky's music for his opera ''Boris Godunov.'' The opera was based on Aleksandr Pushkin's play about Godunov, the 16th-century czar, and they hoped to present what they believed would be a more accurate representation of Pushkin's vision with a 1936 staging featuring a new score by Prokofiev.</p>
        <p>But they never got the chance. Meyerhold ran afoul of Stalin and (like Pushkin) was shot, and the fruits of the Meyerhold-Prokofiev collaboration languished in the Russian State Archive of Literature and Art in Moscow until recently. The work finally had its world premiere on Thursday here at the Roger S. Berlind Theater at Princeton University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty-five fragments of orchestral and vocal music are woven into “Boris Godunov” like carefully rationed accents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sergei Prokofiev and Vsevolod Meyerhold, the Russian stage director, scorned Modest Mussorgsky's music for his opera ''Boris Godunov.'' The opera was based on Aleksandr Pushkin's play about Godunov, the 16th-century czar, and they hoped to present what they believed would be a more accurate representation of Pushkin's vision with a 1936 staging featuring a new score by Prokofiev.</p>
        <p>But they never got the chance. Meyerhold ran afoul of Stalin and (like Pushkin) was shot, and the fruits of the Meyerhold-Prokofiev collaboration languished in the Russian State Archive of Literature and Art in Moscow until recently. The work finally had its world premiere on Thursday here at the Roger S. Berlind Theater at Princeton University.</p>
        <p>Mussorgsky's music for ''Boris Godunov,'' or at least Rimsky Korsakov's familiar and plush re-orchestration of the original, is as luxuriant as the golden domes of an Orthodox church. Like Pushkin before him, Mussorgsky had his own artistic battles with the censors, and the cuts and revisions he made to mollify them ended up mitigating the comic elements and adding a loftier tone to his opera.</p>
        <p>Meyerhold and Prokofiev wanted to restore the lighter, comic aspects of Pushkin's ''Boris Godunov'' that were lost in the stirring, emotive opera score, whose music is sometimes so guilt-laden that even a casual listener can start to feel penitent.</p>
        <p>Prokofiev was adept at collaborating with directors, as demonstrated by his gripping soundtrack to Sergei Eisenstein's ''Alexander Nevsky.'' But whereas that score stands alone as an orchestral work, the score to ''Boris Godunov'' is very much incidental music, which is what the composer and director intended it to be.</p>
        <p>Twenty-five fragments of orchestral and vocal music (done well by members of the Princeton University Glee Club and Orchestra) are woven into the drama like carefully rationed accents, which befits Meyerhold's spare and modern production and emphasizes both the comic and weighty aspects of Pushkin's play. There are long periods with no music; when it appears, it plays a supporting role to Pushkin's lyrical text, performed here in a vital new translation by Antony Wood.</p>
        <p>During wordless behind-the-scenes choruses at the beginning and end of the play, the singers repeat one-syllable vowels with increasing intensity to denote the stirring frustrations of the Russian people. Other scenes feature the widow Ksenia (Boris's daughter) singing a simple, melancholy lament, and irreverent, drunken monks (who did not amuse Pushkin's censors) singing liturgical music set to cheeky lyrics.</p>
        <p>The composer Peter Westergaard, an emeritus professor of music at Princeton, wrote music for one scene Prokofiev did not complete: an effective paraphrase of Russian liturgical chant to heighten the drama while the young monk Grigory Otrepiev begins to lust after Godunov's throne.</p>
        <p>An amusing multicultural battle scene is boosted by a carnival-like brass band and fife and drum, resulting in a cacophony befitting the chaos onstage and in the audience, as the actors romp in the aisles. As in Mussorgsky's opera, there is eerie music for a Holy Fool. A Hollywood-style amoroso is the lighthearted musical backdrop over which Grigory tries to woo the haughty Polish princess, Marina.</p>
        <p>The Polish ball is one of the most visually striking scenes in the staging, which features floor-to-ceiling spaghettilike cords that encourage the actors (all Princeton undergraduates) to adopt fully Meyerhold's intensely physical style of acting. Orchestra musicians in fanciful wigs are seated behind a multilayered red grid, against which the brightly colored round skirts of the dancers whirling to a Tchaikovsky-like waltz and a polonaise intersect like circles and lines in a Malevich painting.</p>
        <p>While perhaps a new, essential Prokofiev work was not revealed with this premiere, it unearthed a fascinating collaboration between important artists in a staging Pushkin would have doubtless enjoyed.</p>
        <p>The final performances of ''Boris Godunov'' are today at the Roger S. Berlind Theater, 91 University Place, Princeton, N.J.; (609) 258-2787. Tickets are sold out.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
