<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amaker Brings Baggage To Harvard</title>
    <meta content="14harvard" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/sports/ncaabasketball/14harvard.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Harvard University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Michigan</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Amaker, Tommy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E5DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amaker Brings Baggage To Harvard</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amaker Brings Baggage to Harvard</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harvard's director of athletics, Robert L. Scalise, introduced Tommy Amaker as the men's basketball coach Friday with a nod to Amaker's credentials, telling a room packed with reporters and alumni about Amaker's 19 postseason appearances in 23 years as a college player, assistant coach and head coach.</p>
        <p>But when Amaker arrived at the lectern moments later, he reminded everyone of the baggage he brings to the job.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harvard’s new basketball coach Tommy Amaker restored the reputation of Michigan’s basketball program, but was fired for his failure to guide the Wolverines to the N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Harvard's director of athletics, Robert L. Scalise, introduced Tommy Amaker as the men's basketball coach Friday with a nod to Amaker's credentials, telling a room packed with reporters and alumni about Amaker's 19 postseason appearances in 23 years as a college player, assistant coach and head coach.</p>
        <p>But when Amaker arrived at the lectern moments later, he reminded everyone of the baggage he brings to the job.</p>
        <p>''Bob, you mentioned so many wonderful things that I have been a part of, and I'm truly thankful for your math there with all the postseasons,'' Amaker said. ''You omitted the fact that I've been fired.''</p>
        <p>Amaker's self-deprecating humor was well received. The people who crowded the room, which overlooked Harvard's football stadium, erupted with laughter.</p>
        <p>Amaker was fired by Michigan on March 16 after six seasons. He restored the reputation of Michigan's basketball program, which was reeling from N.C.A.A. sanctions when he arrived in Ann Arbor. But it was Amaker's postseason record, especially his failure to guide the Wolverines to the N.C.A.A. tournament, that led to his dismissal.</p>
        <p>Amaker, the only African-American among Harvard's 32 head coaches, has joined a program in which the pressure to win is not nearly as intense. Football and men's ice hockey are the top sports at Harvard, and basketball games hardly ever sell out despite an arena that holds only 2,000 spectators. Harvard has never won the Ivy League title. The league began play in 1955.</p>
        <p>''The best thing we can do to turn anything around is to have success,'' Amaker said, although he was vague when he was asked how he would define success at Harvard. He added: ''Our standard will be an internal guideline for us that we'll make and will be realistic for who we are.''</p>
        <p>Success, the way most big-time college basketball programs view it, has rarely come Amaker's way as a head coach. He joined Seton Hall in 1997 and guided the Pirates to three N.I.T. appearances and a berth in the Round of 16 in the N.C.A.A. tournament. He was criticized for taking the Michigan job only days after telling the news media that he intended to stay at Seton Hall.</p>
        <p>At Michigan, Amaker won the N.I.T. title in 2004, but the Wolverines were eliminated in the second round of that tournament this season.</p>
        <p>Harvard would probably be thrilled to appear in the N.I.T., and it is already delighted with its new coach. Scalise said Amaker's experience and pedigree were ''second to none in college basketball.'' But at Michigan, Amaker was sometimes viewed as being too principled to run a major college program.</p>
        <p>''If that's the speculation, then I'll take it every day of the week and twice on Sunday,'' Amaker said, adding that he never felt the need to compromise his principles while at Michigan.</p>
        <p>Amaker played collegiate basketball at Duke in the 1980s, and was an assistant coach for the Blue Devils from 1988 to 1997. Duke assistants are frequently glamorized because of their association with Coach Mike Krzyzewski, who has won three national titles. But like other former Krzyzewski assistants, such as Quin Snyder and Bob Bender, Amaker has had difficulty succeeding as a head coach.</p>
        <p>Noting the expectations that come with being a former Duke assistant, Amaker said, ''I think it's a tough business that we're in.''</p>
        <p>Harvard will play host to Michigan next season, a game tentatively set for Dec. 1. Michigan defeated Harvard, 82-50, in Ann Arbor last November. Amaker said that at that time, he never dreamed of coaching at Harvard. On Friday, he said he would be content with never coaching anywhere else.</p>
        <p>Amaker's wife, Stephanie Pinder-Amaker, was at his side Friday. She was an associate dean of students at Michigan, and Amaker said she was looking forward to new career opportunities.</p>
        <p>With 41 varsity programs, Harvard has the most extensive Division I athletic department in the nation. But it plays in a conference that does not allow athletic scholarships. So recruiting will present new challenges for Amaker.</p>
        <p>Amaker already has a recruiting pitch in mind that no other university in the nation will be able to make.</p>
        <p>''This is considered, arguably, the finest institution,'' he said. ''With this big brand name that we have at Harvard, I'm excited to see the opportunity we have to go find kids that would like to be a part of this.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
