<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Isn't Saltwater Under the Bridge</title>
    <meta content="14sailing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/sports/othersports/14sailing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SAILING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Isn't Saltwater Under the Bridge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It Isn’t Saltwater Under the Bridge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>VALENCIA, Spain</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grant Dalton was on the shore and watching on television as Team New Zealand shattered equipment and a country's illusions during the last America's Cup.</p>
        <p>Dean Barker, the skipper, was on board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After four intense years of fund-raising and match racing, Grant Dalton and Dean Barker are ready to start Team New Zealand’s national rehabilitation project in earnest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Grant Dalton was on the shore and watching on television as Team New Zealand shattered equipment and a country's illusions during the last America's Cup.</p>
        <p>Dean Barker, the skipper, was on board.</p>
        <p>But their reaction was the same: This was not the way for a great sailing nation to leave yachting's premier competition.</p>
        <p>''As a Kiwi, not just a yachtsman, it was really hard to watch,'' Dalton said.</p>
        <p>Within weeks, Dalton, one of the world's most successful around-the-world racers, agreed to take charge of New Zealand's next syndicate, and one of the first personnel moves he made was to tell Barker that, despite all the water under the bridge and on the deck, he wanted him to return as the helmsman.</p>
        <p>Four intense years of fund-raising and match racing later, Dalton and Barker are ready Monday to start their national rehabilitation project in earnest. Financial necessity dictates that the syndicate's official name is Emirates Team New Zealand. Competitive necessity dictates that two well-regarded Americans -- the tactician Terry Hutchinson and the navigator Kevin Hall -- are key elements of the after guard, the nautical term for a crew's brain trust.</p>
        <p>But in an event brimming with Kiwis (there are more than 200 scattered among the 12 syndicates in Auckland, New Zealand), this is still the Kiwis' team. Although Team New Zealand lacks the financial resources as some of its rivals, it has no shortage of sailing resources and belongs on the short list of yachts to challenge Alinghi in the America's Cup in June.</p>
        <p>''When you talk to a lot of people who have been on the receiving end of a bad defeat in whatever sport or pursuit, I think the lessons you learn from that are probably going to be far greater than from any win,'' Barker said recently.</p>
        <p>''If I'm ever struggling for motivation to get out of bed, you don't have to think back too far. I've enjoyed the thrills of victory and suffered the effects of defeat, and I know which one I prefer.''</p>
        <p>Things went wrong in Barker's home, Auckland, in February 2003, when he and his teammates were keelhauled by Barker's mentor, Russell Coutts, and by their own technical and tactical gaffes. Coutts, an Aucklander who had jumped ship to the Swiss-based Alinghi for a considerable profit, ended up driving Alinghi to a 5-0 sweep in the America's Cup.</p>
        <p>It was a triumph for the mercenary spirit more than a triumph for Swiss ingenuity, but what rubbed saltwater into New Zealand's wounds were the humiliations that accompanied the sweep.</p>
        <p>In the opening race, in rougher-than-expected conditions, New Zealand's boat took on so much water that the crew was reduced to bailing with a blue plastic bucket intended for use in the latrine.</p>
        <p>For a team with high-tech dreams that had gambled on a revolutionary hull appendage, this was a low-tech humiliation. And there would be more. In Race 4, the boat's mast snapped. In Race 5, its spinnaker pole broke.</p>
        <p>There would be no Race 6.</p>
        <p>''Their confidence was knocked terribly,'' Dalton said. ''And me coming in, pushing guys down the street left, right and center was even more destabilizing, because it was a question of, 'Who the hell's next?' So we had to move pretty quickly to get past that phase to rebuild.''</p>
        <p>Most important, they had to find the money in a climate in which skepticism was the prevailing sentiment. But Dalton, a straight-talking sailor untainted by the defeat, turned out to be the right messenger, even if he came under some scrutiny from other potential syndicates when he accepted a multimillion-dollar, interest-free loan from Ernesto Bertarelli, the head of Alinghi and the man who had snatched Coutts and his lieutenants away.</p>
        <p>Bertarelli wanted to ensure that the Kiwis did not miss the party in Valencia, which at that stage was short of high-profile challengers. ''I've always viewed that Bertarelli's money is as good as anyone else's,'' Dalton said at the time.</p>
        <p>That was not all he said. He also called Dennis Conner ''fat'' after Conner criticized the loan. But Dalton eventually repaid the loan on his own. ''A lot of the people who came onto our team initially were coming on to a hope,'' Dalton said. ''They believed in the brand and what we were trying to achieve: little guy against the big guy.''</p>
        <p>Dalton says his team now has a satisfactory budget. ''People are close when they say it's around 80 million U.S.,'' Dalton said.</p>
        <p>That is still less than half of what he estimates BMW Oracle Racing is spending.</p>
        <p>Dalton negotiated a lead sponsorship with Fly Emirates, the airline based in Dubai, United Arab Emirates, in 2004, but he has also negotiated dozens of minor sponsorships with New Zealand companies and some restaurants.</p>
        <p>What got Dalton to this point was offshore racing and an acumen for crunching budgets: no surprise considering that he once worked as an accountant before sailing began to pay his bills. He has raced around the world seven times, crewing on one Whitbread winner and skippering another. He also won The Race, a flat-out sprint around the planet in a multihull that he and his crew completed in 2001 in a record time of 62 days 7 hours.</p>
        <p>But the America's Cup remained unfamiliar territory for Dalton, whose biggest quibble with Valencia is the dust that can blow through the port and into eyes and equipment. Technically, this is not his first Cup: He was part of the New Zealand challenger in 1987 but was not chosen by the young skipper Chris Dickson to be part of the sailing team. But Dalton, now 49, has used that slight for fuel over the past two decades, and he and Dickson's BMW Oracle Racing Team are expected to lock egos and expertise on a regular basis over the next two months.</p>
        <p>Both men will sail in the competition, but while Dickson steers his boat, Dalton will often take on the role of a sewerman and pack and unpack sails in the shadows below deck.</p>
        <p>Dalton is actively cultivating the underdog's role, even if New Zealanders have dominated the America's Cup since 1995, when Peter Blake's team swept to victory in San Diego with Coutts at the helm.</p>
        <p>Dalton knew Blake well and, like Blake, who was murdered by bandits on his boat in Brazil in 2001, Dalton is trying to make the transition from sailing between continents to sailing around buoys.</p>
        <p>''In a round-the-world race, it's bloody frightening when you line up on the start line and you're not quite sure how quick the other guy will be, because it's an awful long way around the world when you're slow,'' Dalton said. ''Here at least you kind of have a feel from last year's racing where everybody is.''</p>
        <p>With the nationality rules no longer in effect in the Cup, because of Alinghi's decision to eliminate them, the syndicates have been free to hire whomever they please, which means they have been free to hire plenty of New Zealanders. The majority of the racing team at BMW Oracle are New Zealanders, and like Dalton's team, they also trained and boat tested in Auckland during the Northern Hemisphere winter.</p>
        <p>Dalton has also pushed the envelope in training: intentionally blowing out several spinnakers to learn the limits of his two boats' design.</p>
        <p>After what happened in 2003, a Kiwi can never be too certain that his team and equipment can handle the pressures.</p>
        <p>''It couldn't end that way,'' Dalton said.</p>
        <p>SAILING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
