<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weather Becomes a Prominent Player</title>
    <meta content="14indians" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE7DC103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weather Becomes a Prominent Player</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY; Ben Shpigel and David Picker contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was chilly in Cleveland yesterday afternoon, but Bob DiBiasio, the vice president for public relations for the Indians, said the sun was shining. DiBiasio had not seen any kind of consistent sunshine in a while, especially on a day when the Indians were scheduled to play a home game.</p>
        <p>''It's a beautiful sight,'' he said. The Indians returned to Jacobs Field to play the Chicago White Sox last night, hoping that the snow that turned them into vagabonds this week was not about to return. There was no guarantee that the cold weather would at least remain dry and playable; some precipitation was expected -- yes, maybe even snow -- tonight and tomorrow in Cleveland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was chilly in Cleveland yesterday afternoon, but Bob DiBiasio, the vice president for public relations for the Indians, said the sun was shining. DiBiasio had not seen any kind of consistent sunshine in a while, especially on a day when the Indians were scheduled to play a home game.</p>
        <p>''It's a beautiful sight,'' he said. The Indians returned to Jacobs Field to play the Chicago White Sox last night, hoping that the snow that turned them into vagabonds this week was not about to return. There was no guarantee that the cold weather would at least remain dry and playable; some precipitation was expected -- yes, maybe even snow -- tonight and tomorrow in Cleveland.</p>
        <p>To duck some of what Mother Nature might be sending Cleveland's way, the Indians moved the start of today's game to 1:05 p.m., from 7:05. But tomorrow afternoon's game could be subjected to the same kind of weather that hamstrung the Indians last weekend, when their entire four-game series against Seattle was snowed out.</p>
        <p>Todd Miner, a meteorologist at Penn State, said it would be windy tomorrow afternoon in Cleveland, with temperatures stuck in the high 30s. There could be a dusting of snow, Miner said, or as much as four or five inches if the storm veers north.</p>
        <p>''We think we'll play,'' DiBiasio said with the kind of optimism people in baseball sometimes need. ''We think it'll stay south of us.''</p>
        <p>DiBiasio is one of numerous baseball executives who have been keeping a close eye on the Weather Channel during the first two weeks of the season. Nine games had been postponed through Thursday, the most in the first two weeks of a season since 2003, when 11 were postponed.</p>
        <p>What that all means is hard to say. Katy Feeney, baseball's senior vice president for scheduling and club relations, noted that in three of the past seven years, there have been more postponements in the second half of April than in the first half of the month. Perhaps this season will be the reverse.</p>
        <p>''When you focus on a small part of the schedule, you can find something bad,'' Feeney said. ''It's not a two-week schedule. It's a 26-week schedule. April is unpredictable. You have some gorgeous days and then you have miserable days.''</p>
        <p>Miner said that east of the Great Lakes, temperatures have been, on average, about five degrees colder than normal this April. Excluding the first few days of the month, which were milder, the temperatures east of the Great Lakes have been about 12 degrees colder than normal.</p>
        <p>Mets Manager Willie Randolph says that teams have to play in cold weather, but he wonders how cold is too cold.</p>
        <p>''I just think that M.L.B. should look at the weather and, if it gets to a certain chill factor, you got to call the game,'' Randolph said, referring to Major League Baseball.</p>
        <p>At times over the last two weeks, the players have dressed for football. In Atlanta, Braves center fielder Andruw Jones wore a stocking that covered his head, neck and part of his face. Philadelphia Phillies first baseman Ryan Howard put on a red wool cap before putting on his batting gloves.</p>
        <p>Mets pitcher Tom Glavine spoke about how the weather could affect performance.</p>
        <p>''When you have a cold, windy day, it's hard,'' he said. ''You can deal with just the cold or just the wind, but when you have the combination, it's hard to keep any perspiration on your hand.''</p>
        <p>Feeney said that the schedule-makers were cognizant of having the warm-weather teams play at home in early April, but that the fickleness of the weather prevented that from being a definitive solution. In addition, in cold-weather markets where there are two teams, like New York, Chicago and Washington/Baltimore, one of the clubs needs to open at home.</p>
        <p>The Arizona Diamondbacks are one warm-weather team that began its season on the road, in Colorado and Washington. But Feeney noted that warm-weather teams did not want to pile up home games in April, therefore losing them later in the season.</p>
        <p>Glavine said: ''I don't think it's feasible at this time of the year to have every game on the West Coast or every game in a dome. It's the kind of thing that nobody pays attention to it, unless you're having a year like we're having this year.''</p>
        <p>The weather could remain a problem. Randolph will proudly wear Jackie Robinson's number 42 on Sunday, but heavy rain is forecast for the Mets' game with the Nationals. The Red Sox will attempt to play their traditional Patriot's Day game Monday morning at Fenway Park, but rain could interfere there, too. On Tuesday, the Indians travel to New York, where they could be greeted by more of the same.</p>
        <p>When snow hammered Cleveland last Friday, the Indians were leading, 4-0, with two outs in the fifth inning. Paul Byrd, who was pitching a no-hitter, was one strike away from an official game, but it was called.</p>
        <p>The Indians came no closer to playing for the next three days. More than a foot of snow covered the field and won out over baseball.</p>
        <p>''To see our guys taking batting practice and watching other games on TV, it was a bunch of antsy guys,'' DiBiasio said. ''The whole thing was the weirdest of the weird.''</p>
        <p>The Indians finally gave up and shifted a midweek series against the Los Angeles Angels to Miller Park in Milwaukee. It has a retractable roof. The Indians played there this week, then returned home to deal with the weather again.</p>
        <p>DiBiasio called Cleveland's overall experience ''a week for the ages.'' He recalled how fans at Jacobs Field last weekend built snowmen on the Indians' dugout, wore Santa hats and even sang Christmas carols.</p>
        <p>''They were trying to make the best of it,'' DiBiasio said, although he's hoping they do not have to do it again.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
