<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theft Empties Pantry, but Hungry Keep Coming</title>
    <meta content="14journal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/nyregion/14journal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STATEN ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kitchens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theft Empties Pantry, but Hungry Keep Coming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Theft Empties Pantry, but Hungry Keep Coming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Down at the end of a narrow, stuccoed hallway on the ground floor of a low-income high-rise, Kezlie Mulbah waited with an empty stomach.</p>
        <p>''They steal our food,'' he said flatly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Someone broke into the room where the Staten Island Liberian Community Association runs a weekly food pantry and stole a month’s worth of provisions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Down at the end of a narrow, stuccoed hallway on the ground floor of a low-income high-rise, Kezlie Mulbah waited with an empty stomach.</p>
        <p>''They steal our food,'' he said flatly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulbah was standing in the doorway of the wan, yellow room where the Staten Island Liberian Community Association runs a weekly food pantry. Over the weekend, someone had broken in and hauled off a month's worth of provisions: rice, oil, cereal, juice, tomato paste, the works.</p>
        <p>''I don't understand why someone would steal food when they could get it for free,'' said Mr. Mulbah, 18, a high school student.</p>
        <p>The association scrounged enough last-minute donations to open for its weekly distribution on Wednesday, but not nearly enough to feed the usual 150 families. So Mr. Mulbah arrived about 1 p.m., an hour early.</p>
        <p>''I want some food today,'' he said. ''I have a soccer game this afternoon. I need to eat something.'' He reached for a bag of grapes and popped one in his mouth.</p>
        <p>What kind of miserable criminal, people asked, would hit the food pantry at the Parkhill Apartments, a cluster of grim brick buildings not far from the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge?</p>
        <p>''I don't think it would be someone who needs to eat, because they could come in on Wednesday and get the food for free,'' said Sharon Dixon, a volunteer at the pantry. ''They wanted the food to sell it.''</p>
        <p>Breaking in was not too hard. Someone at the association had apparently left the gate on a window unlocked, and the thief or thieves climbed in and broke down the flimsy hollow door to the storeroom.</p>
        <p>''It was ransacked,'' said the Rev. Comfort Parker, the food program's coordinator. ''Things all over the place. It's like they were rushing to get what they could get.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulbah ate another grape.</p>
        <p>''Take the whole bag,'' Ms. Dixon told him. ''Take it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulbah bowed his head. ''I appreciate it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The association had spread the word about the theft, hoping to discourage turnout, but by 2 p.m. the hallway was full of people. Young, old of various races. Women with little children, men with creased faces.</p>
        <p>''Does everyone have their bags?'' a volunteer called out. The bags had been stolen, too.</p>
        <p>Things grew tense. ''Excuse me, that's my bag,'' a man in a red sweatshirt called after Mr. Mulbah.</p>
        <p>The association's president, George Curtis, arrived and began barking out orders.</p>
        <p>''One of each, one of each,'' Mr. Curtis, an enormous bald man, yelled above the din. ''One each of what we have.'' That meant: cans of beans, peas and tuna; boxes of Snickers bars, oatmeal and cold cereal; bags of macaroni, dry beans and grapes; jars of peanut butter, and enormous sweet potatoes.</p>
        <p>People squeezed into the little room, which is also Mr. Curtis's office. It is furnished with an unplugged freezer, two empty soda refrigerators and a desk made from part of a counter.</p>
        <p>An older woman who had difficulty walking handed her bag to a volunteer. ''I want everything,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Two big boxes of potatoes materialized. Mr. Curtis declared no limit on the potatoes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Curtis approached an older man who wore a baseball cap, a black leatherette jacket and gleaming white sneakers. ''How you doing, sir?'' Mr. Curtis said. ''Welcome to America.''</p>
        <p>The man, Jonathan Moore, 60 years old and one month off a plane from Liberia, looked a little dazed. ''Not bad,'' he said as he held up his bag of food.</p>
        <p>Mr. Curtis started the food pantry three years ago. ''There was the war in Liberia, and we had the refugees coming,'' he said. ''Before you get your papers, and your green card, and food stamps, that takes time. So we had a lot of hungry people coming in.''</p>
        <p>By 2:45 p.m., the grapes were gone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Curtis's cellphone rang.</p>
        <p>''We need food, period,'' he told the caller. ''Any kind of food.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Curtis said that after the theft was discovered on Monday, his suppliers would not replace the missing food until they saw copies of the police report, which had not yet arrived. So he had to hustle. He begged from other pantries. The charity arm of the Richmond County Savings Bank gave him $5,000 to cover the value of the lost food.</p>
        <p>The peas were exhausted by 3:10 p.m., followed quickly by the Snickers.</p>
        <p>Tanya Mitchell came to get food for herself, her daughter and two grandchildren. She frowned at her box. It was only half full, and much of that was potatoes.</p>
        <p>''Usually, I can't get it upstairs by myself,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The pantry usually stays open until 4 p.m., but by 3:30 many shelves were bare, and Mr. Curtis cut the day short. People get belligerent if the selection is not what they expect, he said.</p>
        <p>Sixty-seven families had been fed.</p>
        <p>A few minutes later, Glenda Kahn approached the office hopefully. The door was locked.</p>
        <p>She rolled her empty cart back down the hallway toward the exit.</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
