<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vatican Envoy to Avoid Holocaust Ceremony</title>
    <meta content="14mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/world/middleeast/14mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yad Vashem Holocaust Memorial (Israel)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Medina, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franco, Antonio (Abp)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pius Xii (Pope) (1876-1958)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Jerusalem (Israel)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7DF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vatican Envoy to Avoid Holocaust Ceremony</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vatican Envoy to Avoid Holocaust Ceremony</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER MEDINA; Ian Fisher contributed reporting from Rome.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Medina, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Archbishop Antonio Franco, Vatican's ambassador to Israel, will skip official Holocaust Remembrance Day ceremony at Yad Vashem Museum in Jerusalem to protest museum's depiction of Pope Pius XII as passive bystander to murder of Jews during World War II; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Vatican's ambassador to Israel has said he will skip the official Holocaust Remembrance Day ceremony at a national museum here on Sunday to protest the museum's depiction of Pope Pius XII as a largely passive bystander to the murder of Jews during World War II.</p>
        <p>In a letter sent last week to officials at Yad Vashem, the Holocaust museum and research center here, the ambassador, Archbishop Antonio Franco, said that he would not attend the service because he believed the description of Pope Pius XII offends the Catholic Church.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Vatican’s ambassador to Israel has said he will skip the official Holocaust Remembrance Day ceremony at a national museum to protest the museum’s depiction of Pope Pius XII.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Vatican's ambassador to Israel has said he will skip the official Holocaust Remembrance Day ceremony at a national museum here on Sunday to protest the museum's depiction of Pope Pius XII as a largely passive bystander to the murder of Jews during World War II.</p>
        <p>In a letter sent last week to officials at Yad Vashem, the Holocaust museum and research center here, the ambassador, Archbishop Antonio Franco, said that he would not attend the service because he believed the description of Pope Pius XII offends the Catholic Church.</p>
        <p>The eight-sentence caption next to two photographs of Pius XII in an exhibit says his reaction to the ''murder of the Jews during the Holocaust is a matter of controversy,'' implying he did not do enough.</p>
        <p>''When Jews were deported from Rome to Auschwitz, the pope did not intervene,'' the caption reads. ''The pope maintained his neutral position throughout the war, with the exception of appeals to the rulers of Hungary and Slovakia towards its end. His silence and the absence of guidelines obliged churchmen throughout Europe to decide on their own how to react.''</p>
        <p>There has been much historical debate over Pius XII, accused by some historians of not using his influence to stop the killing of the Jews. But the Vatican has refused to rule out the possibility of making him a saint.</p>
        <p>''I will attend any ceremony on the victims of World War II, but I do not feel at ease at Yad Vashem when the pope is presented in this way,'' Archbishop Franco said in an interview published Friday in The Jerusalem Post, adding that the decision was a ''personal'' one.</p>
        <p>The ceremony is attended by Israeli leaders, Holocaust survivors and scores of diplomats on the national holiday, which begins Sunday. ''Anyone who follows the Israeli body politic knows that this is an extremely important national event and for Jews around the world,'' said Mark Regev, a spokesman for the Israeli Foreign Ministry. ''We think that it is right that all the officials representing foreign governments attend. That is the correct protocol.''</p>
        <p>The dispute could threaten already fragile ties between the Roman Catholic Church and Israel, which established a diplomatic relationship in 1994. The Vatican and Israeli leaders have in the past sparred over the Palestinian conflict and other issues.</p>
        <p>A Vatican official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity because he was not authorized to speak publicly about the matter, said the Vatican was ''following the situation.''</p>
        <p>Archbishop Franco and other Catholic leaders complained privately about the caption a few months after the museum opened in 2005, church and museum officials said.</p>
        <p>The Vatican said it had received no formal response, but museum officials said that they had made clear that they would be open to revisions if they were allowed to study church archives for new information. ''The Holocaust History Museum presents the historical truth on Pius XII as is known to scholars today,'' said Iris Rosenberg, a museum spokeswoman. ''It is unacceptable to use diplomatic pressure when dealing with historical research.''</p>
        <p>Separately, the Israeli Army said Friday that it had suspended a commander in Nablus in the West Bank after Israeli news reports showed a tape of him using two Palestinian boys to guard military vehicles.</p>
        <p>The use of the boys shown in the video, made by a foreign peace activist and posted on the Web site of Yediot Aharonot, an Israeli daily newspaper, was apparently a violation of international law and of a 2005 ruling by Israel's Supreme Court against human shields. The army said an investigation was under way.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
