<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exile Is Rebuked for Urging Ouster of Putin</title>
    <meta content="14london" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/world/europe/14london.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berezovsky, Boris A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Berezovsky, Boris A</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Putin, Vladimir V</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exile Is Rebuked for Urging Ouster of Putin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Exile Is Rebuked for Urging Ouster of Putin</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL; Steven Lee Myers contributed reporting from Moscow.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boris A Berezovsky, self-exiled Russian tycoon, earns sharp rebukes from London and Moscow when he urges forceful ouster of Pres Vladimir V Putin and new revolution in Russia; Moscow denounces comments and demands that Britain arrest and extradite Berezovsky (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boris A. Berezovsky, a self-exiled Russian tycoon, earned sharp rebukes from London and Moscow on Friday when he urged the forceful ouster of Vladimir V. Putin as president of Russia and a new revolution there.</p>
        <p>''We need to use force to change this regime, because this regime is anticonstitutional,'' he said of Mr. Putin's government in an interview in the newspaper The Guardian on Friday. Asked if he was seeking to foment revolution, he declared, ''You are absolutely correct.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boris A. Berezovsky, a self-exiled Russian tycoon, earned sharp rebukes from London and Moscow on Friday when he urged the forceful ouster of Vladimir V. Putin as president of Russia and a new revolution there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Boris A. Berezovsky, a self-exiled Russian tycoon, earned sharp rebukes from London and Moscow on Friday when he urged the forceful ouster of Vladimir V. Putin as president of Russia and a new revolution there.</p>
        <p>''We need to use force to change this regime, because this regime is anticonstitutional,'' he said of Mr. Putin's government in an interview in the newspaper The Guardian on Friday. Asked if he was seeking to foment revolution, he declared, ''You are absolutely correct.''</p>
        <p>The British Foreign Office, seeking to avoid friction with Russia, took umbrage at the comments, saying through a spokesman that it ''deplored anyone who uses their residence in the U.K. as a platform to call for the violent overthrow of a sovereign government.''</p>
        <p>Officials in Moscow responded swiftly, with both the Kremlin and the Foreign Ministry denouncing the comments as unlawful and demanding again that Britain arrest and extradite Mr. Berezovsky.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor general's office in Moscow issued a statement on Friday, saying it had opened an investigation under Article 278 of the country's criminal code, which covers unconstitutional seizure of power.</p>
        <p>''These kinds of words are being treated as a violation of the law, not only in Russia, but in every civilized country,'' a Kremlin spokesman, Dmitri S. Peskov, said in a telephone interview. ''After this statement, we can expect more attention by the British authorities to revisit the question of his political asylum.''</p>
        <p>British officials have long insisted that Mr. Berezovsky's status can be determined only by a court, and the courts have in the past upheld his refugee status.</p>
        <p>But the British government's refusal to act against Mr. Berezovsky has frequently angered the Kremlin, which wants him returned to Russia to face fraud charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berezovsky started a similar appeal for Mr. Putin's overthrow in a radio interview in January 2006, prompting a Russian investigation that appears to have ended without resolution or formal charges.</p>
        <p>Separately, Russian prosecutors announced Friday that Mr. Berezovsky faced new charges relating to old accusations that he misappropriated more than $8 million from Aeroflot, the state-controlled airline.</p>
        <p>The exchange was part of a protracted and vituperative battle between Mr. Putin and Mr. Berezovsky, who supported the Russian president's victory in the 2000 elections before seeking exile in London when the two men fell out.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berezovsky sought to rephrase his comments, issuing a statement that he favored ''direct action,'' like the popular protests that have shaken Ukraine, to force change in Russia, where recent antigovernment street demonstrations have been outlawed or violently repressed by the authorities.</p>
        <p>Russia is preparing for parliamentary and presidential elections scheduled in the next 11 months, and Mr. Berezovsky's remarks appeared intended to encourage opposition.</p>
        <p>Opposition leaders were planning a series of protest marches over the weekend in Moscow and St. Petersburg. The police have warned that they are ready to prevent unlawful gatherings, and the authorities have authorized competing pro-government rallies on Saturday in Moscow.</p>
        <p>In his statement, Mr. Berezovsky accused Russia's leaders of stifling democracy.</p>
        <p>''Under the current regime, freedom of expression is not respected, the media is not free from government control, political opponents are under threat and elections are neither free nor fair,'' he said. ''Under those circumstances, elections are not a viable means of enduring democratic change in Russia. Therefore, I do support using other methods to push for a change back towards democracy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''However, I wish to make very clear that all of these methods would be bloodless with, perhaps, Georgia and Ukraine's recent popular demonstrations and action being good examples,'' he continued.</p>
        <p>''I do support direct action,'' Mr. Berezovsky said. ''I do not advocate or support violence.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
