<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks' Playoff Hopes Crumble</title>
    <meta content="14knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/sports/basketball/14knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jefferson, Richard</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7DC103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks' Playoff Hopes Crumble</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kidd and Nets Seal Knicks’ Fate and Clinch Berth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK; John Eligon contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Isiah Thomas wore a grim expression. Down to his left, Jamal Crawford and Quentin Richardson wore suits. David Lee and Stephon Marbury wore warmups that they never shed.</p>
        <p>And as the final seconds ticked away Friday night at Continental Arena, the Knicks assumed a collective look of despair, a familiar expression for the past several years. The Nets -- their would-be rivals if they ever challenged them -- ran off with a 100-86 victory that officially ended the Knicks' playoff hopes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A triple-double from Jason Kidd pushed the Nets to a victory over the Knicks. They later clinched a playoff berth when the Indiana Pacers lost to the Miami Heat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Isiah Thomas wore a grim expression. Down to his left, Jamal Crawford and Quentin Richardson wore suits. David Lee and Stephon Marbury wore warmups that they never shed.</p>
        <p>And as the final seconds ticked away Friday night at Continental Arena, the Knicks assumed a collective look of despair, a familiar expression for the past several years. The Nets -- their would-be rivals if they ever challenged them -- ran off with a 100-86 victory that officially ended the Knicks' playoff hopes.</p>
        <p>A short time later, the Nets clinched a playoff berth when the Indiana Pacers lost to the Miami Heat. It was a familiar contrast, the Nets (38-41) marching on to better things while the Knicks (32-47) trudged into another spring of unfulfilled hope.</p>
        <p>Elimination from the playoff race had loomed for weeks, after a rash of injuries. When the Knicks were at last eliminated, four of their top six players were spectators.</p>
        <p>''If this whole season was about us making the playoffs, then it was a failure,'' Knicks center Eddy Curry said. ''But if the season was about developing our guys and really coming together as a team and guys really coming into their own, I think it was successful.''</p>
        <p>Curry admitted to looking down the bench, yearning for a Crawford jumper or a Lee rebound. ''You just never know what would have happened if guys were healthy and if we'd have played a little better at the beginning of the season,'' Curry said.</p>
        <p>The Nets weathered a season-ending injury to Nenad Krstic and a long stretch without Richard Jefferson to clinch a sixth straight playoff trip, a franchise record. They took the last step Friday with a classic Nets performance -- a triple-double from Jason Kidd, accompanied by explosive scoring from Jefferson and Vince Carter.</p>
        <p>Kidd had 13 points, 14 rebounds and 11 assists for the 87th triple-double of his career, his 12th this season and his third all-time against the Knicks. Jefferson had 24 points, with five 3-pointers, and Carter finished with 25 points. The Nets had 16 3-pointers, the most this season by a Knicks opponent, including six in the third quarter, when they pulled away.</p>
        <p>Geography dictates that the series be called a rivalry, although the lopsided results do not support the label. With Friday's victory, the Nets have won 23 of the teams' past 24 meetings, including playoff games.</p>
        <p>As if to underline the lack of competitive tension between the teams, Jefferson said the Nets drew no satisfaction from eliminating the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''It's not like we had any extra motivation,'' he said. ''They have a lot of injuries over there. It's not like we're out here holding our chests out. It's just another game.''</p>
        <p>A night earlier, the Nets absorbed an 18-point rout in Cleveland, raising doubts about their playoff readiness. The Knicks made them look championship-worthy.</p>
        <p>The Nets scored 40 points in the third quarter to turn a close game into a rout. Kidd, who was scoreless in the first half, had 10 points in the first four minutes of the period as the Nets went on a 27-11 run.</p>
        <p>Later in the quarter, Kidd dished to Bostjan Nachbar for a 3-pointer to register his 10th assist and complete the triple-double. The lead grew to 23 points in the fourth quarter, and the Knicks never got it down to single digits.</p>
        <p>Mardy Collins, the Knicks rookie, scored a career-high 21 points and had 9 rebounds. Curry added 20 points and 7 rebounds. Steve Francis returned to the starting lineup and scored a team-high 22 points.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' playoff hopes were dim, to say the least, heading into the game. They had to win their final four games, while Orlando and Indiana lost all of their remaining games and Philadelphia lost at least two of its final four games.</p>
        <p>They can throw away the abacus and the spreadsheets now. Only a month ago, the Knicks were in eighth place, briefly, and in the hunt for a playoff spot. After a 3-13 free fall, they were tied for 11th with Charlotte.</p>
        <p>''When you lose five of your top six guys, it's tough to overcome,'' Thomas said.</p>
        <p>''But we'll keep working and we'll keep competing and I know we're better than what's kind of happened. We'll get better.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Jamal Crawford is running, jumping and shooting, all of which implies he is ready to play again. Crawford was cleared for all activity by team doctors on Wednesday. He was inactive Friday but did not rule out playing in one of the Knicks' final three games. ''I'm not expecting to play,'' he said, ''but anything's possible.''  Stephon Marbury and David Lee were in uniform, but were available only for emergency duty, Coach Isiah Thomas said. It is not clear whether Marbury, who has turf toe, will play again this season.  Renaldo Balkman, who, according to the Knicks, has had a stomach virus all week, was not at the game. ... Nets guard Eddie House said he hoped to be back late in the first round of the playoffs, assuming the Nets make it that far. House tore a muscle in his hip just over two weeks ago.  The description of Lee's lower right leg injury has been modified again. After a new series of tests, Lee said, doctors are now calling it a bone bruise, with a strained peroneal tendon. The team had called the injury a stress reaction -- which implies that it happened gradually. But Lee said doctors are now ''trying to stay away from the word stress,'' because it appears that the injury was caused by a single incident -- when Lee landed awkwardly in a Feb. 23 game against Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
