<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Company Be as Visionary As Its Building?</title>
    <meta content="14nocera" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/business/14nocera.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TALKING BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Iac/interactivecorp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nocera, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gehry, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diller, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">InterActiveCorp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Diller, Barry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gehry, Frank</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Company Be as Visionary As Its Building?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Building for Diller by Gehry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE NOCERA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nocera, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joe Nocera Talking Business column on whether IAC/InterActiveCorp founder Barry Diller can be as visionary as company's new Manhattan headquarters designed by Frank Gehry; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was raining hard Thursday morning as I headed to the new headquarters of IAC/InterActiveCorp, Barry Diller's ''Internet conglomerate,'' as he likes to call it. Although some employees had been working there since February -- ''the guinea pigs,'' joked Jason Stewart, IAC's chief administrative officer -- the building had been officially open for business less than two weeks.</p>
        <p>The New York Times's architecture critic, Nicolai Ouroussoff, had reviewed it, somewhat equivocally, in late March. Throughout his review, Mr. Ouroussoff referred to the 10-story $100 million structure as the IAC Building; and though someday we might all call it that, right now New Yorkers mainly know it by the name of its architect. It's the Frank Gehry building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With its billowing sheets of curved glass, its partly white windows, and the world’s largest high-def screen in its expansive lobby, the new headquarters of IAC is unlike anything in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was raining hard Thursday morning as I headed to the new headquarters of IAC/InterActiveCorp, Barry Diller's ''Internet conglomerate,'' as he likes to call it. Although some employees had been working there since February -- ''the guinea pigs,'' joked Jason Stewart, IAC's chief administrative officer -- the building had been officially open for business less than two weeks.</p>
        <p>The New York Times's architecture critic, Nicolai Ouroussoff, had reviewed it, somewhat equivocally, in late March. Throughout his review, Mr. Ouroussoff referred to the 10-story $100 million structure as the IAC Building; and though someday we might all call it that, right now New Yorkers mainly know it by the name of its architect. It's the Frank Gehry building.</p>
        <p>You know the building I mean, don't you? It's Mr. Gehry's first building in New York City. And, with its billowing sheets of curved glass that evoke the sails of a clipper ship, its partly white windows, and the world's largest high-def screen in its stark, expansive lobby, it's unlike anything in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''It's one of the most interesting new buildings that we have in the city,'' said Robert A. M. Stern, the dean of the Yale School of Architecture. The Gehry building is so offbeat that you can't help noticing it as you drive along the West Side Highway in Chelsea. But as I also discovered, it is so far from a subway stop that you simply can't get there on a rainy day, when taxis are in scarce supply, without getting soaked.</p>
        <p>Which is to say, as much of a landmark as the building is likely to become, it's not exactly in a convenient spot. Then again, Mr. Diller's wife, the designer Diane von Furstenberg, who is also on the IAC board, has a studio apartment nearby, and Mr. Diller told me that they are planning to move to the neighborhood full time. Plus, it is close enough to the Hudson River that Mr. Diller can pretty much walk from his office to his New York yacht, Arriva. So at least it will be convenient for him.</p>
        <p>As it turns out, the one IAC New York employee who has not yet moved into the new building is Mr. Diller himself. He's been on vacation the last few weeks. When Mr. Stewart took me through Mr. Diller's sixth-floor office, filled with gorgeous art books, and sleek modern furniture, I could see workers scrambling to add the final touches before Monday, when he is due to show up.</p>
        <p>It was probably just as well that Mr. Diller wasn't around because he has a reputation for being -- how should I put this? -- exacting. All the glitches that come with any new building would probably have driven him crazy, and he in turn would probably have driven his staff crazy. Although Mr. Diller and Mr. Gehry both claim their collaboration worked well, one hears through the grapevine that at times, the demanding chief executive drove the famous architect a little crazy, too.</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Diller who insisted, for instance, that the building be sheathed in glass, instead of the titanium or metal that Mr. Gehry is so renowned for. Mr. Diller is also the one who insisted on white windows. When Mr. Gehry first showed Mr. Diller a model of his design, he used a white material to represent the window panes, and Mr. Diller fell in love with the idea of white windows.</p>
        <p>''Barry got fixated on having a white glass building,'' Mr. Gehry said. ''Which can't be done. For a long time, he didn't want to believe that you couldn't do it.'' Eventually, Mr. Gehry presented Mr. Diller with windows that were half white, which he accomplished through an engineering innovation, and Mr. Diller accepted it.</p>
        <p>True to his reputation for micromanaging, Mr. Diller was immersed deeply in even the tiniest detail. He picked out the bathroom tilesand pored over the rug samples. The boardroom has a big, bold, oval conference table that harkens to the iconic conference furniture of yore -- except that a small, hidden computer can slide out for every person present. All of these touches speak to Mr. Diller's obsessive involvement in the project.</p>
        <p>When I asked Mr. Diller over the phone why he had been drawn to Mr. Gehry, he said he wanted to do something that ''excites the imagination.'' He said he told his staff, ''We can build a box, but why should that be our aspiration?'' When I mentioned that some of the greatest buildings in New York's history were ''boxes''-- the Seagram Building, for starters -- Mr. Diller gave me another rationale.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to pull together all these disparate businesses,'' he said. ''I wanted a work space where people could collaborate and be in an open atmosphere.'' It was difficult, if not impossible, to find that kind of space in a New York skyscraper, he added.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the open, colorful interior is carefully designed to maximize interaction among employees of both ''corporate''-- the parent company -- and the New York-based operating companies that are housed there. (Many of IAC's 22,000 employees work outside New York, of course.)</p>
        <p>But the mere fact that Mr. Diller now has an open, airy building does not necessarily mean that his somewhat hodgepodge collection of Internet businesses will automatically turn into a seamless, integrated company. Nor is it necessarily going to give Mr. Diller what he most wants: not wealth, which he has in spades thanks in part to all the options his board has handed him over the years, but the business community's admiration for the company he would like to build. That's going to require something else.</p>
        <p>Ever since he started IAC 12 years ago, the rap on Mr. Diller has been that he lacks a clear, consistent vision for his company. He's built IAC by wheeling and dealing at a truly dizzying pace. He eats through companies, executives and employees. There was a time, for instance, when he used to describe Expedia as one of IAC's core companies. But late in the summer of 2005, Mr. Diller decided that Expedia's results were overshadowing the rest of the company, and causing Wall Street to ignore faster-growing entities inside IAC. So he spun it off. About three years ago, when he was in a particularly manic deal-making phase, he told Fortune, ''It's hard to be consistent when you are making it up every day.''</p>
        <p>Today, IAC has 64 companies, including LendingTree, TicketMaster, HSN (formerly the Home Shopping Network), Ask.com, Match.com, Evite, Citysearch and CollegeHumor. Although it generates more than $6 billion in revenue, it is not particularly profitable and its assets, with some notable exceptions like TicketMaster, tend to be second-tier. Ask.com, for instance, is a search engine with about 6 percent of the market -- and has lately been losing share to Google. HSN lags behind QVC as a shopping network. As a result, investors tend not to place IAC in the same league as the Googles and Yahoos, and its stock, which was as high as $82 four summers ago (adjusted for a stock split) now hovers in the high 30s. It closed yesterday at $38.25.</p>
        <p>When I spoke to him, Mr. Diller claimed that he had turned over a new leaf, that he was no longer interested in wheeling and dealing so frantically, and that his goal was make the whole more than the sum of the parts. ''There is no question that two years ago we were a holding company,'' he said. ''But we decided strategically that we had enough mass, and we didn't need to be in on the deal of the day.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he said, he wants to transform IAC into a true operating company -- the kind of company that shares resources, takes advantage of the expertise of the different companies to help other companies, and so on. ''If we can do that, it will give us a competitive advantage,'' he said.</p>
        <p>To that end, about a year and a half ago, Mr. Diller brought over Douglas R. Lebda from LendingTree, where he had been founder and chief executive, to be his second-in-command. Mr. Lebda is charged with turning IAC's portfolio of companies into a more integrated whole, something he told me the new building will accelerate. Both he and Mr. Diller cited, as an example of an early success, a new company IAC has started, called AskCity, that combines the expertise of Ask.com and Citysearch to create what they contend is a better version of local search. (When I played with it, I could see its potential to help people find nearby events and stores. But it still had a few kinks.) ''To get these companies to relate to each other is very hard to do,'' Mr. Diller acknowledged. But, he insisted, on a scale of 10, he believed ''we're at a 4 or 5.'' Most people I talked to, though, think they are closer to a 2.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Diller didn't acknowledge is the extent to which he himself will have to change if IAC is to become the company he wants it to be. Mr. Lebda is universally respected inside the company, but Mr. Diller has long been difficult to work for, and over the years, many of his top executives have quit. And Mr. Diller has said things in the past about the path IAC was on -- only to change his matter a short while later. To an outsider, his need to do deals is almost compulsive. That's why so many on Wall Street are loath to give him credit -- they're just not sure if he means it this time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Diller is 65 years old, and at that age, people don't change easily. Maybe it's possible that his fine new building will inspire him to stick to something a little longer than the next quarter. If he does, then someday we may well be calling that curved, unusual, white-glass building down by the West Side Highway the IAC Building. And if he doesn't? Then it's going to be the Frank Gehry building for a very long time.</p>
        <p>TALKING BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
