<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Though Not in April's Rhythm, Pelfrey Doesn't Miss a Beat</title>
    <meta content="14mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/sports/baseball/14mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Washington Nationals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Nationals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pelfrey, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E6DC103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Though Not in April's Rhythm, Pelfrey Doesn't Miss a Beat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Though Not in April’s Rhythm, Pelfrey Doesn’t Miss a Beat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Pelfrey spent the last two weeks in Florida pitching, eating, waiting, working out, waiting, pitching, watching movies, working out and waiting some more until the day finally came for him to fly to New York and be a bona fide major leaguer again.</p>
        <p>And when Pelfrey did arrive at Shea Stadium last night, exiting the wacky alternate universe that came courtesy of the Mets' not needing a fifth starter until the season's 10th game, he noticed his teammates wearing turtlenecks and winter caps, already ensconced in the familiar rhythms of April baseball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Pelfrey’s much-anticipated season debut was only slightly better than the weather, but he kept the Mets in the game long enough to get a victory over Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Pelfrey spent the last two weeks in Florida pitching, eating, waiting, working out, waiting, pitching, watching movies, working out and waiting some more until the day finally came for him to fly to New York and be a bona fide major leaguer again.</p>
        <p>And when Pelfrey did arrive at Shea Stadium last night, exiting the wacky alternate universe that came courtesy of the Mets' not needing a fifth starter until the season's 10th game, he noticed his teammates wearing turtlenecks and winter caps, already ensconced in the familiar rhythms of April baseball.</p>
        <p>Pelfrey's much-anticipated season debut was only slightly better than the weather, but he kept the Mets in the game long enough to dash the Washington Nationals' quixotic dreams of winning a second consecutive game. Julio Franco lashed a pinch-hit single in the seventh inning to score David Wright with the go-ahead run, and the Mets' bullpen held up the lead in their 3-2 victory.</p>
        <p>When the game began at 7:13 p.m., the temperature was 45 degrees, but the 26-mile-an-hour winds gusting from the northwest sent sandwich wrappers and trash bags swirling above the infield and turned last night into the coldest of the season, Franco said. Pelfrey struggled to find a consistent grip, and his control suffered, as he walked four hitters. But his velocity hovered at its normal level, the mid-90s, and he relied on his lethal sinker, the ideal pitch on a night like this, to induce three double plays and mitigate the damage.</p>
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph said Pelfrey ground it out. ''He made a couple of bad pitches, but it's not always easy to go out there and brave the elements,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Pelfrey was in line to take the loss when he was yanked with two outs in the sixth, and the Nationals threatening to add to their 2-1 lead. Pedro Feliciano suppressed the rally, and the Mets tied the score in the bottom of the inning, on Carlos Delgado's single, before taking the lead in the seventh against the reliever Ryan Wagner.</p>
        <p>Wright singled up the middle and advanced to second when José Valentín walked with two outs. Randolph inserted Franco in a prime run-producing opportunity. He took the first pitch low for ball one and then ripped the next pitch through the infield into center to score Wright.</p>
        <p>''In that situation, you just want to concentrate on getting a ball that's down,'' Franco said. ''He's a sinkerball pitcher and keeps the ball low, so you don't want to swing at the balls that are high. I could have hit it anywhere -- to second base, to shortstop -- but it went through the middle.''</p>
        <p>Scott Schoeneweis pitched a spotless eighth, and Billy Wagner a perfect ninth to record his third save and send Washington Manager Manny Acta, the Mets' former third-base coach, back to his hotel with a loss in his managing debut at Shea. The Nationals fell to 2-9 this season, the worst record in the majors.</p>
        <p>''It's scary to play a team like this because their record says that we should beat them handily but it never happens like that,'' Billy Wagner said.</p>
        <p>The Mets entered spring training with a surplus of starters that the Nationals, who needed four to fall in line behind last night's starter, John Patterson, would have surely enjoyed. Pelfrey outclassed his competition for the fifth starter's job. But with three days off in the season's first 10 days, the Mets could start their top four pitchers on normal rest and did not need Pelfrey.</p>
        <p>So, after starting in St. Petersburg, Fla., on March 31, Pelfrey said goodbye to his teammates. He pitched against Class A Vero Beach on April 7 in his lone tuneup.</p>
        <p>''We've been trying to keep him on his regular schedule,'' Randolph said before the game. ''It's not the norm, but I've seen guys who don't skip a beat.''</p>
        <p>Early on, Pelfrey tried locating his fastball on the inner half of the plate in an effort to jam hitters on a cold night. It did not work so well. Pelfrey's control gradually disappeared, and he got into trouble in the second after falling behind in the count to three of the first four batters. After loading the bases with no outs, Pelfrey coaxed a double-play grounder. Dmitri Young scored, tying the game, and the No. 8 hitter, Chris Snelling, followed by blistering a first-pitch hanging changeup into right field to score Austin Kearns and give the Nationals only their third lead of the season.</p>
        <p>Pelfrey wriggled free from potential jams in the fourth and fifth by getting the Nationals to pound his sinker into the dirt for double plays.</p>
        <p>As he walked off the mound in the fifth, the normally reserved Pelfrey allowed a brief fist pump. With rain in the forecast tomorrow and again Monday in Philadelphia, the Mets may shuffle their rotation. Again, Pelfrey may be the odd man out.</p>
        <p>''I have five big-league starts,'' Pelfrey said. ''I don't have any pull around here.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Juan Padilla had successful surgery yesterday to repair a partial tear of the flexor tendon in his right elbow. The Mets did not say when they expected Padilla to return, but the Braves' Mike Hampton had the same surgery earlier this week and will miss the rest of the season.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
