<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawyer Attacked for Book His Panel Deems Offensive</title>
    <meta content="14felder" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE1DE103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawyer Attacked for Book His Panel Deems Offensive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Raoul Felder, a celebrity divorce lawyer who is chairman of a state commission that oversees judges, has been given a unanimous vote of no confidence by the other nine members of the commission for helping to write a book they said is racially and ethnically inflammatory.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued Friday, the commission members said the book, which Mr. Felder and the comedian Jackie Mason wrote, ''repeatedly invokes racial, ethnic and religious invective.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Raoul Felder, a celebrity divorce lawyer who is chairman of a state commission that oversees judges, has been given a unanimous vote of no confidence by the other nine members of the commission for helping to write a book they said is racially and ethnically inflammatory.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued Friday, the commission members said the book, which Mr. Felder and the comedian Jackie Mason wrote, ''repeatedly invokes racial, ethnic and religious invective.''</p>
        <p>The members said they were also troubled that the book asserts that ''anytime you hear the word 'allegedly,' you can bet it's true'' and says that ''nothing in our country is more insidious than affirmative action.'' The book came out late last month.</p>
        <p>The decision by the panel, the state Commission on Judicial Conduct, came amid a heated national debate over the racially and sexually charged language used by Don Imus to describe the Rutgers University women's basketball team. This week MSNBC and CBS canceled Mr. Imus's program, ''Imus in the Morning,'' because of the growing furor.</p>
        <p>The commission said its decision was not related to that controversy.</p>
        <p>''The commission would have made this statement even if it never heard of Don Imus,'' said Robert H. Tembeckjian, the commission's administrator and counsel. ''They're acting in accordance with their responsibility.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Felder said that he could not tell if there was a connection, but that he had been offended by Mr. Imus's statement.</p>
        <p>''He was personal with these people,'' he said in an interview. ''He has a redneck act he does; nothing in my book was personal.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Felder -- whose clients have included Rudolph W. Giuliani and the soon-to-be-former spouses of Elizabeth Taylor, Mike Tyson and Liza Minnelli -- was defiant about the commission's vote.</p>
        <p>''Hey, guys, lighten up. This is a book I wrote with Jackie Mason, a comedian, and the cover of the book is a cartoon,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He added: ''In Germany they burned the books they didn't like, and then they burnt the people after the books. I don't get it. A book is so threatening? I'm not going softly into the night.''</p>
        <p>The commission, made up of lawyers, judges and lay people, is an oversight body that investigates and disciplines judges throughout the state court system. The budget recently passed by the Legislature included a $2 million increase for the commission, bringing its annual spending to $4.8 million. The commission's importance has been highlighted in the wake of growing criticism of the conduct of town and village court judges.</p>
        <p>But now the commission itself is facing a leadership crisis. The statement by its members said they were ''exploring our options in terms of removing'' Mr. Felder as chairman, but it is not clear that they have the authority to do so before his term ends in March 2008.</p>
        <p>Mr. Felder was appointed to the commission by Gov. George E. Pataki in 2003, and his fellow commissioners voted him chairman last year.</p>
        <p>''The point here is not to inhibit anyone's right to publish under the First Amendment but to assure the bench, bar and public that the commission's decisions are fair and impartial, and that they are not driven by anyone's biases,'' the commission members said in the statement.</p>
        <p>''This book by the commission's chair seriously undermines that perception.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Felder and Mr. Mason, longtime friends, appear as cartoon superheroes on the cover of the book, which is titled ''Schmucks! Our Favorite Fakes, Frauds, Lowlifes, Liars, the Armed and Dangerous, and Good Guys Gone Bad.''</p>
        <p>They take shots at a number of public figures and ethnic groups. Barbra Streisand is dubbed ''Mentl'' and the speaker of the House, Nancy Pelosi, is ''Botox-addicted.'' Chapters in the book take on Tom Cruise and France and have titles like ''Al Sharpton, Praise the Lard.''</p>
        <p>The authors write that Mr. Sharpton, who has been one of Mr. Imus's leading critics, could be the first president impeached before being elected.</p>
        <p>They add, ''Who thought it was a good idea to make Jesse Jackson the arbiter of racial healing? That makes as much sense as Ted Kennedy being a lifeguard at a girls' school.''</p>
        <p>The tone of the book is a familiar one to fans of Mr. Mason, who has been condemned by various groups in the past for jokes that veered over racially sensitive lines.</p>
        <p>Referring to Saudi Arabia, the authors write, ''We never cared much for men who wear bedsheets as clothing. Like the Ku Klux Klan. And the Saudis.''</p>
        <p>Asked if the statement perpetuated a stereotype, Mr. Felder said: ''I'm not a fan of Saudi Arabia. I think they blackmail the world because of oil, and successive presidents have treated Saudi oil as more valuable than Israeli blood.'' He said that 11 of the Sept. 11 hijackers ''were not Scandinavian businessmen, they were Saudis.''</p>
        <p>The book also features a chapter that assails The New York Times as ''unfit to print'' and lambastes Frank Rich and Maureen Dowd as ''knee-jerk liberal columnists.''</p>
        <p>While he did not bring up that criticism during the interview, Mr. Felder did praise The Times's recent investigation of judicial conduct in town and village courts.</p>
        <p>The book will be No. 18 on the New York Times best-seller list for nonfiction books this Sunday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
