<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talk of Possible $20 Billion Deal for Sallie Mae Pushes Shares Higher</title>
    <meta content="14sallie" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/business/14sallie.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Slm Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Flowers, J C, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Merced, Michael J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sallie Mae</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EFDF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talk of Possible $20 Billion Deal for Sallie Mae Pushes Shares Higher</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Talk of Possible $20 Billion Deal for Sallie Mae Pushes Shares Higher</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL J. de la MERCED and ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; De La Merced, Michael J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares of Sallie Mae surge nearly 15 percent on prospects that company, SLM Corp, could be be bought out in deal worth more than $20 billion; Sallie Mae is in talks with Blackstone Group and group consisting of private equity firm J C Flowers &amp; Co and JPMorgan Chase (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shares of Sallie Mae, the nation's largest lender to college students, surged nearly 15 percent yesterday on the prospects that the company could be bought out in a deal worth more than $20 billion.</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae, officially the SLM Corporation, is in talks with the Blackstone Group and a group consisting of the private equity firm J. C. Flowers &amp; Company and JPMorgan Chase, people briefed on the discussions said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shares of Sallie Mae, the nation’s largest lender to college students, surged on the prospects that the company could be bought out in a deal worth more than $20 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shares of Sallie Mae, the nation's largest lender to college students, surged nearly 15 percent yesterday on the prospects that the company could be bought out in a deal worth more than $20 billion.</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae, officially the SLM Corporation, is in talks with the Blackstone Group and a group consisting of the private equity firm J. C. Flowers &amp; Company and JPMorgan Chase, people briefed on the discussions said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Representatives from all three companies declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Several analysts yesterday cited what they called significant hurdles to completing a deal. For one, buyers would need to structure a transaction in a way that would not load the company up with a huge amount of debt and endanger its credit ratings.</p>
        <p>More difficult than the financial challenge may be the political one. While no longer a government-sponsored enterprise, Sallie Mae, now wholly owned by its shareholders, has a special relationship with Washington in its role as the biggest originator of federally guaranteed loans, according to StudentMarketmeaure, a research firm.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the prospect of a deal appeared to hearten investors. After The New York Times reported yesterday that Sallie Mae was in talks on a buyout, shares of the company rose $6.01, or 14.75 percent, to $46.71 -- the biggest single-day gain ever for the company.</p>
        <p>Bradley Ball, an analyst with Citigroup, wrote in a note yesterday that an offer for Sallie Mae at $48.72 would seriously undervalue the company. He maintained a target price of $55 a share.</p>
        <p>Kathleen Shanley, an analyst with the research firm Gimme Credit, wrote yesterday that Sallie Mae was a ''poor candidate'' for a leveraged buyout. ''The company is dependent on access to the debt markets, has a razor-thin net interest margin and uses derivatives to manage its interest rate exposure,'' she wrote.</p>
        <p>Still, there are obvious attractions to Sallie Mae. It is by far the leader in the student loan business, with a $142 billion loan portfolio. It is both a lender and debt collector, making profits off both sides of its loans. Last year, the company earned $1.2 billion.</p>
        <p>For JPMorgan, a deal would bolster its own student lending business, run through its Chase Education Finance unit. The bank has made several acquisitions in recent years to bulk up that business, including a $633 million purchase of Collegiate Funding Services in 2005.</p>
        <p>From 1996 until 2005, Sallie Mae and JPMorgan ran a joint venture for student loans. JPMorgan originated the loans, which Sallie Mae then bought and serviced.</p>
        <p>The venture was dissolved after JPMorgan sued Sallie Mae, contending that its partner was undercutting the enterprise by lending directly to students.</p>
        <p>The discussions over a possible deal are taking place at a time when the student loan business has come under increased scrutiny, by the New York attorney general, Andrew Cuomo, and by lawmakers in Washington. Senate and House committees are looking into the relationships between lenders and college financial aid offices.</p>
        <p>In a statement yesterday, Representative George Miller, Democrat from California and chairman of the House Education and Labor Committee, said he was skeptical of efforts to take Sallie Mae private.</p>
        <p>''The American people must be able to hold lenders and schools accountable to ensure that federal student aid dollars are being properly used to help students and families pay for college,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some analysts noted yesterday that the involvement of a financial company like JPMorgan, with large capital and established influence in Washington, could make a buyout of Sallie Mae more palatable to lawmakers and regulators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
