<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Schumer and State Legislators Seek to Block Starrett City Sale</title>
    <meta content="14starrett" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/nyregion/14starrett.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840074"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Schumer, Charles E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Schumer and State Legislators Seek to Block Starrett City Sale</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Schumer and State Legislators Seek to Block Starrett City Sale</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer joined Democratic members of the State Assembly yesterday in a campaign to keep Starrett City from being sold in a $1.3 billion deal that they say would doom the vast Brooklyn housing complex as an affordable home for poor and working-class tenants.</p>
        <p>Senator Schumer called on federal housing officials to reject an investment group's plan to buy the 5,881 apartments on 140 acres on Jamaica Bay because it would require millions of dollars in additional subsidies and would fail to protect the current residents from rent increases and displacement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer joined Democratic members of the State Assembly yesterday in a campaign to keep Starrett City from being sold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer joined Democratic members of the State Assembly yesterday in a campaign to keep Starrett City from being sold in a $1.3 billion deal that they say would doom the vast Brooklyn housing complex as an affordable home for poor and working-class tenants.</p>
        <p>Senator Schumer called on federal housing officials to reject an investment group's plan to buy the 5,881 apartments on 140 acres on Jamaica Bay because it would require millions of dollars in additional subsidies and would fail to protect the current residents from rent increases and displacement.</p>
        <p>He and the Assembly Democrats, including Speaker Sheldon Silver, also announced plans to push for legislation that would extend rent regulation to apartments in the state's middle-class Mitchell-Lama housing program like the ones at Starrett City. They say that the current furor among politicians and tenant groups over the loss of affordable housing at Starrett City and other complexes in the city bodes well for passage.</p>
        <p>Built in 1974, Starrett City is the country's largest federally subsidized housing complex. Under federal and state law, the owners of the complex, Starrett City Associates, a group of investors led by Disque Deane, now have the right to buy out of the housing programs and raise the rents to market levels.</p>
        <p>''While we appreciate the 'tenets' of capitalism, it is the 'tenants' who must remain our No. 1 priority,'' Mr. Schumer said. ''We must act now to protect our affordable housing stock, or this city will become too expensive for the firefighters, police officers, teachers, nurses and so many other valued members of the work force upon whom we depend.''</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether the legislators could stop the sale, which needs the approval of state and federal housing agencies. But at the very least, the legislators have sought to create a political climate that would make it hard for either the buyer or the seller to convert the apartments to market rate. ''The need for affordable housing is more dire than ever,'' Assemblyman Vito J. Lopez said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer said yesterday that the heady purchase price, $1.4 billion when fees and closing costs are included, made it impossible to devise a viable affordable housing plan. He suggested that the owners hold a new auction or renegotiate the price, which he said should be closer to $900 million or $1 billion.</p>
        <p>In response to yesterday's announcement, Starrett City Associates said they planned to go through with the deal to sell the complex to a new investment group, Clipper Equity.</p>
        <p>''We intend to honor our contract,'' said Martin J. McLaughlin, a spokesman for Starrett City Associates.</p>
        <p>But executives who work with the present owners have said that if the deal fails, the owners may privatize the complex themselves, something that worries politicians and housing advocates.</p>
        <p>Clipper's general partner, David Bistricer, has said that the complex would remain an affordable haven for its current residents. He said he also planned to develop more housing on empty land in the complex, which sits between East New York and Canarsie.</p>
        <p>''Our commitment continues to be to retain affordability for Starrett City,'' said Lisa Linden, a spokeswoman for Mr. Bistricer's group. ''To the extent that the proposed legislation could help achieve that goal in a reasonable manner, we support its goals and objectives.''</p>
        <p>But the secretary of housing and urban development, Alphonso R. Jackson, rejected Mr. Bistricer's first proposal in March because it failed to include adequate financial information or a plan for how the complex would remain a ''viable community for New Yorkers of modest means.''</p>
        <p>And last week, the state's housing commissioner, Deborah Van Amerongen, formally rebuffed Mr. Bistricer's second proposal, saying it was unworkable under state housing laws. The federal Department of Housing and Urban Renewal is still reviewing the second proposal.</p>
        <p>Housing experts estimate that the federal, state and city governments funnel roughly $75 million a year in rent subsidies, tax breaks and interest rate reductions to Starrett City. Senator Schumer said that Mr. Bistricer's latest plan would ultimately require an additional $10 million a year in subsidies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
