<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Turtle Goes Home, in Old-School Style</title>
    <meta content="14hale" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/arts/television/14hale.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Turtles and Tortoises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reptiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Abraham, F Murray</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Voyage of the Lonely Turtle (TV Program)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4D6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Turtle Goes Home, in Old-School Style</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Turtle Goes Home, in Old-School Style</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE HALE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hale, Mike</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tomorrow night's installment of ''Nature'' on PBS, plaintively titled ''Voyage of the Lonely Turtle,'' is an odd throwback. It's the animal documentary as sentimental epic, with a stentorian voice -- in this case F. Murray Abraham's -- narrating, a little too poetically, the dangerous journey of a creature driven by some genetic imperative to travel thousands of miles.</p>
        <p>Risky encounters with bad weather, other animals and man occur at convenient dramatic intervals. The voyage completed, we wait to see if the exhausted animal survives. It feels as if it should be an early-1960s Saturday matinee, with Walt Disney giving an on-screen introduction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The “Voyage of the Lonely Turtle” installment of “Nature” on PBS is an animal documentary as sentimental epic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tomorrow night's installment of ''Nature'' on PBS, plaintively titled ''Voyage of the Lonely Turtle,'' is an odd throwback. It's the animal documentary as sentimental epic, with a stentorian voice -- in this case F. Murray Abraham's -- narrating, a little too poetically, the dangerous journey of a creature driven by some genetic imperative to travel thousands of miles.</p>
        <p>Risky encounters with bad weather, other animals and man occur at convenient dramatic intervals. The voyage completed, we wait to see if the exhausted animal survives. It feels as if it should be an early-1960s Saturday matinee, with Walt Disney giving an on-screen introduction.</p>
        <p>It also feels like a bit of bait and switch, at a time when television documentaries tend to be geekily scientific, with degree-laden talking heads explaining every aspect of what you're seeing. ''Voyage of the Lonely Turtle'' purports to show the once-in-a-lifetime, 9,000-mile trip of a particular loggerhead turtle from the coast of Mexico back to the beach in Japan where she was born.</p>
        <p>In the omniscient, let-us-worry-about-the-details style of an earlier era, it's never exactly made clear -- though it's intuitively obvious -- that the program is a stylish re-creation of such a voyage. No explanations are given for where or when particular scenes were filmed, so for all we know, the producers bought a random selection of underwater images and edited them together with their own shots of a cute, tagged loggerhead swimming who knows where.</p>
        <p>Adults and critically thinking children will quickly realize that they're watching an artfully patched-together fiction, but it's easy to imagine people of all ages, hearing the narration's references to ''this loggerhead turtle'' and a ''recent'' scientific tagging project, thinking that they're actually following that steadfast turtle on its incredible journey. This is PBS, after all! (In fact, as the PBS Web site pbs.org/wnet/nature makes clear, the tagged turtle on whose voyage the film is based made her trip, sans cameras, more than a decade ago.)</p>
        <p>For those who aren't bothered by nagging questions of authenticity, there's much to see here: breathtaking scenes of sharks and other predators attacking helpless schools of fish, leaving nothing but clouds of scales floating in the murky water; somber shots of turtle carcasses on the ocean floor, a reminder that these creatures drown if they don't reach the surface occasionally; and lots and lots of impressive or just plain weird sea life, from parasite-encrusted sunfish to hammerhead sharks to blue whales.</p>
        <p>The best way to watch ''Voyage of the Lonely Turtle'' would be on a Saturday afternoon at your local Imax theater. Uncle Walt could bring the munchies.</p>
        <p>Nature  Voyage of the Lonely Turtle</p>
        <p>On most PBS stations tomorrow night (check local listings).</p>
        <p>Fred Kaufman, series executive producer; William Grant, executive in charge; produced by Thirteen/WNET New York and BBC; Thirteen/WNET, series producer.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
