<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don Imus, Over and Out</title>
    <meta content="l14imus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Imus, Don</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Debley, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Lisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bogner, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ray, Allen L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kronenberg, Gretchen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cribelli, Teresa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wheelock, Kathleen E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DE103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don Imus, Over and Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letters from Tom Debley, Lisa Wilson, Michael Bogner, Allen L Ray, Gretchen Kronenberg, Teresa Cribelli and Kathleen E Wheelock respond to firing of Don Imus by CBS for his racist remark about Rutgers University women's basketball team</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Off the Air: The Light Goes Out for Don Imus'' (Business Day, April 13):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Off the Air: The Light Goes Out for Don Imus'' (Business Day, April 13):</p>
        <p>There is a hollow ring to the statement of the CBS chief executive, Leslie Moonves. He says Don Imus ''flourished in a culture that permits a certain level of objectionable expression that hurts and demeans a wide range of people. In taking him off the air, I believe we take an important and necessary step  in changing that culture, which extends far beyond the walls of our company.''</p>
        <p>The fact is ''shock jocks'' are called that for a reason. Radio and television executives have played a huge role in creating the culture that extends beyond their walls. Indeed, they shell out tens of millions of dollars a year to put ''shock jocks'' on the air because it returns tens of millions more in revenues.</p>
        <p>Tom Debley  Oakland, Calif., April 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I'm a white, prudish suburban woman with the requisite huffy indignation for all things racist and sexist. Yet I watched Don Imus most mornings. It often made me squirm, but I could justify the puerile banter as being another part of urban culture that I just didn't get. So I was ready to defend Mr. Imus because of the platform he provided for in-depth, high-caliber interviews.</p>
        <p>When I saw the young women of Rutgers, I was shamed as I have never been shamed before. I suddenly saw my very real contribution to our racial divide. Indifference. I'd been willing to dismiss the denigration of African-Americans and women because it's become common and because it suited me.</p>
        <p>And I learned the true meaning of grace and courage from those young women.</p>
        <p>Thank you all for showing me that I have much work to do.</p>
        <p>Lisa Wilson  Yarmouth, Me., April 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>There was a missed opportunity with the firing of Don Imus. Instead of opening a dialogue on a national level, the door has closed. We fool ourselves into thinking that the problems will go away with this firing.</p>
        <p>Michael Bogner  Manasquan, N.J., April 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It is shameful that CBS needed eight days to decide that Don Imus should be fired for his outrageous comments regarding the Rutgers women's basketball team. Mr. Imus should have been terminated immediately.</p>
        <p>While criticism of Mr. Imus is richly deserved, CBS deserves equal criticism for its delay in dismissing him. One suspects that CBS needed to see how public opinion evolved before it made the decision to terminate Mr. Imus. This was wrong.</p>
        <p>CBS should have evaluated Mr. Imus's comments for what they were and fired him immediately. CBS's termination process was substantially less than principled.</p>
        <p>Allen L. Ray  Skokie, Ill., April 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Our Prejudices, Ourselves,'' by Harvey Fierstein (Op-Ed, April 13):</p>
        <p>After the dust settles from Don Imus's racial slurs, will anything change for homosexuals or fat people? Probably not. It is not only shock jocks who so easily abuse gay and fat people, but also media stars, politicians and others in authority. Being gay or fat is too often treated as a moral failing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fierstein says it best: ''Prejudice tolerated is intolerance encouraged.''</p>
        <p>Gretchen Kronenberg  Belmont, Mass., April 13, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I agree with Bob Herbert (''Paying the Price,'' column, April 12) that if there is anything positive about Don Imus's recent racist and sexist remark, it's that it opens up a conversation about how profoundly prejudiced our culture really is. The sad part is that Mr. Imus will only eventually be replaced by a similar ''shock jock.''</p>
        <p>Why not boycott all such toxic commentary? I'm not advocating censorship, but when Americans quit listening to the Howard Sterns and Ann Coulters of the world, the media will stop putting them on the air. What passes for ''entertainment'' in our country is harming us.</p>
        <p>Teresa Cribelli  Rio de Janeiro, April 12, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Paying the Price,'' by Bob Herbert (column, April 12):</p>
        <p>It would seem to me that the huge, indignant outcry over Don Imus's ill-considered and unacceptable remarks about the young women of the Rutgers basketball team, rather than proof of ''just how profoundly racist and sexist the culture is,'' is in fact proof of just the opposite: American society has demonstrated its disgust loud and clear.</p>
        <p>Kathleen E. Wheelock  New York, April 12, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
