<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Google Buys an Online Ad Firm for $3.1 Billion</title>
    <meta content="14deal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/technology/14deal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Google Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Doubleclick Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hellman &amp; Friedman</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">JMI Equity</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Story, Louise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Helft, Miguel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmidt, Eric E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenblatt, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Google Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Google Buys an Online Ad Firm for $3.1 Billion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Google Buys an Online Ad Firm for $3.1 Billion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUISE STORY and MIGUEL HELFT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Helft, Miguel; Story, Louise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Google acquires DoubleClick, online advertising company, from private equity firms Hellman &amp; Friedman and JMI Equity for $3.1 billion in cash; deal is another step in Google's transformation from search engine into advertising powerhouse; DoubleClick specializes in software for display advertising and has close relationships with Web publishers, advertisers and advertising agencies; Google's chief executive Eric E Schmidt says merger is part of global growth strategy for company; DoubleClick's chief executive David Rosenblatt says his company's strength lies in flashy banner ads and video advertising; deal keeps DoubleClick from Microsoft; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Google agreed to its largest acquisition yesterday, reaching a deal to purchase DoubleClick, the online advertising company, from two private equity firms for $3.1 billion in cash, almost double what it paid for YouTube last year. And perhaps just as important, the deal kept DoubleClick from the hands of Microsoft.</p>
        <p>For Google, the purchase is another step in its transformation from a search engine into an advertising powerhouse. DoubleClick, which is based in New York City, specializes in software for display advertising and has close relationships with Web publishers, advertisers and advertising agencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Google agreed to its largest acquisition Friday, reaching a deal to purchase DoubleClick for almost double what it paid for YouTube last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Google agreed to its largest acquisition yesterday, reaching a deal to purchase DoubleClick, the online advertising company, from two private equity firms for $3.1 billion in cash, almost double what it paid for YouTube last year. And perhaps just as important, the deal kept DoubleClick from the hands of Microsoft.</p>
        <p>For Google, the purchase is another step in its transformation from a search engine into an advertising powerhouse. DoubleClick, which is based in New York City, specializes in software for display advertising and has close relationships with Web publishers, advertisers and advertising agencies.</p>
        <p>''It's the two juggernauts in search and display getting together,'' said Martin Reidy, president of Modem Media, an ad agency in the Publicis Groupe.</p>
        <p>For computer users, the deal could mean more advertising tailored to their online habits, especially if DoubleClick and Google combine some of their huge databases of information on Internet use to direct specific ads to different Web surfers' tastes.</p>
        <p>''This merger is really a part of a global growth strategy for Google,'' Eric E. Schmidt, Google's chief executive, said in a conference call.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schmidt said that being able to kick-start Google's display advertising business and marry it with search advertising was the most compelling reason for the purchase.</p>
        <p>The sale of DoubleClick involved weeks of negotiation that included at one point Yahoo, AOL and, most prominently, Microsoft, which has been trying to position itself as an advertising rival to Google. Even though Microsoft has more cash on hand than Google, the company was ultimately outbid.</p>
        <p>''Keeping Microsoft away from DoubleClick is worth billions to Google,'' an analyst with RBC Capital Markets, Jordan Rohan, said. ''Yet again, Microsoft is on the sidelines and away from the action.''</p>
        <p>The acquisition will also strengthen Google's position with respect to Yahoo, its chief rival in Internet search and advertising and a leader in the sale of display ads.</p>
        <p>DoubleClick may not be a household name, but it is the most prominent ad serving company on the Web, meaning that it delivers display ads from ad agencies to the sites where they are run.</p>
        <p>DoubleClick provides software and services to both Web publishers like MySpace and AOL and to advertisers and agencies, who buy the ads. DoubleClick's software culls data about Web surfers' interaction with ads to determine how to place the most effective display ads.</p>
        <p>Google, for all its outsize reputation, has made most of its money in the online basics: the text-based search engine and small text ads that are like the Yellow Pages of the online advertising. DoubleClick's strength, by contrast, lies in flashy banner ads and, more recently, video ads that are more like high-end magazine or television ads. Google has taken steps in the last year to enter display advertising by expanding its AdSense program but has not gained great traction.</p>
        <p>''Google really wants to get into the display advertising business in a big way, and they don't have the relationships they need to make it happen,'' said Dave Morgan, the chairman of Tacoda, an online advertising network. ''But DoubleClick does. It gives them immediate access to those relationships.''</p>
        <p>Google, of course, has its own formulas for aiming ads and has been very successful delivering text ads related to the content people are reading about. The two companies will work together to deliver what Google called ''more relevant'' ads in a news release.</p>
        <p>''You can dive deep into that data and say who were those people, where do they live, what were they doing when they looked at those ads?'' said Randall Rothenberg, the chief executive of the Internet Advertising Bureau, a group in New York that represents online publishers, including Google. ''You can protect privacy and provide great insights for advertisers.''</p>
        <p>The sale raises questions about how Google will manage its existing business and that of the new DoubleClick unit while avoiding conflicts of interest. If DoubleClick's existing clients start to feel that Google is using DoubleClick's relationships to further its own ad network, some Web publishers or advertisers might jump ship.</p>
        <p>Most of DoubleClick's clients are locked into long-term contracts to keep using DoubleClick. And DoubleClick's chief executive, David Rosenblatt, said in an interview last night that the company would protect its ability to remain neutral with its clients.</p>
        <p>''We are exquisitely sensitive to our role as Switzerland,'' Mr. Rosenblatt said. ''In the simplest sense, they bought customer relationships, and they're primarily focused on making sure not only are those relationships preserved but that they are enhanced and made better.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosenblatt said that Google's vast network of advertisers would offer DoubleClick publishers more opportunities to monetize their sites.</p>
        <p>A highflying stock in the late 1990s, DoubleClick was an early pioneer in online advertising and was one of the few online ad companies to survive the burst of the dot-com bubble. In 2005, it was taken private by two private equity firms, Hellman &amp; Friedman and JMI Equity, in a deal valued at $1.1 billion.</p>
        <p>Since then, the company has sold two data and e-mail advertising businesses and acquired Klipmart, which specializes in online video. DoubleClick generated about $300 million in revenue and $50 million in earnings before interest, depreciation and taxes last year, mostly from providing ads on Web sites.</p>
        <p>While some suggested that $3.1 billion was a high price for DoubleClick others said Google was buying far more than DoubleClick's cash flow. And, Google has plenty of cash to spare. At the end of last year it had $11.24 billion in cash and marketable securities.</p>
        <p>People close to the deal said it came down to a matter of price. Google outbid Microsoft, in an echo of a bout in December 2005 when the two rivals bid for the right to sell ads on Time Warner's AOL unit. Google won then, too, agreeing to pay $1 billion for a 5 percent stake in AOL.</p>
        <p>One attraction for Google was DoubleClick's new exchange that brings Web publishers and advertising buyers together on a Web site where they can participate in auctions for ad space.</p>
        <p>''What this represents is the further acceleration of Google creating the spine of being able to manage information on consumer entertainment,'' said Richard Beaven, chief executive of Initiative North American, an agency in the Interpublic Group of Companies that buys ads. ''In the context of that vision, this is a very important step.''</p>
        <p>PERSONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
