<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking His Theater Talent Well Over the Rainbow</title>
    <meta content="14gree" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/theater/14gree.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Terrence McNally</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenspan, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4D6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking His Theater Talent Well Over the Rainbow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Taking His Theater Talent Well Over the Rainbow</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Remember ''happenings''? I don't, actually. The term dates from the 1960s, when it was used to describe aesthetic events of somewhat spontaneous origin and general fabulousness. It has a quaint ring now, but it sprang to mind recently when I found myself searching for a way to describe the eruption of something unusual -- and, yes, fabulous -- in the middle of Terrence McNally's ''Some Men,'' a sweet, sentimental and otherwise unexceptional comedy of gay life in 20th-century America at the Second Stage Theater.</p>
        <p>The event in question occurred at the end of the first act, during a scene set in a piano bar full of sweater-wearing fellows nursing martinis, mourning the fresh loss of Judy Garland and wondering what all that racket is outside. (That would be the Stonewall riots, guys.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once seen  perhaps experienced is a better word  actor David Greenspan is not forgotten.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Remember ''happenings''? I don't, actually. The term dates from the 1960s, when it was used to describe aesthetic events of somewhat spontaneous origin and general fabulousness. It has a quaint ring now, but it sprang to mind recently when I found myself searching for a way to describe the eruption of something unusual -- and, yes, fabulous -- in the middle of Terrence McNally's ''Some Men,'' a sweet, sentimental and otherwise unexceptional comedy of gay life in 20th-century America at the Second Stage Theater.</p>
        <p>The event in question occurred at the end of the first act, during a scene set in a piano bar full of sweater-wearing fellows nursing martinis, mourning the fresh loss of Judy Garland and wondering what all that racket is outside. (That would be the Stonewall riots, guys.)</p>
        <p>Enter a drag queen, in a dainty white-and-peach ensemble, accessorized with white gloves, pearls and a foul tongue. Archie, as he is called, knows that the drag queens don't mix with the sweater set -- and doesn't take kindly to the fisheye he's getting from the bartender. A shrill rant ensues, until a friendly gesture from a patron calms the storm. Soon all feathers are unruffled, and the visitor kindly offers to sing a song to celebrate the peace, and pay tribute to the beloved performer who died for their sorrows, all too soon.</p>
        <p>The song chosen is -- no prizes for guessing -- ''Over the Rainbow,'' made immortal by the great Judy, and massacred by many a boozy band of brothers gathered round a piano over the last half-century or so. If you are now demanding to know how a drag queen singing this sentimental standard could possibly be described as anything but a camp cliché -- let alone a happening -- you need to make the acquaintance of the man singing it, an actor of uncommon gifts and uncommoner aspect named David Greenspan.</p>
        <p>Once seen -- perhaps experienced is a better word -- Mr. Greenspan, 51, is not forgotten. You may not be able to recall the play you saw him in -- like any actor, he's been in his share of negligible ones -- but the performer you would certainly remember. His notable appearances Off Broadway over the last decade or so have included revivals of ''The Boys in the Band'' and Tennessee Williams's ''Small Craft Warnings,'' Harry Kondoleon's ''Saved or Destroyed'' and a staging of Goethe's ''Faust,'' in which he played Mephistopheles.</p>
        <p>He has also written numerous plays (among them, ''She Stoops to Comedy,'' at Playwrights Horizons; ''Dead Mother, or Shirley Not All in Vain,'' at the Public) and directed them too. In June his solo play ''The Argument,'' based on the classical scholar Gerald Else's writings about Aristotle's ''Poetics,'' is being produced by the Target Margin Theater.</p>
        <p>Mainstream he certainly isn't, but his extensive career Off and Off Off Broadway is a testament to the ability of New York theater to accommodate the gifts of truly singular performers -- glorious freaks.</p>
        <p>Pressed to evoke his unique manner in a phrase, I'd say he's sort of like a David Lynch movie incarnated in a single human being. A little eerie, stylized, weirdly mesmerizing. And, unlike some of Mr. Lynch's movies, never boring. His looks are not particularly extraordinary -- aquiline nose, lush lips, sloping cheekbones -- but his presence is both contained and intense. He moves like a graceful animal on the prowl, a panther perhaps.</p>
        <p>Allergic to naturalism (he has this in common with most drag queens), Mr. Greenspan recalibrates his roles to suit his own, highly theatrical personal style. He speaks dialogue as if it's modernist music. Sometimes he chooses a note and sustains it with strange consistency. Or he'll move up and down a scale with a playful manner that seems to give a twisted or comic new meaning to the words he's speaking. Phrases are stretched and manipulated at will.</p>
        <p>I don't want to suggest that he overwhelms or betrays the intentions of the playwright. In ''Some Men'' Mr. Greenspan plays a trio of roles, and while he is hardly an actor who disappears into a character, he invests each with different colors from his distinctive palette that individualize each. It's a particularly valuable gift as applied to Mr. McNally's play, which sometimes tends toward the generalized in its wide-angled view of gay men's lives.</p>
        <p>As a middle-aged man being interviewed, with his life partner, by a couple of earnest young ''queer'' radicals investigating what appears to them to be the ancient history of the gay movement -- meaning stuff that happened 20 years ago -- he is warm and wryly mocking in his understanding of the gulf that separates them.</p>
        <p>In a scene set at a group therapy session for gay men, and later at a gay wedding, he plays a chronically sour and terminally single man dripping resentment and anomie. In the therapy scene Mr. Greenspan is particularly funny, at one point making a repeated apology -- ''Sorry, sorry, sorry'' -- sound exhausted, scornful, vindictive. In short, anything but remorseful.</p>
        <p>But it's Archie, the drag queen and the uncle of that peevish fellow in the group, who both stops the show and sends it soaring onto another plane entirely for the few minutes that he's singing. Avoiding the brass of a typical drag-queen belt, Mr. Greenspan quietly croons the song, retaining Archie's Long Island vowels, but investing the performance with a depth of feeling that carries us all outside Mr. McNally's amiable play for a moment.</p>
        <p>Suddenly this oft-sung song sounds strange again, its wistful plaint cutting to the heart with fresh immediacy. ''Over the Rainbow,'' fresh? Perhaps you'd have to see Mr. Greenspan to believe it. But Judy Garland, the glorious freak who immortalized the song and surely grew sick of it shortly thereafter, would probably be pleased.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
