<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nose With an Imagination, And Hard-Boiled Crime</title>
    <meta content="14burn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/movies/14burn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beach, Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liotta, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">L L Cool J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Slow Burn (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">LL Cool J</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Slow Burn (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFD6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nose With an Imagination, And Hard-Boiled Crime</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nose With an Imagination, and Hard-Boiled Crime</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews film Slow Burn, written and directed by Wayne Beach; Ray Liotta and James Todd Smith, aka L L Cool Jstar; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''She walks in smelling like mashed potatoes, and every guy within 30 feet wants to be the gravy.'' Such mouthfuls of hard-boiled nonsense regularly erupt from Luther Pinks (James Todd Smith, a k a LL Cool J, as he is billed) in ''Slow Burn,'' a wooden police thriller that is as dull as it is impenetrable and ultimately beyond ludicrous. Luther has a thing about odors. People and places conjure the scents of grapefruit, mangoes and tangerines and even Big Macs in his amazingly sensitive nostrils.</p>
        <p>Luther might be an F.B.I. agent, a gangster, both or neither in a movie so haphazardly put together that it has the coherence of fragments tossed into the air and randomly reassembled. There's not a line of dialogue in the movie, directed and written by Wayne Beach, that doesn't sound squeezed from a grade C ''Law &amp; Order'' imitator affecting a bogus inner-city street cred.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Slow Burn” is a wooden police thriller that is as dull as it is impenetrable and ultimately beyond ludicrous.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''She walks in smelling like mashed potatoes, and every guy within 30 feet wants to be the gravy.'' Such mouthfuls of hard-boiled nonsense regularly erupt from Luther Pinks (James Todd Smith, a k a LL Cool J, as he is billed) in ''Slow Burn,'' a wooden police thriller that is as dull as it is impenetrable and ultimately beyond ludicrous. Luther has a thing about odors. People and places conjure the scents of grapefruit, mangoes and tangerines and even Big Macs in his amazingly sensitive nostrils.</p>
        <p>Luther might be an F.B.I. agent, a gangster, both or neither in a movie so haphazardly put together that it has the coherence of fragments tossed into the air and randomly reassembled. There's not a line of dialogue in the movie, directed and written by Wayne Beach, that doesn't sound squeezed from a grade C ''Law &amp; Order'' imitator affecting a bogus inner-city street cred.</p>
        <p>Ray Liotta is the crime-busting district attorney Ford Cole, whose slinky assistant Nora Timmer (Jolene Blalock) is his part-time lover. Nora has had remarkable success infiltrating the underworld of the unnamed Everycity through which the movie scuffles like a rat in a sewer. Ford's troubles begin when Nora claims to have been raped, and her connections to an enigmatic crime lord whom no one has ever seen point toward layers of duplicity and corruption involving a $500 million real estate scheme and offshore assets.</p>
        <p>Nora is frequently referred to as a chameleon and a trick of the light. Is she really African-American, as we initially are led to believe, or is she posing as one? Whatever she is, she is without charm, though not without a certain chilly allure. Her labored lip-locks with Isaac Duparde (Mekhi Phifer), a cabdriver and a second candidate for the movie's crime lord, have all the warmth of a cold shower in a meat locker.</p>
        <p>Taye Diggs, who appears late in the movie, is a third suspect. Even Ford himself falls under suspicion. Hanging around police headquarters is a nosy reporter (Chiwetel Ejiofor), who is working on a profile of Ford.</p>
        <p>Trudging through this mess, Mr. Liotta looks extremely uncomfortable. He bellows his hopeless dialogue in the sad hope that raising the volume can add authenticity. He should be red in the face in more ways than one.</p>
        <p>''Slow Burn'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes sexual situations, violence, strong language and some nudity.</p>
        <p>Slow Burn  Opened yesterday nationwide.</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Wayne Beach; based on a story by Mr. Beach and Anthony Walton; director of photography, Wally Pfister; edited by Kristina Boden; music by Jeff Rona with songs by Wax Poetics; production designer, Tim Galvin; produced by Fisher Stevens, Sidney Kimmel, Bonnie Timmerman and Tim Williams; released by Lionsgate. Running time: 93 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Ray Liotta (Ford Cole), James Todd Smith, a k a LL Cool J (Luther Pinks), Mekhi Phifer (Isaac Duparde), Bruce McGill (Godfrey), Chiwetel Ejiofor (Ty Trippin), Taye Diggs (Jeffrey Sykes) and Jolene Blalock (Nora Timmer).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
