<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Seeking Red Truck That Left the Crash Scene</title>
    <meta content="14trooper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/nyregion/14trooper.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CORZINE'S CRASH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEEDE103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Seeking Red Truck That Left the Crash Scene</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Highway Instant, a Driver Is Tested</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE F. KOVALESKI and RICHARD G. JONES; David Kocieniewski contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kovaleski, Serge F; Jones, Richard G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Police officials were scouring New Jersey yesterday for a red Ford pickup truck that is believed to have fled the scene Thursday evening after setting off the chain-reaction accident in which Gov. Jon S. Corzine was seriously injured, officials said.</p>
        <p>One official who had been briefed on the investigation said the police have identified at least one truck that is similar to the one involved in the crash in the northbound lanes of the Garden State Parkway. It was spotted on security video moving through a parkway toll booth after using an E-ZPass shortly after the accident, the official said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>State police supervisors said they were pleased with the way Trooper Robert J. Rasinski, who was driving Gov. Jon S. Corzine’s car, had reacted to the sudden appearance of another vehicle in his lane.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Police officials were scouring New Jersey yesterday for a red Ford pickup truck that is believed to have fled the scene Thursday evening after setting off the chain-reaction accident in which Gov. Jon S. Corzine was seriously injured, officials said.</p>
        <p>One official who had been briefed on the investigation said the police have identified at least one truck that is similar to the one involved in the crash in the northbound lanes of the Garden State Parkway. It was spotted on security video moving through a parkway toll booth after using an E-ZPass shortly after the accident, the official said.</p>
        <p>The authorities said they were interviewing tollbooth clerks and reviewing the video from the toll plazas. They were looking for late-1980s or early-1990s Ford F-150 truck that witnesses said caused the accident. The truck was described as a two-wheel-drive, faded-red pickup with a red or white cap over the truck bed.</p>
        <p>If an E-ZPass was used at a toll plaza, it may be possible to track him through account information, police officials said.</p>
        <p>The closest tollbooth on the northbound side of the parkway is about 10 miles north, but there is an exit closer to the crash site.</p>
        <p>The police report released yesterday faults the driver of the red truck for barreling back onto the two-lane parkway after veering erratically onto the shoulder, a maneuver that began the sequence of events that led the governor's S.U.V. to crash Thursday evening.</p>
        <p>The identity and conduct of the driver are two questions facing investigators as they try to plot the crash that has left the governor in critical condition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine had just delivered a speech in Atlantic City and was en route, though late, to a meeting in Princeton with the Rutgers University women's basketball team and Don Imus, the talk-show host who had been fired earlier that day for his racist and sexist characterization of the players.</p>
        <p>At the wheel of his black 2005 Suburban was state Trooper Robert J. Rasinski, who had joined the governor's security detail a year ago. The assignment included driving the governor, and the training included instruction in protecting him from assassination attempts and other threats.</p>
        <p>As the Suburban was northbound in the left lane of the parkway as it passes through Galloway Township, the red pickup, which had been on the right shoulder, moved erratically into the flow of traffic, jerking into the right northbound lane. That forced the driver of a white 2003 Dodge Ram pickup truck to swerve to the left to avoid it.</p>
        <p>In doing so, the Dodge smacked the right front corner of the governor's vehicle, which then spun out in a clockwise direction before the driver's side slammed into the end of a guardrail in the median at milepost 43.4, according to an accident report by the state police.</p>
        <p>''The guardrail penetrated the vehicle and struck both Rasinski and Governor Corzine,'' the one-page document said. Aides and the police explained that Mr. Corzine, who was sitting in the front passenger seat and apparently was not wearing a safety belt, hit his head on the windshield and was then thrown into the back of the vehicle.</p>
        <p>The police said they were still investigating whether the air bag on the governor's side of the car deployed as it should. Photos of the vehicle do not appear to show a deployed bag.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine broke his left leg, sternum, collarbone, six ribs on each side and a lower vertebra. After rescue workers pulled him from the rear of the S.U.V. -- shrouding his body in blankets, placing an oxygen mask on him and strapping him into a gurney -- he was whisked to a waiting helicopter on the closed roadway and flown to Cooper University Hospital in Camden.</p>
        <p>State police supervisors said Trooper Rasinski had reacted appropriately to the sudden appearance of another vehicle in his lane. Col. Joseph R. Fuentes, superintendent of the state police, called it ''an excellent job.''</p>
        <p>The trooper was also carried by helicopter to the hospital, but police officials said yesterday that, at his request, they would not discuss his injuries. He was released from the hospital yesterday, according to the third passenger in the car, an aide to the governor, Samantha Gordon. She was in the back seat and using a phone at the time of the accident and was shaken up, the police said.</p>
        <p>The driver of the white Dodge pickup truck, John M. Carrino Jr., 24, of Glenwood, N.J., pulled over and was not injured in the accident, according to the police.</p>
        <p>''We have no issues with that driver in that car,'' said Capt. Al Della Fave, a spokesman for the state police.</p>
        <p>Officials are investigating what role speed may have played in the crash, but they will not have a firm estimate until they analyze things like skid marks and damage to Mr. Corzine's S.U.V.</p>
        <p>Trooper Rasinski began working with the executive protection unit, a division of the state police that serves as bodyguards and drivers for the governor, last April.</p>
        <p>The unit is housed in a small office in a basement of the State House and goes about its work with such secrecy that officials refused to release a photograph of the trooper, a 34-year-old resident of Ocean County who has been a trooper for nine years.</p>
        <p>CORZINE'S CRASH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
