<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Immigration, Through Many Lenses</title>
    <meta content="l14immig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Ed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wickremaratne, Sonali</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landever, Arthur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koppel, John S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5DE103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Immigration, Through Many Lenses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letters from Ed White, Sonali Wickremaratne, Arthur Landever and John S Koppel comment on immigration debate</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>According to ''Bush on the Border'' (editorial, April 11), the president displayed his understanding of the immigration issue when he said ''America suffers from a system that exploits people who come to do jobs that citizens won't do.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>According to ''Bush on the Border'' (editorial, April 11), the president displayed his understanding of the immigration issue when he said ''America suffers from a system that exploits people who come to do jobs that citizens won't do.''</p>
        <p>But many of these jobs are shunned because of the abysmal compensation more than because of the nature of the work.</p>
        <p>This conception of immigration merely perpetuates the gross income inequalities in our society, which in turn reinforces the perception of low-paid immigrants as second class. Without just compensation, everyone is exploited by such jobs, immigrant and citizen alike.</p>
        <p>Ed White  Knoxville, Tenn., April 11, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bush Ties Drop in Illegal Immigration to His Policies'' (news article, April 10):</p>
        <p>The absence of an organized process to manage the influx of illegal immigrants to the United States is understood. It is frequently expressed by the White House. But when will the politicians and the public address the chaotic immigration process available for legal immigrants?</p>
        <p>Millions of legal immigrants (including me) have been standing in line for years in hope of citizenship. The route to citizenship is painful, unreasonable and impractical.</p>
        <p>I am not against managing the influx of illegal immigrants. But legal immigrants deserve a practical answer to their immigration miseries.</p>
        <p>Sonali Wickremaratne  Atlanta, April 10, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The immigration debate focuses upon the ''usual suspects'': the millions of undocumented aliens in the United States (and what we ought to do about them). But let's not forget about other possible elements in a sound and creative immigration package.</p>
        <p>Presumably, there are countless children of ''genius'' languishing, undiscovered, in the third world. Why not start a pilot program, with the cooperation of home governments, to search out and identify such youngsters and give them an opportunity to come to America with their parents and be educated here?</p>
        <p>Their governments could be enticed by financing and by retaining an option to educate half the ''discovered'' at home. As to the children who accept the chance to come to the United States, surely they would enrich us with their talent as we empowered them and taught them about America.</p>
        <p>Arthur Landever  Cleveland, April 11, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a professor at the Cleveland-Marshall College of Law, Cleveland State University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''U.S. Raid on an Immigrant Household Deepens Anger and Mistrust on L.I.'' (news article, April 10) illustrates the ugly xenophobia, racism, classism and cultural intolerance underlying the anti-immigrant furor that has swept the country.</p>
        <p>It appears that the Leon family was targeted by both local and federal authorities chiefly for the ''offense'' of being relatively poor Hispanics in the wealthy Hamptons.</p>
        <p>What is particularly egregious is that many prosperous people who object so loudly to the presence of Hispanic immigrants have no problem with such immigrants -- legal or illegal -- when they are cleaning the houses of the affluent, mowing lawns or doing construction work, all for low wages.</p>
        <p>John S. Koppel  Bethesda, Md., April 10, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
