<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Illinois, Hunters Discover Ideal Setting for Trophy Bucks</title>
    <meta content="14outdoors" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/sports/othersports/14outdoors.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Illinois</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Illinois, Hunters Discover Ideal Setting for Trophy Bucks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Illinois, Hunters Discover Ideal Setting for Trophy Bucks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM VAUGHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vaughn, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSFIELD, Ill.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The natural abilities of the United States' most widely distributed big-game animal, the white-tailed deer, are amazing. It can leap tall fences, see small movement from a great distance, and even tell if a tiny, drifting scent belongs to the same farmer who is out in his fields regularly or to one of the human predators who infiltrate the woods every fall.</p>
        <p>A deer can also cause a debilitating increase in the pulse of an archery deer hunter, especially when it eases into view like royalty with a crown of antlers, massive in diameter and spread. And, if such a trophy buck resides in a region where there are many more like him, it can also change a local economy. This may be the animal's most impressive feat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every truly dedicated deer hunter has heard stories about huge bucks taken from Pike County, which leads all Illinois counties every year in total deer taken.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The natural abilities of the United States' most widely distributed big-game animal, the white-tailed deer, are amazing. It can leap tall fences, see small movement from a great distance, and even tell if a tiny, drifting scent belongs to the same farmer who is out in his fields regularly or to one of the human predators who infiltrate the woods every fall.</p>
        <p>A deer can also cause a debilitating increase in the pulse of an archery deer hunter, especially when it eases into view like royalty with a crown of antlers, massive in diameter and spread. And, if such a trophy buck resides in a region where there are many more like him, it can also change a local economy. This may be the animal's most impressive feat.</p>
        <p>The deer have done just that for Pike County in west-central Illinois.</p>
        <p>Every truly dedicated deer hunter has heard stories about huge bucks taken from Pike County. It leads all Illinois counties every year in total deer taken. It has also led the nation in number of submissions to the Boone and Crockett Club record book for nontypical bucks for the past 10 years.</p>
        <p>Brenda Middendorf is the coordinator of Access Illinois Outdoors, which she said was ''similar to a dating service'' for landowners with hunting property and hunters wishing to find land to hunt on for a fee. She said the fame of the area's large-sized ungulates has helped raise total land value in the county an estimated $80 million.</p>
        <p>There are 58 registered outfitters and 260 guides in the county, and Middendorf said any business operator who could conceivably serve a tourist would say that hunting season makes their economic year.</p>
        <p>Tim Krumwiede, a district wildlife biologist for Region IV of the Illinois Department of Natural Resources, said the bucks' presence in Pike County was no mystery. Trophy deer are produced by outstanding habitat that provides good nutrition and great cover, combined with factors that reduce the loss of the animals before they have a chance to grow big.</p>
        <p>The central latitudes of the United States have increasingly milder winters that are strong enough to allow deer to grow large, Krumwiede said, but not harsh enough to reduce buck numbers. The rich agricultural production of this region does not hurt, either.</p>
        <p>Pike County lies in what hunters call the Golden Triangle, formed by the confluence of two river systems, the Illinois and the Mississippi. The Illinois River flood plain on the east and the Mississippi's on the west are bordered by bluffs, creating an intervening topography of ridge tops with small pasture and crop fields. They are bordered by draws and hills of quality hardwood timber, especially in the southern part of the county. The steep hills and brushy hollows allow deer to hide or escape easily and, with the forest browse and acorns, create ideal deer territory.</p>
        <p>Pike County also benefits from factors that are not influenced by nature, like sound management. Many outfitters have adopted restrictions on the antler size of bucks harvested and have incorporated wildlife-specific foods plots that last through the year.</p>
        <p>As Pike County's reputation among hunters has spread throughout the country, access to land has become an issue. Land leases and purchases have boomed, with more and more people wanting to grow and hunt trophy deer --then profit by offering hunting opportunities to others. Some outfitters are based in other states, and a huge influx of nonresident hunters occurs every fall.</p>
        <p>Chamber of Commerce members are pleased, landowners supplement their income by leasing land for $70 to $90 an acre and some residents have become millionaires by selling their property. But the surge of outsiders has its drawbacks. Cathy Chamberlain of Nebo, who rents and leads her horses for a local guest lodge, expressed an increasingly common sentiment here: The locals are feeling crowded by hunters from other places who are flocking to Pike County.</p>
        <p>''My sons used to hunt this land,'' she said, referring to the 1,200 acres owned by the lodge. ''Now, they have about 30 acres they can hunt.''</p>
        <p>Jeremy Priest of Pittsfield, a hunter and taxidermist, said he grew up freely hunting his grandfather's land. ''Now I have to lease 300 acres of land from my own grandfather to be able to hunt,'' he said. ''I'll get a guide's license and take other hunters to help with the cost.''</p>
        <p>Despite the frustration of limited land access, no one here is hoping the coveted deer population goes away. After all, this is a region that takes its hunting seriously. The first Friday of deer season when firearms are permitted is a school holiday.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
