<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Banker Gathers His Defenders, but There Aren't Many</title>
    <meta content="14wolfowitz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/washington/14wolfowitz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riza, Shaha Ali</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Bank</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5DF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Banker Gathers His Defenders, but There Aren't Many</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Banker Gathers His Defenders, but There Aren’t Many</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN; Jim Rutenberg contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Disclosure of World Bank pres Paul D Wolfowitz's involvement in raise given to his companion, Shaha Ali Riza, has stirred furor within bank and prompted demands from its staff association that he step down; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz, the embattled president of the World Bank, worked behind the scenes on Friday to gain the support of finance and development ministers from around the world, but there were few endorsements of his leadership outside the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>''We must just allow the process to work through,'' said Trevor Manuel, the finance minister of South Africa, referring to the bank board's announcement on Friday that it would continue to weigh Mr. Wolfowitz's role in the transfer and pay raise of his companion after he became president in 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were few endorsements of the leadership of Paul D. Wolfowitz, the embattled president of the World Bank, outside the Bush administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz, the embattled president of the World Bank, worked behind the scenes on Friday to gain the support of finance and development ministers from around the world, but there were few endorsements of his leadership outside the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>''We must just allow the process to work through,'' said Trevor Manuel, the finance minister of South Africa, referring to the bank board's announcement on Friday that it would continue to weigh Mr. Wolfowitz's role in the transfer and pay raise of his companion after he became president in 2005.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manuel also said the bank must avoid a rush to judgment. But Mr. Manuel is close to Mr. Wolfowitz, and the failure to praise him was significant. Mr. Wolfowitz visited South Africa this year and has called Mr. Manuel one of Africa's most talented leaders.</p>
        <p>In Paris, a Foreign Ministry spokesman was similarly tepid and noncommittal, noting that the bank's board had a process under way. He said France would make its own views known when appropriate.</p>
        <p>Throughout the day, Bush administration officials praised Mr. Wolfowitz's leadership, but at an evening news conference, Treasury Secretary Henry M. Paulson Jr. said that because the bank board was still considering the matter, he would not comment on what he thought the outcome should be.</p>
        <p>''This should not be read as any lessening of the United States' support for Paul Wolfowitz,'' he said. Asked specifically if he would call for Mr. Wolfowitz to remain as head of the World Bank, he responded, ''I said what I said.''</p>
        <p>The disclosure on Thursday of Mr. Wolfowitz's involvement in the raise given to his companion, Shaha Ali Riza, has stirred a furor within the bank and prompted demands from its staff association that he step down. Board members are said to be considering whether to reprimand him or encourage him to resign.</p>
        <p>Bank officials familiar with the thinking of some of the 24 members of the board, who represent countries or groups of countries, said they were uncertain how to proceed and would be consulting this weekend with finance ministers here for meetings of the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund.</p>
        <p>The bank leadership was also looking for a signal from the United States, including an indication as to whether President Bush would insist that Mr. Wolfowitz had done nothing wrong, or whether some in the administration might encourage him to resign from an institution that is in a virtual uprising against his leadership.</p>
        <p>''He could decide that his relationship with the staff and the board is so soured that he doesn't have the trust he needs to go forward,'' one administration official said, adding that he saw no evidence the White House was pushing for that.</p>
        <p>Early Friday morning, after meeting the previous evening, the bank's board released a sheaf of documents about Mr. Wolfowitz's decision to direct the bank's vice president for human resources to reassign Ms. Riza to the State Department with a promotion, a raise and guarantees of future raises and promotions.</p>
        <p>The staff association has charged that several of Mr. Wolfowitz's actions violated normal bank rules.</p>
        <p>The board issued a statement saying that Mr. Wolfowitz did not involve the ethics and legal counsel in many of the decisions relating to the transfer, contrary to earlier suggestions by Mr. Wolfowitz. But it did not conclude that he had deliberately flouted the rules.</p>
        <p>The 7,000 employees of the World Bank in Washington have been exchanging e-mail messages and comments, many of them critical of Mr. Wolfowitz but some expressing sympathy with his situation and his dealings with Ms. Riza, who had been a bank officer for seven years when he became president in 2005.</p>
        <p>Supporters and critics of Mr. Wolfowitz seized on the documents as evidence for the two different points of view.</p>
        <p>On one hand, the documents made it clear that Mr. Wolfowitz was very much involved in the decision to give Ms. Riza a raise to more than $190,000 a year, with the aim of compensating her for the disruption of the transfer, but critics said he violated his own preaching to the bank about the need for transparency and integrity.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Mr. Wolfowitz's defenders noted that the documents showed he had tried to recuse himself from involvement in personnel decisions affecting Ms. Riza when he arrived at the bank, and reluctantly became involved in her transfer only after the head of ethics for the board directed him to do so.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz remained out of public view on Friday, as did Ms. Riza, a British citizen who was born in Libya. But the board's documents provided a glimpse into the emotions of both as they struggled to reconcile their professional and personal lives.</p>
        <p>In his first month at the bank, Mr. Wolfowitz appeared from the documents to have been almost preoccupied by the matter. He had at first tried to allow Ms. Riza to stay at the bank and even to deal with her professionally there, with the promise to recuse himself if conflicts arose. That wish was denied by the ethics staff.</p>
        <p>With some irritation, Mr. Wolfowitz wrote a note in August 2005 saying the ethics committee had ''explicitly directed me to resolve the matter by providing instruction'' to a vice president for human resources. Later, he sent that vice president a directive that Ms. Riza be given promotions and pay raises. The documents show that the officials involved in making arrangements for the transfer to the State Department included J. Scott Carpenter, a deputy assistant secretary of state.</p>
        <p>Ms. Riza displayed even more displeasure in a letter written to the board this month from her position as an adviser to a semi-independent foundation that promotes democracy. She said she felt ''victimized for agreeing to an arrangement that I have objected to, and that I did not believe from the outset was in my best interest.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
