<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Music in Review; Monk Tribute -- TriBeCa Performing Arts Center</title>
    <meta content="14roun-2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Music in Review; Monk Tribute -- TriBeCa Performing Arts Center</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE CHINEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chinen, Nate</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roughly six months from now, the world will celebrate what would have been the 90th birthday of the pianist and composer Thelonious Monk. On Thursday night, concertgoers at the TriBeCa Performing Arts Center got a generous head start, at the latest installment of Jack Kleinsinger's longstanding series Highlights in Jazz.</p>
        <p>Monk, who died in 1982 but withdrew from the public years earlier, has hardly slipped into oblivion. His piquant harmonic language and craggy instrumental style are enduring features of the jazz landscape, and show no signs of fading. The main attractions of Mr. Kleinsinger's tribute were the pianist Kenny Barron and a group led by the drummer Ben Riley, and neither had to adjust his style to suit the occasion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roughly six months from now, the world will celebrate what would have been the 90th birthday of the pianist and composer Thelonious Monk. On Thursday night, concertgoers at the TriBeCa Performing Arts Center got a generous head start, at the latest installment of Jack Kleinsinger's longstanding series Highlights in Jazz.</p>
        <p>Monk, who died in 1982 but withdrew from the public years earlier, has hardly slipped into oblivion. His piquant harmonic language and craggy instrumental style are enduring features of the jazz landscape, and show no signs of fading. The main attractions of Mr. Kleinsinger's tribute were the pianist Kenny Barron and a group led by the drummer Ben Riley, and neither had to adjust his style to suit the occasion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Riley, a Monk alumnus, appeared with his Monk Legacy Septet, which released a refreshing album called ''Memories of T'' last year. The group consists of trumpet, three saxophones, guitar, bass and drums; the omission of a pianist is purposeful. Don Sickler, the trumpeter, also serves as an arranger and musical director, and at times his horn arrangements reach beyond the surface details of melody, toward the chiming piano interjections that Monk would often work into the songs.</p>
        <p>On ''Brake's Sake,'' a lesser-known tune that opened the concert, Mr. Sickler and the alto saxophonist Bruce Williams played a jauntily syncopated line; on the piano it would have been the part assigned to the right hand. Across the stage, Wayne Escoffery and Jay Brandford played an upward-creeping countermelody -- the left-handed part -- on, respectively, tenor and baritone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Riley plays with a cruising time feel, a shade behind the beat. So the burden of propulsion fell largely upon the bassist Kiyoshi Kitagawa and the guitarist Freddie Bryant. They struggled with the task on ''Bemsha Swing,'' but grew steadily stronger, building up to a fluent ''Bye-Ya.'' The band finally seemed warmed up, but too late: after a tantalizing dose of ''Epistrophy,'' they were done.</p>
        <p>The concert's second half featured Mr. Barron alone at the piano, an intimate and altogether more rewarding experience. But where Mr. Riley and his crew had built their set as a crescendo, Mr. Barron took the opposite approach, opening with a frenetic take on ''Well You Needn't.'' His elaboration -- a quick stream of 16th notes, with occasional bass-clef harrumphs -- hugged the song's contours like a stock car circling a track.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barron went on to play a gentler ''Ask Me Now,'' a highlight of the evening. Oddly, he closed with a medley of songs unaffiliated with Monk, including several by Billy Strayhorn. It was beautiful, though, and Mr. Barron made it fit. The only disappointment was that he didn't play at all with Mr. Riley, his longtime partner in Sphere, a well-traveled Monk repertory band. (Given that Mr. Kitagawa is Mr. Barron's regular bassist, a trio number surely could have been arranged.)</p>
        <p>That was the only musical disappointment, anyway. Amiri Baraka, reading some Monk-related poems, didn't linger long enough to scratch beyond the surface. And then there was the actor Rome Neal, who portrayed Monk not long ago in a one-man play. Appearing onstage periodically to deliver clumsily conceived monologues, Mr. Neal reduced his subject to a caricature. It was a poor corollary to the music, and the effort that created it.</p>
        <p>NATE CHINEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
