<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Senator Will Not Run For Governor Of Louisiana</title>
    <meta content="14lousiana" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/us/14lousiana.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Louisiana</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nossiter, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Breaux, John B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Louisiana</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Breaux, John B</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EEDF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Senator Will Not Run For Governor Of Louisiana</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Senator Will Not Run for Governor of Louisiana</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NOSSITER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nossiter, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former US Sen John B Breaux, Democrat, declares that he will not be candidate in Louisiana governor's race (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former United States Senator, John B. Breaux, ended his monthslong flirtation with the Louisiana governor's race Friday evening, declaring that he would be not be a candidate in the election this fall.</p>
        <p>The decision seemed likely to disappoint Democrats in the state who saw Mr. Breaux as a unifying figure for a party damaged by the perceived post-Hurricane Katrina missteps of Gov. Kathleen Babineaux Blanco. Last month, Ms. Blanco said she would not seek re-election, and Mr. Breaux was looked to as a candidate who could mediate between the state's disparate factions, as he did in his 18-year Senate career.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John B. Breaux’s announcement on Friday came after the state attorney general refused to declare him a Louisiana “citizen” under the state’s Constitution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former United States Senator, John B. Breaux, ended his monthslong flirtation with the Louisiana governor's race Friday evening, declaring that he would be not be a candidate in the election this fall.</p>
        <p>The decision seemed likely to disappoint Democrats in the state who saw Mr. Breaux as a unifying figure for a party damaged by the perceived post-Hurricane Katrina missteps of Gov. Kathleen Babineaux Blanco. Last month, Ms. Blanco said she would not seek re-election, and Mr. Breaux was looked to as a candidate who could mediate between the state's disparate factions, as he did in his 18-year Senate career.</p>
        <p>His announcement on Friday came after the state attorney general refused to declare him a Louisiana ''citizen'' under the state's Constitution. Republicans in Louisiana had already begun to use the issue of what they said were shaky ties to the state against Mr. Breaux, who is now a lobbyist, in advertising and public pronouncements, even though he never officially declared his candidacy. They cited his Maryland driver's license, among other things, in asserting that Mr. Breaux had long ceased to be a ''citizen'' of Louisiana, a point on which the state's Constitution is ambiguous.</p>
        <p>Mr. Breaux, in response, announced last month that he would be guided by the opinion of Attorney General Charles C. Foti Jr. But on Friday, Mr. Foti declined to come down on one side or the other, saying the matter should be left up to the Louisiana courts, which would have been nearly certain to take it up after official qualifying in September, given the likelihood of a Republican lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Hours later, Mr. Breaux said he would not run.</p>
        <p>''For me to run now means that we would face a campaign based on an eligibility to run, with the prospects of being in a courtroom only weeks before the election,'' he said in a statement. ''That is not in the best interest of our state or what this election should be about.''</p>
        <p>Louisiana voters have watched Mr. Breaux flirt with the governor's race before, but this time he appeared to be more serious, reportedly telling associates months ago he wanted to run if Ms. Blanco stepped out.</p>
        <p>His decision leaves the governor's race, normally a free-for-all of rhetoric and aggressive campaigning, even more wide open. Several big-name Louisiana Democrats could now enter the race, including the lieutenant governor, Mitch Landrieu, who ran unsuccessfully for mayor of New Orleans last spring. Mr. Landrieu, a scion of one of the state's leading political families, was traveling back from New York on Friday evening and could not be reached.</p>
        <p>Under Louisiana's electoral system, all candidates irrespective of party run together in an open primary, in October, and the top two vote-getters then face each other in a runoff if neither receives more than 50 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>The position of the leading Republican, Representative Bobby Jindal, who represents the New Orleans suburbs, is improved by Mr. Breaux's decision, analysts said. A Democrat already in the race, Foster Campbell, a member of the state's Public Service Commission, which regulates utilities, is not well-known statewide, though he is considered an effective and colorful orator in the tradition of the state's politicians.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jindal ran for governor in 2003 against Ms. Blanco. Though he leads in early polls and has demonstrated impressive fund-raising strength, reportedly having raised over $5 million already, Mr. Jindal, the son of Indian immigrants, still must face a conservative rural electorate that voted decisively for his Cajun opponent four years ago. Analysts noted at the time that Ms. Blanco had polled well in parishes carried by David Duke, the former Ku Klux Klan leader, in the 1991 governor's race.</p>
        <p>''Jindal's clearly the favorite now, but you will see one Democrat or another jump in,'' said Wayne Parent, a political scientist at Louisiana State University. ''I think the race gets very interesting right now.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Parent said, ''Democrats not associated with one candidate or another are going to be disappointed. John Breaux is a very popular figure in Louisiana, and Democrats are going to have to look to someone else.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
