<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ATHLETICS 5, YANKEES 4, 11 INNINGS: Yankees' Bullpen Can't Secure Igawa's First Victory</title>
    <meta content="14yanks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/sports/baseball/14yanks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1D8103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ATHLETICS 5, YANKEES 4, 11 INNINGS: Yankees' Bullpen Can't Secure Igawa's First Victory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yankees’ Bullpen Can’t Secure Igawa’s First Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Joe Torre summoned Kyle Farnsworth in the seventh inning on Friday, three outs earlier than usual, it was a subtle demotion. Farnsworth is usually the eighth inning pitcher for the Yankees, but he has been shaky lately and cannot work more than one inning at a time. He did nothing to restore his manager's faith.</p>
        <p>Kei Igawa's chance for his first major league victory vanished when Farnsworth allowed a two-out, game-tying home run to the Oakland Athletics' Nick Swisher. Four innings later, in the 11th, the A's beat the Yankees, 5-4, on a fielder's choice-grounder by Bobby Kielty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kei Igawa’s chance for his first major league victory vanished when Kyle Farnsworth allowed a game-tying home run to Nick Swisher in the seventh inning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Joe Torre summoned Kyle Farnsworth in the seventh inning on Friday, three outs earlier than usual, it was a subtle demotion. Farnsworth is usually the eighth inning pitcher for the Yankees, but he has been shaky lately and cannot work more than one inning at a time. He did nothing to restore his manager's faith.</p>
        <p>Kei Igawa's chance for his first major league victory vanished when Farnsworth allowed a two-out, game-tying home run to the Oakland Athletics' Nick Swisher. Four innings later, in the 11th, the A's beat the Yankees, 5-4, on a fielder's choice-grounder by Bobby Kielty.</p>
        <p>Brian Bruney was pitching then, and he took the loss. But the game turned when Farnsworth entered and could not find the strike zone. He went to 2-0 on his first hitter and 3-0 on his second, but survived to get two outs. He did not have such luck against Swisher.</p>
        <p>After falling behind, 2-0, Farnsworth needed a strike and fired a 96 mile-an-hour fastball. Swisher pounded it over the fence in right center.</p>
        <p>"Swisher, when he sits on a fastball, he gets to it," Torre said. "That's basically what happened."</p>
        <p>Farnsworth was the losing pitcher on Wednesday in Minnesota, when he walked the leadoff man on four pitches in a tie game, and then gave up four one-out hits. Torre said Luis Vizcaino would now be an option in the eighth inning because, unlike Farnsworth, Vizcaino can pitch multiple innings at a time.</p>
        <p>Farnsworth, who also is not used on consecutive days, said he is struggling to stay on top of the ball when he releases it.</p>
        <p>"Obviously, I can't find the strike zone," Farnsworth said. "That's the biggest problem."</p>
        <p>Igawa, at least, was able to find his strike zone. After battling wildness at times in spring training, Igawa was shelled in his debut on April 7, allowing seven runs on eight hits, three walks and a hit batter. He was better this time, lasting 5 1/3 innings and allowing two earned runs on three hits, two walks and a hit batter.</p>
        <p>The outing consumed 95 pitches, though, and ended with a two-run homer by Eric Chavez that cut the Yankees' lead to 4-3 in the sixth inning.</p>
        <p>"I'm not satisfied yet," Igawa said through his translator, Yumi Watanabe. "I need to work on the pace of the game and go from there."</p>
        <p>The Yankees had rallied in the top of the sixth off Danny Haren and Alan Embree, with four singles in a row and Robinson Cano's bases-loaded walk with no outs.</p>
        <p>But Doug Mientkiewicz bounced into a double play, scoring a run but quelling the rally, and Melky Cabrera flied to right to end the inning. Mientkiewicz went 0 for 5 and is hitless in his last 21 at-bats.</p>
        <p>With the game tied in the eighth, Mientkiewicz batted with one out and the bases loaded. He managed a blooper behind the mound. Reliever Justin Duchscherer dropped it and bobbled it again, but he recovered to throw out Alex Rodriguez at the plate. Cabrera then grounded out to keep it 4-4.</p>
        <p>In the 10th, with Cano at second and two out, Mientkiewicz lofted a pop up in foul territory down the third base line. Chavez, a Gold Glover, chased after the ball but let it pop from his glove. Chavez juggled it and trapped it against his body as he slid near the tarp on the warning track, standing and posing after the catch with an incredulous look. He flipped the ball over his back to the crowd.</p>
        <p>"The bad thing about playing here is there's a lot of foul ground," Mientkiewicz said. "That one's solely on me. You've got to drive guys in when you have the chance. I didn't do it."</p>
        <p>Mientkiewicz also found himself involved in the game's final play. Travis Buck was at third base after a one-out triple to the gap in right center. After a hit batter and an intentional walk to Swisher, Bruney faced Kielty with the infield in. Kielty did not hit the ball hard, but he hit it perfectly.</p>
        <p>"He couldn't have thrown the ball in a better place," Bruney said. "It was soft enough, slow enough. Things like that happen. That's why it's baseball."</p>
        <p>The ball could have been Cano's or it could have belonged to Mientkiewicz. When Mientkiewicz came up with it, his only choice was an off-balance throw to catcher Jorge Posada.</p>
        <p>"I was just trying to get rid of it as quick as I could," Mientkiewicz said. "I didn't really get a good grip on it and just made a bad throw."</p>
        <p>Given how the game turned on Farnsworth's control problems, it was fitting that it ended on a wild throw.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
