<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Direct Any Hate Mail to Imus, His Wife Says</title>
    <meta content="14imus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/arts/television/14imus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Direct Any Hate Mail to Imus, His Wife Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Direct Any Hate Mail to Imus, His Wife Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOTOKO RICH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after CBS Radio canceled ''Imus in the Morning,'' Don Imus's wife, Deirdre, was co-host of a radiothon to benefit children's charities on WFAN, the New York radio station that had broadcast Mr. Imus's show.</p>
        <p>During the broadcast, Ms. Imus described the members of the Rutgers University basketball team that Mr. Imus had insulted with a racial and sexual epithet as ''unbelievably courageous and beautiful women.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after CBS Radio canceled “Imus in the Morning,” Don Imus’s wife, Deirdre, was co-host of a radiothon to benefit children’s charities on WFAN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A day after CBS Radio canceled ''Imus in the Morning,'' Don Imus's wife, Deirdre, was co-host of a radiothon to benefit children's charities on WFAN, the New York radio station that had broadcast Mr. Imus's show.</p>
        <p>During the broadcast, Ms. Imus described the members of the Rutgers University basketball team that Mr. Imus had insulted with a racial and sexual epithet as ''unbelievably courageous and beautiful women.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Imus added: ''One thing I want to say is, the hate mail that's being sent to them must stop. If you want to send hate mail, send it to my husband.''</p>
        <p>In a statement yesterday, the coach of the Rutgers University women's basketball team said the team members had accepted the apology that Mr. Imus delivered at the New Jersey governor's mansion on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>''We, the Rutgers University Scarlet Knight basketball team, accept Mr. Imus's apology, and we are in the process of forgiving,'' said C. Vivian Stringer, the team's head coach.</p>
        <p>Ms. Imus had been scheduled to go on a book tour for ''Green This! Volume 1: Greening Your Cleaning,'' her paperback guide to environmentally friendly house cleaning, published by Simon &amp; Schuster. But the publisher postponed the tour indefinitely, citing in a statement the ''enormous pressure that Deirdre and her family are under.''</p>
        <p>Numerous television appearances, including ''Larry King Live'' on CNN and Tim Russert's show on CNBC, had been planned to publicize the book, which went on sale on Tuesday. Mr. Imus had been scheduled to appear alongside his wife on the King and Russert shows.</p>
        <p>Ms. Imus was also scheduled to promote the book at a number of independent bookstores in Connecticut, New Jersey and New York, but all those appearances have also been postponed.</p>
        <p>The book has sold 1,000 copies, according to Nielsen Bookscan, which tracks about 70 percent of books sold in retail outlets and online. Ms. Imus is donating all profits from the sale of the book -- including her seven-figure advance for the current book and four others -- to the couple's ranch for children with cancer in New Mexico. Her first book, ''The Imus Ranch: Cooking for Kids and Cowboys,'' published in 2004 by Rodale Books, has sold 45,000 copies in hardcover, according to Bookscan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
