<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders to Wait Until Game Time to Decide on DiPietro</title>
    <meta content="14islanders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/sports/hockey/14islanders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dipietro, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders to Wait Until Game Time to Decide on DiPietro</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Isles to Wait Until Game Time to Decide if DiPietro Will Play</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>AMHERST, N.Y., April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By most appearances, Rick DiPietro is ready to return to the net Saturday night for Game 2 of the Islanders' first-round playoff series against the Buffalo Sabres.</p>
        <p>He has been free of symptoms from the concussion he sustained last month for more than a week. He resumed practicing with his teammates Friday. He even has a head start on a playoff beard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>By most appearances, goaltender Rick DiPietro is ready to return to the net Saturday night for Game 2 of the Islanders’ playoff series against the Buffalo Sabres.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By most appearances, Rick DiPietro is ready to return to the net Saturday night for Game 2 of the Islanders' first-round playoff series against the Buffalo Sabres.</p>
        <p>He has been free of symptoms from the concussion he sustained last month for more than a week. He resumed practicing with his teammates Friday. He even has a head start on a playoff beard.</p>
        <p>But Coach Ted Nolan said Friday that no decision would be made about DiPietro, the Islanders' franchise goalie, until after a pregame skate Saturday.</p>
        <p>''Every time Ricky steps on the ice, he always looks good to me,'' Nolan said. ''But we'll see how he feels with a good night's rest tonight and gets back on the ice tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>DiPietro has been out of action with postconcussion symptoms like headaches since a game against the Rangers on March 25, when he sustained his second concussion in two weeks.</p>
        <p>DiPietro sustained the first one March 13, when Montreal forward Steve Bégin collided with him during a race for a loose puck. He sat out the next two games and returned to the lineup a week later, playing in the Islanders' next four games before the second concussion occurred.</p>
        <p>DiPietro was cleared to resume practice Thursday after being free of symptoms for seven days. That night, he flew to Buffalo by private plane and watched his teammates lose, 4-1, in Game 1 of their series.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the 25-year-old DiPietro participated in his first team practice in almost three weeks. During drills he slid and flopped to stop shots. Although his game readiness could be another matter, DiPietro's competitive streak remained strong. At one point, he yelled and slammed his stick against the net after giving up a goal.</p>
        <p>''If you're a competitor, you want to play, and I realize how important these games are,'' DiPietro said afterward at the Sabres' practice facility. ''So I'm going to do everything I can tomorrow morning to make myself ready.''</p>
        <p>DiPietro's return could provide his team with a much-needed boost after Game 1. The Islanders could not contend with the Sabres' speed and firepower. Buffalo, the top seed in the Eastern Conference, took 35 shots on Wade Dubielewicz, a journeyman minor leaguer who has been outstanding for the Islanders in DiPietro's absence.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz took over March 30 in relief of the backup Mike Dunham, then led a late push that gave the Islanders the final playoff seed in the conference. He went 4-1 in his five consecutive starts. A shootout victory over the Devils on the final day of the regular season clinched the Islanders' first playoff berth since 2004.</p>
        <p>Still, he is not DiPietro, whom Nolan called the team's most valuable player during the season.</p>
        <p>Sabres Coach Lindy Ruff also sees DiPietro's possible return as a boost for the Islanders.</p>
        <p>''This is no criticism of Dubielewicz because he has played well,'' Ruff said. ''But he is their starting goaltender. I think it's a big addition. It provides a big lift for their team. I think it fills the hope tank up again.''</p>
        <p>Before the season, the Islanders signed DiPietro to an N.H.L.-record 15-year deal for $67.5 million. He then tied a franchise record with 32 victories.</p>
        <p>He is noted for his puck handling, which Ruff said could force the Sabres to alter their game plan. But first the Sabres, like everyone else, will have to wait to find out if DiPietro will play.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
