<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Charge Again, Codey Plans No Surprises</title>
    <meta content="14codey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/nyregion/14codey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CORZINE'S CRASH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Codey, Richard J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E1DE103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Charge Again, Codey Plans No Surprises</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Charge Again, Codey Plans No Surprises</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS; Ronald Smothers contributed reporting from Trenton and John Eligon from East Rutherford, N.J.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>WEST ORANGE, N.J., April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stranded by a punctured tire, Richard J. Codey, the State Senate president, was waiting for a ride home from the parking lot of his district office here on Thursday night when a stranger marveled that he was even standing, let alone contemplating changing the flat.</p>
        <p>''But, Governor,'' the woman exclaimed, ''I thought you were in an accident and broke your leg.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Self-effacing and plain-spoken, but blessed with a cutting-edge sense of humor, Richard J. Codey, 59, is a warmly regarded politician in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stranded by a punctured tire, Richard J. Codey, the State Senate president, was waiting for a ride home from the parking lot of his district office here on Thursday night when a stranger marveled that he was even standing, let alone contemplating changing the flat.</p>
        <p>''But, Governor,'' the woman exclaimed, ''I thought you were in an accident and broke your leg.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey, who does not carry a cellphone and had no idea what the woman was talking about, told her that his bones were intact, and reminded the stranger that it had been well over a year since Jon S. Corzine was sworn in as governor of New Jersey, ending Mr. Codey's 14-month term as a caretaker after Gov. James E. McGreevey's abrupt resignation in 2004.</p>
        <p>The anecdote, relayed with a characteristic shrug as Mr. Codey sat in his office here on Friday morning juggling phone calls, spoke volumes about the man who will be running the state until Mr. Corzine recovers from a car accident near Atlantic City on Thursday night that left him critically injured.</p>
        <p>Self-effacing and plain-spoken, but blessed with a cutting sense of humor, Mr. Codey, 59, is a warmly regarded politician in New Jersey, a man who keeps a bobblehead doll of himself on his desk.</p>
        <p>Yet he remains unrecognizable to most voters despite more than three decades in the Legislature and two spins in the governor's chair -- the first lasting less than four days.</p>
        <p>Under state law, the Senate president steps in when a governor is incapacitated, out of state or leaves office early, although that will change in 2010. New Jersey has survived more than two centuries without a lieutenant governor, but voters approved a change to the Constitution in 2005 after two governors -- Christie Whitman in 2001 and then Mr. McGreevey just a few years later -- left office before their terms were up.</p>
        <p>It was only after Mr. Codey returned home to frantic messages from the state police and political compatriots on Thursday night that he realized he was once again the most powerful public figure in the state.</p>
        <p>His response to the news? ''Been there, done that,'' he said with a weary smile on Friday. ''I had my 14 months of fame and glory, and to be honest, I feel bad for Jon.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey struck a similar note later in the day in Trenton, where he held a brief news conference before stepping into a state police helicopter to return to West Orange. ''Some would say maybe it's a cameo role or whatever,'' he told reporters. ''In any case, I'm a stand-in.''</p>
        <p>Those who know him, however, say his unruffled detachment does not reflect Mr. Codey's true mind-set. Although he seems to get more of a thrill golfing or coaching eighth-grade basketball, friends and colleagues say Mr. Codey, a tried-and-true Democrat, also enjoys the art of a good political deal, quietly brokered in a back room of the State House or over lunch at a diner.</p>
        <p>''Don't be fooled by the nonchalant veneer,'' said John F. McKeon, a state assemblyman who is also mayor of West Orange and a longtime friend of Mr. Codey.</p>
        <p>Raised on the rough-and-tumble streets of Orange, Mr. Codey, the son of an undertaker, is a politically astute pragmatist who often says what he thinks, usually punctuated with an expletive or two. He is perhaps best known for his advocacy on public health issues like stem cell research and antismoking initiatives; he has long given special attention to mental illness, a response to his wife's struggle with postpartum depression.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Mr. Codey said he would not promote his own agenda while sitting in for Mr. Corzine, right down to staying in his office in another wing of the State House rather than working out of the governor's office. (He added with a wink that he would not use his expanded influence to build statewide support for John Edwards in his battle for the Democratic presidential nomination against Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, whom Mr. Corzine supports.)</p>
        <p>But if the governor remains incapacitated and Mr. Codey's cameo lasts more than a few weeks, he may be forced to grapple with some of the more vexing issues crowding Mr. Corzine's plate, including a $2 billion budget deficit, questions about the state's troubled pension system and a federal investigation into the way Trenton puts together its budget.</p>
        <p>''He knows his job is not to shake up the state in any way, but if he has to take on tough issues, he'll do what's necessary,'' said David P. Rebovich, a political scientist at Rider University in Lawrenceville, N.J. ''He's got 30 years' experience in the Legislature, so he understands the concerns and the egos that have to be stroked.''</p>
        <p>But on Friday morning, Mr. Codey seemed less consumed with governing than with a coming comedy show benefit for a local hospital that will pair him with Bill Cosby; also on his mind were a series of basketball tournaments that are supposed to take him out of town the next few weekends.</p>
        <p>And he was preoccupied with his other job: running the mortuary business that has been in his family since 1906. Even after learning of Mr. Corzine's accident and his own elevation to acting governor about 7 p.m. Thursday, Mr. Codey spent the next few hours at the funeral home helping to arrange a burial.</p>
        <p>On Friday, as he headed out his door on the way to a waiting helicopter, Mr. Codey glanced at a pile of congratulatory e-mail messages. ''You've saved the day,'' said one note. Another, from a local religious leader, suggested it was destiny that he had again become the state's chief executive.</p>
        <p>They made Mr. Codey cringe.</p>
        <p>''I'm no superhero,'' he said, shaking his head and adding that he did not relish the job ahead of him. ''Right now, all I really want is for Jon to get well and come back to finish what he started.''</p>
        <p>On Friday evening, Mr. Codey went to a basketball game between the Nets and the Knicks at the Meadowlands. As he walked out, a fan asked, ''Hey, Dick, you need a chauffeur?'' To which the former and again acting governor shook his head no, adding, ''I wear a seat belt.''</p>
        <p>CORZINE'S CRASH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
