<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Qaeda Group in Iraq Says It Led Attack on Parliament</title>
    <meta content="14iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/world/middleeast/14iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Islamic State of Iraq (Orgn)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EED6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Qaeda Group in Iraq Says It Led Attack on Parliament</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Qaeda Group in Iraq Says It Led Attack on Parliament</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG; Reporting was contributed by Ali Adeeb from Baghdad, Thom Shanker from Washington and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Diwaniya and other Iraqi cities.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Islamic State of Iraq, umbrella group that includes Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia, claims responsibility for suicide bombing inside Parliament building; attack killed one legislator and wounded at least 22 other people; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An umbrella insurgent group that includes Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia claimed responsibility on Friday for a brazen suicide bombing the previous day inside the Parliament building. The attack killed one legislator and wounded at least 22 other people.</p>
        <p>The group, the Islamic State of Iraq, has a longstanding goal of toppling the government and driving the Americans from the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The group, the Islamic State of Iraq, has a longstanding goal of toppling the Iraqi government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An umbrella insurgent group that includes Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia claimed responsibility on Friday for a brazen suicide bombing the previous day inside the Parliament building. The attack killed one legislator and wounded at least 22 other people.</p>
        <p>The group, the Islamic State of Iraq, has a longstanding goal of toppling the government and driving the Americans from the country.</p>
        <p>''A heroic knight of the Islamic State of Iraq, may God bless its men, went inside the crowd of the infidels of the so-called Parliament on Thursday, April 12, 2007,'' the group said in an Internet posting, according to a translation from the SITE Institute, which tracks jihadist messages. ''God has destroyed the crowds of defectors and infidels.''</p>
        <p>The American military said Friday that despite its earlier reports, only one person had been killed and 22 wounded in the explosion, which took place in the heart of the protected International Zone. On Thursday, the military said eight people had been killed and 23 wounded; it revised the numbers after further research and talking to Iraqi officials.</p>
        <p>''Yesterday's reports were based on initial reports from the scene,'' the military said in a statement. ''During evacuation operations, emergency responders and eyewitnesses reported that casualties were being evacuated in multiple directions.''</p>
        <p>Parliament held an emergency session on Friday, the Muslim day of prayer, to mourn the death of Muhammad Awad, the legislator who was killed. Mr. Awad was a member of the National Dialogue Front, a Sunni Arab political party.</p>
        <p>The special session was shown on television. It was sparsely attended. Some legislators wept. Others put flowers in the empty chair of Mr. Awad. Prominent politicians marched up to a podium to give a eulogy.</p>
        <p>One of them, Nada Muhammad Ibrahim al-Jubouri, from the same party as Mr. Awad, had also been in the Parliament cafeteria when the bomb went off, and she spoke with a brace on her neck.</p>
        <p>''I thought yesterday not of my brothers or sisters in the mean incident that took place, but of the Iraqi citizens who are subject to violence and killing,'' she said. ''The citizens might not get the treatment we received in Ibn Sina Hospital from the American doctors.</p>
        <p>''We have to forget our differences and make concessions to Iraq. We have to forget pain and reunite again. We have only Iraq.''</p>
        <p>Barham Salih, a deputy prime minister, told Iraqiya, the state-run television network, that three people had been detained so far in the investigation.</p>
        <p>At least one other insurgent group, the Islamic Army of Iraq, said on Al Jazeera television this week that it was fighting against the Islamic State of Iraq because it had killed members of the Islamic Army, The Associated Press reported.</p>
        <p>The American military is responsible for securing large portions of the International Zone, formerly called the Green Zone. But the commander of day-to-day military operations in Iraq, Lt. Gen. Raymond T. Odierno, said there were no plans to take over security of the Parliament building itself.</p>
        <p>''I think that what we have to do is, we have to work with the Iraqi security forces and continue to work with them and help them to be able to maintain security of their own Parliament,'' General Odierno said in a video news conference from Baghdad with correspondents at the Pentagon. ''They are capable of doing it.''</p>
        <p>General Odierno acknowledged that ''frankly, yesterday was a bad day, a very bad day, but we're going to come back from that.''</p>
        <p>Details of the bomber's identity and how he entered Parliament were still to be determined, General Odierno said.</p>
        <p>''Something didn't go right,'' he said. ''There's plenty of defenses there, and they should not be able to penetrate it. But either they figured out a way for us not to detect it or simply somebody didn't do their job, and we have to find out what happened.''</p>
        <p>In Diwaniya, in the south, where American and Iraqi forces have been clashing for more than a week with militiamen loyal to the radical Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr, American soldiers prevented Mr. Sadr's followers from gathering and praying at a mosque dedicated to Imam Ali, an important figure in Shiism.</p>
        <p>The militiamen then went to pray at the Sadr group's office, where Americans arrested three men, including the main spokesman. Mr. Sadr's supporters blocked the American vehicles from leaving, and the Americans released the three men, witnesses said.</p>
        <p>The American military has moved a Stryker unit out of Baghdad, where a new security plan is under way, to deal with surging violence in Diwaniya, a haven for Shiite militiamen.</p>
        <p>The military said Friday that insurgents attacked a patrol base south of Baghdad on Thursday, killing two American soldiers and two of their interpreters and wounding seven other soldiers. Another soldier was killed and one wounded by a bomb south of the capital on Thursday. A soldier was also killed by small-arms fire north of Baghdad on Friday, and a soldier died Thursday from a noncombat cause.</p>
        <p>Police officials said that a prominent Sunni Arab cleric was shot dead in Mosul on Friday. At least seven other people were killed and dozens wounded in separate attacks on Friday across Iraq. At least five bodies were found in Baghdad.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, at least 25 people were killed or found dead across Iraq, police and hospital officials said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
