<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lender Sought Favor At College, Papers Say</title>
    <meta content="14loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/education/14loans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Student Loan Xpress</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Capella University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Notre Dame</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morehouse College</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stanford University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Balestri, Fabrizio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lehmann, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Student Loan Xpress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Balestri, Fabrizio</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1DF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lender Sought Favor At College, Papers Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Lender Sought Favor at College, Papers Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN D. GLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glater, Jonathan D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Student Loan Xpress pres Fabrizio Balestri in 2004 asked Capella University to re-order its list of recommended lenders, according to documents being reviewed by Senate officials who are examining relationship between loan company and academic institution; Tim Lehmann, director of financial aid at Capella, was recently placed on leave following disclosure that he had accepted more than $12,000 as consultant to the loan company; government filings with Securities and Exchange Commission show that high-ranking officials at University of Notre Dame, Morehouse College and Stanford University hold positions on boards of financial institutions that provide student loans (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A top executive of a student loan company asked Capella University to re-order its list of recommended lenders, according to documents being reviewed by Senate officials who are examining the relationship between the loan company and the academic institution.</p>
        <p>The documents, provided to the staff of Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts and chairman of the education committee, appear to have been prepared in late 2004 or early 2005 for a presentation at the company, Student Loan Xpress, about its relationship with Capella, an online institution based in Minneapolis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A top executive of a student loan company asked Capella University to re-order its list of recommended lenders, according to documents being reviewed by Senate officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A top executive of a student loan company asked Capella University to re-order its list of recommended lenders, according to documents being reviewed by Senate officials who are examining the relationship between the loan company and the academic institution.</p>
        <p>The documents, provided to the staff of Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts and chairman of the education committee, appear to have been prepared in late 2004 or early 2005 for a presentation at the company, Student Loan Xpress, about its relationship with Capella, an online institution based in Minneapolis.</p>
        <p>Tim Lehmann, the director of financial aid at Capella, was recently placed on leave following the disclosure that he had accepted more than $12,000 as a consultant to the loan company. The documents state that Mr. Lehmann decides on the ''final lender ranking.''</p>
        <p>The documents provide yet another example of how important loan companies consider being included on recommended lender lists, because students seeking loans rely heavily on these lists and rarely comparison shop. The documents also show the influence that loan companies can wield at universities, and the close ties between them.</p>
        <p>According to government filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission, high-ranking officials at three universities --University of Notre Dame, Morehouse College and Stanford University -- hold positions on boards of financial institutions that provide student loans. Bloomberg News reported on these three and additional university officials with ties to loan companies yesterday.</p>
        <p>The documents reviewed by Senate aides appear to be part of an electronic slide presentation. One slide states, ''Preferred lender list was adjusted by request of Breeze in Sept. 2004. SLX is currently listed 2nd.'' ''Breeze'' is the nickname of Fabrizio Balestri, the president of the loan company.</p>
        <p>Messages left at Mr. Balestri's office at Student Loan Xpress in San Diego were not answered. C. Curtis Ritter, a spokesman for the CIT Group, which acquired Student Loan Xpress in 2005, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Capella University said in a statement that it is ''reviewing our relationship with Student Loan Xpress as part of an internal review.''</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. filings show that Walter E. Massey, president of Morehouse College, is a member of the board of directors at Bank of America, a recommended lender at the institution.</p>
        <p>Filings show that John Affleck-Graves, an executive vice president at the University of Notre Dame, is a member of the board of Student Loan Corporation, which is a unit of Citigroup, and a loan company on the university's recommended lender list. And filings for Wells Fargo show that Robert L. Joss, dean of the Stanford Graduate School of Business, is a director. Wells Fargo is not a recommended lender at the business school, according to the university.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Notre Dame officials said Dr. Affleck-Graves' service on the Student Loan Corporation board complied with the university's policy on conflicts of interest. ''He has recused himself from student loan discussions and decisions at the university,'' the university said. The statement added, ''Given the current controversies, Dr. Affleck-Graves will re-examine his position on the SLC board to determine how he can best be of service to all concerned parties.''</p>
        <p>Morehouse College stated it would remove Bank of America from its list of recommended lenders while reviewing the decision to include it. That decision ''will be reviewed by the audit committee of the college's board of trustees,'' the institution said in a statement.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Stanford University, Alan Acosta, said Mr. Joss's service on the board of Wells Fargo did not violate the institution's policy on conflicts of interest. In addition, Mr. Acosta said, Mr. Joss ''has no role in selection of recommended lenders at the Graduate School of Business or preferred lenders at Stanford's central Financial Aid Office.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
