<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Amazing Race, With Cars as the Stars</title>
    <meta content="14heff" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/arts/television/14heff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Drive (TV Program)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4D6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Amazing Race, With Cars as the Stars</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Amazing Race, With Cars as the Stars</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Insincerity pervades ''Drive,'' the mysterious drama about a cross-country road race that starts tomorrow on Fox. It's apparent in the wooden performances, the on-the-nose score and the sterile stagecraft.</p>
        <p>''Drive'' resembles nothing so much as high-end religious propaganda, or pornography before the sex starts: hollow drama with an ulterior motive. Surely this show cannot have been made chiefly to entertain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The insincerity that pervades “Drive” is apparent in the wooden performances, the on-the-nose score and the sterile stagecraft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Insincerity pervades ''Drive,'' the mysterious drama about a cross-country road race that starts tomorrow on Fox. It's apparent in the wooden performances, the on-the-nose score and the sterile stagecraft.</p>
        <p>''Drive'' resembles nothing so much as high-end religious propaganda, or pornography before the sex starts: hollow drama with an ulterior motive. Surely this show cannot have been made chiefly to entertain.</p>
        <p>Its actual intent does come through, though not in the story line or the speed-demon scenes. To keep it simple, let's just call the race in ''Drive'' an amazing one, propelled by clues, and let that suffice for plot summary. The action scenes are distractions. To pay too much attention to the stuff palmed off as narrative makes a person feel cruel, gullible or both.</p>
        <p>''Drive,'' at its essence, seems to exist as a support system for its painstaking close-ups, especially the lingering beauty shots of cars. And while the show's sprawling, ''Lost''-like cast makes it hard to remember the names of characters, much less their flimsy reasons for taking to the road in hope of winning $32 million by making it first to an arbitrary finish line, it's not hard to remember the stars of ''Drive.'' Their names are Ford, GM and Chevrolet. A classic trio.</p>
        <p>''Drive'' features cars of all varieties. There are minivans, sports cars, pickup trucks, roadsters, S.U.V.'s and vintage sedans on jacked-up wheels. For a minute or two, you might even think they're all different makes, these cars, like the ones you see on the highway.</p>
        <p>But no. First, they're all American. Second, several of the most prominent are Fords, fast becoming the house car at Fox. (Ford is a conspicuous sponsor of ''American Idol'' and this season, according to a January news release, has been using ''Idol'' as ''the key platform to integrate a variety of Ford vehicles, including the new Ford Edge, plus the Fusion, Escape Hybrid and Mustang.'')</p>
        <p>On ''Drive,'' the burnt-sienna pickup truck, which belongs to Alex Tully (Nathan Fillion), the hero, whose wife has gone missing, has the letters ORD across the front. The F is picturesquely missing, because he's from Nebraska, and very wholesome and real. It's a 1972 Ford F-100 pickup.</p>
        <p>Similarly, the nerdy John Trimble (Dylan Baker) and his pouty daughter, Violet (Emma Stone), drive a 1998 Ford Taurus with California plates -- the kind the rental places all used to offer. The camera, quite literally, gets right up in its grille.</p>
        <p>Ivy Chitty (Taryn Manning) and Susan Chamblee (Michael Hyatt), survivors of Hurricane Katrina, drive a Land Rover. Unless you have the Ford ''family of brands'' firmly in mind -- Mazda, Volvo, Jaguar and Land Rover are all kin now -- you might think this one's something different, but no. It's another Ford.</p>
        <p>A tougher character, Winston (Kevin Alejandro), has a sinuous, bare-breasted lady as a hood ornament -- a kind of precursor to the silhouette lady of mudflaps -- that, along with a logo, denotes a low-riding Chevy Impala. The camera savors its retro flair.</p>
        <p>Some Dodges also come into play, and a tarty couple drive a Firebird, with the big bird painted in blue on its white hood. There's no mistaking that. In fact, there's no mistaking any of this. There's nothing subliminal about it. There's nothing liminal about it. It's a television series as a prolonged commercial, and it absolutely crosses the line.</p>
        <p>Still, for all the current talk of integrating advertising into programming, as opposed to alternating programming with ads in the old model, there's something distinctly unintegrated about this finished product. ''Drive'' just doesn't harmonize. It doesn't look like anyone's vision; it looks like a series of compromises, deals and experiments in sales. The show's pacing, most notably, is irremediably messed up by all the long, slow caresses the camera gives the cars' branding elements.</p>
        <p>While the race is on, how do we have time for so many words from our sponsor? Until someone figures out how to make integration run better, let's just play commercials during pit stops, the way we used to.</p>
        <p>Drive  Fox, tomorrow and Monday at 8 p.m., Eastern and Pacific times; 7, Central time.</p>
        <p>Created by Tim Minear and Ben Queen; Mr. Minear, Mr. Queen and Greg Yaitanes, executive producers; directed by Mr. Yaitanes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Nathan Fillion (Alex Tully), Kristin Lehman (Corinna Wiles), Kevin Alejandro (Winston Salazar), Dylan Baker (John Trimble), Michael Hyatt (Susan Chamblee), Melanie Lynskey (Wendy Patrakas), Taryn Manning (Ivy Chitty), Charles Martin Smith (Mr. Bright), J. D. Pardo (Sean Salazar), Riley Smith (Rob Laird) and Emma Stone (Violet Trimble).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
