<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Guardedly Kicking the Tires on Chrysler</title>
    <meta content="14auto" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/automobiles/14auto.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cerberus Capital Management</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blackstone Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Magna International Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maynard, Micheline</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">DaimlerChrysler AG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chrysler Group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDE103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Guardedly Kicking the Tires on Chrysler</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Guardedly Kicking the Tires on Chrysler</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELINE MAYNARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maynard, Micheline</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Effort by DaimlerChrysler to find buyer for Chrysler is becoming drawn-out, complicated process that barely advanced this week, bogged down by issues including debt, Chrysler's health care liability and role of United Automobile Workers union; none of bidders appear to be in rush to snap up struggling car company; Canadian automobile supplier Magna International confirms widely reported speculation that it is among those interested in Chrysler; Chrysler has drawn interest from Cerberus Capital and Blackstone Group as well as Magna; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dieter Zetsche, the chief executive of DaimlerChrysler, found out last summer that selling cars as a TV pitchman is harder than it looks.</p>
        <p>Now it turns out that selling Chrysler isn't all that easy either.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The effort by DaimlerChrysler to find a buyer for Chrysler is becoming a drawn-out, complicated process beset by issues including debt, health costs and unions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dieter Zetsche, the chief executive of DaimlerChrysler, found out last summer that selling cars as a TV pitchman is harder than it looks.</p>
        <p>Now it turns out that selling Chrysler isn't all that easy either.</p>
        <p>The effort by DaimlerChrysler to find a buyer for Chrysler is becoming a drawn-out, complicated process that barely advanced this week, bogged down by issues including debt, Chrysler's health care liability and the role of the United Automobile Workers union, bankers involved in the negotiations said.</p>
        <p>Moreover, none of the bidders appear to be in a rush to snap up the struggling car company.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the Canadian automobile supplier Magna International confirmed the widely reported speculation that it was among those interested in Chrysler. But Magna, in a statement, said, ''There is no assurance that any transaction will result from Magna's current involvement.''</p>
        <p>Even if they represent firm offers, the proposals are likely to be laden with contingencies and requirements that DaimlerChrysler might find too onerous to accept, the bankers said. They insisted on anonymity because of the sensitive nature of the talks.</p>
        <p>That raises the possibility that some or all of the bidders eventually could drop out, these bankers and industry analysts said.</p>
        <p>''We are really at the very early stage of the process,'' Stefano Aversa, co-president of AlixPartners, a restructuring firm based in Southfield, Mich., said Wednesday. ''It won't be an easy decision for DaimlerChrysler. This is not going to be by any means just a simple acquisition.''</p>
        <p>Investors, who sent DaimlerChrysler shares to a new high last week when the billionaire investor Kirk Kerkorian offered to pay $4.5 billion for Chrysler, apparently do not like the cold shoulder that he is getting from the company. DaimlerChrysler shares ended the week at $82.26, down 76 cents Friday. By contrast, the shares closed at $84.80 on April 5 when Mr. Kerkorian's bid came to light.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerkorian made his bid public after JPMorgan Chase, which is handling the Chrysler sale, failed to send his advisers the packet of information that was given to other bidders. And while company officials held meetings with some of those bidders in New York this week, Mr. Kerkorian's representatives apparently were not included.</p>
        <p>The animosity has deep roots. Mr. Kerkorian, who as Chrysler's biggest shareholder constantly pushed it to place more emphasis on shareholder returns, sued DaimlerChrysler in 2000. He asserted that he had been misled into supporting the deal by the assertions of executives that it was a ''merger of equals'' instead of a takeover by Daimler-Benz. A federal judge ruled against Mr. Kerkorian in 2005.</p>
        <p>Thus far, Chrysler has drawn interest from two investment firms -- Cerberus Capital and the Blackstone Group -- as well as Magna, which is involved in a number of production ventures with DaimlerChrysler.</p>
        <p>But the discussions, which this week included Rüdiger Grube, a DaimlerChrysler board member, have not yet begun to narrow down the particulars, the bankers who have been advising those bidders said.</p>
        <p>Although some reports have said DaimlerChrysler would like to focus on a leading candidate by the end of the month, these advisers said it could take weeks more for the potential bidders to get a true picture of how any transaction was likely to be structured.</p>
        <p>Further, there seems to be no hurry on the part of either DaimlerChrysler or the bidders to come up with a price for Chrysler, which is likely to be billions less than Daimler-Benz paid. The old price is ''not material'' to the current discussions, Mr. Aversa of AlixPartners said.</p>
        <p>Daimler-Benz paid $36 billion for Chrysler in 1998 in what was originally termed a ''merger of equals'' but turned out to be a takeover by the German automaker of the American company.</p>
        <p>In February, Mr. Zetsche, who played pitchman as Dr. Z in Chrysler commercials, said the company was keeping its options open for Chrysler. Chrysler lost $1.5 billion last year, and has required two restructurings in the last seven years.</p>
        <p>Valuing an independent Chrysler is particularly difficult because it does not have independently traded shares and because transferring ownership of a huge automaker at a time of such turmoil in the industry is complex.</p>
        <p>The only means for determining a fair value will come from a potential buyer's plan to restructure Chrysler, Mr. Aversa said. ''I'm sure the business plan is not going to be just business as usual, given the losses,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, bankers say the discussions have centered less on the overall value of Chrysler and more on issues surrounding the company, like the debt load that DaimlerChrysler carries on Chrysler's behalf, a burden it might want to transfer to the new owners.</p>
        <p>The company also is far from resolving what it might do about the $18 billion liability it faces for current and future health care coverage for employees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerkorian, in his bid, suggested that the liability be shared between the Tracinda Corporation, his investment arm, and DaimlerChrysler, but other bidders may push for DaimlerChrysler to absorb the entire expense. Likewise, it is far from clear what role the U.A.W. would play under new ownership.</p>
        <p>The U.A.W.'s president, Ron Gettelfinger, who sits on the DaimlerChrysler supervisory board and has a vote in the outcome, has said he would prefer that Chrysler remain under DaimlerChrysler's wing, rather than be sold to private investors. The president of the Canadian Auto Workers union, Basil Hargrove, has said he opposes a sale to Mr. Kerkorian.</p>
        <p>The situation is easily as complicated as the sale by General Motors last year to Cerberus of a 51 percent stake in its financing arm, the General Motors Acceptance Corporation, said one person involved in the Chrysler discussions.</p>
        <p>In that case, the estimated price of the G.M.A.C. stake fell several times as G.M. looked for buyers.</p>
        <p>Early on, analysts estimated G.M. might get as much as $16 billion for half of G.M.A.C. But those estimates dropped to about $11 billion, after G.M.'s auto sales declined and the company encountered problems at Residential Capital, its residential mortgage unit.</p>
        <p>The final agreement, announced a year ago, was for $7.4 billion from a consortium headed by Cerberus, along with $2.7 billion in G.M.A.C. assets that G.M. credited to Cerberus.</p>
        <p>G.M. said last month that it would pay settlement charges of $1 billion to reflect changes in G.M.A.C.'s balance sheet, and analysts say more revisions may be in store for the G.M.A.C. deal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
