<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Music in Review; New York Philharmonic -- Avery Fisher Hall</title>
    <meta content="14roun-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Music in Review; New York Philharmonic -- Avery Fisher Hall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having young conductors on the podium of the New York Philharmonic is not as novel as it sometimes seems: It's part of the business of a modern orchestral season, in which guest conductors lead an ensemble for more weeks than its music director does. Lately, the Philharmonic has been visited by a small parade of young but experienced conductors. Often they come with fresh ideas and infectious energy, and in a rational business, any of them might be considered in the search for a successor to Lorin Maazel.</p>
        <p>But the Philharmonic isn't about youth, freshness or energy. It considers itself entitled to a thoroughly established conductor, if not an elder statesman with a household name. Never mind that across the continent, the Los Angeles Philharmonic was able to excite its audiences this week, seize the national headlines and engender jealousy throughout the orchestra world all at a stroke by snagging the 26-year-old Gustavo Dudamel. Or that the New York Philharmonic's own postwar zenith was its appointment of Leonard Bernstein as music director when he was in his early 30s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having young conductors on the podium of the New York Philharmonic is not as novel as it sometimes seems: It's part of the business of a modern orchestral season, in which guest conductors lead an ensemble for more weeks than its music director does. Lately, the Philharmonic has been visited by a small parade of young but experienced conductors. Often they come with fresh ideas and infectious energy, and in a rational business, any of them might be considered in the search for a successor to Lorin Maazel.</p>
        <p>But the Philharmonic isn't about youth, freshness or energy. It considers itself entitled to a thoroughly established conductor, if not an elder statesman with a household name. Never mind that across the continent, the Los Angeles Philharmonic was able to excite its audiences this week, seize the national headlines and engender jealousy throughout the orchestra world all at a stroke by snagging the 26-year-old Gustavo Dudamel. Or that the New York Philharmonic's own postwar zenith was its appointment of Leonard Bernstein as music director when he was in his early 30s.</p>
        <p>The orchestra's guest this week is Sakari Oramo, a Finnish conductor in his early 40s who succeeded Simon Rattle as music director of the City of Birmingham Symphony Orchestra in England in 1998 and is also the principal conductor of the Finnish Radio Symphony Orchestra. He came to conducting by a time-honored route: starting as an orchestral violinist and working his way to the concertmaster's chair before deciding to study conducting.</p>
        <p>It took a while Thursday night to see what Mr. Oramo could do, mainly because he devoted the first half of his program to Shostakovich's First Violin Concerto, in which the orchestra plays an unusually subdued role in the first two movements and doesn't fully edge its way into the spotlight until the finale. Until then, the focus is all on the solo violin. Lisa Batiashvili played with a captivating sense of drama and a pure, tightly focused tone. She took Shostakovich's acidic bitterness into account yet gave the solo line a warm glow.</p>
        <p>Ms. Batiashvili brought a similar sound and interpretive sensibility to Magnus Lindberg's Violin Concerto last summer at the Mostly Mozart Festival at Lincoln Center. If anything, she was more assertive here, not only in her subtle use of color but also in her almost choreographic approach to the variety of bowing styles Shostakovich demands.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oramo's own canvas was a pair of Sibelius works, and if his gestures were sometimes broad (though neither as broad nor as self-consciously showy as Mr. Maazel's), they were consistently clear and detailed. In Sibelius's Sixth Symphony, Mr. Oramo drew on the Philharmonic's finely polished string tone and its sharply articulated woodwinds, offering an expansive, sumptuous and at times driven reading.</p>
        <p>More telling was his account of ''Tapiola,'' Sibelius's tone poem describing adventures of Tapio, the forest god of the ''Kalevala,'' Finland's national folk epic. This is an object lesson in creating vast, dramatic panoramas in sound, and Mr. Oramo and the Philharmonic made Sibelius's wintry pictures seem three-dimensional and vivid. Particularly effective was the howling, icy wind evoked by the briskly bowed strings near the end of the score.</p>
        <p>ALLAN KOZINN</p>
        <p>Sakari Oramo, Lisa Batiashvili and the New York Philharmonic will perform this program tonight at 8 at Avery Fisher Hall; (212) 875-5656 or nyphil.org</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
