<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Uncertain Prognosis, and Many Risks</title>
    <meta content="14condition" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/nyregion/14condition.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E1DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Uncertain Prognosis, and Many Risks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Uncertain Prognosis, and Many Risks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like any victim of life-threatening injuries, Gov. Jon S. Corzine's recovery will be a step-by-step process measured initially by the hour.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, 60, was sedated and under heavy pain medication yesterday at Cooper University Hospital in Camden, N.J., for the more than a dozen broken bones, including half of his rib cage, and other injuries he suffered in a traffic accident on Thursday night. He was listed in critical condition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine’s recovery will be a step-by-step process measured initially by the hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like any victim of life-threatening injuries, Gov. Jon S. Corzine's recovery will be a step-by-step process measured initially by the hour.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, 60, was sedated and under heavy pain medication yesterday at Cooper University Hospital in Camden, N.J., for the more than a dozen broken bones, including half of his rib cage, and other injuries he suffered in a traffic accident on Thursday night. He was listed in critical condition.</p>
        <p>The time it takes to recover from such devastating injuries varies widely, and it is far too early to tell how soon Mr. Corzine can resume his duties as governor.</p>
        <p>''It is way out of place to conjecture as to how well he will do,'' said Dr. Thomas M. Scalea, physician in chief of the R Adams Crowley Shock Trauma Center at the University of Maryland Medical Center. ''There's no way to know,'' added Dr. Scalea, who is not involved with Mr. Corzine's case.</p>
        <p>Because of the severe pain from having fractured 12 ribs, a tube that is connected to a mechanical ventilator has been placed in Mr. Corzine's throat to help him breathe. The tube prevents Mr. Corzine from speaking.</p>
        <p>The full extent of Mr. Corzine's injuries may not yet be known in part because no diagnostic test is perfect. Doctors may not have been able to perform a full neurological evaluation in the initial hours of Mr. Corzine's treatment because of the pain, the extent of his injuries and his need for medication.</p>
        <p>''He does awaken and is able to communicate with us a little bit'' and ''is able to answer simple yes-or-no questions about whether he is having pain and things like that,'' Dr. Steven E. Ross, head of the division of trauma and emergency services at Cooper, said at a news conference yesterday.</p>
        <p>Presumably, Dr. Ross eased the sedation to check Mr. Corzine's mental status.</p>
        <p>Doctors generally use what is known as the Glasgow Coma Scale to measure a patient's mental condition at the time of a serious injury. Mr. Corzine's doctors have not released the results of that test.</p>
        <p>Although a CT scan showed no structural brain injury, that X-ray test does not rule out mental or physical damage. Mr. Corzine also suffered a broken lower vertebra, a bone that protects the spinal cord. Mr. Corzine's doctors did not say whether there was any indication of paralysis or other spinal cord damage.</p>
        <p>Any of a number of complications -- ranging from respiratory failure to heart problems to bone and systemic infections -- could occur along the way, even under the care of doctors in a nationally respected trauma center like Cooper University Hospital.</p>
        <p>The broken leg and severe chest injuries each carry their own risks. The combination makes recovery much more complicated.</p>
        <p>One favorable factor is that the surgical team was able to stabilize Mr. Corzine's left femur. That thigh bone was broken in two places, and a piece punctured the skin. The team, headed by Dr. Robert F. Ostrum, Cooper's head of orthopedic surgery, ran a rod through the center of the femur, connecting the broken pieces so that it can heal as a single bone over the next several weeks.</p>
        <p>Fixing the femur fractures this early permits better cleaning of the wounds and allows him to get out of bed sooner. ''He does not have to be flat in bed in traction, which is a huge advantage to his lungs,'' Dr. Scalea said in an interview.</p>
        <p>''The big player here in how he will do is going to be much more driven by his thoracic injuries than his femur fracture,'' Dr. Scalea said, referring to Mr. Corzine's broken ribs and sternum and other chest injuries.</p>
        <p>There usually is no specific treatment for a broken sternum (breastbone), clavicle (collarbone) and ribs beyond pain relief and general supportive care.</p>
        <p>But the number of broken bones indicates the severity of the blow that injured Mr. Corzine's chest. The force that is necessary to break the thick sternum and a dozen ribs in a cage that nature designed to protect the lungs and heart could have damaged those organs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine is receiving intravenous injections of narcotics to relieve pain. Doctors usually tell patients they will need pain relief for up to six weeks or so after breaking ribs, though they may not need narcotics for the entire period. The drugs can affect an individual's mental status, but patients differ in their pain tolerance and the amount and type of drugs needed to relieve it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine faces at least two additional operations. The first, scheduled for today, is expected to remove dead tissue to reduce risk of infection and to make sure the wounds are healing well. The second is scheduled for Monday.</p>
        <p>Among the complications that Mr. Corzine faces are clots that develop in the legs, a problem known as deep venous thrombosis; the potentially fatal dislodging of pieces of fat from the broken bones that can then float with the blood to lodge in the lungs and damage them; pneumonia; and respiratory failure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine lost about half the amount of blood in his body, and he could develop infections from the seven units of blood that he received as replacement transfusions to prevent him from going into shock, a potentially fatal condition. He may also need additional transfusions.</p>
        <p>NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
