<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.E.'s Earnings Increase 2%; High-Cost Products Sell Well</title>
    <meta content="14electric" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/business/14electric.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFDF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.E.'s Earnings Increase 2%; High-Cost Products Sell Well</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">G.E.’s Earnings Increase 2%; High-Cost Products Sell Well</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Electric Co says earnings in recent quarter were up 2 percent over last year and revenue was up 6 percent; earnings were $4.5 billion on revenue of $40.2 billion; GE lost $373 million in subprime mortgages, and has put up $330 million in reserves; sales and earnings of specific units detailed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The General Electric Company benefited from robust sales of engines, turbines and other big-ticket items in the first quarter, even as it grappled with problems in its consumer finance, plastics and health care businesses.</p>
        <p>A result, G.E. said yesterday, was that earnings in the quarter were up 2 percent over last year and revenue was up 6 percent. The numbers -- specifically, earnings of $4.5 billion, or 44 cents a share, on revenue of $40.2 billion -- were in line with Wall Street's expectations, but many analysts expressed relief.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The General Electric Company benefited from robust sales of engines, turbines and other big-ticket items in the first quarter, even as it grappled with problems in its consumer finance, plastics and health care businesses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The General Electric Company benefited from robust sales of engines, turbines and other big-ticket items in the first quarter, even as it grappled with problems in its consumer finance, plastics and health care businesses.</p>
        <p>A result, G.E. said yesterday, was that earnings in the quarter were up 2 percent over last year and revenue was up 6 percent. The numbers -- specifically, earnings of $4.5 billion, or 44 cents a share, on revenue of $40.2 billion -- were in line with Wall Street's expectations, but many analysts expressed relief.</p>
        <p>''There were few surprises, and the quality of the earnings was really high,'' said Deane M. Dray, an analyst at Goldman Sachs who rates G.E. shares a buy.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in January, when G.E. reported an earnings increase of 11 percent for 2006, investors worried that the numbers reflected favorable tax rates and earnings restatements, and sent G.E. shares down.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, G.E. shares closed at $35.38, up 20 cents, partly because investors felt that earnings growth stemmed from sales and productivity gains. Many were pleased that G.E. used the $558 million gain from the sale of its reinsurance business to offset charges related to an asbestos settlement and to 3,900 job cuts.</p>
        <p>''I feel better about the stock's long-term prospects,'' said Robert Spremulli, an analyst at TIAA-CREF, which owns G.E. shares.</p>
        <p>The quarter had its blips. A new rule in Japan that limits interest rates to 20 percent is causing snags for GE Money. In the United States the unit suffered from the debacle in the so-called subprime mortgage market, which serves people with questionable credit.</p>
        <p>G.E. is a wholesaler in that market, issuing mortgages and selling the debt to other companies. ''In the fourth quarter, the capital markets just shut down,'' said Mark W. Begor, who heads GE Money's American operations.</p>
        <p>Just as bad, the number of people defaulting on payments soared. Such defaults drove the delinquency rate for GE Money to 5.5 percent. While the unit's sales rose 14 percent, its profits inched up only 2 percent.</p>
        <p>G.E. lost $373 million in subprime mortgages, and has put up $330 million in reserves. Mr. Begor said it has also tightened its lending criteria.</p>
        <p>GE Healthcare has had to shut two equipment factories while it fixes quality issues raised by the Food and Drug Administration. Medicare has reduced reimbursements to clinics for M.R.I. tests, leading to fewer equipment orders.</p>
        <p>Those factors resulted in a $50 million hit to earnings.</p>
        <p>But those areas of weakness were offset by booming sales of locomotives, aircraft engines and other items needed in growing economies. Across the company, G.E. has a backlog of $6 billion in orders.</p>
        <p>''We are in the first inning of a nine-inning game in infrastructure,'' Jeffrey R. Immelt, G.E.'s chief executive, said in a conference call.</p>
        <p>Investors believe him. ''The growth seems poised to continue over the next few years,'' said Daniel J. Rosenblatt, an analyst with Marble Harbor Investment Counsel, which has added to its G.E. holdings.</p>
        <p>G.E. expects the domestic market to pick up soon, too. Keith S. Sherin, the chief financial officer, predicts that sales of big gas turbines will rise as environmentalists continue to oppose new coal plants and as nuclear plants age.</p>
        <p>He also predicts that domestic airlines, which have not been buying planes lately, will be ready to add to their fleets in a few years.</p>
        <p>Profits are up at NBC Universal. And G.E. is close to a deal to sell its plastics business, which faces price pressures and soaring materials costs. ''The auction is going very well,'' Mr. Sherin said.</p>
        <p>G.E. is sticking with its estimates of earnings of $2.18 to $2.23 a share for the full year, and is promising to increase earnings 10 to 12 percent for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>''Wall Street still discounts conglomerate stocks, but this quarter showed the power of a diverse portfolio to manage through troubles,'' said Richard D. Steinberg, president of Steinberg Global Asset Management, which owns G.E. shares.</p>
        <p>Solaris Asset Management, not a G.E. shareholder now, may soon become one. ''Problems like the subprime delinquencies are just a pimple on a company of G.E.'s size,'' said Timothy M. Ghriskey, chief investment officer for Solaris. ''This stock has underperformed so badly that yes, I think it is presenting a buying opportunity again.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
