<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The 3-Paragraph Job Review</title>
    <meta content="14offline" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/business/14offline.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S OFFLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Absenteeism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard Business Review</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Best Life (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Working Mother (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Prevention (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Careerbuilder Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Paul B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bossidy, Lawrence A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dailey, Kate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appraisals and Valuation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appraisals and Valuation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Harvard Business Review</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bossidy, Lawrence A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4D6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The 3-Paragraph Job Review</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The 3-Paragraph Job Review</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL B. BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Paul B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Offline column; Lawrence A Bossidy, in The Harvard Business Review, suggests new way of doing performance appraisals; Kate Dailey, in Best Life, reviews basics of time management; Working Mother cites study by researchers at Florida State University showing that bad boss can be bad for employee's health; Prevention, based on CareerBuilder.com study, writes that some 32 percent of workers say they recently called in sick, when they actually felt fine; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS part of a terrific article entitled ''What your leader expects of you'' in The Harvard Business Review, the former chairman and chief executive of Allied Signal, Lawrence A. Bossidy, suggests a new way of doing performance appraisals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bossidy, who now serves as a consultant and board member, wrote that the typical appraisal form is often three pages long and filled with the ''vaguest, most uncommunicative language imaginable.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an article in The Harvard Business Review, the former chairman and chief executive of Allied Signal suggests a new way of doing performance appraisals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS part of a terrific article entitled ''What your leader expects of you'' in The Harvard Business Review, the former chairman and chief executive of Allied Signal, Lawrence A. Bossidy, suggests a new way of doing performance appraisals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bossidy, who now serves as a consultant and board member, wrote that the typical appraisal form is often three pages long and filled with the ''vaguest, most uncommunicative language imaginable.''</p>
        <p>''People write and write and write -- and say nothing.''</p>
        <p>Appraisals, he says, should be on a form that takes up less than half a page, and covers three topics only: What the boss likes about your performance, what you can improve and how you and your boss are going to make sure that improvement happens.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bossidy doesn't think the descriptions that fill up the three categories need a lot of words, but they do require detailed information.</p>
        <p>For example, under what I (the boss) like, managers might write that you are ambitious, a team player, you volunteer to lead initiatives and quash bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>And he would be as brief, but specific, in the ''what can improve'' category. ''It might include phrases about you such as: 'inconsistent communicator; impetuous; often fails to anticipate and vague in appraising performance of others.' ''</p>
        <p>The crucial thing is what you do with your evaluation. In the comment section, Mr. Bossidy said he might write something like: ''Joe, it's great to have you and your talents, but we need to decide how to progress on your development. Let's meet on Tuesday, after you've had a chance to consider an action plan.''</p>
        <p>Assessments, Mr. Bossidy believes, should be ''simple and to the point.''</p>
        <p>TICK TOCK -- One way to make the boss happy is to concentrate on the things she believes are really important. In other words, make her priorities your priorities.</p>
        <p>For everyone who has said ''there aren't enough hours in the day,'' Kate Dailey in Best Life reviews the basics of time management:</p>
        <p>Delegate. ''There are times when only your skill, wit, charm or intellect will suffice,'' Ms. Dailey writes. ''Those times are rare, and they're almost never meetings.'' If possible, get someone else to represent you. That gives you more time to spend with the higher-ups -- unless, of course, it is their meeting.</p>
        <p>Do you have to be there? Can you handle the situation with an e-mail message or a phone call, instead of in person? While meeting face-to-face is important to establish a relationship, once the relationship is in place, you probably don't have to go.</p>
        <p>Ask: What will happen if I don't do this? If no one will notice, or care, it isn't a priority, and it isn't worth doing.</p>
        <p>Balance important and urgent. Something that needs to be done right away -- the boss wants the sales figures now -- is urgent. But you need also to be working on the important stuff, things that are critical to the long-term success of the organization. If all you are doing is putting out fires, you won't be effective in the long run.</p>
        <p>Says Mark Ellwood, a productivity consultant in Toronto, ''The priorities that people set, and what they actually do are often inconsistent.''</p>
        <p>YOU MAKE ME SICK -- ''A bad boss can be bad for your health.'' So writes Working Mother magazine, reporting on a study by researchers at Florida State University.</p>
        <p>''Employees stuck in an abusive work relationship,'' say, ones where the boss fails to keep promises or bad-mouths someone to other employees, ''experience more exhaustion, job tension, nervousness, depressed moods and distrust,'' writes the study's lead author, Wayne Hochwarter, based on a survey of more than 700 workers in various occupations.</p>
        <p>FINAL TAKE -- Some 32 percent of workers ''say they've recently called in sick, when they actually felt fine,'' Prevention writes, based on a CareerBuilder.com survey.</p>
        <p>That probably doesn't surprise you. But this might: Some 27 percent of employers ''fired an employee for doing just that.</p>
        <p>PAUL B. BROWN</p>
        <p>WHAT'S OFFLINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
