<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Companion Of Wolfowitz Rejects Portrayal</title>
    <meta content="14riza" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/washington/14riza.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Bank</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Helene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riza, Shaha Ali</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Bank</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Riza, Shaha Ali</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5DF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="386" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Companion Of Wolfowitz Rejects Portrayal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Companion of Wolfowitz Rejects Portrayal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HELENE COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Helene</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shaha Ali Riza, Libyan-born British citizen, had already worked at World Bank for seven years by 2005, when Paul D Wolfowitz, whom she had been seeing for several years, arrived as president; Riza has written memo to bank committee investigating her transfer to State Dept and unusually large pay increase; she maintains that she did not see any conflict of interest, and reminds committee that she had not wanted to leave bank; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before she became the subject of intensive news coverage as the companion of Paul D. Wolfowitz, the World Bank president, Shaha Ali Riza was known as a highly educated international bureaucrat who worked on issues related to women and girls in developing countries.</p>
        <p>The Libyan-born Ms. Riza, a British citizen, holds degrees from the London School of Economics and Oxford University. She had already worked at the World Bank for seven years by 2005, when Mr. Wolfowitz, whom she had been seeing for several years, arrived as president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shaha Ali Riza is said to have complained that the news media is portraying her as Paul D. Wolfowitz’s partner or close friend, and glossing over her accomplishments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before she became the subject of intensive news coverage as the companion of Paul D. Wolfowitz, the World Bank president, Shaha Ali Riza was known as a highly educated international bureaucrat who worked on issues related to women and girls in developing countries.</p>
        <p>The Libyan-born Ms. Riza, a British citizen, holds degrees from the London School of Economics and Oxford University. She had already worked at the World Bank for seven years by 2005, when Mr. Wolfowitz, whom she had been seeing for several years, arrived as president.</p>
        <p>At the bank, Ms. Riza worked with the Middle East and North Africa Social and Economic Development Group, as the senior gender and civil society coordinator in the office of the group's chief economist. She was later appointed the group's senior communications officer.</p>
        <p>Ms. Riza, who speaks Arabic, French, Italian, Turkish and English, was married to Bulent Aliriza, a Turkey expert at the Center for Strategic and International Studies, and has a son. She could not be reached for comment. Mr. Wolfowitz is divorced.</p>
        <p>Her friends say that she has complained in recent days that she is being portrayed in the news media in a one-dimensional way, as Mr. Wolfowitz's partner or close friend, not for her accomplishments. They say she believes that she is a vehicle for employees of the bank to get rid of Mr. Wolfowitz, with whom they have clashed on policy and style.</p>
        <p>On April 9, Ms. Riza wrote a memo to the bank committee investigating her transfer to the State Department and an unusually large pay increase. She maintained that she did not see any conflict of interest, and reminded the committee that she had not wanted to leave the bank for the State Department. Ms. Riza made no mention in the memo of her pay raises, which increased her salary by more than $60,000 to $193,590. The World Bank's staff association has questioned the propriety of the increase.</p>
        <p>''I have now been victimized for agreeing to an arrangement that I have objected to and that I did not believe from the outset was in my best interest,'' Ms. Riza wrote, describing the ''personal pain and stress that my son and I have been subjected to, and the damage that this whole episode has caused me professionally, physically and psychologically.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
