<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Markets Suffer After Russia Bans Immigrant Vendors</title>
    <meta content="14market" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/world/europe/14market.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kramer, Andrew E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EED6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Markets Suffer After Russia Bans Immigrant Vendors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Markets Suffer After Russia Bans Immigrant Vendors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW E. KRAMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kramer, Andrew E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russia has declared that only citizens can sell vegetables in markets; decree is seen as one of more draconian anti-immigration measures in Europe; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From a stall inside the Rizhskiy vegetable market, Rustam K. Umarov conducts an illegal trade in oregano, cinnamon sticks, peppercorns, saffron powder and shish kebab marinade.</p>
        <p>Under a government decree that took effect April 1, Mr. Umarov, as a citizen of Uzbekistan, has been banned from working as a vendor at any of Russia's 5,200 markets, which were a mainstay for groceries and household goods through the 1990s and still account for a fifth of all retail trade here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A strict anti-immigrant measure allowing only Russians to sell vegetables and other market goods is resulting in acute shortages and price increases in some regions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From a stall inside the Rizhskiy vegetable market, Rustam K. Umarov conducts an illegal trade in oregano, cinnamon sticks, peppercorns, saffron powder and shish kebab marinade.</p>
        <p>Under a government decree that took effect April 1, Mr. Umarov, as a citizen of Uzbekistan, has been banned from working as a vendor at any of Russia's 5,200 markets, which were a mainstay for groceries and household goods through the 1990s and still account for a fifth of all retail trade here.</p>
        <p>It does not matter that he is a legal immigrant. Under the decree, seen as one of the more draconian anti-immigrant measures in Europe, only Russian citizens can sell vegetables.</p>
        <p>''They are happy to buy my spices, but in the street there is hate for immigrants,'' Mr. Umarov said, spooning dried mint leaves into a bag with practiced care.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Umarov has kept a low profile and his business running, thousands of immigrant market workers have closed their stalls across Russia.</p>
        <p>As a result, only 68 percent of the market stalls in Russia are occupied, according to government figures, while shortages and price increases are becoming acute in some regions. In one market in Chelyabinsk, in the Ural Mountains, prices for nonfood items rose 16 percent, according to the government, which surveyed 14 markets earlier this month. In Moscow, some 10,000 of the estimated 60,000 market stalls were vacant, according to the city government.</p>
        <p>Shoppers are starting to grumble. ''They aren't selling as many fruits and vegetables,'' said Yeva Y. Terekova, a retired teacher shopping for groceries at Syestniye Ryady market in Moscow on a recent afternoon. ''Prices went up, too.''</p>
        <p>Another pensioner standing nearby, however, offered, ''It's better now without the Azeris in the market.''</p>
        <p>After the collapse of the Soviet Union, the vegetable markets came to be dominated by thousands of immigrants, mostly young men and women from the former Soviet states. Like immigrants everywhere, they came to Russia for work. And as elsewhere, their presence has stirred resentment and demands that the jobs they created be given to natives.</p>
        <p>Police teams from the Federal Migration Service have arrived in buses to enforce the new rule, arresting and deporting immigrants. Notices pinned to the doors of markets advertise open spaces for Russians, or ''farmers from the Fatherland.''</p>
        <p>In one poll by the independent Levada Center, 54 percent of Russians supported the statement that ''Russia is for Russians,'' a phrase the pollsters used to gauge the extent of anti-immigrant feeling. The survey, conducted in December, had a margin of sampling error of 1.7 percentage points.</p>
        <p>''The government is playing with the crowd in a dangerous way,'' Lev D. Gudkov, the center's director, said. ''The level of xenophobia is high.''</p>
        <p>The government decree was intended, ostensibly, to ease ethnic tension after anti-immigrant rioters in the northern Russian town of Kondopoga set fire to market stalls owned by immigrants last fall.</p>
        <p>The government's solution was to reserve market stalls for Russian farmers while cracking down on the grocery mafias that, according to popular lore and official statements, control the markets.</p>
        <p>''This will ease tension on the labor market and make it more civilized,'' President Vladimir V. Putin said in November, when the law was drafted, in remarks carried by the state news agency, RIA.</p>
        <p>The decree bans immigrants from trading, but not from jobs as porters or janitors. Critics say that plays into stereotypes of Central Asians and Caucasians as crafty, cheating on the scales or gouging prices.</p>
        <p>Critics also say the decree plays into the hands of Russian nationalists who are playing an ever more prominent role as presidential elections approach next year.</p>
        <p>Galina V. Kozhevnikova, a deputy director at SOVA, which monitors hate crimes, said the rule would embolden anti-immigrant groups. SOVA recorded 539 attacks on members of ethnic minorities in 2006, including 54 racially motivated murders.</p>
        <p>Russia's vegetable markets operated on a network of immigrant families -- principally Azeris, Uzbeks and Tajiks in the west and Chinese in the eastern parts of Siberia -- with ties to the warmer climates where the produce grows. Now, some are half empty, and traders say an era is coming to a close.</p>
        <p>Mr. Umarov must speak furtively to clients who ask how to apply his marinades, or ask for a whiff of the ground pepper. At any moment, he said, he could be shut down.</p>
        <p>The city's low regard for immigrants was baldly displayed last winter, when the snow-laden roof of a vegetable market collapsed and crushed 66 people to death, 64 of them immigrants. Mayor Yuri M. Luzhkov said the victim's families would be compensated -- but only the few living legally in the city.</p>
        <p>The rule took effect in stages, limiting immigrant traders to 40 percent of the total in markets from Jan. 15 through April 1, and now prohibiting them entirely.</p>
        <p>At the Dorogomilovsky Market in Moscow, a notice on an empty stall advertised, ''Help wanted, a Russian citizen trader.'' A Central Asian man leaned against a wall nearby, idly cracking sesame seeds in his teeth.</p>
        <p>At the meat counter, a young Slavic man awkwardly wielded an ax to hack ribbons of fat from mutton ribs, under the eye of an Azeri butcher. Mostly, the stalls vacated by immigrants remained empty, with few Russians apparently willing to try the menial work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Umarov, for one, thinks the government will eventually rescind the decree. ''They think that they will take this work from us, that when we leave, they will have this work,'' he said. ''But they cannot work like us.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
