<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Republican Candidates Set Fast Pace for Spending</title>
    <meta content="14donate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/us/politics/14donate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HEADING TOWARD 2008"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirkpatrick, David D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Election Commission</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E7DC103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Republican Candidates Set Fast Pace for Spending</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Republican Candidates Set Fast Pace for Spending</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK and JOHN M. BRODER; Russ Buettner, Griff Palmer, Aron Pilhofer and Jeff Zeleny contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D; Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mitt Romney, whose presidential campaign leads Republican primary field in fund-raising, spent nearly 60 percent of $20.7 million he raised in first quarter, setting breakneck pace for start of 2008 race; Rudolph W Giuliani, runner-up in fund-raising among Republicans, spent over 40 percent of $13.8 million his campaign brought in, leaving both candidates with roughly same amount in bank as of beginning of April (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mitt Romney, whose presidential campaign leads the Republican primary field in fund-raising, spent nearly 60 percent of the $20.7 million he raised in the first quarter, setting a breakneck pace for the start of the 2008 race.</p>
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani, the runner-up in fund-raising among the Republicans, spent more than 40 percent of the $13.8 million his campaign brought in, leaving both candidates with roughly the same amount in the bank as of the beginning of April.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mitt Romney, who leads Republican fund-raising, spent nearly 60 percent of his $20.7 million first-quarter take.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mitt Romney, whose presidential campaign leads the Republican primary field in fund-raising, spent nearly 60 percent of the $20.7 million he raised in the first quarter, setting a breakneck pace for the start of the 2008 race.</p>
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani, the runner-up in fund-raising among the Republicans, spent more than 40 percent of the $13.8 million his campaign brought in, leaving both candidates with roughly the same amount in the bank as of the beginning of April.</p>
        <p>Their expenses, disclosed Friday in first-quarter financial reports filed with the Federal Election Commission, underscore the heavy costs that each candidate has incurred to bring in their contributions and, in Mr. Romney's case, raise his profile among voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney, for his part, spent more than any candidate had even raised during this stage of the 2004 presidential race. He spent $11.6 million during the quarter.</p>
        <p>The reports also indicate the relatively narrow base of big donors behind each of the Republican primary's two fund-raising leaders. Mr. Romney raised about $9.2 million, nearly half his first-quarter total, from about 4,000 contributors who gave the maximum $2,300 allowed under campaign finance laws. Mr. Giuliani's primary campaign raised about $7.6 million, more than half its total, from about 3,300 donors who paid the maximum. About 430 gave an additional $2,300 to Mr. Giuliani's general election fund, as well.</p>
        <p>With 32,000 donors, Mr. Romney's average contribution was about $650. With about 28,000 donors, Mr. Giuliani's average contribution was over $500. In contrast, the campaign of Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, had 50,000 donors. The campaign of Senator Barack Obama, Democrat of Illinois, had more than 100,000. Both had average contributions of about $250 a donor, based on their disclosures so far.</p>
        <p>The first-quarter reports are the first look at the scramble for money behind the 2008 presidential race. For the first time since the advent of public financing of presidential campaigns in the aftermath of Watergate, all the leading candidates are planning to reject public matching funds to spend without limits for the primary and the general election.</p>
        <p>Unlike the case before public financing, election laws now cap individual contributions -- this year at $2,300 each for the primary and the general election -- placing special importance on so-called bundlers who collect $2,300 checks from rich friends and associates.</p>
        <p>Candidates are required to file their reports by Sunday. Mr. Romney and Mr. Giuliani's campaigns chose to file two days ahead of that deadline. Mr. Giuliani's campaign filed in the morning, presumably to maximize attention to the amount of cash he has on hand.</p>
        <p>Dependence on a relatively small number of donors who have already contributed the maximum to the campaign could be a potential liability in part because it could make it hard for candidates to sustain their fund-raising pace. Candidates with a larger number of smaller contributors can go back to them again for more cash, and they can also cite their donor rolls as evidence of popular support.</p>
        <p>The Romney and Giuliani campaign reports provide snapshots of their respective candidacies. Mr. Romney began the campaign little known outside of Massachusetts, where he was governor; Michigan, where his father was governor; and Utah, where he was chief executive of the 2002 Winter Olympics in Salt Lake City. And as he stepped forward to introduce himself to Republican primary voters, he came under fire from the right for past liberal stances on social issues like abortion (he says his views evolved).</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney had substantial financial resources. He is the multimillionaire founder of a major private equity firm, and his personal wealth gives his campaign a reserve if needed. (To jump-start his fund-raising, he lent the campaign $2.35 million.) His family is among the best-known in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, enabling him to tap networks of rich Mormons, as well as Wall Street financiers. He raised about $2.8 million in Utah, $2.3 million in Massachusetts and $1 million in Michigan -- about 30 percent of his total. He raised more than $140,000 from executives of his former companies, Bain consulting and Bain Capital.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney used his war chest to spend nearly $2 million on television advertising in selected states, much more than any of his primary rivals, to introduce himself to voters on his own terms before others could characterize him. He also spent heavily on fund-raising consultants in 16 states, for example paying more than $200,000 to buy a list of potential donors from a Virginia direct mail firm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's greatest asset, in contrast, is the fame he acquired as the mayor of New York after the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11, 2001. In a conference call to discuss the fund-raising report, Mr. Giuliani's aides noted that they had raised most of their campaign contributions, about $10 million, in the last month of the quarter. They acknowledged a late start in spending and fund-raising, but said the big March demonstrated their momentum.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's first-quarter report did little to address the question of whether he can extend his reputation for strength under fire into deeper support from Republican primary voters in other parts of the country, where his liberal views on social issues are not yet well known.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani raised more than 30 percent of his first-quarter contributions from three states, New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, with about $4.5 million coming from the New York area and $1.3 million from Los Angeles. Employees of Mr. Giuliani's law and consulting firms gave about $77,000.</p>
        <p>The rest of the presidential candidates are expected to file their reports over the weekend. In anticipation of new scrutiny, Mr. Obama, who raised $25 million during the first quarter, disclosed Friday that his campaign had returned 49 political contributions totaling $50,566 from registered lobbyists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama's campaign has promised to refuse contributions from registered lobbyists. Accepting such donations is legal, and the Obama campaign has sought contributions from the clients of lobbyists or other interest parties. But the campaign has declared the ban on lobbyists' money to burnish Mr. Obama's image as a candidate intent on changing the business of Washington. The campaign said the checks were accepted inadvertently.</p>
        <p>''Giving back these donations is part of our best efforts to ensure we stay true to our commitment to not take money from federal lobbyists,'' Bill Burton, a campaign spokesman, said. ''As we've said and as this illustrates, this policy isn't a perfect solution to the problem of money and politics and special interest sway in Washington.''</p>
        <p>HEADING TOWARD 2008</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
