<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Aches And Pains: Now Pavano Will Miss Start</title>
    <meta content="14yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/sports/baseball/14yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pavano, Carl</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DC103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Aches And Pains: Now Pavano Will Miss Start</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">More Aches and Pains: Now Pavano Will Miss Start</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees' most fragile player has added himself to the team's growing list of wounded pitchers. Carl Pavano, who missed most of the last two seasons with a variety of injuries, will miss his start here Saturday with stiffness in his right arm.</p>
        <p>Pavano said the stiffness was in a muscle area of his forearm, near his pitching elbow; Manager Joe Torre described it as a soft-tissue problem. Darrell Rasner will start against the Oakland Athletics on Saturday, and Torre said Pavano was scheduled to pitch Tuesday at Yankee Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carl Pavano, who missed most of the last two seasons with a variety of ailments, will miss his start on Saturday with stiffness in his right arm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees' most fragile player has added himself to the team's growing list of wounded pitchers. Carl Pavano, who missed most of the last two seasons with a variety of injuries, will miss his start here Saturday with stiffness in his right arm.</p>
        <p>Pavano said the stiffness was in a muscle area of his forearm, near his pitching elbow; Manager Joe Torre described it as a soft-tissue problem. Darrell Rasner will start against the Oakland Athletics on Saturday, and Torre said Pavano was scheduled to pitch Tuesday at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>''It's dependent on the fact that he feels well enough to do it,'' Torre said. ''If he's not the one, we'll have someone. Who that pitcher is right now, I can't tell you. But we'll have someone.''</p>
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang is pitching Saturday, but it will be in a rehabilitation game in Tampa, Fla. Wang is on the disabled list with a strained right hamstring, and the Yankees hope he can rejoin them to pitch against the Tampa Bay Devil Rays on April 24.</p>
        <p>Mike Mussina left his start Wednesday with a strained left hamstring, and Torre said Mussina could be ready by next weekend in Boston. Jeff Karstens, who is out with elbow stiffness, will start in the minors Monday.</p>
        <p>''With the way things have gone with Chien-Ming and Moose, yeah, it's disappointing,'' Pavano said. ''I want to be out there every fifth day. But I think the wiser course of action is the way to do it.''</p>
        <p>Pavano threw seven strong innings in Minnesota on Monday for his first victory since May 22, 2005. But he said he felt elbow stiffness near the end of the Twins game, then felt tightness when he played catch the next two days.</p>
        <p>''I threw on Tuesday and Wednesday, but it didn't feel like I thought it should feel,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Since June 2005, Pavano has missed time with injuries to his shoulder, back, buttocks, elbow and rib cage. Only the elbow required surgery; he had a bone chip removed last May. Pavano said that injury was not related to this one.</p>
        <p>''It's in a totally different spot than what I felt last year,'' said Pavano, adding that he would throw off the bullpen mound Sunday to test his arm.</p>
        <p>Torre said Pavano's long layoff from pitching in the majors had probably tired him out.</p>
        <p>''He was asking his body to do something it hadn't done in a year and a half,'' Torre said. ''Extending, getting out there, letting it go.''</p>
        <p>Rasner lost his first start last Sunday against Baltimore, when blisters hindered his command of off-speed pitches. He has treated the blisters since then and threw in the bullpen Wednesday with no problems.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's going to be an issue,'' Rasner said.</p>
        <p>Mussina played catch and did running exercises Friday, and he will also throw off a mound Sunday. Mussina said that while his hamstring felt sore, it was better than he expected over all. ''We haven't made any target dates and we haven't talked much about the disabled list,'' Mussina said. ''We're all thinking pretty positively right now.'' The injuries come at a time when the Yankees' strength and conditioning program is facing increasing scrutiny. During the off-season, General Manager Brian Cashman hired Marty Miller to the newly created position of director for performance enhancement. Cashman promoted Dana Cavalea to assist him.</p>
        <p>But while injuries are increasing, not decreasing, in frequency, Torre is not blaming Miller.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, we talked to Marty Miller when he first came on, and everything he does is geared toward making the body stronger and making the body function better,'' Torre said. ''A lot of things in baseball are unpredictable, as far as moves. I think that's more the cause of anything than, for some reason, we're changing the routine.</p>
        <p>''And, understand, we're not forcing players to do things. Guys who are used to doing things a certain way are still doing things a certain way. I don't, at this point in time, think there's any reason to tie the two together. ''But it doesn't mean you're defending something you're not sure of. I don't think we have enough information yet to make that connection and say, 'Oh my God, what did we do?' Because Marty certainly has information to back up everything he's doing.''</p>
        <p>If Pavano cannot start Tuesday, it is unclear who would do so. Sean Henn is the long reliever, but he tired after about 40 pitches when he replaced Mussina on Tuesday. The Yankees would probably have to summon a pitcher from the minors, but none of those starters have major league experience.</p>
        <p>The rotation at Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre includes Tyler Clippard, Phil Hughes, Ross Ohlendorf, Matt DeSalvo and Steven Jackson, none of whom are on the 40-man roster. Hughes, 20, may be the best pitching prospect in baseball, but he does not seem quite ready, allowing five runs on seven hits and two walks over five innings in his last start.</p>
        <p>The prospect pitching best now is Chase Wright, a Class AA left-hander with a devastating changeup who is already on the 40-man roster. Wright, 24, has allowed no runs while striking out 19 in 14 innings this season, but he has pitched only two games above Class A.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
