<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Reap Benefits of Having Hossa in Lineup</title>
    <meta content="14rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/sports/hockey/14rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840135"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hossa, Marcel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Reap Benefits of Having Hossa in Lineup</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers Reap Benefits of Having Hossa in Lineup</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rangers Coach Tom Renney wanted to keep left wing Marcel Hossa's shifts short in Game 1 against the Thrashers. After all, the 25-year-old Hossa had missed the past month with an injured left knee.</p>
        <p>So when Hossa was stuck on the ice too long Thursday night while center Michael Nylander skated the puck around the offensive zone for what seemed like minutes, Renney cringed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marcel Hossa, who had missed the past month with an injured left knee before Thursday night’s game, has returned quickly to the way he was playing before his injury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rangers Coach Tom Renney wanted to keep left wing Marcel Hossa's shifts short in Game 1 against the Thrashers. After all, the 25-year-old Hossa had missed the past month with an injured left knee.</p>
        <p>So when Hossa was stuck on the ice too long Thursday night while center Michael Nylander skated the puck around the offensive zone for what seemed like minutes, Renney cringed.</p>
        <p>But his anxiety quickly turned to a cheer. Nylander passed the puck to defenseman Fedor Tyutin, who shot it toward the Atlanta net. Hossa was camped in front of it and deflected the puck in for his first career playoff goal in the Rangers' 4-3 victory.</p>
        <p>''For Marcel, it was his first game in five weeks and I know he's going to be better,'' said Jaromir Jagr, who had a goal and an assist. ''He played good, but he's going to be a lot better. And it gives us a chance to play better.''</p>
        <p>Playing on the No. 1 line with Jagr and Nylander, Hossa appears to be the answer to the question, Which of these three does not belong? Hossa is a late bloomer, which seems more noticeable because of the spectacular success of his brother, Marian, the Thrashers' star right wing, who has 270 career goals and had 100 points this season.</p>
        <p>Marcel Hossa had a grand total of 22 career goals before joining the top line in early February. He then added eight goals before his regular season ended March 5, when he sprained the medial collateral ligament in his left knee.</p>
        <p>The Rangers' top line is probably responsible for Atlanta Coach Bob Hartley's sudden decision Friday to bench goalie Kari Lehtonen for Game 2 on Saturday. Hossa, Nylander and Jagr each scored in Game 1.</p>
        <p>For Game 2, Hartley will turn to Johan Hedberg, who helped lead Pittsburgh to the Eastern Conference finals in 2001. Hartley's move, which came just hours after he seemed to chalk up Lehtonen's performance to nerves, was the second surprise of the series.</p>
        <p>The first was Hossa's remarkably quick return to the way he was playing before he hurt his knee.</p>
        <p>The injury interrupted Hossa's coming-of-age story. In 14 games playing with Nylander and Jagr, Hossa had eight goals and four assists. His confidence grew visibly with each game.</p>
        <p>''For me, I like playing there,'' Hossa said. ''They hold the puck in the zone and create some chances. For me, I'm still learning from them. It's good experience for me and I'm looking forward to playing the whole time with them.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers' top line can paralyze opponents. Jagr and Nylander can hold the puck for impossibly long stretches, skating it around and passing to each other. They keep the other team pinned near its own net and they force opponents to exhaust themselves trying to take the puck away. That sort of shift produced Jagr's goal 12 minutes 50 seconds into Game 1.</p>
        <p>A line with Jagr and Nylander requires a strong left wing who will fight for possession along the boards and set up in front of the net for deflections or to screen the goalie. After searching for that piece of the puzzle for most of the season, Renney settled on Hossa in February.</p>
        <p>While Hossa was injured, Brad Isbister moved in. Isbister did not score a single goal, but he did have four assists. Hossa, who is 6 feet 3 inches and 220 pounds, battles for the puck and adds a scoring touch.</p>
        <p>''Both guys, Marcel and Izzy, they're strong guys that can play on the boards,'' Jagr said. ''That's very important. They can battle on the boards and make it easier for me and Mike. We don't have to be there all the time. If you don't have anybody like that, it's tough to score from the corners.''</p>
        <p>Hossa admitted to being nervous in Game 1. He took a big hit from defenseman Alexei Zhitnik in the second period that sent him to the bench for a shift. He said his knee, which is supported by a brace while he skates, was sore Friday, but otherwise felt strong.</p>
        <p>''When you see the first line going like that, it really lifts everybody up and we all try to do the job, too, especially defensively, so those guys can score,'' center Martin Straka said Friday. ''It doesn't mean they are going to do it every game, but it was great last night.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Rangers defenseman Karel Rachunek practiced and is now considered day-to-day. Rachunek, who sprained a ligament in his right knee March 13, could rejoin the lineup next week.  Rangers center Blair Betts sat out practice Friday. He said he was banged up but would play in Game 2.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
