<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witnesses for the Persecution</title>
    <meta content="14zumwalt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/opinion/14zumwalt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minneapolis-St Paul International Airport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Good Samaritans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">US Airways</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zumwalt, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
        <org class="online_producer">US Airways</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DE103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witnesses for the Persecution</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Witnesses for the Persecution</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Zumwalt</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zumwalt, James</byline>
      <dateline>RESTON, Va.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Zumwalt Op-Ed article notes that six Muslim imams who were removed from US Airways flight at Minneapolis-St Paul airport after fellow passengers complained that they were acting suspiciously have filed lawsuit against airline and unknown John Doe defendants; says John Doe defendants are passengers who voiced concern to airline employees, and once their identities are determined, complaint will be amended to name them specifically; proposes good Samaritan federal law that would protect anyone who reports concerns in good faith from suffering consequences of civil liability for speaking up (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN an echo of the final episode of ''Seinfeld,'' which involved a violation of a ''good Samaritan law'' that required a witness to a crime to come to the victim's assistance, a recent lawsuit in a United States federal court demands consideration of a related law -- with real-life application -- to protect good Samaritans.</p>
        <p>The incident that gave rise to the claim occurred last Nov. 20 at the Minneapolis-St. Paul airport. Six Muslim religious leaders, or imams, were removed from a domestic US Airways flight after fellow passengers and airline personnel became concerned about what they deemed suspicious behavior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>We need a good Samaritan federal law to protect anyone motivated to report concerns in good faith from suffering the consequences of civil liability for speaking up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN an echo of the final episode of ''Seinfeld,'' which involved a violation of a ''good Samaritan law'' that required a witness to a crime to come to the victim's assistance, a recent lawsuit in a United States federal court demands consideration of a related law -- with real-life application -- to protect good Samaritans.</p>
        <p>The incident that gave rise to the claim occurred last Nov. 20 at the Minneapolis-St. Paul airport. Six Muslim religious leaders, or imams, were removed from a domestic US Airways flight after fellow passengers and airline personnel became concerned about what they deemed suspicious behavior.</p>
        <p>Witnesses described conduct that suggested something ominous might in fact be in the offing. The imams, the passengers reported, prayed loudly in the open terminal before boarding, sat in different seats on the plane from those assigned, positioned themselves near exits, asked for unneeded seatbelt extensions (which they then placed under their seats) and, most disturbingly, made anti-American comments.</p>
        <p>The six were escorted off the plane so security personnel could conduct additional screening to ensure that they represented no threat to flight safety. By the time they were cleared by security, the plane had departed without them.</p>
        <p>Four months later, the imams filed their lawsuit against US Airways. Such claims normally are filed just against the airlines for allegedly improper conduct of its personnel. However, this suit went further, listing unknown (''John Doe'') defendants as well. The John Doe defendants are the fellow passengers who voiced concerns to airline employees about the suspect behavior. Once the John Doe defendants' identities are determined through discovery, the intent is to amend the complaint to name them specifically.</p>
        <p>While the imams may or may not have suffered an injury, the harm these John Doe claims can cause will go far beyond what the defendants themselves will suffer by being dragged into litigation. It is clear this lawsuit seeks to warn Americans against voicing similar concerns. For if they do, they run the risk of opening themselves up to liability and incurring enormous legal defense costs. The effect this would have -- discouraging Americans from playing an active role on the home front in fighting the war on terrorism -- is chilling.</p>
        <p>Some security experts suggest the imams' conduct may have been intended to identify aviation security weaknesses. Their John Doe lawsuit tends to support this theory, as such a complaint can also serve to manipulate our legal system to silence those who might otherwise report suspicious activity.</p>
        <p>Anyone in the security business knows that if a passenger exhibits suspicious behavior before takeoff, he or she cannot be allowed to board -- or remain on -- the plane until that behavior has been satisfactorily explained or otherwise resolved. Post-9/11, anyone entering an air terminal should be sensitive to this need and should work in a cooperative spirit to remove any suspicion.</p>
        <p>Nothing can prevent a passenger who believes he has been wronged by the screening process from filing a lawsuit. What is outrageous is to hold good Samaritans liable simply for doing what any reasonable person observing suspicious activity should do. This is pure and simple intimidation.</p>
        <p>In the interests of national security, Congress cannot allow this to happen. While the House has taken the initiative to insert protective language in a public transportation bill, that bill does not go far enough. Such protection needs to be comprehensive, extending to the public at large rather than just those using airplanes or other public transportation. (Obviously, such a law should not protect anyone whose motivation is based on personal profiling.)</p>
        <p>The good Samaritan law in ''Seinfeld'' created a duty to act. In the real world, such a law would obviously fail judicial scrutiny. Not even in fighting the war on terrorism could a legal duty to report suspicious activities be imposed upon observers -- although, one would hope, good citizens would feel a moral obligation to do so.</p>
        <p>What can be legislated, however, is a good Samaritan federal law to protect anyone motivated to report concerns in good faith from suffering the consequences of civil liability for speaking up. We need to understand that it takes a collective effort to keep us safe, and we need to protect those who act with that in mind.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor James Zumwalt is a retired marine and a member of the Committee on the Present Danger, an anti-terrorism education and advocacy group.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Zumwalt is a retired marine and a member of the Committee on the Present Danger, an anti-terrorism education and advocacy group.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
