<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>UNDER SEDATION, CORZINE IS FACING A LONG RECOVERY</title>
    <meta content="14corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/nyregion/14corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CORZINE'S CRASH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cody, Richard J (Acting Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E1DD103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>UNDER SEDATION, CORZINE IS FACING A LONG RECOVERY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine Facing Severe Hurdles in Intensive Care</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN and DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI; David W. Chen reported from Trenton and David Kocieniewski from Camden; Ken Belson and Serge F. Kovaleski, in New York, and Ronald Smothers, in Trenton, contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David; Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov Jon S Corzine of New Jersey is in critical condition at Camden hospital, as his children and colleagues wrestle with litany of medical and political uncertainties after devastating traffic accident in which he was not wearing seat belt; medical experts say that Corzine faces life-threatening complications and will undergo more operations in days ahead; state officials vow that business of New Jersey will continue uninterrupted; Sen Pres Richard J Cody has become acting governor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Relying on a ventilator to help him breathe, Gov. Jon S. Corzine was in intensive care at a Camden hospital on Friday night as his children and colleagues wrestled with a litany of medical and political uncertainties after a devastating traffic accident in which he was by all accounts not wearing a seat belt.</p>
        <p>On the surface, at least, state officials vowed that the business of New Jersey would continue uninterrupted. At a news conference on Friday afternoon in the State House, Senate President Richard J. Codey, who became acting governor Thursday night, appeared with Mr. Corzine's chief of staff, Tom Shea, and said, ''It's their administration, not mine.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a devastating car crash, Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey is to undergo more operations, one today and another on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Relying on a ventilator to help him breathe, Gov. Jon S. Corzine was in intensive care at a Camden hospital on Friday night as his children and colleagues wrestled with a litany of medical and political uncertainties after a devastating traffic accident in which he was by all accounts not wearing a seat belt.</p>
        <p>On the surface, at least, state officials vowed that the business of New Jersey would continue uninterrupted. At a news conference on Friday afternoon in the State House, Senate President Richard J. Codey, who became acting governor Thursday night, appeared with Mr. Corzine's chief of staff, Tom Shea, and said, ''It's their administration, not mine.''</p>
        <p>But medical experts cautioned that Mr. Corzine still faced considerable hurdles and even life-threatening complications in the days ahead, including the possibility of pneumonia and infection. He remained in critical condition and heavily sedated, and doctors said that he is to undergo more operations, one on Saturday and another on Monday. [Page B2.]</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's condition, and his difficult prognosis, clearly drained two of his three adult children, Jeffrey and Jennifer Corzine, who appeared at a news conference on Friday morning at Cooper University Hospital.</p>
        <p>They said they were heartened by the support pouring in from throughout the state and nation. But they also departed from a written statement that had aimed for a more optimistic tone, with words like ''encouraged'' tucked into the text, and instead offered a far more raw and measured response.</p>
        <p>''We got a really good vibe today,'' said Ms. Corzine, 36, who lives in Manhattan, and spent Thursday night at a hotel near the hospital. ''He's a fighter,'' she added, her voice breaking and fighting back tears. ''I think he's going to be O.K.''</p>
        <p>Still, doctors and state officials did not mince words in discussing Mr. Corzine's situation after a crash that was much worse than initially reported, with the unbelted Mr. Corzine jettisoned from the front passenger seat into the back from the impact.</p>
        <p>Both Robert J. Rasinski, the state trooper driving the car, and Samantha Gordon, the aide in the back seat, were apparently wearing their seat belts. Mr. Rasinski left the hospital at 5:15 p.m. Friday. Ms. Gordon was sore, but otherwise uninjured.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gordon, a personal assistant to the governor, spent much of Friday at the hospital and said she was confident the governor would recover. ''I feel blessed and so is he,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The accident comes at a critical juncture for Mr. Corzine, 60, a liberal Democrat in his first term who has yet to gain real traction with the public or fellow politicians around the state. He faces a $2 billion deficit to plug by summer, a growing crisis over the state's pension system, and questions over financial gifts he gave a former companion who runs the largest union of state workers.</p>
        <p>Months of painful rehabilitation could well limit Mr. Corzine's physical and political stamina for tackling such an array of problems that would challenge the healthiest and most established of political figures.</p>
        <p>The crash occurred about 6:15 p.m. Thursday in the northbound lanes of the Garden State Parkway, about five miles north of the Atlantic City Expressway. The governor's Chevrolet Suburban swerved to avoid a Dodge Ram truck that had, in turn, turned to avoid a red pickup that was described by the police as driving erratically.</p>
        <p>The Suburban slid into the end of a guardrail, which ''penetrated the vehicle, and struck both Rasinski and Governor Corzine,'' according to a police report.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's left thigh bone, or femur, was fractured, and it punched two holes through his skin. He lost about half of the blood in his body, requiring seven units during surgery Thursday night, and broke six ribs on each side, along with his sternum, collarbone and a lower vertebra.</p>
        <p>Doctors provided few details about the extent of internal injuries, the arc of Thursday night's treatment, or the prognosis for recovery. Mr. Corzine remained unable to speak because of the breathing tube.</p>
        <p>''He's very lucky,'' Dr. Steven E. Ross, Cooper's head of trauma, said at a morning briefing, dismissing initial reports from political aides that Mr. Corzine's injuries were not considered life-threatening. He added: ''He has significantly improved over the course of the night. He does awaken and is able to communicate with us a little bit.''</p>
        <p>It was unclear when Mr. Corzine would return to work, though Mr. Shea estimated he might be coherent enough to conduct some state business within a week or 10 days.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert F. Ostrum, Cooper's director of orthopedic trauma, who led the surgical team, said Mr. Corzine would require extensive rehabilitation. He will probably need to use a wheelchair, a walker or crutches for a while, and Dr. Ostrum said it could be six months ''before he's able to get around well by himself.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine became governor in January 2006 after serving five years in the United States Senate, where he led his party's Senate campaign committee for the 2004 elections. A former co-chairman of the investment bank Goldman Sachs, he spent $100 million of his own fortune on his two campaigns, first to the United States Senate, then to the governor's office.</p>
        <p>But all day Friday, Trenton's establishment struggled to digest the frailty of life for Mr. Corzine, who is not just the most heavily guarded public official in the state, but also a physically imposing 6-foot-3 former marine with ample self-confidence.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, New Jersey had two points of political gravity. One was in Camden, at one of the state's three major trauma centers, a place more accustomed to gunshot wounds and gang members than harried government officials and reporters. The other was in Trenton, which is usually moribund on Fridays, but on this day 20 television cameras and dozens of reporters crowded into a news conference. It lasted only 17 minutes and many questions remained.</p>
        <p>Why did the front airbags -- standard on a 2005 Suburban like the one Mr. Corzine was riding in -- fail to deploy? Who is in charge of making medical decisions on behalf of Mr. Corzine, who was divorced in 2003? (An aide said on late Friday that he has a living will, but declined to provide any details.)</p>
        <p>Where was the red pickup truck that is believed to have started the chain reaction? (According to Lt. Gerald Lewis Jr. of the state police, it is a 1980s or early 90s Ford F150 pickup truck, possibly with New Jersey license plates, faded red paint, and a white or red top covering the cargo portion; investigators are reviewing security videotapes from toll plazas in the area in hopes of finding it.)</p>
        <p>And why was Governor Corzine not wearing a seat belt, which is required by the law in his state? New Jersey was the second state in the nation, after New York, to make seat-belt use mandatory, the law taking effect in 1985. But ever since the law was upgraded in 2000, allowing the police to pull over drivers whom they suspect are not wearing seat belts, seat belt use has been rising, with 90 percent of drivers and front seat passengers in New Jersey wearing them in 2006, the eighth-highest rate in the country, according to a federal traffic survey.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea said that Mr. Corzine had worn his seat belt most of the time he was traveling on Thursday, even though friends have long said that they have rarely seen him wear one. But Mr. Shea said that for some reason, he did not appear to wear one when the accident occurred.</p>
        <p>''If he was not, he certainly should have been, and we should encourage the state police to issue a citation,'' Mr. Shea said.</p>
        <p>Asked if the trooper serving as his driver and protector might have tried to persuade the governor to put on his seat belt, Mr. Shea, alluding to the governor's headstrong nature, said, ''Those who know Governor Corzine know that he is not always amenable to suggestions.''</p>
        <p>For now, political opponents and friends said they were united in wishing the governor well, and in expressing confidence in Mr. Codey. After all, Mr. Codey, a fellow Democrat, filled in as governor for 14 months after Gov. James E. McGreevey resigned in 2004 after announcing that he had had a gay affair.</p>
        <p>Out of deference to Mr. Corzine, Mr. Codey said he would not work in the governor's office, but in his own Senate office. He said that he -- and by extension the government -- would travel to wherever Mr. Corzine was to conduct business, whether it be Drumthwacket, the governor's mansion in Princeton, or Hoboken, where Mr. Corzine rents a condominium.</p>
        <p>Two top Republicans -- Senate Minority Leader Leonard Lance and State Senator Joseph M. Kyrillos, a former state party chairman -- said that they did not think the accident and the governor's period of recuperation would alter basic Corzine administration goals, like the possible lease of the state's toll roads. They also praised Mr. Codey's pinch-hitting abilities.</p>
        <p>''He is a steady man and knows his place in this situation and he will not enact sweeping policy or try to remake the office,'' Mr. Kyrillos said. ''He is there to hold things steady until the Governor returns.''</p>
        <p>CORZINE'S CRASH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
