<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Friends Reunite for Film, But Actress's Death Casts Pall on Premiere</title>
    <meta content="14orph" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/movies/14orph.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E1D6133FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Friends Reunite for Film, But Actress's Death Casts Pall on Premiere</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Friends Reunite for Film, but Actress’s Death Casts Pall on Premiere</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL AMDUR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Amdur, Neil</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lily Wheelwright and Ry Russo-Young were friends while growing up in the West Village and pursuing their artistic dreams as classmates at Saint Ann's School in Brooklyn. So when Ms. Russo-Young became a writer-director and began casting her first full-length movie, ''Orphans,'' it seemed somehow fitting that she would pick Ms. Wheelwright for one of the two lead characters.</p>
        <p>But at a time when the pair should be savoring the excitement of their first film, including next week's screening at the Sarasota Film Festival in Florida, a pall hangs over any celebrations. Ms. Wheelwright died on March 22 in New York at 24, apparently of a drug overdose. Ms. Russo-Young, 25, has remastered the print, dedicating the film to Ms. Wheelwright. And this afternoon, a memorial service will be held at the Meeting House of Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims in Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A “free spirit” makes her movie debut in “Orphans” and then, suddenly, dies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lily Wheelwright and Ry Russo-Young were friends while growing up in the West Village and pursuing their artistic dreams as classmates at Saint Ann's School in Brooklyn. So when Ms. Russo-Young became a writer-director and began casting her first full-length movie, ''Orphans,'' it seemed somehow fitting that she would pick Ms. Wheelwright for one of the two lead characters.</p>
        <p>But at a time when the pair should be savoring the excitement of their first film, including next week's screening at the Sarasota Film Festival in Florida, a pall hangs over any celebrations. Ms. Wheelwright died on March 22 in New York at 24, apparently of a drug overdose. Ms. Russo-Young, 25, has remastered the print, dedicating the film to Ms. Wheelwright. And this afternoon, a memorial service will be held at the Meeting House of Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''It was really pretty shocking,'' said Joe Swanberg, a 25-year-old director who had seen rough and final cuts of ''Orphans'' and had met Ms. Wheelwright. ''All of us are working on a small level, a community, and it's like we've lost one of our own.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wheelwright's death follows that of another New York independent film artist, Adrienne Shelly, who was murdered on Nov. 1. The movie ''Waitress,'' which she directed, is scheduled to open in limited release May 2.</p>
        <p>''Orphans'' tells the story of two sisters: Sonia (James Katharine Flynn), a teacher in a rural town, and Rosie (Ms. Wheelwright), a struggling writer with a drug problem in the city. The two meet at Sonia's house in the country for a birthday party that painfully links past and present but ultimately offers some hope for the future. Andrew O'Hehir of Salon.com called ''Orphans'' a ''striking (if unevenly crafted) first film that simultaneously summons the spirits of Bergman's 'Cries and Whispers' and Brian De Palma's 'Sisters.' ''</p>
        <p>After high school, Ms. Wheelwright and Ms. Russo-Young had parted ways. Ms. Wheelwright spent a year at Yale and then enrolled in Columbia's general studies program, said her mother, Eliza Hicks.</p>
        <p>''She liked the school of the streets and visual arts,'' Ms. Hicks said of her daughter's instinctive streak, which included bungee jumping naked off a bridge.</p>
        <p>Her bungee-jumping friend, the photographer Ryan McGinley, recalled in an e-mail message that ''everyone else freaked out about it, but Lily was excited to do it.'' Mr. McGinley, who is preparing a photo book on Ms. Wheelwright for the memorial service, described her as his muse.</p>
        <p>''She was a beautiful tomboy,'' he said. ''She was always looking for an adventure and never scared to get into trouble. And if we ever did get in trouble, Lily would always get us out of it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Russo-Young, who attended Oberlin College, reunited with her old friend after Ms. Wheelwright's younger sister, Josie, auditioned for ''Orphans'' and then mentioned her to Ms. Russo-Young. ''Josie was funny and full of life, but the character of Rosie was a little bit more edgy, someone less innocent, who had seen the world,'' Ms. Russo-Young said. ''Lily didn't act beautiful, and she was a completely free spirit.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wheelwright was still so nervous about her first on-screen crying scene that she spent a day with an acting coach. She also mentioned her history with drugs to Ms. Russo-Young and Ms. Flynn, another Saint Ann's alumna. Ms. Russo-Young said there were no problems during filming in upstate New York in early 2006.</p>
        <p>After finishing the film, while Ms. Russo-Young edited, Ms. Wheelwright, who was fluent in Spanish, decided to move to Barcelona. She rejoined the cast in Austin, Tex., at the South by Southwest Film Festival where, Ms. Russo-Young said, ''we all thought she looked great.''</p>
        <p>''At the festival, I hung out with her, we saw some movies, went to some parties together, stayed up late and had a fun time,'' Ms. Russo-Young said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wheelwright returned to New York for her parents' 25th wedding anniversary and a 60th-birthday party for her mother. ''There were people there she hadn't seen in years,'' Ms. Hicks said. ''Lily was talking about going for more acting calls and was torn between going back to Barcelona and staying in New York.''</p>
        <p>Then came the news of Ms. Wheelwright's death. Ms. Hicks said the medical examiner surmised that Ms. Wheelwright ''had a relapse moment real bad.''</p>
        <p>''It was something that would call to her -- something in the brain -- that takes time to get out when they have a relationship,'' she added, speaking of her daughter's problems.</p>
        <p>A screening in Ms. Wheelwright's memory will be held April 30 at 10 p.m. at the IFC Center on West Third Street in Greenwich Village. ''Since Lily's death, everybody wants to see the movie,'' said Ms. Russo-Young, who estimated the cost of the film at ''under $1 million.'' Distribution can be difficult for neophyte directors, but Ms. Russo-Young said she has received offers for theatrical distribution and a DVD release. (She declined to provide specifics.)</p>
        <p>The sequence of events, however, continues to haunt her. ''I have no idea how to make sense of it,'' she said. ''It feels freaky, weird, something I never could have foreseen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
