<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prosecutor Loses Effort to Dismiss Main Ethics Charge</title>
    <meta content="14duke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/us/14duke.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dna (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Duke University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Duff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nifong, Michael B (Dist Atty)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Duke University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nifong, Michael B</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1DF103FF937A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prosecutor Loses Effort to Dismiss Main Ethics Charge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Prosecutor Loses Effort to Dismiss Main Ethics Charge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DUFF WILSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Duff</byline>
      <dateline>RALEIGH, N.C. April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Durham County Dist Atty Michael B Nifong, facing criticism for pressing sexual assault charges against three Duke University lacrosse players he now agrees were wrongly accused, argues for dismissal of most serious ethics charge against him; charge accuses Nifong of failing to properly disclose DNA reports to defense lawyers; hearing panel rules that all ethics charges will be heard at trial in June; Nifong photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Facing a hailstorm of criticism for pressing sexual assault charges against three men he now agrees were wrongly accused, the Durham County district attorney was before a hearing on Friday where his lawyers argued for dismissal of the most serious ethics charge against him.</p>
        <p>The charge accuses the prosecutor, Michael B. Nifong, of failing to properly disclose DNA reports to defense lawyers in the Duke lacrosse rape case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A hearing panel ruled that all the ethics charges against Michael B. Nifong, the prosecutor in the Duke lacrosse rape case, would be heard at a four-day trial in June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Facing a hailstorm of criticism for pressing sexual assault charges against three men he now agrees were wrongly accused, the Durham County district attorney was before a hearing on Friday where his lawyers argued for dismissal of the most serious ethics charge against him.</p>
        <p>The charge accuses the prosecutor, Michael B. Nifong, of failing to properly disclose DNA reports to defense lawyers in the Duke lacrosse rape case.</p>
        <p>A hearing panel ruled that all the ethics charges, including one that Mr. Nifong had made inflammatory public comments, would be heard at a four-day trial in June. Mr. Nifong could face penalties up to disbarment.</p>
        <p>His appearance here came two days after the North Carolina attorney general, Roy A. Cooper, dismissed sexual offense and kidnapping charges against three former Duke lacrosse players, blaming a false accuser and a ''rogue prosecutor'' for a miscarriage of justice. Mr. Cooper's office had spent three months reinvestigating the case after Mr. Nifong recused himself to fight the ethics charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong apologized on Thursday in a statement, saying, ''To the extent that I made judgments that ultimately proved to be incorrect, I apologize to the three students that were wrongly accused.''</p>
        <p>On Friday, he said, ''My statement yesterday was in plain language.'' Lips pursed, surrounded by reporters and cameras before and after the one-hour preliminary hearing, he declined to comment further.</p>
        <p>His lawyer, David B. Freedman, said: ''I don't know how much more you can apologize when you say 'I apologize to the three players who were wrongly accused.' We would hope people would understand that apology by Mr. Nifong. It takes a lot to admit he was wrong.''</p>
        <p>The apology was rejected by defense lawyers. One of them, Brad Bannon, attended the hearing, taking careful notes, and said afterward that the former Duke students and their families wanted Mr. Nifong ''to have what he denied them -- a fair hearing.''</p>
        <p>The hearing considered Mr. Nifong's motion to dismiss the ethics charges that he had hid exculpatory DNA evidence.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the North Carolina State Bar, which is pursuing the ethics case against Mr. Nifong, said he had misled judges and lawyers and failed to properly disclose reports showing at least four samples of unidentified male DNA on the accuser or her clothes, none of it from lacrosse players.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong's lawyers argued that he turned over 1,844 pages of DNA reports in October, well before a trial was scheduled. They said that met the requirements of the law.</p>
        <p>Katherine Jean, prosecuting the ethics case for the bar, said Mr. Nifong learned of the DNA results six months earlier, in April -- a week before he issued indictments against two of the men. Ms. Jean said it was ''scary'' to consider what would have happened if the men had had to plea bargain in the case, as commonly occurs, without the evidence.</p>
        <p>F. Lane Williamson, a Charlotte lawyer who is chairman of the three-member hearing panel, sided with the bar, though he cautioned that this was a preliminary issue without any evidence being heard. ''If you were trying to hide that, you would do exactly that,'' Mr. Williamson said. ''You would dump the information rather than simply say, 'Yeah, there were four other guys with DNA there.' ''</p>
        <p>A few more details emerged late Thursday about the weakness of the case against the three men. Attorney General Cooper has promised a detailed report next week.</p>
        <p>He told the CBS program ''60 Minutes'' that the accuser had acted irrationally and appeared to be under the influence of drugs or alcohol when she spoke with his staff, according to a CBS news release. In a segment to be shown on Sunday, Mr. Cooper said the woman gave a new and unlikely version of the attack.</p>
        <p>Further, he said, the woman gave irrational answers when she was shown time-stamped photographs from the party that contradicted parts of her story. ''It was usually that the picture was doctored or 'that just can't be true,' or 'Duke University paid someone off,' '' Mr. Cooper said for the program.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cooper said the woman still wanted to press charges. But The News and Observer of Raleigh reported on Friday that the woman's cousin has talked with her and ''she's just glad it's over with.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
