<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disabled List Is Next Stop For Mussina And Pavano</title>
    <meta content="16pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/sports/baseball/16pins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mussina, Mike</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pavano, Carl</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disabled List Is Next Stop For Mussina And Pavano</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yankees Add Pavano and Mussina to D.L.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the Yankees' most hopeful outcome, Mike Mussina and Carl Pavano would have taken the bullpen mound on Sunday morning, thrown with no pain and made their turns in the rotation this week.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mussina threw seven pitches and shut himself down. Pavano never even made it to the mound. By noon, both pitchers had been placed on the disabled list, sending the Yankees scrambling for replacements.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two weeks into the season, New York’s pitching rotation is in tatters, with Mike Mussina and Carl Pavano added to the disabled list on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the Yankees' most hopeful outcome, Mike Mussina and Carl Pavano would have taken the bullpen mound on Sunday morning, thrown with no pain and made their turns in the rotation this week.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mussina threw seven pitches and shut himself down. Pavano never even made it to the mound. By noon, both pitchers had been placed on the disabled list, sending the Yankees scrambling for replacements.</p>
        <p>The season is two weeks old, and the rotation is in tatters. Chien-Ming Wang and Jeff Karstens are already on the disabled list, and now they have company. Mussina's injury is a strained left hamstring, and Pavano's is right forearm stiffness.</p>
        <p>Chris Britton joined the team as insurance for a tired bullpen. More pressing, though, is the need for healthy starters.</p>
        <p>Chase Wright will start Tuesday against the Cleveland Indians at Yankee Stadium, a reward for his two outstanding outings this season for Class AA Trenton. Kei Igawa, Darrell Rasner and Andy Pettitte are scheduled to start the next three games. The starter for Saturday against the Red Sox at Fenway Park is unknown.</p>
        <p>''We just have to fight through it,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said. ''Whoever gets the opportunity to take the ball gets a chance to show what he's got, no different than Wang two years ago when he took Kevin Brown's spot.''</p>
        <p>Wright, 24, has allowed no runs on four hits and a walk for Trenton, striking out 19 over 14 innings. He is on the 40-man roster, unlike the starters at Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre, but he did not appear above Class A until this season, his seventh in the Yankees' system.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' best prospect is Phil Hughes, who is 1-1 with a 6.30 earned run average at Class AAA. The Yankees are being careful not to rush the 20-year-old Hughes, although Cashman also said, ''He wasn't the recommended choice.''</p>
        <p>Wang is out with a strained right hamstring and will make his second minor league start on Thursday. He is on schedule to return April 24 at Tampa Bay. Karstens had elbow stiffness at the end of spring training and will start for Class A Tampa on Monday. Five days later is the open spot in Boston.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to project that far ahead,'' Cashman said. ''Karstens hasn't even made his first start yet.''</p>
        <p>Mussina can jog and throw with no pain, but pitching on a downhill slope is more demanding. The left hamstring absorbs a right-hander's weight when he lands at the end of his delivery. Mussina said he felt it in the bullpen.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to go back to the beginning,'' said Mussina, who left his start on Wednesday after 43 pitches. ''I've made a lot of improvements. I don't want to start over.''</p>
        <p>He had already been scratched from his turn on Tuesday, but the Yankees hoped he could slide into the Saturday spot against Boston. Mussina saw no reason to push it.</p>
        <p>''Was it realistic to think I could pitch? I don't know,'' Mussina said. ''Is it smarter to get rid of it and then go pitch? Yeah. We'll take our time and do it right. If I can improve this much in the next four days, I'll feel pretty good about it.''</p>
        <p>Pavano sounded more discouraged, a familiar refrain for a pitcher defined by his growing list of injuries. Since June 2005, he has been sidelined for problems with his shoulder, back, buttocks, elbow, ribcage and forearm.</p>
        <p>''Not where I expected to be and not where I wanted to be,'' Pavano said after his brief workout. ''It doesn't feel good at a time like this, when guys are going down. I need to be part of the staff, but it's not something that's going to get any better by going out there and trying to be a hero.</p>
        <p>''I learned last year, I was up front about it right away. I got some treatment and hopefully get it right, but it's not responding to what we're trying to do. Maybe a little rest will get it right.''</p>
        <p>Pavano disputed the idea that his long layoff from pitching in the majors had simply tired out his arm. He said he traced the injury to two sidearm throws in his victory over the Twins last Monday -- one to second base on a double play, one on a pickoff throw.</p>
        <p>''Last year, before I had my elbow surgery for the bone chip, I did the same thing on some bunts and I strained my forearm,'' Pavano said. ''It could pertain to something like that.''</p>
        <p>Cashman said he would not rule out tests for Pavano, who said he assumed he would have his arm examined when the Yankees return to New York. But Pavano insisted he was not worried about significant damage.</p>
        <p>''The key for me is the spot where it's at,'' he said. ''A lot of it's muscle. It could just be a strain. It doesn't feel like it's anything where the ligaments or tendons are involved, and I know my arm pretty good.''</p>
        <p>Considering Pavano's history, the Yankees may have seen the last of him for a while. But Cashman, who signed Pavano to a four-year, $39.95 million contract in December 2004, said he would not assume that much.</p>
        <p>''I treat every injury as a new, distinct injury,'' Cashman said. ''If there's an injury history prior to that, I'm not sure how relevant that is.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
