<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Guys Can Indulge in a Little 'Me Time'</title>
    <meta content="16groom" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business Travel" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16groom.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GROOMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty Salons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E2DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Guys Can Indulge in a Little 'Me Time'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Guys Can Indulge in a Little ‘Me Time’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT VILLANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Villano, Matt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FAR from home, hours before his biggest business meeting of the month, the stylishly bald Adrian Anderson recently found himself in desperate need of a head shave.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson was traveling in Los Angeles, and he wasn't sure whom to trust. He had never been satisfied with unisex salons or women's salons that dabbled in men's hair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In recent years, salons with a decidedly masculine focus are offering male business travelers a range of grooming options.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FAR from home, hours before his biggest business meeting of the month, the stylishly bald Adrian Anderson recently found himself in desperate need of a head shave.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson was traveling in Los Angeles, and he wasn't sure whom to trust. He had never been satisfied with unisex salons or women's salons that dabbled in men's hair.</p>
        <p>Then he discovered Major League Trim, a year-old salon in West Los Angeles with flat-screen televisions and DirecTV at every cutting station, as well as a stockpile of magazines like Men's Health and GQ. Customers are offered water, beer or Gatorade when they walk in, and all the stylists are women.</p>
        <p>''I always heard about my girlfriend and their friends going to salons and sitting around getting their hair done, having wine,'' said Mr. Anderson, who is a project manager for Sprint Communications in Fairfax, Va. ''Until I found this place, I wondered why we men couldn't have that, too.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, salons with a decidedly masculine focus have popped up in major cities across the country, offering male business travelers a range of grooming options wherever they go. In addition to haircuts, many offer manicures, head massages and shoeshines.</p>
        <p>None of them serve women.</p>
        <p>Rob Reed, co-owner of Major League Trim, said the thinking behind this fraternity-style approach was simple: men want to feel comfortable when they indulge in certain spa services, and the best way to put them at ease is to provide an atmosphere that is male and a service that caters specifically to men.</p>
        <p>''For guys, between the Better Homes &amp; Gardens and Oprah on the television, getting a haircut at a traditional salon can be completely emasculating,'' Mr. Reed said. ''We're just trying to make the experience more enjoyable for our particular clientele.''</p>
        <p>The atmosphere is decidedly male at Major League Trim, which boasts on its Web site that it has ''L.A.'s hottest and most talented stylists''; the emphasis is on male sports.</p>
        <p>More upscale salons feature conservatively dressed stylists and décor that includes leather recliners, exposed brick and dark colors like tan, maroon and forest green.</p>
        <p>Take the 316 Club Barber Spa in the heart of Chicago's financial district. Co-owners Greg Savarese and Tony Montemurro founded the 2,800-square-foot salon as a throwback to the Las Vegas of the 1960s.</p>
        <p>Today, the atmosphere screams Rat Pack, with dark, sharp-edged furniture, a sound system playing vocal standards and a red-felt pool table for waiting customers.</p>
        <p>''It's like an old boys club, only for guys of every age,'' said Carmelo Preiti, the salon's manager. ''With the pool table and the bar going on, we've got a real lounge feel that all of our customers seem to love.''</p>
        <p>Other high-end men's salons focus as much on customer service as they do on ambience.</p>
        <p>The new Qua Bath and Spa at Caesars Palace in Las Vegas has a Men's Zone, where guests are encouraged to explore baths of varying temperatures and an arctic ice room before the master barber Sal Jeppi administers hourlong facials and haircuts. HairM, with locations in downtown Portland, Ore., and nearby Beaverton, sells a variety of cigars, which customers can smoke on a patio while they wait. There's also free wireless Internet, for those e-mail messages that simply must be answered.</p>
        <p>At Grooming Lounge, a men's salon with outposts in Washington and McLean, Va., each customer gets a steam towel over his face and a neck and shoulder massage. Other amenities include custom cocktails, like martinis and gin and tonics with top-shelf gin.</p>
        <p>Michael Gilman, who founded the salon with Pirooz Sarshar in 2002, noted that his employees would even help arrange rides to the airport for business travelers.</p>
        <p>''We run the business as if everyone has a personal concierge,'' he said, adding that the little extras are included in the price of haircuts and manicures.</p>
        <p>''For all of our customers,'' he said, ''that kind of service in the middle of the day is refreshing.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the grandfather of men's salons is John Allan Meing, who owns and operates four men's salons in New York under the name John Allan's.</p>
        <p>All of Mr. Meing's salons offer what is called the full service, an hourlong treatment that includes a scalp-massaging shampoo, hair conditioning, a hot towel on the face, a haircut, a manicure, a shoeshine and unlimited beverages. The price: $65, or $600 annually for unlimited visits at any club.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meing opened his first salon in 1988 on Stone Street behind the Goldman Sachs building in downtown Manhattan. For years, this salon exclusively served the financial services industry. All of the customers came in wearing designer suits, he said.</p>
        <p>Several years ago, Mr. Meing expanded his empire, with salons in Midtown, TriBeCa and the seventh floor at Saks Fifth Avenue. Commuters streaming through Grand Central Terminal stop in at the Midtown salon for ''cleanup'' haircuts. Movie moguls drop by the TriBeCa spa for manicures and shoeshines before catching limousines to Newark Liberty International Airport.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't matter who you are -- when you're sitting in our chairs, we're going to treat you like the most important person in the world,'' said Mr. Meing, a native of Nutley, N.J.</p>
        <p>''As a guy, when you feel good about grooming, the whole process stops becoming a chore and starts becoming part of your usual routine.''</p>
        <p>One satisfied customer is Doug Roberts, an executive director of education for Wireless Generation, a technology company in Brooklyn. He travels frequently, and used to squeeze in haircuts on the road, whenever he could. Now the ritual of John Allan's is something Mr. Roberts looks forward to.</p>
        <p>''I never expected that I would ever spend more than $15 on a haircut, especially since my hair is in the process of a slow exodus from my scalp,'' he said. ''Now, with the hot towels, manicures and beer, it's so much more than just a haircut -- it's a lifestyle, and it rules.''</p>
        <p>GROOMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
