<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Kindness of Strangers</title>
    <meta content="16network" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business Travel" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16network.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840796"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="INFORMATION, PLEASE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Kindness of Strangers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Kindness of Travel-minded Strangers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT VILLANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Villano, Matt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Considering that he's on the road at least one week a month, Eran Steinberg relies pretty heavily on local car service companies to take him from his New York City office to area airports. So when he caught one of the usual limo drivers padding the bill on a recent trip, Mr. Steinberg was desperate for another service he could trust.</p>
        <p>He took his search online, focusing efforts on a social networking site called LinkedIn (linkedin.com). There, Mr. Steinberg posted a simple question for other business travelers: ''What is the best airport car/limo service in N.Y.C.?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A growing number of business travelers are looking to the Web for specific answers before they ever pack a bag.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Considering that he's on the road at least one week a month, Eran Steinberg relies pretty heavily on local car service companies to take him from his New York City office to area airports. So when he caught one of the usual limo drivers padding the bill on a recent trip, Mr. Steinberg was desperate for another service he could trust.</p>
        <p>He took his search online, focusing efforts on a social networking site called LinkedIn (linkedin.com). There, Mr. Steinberg posted a simple question for other business travelers: ''What is the best airport car/limo service in N.Y.C.?''</p>
        <p>The query brought eight replies in a matter of days, each suggesting a different company. A week later, Mr. Steinberg had selected a new transportation provider.</p>
        <p>''If I had done it the old-fashioned way and just asked my friends, who knows how long it would have taken?'' said Mr. Steinberg, senior vice president of Capital IQ, a division of Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
        <p>With the preponderance of social networking Web sites designed to spark interaction among users, a growing number of business travelers are logging on for specific answers before they ever pack a bag.</p>
        <p>These sites are like Facebook or MySpace for the business-travel crowd. Users interact with other frequent travelers to swap secrets about where to stay, where to eat and where to take clients.</p>
        <p>Travelers also use the sites to facilitate face-to-face connections in the air and on the ground.</p>
        <p>Gina Bianchini, chief executive of Ning (ning.com), a fledgling social networking company in Palo Alto, Calif., said: ''Business travelers are time-poor. Any site that helps them make connections and unearth valuable information quickly and painlessly is going to be something they use again and again.''</p>
        <p>Many business travelers frequent common travel-oriented social networking sites, scouring general hotel and restaurant reviews to get an idea of what a destination is really like. For Brian Kaplan, co-founder of Parent Play, an event planning company in New York, this means a regular dose of pre-trip research on VirtualTourist (virtualtourist.com).</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan said he had recently used this site to research a ''European-style'' hotel in Atlanta. One reviewer, ''sulu88,'' said the hotel was not ''exactly a wonderful property.'' The second reviewer, ''kenadams,'' noted that ''there is nothing 'European' about this place.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Mr. Kaplan made reservations elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''I had no idea who those people were, but their input helped me avoid a bad decision,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While there is no site like VirtualTourist for business travel yet, many general social networking sites have dedicated sections to the subject. LinkedIn, for instance, has developed a message board for members to ask and answer travel-specific questions about everything from securing exit rows to connecting wirelessly from Starbucks.</p>
        <p>Internationally, other sites have taken the same approach. For example, LivingInPeru (livinginperu.com) offers a number of areas for visiting English-speakers to find details about the local business environment.</p>
        <p>For some travelers, this material can be invaluable. Kenneth Bengtsson, a private investor who lives in London, said that on a recent trip to Lima, he consulted site directories for recommendations on an overnight shipping firm and a ceviche restaurant.</p>
        <p>''When doing business in parts of the world where language is a barrier, it can be difficult to get around and to make the most of your stay,'' he wrote in a recent e-mail message. ''When I am in Peru I use the site on a daily basis.''</p>
        <p>Hotel chains are getting in on social networking for their business customers, too. Both Sheraton and Extended Stay Hotels recently started blogs where visitors can share experiences and exchange ideas.</p>
        <p>The InterContinental Hotels Group has taken this concept one step further, starting a service called eConcierge. Tom Conophy, the company's executive vice president and chief information officer, said work travelers who book online can use the service before they arrive to consult with hotel employees about dinner reservations and show tickets.</p>
        <p>Other companies use social networking sites to help set up face-to-face connections. PairUp (pairup.com) lets members share travel plans and schedule meetings with those whose itineraries overlap.</p>
        <p>AirTroductions (airtroductions.com) takes a different spin on the same idea, connecting business travelers before they ever touch the ground. Members enter their flight information for upcoming trips and check to see which other members are scheduled to be onboard. If they wish, the parties can arrange to meet, sit together and talk shop.</p>
        <p>Airlines themselves have been slow to embrace social networking. As of last month, KLM was the only major company to do so.</p>
        <p>KLM's sites connect passengers with certain interests. In June 2006, the carrier started Club China for travelers to the Far East and has added clubs for travelers to Africa (Club Africa) and for golfers (Flying Blue Golf Club). Participation in these groups is by invitation.</p>
        <p>Of course, no social networking site is flawless. Adam Rugel, founder of 71miles (71miles.com), an online travel guide in San Francisco, said that travelers should always visit more than one site, and should approach every recommendation with a healthy dose of skepticism.</p>
        <p>''Inevitably there will be reviews from folks with an ax to grind or reviews written by hotels and restaurants themselves,'' he said. ''It's always up to the reader to sort the good from the bad.''</p>
        <p>INFORMATION, PLEASE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
