<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Turbulence at CBS Radio, an Old Hand Is Back</title>
    <meta content="16cbs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/media/16cbs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFDF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Turbulence at CBS Radio, an Old Hand Is Back</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amid Turbulence at CBS Radio, an Old Hand Is Back</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF LEEDS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leeds, Jeff</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five years after leaving a top post at CBS Radio, Dan Mason officially returns today to lead the unit again. He is likely to find that the headaches have worsened.</p>
        <p>Almost by default, this week promises to be a quieter one at CBS, which suspended and then ousted the talk-show host Don Imus from his longtime home station last week amid a firestorm over a racially offensive remark he made on his program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new chief of CBS Radio, who starts Monday, faces problems that relate more to iPods than Don Imus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five years after leaving a top post at CBS Radio, Dan Mason officially returns today to lead the unit again. He is likely to find that the headaches have worsened.</p>
        <p>Almost by default, this week promises to be a quieter one at CBS, which suspended and then ousted the talk-show host Don Imus from his longtime home station last week amid a firestorm over a racially offensive remark he made on his program.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Mason's arrival is unrelated to Mr. Imus's departure, and there are more profound problems facing Mr. Mason.</p>
        <p>In an industry suffering from sluggish advertising sales, CBS and other broadcasters have been laboring to cling to listeners -- many of whom are spending more time these days with their mobile phones, Internet radio and portable music players.</p>
        <p>Broadcast radio remains the dominant source of entertainment in cars, according to survey data released last year by Bridge Ratings, a radio research company. But while 94 percent of people in the survey said they listened to radio, a share that has been slowly declining, 15 percent said they used digital music players, more than triple the figure two years earlier.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mason, who will be president and chief executive of CBS Radio, said it would play to radio's strengths in delivering local news and entertainment. Part of that, though, will be making local content from CBS stations available on demand to a global audience through a new digital platform, he said.</p>
        <p>But first, Mr. Mason must stabilize CBS's businesses in major media markets, including New York, where Mr. Imus was considered a mainstay. One estimate last week, from Bear Stearns, said Mr. Imus's program accounted for $15 million to $17 million in revenue. By another account, it generated in excess of $20 million in annual revenue for CBS Radio and the flagship New York station WFAN. Combined with ad sales for affiliates, the figure was put closer to $50 million.</p>
        <p>The last time CBS was forced to replace a marquee talent, it struggled. In 2006, Howard Stern decamped to Sirius Satellite Radio and left CBS scrambling to replace the estimated $100 million in annual revenue he had generated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mason, who was involved in the company's reaction to the escalating criticism of Mr. Imus, said ''it was a good decision'' to cancel the show, but added, ''I'm very sad about the whole situation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mason -- who has said he grew up with a radio and telephone under the bed covers at night so his parents could not hear him dial to win prizes in contests -- broke into the radio business as a late-night disk jockey on a station in his native Kentucky.</p>
        <p>He eventually moved to programming stations in Atlanta, Washington and San Antonio. In 1993, he joined Westinghouse as president of the Group W radio unit, and later oversaw the integration of Westinghouse's stations with CBS.</p>
        <p>He spent the last few years as a consultant, including for CBS.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mason was hired to replace Joel Hollander, an executive who had served as a top lieutenant to the former CBS chief executive, Mel Karmazin.</p>
        <p>Now that he is back, Mr. Mason is likely to review the company's experiments with flipping formats in big markets -- which have so far delivered mixed results. Perhaps the most prominent was the decision to switch from oldies or classic rock in cities like New York and Los Angeles and replace them with more diverse formats, including Jack FM, which includes hit songs from several decades and is said to sound like an iPod-style play list.</p>
        <p>CBS said eight of its nine Jack stations had generated better ratings in the crucial 25- to 54-year-old demographic group than the previous formats did.</p>
        <p>All that comes as the company is under pressure to improve its financial performance. CBS Radio accounts for 14 percent of the parent company's revenue, and was the only CBS business unit to report lower sales and operating income last year. It reported $1.96 billion in sales, down 7 percent from the previous year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mason's challenge is doing something in the programming area to regain audiences, said Michael Nathanson, a research analyst at Stanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>''We on the Street are wondering, what is it going to cost them?'' he said. ''It may not be cheap. They probably have to spend on marketing, they have to go and rethink the talent. This guy has his work cut out for him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mason has not addressed how he might handle changes in specific cities, though radio analysts who know him predict that he will not show much patience for national brand-name formats.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot of generic radio out there, across all companies,'' Mr. Mason said. ''For the radio industry to be able to maintain listening levels, it has to create interesting content that people want to hear.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
