<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opposition Rally in Russia Halted by Police for 2nd Day</title>
    <meta content="16russia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/world/europe/16russia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Moscow (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Petersburg (Russia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Human Rights Watch</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kramer, Andrew E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/St. Petersburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EEDD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opposition Rally in Russia Halted by Police for 2nd Day</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Opposition Rally in Russia Halted by Police for 2nd Day</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW E. KRAMER; Michael Schwirtz contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kramer, Andrew E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Riot police officers in St Petersburg, Russia, disperse opposition rally, rounding up and arresting leaders; crackdown follows similar police action in Moscow days earlier; in both cities, Russian Interior Ministry troops line streets, dispersing protesters with truncheons; Human Rights Watch says one hospital in Moscow treated 54 people who claim they were beaten by police; events involve some of largest displays of police force used against political opposition since Pres Vladimir V Putin took office seven years ago; critics of Kremlin and political analysts attribute this to Putin's concern that street protests could snowball ahead of parliamentary elections planned for this fall; authorities have laregely ignored opposition rallies and marches in past (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Riot police officers dispersed an opposition rally in St. Petersburg on Sunday, rounding up and arresting protesters and their leaders in a chaotic street scene.</p>
        <p>The crackdown, on several hundred people who had gathered for an authorized rally but who then began an unauthorized march, followed a similar police action on Saturday in Moscow after a protest that attracted several thousand people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Riot police officers rounded up and arrested protesters and their leaders at an opposition rally in a chaotic street scene.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Riot police officers dispersed an opposition rally in St. Petersburg on Sunday, rounding up and arresting protesters and their leaders in a chaotic street scene.</p>
        <p>The crackdown, on several hundred people who had gathered for an authorized rally but who then began an unauthorized march, followed a similar police action on Saturday in Moscow after a protest that attracted several thousand people.</p>
        <p>Interior Ministry troops lined the streets in both cities, dispersing the protesters with truncheons.</p>
        <p>The weekend's events involved some of the largest displays of police force used against the political opposition since President Vladimir V. Putin took office seven years ago. The marches have become a test both of the determination of the opposition and the willingness of the government to use force to suppress it, imbuing the marches with more weight in Russian politics than the small numbers of demonstrators imply.</p>
        <p>By Sunday, the police in the two cities estimated that they had arrested 370 people. Human Rights Watch said that at just one hospital in Moscow, 54 people had sought medical attention after being beaten by the police.</p>
        <p>''This police violence is only the latest example of the growing government hostility toward peaceful dissent in Russia,'' Holly Cartner, the executive director of the Europe and Central Asia division at Human Rights Watch, said in a statement. ''It has to be viewed in the context of intensifying harassment of the political opposition, human rights defenders and independent media in Russia.''</p>
        <p>Critics of the Kremlin and political analysts said that the abundance of Interior Ministry troops on the streets over the weekend -- and their use of force -- reflected concern by Mr. Putin and his advisers that street protests could snowball ahead of parliamentary elections planned for the fall. They point to the large rallies in Ukraine that came to be known as the Orange Revolution, which forced a change of government in 2004.</p>
        <p>Protesters interviewed on Saturday, most of them from a loose coalition of opposition parties called Other Russia, expressed surprise at the crackdown. They wondered what threat they could pose to Mr. Putin, who has consolidated much of Russia's political and economic power under the presidency in his seven years in the Kremlin. They noted his popularity, with polls indicating Mr. Putin has the support of more than 70 percent of Russians.</p>
        <p>In the past, the authorities had largely ignored opposition rallies and marches. Most of the pressure on opponents to Mr. Putin had come in the form of denial of permits, crackdowns on the news media and insider maneuvering to fracture the already demoralized opposition. But the events of this weekend, along with arrests at a protest in St. Petersburg in March, are likely to have a chilling effect.</p>
        <p>Organizers of the rallies, including the former chess champion Garry Kasparov, who was arrested Saturday and later released, call them ''dissenters' marches.'' They have been supported by people with diverse political views who say they are standing up for their right to oppose Mr. Putin. The groups taking part include the National Bolshevik Party of the novelist Eduard Limonov, which is known for its acts of civil disobedience and which has been banned by the government as an extremist group.</p>
        <p>The Other Russia alliance had applied for a permit for the Moscow march but was refused. The alliance defied the ban, as it did for both marches in St. Petersburg and one in the Volga River city of Nizhny Novgorod in March.</p>
        <p>On Saturday in Moscow, Mr. Kasparov was arrested in a cafe before the rally even began. He was held until late Saturday evening, accused of shouting antigovernment slogans. He was eventually released and fined 1,000 rubles, or about $39.</p>
        <p>Riot police officers tugged at the clothing of Mikhail M. Kasyanov, Mr. Putin's former prime minister and now an opposition leader, but did not arrest him. His bodyguards were arrested. The police also detained Maria Gaidar, a daughter of a former prime minister, and Ilya Yashin, the leader of the youth wing of the Yabloko opposition party.</p>
        <p>In St. Petersburg on Sunday, the police said they arrested 120 people. Among those held was Mr. Limonov, who was arrested in an apartment together with eight members of his group.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
