<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Brownstone to Baghdad, TV Crew Armed With Ingenuity</title>
    <meta content="16rain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/arts/television/16rain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Frontline Limited</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Corporation for Public Broadcasting</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Smith, Martin</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Gangs of Iraq (TV Program)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Brownstone to Baghdad, TV Crew Armed With Ingenuity</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Brownstone to Baghdad, TV Crew Armed With Ingenuity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH JENSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jensen, Elizabeth</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the producer Marcela Gaviria and the correspondent Martin Smith traveled to Iraq in November for the PBS series ''Frontline,'' they found themselves without a translator after the man they had lined up canceled abruptly because his brother had been kidnapped, shot and left for dead. (The brother lived, they were told.)</p>
        <p>They forged on with the reporting, not always knowing exactly what their Australian cameraman, Tim Grucza, had captured. So it wasn't until they returned to New York and an Arabic-speaking employee was going through the videotape that they uncovered the eye-opening scene featured in their report ''Gangs of Iraq,'' to be shown by PBS tomorrow as part of the weeklong ''America at a Crossroads'' series. As the camera hovers, Iraqi soldiers, ostensibly searching for cached weapons under the tutelage of American troops, discuss among themselves where the contraband is hidden and why the Americans won't find it, bringing home in a concise way the challenges faced by the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Gangs of Iraq,” a critical look at how Iraqi sectarianism is hampering American efforts, is the fifth post-Saddam Hussein “Frontline” film by Marcela Gaviria and Martin Smith.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the producer Marcela Gaviria and the correspondent Martin Smith traveled to Iraq in November for the PBS series ''Frontline,'' they found themselves without a translator after the man they had lined up canceled abruptly because his brother had been kidnapped, shot and left for dead. (The brother lived, they were told.)</p>
        <p>They forged on with the reporting, not always knowing exactly what their Australian cameraman, Tim Grucza, had captured. So it wasn't until they returned to New York and an Arabic-speaking employee was going through the videotape that they uncovered the eye-opening scene featured in their report ''Gangs of Iraq,'' to be shown by PBS tomorrow as part of the weeklong ''America at a Crossroads'' series. As the camera hovers, Iraqi soldiers, ostensibly searching for cached weapons under the tutelage of American troops, discuss among themselves where the contraband is hidden and why the Americans won't find it, bringing home in a concise way the challenges faced by the United States.</p>
        <p>''Gangs of Iraq,'' a critical look at how Iraqi sectarianism is hampering American efforts, is the fifth post-Saddam Hussein ''Frontline'' film made by Ms. Gaviria and Mr. Smith, who work from a home base in a narrow warren of brownstone offices on the Upper West Side of Manhattan, supplemented by lengthy location trips. ''Gangs of Iraq'' also includes video from freelance journalists working there and interviews with reporters who have been based there, including some from The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Starting with the DuPont Award-winning 2003 report ''Truth, War and Consequences,'' the team, working under Mr. Smith's independent production company Rain Media, has charted the course of the war. ''Truth'' looked at the planning for postwar occupation. ''Beyond Baghdad'' (2004), a road trip across Iraq that documented the fractured nature of the country, grew out of a challenge from L. Paul Bremer III, who was then the U.S. administrator in Iraq and was frustrated by the attention placed on Baghdad. A third film, ''Reporting the War'' (2005), chronicled the life of foreign journalists in Iraq; a fourth, ''Private Warriors'' (also 2005), examined the role of private contractors in the war effort. ''Frontline'' has also shown a string of reports, produced from Washington, exploring American policy in Iraq.</p>
        <p>The Rain Media team members travel light in Iraq with a footlong digital camera and about 10 cases of equipment, less than half of what they would use in the United States. ''We've always gone under the radar, without a lot of security, not working with soundmen or assistants, and so it's often just the three of us, sometimes just the two us and occasionally sometimes just Tim,'' said Mr. Smith, 58, who sometimes handles the camera work himself. While most journalists live outside the fortified International Zone (formerly called the Green Zone), Ms. Gaviria and Mr. Smith stay in a hotel inside the zone ''because we don't have a network, we don't have armored cars,'' Ms. Gaviria, 37, said. When they traveled this time without troop protection, to the Ministry of the Interior among other places, it was in two beat-up, unarmored cars, using drivers they trusted.</p>
        <p>''Those trips were terrifying,'' Ms. Gaviria said. ''Other journalists would say that's simply foolish, and frankly it probably was. But you've got to get your story, and you've got limited resources 'cause you are PBS, and you're not a network, and you don't have full-time security. You try to weigh it.''</p>
        <p>Although the PBS-size budget may be less than the commercial networks spend, the resources ''Frontline'' has invested in its Iraq and Afghanistan coverage are considerable, said David Fanning, the program's executive producer, who pinches money here and there from other projects to finance what are its most expensive reports. ''Gangs of Iraq,'' which received about $800,000 in production money from the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, was produced on a budget of just about $1 million, far more than the usual $550,000 to $600,000.</p>
        <p>The petite, soft-spoken Ms. Gaviria -- who walks with a cane -- was once held by guerrillas while on a reporting trip in her home country, Colombia. Still, while in Iraq she chooses carefully which times she ventures out for her work. ''If something really bad happens, I can't really run,'' she says. ''You just have to weigh what you can and cannot do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fanning stopped Ms. Gaviria from traveling to Iraq for the film on foreign journalists, he said, ''because I didn't feel like we should take another risk at that moment.'' Instead they relied on an on-site cameraman to get the material they needed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith has been producing for ''Frontline'' almost since the series began in 1983 and is one of the most prolific producers ''in the history of the series,'' Mr. Fanning said. He was on staff of the program at one point, and in the mid-1990s produced documentaries for ABC News before forming Rain Media in 1998.</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Fanning who pushed Mr. Smith to become an on-camera correspondent. ''He's got a great authority and a presence,'' Mr. Fanning said.</p>
        <p>At 6 foot 6 Mr. Smith is something of a celebrity among the troops. But one Iraqi driver on the last trip quit because he feared being seen with the obvious American. The Rain Media team also includes Ali Fadhil, an Iraqi doctor studying in New York on a Fulbright scholarship, who translated every shot they brought back. He discovered the patrol scene that Mr. Grucza had filmed ''on pure instinct,'' Mr. Smith said. The cameraman, he said, had ''just sensed that this little conversation off to the side was worth photographing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fanning said that sectarianism in Iraq was an obvious subject for this ''Frontline.'' Still, he said, ''Frontline'' reports ''are never subjects; we are always looking for the narrative thread'' that will persuade viewers to devote an hour to a single topic.</p>
        <p>In ''Gangs of Iraq'' ''we had two films,'' Ms. Gaviria said. ''It was the militia story, and it was 'standing up the Iraqi forces,' and how those two stories intersect and collide along the way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
