<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Few Good Lawyers</title>
    <meta content="16schizer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/opinion/16schizer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840785"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Internal Revenue Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schizer, David M (Dean)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Boies, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EEDE113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Few Good Lawyers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Few Good Lawyers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David M. Schizer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schizer, David M (Dean)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by David M Schizer, law school dean, says many taxes will go unpaid at top of income scale; says lawyers working for government who write tax rules are overworked, sometimes inexperienced, and they leave loopholes that are exploited by private lawyers who are more experienced and much higher paid; says that is why government should substantially increase government salaries and staffing levels at Internal Revenue Service; says tax system can be only as strong as people who run it (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOSE of us hurrying to finish our taxes by tomorrow's deadline will probably, at some point, succumb to thoughts of the I.R.S. as an all-powerful bully. But the truth is, the government is not always a match for the tax advisors of wealthy people, so a lot of taxes will go unpaid at the top of the income scale.</p>
        <p>Lawyers who represent high-income taxpayers earn more than 10 times what senior government lawyers do -- an obvious disadvantage for the I.R.S., the Departments of Justice and Treasury, and for Capitol Hill in attracting and retaining top talent. The lawyers who write our tax rules are overworked and sometimes inexperienced, so they leave loopholes that are exploited by more experienced private lawyers. When the government challenges these aggressive strategies, it loses some cases that it should win, setting precedents that taxpayers then invoke to justify other aggressive strategies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tax system can be only as strong as the people who run it, so the government has to recruit and retain the most promising talent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOSE of us hurrying to finish our taxes by tomorrow's deadline will probably, at some point, succumb to thoughts of the I.R.S. as an all-powerful bully. But the truth is, the government is not always a match for the tax advisors of wealthy people, so a lot of taxes will go unpaid at the top of the income scale.</p>
        <p>Lawyers who represent high-income taxpayers earn more than 10 times what senior government lawyers do -- an obvious disadvantage for the I.R.S., the Departments of Justice and Treasury, and for Capitol Hill in attracting and retaining top talent. The lawyers who write our tax rules are overworked and sometimes inexperienced, so they leave loopholes that are exploited by more experienced private lawyers. When the government challenges these aggressive strategies, it loses some cases that it should win, setting precedents that taxpayers then invoke to justify other aggressive strategies.</p>
        <p>As this vicious cycle shows, skimping on tax administration is a false economy. We collect less tax revenue, while encouraging taxpayers to invest in socially unproductive tax planning. Instead, if we substantially increase government salaries and staffing levels (the I.R.S. needs more than the 1,500 lawyers it has now) we can raise more revenue, with lower tax rates and less waste. Four reforms should be adopted immediately.</p>
        <p>First, the government should focus on hiring talented young lawyers, since the pay disparity with the private sector is narrower for them. For example, new I.R.S. lawyers earning $65,000 to $70,000 are making about 50 percent of the starting salary in the private sector; by contrast, senior lawyers there earn barely 10 percent of a partner's compensation at a leading law firm. To his credit, the I.R.S. Chief Counsel, Donald Korb, is already trying to recruit young lawyers. These efforts will be more effective if Congress helps new graduates repay student loans, which often are more than $100,000. A loan repayment program would be a powerful recruiting device.</p>
        <p>Second, the government should tap another promising talent pool -- recent retirees from private practice -- to mentor young lawyers. The salary gap is less of an issue for retirees, and the opportunity to give back to the tax system can be quite appealing.</p>
        <p>Third, the government should retain a small team of a dozen top tax lawyers at salaries closer to the market rate. They can serve as a rapid reaction force, deciding whether to shut down a new aggressive strategy immediately or to let it be evaluated through usual government channels.</p>
        <p>Fourth, the government should retain private lawyers to help with high-priority projects. An important constraint, of course, is that lawyers who represent private clients may view it as a conflict to help the government. But this is not always true.</p>
        <p>Through bar associations, private lawyers already volunteer to review proposed changes in the tax law and offer ways to improve them -- advice that the government can put to good use. Tax academics can also be a valuable and conflict-free source of expertise, since they ordinarily do not represent clients. And some tax litigators may view it as a prestigious opportunity, as well as a patriotic service, to represent the government in a tax case that could set an important precedent -- just as the prominent lawyer David Boies represented the government in an antitrust action against Microsoft.</p>
        <p>The tax system can be only as strong as the people who run it, so the government has to recruit and retain the most promising talent. I am reminded of an old story about a man who loves Beethoven and readily agrees when his brother invites him to come hear the Ninth Symphony -- only to learn that the performance actually is by his nephew's middle school orchestra. Just as a symphony is at its best when it is played properly, a tax system can be fair and efficient only when it is administered soundly.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor David M. Schizer, the dean of the Columbia Law School, is a lawyer who specializes in tax law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David M. Schizer, the dean of the Columbia Law School, is a lawyer who specializes in tax law.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
