<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Ailing Yankees, Most Painful Pitch Comes From Rivera</title>
    <meta content="16yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E3DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Ailing Yankees, Most Painful Pitch Comes From Rivera</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The clock in the visitors' clubhouse here read 4:42 p.m. when Jorge Posada answered his final question before boarding a bus to the airport on Sunday. The time was appropriate, because four Yankees had worn No. 42 -- including, of course, the great Mariano Rivera.</p>
        <p>But Rivera was not so great this time. He had just allowed a game-ending home run to the Oakland Athletics' Marco Scutaro, a sudden sucker punch of an ending to Jackie Robinson Day. Posada, who had called for a cutter that cut too much, was not yet ready to give a scouting report on Tuesday's emergency starter, the Class AA left-hander Chase Wright.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The clock in the visitors' clubhouse here read 4:42 p.m. when Jorge Posada answered his final question before boarding a bus to the airport on Sunday. The time was appropriate, because four Yankees had worn No. 42 -- including, of course, the great Mariano Rivera.</p>
        <p>But Rivera was not so great this time. He had just allowed a game-ending home run to the Oakland Athletics' Marco Scutaro, a sudden sucker punch of an ending to Jackie Robinson Day. Posada, who had called for a cutter that cut too much, was not yet ready to give a scouting report on Tuesday's emergency starter, the Class AA left-hander Chase Wright.</p>
        <p>''I have no idea,'' Posada said. ''I'm still trying to swallow this one.''</p>
        <p>Instead of rumbling home with a winning record on a trying trip, the Yankees left dazed after a 5-4 loss to the A's at the Coliseum. A day that began with two Yankees starters going on the disabled list ended with a No. 9 hitter taking down the game's best closer.</p>
        <p>''For me to do what I did was unacceptable,'' Rivera said.</p>
        <p>It was also unbelievable, practically. Rivera had not allowed a run since last Aug. 27, a span of 20 innings that included the postseason and spring training. Scutaro had one hit in 20 at-bats this season, including two strikeouts on Sunday, and he was down in the count, 0-2.</p>
        <p>Rivera had gotten no save opportunities this season until coming into the game to start the ninth inning, protecting a 4-2 lead. He retired the first two hitters before Todd Walker singled and Jason Kendall worked a nine-pitch walk.</p>
        <p>Posada went to the mound to make sure Rivera was all right and remind him to pitch aggressively. Rivera told Posada he felt strong, and Posada went back behind the plate.</p>
        <p>On 0-2, Rivera said he tried to come ''in, in, in'' with a pitch that Scutaro called a front-door cutter. But the ball ran too far over the plate, at 94 miles an hour, and Scutaro turned on it, blasting a screamer down the left-field line.</p>
        <p>The ball crashed into the foul pole for a homer. Rivera looked away and slashed at the air with his fist. The A's swarmed the plate to wait for Scutaro, who raised both arms as he sprang into the pack.</p>
        <p>''I was upset at myself,'' Rivera said. ''I can't control what the hitter's going to do, but I can control what I'm going to do. I have to control my pitches. I didn't, and the result is I lost a game that we should have won. Simple as that.''</p>
        <p>Posada said he was sure the ball would stay fair. Scutaro was not convinced.</p>
        <p>''I was just praying that ball wouldn't go foul,'' he said. ''He doesn't give me too many pitches to hit. Even when he throws one down the middle, it's hard to hit. Against Mariano, the last thing I expect to do was hit a home run.''</p>
        <p>Walk-off hits are a specialty for Scutaro, who has nine in four seasons with the A's. But the homer was his first hit in six career at-bats against Rivera.</p>
        <p>''Just one of those things,'' Posada said. ''Anybody's dangerous.''</p>
        <p>The loss dropped the Yankees' overall record to 5-6. They split six games on the trip while losing Carl Pavano and Mike Mussina to injuries. At least Andy Pettitte found his form, beating the Minnesota Twins with six shutout innings last Tuesday and stifling the A's for most of seven innings on Sunday.</p>
        <p>The first Oakland hitter, Shannon Stewart, reached first base on Derek Jeter's third error in two games. Jeter, who has six errors this season, could not backhand a ball in the hole.</p>
        <p>''I stayed down, and it kicked up and hit the heel of my glove,'' Jeter said. ''I wish it would have stayed down, but it came up.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte gave up hits to three of the next four batters, leading to two runs (one earned). But Pettitte and Posada adjusted, and the A's never scored again until Scutaro's home run.</p>
        <p>After using every reliever to win in 13 innings Saturday, the Yankees were thrilled that Pettitte lasted seven innings.</p>
        <p>''He gave us everything we needed,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''It was a great outing when we needed one.''</p>
        <p>For a while, Pettitte's problem was that Oakland's Rich Harden pitched better. Through six innings, the Yankees had no runs, coming close when Doug Mientkiewicz was thrown out at home plate on a ball that got away from Kendall, the catcher.</p>
        <p>There were two out and two on with Alex Rodriguez batting. Rodriguez waved Mientkiewicz home, but the ball bounced off a rotating billboard directly to Kendall, who fired to Harden to nail Mientkiewicz at the plate.</p>
        <p>''The last thing I want to do is take the bat out of Al's hand with guys on base,'' said Mientkiewicz, who had singled to snap an 0-for-24 slump. ''But when the ball gets by the catcher, 99 out of 100 times, you score on that ball.''</p>
        <p>When Rodriguez got to hit, in the top of the seventh, he doubled to chase Harden, who left with tightness in his right shoulder. Jason Giambi singled, Posada doubled in a run, and two sacrifice flies gave the Yankees a 3-2 lead.</p>
        <p>They scored again in the eighth, when center fielder Nick Swisher leaped to grab Rodriguez's drive at the wall, turning what would have been a two-run extra-base hit into a sacrifice fly.</p>
        <p>Still, a two-run lead is usually plenty for Rivera. He had allowed only three game-ending home runs in his career before Scutaro struck.</p>
        <p>''More than anything, you realize Mo's a human being,'' Pettitte said. ''I don't think people realize that at times -- including us.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
