<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hotel Extravaganzas</title>
    <meta content="16amenities" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business Travel" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16amenities.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LODGING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hotel Extravaganzas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hotel Extravaganzas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY GUNDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gunderson, Amy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CALL it the yin-yang of business travel. First, there is the transit part of the journey -- an often-harried navigation through crowded airports, where an oversize container of hair gel could be contraband and bad weather can result in delays on the tarmac. Yet dark clouds can give way to clear skies provided you have a generous expense account. A pickup from the airport in a luxury automobile? Sure. Hotel check-in at the bar instead of the lobby? No problem. A personalized monogrammed bathrobe hanging in the closet. Why not?</p>
        <p>With basic amenities covered, hotels are coddling their business-traveler guests in more extravagant ways, including quick check-in procedures, improved technology in the rooms and more attention on ''wellness,'' a term that encompasses workout services and spa treatments. Here are the latest advances.</p>
        <p>THE ARRIVAL</p>
        <p>More hotels are offering alternatives for bypassing the check-in desk. Frequent guests at Le Méridien in San Francisco (lemeridien.com), can pick their keys up from the doorman and head straight to their room, where they will find a personalized monogrammed bathrobe. At the 44-room Dylan Hotel Dublin in Ireland (dylan.ie), which opened last fall, staff members use palm-size Samsung computers to check in guests from anywhere on the property. The 248-room Ritz-Carlton Tokyo, which opened in March (ritzcarlton.com), is starting the hotel chain's first curbside check-in. Recognizing that a trip from the airport to the hotel can be draining after, say, a 14-hour flight from New York, the hotel can also arrange for guests to be picked up in a Rolls-Royce Phantom for $650 one way.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY, IN ROOM AND OUT</p>
        <p>Business travelers expect a hotel business center with some work stations and a fax machine, as well as high-speed Internet access in the room and wireless Internet access in the lobby. But hotels are adding a more refined service element. Butlers at St. Regis hotels (stregis.com), essentially personal concierges for guests, are each equipped with a BlackBerry so they can be reached at any time. Booking one of the new terrace suites at the Regent South Beach in Miami (theregentsouthbeach.com) gets you a mini-cellphone that the hotel calls a ''pocket butler,'' a credit-card-size device that can link guests with a push of a button to the real butler, the concierge, the hotel chauffeur or even the general manager.</p>
        <p>The Langham Place Hotel in Hong Kong (langhamhotels.com) provides an in-room phone with a color touch screen that can be configured to pull up weather and flight information.</p>
        <p>This fall, when the Peninsula Tokyo (peninsula.com) opens, all rooms will have mobile phones that can work anywhere in the city.</p>
        <p>When guests make reservations at the InterContinental London Park Lane (ichotelsgroup.com), which fully reopened this month after an extensive renovation, they are directed to a Web site to send e-mail messages to the concierge before their trip so they can, say, line up dinner reservations.</p>
        <p>THE SPA TREATMENT</p>
        <p>Spa treatments and yoga classes may sound like features of a leisure trip, but the hotel industry is recognizing that business travelers want massages, too. A result is extended spa hours and shorter treatments, which cater to people with hectic schedules or travelers who just need a 20-minute rubdown before heading to bed. The Four Seasons in Chicago (fourseasons.com/chicagofs) recently rolled out quick spa treatments, like 25- and 30-minute facials, massages and foot rubs. The InterContinental London Park Lane is opening a new spa in May with flexible treatment lengths, too. The hotel partnered with Elemis, a day spa near New Bond Street, and will have treatments as short as 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>Hotel gyms have hardly been an oasis for travelers, but working out while on the road is becoming a more flexible and accessible experience. Select rooms in Westin hotels have such workout equipment as treadmills, spin bikes and stability balls, as well as exercise DVDs. The Westin San Francisco Market Street, which opened this month (westin.com), makes it easier for guests to run before or after work. The concierge will lead three-mile runs and two-mile walks, and also hand out maps of the route so guest can go on their own. Le Méridien in San Francisco offers free laundry services for gym gear.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to put the stinky workout clothes in your suitcase,'' said Kristi Allen, the director of operations. ''And you don't need to bring a separate set of clothes for each day you work out.'' The laundry bags are at the hotel gym; as long as the clothes are in by 9 a.m., they are back in the guest's room by 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>Mixing work with play could be no more evident than at the Ritz-Carlton in Palm Beach this fall. That is when it is scheduled to open business cabanas -- ground-level rooms with private patios, Internet access, printers, phone lines and even meeting spaces -- steps from the beach and the pool. For globe trekkers, it means more downtime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hotels are coddling their business-traveler guests in more extravagant ways, including quick check-in procedures and improved technology in the rooms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CALL it the yin-yang of business travel. First, there is the transit part of the journey -- an often-harried navigation through crowded airports, where an oversize container of hair gel could be contraband and bad weather can result in delays on the tarmac. Yet dark clouds can give way to clear skies provided you have a generous expense account. A pickup from the airport in a luxury automobile? Sure. Hotel check-in at the bar instead of the lobby? No problem. A personalized monogrammed bathrobe hanging in the closet. Why not?</p>
        <p>With basic amenities covered, hotels are coddling their business-traveler guests in more extravagant ways, including quick check-in procedures, improved technology in the rooms and more attention on ''wellness,'' a term that encompasses workout services and spa treatments. Here are the latest advances.</p>
        <p>THE ARRIVAL</p>
        <p>More hotels are offering alternatives for bypassing the check-in desk. Frequent guests at Le Méridien in San Francisco (lemeridien.com), can pick their keys up from the doorman and head straight to their room, where they will find a personalized monogrammed bathrobe. At the 44-room Dylan Hotel Dublin in Ireland (dylan.ie), which opened last fall, staff members use palm-size Samsung computers to check in guests from anywhere on the property. The 248-room Ritz-Carlton Tokyo, which opened in March (ritzcarlton.com), is starting the hotel chain's first curbside check-in. Recognizing that a trip from the airport to the hotel can be draining after, say, a 14-hour flight from New York, the hotel can also arrange for guests to be picked up in a Rolls-Royce Phantom for $650 one way.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY, IN ROOM AND OUT</p>
        <p>Business travelers expect a hotel business center with some work stations and a fax machine, as well as high-speed Internet access in the room and wireless Internet access in the lobby. But hotels are adding a more refined service element. Butlers at St. Regis hotels (stregis.com), essentially personal concierges for guests, are each equipped with a BlackBerry so they can be reached at any time. Booking one of the new terrace suites at the Regent South Beach in Miami (theregentsouthbeach.com) gets you a mini-cellphone that the hotel calls a ''pocket butler,'' a credit-card-size device that can link guests with a push of a button to the real butler, the concierge, the hotel chauffeur or even the general manager.</p>
        <p>The Langham Place Hotel in Hong Kong (langhamhotels.com) provides an in-room phone with a color touch screen that can be configured to pull up weather and flight information.</p>
        <p>This fall, when the Peninsula Tokyo (peninsula.com) opens, all rooms will have mobile phones that can work anywhere in the city.</p>
        <p>When guests make reservations at the InterContinental London Park Lane (ichotelsgroup.com), which fully reopened this month after an extensive renovation, they are directed to a Web site to send e-mail messages to the concierge before their trip so they can, say, line up dinner reservations.</p>
        <p>THE SPA TREATMENT</p>
        <p>Spa treatments and yoga classes may sound like features of a leisure trip, but the hotel industry is recognizing that business travelers want massages, too. A result is extended spa hours and shorter treatments, which cater to people with hectic schedules or travelers who just need a 20-minute rubdown before heading to bed. The Four Seasons in Chicago (fourseasons.com/chicagofs) recently rolled out quick spa treatments, like 25- and 30-minute facials, massages and foot rubs. The InterContinental London Park Lane is opening a new spa in May with flexible treatment lengths, too. The hotel partnered with Elemis, a day spa near New Bond Street, and will have treatments as short as 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>Hotel gyms have hardly been an oasis for travelers, but working out while on the road is becoming a more flexible and accessible experience. Select rooms in Westin hotels have such workout equipment as treadmills, spin bikes and stability balls, as well as exercise DVDs. The Westin San Francisco Market Street, which opened this month (westin.com), makes it easier for guests to run before or after work. The concierge will lead three-mile runs and two-mile walks, and also hand out maps of the route so guest can go on their own. Le Méridien in San Francisco offers free laundry services for gym gear.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to put the stinky workout clothes in your suitcase,'' said Kristi Allen, the director of operations. ''And you don't need to bring a separate set of clothes for each day you work out.'' The laundry bags are at the hotel gym; as long as the clothes are in by 9 a.m., they are back in the guest's room by 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>Mixing work with play could be no more evident than at the Ritz-Carlton in Palm Beach this fall. That is when it is scheduled to open business cabanas -- ground-level rooms with private patios, Internet access, printers, phone lines and even meeting spaces -- steps from the beach and the pool. For globe trekkers, it means more downtime.  LODGING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
