<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Discount Carriers Where You Least Expect Them</title>
    <meta content="16air" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business Travel" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16air.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AIR TIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Discount Carriers Where You Least Expect Them</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Discount Carriers Where You Least Expect Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a business trip to India last year, Josef Woodman, an author and publisher from Chapel Hill, N.C., unexpectedly found himself crisscrossing the subcontinent while researching a book on the booming medical tourism industry. What was intended to be a brief visit to New Delhi evolved into a weeklong trek to cities like Hyderabad, Chennai and Mumbai to track an elusive source.</p>
        <p>''I suddenly had to move fast, even though I knew nothing about internal flights in India,'' said Mr. Woodman, whose book, ''Patients Beyond Borders: Everybody's Guide to Affordable, World-Class Medical Tourism,'' has just been released. So he got online and started searching for flights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once common only in Europe, low-cost carriers are rapidly emerging in Asia, Latin America and the Middle East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a business trip to India last year, Josef Woodman, an author and publisher from Chapel Hill, N.C., unexpectedly found himself crisscrossing the subcontinent while researching a book on the booming medical tourism industry. What was intended to be a brief visit to New Delhi evolved into a weeklong trek to cities like Hyderabad, Chennai and Mumbai to track an elusive source.</p>
        <p>''I suddenly had to move fast, even though I knew nothing about internal flights in India,'' said Mr. Woodman, whose book, ''Patients Beyond Borders: Everybody's Guide to Affordable, World-Class Medical Tourism,'' has just been released. So he got online and started searching for flights.</p>
        <p>Amid the costly options offered by full-service leaders like Air India and Indian Airlines, Mr. Woodman stumbled upon SpiceJet, India's popular low-cost carrier. Started in May 2005, privately owned SpiceJet (spicejet.com) flies a single-class 737 fleet to 13 domestic destinations from its New Delhi base, including business centers like Mumbai and Bangalore.</p>
        <p>With its easy-to-follow Web site and flexible policies, ''SpiceJet looked and felt like Southwest,'' said Mr. Woodman, a longtime fan of domestic discount carriers. ''There may have been no frills, but there were also no hassles.'' And those unexpected flights ended up being unexpectedly affordable.</p>
        <p>Once common only in Europe, low-cost carriers like SpiceJet are rapidly emerging in Asia, Latin America and the Middle East. While most at first concentrated on leisure travelers -- like the estimated 99 percent of Indians who have never flown -- the airlines are now luring business travelers as well, including more Westerners. They are travelers who may fly long-haul at the front of the cabin, but they are willing to forsake creature comforts on short-haul flights to cushion the bottom line.</p>
        <p>''These airlines can represent great value for business travelers,'' said Henry Harteveldt, a vice president and principal travel analyst at Forrester Research in San Francisco. ''And because they often fly the newest planes, the in-flight experience can exceed what you get in economy on regular U.S. carriers.''</p>
        <p>Mostly privately owned, many of these airlines are already competing on the same routes for the same market share, while simultaneously waging aggressive price wars with state-run carriers. Besides SpiceJet, India is served by discount airlines like GoAir (goair.in), Air-India Express (airindiaexpress.in) and IndiGo (www.indigo.com); the Persian Gulf region by both Sharjah-based Air Arabia (airarabia.com) and Kuwait's Jazeera Airways (jazeeraairways.com); Brazil by Gol (voegol.com.br); and Southeast Asia and Oceania by Malaysia-based AirAsia (airasia.com), Singapore-based Tiger Airways (tigerairways.com) and Australia's Jetstar (jetstar.com) and Virgin Blue (virginblue.com.au).</p>
        <p>While business travelers typically make up no more than 25 percent of all passengers, on more established low-cost carriers like Gol Airlines they fill more than half the seats.</p>
        <p>''We've seen our passenger mix shift from 60 percent leisure and 40 percent business to the exact opposite in six years,'' said Wilson Maciel Ramos, Gol's executive vice president for planning and information technology.</p>
        <p>Air Arabia's commercial director, Kyle Haywood, said that flights between its Sharjah hub (part of the United Arab Emirates) and Bahrain, Kuwait and Oman are also more than half filled by business travelers. ''They're a real microcosm of the gulf today,'' Mr. Haywood said of the passenger mix, ''from locals wearing traditional dress to expat Westerners in suits to numerous Indian traders.''</p>
        <p>Although some carriers, like Jetstar (a Qantas subsidiary), offer loyalty programs, a lack of frequent-flier points is one of many amenities business travelers appear willing to sacrifice. Like their American counterparts, global discount carriers typically serve second-tier airports and charge for meals, luggage weighing more than 55 pounds and entertainment.</p>
        <p>''But on such short flights, it's just as easy to bring your lunch on board,'' said Victoria Baldock, a managing director of Verve Entertainment in Sydney, who flies Jetstar to her satellite office in Byron Bay, a resort town about 550 miles from Sydney served only by Jetstar.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, both Jetstar and Jazeera Airways, which both offer leather seats cabinwide, have introduced premium classes for travelers who want full-service comforts, but still at a cost below major carriers. Introduced in November, Jetstar's StarClass includes hot meals, video-on-demand systems, laptop power outlets and wider seats -- at roughly a 50 percent premium. StarClass passengers can also earn frequent-flier points with Qantas, as well as use Qantas lounges before departures and make reservation changes free.</p>
        <p>On Jazeera Airways' Jazeera Plus, now 18 months old, ''we've replaced the middle seat with a workstation in each row,'' said Marwan Boodai, the chairman and chief executive. The carrier recently opened a second hub in Dubai. The move there brings low-cost air travel to the Middle East's busiest airport for the first time, with new links to seven cities in India and the Persian Gulf. It also places Jazeera in the backyard of the regional low-cost incumbent Air Arabia, which flies to more than 30 similar destinations from the emirate of Sharjah, about 45 minutes from Dubai.</p>
        <p>While the ease of the Dubai airport, connected to the United States via nonstops from New York and Houston on Emirates (and Delta plans to add service from Atlanta starting in May), will appeal to many travelers, the small size of Air Arabia's Sharjah base has advantages.</p>
        <p>''Dubai airport may theoretically be just 15 minutes from my office, but traffic can turn this journey into an hour,'' said Alasdair Evans, the area publishing manager for Arabian Trader magazine in Dubai, who flies Air Arabia to meetings in Bahrain. ''Then once in Sharjah, it takes just 10 minutes to get from check-in to the gate, much shorter than in Dubai.''</p>
        <p>For the moment, the new global discount carriers are mostly limited in use -- and appeal -- for short-haul passengers with reasonably definitive travel plans. Still, for those demanding flexibility, the carriers' pricing policies are far more forgiving than those of their full-service counterparts. ''While most of the discounters will charge to make changes, the fees will usually not be too onerous,'' Mr. Harteveldt of Forrester said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, change-fees on Jazeera Airways are roughly $10; on Air Arabia, approximately $14. Jetstar's range from $23 to $60, while they are free on SpiceJet and Gol. Like Jazeera, many of the international low-cost upstarts are either establishing additional hubs or upgrading their fleets to extend internationally. Late last year, Jetstar started flights to both Southeast Asia and as far away as Honolulu on Airbus A330s. In Latin America, Gol hopes to reach Mexico (via Peru) soon, while Air Arabia is exploring a second hub in Istanbul to better link the carrier to Europe's elaborate discount aviation network.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Woodman, who also flew through Asia on AirAsia and Jetstar during a subsequent business trip this year, concedes that the airlines ''lacked the elegance and graciousness of Singapore Airlines or Cathay Pacific,'' he says the discounters make up in spirit what they miss in service.</p>
        <p>''These smaller airlines just seemed to have more hustle,'' he said. ''On the larger carriers there is this discouraging 'who cares' attitude, but on these smaller airlines you felt like the staff was really making an effort.''</p>
        <p>AIR TIME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
