<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="16Diary" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/nyregion/16Diary.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2DE113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Overheard conversation between two men walking east on 50th Street between Eighth Avenue and Broadway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A beleaguered lawyer yearns for a more adventurous, but perhaps less reasonable, lifestyle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Overheard conversation between two men walking east on 50th Street between Eighth Avenue and Broadway.</p>
        <p>First man to his companion: ''You know, these new generations just don't get it. I don't know how they will cope in the future.''</p>
        <p>Second man replies: ''I know, especially since the world is coming to an end in 2014.''</p>
        <p>My observation: I just wish the second man had provided a month and day.</p>
        <p>Kyle Barrios</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I was born in Manhattan. Other than a forced 17-year detour to suburbia (for the children, my parents said), I have lived here my entire life. Like many Manhattanites I have a certain, shall we say, disdain for the tourists. So imagine my shock when, on my way to jury duty last month, I was greeted by the young barista at the Canal and Centre Street Starbucks with this friendly question: ''Where are you visiting from?''</p>
        <p>He could tell from the look of horror on my face that he had said something very wrong. ''Oh, you're from here,'' he said nervously. ''I'm so sorry.''</p>
        <p>Pulling myself up to my full 5 feet 4 inches, I asked, with vast Manhattanista hauteur, ''What makes you think I'm a tourist?''</p>
        <p>He looked at me apologetically and said, quietly, ''You smiled at me.''</p>
        <p>Jilann Picariello</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I thought I was inured to audience assault. There was the group munching on sandwiches at ''Jersey Boys,'' and the woman text messaging at ''King Lear.'' Every performance has its cell call rings, wristwatch dings and feedback whistles from headsets provided by the theaters.</p>
        <p>But last month we discovered a whole new branch of weaponry. Behind us at a New York Philharmonic concert two young women were sharing the headphones of an iPod. Their loud rock leaked out as Mitsuko Uchida passionately played Mozart's 19th Piano Concerto.</p>
        <p>Oh well, I guess it could have been someone watching March Madness on a laptop.</p>
        <p>Stanley Shapiro</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Early last month, at a nail salon on the Upper West Side, a college student seated to my right chatted incessantly on her cellphone, loudly sharing the details of her love life. Occasionally, for a juicy tidbit, she resorted to elementary Hebrew.</p>
        <p>When the woman on my left snorted in response to one of the racier comments, the two of us locked eyes and instantly knew we were both understanding the words.</p>
        <p>When the woman got up to leave, she called out loudly to me, ''Happy Purim!'' -- making sure the chatterer understood that when it comes to secret languages on the Upper West Side, basic Hebrew is not an option!</p>
        <p>Ora Shtull</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Overheard in a coffee shop on Court Street in Brooklyn that is frequented by lawyers:</p>
        <p>''What I really want to do is quit and start a rock band. I already have a fantastic name for one: 'Reasonable Causation.' ''</p>
        <p>Ellen D. Murphy</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I used to have my office in the East 60s. At 61st Street and Second Avenue a homeless middle-aged lady would leave her bags on the corner, step off the curb and direct traffic. I would pass her in the morning and later when I left work. There she would be, always directing traffic.</p>
        <p>One day I bought her one of those silver police whistles that every traffic cop used to have. She quickly scooped it from my hand without looking at me or saying a word, put it in her mouth, assumed her usual position and blew softly with each change of the light. The whistle was in her mouth each time I saw her.</p>
        <p>This went on for many years. I've moved my office since but still wonder how my traffic lady with the whistle is doing!</p>
        <p>Mel Reiss</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>My husband and I return to New York every now and then. Recently, we took a taxi from Midtown Manhattan to Brooklyn. As soon as we got out of the cab, my husband realized that he had left his belly pack -- containing cash, glasses, keys and cellphone -- on the cab's back seat. We despaired of ever seeing it again.</p>
        <p>Late in the day, however, we received a call from our daughter in North Carolina. She told us to phone a police station in Lower Manhattan; the taxi driver, Muhammad, had taken the belly pack to the station. The officer on duty used our cellphone to call the first number in the directory, which happened to be our daughter in North Carolina.</p>
        <p>When we retrieved the pack, we called Muhammad, who had left his phone number at the station, to thank him and to offer him something for his thoughtfulness. He would not give us his address, refusing to accept any compensation. New York, I love you!</p>
        <p>Sonya Monosoff Pancaldo</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
