<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="16forsumm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFDD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1125" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-10</p>
        <p>Iraqi Town Becomes Haven For Seasoned Insurgents  The Sunni guerrillas and extremists who now dominate Baquba, Iraq, demonstrate a sophistication and lethality born of years of confronting American military tactics. While the increase of American troops plays out in Baghdad, Baquba has emerged as a magnet for insurgents from around the country.  A1</p>
        <p>At least 34 people were killed in Baghdad in another day punctuated by car bombings and suicide vest attacks on civilian targets of the kind that the two-month-old American security crackdown has so far been unable to restrain.  A8</p>
        <p>Russia Lifts Bear Hunting Ban  For the first time in more than five decades, the Russian government is preparing to allow hunters to kill polar bears, which are descending with greater regularity on coastal villages in parts of the far north as a result of shrinking sea ice generally attributed to a warming planet. A1</p>
        <p>Wolfowitz Says He Won't Quit  Senior policy makers at the World Bank delivered a public rebuke in a communiqué to the bank's president, Paul D. Wolfowitz, making it clear they expected him to resign. After learning of the rebuke, Mr. Wolfowitz adamantly made it known at a news conference that he intended to stay on the job. A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Closes Morocco Consulate  The United States Consulate in Morocco said it would close until further notice, a day after two brothers carried out puzzling suicide attacks near the consulate amid a spate of bombings in Morocco and Algeria. A10</p>
        <p>Iran Seeks Bids on Atom Plants  The deputy head of the nation's Atomic Energy Organization was quoted by the ISNA news agency as saying the country was seeking international bids for building two more nuclear power plants despite international pressure over its nuclear program. A3</p>
        <p>Protests on Nigerian Elections  Violent protests broke out in several of Nigeria's 36 states as partial results from contested state elections seemed to hand most of the victories to the governing People's Democratic Party.  A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-15</p>
        <p>Donors Linked to Clintons Shift Support to Obama  Aides to Senator Barack Obama released a list of top fund-raisers that showed how deep his presidential primary campaign has cut into the Democratic party establishment once presumed to back his rival, Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Gonzales Has 'Nothing to Hide'  Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales offered a measured apology for his mistakes in the dismissal of eight United States attorneys, but said in testimony prepared for a Senate hearing tomorrow that he had ''nothing to hide'' and insisted that none of the prosecutors were removed to influence the outcome of a case.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Georgia Prosecutor Unyielding  When North Carolina's attorney general said an overreaching prosecutor lacked evidence to support charges of rape against three Duke University lacrosse players, some in Georgia hoped his pronouncement would help free a former star high school football player serving 10 years without parole for having consensual oral sex with a 15-year-old girl, even though he was 17 at the time.  A12</p>
        <p>Lobster Season in Distress  Although spring is traditionally when lobster prices are highest, lobsters have rarely been as scarce or expensive as they have been in the last few weeks, thanks to a confluence of bad weather, extremely cold water and a lack of reserve supply.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Festival Honors Rural Legacy  The celebration of Mule Day in Columbus, Tenn., marks the arrival of spring, but the event also acts as a window into the area's rural heritage and an homage to the humble beasts that turned the soil, gave a leg up to farmers, and cemented the county's reputation in the South for well-bred mules.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Student Loan Company Settles  Education Finance Partners, a student loan company that investigators found had paid more than 60 colleges and universities across the country for steering students to its loans, has agreed to pay $2.5 million to resolve an investigation of its practices by the New York attorney general.  A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-5</p>
        <p>Increase in Tax Returns From Illegal Immigrants  With the tax deadline approaching, illegal immigrants are sending in federal returns in what appear to be record numbers in hopes that filing a return will create a paper trail that could one day lead to citizenship.  A1</p>
        <p>Storm Sets Rainfall Records  A rare spring northeaster roared up the coast and across the New York region and the Northeast, dumping record-setting rainfall that flooded coasts and rivers, disrupted airline travel at the three major airports, and cut power lines for thousands in New York and Connecticut.  B1</p>
        <p>Church Abuse Case to Trial  While only a small fraction of sexual abuse complaints involving the Catholic Church have resulted in litigation or prosecutions, a trial involving a former youth minister is taking place in Nassau County, with jury selection giving a hint of what could come.  B1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-10</p>
        <p>More Middle-Class Audits  Since 2000, authorities at the Internal Revenue Service have nearly tripled audits of tax returns filed by people making $25,000 to $100,000 as part of a broad change in audit strategy.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Deal for Sallie Mae  Sallie Mae, the nation's largest provider of student loans, agreed to be sold to JP Morgan Chase and Bank of America and two private equity firms for $25 billion, people involved in the negotiations said. The deal would move the lender, which is facing increasing turmoil, into private control.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Google Makes Radio Deal  Google has a deal to begin selling advertisements across all of the stations of Clear Channel Communications, the No. 1 radio station owner in the United States.  C4</p>
        <p>New Health Web Site  Stephen M. Case, the America Online founder who oversaw an ill-fated merger with Time Warner before he left, has invested heavily in a new Web site on health issues, RevolutionHealth.com.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY D1-8</p>
        <p>The Rain and the Marathon  More rain is expected for the Boston Marathon today, and winds could be 15 to 20 miles per hour. About 23,000 runners are expected to compete in the 111th edition of the sport's most historic race, which has never been postponed or canceled because of weather.  D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES B6</p>
        <p>Pat Buckley  A leading player in Manhattan's social circuit for decades and the wife of William F. Buckley Jr., the author, columnist and editor, she was 80. B6</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Cleaning up the alternative tax; China's signals on warming; time for Mr. Wolfowitz to go; Adam Cohen on a U.S. attorney who kept his job.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  Crossword E6  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E9  Weather A17</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-10</p>
        <p>Iraqi Town Becomes Haven For Seasoned Insurgents  The Sunni guerrillas and extremists who now dominate Baquba, Iraq, demonstrate a sophistication and lethality born of years of confronting American military tactics. While the increase of American troops plays out in Baghdad, Baquba has emerged as a magnet for insurgents from around the country.  A1</p>
        <p>At least 34 people were killed in Baghdad in another day punctuated by car bombings and suicide vest attacks on civilian targets of the kind that the two-month-old American security crackdown has so far been unable to restrain.  A8</p>
        <p>Russia Lifts Bear Hunting Ban  For the first time in more than five decades, the Russian government is preparing to allow hunters to kill polar bears, which are descending with greater regularity on coastal villages in parts of the far north as a result of shrinking sea ice generally attributed to a warming planet. A1</p>
        <p>Wolfowitz Says He Won't Quit  Senior policy makers at the World Bank delivered a public rebuke in a communiqué to the bank's president, Paul D. Wolfowitz, making it clear they expected him to resign. After learning of the rebuke, Mr. Wolfowitz adamantly made it known at a news conference that he intended to stay on the job. A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Closes Morocco Consulate  The United States Consulate in Morocco said it would close until further notice, a day after two brothers carried out puzzling suicide attacks near the consulate amid a spate of bombings in Morocco and Algeria. A10</p>
        <p>Iran Seeks Bids on Atom Plants  The deputy head of the nation's Atomic Energy Organization was quoted by the ISNA news agency as saying the country was seeking international bids for building two more nuclear power plants despite international pressure over its nuclear program. A3</p>
        <p>Protests on Nigerian Elections  Violent protests broke out in several of Nigeria's 36 states as partial results from contested state elections seemed to hand most of the victories to the governing People's Democratic Party.  A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-15</p>
        <p>Donors Linked to Clintons Shift Support to Obama  Aides to Senator Barack Obama released a list of top fund-raisers that showed how deep his presidential primary campaign has cut into the Democratic party establishment once presumed to back his rival, Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Gonzales Has 'Nothing to Hide'  Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales offered a measured apology for his mistakes in the dismissal of eight United States attorneys, but said in testimony prepared for a Senate hearing tomorrow that he had ''nothing to hide'' and insisted that none of the prosecutors were removed to influence the outcome of a case.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Georgia Prosecutor Unyielding  When North Carolina's attorney general said an overreaching prosecutor lacked evidence to support charges of rape against three Duke University lacrosse players, some in Georgia hoped his pronouncement would help free a former star high school football player serving 10 years without parole for having consensual oral sex with a 15-year-old girl, even though he was 17 at the time.  A12</p>
        <p>Lobster Season in Distress  Although spring is traditionally when lobster prices are highest, lobsters have rarely been as scarce or expensive as they have been in the last few weeks, thanks to a confluence of bad weather, extremely cold water and a lack of reserve supply.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Festival Honors Rural Legacy  The celebration of Mule Day in Columbus, Tenn., marks the arrival of spring, but the event also acts as a window into the area's rural heritage and an homage to the humble beasts that turned the soil, gave a leg up to farmers, and cemented the county's reputation in the South for well-bred mules.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Student Loan Company Settles  Education Finance Partners, a student loan company that investigators found had paid more than 60 colleges and universities across the country for steering students to its loans, has agreed to pay $2.5 million to resolve an investigation of its practices by the New York attorney general.  A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-5</p>
        <p>Increase in Tax Returns From Illegal Immigrants  With the tax deadline approaching, illegal immigrants are sending in federal returns in what appear to be record numbers in hopes that filing a return will create a paper trail that could one day lead to citizenship.  A1</p>
        <p>Storm Sets Rainfall Records  A rare spring northeaster roared up the coast and across the New York region and the Northeast, dumping record-setting rainfall that flooded coasts and rivers, disrupted airline travel at the three major airports, and cut power lines for thousands in New York and Connecticut.  B1</p>
        <p>Church Abuse Case to Trial  While only a small fraction of sexual abuse complaints involving the Catholic Church have resulted in litigation or prosecutions, a trial involving a former youth minister is taking place in Nassau County, with jury selection giving a hint of what could come.  B1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-10</p>
        <p>More Middle-Class Audits  Since 2000, authorities at the Internal Revenue Service have nearly tripled audits of tax returns filed by people making $25,000 to $100,000 as part of a broad change in audit strategy.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Deal for Sallie Mae  Sallie Mae, the nation's largest provider of student loans, agreed to be sold to JP Morgan Chase and Bank of America and two private equity firms for $25 billion, people involved in the negotiations said. The deal would move the lender, which is facing increasing turmoil, into private control.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Google Makes Radio Deal  Google has a deal to begin selling advertisements across all of the stations of Clear Channel Communications, the No. 1 radio station owner in the United States.  C4</p>
        <p>New Health Web Site  Stephen M. Case, the America Online founder who oversaw an ill-fated merger with Time Warner before he left, has invested heavily in a new Web site on health issues, RevolutionHealth.com.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY D1-8</p>
        <p>The Rain and the Marathon  More rain is expected for the Boston Marathon today, and winds could be 15 to 20 miles per hour. About 23,000 runners are expected to compete in the 111th edition of the sport's most historic race, which has never been postponed or canceled because of weather.  D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES B6</p>
        <p>Pat Buckley  A leading player in Manhattan's social circuit for decades and the wife of William F. Buckley Jr., the author, columnist and editor, she was 80. B6</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Cleaning up the alternative tax; China's signals on warming; time for Mr. Wolfowitz to go; Adam Cohen on a U.S. attorney who kept his job.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  Crossword E6  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E9  Weather A17</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
