<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Parable Cuts Across Cultures</title>
    <meta content="16curl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/arts/music/16curl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Japan Society</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Britten, Benjamin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Parable Cuts Across Cultures</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Parable Cuts Across Cultures</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Candle flames flicker. Water sloshes. Monks chant. An organ keens. A madwoman mourns her dead child. Benjamin Britten's ''Curlew River,'' a not-quite-opera labeled a ''church parable'' by its composer, cuts across cultures, from Japanese to Western Christianity, to channel a sense of dark ritual borne on music.</p>
        <p>In 1998 the actor and director Yoshi Oida created a production for young artists at the Aix-en-Provence Festival that touched on the piece's Japanese roots -- it was based on the noh drama ''Sumidagawa'' -- and respected its monastic spareness. This production has since traveled to Europe, conducted by David Stern. On Thursday it arrived at the Japan Society, which is marking its 100th anniversary with, among other events, a festival called ''Noh-Now'' that examines the ways noh drama has been reflected and refracted in contemporary work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Benjamin Britten’s not-quite-opera cuts across cultures, from Japanese to Western Christianity, to channel a sense of dark ritual borne on music.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Candle flames flicker. Water sloshes. Monks chant. An organ keens. A madwoman mourns her dead child. Benjamin Britten's ''Curlew River,'' a not-quite-opera labeled a ''church parable'' by its composer, cuts across cultures, from Japanese to Western Christianity, to channel a sense of dark ritual borne on music.</p>
        <p>In 1998 the actor and director Yoshi Oida created a production for young artists at the Aix-en-Provence Festival that touched on the piece's Japanese roots -- it was based on the noh drama ''Sumidagawa'' -- and respected its monastic spareness. This production has since traveled to Europe, conducted by David Stern. On Thursday it arrived at the Japan Society, which is marking its 100th anniversary with, among other events, a festival called ''Noh-Now'' that examines the ways noh drama has been reflected and refracted in contemporary work.</p>
        <p>Britten is a composer of restrictions. It's fashionable today to see a reflection of his homosexuality in the buttoned-down presentation of his characters. In ''Curlew River'' formal stylization reigns, and the instruments of the unusual seven-piece ensemble -- double bass and harp, viola and horn, odd combinations intended to capture some of the flavor of a gagaku orchestra -- are more individualized than the figures onstage.</p>
        <p>Some of Britten's favorite themes surface in this spare piece, with its shifting, watery score: the individual against the crowd (the story tells of a madwoman who is traveling in search of her son and mocked in the attempt), the love of a man for a boy. But in this ritualistic presentation, emotions are slightly blunted or generalized: the madwoman is a symbol as well as a character.</p>
        <p>Britten set the action in an early monastery, where monks (hence an all-male ensemble) enact the story, starting with plainchant emerging full-formed out of silence, like a small miracle of creation. A drum then starts the play within a play, ushering in the new colors of a dark-hued crowd of instruments.</p>
        <p>The flute has a starring role, accompanying the madwoman's wanderings. The ensemble, which came from the production's last incarnation at the Rouen opera, sounded a little shaky at the start but settled in under Mr. Stern's vigorous conducting. (Britten intended the piece to be performed without a conductor.)</p>
        <p>What is nice about the intimacy of the work's scale is that it puts the leading role within the reach of a smaller-voiced tenor who would normally take secondary ''character'' parts. Michael Bennett, who has been with this production since its original Aix version, inhabits the part: pale skin, bald head, staring eyes, projecting a vulnerable lightness that also contains an element of radiance. An English tenor, he projected, consciously or not, the influence of Peter Pears, Britten's partner and the originator of the role: the slightly otherworldly, sexless voice; the clipped diction and tidily rolled R's.</p>
        <p>Strong singing is not the point of the exercise. The more the figures appear to be Everymen, the better. Reuben Willcox was strong and rough as the ferryman; Jonathan May, a sympathetic traveler. The ensemble of pilgrims-monks was outstanding in the framing plainchant that opened and closed the piece. And the boy was played by a girl: Lauren Libaw, bright-toned, gave his offstage voice.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
