<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DiPietro Is Reason for Optimism, and Yashin for Concern</title>
    <meta content="16isles" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/sports/hockey/16isles.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dipietro, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3DE113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DiPietro Is Reason for Optimism, and Yashin for Concern</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">DiPietro’s Return Has Islanders Optimistic About Playoffs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>SYOSSET, N.Y., April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Islanders held an optional practice Sunday, and goaltender Rick DiPietro was the first player on the ice. Soon, he was firing pucks, either into a net or at the glass, just to arouse a few quiet spectators.</p>
        <p>DiPietro has certainly awakened the Islanders. Twenty days after he was sidelined with a concussion, he returned to the lineup Saturday night to help the Islanders beat the heavily favored Buffalo Sabres, 3-2. Their best-of-seven Eastern Conference first-round playoff series is tied at 1-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty days after he was sidelined with a concussion, goaltender Rick DiPietro has awakened the New York Islanders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Islanders held an optional practice Sunday, and goaltender Rick DiPietro was the first player on the ice. Soon, he was firing pucks, either into a net or at the glass, just to arouse a few quiet spectators.</p>
        <p>DiPietro has certainly awakened the Islanders. Twenty days after he was sidelined with a concussion, he returned to the lineup Saturday night to help the Islanders beat the heavily favored Buffalo Sabres, 3-2. Their best-of-seven Eastern Conference first-round playoff series is tied at 1-1.</p>
        <p>''Things worked out better than I expected,'' he said.</p>
        <p>DiPietro made 32 saves, some of them spectacular. More important, he said he did not have any symptoms of a concussion, during the game or afterward. The Sabres bumped into him a few times, he said, but other than being sore and tight, he felt fine.</p>
        <p>''All positive stuff,'' he said Sunday as he took off his pads.</p>
        <p>A feel-good vibe surged through the Islanders' dressing room at their practice facility as they prepared for Game 3, which will be Monday night at Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>Although they have made sure to note that the third-stringer Wade Dubielewicz played well in DiPietro's absence, the Islanders say they believe DiPietro gives them a better chance to beat the powerful and talented Sabres.</p>
        <p>''When he's in the lineup, I think the guys are a little more confident, a little more at ease,'' Islanders forward Jason Blake said of DiPietro. ''He's so active out there, it's like having another defenseman.''</p>
        <p>DiPietro's return Saturday was so encouraging that it seemed to overshadow an interesting decision by Ted Nolan, the Islanders' first-year coach. Alexei Yashin, the captain, played only 7 minutes 7 seconds and 10 shifts, the least of any Islanders player.</p>
        <p>''Whatever I get, I will give my best,'' Yashin said Sunday.</p>
        <p>He has not produced much in this series, with only one shot in two games. Since arriving on Long Island in 2001, Yashin has insisted that personal statistics mean little to him. The Islanders won Saturday, and that is all that mattered.</p>
        <p>''Ricky played unbelievable,'' Yashin said of DiPietro. ''It's one of the reasons why we won.''</p>
        <p>When Yashin was asked if Nolan had told him why his playing time was reduced, he said, ''It's nothing else I can say, really,'' then ended the interview.</p>
        <p>Yashin later met with Nolan, who tried to play down the matter by saying he met with a lot of players. Nolan relied on forwards like Richard Park and Richard Zednik after the Islanders broke a 2-2 tie in the third period on a power-play goal by Marc-André Bergeron.</p>
        <p>''We need a little bit more from everybody -- from the 20th man to the first man,'' Nolan said.</p>
        <p>That explains the note written in neat capital letters on a dry-erase board in the Islanders' dressing room: play hard, play smart, play together.</p>
        <p>Later, Nolan said, referring to Yashin, ''Just because a guy has a C on his sweater, he gets more attention sometimes.''</p>
        <p>DiPietro said he was anticipating a mighty countercharge in Game 3 by Buffalo, which finished the season with the best record in the N.H.L.</p>
        <p>The Islanders have been in this situation twice before. In 2003 and 2004, they returned to Nassau Coliseum with their first-round series tied entering Game 3. Each time, they lost the next three games, to Ottawa in 2003, and to Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>''I know that everybody is coming to realize that it's going to be a tough series, a long series,'' DiPietro said. ''I'm confident in the leadership in this room.''</p>
        <p>The other people in the room are confident in DiPietro. Even though he was playing his first game since March 25, DiPietro was strong. The announcement that he was returning to the lineup gave the team a jolt. DiPietro, an adroit stick handler, helps the team's attack.</p>
        <p>''When you got the No. 1 goaltender and a franchise player back, it sends a little buzz through the locker room in a good way,'' Blake said.</p>
        <p>Nolan said he hoped that big crowds for the next two games would also supply a little buzz. And he is looking for a lift from some of his other players. It would appear to be Yashin's turn to flip a switch.</p>
        <p>''If we get our game going,'' Nolan said, ''you never know what's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
