<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kastor Will Be in Her Elements in Boston</title>
    <meta content="16marathon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/sports/othersports/16marathon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARATHON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kastor, Deena</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kastor Will Be in Her Elements in Boston</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kastor Says She Will Be in Her Elements in Boston Marathon Debut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sunday afternoon and night brought two to four inches of rain here, driven by winds of 25 to 40 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Boston Marathon day, more rain is expected, although not as heavy, and winds could be 15 to 20 m.p.h. Still, about 21,000 runners are expected to compete in the 111th edition of the sport's most historic race, which has never been postponed or canceled because of weather.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A cold and rainy forecast does not discourage Deena Kastor, holder of the American marathon record, who will make her Boston Marathon debut on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sunday afternoon and night brought two to four inches of rain here, driven by winds of 25 to 40 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Boston Marathon day, more rain is expected, although not as heavy, and winds could be 15 to 20 m.p.h. Still, about 21,000 runners are expected to compete in the 111th edition of the sport's most historic race, which has never been postponed or canceled because of weather.</p>
        <p>Race officials have sent e-mail messages to runners warning them to dress in layers -- temperatures are expected to be in the 30s and 40s. Sara Mae Berman, who won the women's race three times from 1969 to 1971, had three words of advice: ''Hats and gloves.''</p>
        <p>To Deena Kastor, making her Boston debut, the bad weather was not even an inconvenience. She and her husband, Andrew, a massage therapist, live in Mammoth Lakes, Calif. She trains there at an altitude of 8,000 feet, where a winter may bring 50 feet of snow. Besides, she said in an interview here, ''I love running in adverse cold; I can run through puddles.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''It looks like a big cross-country race, and I love cross-country. I'm going out there and push the pace.''</p>
        <p>But in a strong headwind, rivals could race single file behind her and let her block the wind. That would be good for them, not for her. She shrugged.</p>
        <p>''They can do anything they want,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Kastor has earned a right to be confident. A year ago in London, she set an American record of 2 hours 19 minutes 36 seconds, making her the fourth-fastest female marathoner. At 34, she has won 20 United States road, track and cross-country titles, and a bronze medal in the 2004 Olympics.</p>
        <p>She, Rita Jeptoo of Kenya and Jelena Prokopcuka of Latvia are the women's favorites. Last year, Jeptoo beat Prokopcuka by 10 seconds, the closest women's finish in Boston. The last American woman to win this race was Lisa Larsen-Weidenbach in 1985.</p>
        <p>There are high expectations for Kastor, but she insisted: ''I don't feel pressure. I don't feel a burden. I'm not carrying any weight of my country on my back.''</p>
        <p>Much of that has to do with her preparation.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I could have done anything different,'' Kastor said. ''The last four months have been so flawless, so consistent.''</p>
        <p>Part of her confidence came from a 26-mile training run three weeks ago, in effect a marathon three weeks before this marathon.</p>
        <p>''I was focused on the distance and wasn't worried about speed,'' she said. ''I started with seven-minute miles and at the end was down to six minutes or a little under. It seemed like a play day out there.''</p>
        <p>It was hardly a play day in last November's marathon in New York, where she finished sixth in 2:27:54.</p>
        <p>''My training was not going well then,'' she said, ''but you don't say that the day before the race when your competitors are sitting by your side. It was a bad year. I canceled my track season because I couldn't get my legs under me. I had back problems. I could not complete some workouts.''</p>
        <p>Kastor has been completing them lately as part of a tight program. She recently described a typical day: ''It's very boring. I get up at 6 and immediately have breakfast, whether it's a bowl of oatmeal or a bagel, and tea or coffee. I go out and walk the dog. I get on the massage table in Andrew's office and he gives me a light massage and stretch. I meet my teammates wherever the practice site is. We do either a 12-mile workout on pavement or intervals.</p>
        <p>''I get home, get a quick post-workout massage and take a nap for an hour or two. Then I get ready for the second run of the day, four to six miles. Then I lift weights, go home, make dinner and go to bed soon after that. I'm in bed by 8:30.''</p>
        <p>The early-to-bed routine continued here, but she was up early Saturday for perhaps the greatest honor Boston can bestow. She threw out the first pitch at a Red Sox game.</p>
        <p>''Make sure and say it was a strike,'' she said.</p>
        <p>NOTES</p>
        <p>Robert Cheruiyot of Kenya will seek his third consecutive men's title.  For the first time, the United States women's championship will be run simultaneously with the marathon.  The starting times have been moved up two hours, to 9:35 a.m. for the elite women and 10 a.m. for the elite men. Officials wanted runners to have cooler temperatures and to enable communities along the route to reopen roads to traffic earlier in the day. Cheruiyot and Jelena Prokopcuka lead the World Marathon Majors standings, which incorporates the Boston, New York City, Chicago, London and Berlin races.</p>
        <p>MARATHON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
