<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Those Who Visit, a Glimpse of Corzine's Private Life</title>
    <meta content="16corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/nyregion/16corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Those Who Visit, a Glimpse of Corzine's Private Life</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Visitors, a Glimpse of Corzine’s Private Life</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN; Kareem Fahim and David Kocieniewski contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His three adult children are spending much of their time in a small conference room at Cooper University Hospital here, talking on their cellphones or reading get-well notes from all over the country. His companion of about two years has tried to maintain some sense of normalcy, she said Sunday afternoon, by reading ''every single paper in America.''</p>
        <p>Two of his closest aides, meanwhile, shuttle regularly between the public maw of a hospital lobby overflowing with out-of-town reporters and the private confines of a makeshift office on the second floor, not far from the family and the employee cafeteria.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey is still sedated, but his loved ones say they are encouraged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His three adult children are spending much of their time in a small conference room at Cooper University Hospital here, talking on their cellphones or reading get-well notes from all over the country. His companion of about two years has tried to maintain some sense of normalcy, she said Sunday afternoon, by reading ''every single paper in America.''</p>
        <p>Two of his closest aides, meanwhile, shuttle regularly between the public maw of a hospital lobby overflowing with out-of-town reporters and the private confines of a makeshift office on the second floor, not far from the family and the employee cafeteria.</p>
        <p>For most of his life in the public spotlight, Jon S. Corzine has been defined largely by his résumé: as co-chairman of the investment bank Goldman Sachs, as a Democratic United States senator and, since January 2006, as governor of New Jersey. But since a car crash Thursday evening in which he was critically injured, another dimension of Mr. Corzine has emerged that has little to do with wealth or power, but with who is closest to him in the most trying of circumstances.</p>
        <p>Those relatives and close friends, none of whom are well known to voters, have now come out of the shadows as a proxy first family of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''We get to see our dad all the time, and we're really encouraged by what's been going on,'' said Mr. Corzine's son Joshua Corzine, 30, who works in commercial real estate in San Francisco. He appeared at a three-minute news conference here Sunday with his sister, Jennifer Corzine-Pisani, 36, and brother, Jeffrey Corzine, 24. ''Everyone's in good spirits, just trying to get through this tough time.''</p>
        <p>The governor is still heavily sedated and had a 15-minute procedure Sunday morning to remove fluid outside his left lung, which doctors described as successful.</p>
        <p>By afternoon, Mr. Corzine's companion, Sharon Elghanayan, a psychotherapist who lives on the Upper East Side of Manhattan, seemed to be in good spirits as she left the hospital with a friend through the front door, not the emergency-door exit she has been sneaking in and out of.</p>
        <p>''He's doing really great,'' she said before slipping away, adding that she would return later in the evening.</p>
        <p>Many questions remain about the crash on Thursday in which Governor Corzine, riding in the front passenger seat without a seat belt, broke his left femur, a dozen ribs, his collarbone, his sternum and a lower vertebra.</p>
        <p>Running late from a speech in Atlantic City, Mr. Corzine was in a state police vehicle, emergency lights flashing, that swerved to avoid another car and slammed into a guardrail. He had been heading to Drumthwacket, the governor's mansion in Princeton, for a meeting with the Rutgers women's basketball team and Don Imus, the fired talk show host.</p>
        <p>The state trooper who was driving and an assistant who was talking on a cellphone in the back seat apparently were wearing seat belts, as is required by law in New Jersey, and suffered minor injuries.</p>
        <p>Richard J. Codey, the State Senate president, is serving as acting governor until Mr. Corzine recovers, and on Sunday afternoon he deferred most questions about the crash until the completion of the state police investigation. He added at a news conference that he did not expect the inquiry to take ''an extremely long period of time.''</p>
        <p>When asked under what circumstances Mr. Corzine's driver would have activated the car's emergency lights and whether it might have been related to the speed of the car, Mr. Codey said, ''There is no set protocol on that at all.''</p>
        <p>He added that he had heard rumors that the two-car caravan might have been speeding, perhaps up to 90 miles per hour, but he added: ''I was never in one that went 90. Nor would I want to be.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Codey said that he and his wife hoped to visit Mr. Corzine by Thursday, depending on his progress.</p>
        <p>The governor spent his third full day in critical but stable condition, breathing with a ventilator. The procedure he underwent Sunday morning, called thoracentisis, is considered minor and usually done with a needle to help a patient breathe more easily.</p>
        <p>Another operation is scheduled for Monday. But his family said Sunday that they were encouraged that he was communicating a bit more by moving his hands.</p>
        <p>''When you talk to him, he can recognize your voice,'' Joshua Corzine said. ''He definitely responds when you let him know who you are.''</p>
        <p>A poised family spokesman, Joshua Corzine is married and the father of a baby girl, Emma Rachel, born in September. His sister, Jennifer Corzine-Pisani, lives in Manhattan with her husband and runs a tea shop with a childhood friend called Pen and Jen's. Jeffrey Corzine, the youngest, is a student at New York University.</p>
        <p>The three siblings have been staying at a nearby hotel and have been spotted searching for coffee several times in the hospital's crowded lobby. On Sunday, the trio arrived at the hospital a little before 9 a.m. and, escorted by a state trooper, were overheard asking, ''Is Sharon here?''</p>
        <p>The question referred to Ms. Elghanayan, the ex-wife of Thomas Elghanayan, president of the Rockrose real estate development company. She was in Paris when the crash occurred but returned over the weekend and, accompanied by a friend, has spent most of her time since at the hospital.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's older brother Allen was also here. He came from suburban Chicago, where he owns a bicycle shop, friends of the governor said.</p>
        <p>Together, the family and close friends have been huddled in a second-floor conference room, one floor below the intensive care unit where Mr. Corzine is recuperating. Not far away is another room in which Mr. Corzine's spokesman, Anthony Coley, and Tom Shea, Mr. Corzine's chief of staff, process information related to Mr. Corzine's medical condition, state business and politics.</p>
        <p>One task is simply collecting get-well messages. President Bush sent wishes through his chief of staff, Joshua Bolton, who used to work for Mr. Corzine at Goldman. Former President Bill Clinton and Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton -- whose presidential bid Mr. Corzine recently endorsed -- have called, as have Senator Barack Obama, another Democratic hopeful, and former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who is seeking the Republican presidential nomination.</p>
        <p>The government of Israel, where Mr. Corzine had been scheduled to visit this week, and the trade ministry of China also offered well wishes, along with numerous governors and even kindergartners.Mr. Coley, the spokesman, said top aides had discouraged other administration members, friends and political supporters from visiting the hospital.</p>
        <p>In a sense, Mr. Corzine's accident has brought his family together in a way that was often difficult previously, given his hectic schedule as an executive and as a politician.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine has talked at times about that compromise. In a debate in 2005 during the campaign for governor, he mentioned that his greatest regret was not spending as much time with his children as he would have liked, saying his life reminded him of the Harry Chapin song ''Cat's in the Cradle.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
