<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of Playoffs, Knicks Run Out of Gas, Too</title>
    <meta content="16knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/sports/basketball/16knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of Playoffs, Knicks Run Out of Gas, Too</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Out of Playoffs, Knicks Run Out of Gas, Too</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With their playoff hopes ended, the Knicks reverted to a familiar script Sunday night. They were in the game throughout but could not come up with plays at critical times in a 107-105 loss to the Toronto Raptors.</p>
        <p>The Raptors won their sixth straight game and gained the No. 3 seed in the Eastern Conference playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Knicks were in the game throughout but could not come up with critical plays in a loss to the Raptors Sunday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With their playoff hopes ended, the Knicks reverted to a familiar script Sunday night. They were in the game throughout but could not come up with plays at critical times in a 107-105 loss to the Toronto Raptors.</p>
        <p>The Raptors won their sixth straight game and gained the No. 3 seed in the Eastern Conference playoffs.</p>
        <p>''It was definitely tough,'' said the Knicks' Steve Francis, who scored 28 points. ''We had control of the game for most of it. Turnovers hurt us late in the game. We came up empty on our possessions.''</p>
        <p>Chris Bosh, the young star forward, led the Raptors with 23 points, including two free throws with 8.6 seconds remaining to give Toronto a 104-101 lead.</p>
        <p>The Knicks had cut their deficit to a point, at 100-99, with just more than a minute remaining when Malik Rose sank two foul shots. But Bosh hit a basket to give the Raptors a 3-point lead, and Knicks Coach Isiah Thomas called a timeout with 45.8 seconds remaining.</p>
        <p>The Knicks set up a play for Francis, but his shot from the left side hit the side of the backboard. It had been that kind of game and season for the Knicks, who have lost four in a row.</p>
        <p>''We had an opportunity to win the basketball game,'' Thomas said. ''Guys are still giving the same effort, and right now we just don't have the weapons, but the effort was there.''</p>
        <p>Eddy Curry led the Knicks with 30 points.</p>
        <p>Francis began the game animated, shouting instructions to his teammates on defense. He scored 8 of the Knicks' first 12 points and finished with 13 in the first quarter as the Knicks trailed, 30-27.</p>
        <p>Anthony Parker scored 19 points for the Raptors, including 10 during the first quarter. But when he came out of the game, the Knicks went on a 16-0 run in the second quarter to take a 41-31 lead. By halftime, they led by 59-50.</p>
        <p>In the second half, however, the teams went in opposite directions, perhaps fitting given their seasons. Toronto (47-33), which opened the third quarter with a 9-5 run to get back into the game, played in front of a raucous capacity crowd at Air Canada Center.</p>
        <p>The Raptors will open the playoffs at home next week.</p>
        <p>Toronto and the Knicks (32-48) are a study in contrasts. The Raptors are the most improved team in the N.B.A., winning 20 more games than they did in 2005-6. They have clinched their first Atlantic Division title.</p>
        <p>The Knicks played a role in Toronto's turnaround by trading Antonio Davis to the Raptors for Jalen Rose last February. The swap saved Toronto $17 million in salary-cap space, allowing General Manager Bryan Colangelo to sign Bosh to a long-term contract.</p>
        <p>The Knicks, plagued by injuries, are finishing out their third straight season without qualifying for the playoffs and their sixth straight with a losing record. The Knicks were eliminated from playoff contention Friday in a 100-86 loss to the Nets.</p>
        <p>After hanging around in playoff contention in March, the Knicks went into a 3-14 free fall. The slide coincided with injuries to Jamal Crawford, Quentin Richardson, David Lee and Stephon Marbury.</p>
        <p>''We know we're a good team,'' Curry said. ''We've just been hampered by injuries. You've got to play almost perfect basketball to win with the lineups that we've had.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
