<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burton Passes Kenseth for Second Win at Texas Track</title>
    <meta content="16nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/sports/othersports/16nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840820"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Fort Worth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Fort Worth (Tex)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Burton, Jeff</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kenseth, Matt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burton Passes Kenseth for Second Win at Texas Track</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Burton Passes Kenseth for Second Win at Texas Track</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN DALEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Daley, Ken</byline>
      <dateline>FORT WORTH, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To say the Texas Motor Speedway has been fickle understates its capriciousness. No track on the Nascar circuit could match the speedway's record of a different winner for each of its first 12 Nextel Cup series races.</p>
        <p>But this year's running of the Samsung 500 brought its first repeat winner when Jeff Burton, who won the speedway's inaugural Cup race in 1997, passed Matt Kenseth in the final lap Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Texas Motor Speedway saw its first repeat winner when Jeff Burton, who won the inaugural Nextel Cup race there, passed Matt Kenseth in the final lap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To say the Texas Motor Speedway has been fickle understates its capriciousness. No track on the Nascar circuit could match the speedway's record of a different winner for each of its first 12 Nextel Cup series races.</p>
        <p>But this year's running of the Samsung 500 brought its first repeat winner when Jeff Burton, who won the speedway's inaugural Cup race in 1997, passed Matt Kenseth in the final lap Sunday.</p>
        <p>''I love being part of close finishes,'' said Burton, who beat Kenseth to the finish line by 0.41 seconds. ''They haven't always gone my way, but I love them.''</p>
        <p>So did the estimated crowd of 191,000, which got over its collective disappointment of Dale Earnhardt Jr.'s early exit by seeing a finish as notable for its sportsmanship as its excitement.</p>
        <p>Burton had stalked Kenseth for more than 15 laps in his No. 31 Chevrolet, which looked demonstrably stronger than Kenseth's fading No. 17 Ford. But Kenseth was masterly at holding off Burton, his former Roush Racing teammate, until the final lap.</p>
        <p>''We were quite a bit faster than he was and he held us off for 15 laps; that's how good he is,'' Burton said. ''For me, it was a matter of patience.''</p>
        <p>It was not until the final lap that Burton nosed his machine under Kenseth's and surged ahead coming out of Turn 2.</p>
        <p>Kenseth's car had drifted about three feet higher midway through that turn, and he could only watch helplessly as Burton outran him down the remainder of the mile-and-a-half quadoval.</p>
        <p>''It stunk from my vantage point,'' said Kenseth, who won Saturday's Busch Series race here. ''Jeff is a great friend of mine and nobody is more deserving than him, but I like racing against him better when I beat him.''</p>
        <p>That the cars never touched during their final duel spoke volumes about the drivers' respect for each other and the sport.</p>
        <p>''It's disheartening to get passed on the last lap for the win, but there was nothing else I could do except wreck,'' Kenseth said. ''He figured out how to get around me when I was doing the best I could. It's painful not to win on the last lap, but if I had a chance to do it again, I'll be beat the same way.''</p>
        <p>Burton, whose second victory in six years was the 19th of his career, said he went as far as he was willing to go to beat Kenseth.</p>
        <p>''Winning a race because you knocked somebody out of the way doesn't mean that you were better,'' Burton said. ''It just means you were willing to give something away. You were willing to give away some integrity to win a trophy.''</p>
        <p>Burton, 39, finished seventh in last season's points standings. He has been revitalized since joining Richard Childress Racing midway through the 2004 season, and is mounting a strong championship challenge early this season.</p>
        <p>In seven races, Burton has finished lower than sixth only once, a 15th-place showing at Las Vegas. His victory Sunday kept him second in the points standings, closing the gap behind Jeff Gordon to 8 points.</p>
        <p>''What Richard has given me an opportunity to do here, I feel like I'm new again,'' Burton said. ''My enthusiasm and my excitement is as high as it's ever been. I never forgot I could drive. Some other people forgot I could drive.''</p>
        <p>Hendrick Motorsports was seeking its fifth consecutive victory, an achievement not seen in Cup racing for 36 years. For much of Sunday, it appeared that its flagship driver, Gordon, might pull it off.</p>
        <p>Gordon led the most laps (173 of 334), but damaged the right side of his car when he skidded untouched into the wall coming out of Turn 4 with 23 laps to go. Gordon was leading at the time, but the collision damaged his car's handling and he was overtaken by Kenseth seven laps later. Gordon was later passed by Mark Martin and faded to a fourth-place finish.</p>
        <p>Martin took third, and remained 11th in the season standings despite running only a partial schedule.</p>
        <p>Kenseth improved one spot to third in the standings, 125 points behind Gordon. Jimmie Johnson dropped a spot to fourth, 181 points out, after a wreck sent him to a 38th-place finish.</p>
        <p>The other Hendrick drivers, Kyle Busch and Casey Mears, were involved in accidents and finished 7th and 32nd. Earnhardt, whose No. 8 Chevrolet led 96 laps before crashing with Kyle Busch, wound up finishing the race by running nine laps in Busch's car after the No. 5 team's driver left the track assuming his vehicle could not be repaired.</p>
        <p>''I appreciate them asking me,'' Earnhardt said. ''I was honored; it means a lot to me.''</p>
        <p>The curious decision wound up giving Earnhardt's teammate an extra 3 points in the standings.</p>
        <p>''It don't matter,'' Earnhardt said. ''I was glad to do it.''</p>
        <p>Twenty of the 43 drivers starting the race were behind the wheels of Chevrolet Monte Carlos, and five of those cars were equipped for the first time with Chevy's new R07 engine. Of those with the new engine, Denny Hamlin was the highest finisher in ninth place, but Tony Stewart, J. J. Yeley and Mears were taken out by accidents.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
