<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lobster Elusive, and Price Exclusive, as Harvest Suffers</title>
    <meta content="16lobster" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/us/16lobster.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lobsters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobsters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4DE113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lobster Elusive, and Price Exclusive, as Harvest Suffers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lobster Elusive, and Price Exclusive, as Harvest Suffers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATIE ZEZIMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zezima, Katie</byline>
      <dateline>NORTH PROVIDENCE, R.I., April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark Castelli has plenty of king crab, shrimp and tilapia for sale at his seafood store here, Captain's Catch, but lobster is nowhere to be found.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time in 25 years my tanks are empty,'' Mr. Castelli said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The retail price for a one-pound lobster is nearly double what it was last spring, thanks to bad weather, extremely cold water and a lack of reserve supply.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mark Castelli has plenty of king crab, shrimp and tilapia for sale at his seafood store here, Captain's Catch, but lobster is nowhere to be found.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time in 25 years my tanks are empty,'' Mr. Castelli said.</p>
        <p>Lobsters have rarely been as scarce or expensive as they have been in the last few weeks, thanks to a confluence of bad weather, extremely cold water and a lack of reserve supply.</p>
        <p>The retail price is about $15 a pound for a one-pound lobster, nearly double what it was last spring, and restaurateurs are having difficulty obtaining lobsters, particularly large ones.</p>
        <p>Where they can be found, large lobsters come with big price tags. Anthony's Pier 4 in Boston is selling three-and-a-half-pound lobsters for $112. A scarce two-pound lobster at the Union Oyster House in Boston is $47.95, the manager, Troy C. Thissell, said, and a one-pounder at Warren's Lobster House in Kittery, Me., is $29.99, said the owner, Scott Cunningham.</p>
        <p>''Basically, all we're selling is one- or one-and-a-half-pounders,'' Mr. Cunningham said. ''The big ones are scarce, and the price is outrageous. We thought we might have to change our name to Warren's Chicken House or something.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cunningham, who has owned the restaurant since the mid-'80s, said he had never seen prices so high and lobsters so scarce.</p>
        <p>Although spring is traditionally a slow season for lobstermen and the time when prices are the highest, this season is shaping up to be one of the worst in a generation.</p>
        <p>''What we have now is it's windy, snowing sideways, record-high prices, and there's no lobster to speak of in the inventory,'' said Pete McAleney, owner of New Meadows Lobster, a dealer in Portland, Me. ''Everything that can go wrong is going wrong.''</p>
        <p>A pattern of strong northwest winds has made it difficult for lobstermen to head out to sea for the last two months or so, said Robert C. Bayer, executive director of the University of Maine Lobster Institute.</p>
        <p>When lobstermen do head out, they find their traps filled with more bait than lobsters. Unseasonably cold spring weather has lowered water temperatures about six degrees, too cold for lobsters to want to feed, Dr. Bayer said.</p>
        <p>Dealers, many of whom are in Canada, keep thousands of pounds of reserve lobsters in tidal pounds or protected coves each fall, when the price is low. The lobsters are sold starting in late December, as cold sets in and prices increase.</p>
        <p>Because of surpluses in recent years, fewer lobsters were put in tidal pounds, Dr. Bayer said, and the reserves have all but run out. Some fishermen say they believe that the Canadian companies are selling lobsters to Europe and Asia, where prices are even higher.</p>
        <p>''This year, we didn't put as much away as we thought we should,'' Mr. McAleney said. His company has 1,000 pounds of lobster in stock, compared with 35,000 pounds or so in the summer.</p>
        <p>Lobstermen say they are barely making money, despite the high prices.</p>
        <p>''I'm not catching nothing, but it's pretty close,'' said Jack Merrill, a lobsterman from Mount Desert, Me. ''This morning when I went out, there was still ice in the harbor. In the middle of April, that's almost unheard of. That's really cold, and it's why the lobsters aren't moving and the price is so high.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Castelli said his customers here refused to pay top dollar, because they were used to ''going down to the docks and getting them for $5.''</p>
        <p>Despite the price, restaurants say they continue to sell lobster, mostly to tourists intent on having a taste of New England. Mr. Thissell said the Union Oyster House expected to sell what lobster it had this weekend to visitors in town for the Boston Marathon on Monday and hoped that the supply would not run out.</p>
        <p>''People want lobster, and they'll still pay for it,'' Mr. Thissell said. ''People are already spending $1,000 on hotels. They've come to Boston. So they think, 'Why not have the lobster?' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
