<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rest for the Weary, and Wi-Fi Too, All for Less Money</title>
    <meta content="16budget" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business Travel" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16budget.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EUROPE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rest for the Weary, and Wi-Fi Too, All for Less Money</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rest for the Weary, and Wi-Fi Too, All for Less Money</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH WILDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wildman, Sarah</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SADLY for many budget business travelers, low-cost hotels in Europe are often not nearly as cheap as their rooms feel. On a recent Monday night at the Ibis Madrid Centro -- one of the French chain Accor's budget hotels that are pitched to a white-collar crowd -- a clutch of business travelers quickly found that out.</p>
        <p>On the Web, Ibis says it offers wireless connections and a convenient, central location. But inside the feeling is distinctly less business-friendly. The Wi-Fi service costs 12 euros (about $15) for 24 hours, CNN is not available, and outlets do not accommodate the business traveler's trilogy of computer, mobile phone and portable music player. Worse, the décor evokes a decaying highway motel. Even though the Web site promised rates ''starting at'' 59 euros a night, the fee on that recent Monday night was 89 euros; breakfast cost an additional 6 euros, and then there was the Wi-Fi fee. At a total of 107 euros (or $140) for the night, Ibis Madrid Centro was medium cost for low value.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is a trend toward small hotels offering transparency in pricing and a bundle of business-friendly amenities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SADLY for many budget business travelers, low-cost hotels in Europe are often not nearly as cheap as their rooms feel. On a recent Monday night at the Ibis Madrid Centro -- one of the French chain Accor's budget hotels that are pitched to a white-collar crowd -- a clutch of business travelers quickly found that out.</p>
        <p>On the Web, Ibis says it offers wireless connections and a convenient, central location. But inside the feeling is distinctly less business-friendly. The Wi-Fi service costs 12 euros (about $15) for 24 hours, CNN is not available, and outlets do not accommodate the business traveler's trilogy of computer, mobile phone and portable music player. Worse, the décor evokes a decaying highway motel. Even though the Web site promised rates ''starting at'' 59 euros a night, the fee on that recent Monday night was 89 euros; breakfast cost an additional 6 euros, and then there was the Wi-Fi fee. At a total of 107 euros (or $140) for the night, Ibis Madrid Centro was medium cost for low value.</p>
        <p>While Europe is at the forefront of low-cost airline travel, budget business travelers can still feel gouged on accommodations. Yet there are signs that the situation is improving. In 2006, some European hoteliers began using innovative design to rethink what budget business travelers crave: convenience, comfort and, above all, value.</p>
        <p>''Hotels have been underinvesting and overcharging for years, leaving them wide open to someone who is concerned with their customer and wants to provide good value for money,'' said Sinclair Beecham, a founder of the sleek Hoxton Hotel in London (hoxtonhotels.com), which is leading a new wave of lower-cost business hotels.</p>
        <p>The trend is about addition through subtraction. At its most extreme, some of the hotels disregard space considerations -- and even windows -- to give guests ''mod pods'' equipped with Wi-Fi and flat-screen televisions. They borrow low-cost ideas from easyHotel (founded by the budget airline easyJet and priced on the same tiered scale), but go one better: easyHotel charges an additional fee for everything from cleaning to use of a television remote control. These new hotels present transparency in pricing and a bundle of business-friendly amenities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beecham, best known for his successful chain of Pret a Manger London-based takeout shops, gained notoriety last fall when he floated a very low-cost-airline-like offer: £1 per night.</p>
        <p>''We set up a low-cost-airline pricing model,'' he said. ''We thought we'd sell five rooms a night for £1 and five rooms for £29.'' The rest cost about £79 pounds (or $155). Business travelers gleefully learn that the rate includes Wi-Fi, nonalcoholic beverages, a small breakfast and telephone calls for pennies a minute. By billing customers the way an airline does -- early booking is cheaper, with your credit card charged immediately -- Hoxton can splurge on expensive linens, name-brand toiletries and other high-quality materials throughout.</p>
        <p>Those £1 rooms have created a glut of demand: the Hoxton Web site has crashed again and again.</p>
        <p>By price and size, Hoxton's 250 rooms fall in the middle of the new business-hotel spectrum. NiteNite and Yotel, which are both opening their first hotels in Britain, are smaller, high-tech updates on the 1980s Japanese pod-hotel-room prototype. Marina Bruce, 43, a small-business owner, booked her NiteNite pod in October for £39.95.</p>
        <p>''The room was small, but high quality,'' Ms. Bruce said. ''The power shower was a blessing.'' She added that the bed was comfortable, and she was not bothered by the windowless room she chose.</p>
        <p>The idea is yacht rather than cocoon: 42-inch plasma screen televisions, full-size double beds, Wi-Fi and touches like leather and cherry wood in the furniture. ''Because the rooms are compact spaces, more can be slotted into a site, thus creating more revenue and enabling us to cut the price of the rooms,'' said Kat Bailey, the marketing manager for NiteNite's hotel in Birmingham (nitenite.com).</p>
        <p>Using the pod concept, Simon Woodroffe, the founder of Yo Sushi, a popular British sushi-bar franchise, will open a Yotel inside Gatwick Airport this spring (yotel.com) and at Heathrow Airport in the summer. Science-fiction-looking rooms rent in four-hour increments starting at £25, aimed at travelers with layovers and early flights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woodroffe said he envisioned luxury ''first-class business cabins'' in city centers and airports around the world. He said that a ''250 percent occupancy'' rate would reduce operating expenses because rooms would be used for a variety of purposes: layovers; overnights; watching a movie; or merely having a private room at an airport.</p>
        <p>Robert Nadler, the founder of Base2Stay (base2stay.com), said he decided that working travelers' needs were even broader than capsule spaces at airports. ''We call the concept 'edited services,' '' he said by phone from London. ''We edit out the things a lot of travelers normally simply choose not to use but pay for.''</p>
        <p>Originally hoping to provide high-end, short-term leases, Base2Stay's £80 rooms have kitchenettes, Wi-Fi (for a small fee), free WebTV, plenty of electrical outlets and everything else Mr. Nadler said he missed as he hopscotched around the globe. But there is no restaurant or bar. ''Starbucks does better coffee, so why have a second-rate substitute?'' Mr. Nadler asked.</p>
        <p>Britain is ahead of the curve on low-cost, high-value business hotels, but a few accommodations have popped up on the Continent as well. Like Hoxton Hotels, Qbic Hotels (qbichotels.com) in Amsterdam (opening in May) and Antwerp, Belgium (September), will be priced using the low-cost airline model. Book early and the 300-square-foot rooms with Philippe Starck-designed bathrooms and high-speed Internet access ring in at 39 euros. The staff is virtually nonexistent: check-in and check-out happens at a computer terminal.</p>
        <p>At Ciutat Barcelona (ciutatbarcelona.com), the design is minimalism meets Mondrian for 95 euros. Wi-Fi and unlimited bottled water are free, and while the bathroom is pure Ikea, beds are made up with luxurious crisp white-on-white cotton duvets.</p>
        <p>These hotels are nudging chains to attention. Sercotel hotels in Spain and AC Hotels in Spain, Italy and Portugal now offer free minibars, coffee shops with free snacks (at the AC) and free or low-cost Wi-Fi. Although city center fees can run high, the hotels' branches on city outskirts offer room rates under 90 euros.</p>
        <p>''It's not about being cheap,'' said Mr. Nadler of Base2stay. ''It's value. You can stay in a room that costs $50 and still feel ripped off.''</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
