<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E-Mail Innovator Plans to Enlist in the Wireless Campaign of the Patent Wars</title>
    <meta content="16email" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/technology/16email.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wireless Communications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2DF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1211" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E-Mail Innovator Plans to Enlist in the Wireless Campaign of the Patent Wars</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">E-Mail Innovator Plans to Enlist in the Wireless Campaign of the Patent Wars</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <dateline>PALO ALTO, Calif., April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nicholas Fodor is about to dive into the patent wars that have tangled up the business of wireless e-mail. But his weapon of choice is not a lawsuit. It is a new e-mail service he is developing using the knowledge gained from years of experience with e-mail software.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fodor, 43, a French computer programmer, said that in the early 1990s he worked on ''push'' e-mail services that predated the filing of important patents in this area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Freedom Mail will make it possible to view and respond by cellphone to messages sent to almost any e-mail account.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nicholas Fodor is about to dive into the patent wars that have tangled up the business of wireless e-mail. But his weapon of choice is not a lawsuit. It is a new e-mail service he is developing using the knowledge gained from years of experience with e-mail software.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fodor, 43, a French computer programmer, said that in the early 1990s he worked on ''push'' e-mail services that predated the filing of important patents in this area.</p>
        <p>He intends to test his claims as soon as next month by introducing Freedom Mail, a simple free service that he says will make it possible to view and respond to messages sent to almost any e-mail account on a cellphone or other mobile device.</p>
        <p>''Freedom Mail will liberate wireless e-mail from expensive and spurious litigation driven by very few patent owners for the sole purpose of dominating global wireless e-mail communications,'' Mr. Fodor said in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>The service, which he said would work with almost all cellphones that can connect to the Internet, will be supported by small advertisements appended to messages. Mr. Fodor said that in advanced phones, the service would match the capabilities of push e-mail services like that available on the BlackBerry from Research in Motion, where messages on the phone and on a personal computer are automatically synchronized.</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that he is an underdog in the wireless e-mail world, where heavyweights like Google, Yahoo and Microsoft are battling for market share. But he said that he would soon announce partnerships and was hoping to take advantage of grass-roots marketing online.</p>
        <p>And though he is not well known in the industry, an earlier version of his software has been used by SFR in France, owned by Vodafone and Vivendi, through a partnership of Mr. Fodor's company, SetNet, with Hewlett-Packard.</p>
        <p>If it works as promised, Freedom Mail will compete with highly profitable services like those provided by Research in Motion, and could also undermine the lucrative patent portfolios of NTP and Visto, two firms that have won hundreds of millions of dollars in court with claims that they invented the idea of wireless electronic mail and mail synchronization.</p>
        <p>''Visto could have some real problems,'' said Gregory Aharonian, publisher of Internet Patent News Service, an industry newsletter, and an intellectual property consultant who has worked with Visto in the past. He said that once the service became widely available, ''everyone they are suing is going to slap them with discovery requests to find out how much they knew about Mr. Fodor's software.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fodor, who founded SetNet in Florida in 1993, said he was the first to offer a commercial product that could synchronize e-mail between machines.</p>
        <p>He demonstrated e-mail synchronization in 1996 at an industry conference, three years before Visto received its first patent for the idea of synchronizing ''work spaces'' over a network in 1999.</p>
        <p>SetNet's software, which was sold in partnership with Hewlett-Packard beginning in 2002, could be viewed as important ''prior art'' in the intellectual-property wars that have pitted Visto and its investment partner, NTP, against Seven Networks and Motorola's Good Technology Group, as well as Microsoft and Research in Motion.</p>
        <p>The protracted patent battles are cited by many legal scholars and industry executives as a principal example of the failings of the United States patent system, which they say has limited technology innovation more than fostering it.</p>
        <p>''The fact is that ideas spring up simultaneously all the time,'' said Mark A. Lemley, a Stanford University professor who specializes in patent law. He said there was a growing movement among legal scholars and economists to back changes in patent law to protect the concept of independent invention.</p>
        <p>NTP won a $612.5 million judgment against Research in Motion last year, even though the patent office had largely invalidated its claim that its founder, Thomas J. Campana Jr., who died in 2004, was the inventor of wireless e-mail.</p>
        <p>Before that judgment, NTP invested in Visto, which has successfully sued Seven Networks and in the last decade has raised more than $300 million from about a dozen investors.</p>
        <p>But further legal claims by Visto could be undermined by SetNet -- a risk that Brian Bogosian, Visto's chief executive, appeared to acknowledge in 2003.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fodor has a short e-mail message that he says Mr. Bogosian sent him on Aug. 14, 2003, saying only: ''O.K., I need you but, you really need us. Next step?''</p>
        <p>A venture capitalist had told Mr. Bogosian that SetNet needed funds, Mr. Fodor said, which was not the case. He spurned Mr. Bogosian's overtures.</p>
        <p>Through a spokesman, Visto executives declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Fodor grew up in France and studied law in Paris, some aspects of his background parallel those of many American computer entrepreneurs. He said he was diverted from a legal career in the 1970s when he discovered VisiCalc, the first spreadsheet software. ''VisiCalc changed everything for me,'' he said. ''I was seduced by the fun of programming.''</p>
        <p>He went on to form a small business developing database software for the real estate industry. In 1992, he decided to move to the United States when a bank said it was prepared to invest in his business, but only if he was willing to convert his software for a French computer company.</p>
        <p>Settled in Coral Gables, Fla., he stumbled on the idea of e-mail synchronization because he had one computer that was connected to the Internet and multiple computers around his home, plus multiple e-mail accounts on services like CompuServe and MCI Mail. Synchronizing them in one universal mailbox on all his computers seemed an obvious step, he said.</p>
        <p>''I was tired of having to swap between multiple clients all the time,'' Mr. Fodor said. He began selling his synchronization software through CompuServe in 1993. In 1999 he sold a robust version of the original program to SFR, which is the second-largest mobile operator in France.</p>
        <p>In 2002, SetNet reached a distribution deal with Hewlett-Packard. This made it possible for a cellular carrier to offer push e-mail to consumers with ordinary e-mail accounts, without the need for Microsoft Exchange or BlackBerry software. From 2003 to 2006, the service was available to several million subscribers on the Vodafone Live service in Europe, Mr. Fodor said.</p>
        <p>Now, he thinks he has found a way to extend his software. In addition to synchronizing accounts on services like Yahoo Mail, Hotmail and Gmail, Freedom Mail will offer spam filtering and privacy protection and, in the future, additional features that may be sold by subscription, Mr. Fodor said.</p>
        <p>The service is being developed by a team of 11, including legal and business staff members, and backed by $6 million in financing from family and friends. Mr. Fodor said he might file for patents on some aspects of the service to give it a clear path for future development, but would consider allowing others to make use of them without paying royalties.</p>
        <p>Despite the hurdles his service will face, Mr. Fodor has supporters who think he is in a good position.</p>
        <p>''I'm confident that he was there first,'' said Bill Race, an independent technology consultant, who as worldwide manager of telecommunications for Hewlett-Packard helped strike a deal with SetNet. ''Nick is probably holding all the cards.''</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
