<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Number to Remember</title>
    <meta content="16anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/sports/baseball/16anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uniforms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Robinson, Jackie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEEDD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Number to Remember</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Honoring Robinson’s Achievement and Carrying On His Legacy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The street sign is the same, but nothing else is. Sullivan Place was outside the Brooklyn Dodgers' clubhouse, under the stands along the right-field foul line, when Jackie Robinson arrived there for opening day on April 15, 1947. But yesterday, amid the wind and rain, Sullivan Place was next to a tree-lined courtyard of the 23-story yellow-brick Ebbets Field Apartments, around the corner from the Jackie Robinson Intermediate School on McKeever Place.</p>
        <p>All over the major leagues, on the 60th anniversary of his first major league game, dozens of players, including the entire Los Angeles Dodgers team, were wearing uniforms with his No. 42 on the back in honor of Jackie Robinson Day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jackie Robinson’s No. 42 jersey was once a target for racist hatred. Yesterday, it was a source of pride for scores of major league ball players and the entire Dodgers team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The street sign is the same, but nothing else is. Sullivan Place was outside the Brooklyn Dodgers' clubhouse, under the stands along the right-field foul line, when Jackie Robinson arrived there for opening day on April 15, 1947. But yesterday, amid the wind and rain, Sullivan Place was next to a tree-lined courtyard of the 23-story yellow-brick Ebbets Field Apartments, around the corner from the Jackie Robinson Intermediate School on McKeever Place.</p>
        <p>All over the major leagues, on the 60th anniversary of his first major league game, dozens of players, including the entire Los Angeles Dodgers team, were wearing uniforms with his No. 42 on the back in honor of Jackie Robinson Day.</p>
        <p>But opening day wasn't Robinson's first time in that Dodger clubhouse. The previous Thursday, during an exhibition game at Ebbets Field with the minor league Montreal Royals, for whom Robinson played in 1946 and throughout spring training, the Dodgers announced the purchase of his contract.</p>
        <p>When that game ended, still in his Montreal uniform, Jackie Robinson, 28, a four-letter athlete at U.C.L.A. and an Army lieutenant during World War II, entered the Dodgers' clubhouse.</p>
        <p>''As I remember, he walked in with Branch Rickey Jr.,'' said Ralph Branca, a 21-game winner for those pennant-winning Dodgers that season, referring to the son of the Dodgers general manager who had signed Robinson to shatter organized baseball's color line. ''There weren't any lockers available, so Jackie had to hang his clothes on a couple of nails on the wall near the trainer's room. Then somebody handed him a white uniform with 42 in blue numbers on it.''</p>
        <p>Branca welcomed Robinson with a handshake; so did a few other Dodgers.</p>
        <p>''Some of the Southern guys didn't shake his hand,'' Branca said in a telephone interview, ''but it wasn't dramatic. I don't think anybody really grasped the social importance of what was happening. He had been in Montreal and he was just another ballplayer who could help us win. Growing up in south Mount Vernon, I'd played with and against blacks all my life. Four black families lived on our block. So did Irish, Italian and German families.''</p>
        <p>That weekend, Robinson played first base in three exhibition games against the Yankees, an annual series in those years, before the April 15 season opener against the Boston Braves on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>But one of the Southern guys on that Dodgers team, the right-handed relief pitcher Clyde King, out of Goldsboro, N.C., and the University of North Carolina, did shake Robinson's hand.</p>
        <p>''I remember when Mr. Rickey signed me in 1944,'' King said in a telephone interview, ''he asked me the questions he asked everybody: 'Do you plan to have a family? Do you believe in God?' Then he asked me, 'Would it bother you if you played with a black man?' So he was thinking about it even then. I told him, 'No, I'd played with black kids in Goldsboro; a black lady helped my mother around the house.' I never knew the difference, I really didn't.''</p>
        <p>Robinson soon had a real locker, not far from Branca's, and later his locker was along the wall near those of Pee Wee Reese, Duke Snider and Gil Hodges. By then the Dodgers and all of baseball had realized that Jackie Robinson, the National League rookie of the year in 1947, had more than a bat and a glove.</p>
        <p>''He was the best base runner I ever saw,'' said King, once a manager of the Yankees. ''One time against the Phillies, he hit a double and when their second baseman came around with the late tag, he slammed his glove into Jackie's head so loudly, we could hear it in the dugout. Jackie never said a word, but two pitches later, he stole third. That was his answer.''</p>
        <p>King, who had a 6-5 record with a 2.77 earned run average that season, recalled the Dodger infielders surrounding him when he arrived in a bases-loaded jam.</p>
        <p>''Pee Wee joked, 'You're so smart, you're a college guy, let's see you get out of this,' '' King said, referring to the Hall of Fame shortstop and team captain. ''But all Jackie said was: 'Don't worry about it. Just get 'em to hit the ball to me.' That's how confident he was, even as a rookie. When I got out of it, Pee Wee told me, 'Nice going.' Jackie didn't say anything. He didn't have to.''</p>
        <p>As a rookie, Robinson, batting second and playing first base, hit .297 and scored 125 runs. In 1949, batting cleanup and playing second base, he was the National League's most valuable player and batting champion with a .342 average, 203 hits, 124 runs batted in, 122 runs scored and 37 stolen bases. He was on his way to the Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>Wherever the Dodgers played, especially in cities like St. Louis and Cincinnati, blacks from all over the South would travel to cheer him. But not everybody accepted him. Early in the 1951 season, four years after his arrival, the Dodgers arrived in Cincinnati after a letter that included a death threat was delivered to the Reds' offices, The Cincinnati Enquirer and the police department.</p>
        <p>''In a clubhouse meeting, our manager, Charlie Dressen, got up and read the letter to us about how if Jackie took the field, he'll be shot,'' Carl Erskine, a Dodger right-hander of that era, recalled over the telephone. ''There was complete silence.'' Erskine then mentioned the Dodgers' left fielder at the time, saying: ''But then Gene Hermanski piped up: 'Hey, Skip, I've got an idea. If we all wore 42 out there, they won't know who to shoot.' ''</p>
        <p>Everybody laughed, especially Robinson.</p>
        <p>When the Dodgers went out to warm up before the game, Robinson was standing near Reese when Reese joked: ''You mind moving over a little, Jack? This guy might be a bad shot.''</p>
        <p>Until the run-up to yesterday's ceremonies, Hermanski's joke was the only time it had been suggested that No. 42 should be worn by all the Dodgers, much less by dozens of other major leaguers.</p>
        <p>It should happen more often than once every 60 years.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
