<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 30th-Anniversary Retrospective Offers Both a Primer and a Premiere</title>
    <meta content="16bori" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/arts/dance/16bori.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070514T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840729"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Eifman Ballet Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Graham, Martha</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Diaghilev, Serge</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE0DF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 30th-Anniversary Retrospective Offers Both a Primer and a Premiere</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A 30th-Anniversary Retrospective Offers Both a Primer and a Premiere</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Boris Eifman Ballet of St. Petersburg swept into City Center on Friday night for a three-week season that is a 30th-anniversary retrospective and has an American premiere, ''The Seagull,'' tucked in for good measure. The opening program was, for the most part, an eye-filling canter through three decades of repertory, seen in excerpts. Mr. Eifman's ''Red Giselle'' was performed in full the following night.</p>
        <p>The two evenings suggested much about Mr. Eifman's vivid, problematic works. The first program offered an ideal way to get a feeling for his style and ballets, a primer of sorts, though clearly none was needed for the happy, avid Russian émigrés who seem to make up most of the Eifman audiences in New York. The less said the better about the opening work, ''Cassandra,'' a world premiere by Nikita Dmitrievsky and set to music by Holst that dragged on through a confusing retelling of the story of the doomed seer of Greek mythology.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The opening program was, for the most part, an eye-filling canter through three decades of repertory, seen in excerpts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Boris Eifman Ballet of St. Petersburg swept into City Center on Friday night for a three-week season that is a 30th-anniversary retrospective and has an American premiere, ''The Seagull,'' tucked in for good measure. The opening program was, for the most part, an eye-filling canter through three decades of repertory, seen in excerpts. Mr. Eifman's ''Red Giselle'' was performed in full the following night.</p>
        <p>The two evenings suggested much about Mr. Eifman's vivid, problematic works. The first program offered an ideal way to get a feeling for his style and ballets, a primer of sorts, though clearly none was needed for the happy, avid Russian émigrés who seem to make up most of the Eifman audiences in New York. The less said the better about the opening work, ''Cassandra,'' a world premiere by Nikita Dmitrievsky and set to music by Holst that dragged on through a confusing retelling of the story of the doomed seer of Greek mythology.</p>
        <p>According to his program biography, Mr. Dmitrievsky, the Eifman company's first guest choreographer, trained in ballet, modern dance, jazz dance, acrobatics, hip-hop and breakdance. A few head spins might have helped ''Cassandra,'' though the brief male costumes were fun at first. Mr. Dmitrievsky may have achieved a record early in his career by creating 40 ballets in 10 months. But ''Cassandra'' looks like the effort of a new artist cramming everything he knows into a first ballet, including a good bit of Martha Graham. Graham did it better.</p>
        <p>It was a great relief to swing into undiluted Eifman, in extended snippets from six ballets (''Who's Who,'' ''The Karamazovs,'' ''Anna Karenina, ''Don Quixote,'' ''Don Juan &amp; Molière'' and his 1977 ''DoubleVoice,'' an American premiere, all set to big, familiar music). His theatrical imagination was in full play here, evident both in his reworking of traditional narratives and in stunning scenic and glittering costume effects that also suggest an unlimited production budget. Two scenes from ''The Karamazovs'' say it all.</p>
        <p>In one, shifting proletarian masses surge about the stage with the slightly robotic quality seen in much of Eifman's group choreography and with the sharp-angled bodies frequently seen in his pas de deux. In the second scene lovers meet on either side of a grill of prison bars that eventually sweeps away exhilaratingly to free the two for an ardent romantic encounter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eifman's re-envisioning of Don Quixote as a madman in an asylum is bold. And Yuri Smekalov, one of several outstanding male performers in the company, portrayed the Don with wonderfully cheeky humor and poignant shading. Here indeed was a madman for all seasons. A scene from ''Don Juan'' closed the program, doubling as an ingenious but slightly creepy coda in which the dancers might have been consuming the choreography of Mr. Eifman, who sat at the head of the table where they ate.</p>
        <p>In comparison ''Red Giselle'' was something of a disappointment. Mr. Eifman takes considerable liberties with the life story of Olga Spessivtseva, the Russian ballerina who became a legend during her years with the Maryinsky, which she left in 1918 to dance for Serge Diaghilev in the West. Beloved for her ethereal quality and classically pure technique, Spessivtseva later went mad. Mr. Eifman questionably attributes her breakdown to disappointments in love, first with a KGB agent (Ivan Kozlov) then with a partner, compellingly portrayed by Mr. Smekalov, who is revealed to be gay. Nina Zmievets is appropriately delicate but a mite too mopey in the title role, in a lead cast completed by Oleg Markov as a dictatorial ballet teacher.</p>
        <p>That character and a mercifully short burst of supposedly modern ballet choreography in the second act suggest a surprising naïveté in Mr. Eifman, though Mr. Markov nobly survives the absurdities. More serious is the dullness of ''Red Giselle'' on repeated viewing, despite a few muffed set changes on Saturday that seemed to mirror Spessivtseva's disturbed emotions.</p>
        <p>Passages in ''Red Giselle'' make use of classical ballet technique, but only to create a context. Mr. Eifman's thin choreographic vocabulary functions for the most part as the motor that sweeps his dancers dramatically about the stage, tumbling them at appropriate moments into slow acrobatic pas de deux. The ballerina's duet with a disembodied head is still audaciously inventive and great fun, in one of Mr. Eifman's most filmic moments. But there is no need for toe shoes in ''Red Giselle.'' The paucity of steps -- of a strong vocabulary -- robs the work of a strong expressive core.</p>
        <p>The Boris Eifman Ballet of St. Petersburg will perform through April 29 at City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan; (212) 581-1212 and nycitycenter.org.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 14, 2007, Monday  A dance review on April 16 about the Boris Eifman Ballet, at City Center, misstated the history of Mr. Eifman's new ballet, ''The Seagull.'' Its American premiere was in March at the University of California, Berkeley -- not at City Center in April.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 14, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>A dance review on April 16 about the Boris Eifman Ballet, at City Center, misstated the history of Mr. Eifman's new ballet, ''The Seagull.'' Its American premiere was in March at the University of California, Berkeley -- not at City Center in April.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
