<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Before the Flight, a Taste of Lounge Life</title>
    <meta content="16lounge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business Travel" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16lounge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CONVENIENCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Before the Flight, a Taste of Lounge Life</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Before the Flight, a Taste of Lounge Life</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Daniel</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR most travelers, it is a mythical domain behind a frosted-glass door, but for a fortunate few it can be a peaceful haven before the rigors of a long flight: the airline lounge. And though travelers may be spending more and more time in lounges, why do some offer gourmet meals and spa treatments, while others dole out only soda and stale pretzels?</p>
        <p>It is a question with complex answers, having to do with customer surveys, tight budgets, co-branding agreements and space limitations. Lounges are also becoming more relevant as competition heats up for business-class flights, the number of premium-level frequent fliers multiplies and airport regulations change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Why do some airline lounges offer gourmet meals and spa treatments, while others dole out only soda and stale pretzels?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR most travelers, it is a mythical domain behind a frosted-glass door, but for a fortunate few it can be a peaceful haven before the rigors of a long flight: the airline lounge. And though travelers may be spending more and more time in lounges, why do some offer gourmet meals and spa treatments, while others dole out only soda and stale pretzels?</p>
        <p>It is a question with complex answers, having to do with customer surveys, tight budgets, co-branding agreements and space limitations. Lounges are also becoming more relevant as competition heats up for business-class flights, the number of premium-level frequent fliers multiplies and airport regulations change.</p>
        <p>''Since 9/11, what you've found is the dwell time in airports is generally longer,'' said Steven Clark, a senior vice president for customer service for British Airways in the Americas. ''People for the most part don't know how long it's going to take them to get through the security line, so they tend to show up earlier.''</p>
        <p>Access to a private lounge can come with a business-class ticket, a high-level frequent-flier card or even a platinum charge card. A first-class ticket or top frequent-flier card often allows entry into an even more exclusive lounge.</p>
        <p>''I'm very particular about this stuff,'' said Andrew Ertel, the president and chief executive of Evolution Markets, an emissions trading company in White Plains. Mr. Ertel travels to scores of countries every year. ''It's a balance of cost and quality of service onboard versus in the lounges,'' he said. ''All things equal, it definitely makes that little difference.''</p>
        <p>Despite the importance of lounges, however, passengers can find a wide and sometimes puzzling variation in services.</p>
        <p>Lufthansa, for example, offers a fairly sophisticated intercontinental business-class service, with on-demand entertainment, ergonomically designed seats and a small bar on its Boeing 747s. But in the business-class lounges at its Frankfurt and Munich hubs, passengers find a meager choice of soft drinks, beer and crackers. British Airways, on the other hand, lays out a full buffet and provides private showers to business-class customers at its Gate 1 Lounge in Terminal 4 at Heathrow.</p>
        <p>Services that can be used upon arrival, like free suit pressing, make a difference to travelers, Mr. Ertel said. ''More than half the time, you're getting off the plane, you're getting in early morning time in Europe and going straight to your meeting.''</p>
        <p>The choice of services is not always up to the airline; infrastructure can be the heart of the problem. ''In our biggest hub, Frankfurt, we simply can't get any more space from the airport company to improve our service,'' said Jan Bärwalde, a spokesman for Lufthansa.</p>
        <p>When an airline is trying to offer a variety of lounge settings for different types of customers, space is especially important. In Virgin Atlantic's upper-class lounge at Heathrow, for instance, travelers can find everything from retro arcade games to reclining chairs facing the runway -- just not in the same place. ''It's very much designed in different sections, so if you do want to play pool, the pool table's not next to the place where you have a quick nap before your flight,'' said Angus D. Struthers, head of the airline's upper-class product and service.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bärwalde said that Lufthansa was updating its food and beverage selections and trying to increase room in its lounges as part of a systemwide enhancement that will cost 100 million euros (about $130 million). But he also said that making lounges a priority was not always easy.</p>
        <p>''It's quite hard to measure if lounge and lounge services are part of the decision from which airline I buy a ticket,'' he said. ''People or guests take it for granted. They suppose it should be there, and they're expecting it to be there. But you can't really say, 'That is a percentage of the whole decision for buying a ticket.' ''</p>
        <p>John Reber, a spokesman for Air Canada, said that cultural traditions could also affect expectations. ''There may be a difference between what Canadian consumers expected versus what other North American travelers have come to expect,'' he said. ''For example, historically, Canadian carriers were still offering hot breakfasts when there was no breakfast on other carriers.''</p>
        <p>The difference is apparent in Air Canada's lounges. Though travelers may not see much variation between in-flight service on Air Canada and other major North American carriers, Air Canada's business-class lounge in Toronto is a far cry even from United Airlines' international first-class lounge at its Dulles hub in Washington. The Toronto lounge offers relaxation rooms, entertainment centers, laptop computer services, showers and panoramic views of the airport from double-high windows. The United space is dimly lighted with only a buffet of miniature snacks and top-brand liquors, and passengers must pay for Internet access. (United did not respond to a request for comment about the services.)</p>
        <p>Air Canada can offer such services, Mr. Reber said, partly because of its co-branding agreements with Sony, BMW, Steelcase, Xerox and other well-known companies. ''Each partnership has its own terms and conditions and is negotiated separately, but it's a win-win situation for both parties,'' Mr. Reber said. ''What this allows us to do is to always offer the latest products that the suppliers wish to feature.''</p>
        <p>With all these services available, travelers may even prefer hanging around in a lounge to sitting at home or in the office until it is time to go to the airport. That is exactly what some of Lufthansa's first-class passengers are doing.</p>
        <p>These folks are welcomed at the airport entrance by personal assistants who take care of their tickets, documents and bags. They are then whisked off to their own private terminal, a world away from the dull gray décor of business-class lounges. When a flight is ready to leave, passengers are taken by limousine to the tarmac and the plane's door.</p>
        <p>The average time a passenger stays in the first-class terminal is 90 to 105 minutes, Mr. Bärwalde said, but some stay much longer. ''Their planes start deep in the night, late in the evening, 10 p.m. or something, and they come way before noon,'' he said. ''That means they spend 10 to 12 hours in the lounge.''</p>
        <p>CONVENIENCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
