<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kiss and Howl: This Man Is a Wolf's Best Friend</title>
    <meta content="16wolv" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/arts/television/16wolv.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Ellis, Shaun</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E0DF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kiss and Howl: This Man Is a Wolf's Best Friend</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kiss and Howl: This Man Is a Wolf’s Best Friend</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Susan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''A Man Among Wolves,'' a bizarre and riveting nature documentary that will be shown tonight on the National Geographic Channel, a British former gamekeeper named Shaun Ellis feeds wolf cubs prechewed food from his own mouth. He licks them on their chops. They lick him on the lips. He howls, eats and frolics with them.</p>
        <p>The only thing Mr. Ellis does not do is to instruct the cubs in mating behavior. Perhaps that is because this is an all-male wolf pack. Perhaps it is because fanaticism has its limits. Whatever the reason, this omission is one of the best things about ''Wolves.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This bizarre and riveting nature documentary follows a British man who lives the lupine life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''A Man Among Wolves,'' a bizarre and riveting nature documentary that will be shown tonight on the National Geographic Channel, a British former gamekeeper named Shaun Ellis feeds wolf cubs prechewed food from his own mouth. He licks them on their chops. They lick him on the lips. He howls, eats and frolics with them.</p>
        <p>The only thing Mr. Ellis does not do is to instruct the cubs in mating behavior. Perhaps that is because this is an all-male wolf pack. Perhaps it is because fanaticism has its limits. Whatever the reason, this omission is one of the best things about ''Wolves.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellis says his calling is ''not for the fainthearted.'' He might well say the same thing about this program, which features many close-ups of wolves and their alpha-man chomping raw deer. Because he is the leader of the pack, Mr. Ellis eats the liver, lungs and heart, which are cooked briefly to make them fit for human consumption, then stuffed back into the deer's abdominal cavity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellis has lived the lupine life for almost two years, at a wildlife park in southern England. His three cubs were abandoned at birth. Mr. Ellis, whose partner and four children have abandoned him because of this project, adopted the cubs. There are scenes of him feeding the baby wolves milk and, most adorably, teaching them to howl.</p>
        <p>Howling is serious business for wolves, who use it to communicate and guard territory. The sight of Mr. Ellis yodeling along with his snub-nose charges is so cute it will make you want your own wolf pack. But beware: Having a baby wolf is like having a baby. One minute they're defenseless cuddleballs sucking a bottle, and the next they're ripping up your face with their love bites. (When this happens, Mr. Ellis says wolf saliva heals his cuts faster than conventional medicine.)</p>
        <p>Eventually the child becomes father to the man. Late in ''Wolves'' Mr. Ellis is called away from his furry family. The emergency: Polish farmers plagued by wolves need his help. Mr. Ellis goes to Poland and sets up a tape of wolf howls to drive away the predators. This is probably interesting to scientists, but to viewers it's a letdown. Who cares about Polish cattle, when there's a wolf-man to gawk at?</p>
        <p>By the time Mr. Ellis returns to his cubs, they've outstripped him in every way. ''Wolves'' ends with our hero in a subservient, stomach-up posture so the new alpha-male won't hurt him. It's a bittersweet moment that will strike a nerve in anyone who has ever had the bad judgment to give birth to children.</p>
        <p>''Wolves'' features the requisite wildlife experts debating the usefulness of Mr. Ellis's research. They give the program an air of legitimacy: this is no freak show, it's behavioral science. But a small English boy visiting the wildlife park says it best. Asked about Mr. Ellis, he replies, ''Well, he's kind of a bit mad.''</p>
        <p>A Man Among Wolves  National Geographic Channel, tonight at 9, Eastern and Pacific times, 8 p.m., Central.</p>
        <p>Produced by Aqua Vita Films for the National Geographic Channel. For Aqua Vita Films: Bernard Walton, executive producer and director; Petra Regent, writer. For the National Geographic Channel: Chris Valentini, executive producer; Juliet Blake, senior vice president for production; John Ford, executive in charge of production.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
