<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Derby Run-Up, Finding Flaws With Favorites Is Popular Sport</title>
    <meta content="16racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/sports/othersports/16racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Derby Run-Up, Finding Flaws With Favorites Is Popular Sport</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Horses’ Victories Garner Attention, but Also Raise Some Questions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>LEXINGTON, Ky., April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like them or not, 20 horses have shown that they are worthy of a place in the starting gate for the 133rd running of the Kentucky Derby. The latest two did so in jaw-dropping fashion Saturday: Dominican ran down the 2-year-old champion Street Sense to capture the Blue Grass Stakes here by a nose, and Curlin zoomed to a record 10 1/2-length victory in the Arkansas Derby.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, an impressive victory is not enough to dispel the questions about this bunch of 3-year-olds. Yes, Dominican looked to have a rapid turn of foot in the stretch as he rumbled to his third career victory against perhaps the most accomplished field of the prep season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like them or not, 20 horses have shown that they are worthy of a place in the starting gate for the 133rd running of the Kentucky Derby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like them or not, 20 horses have shown that they are worthy of a place in the starting gate for the 133rd running of the Kentucky Derby. The latest two did so in jaw-dropping fashion Saturday: Dominican ran down the 2-year-old champion Street Sense to capture the Blue Grass Stakes here by a nose, and Curlin zoomed to a record 10 1/2-length victory in the Arkansas Derby.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, an impressive victory is not enough to dispel the questions about this bunch of 3-year-olds. Yes, Dominican looked to have a rapid turn of foot in the stretch as he rumbled to his third career victory against perhaps the most accomplished field of the prep season.</p>
        <p>But each of his victories came on synthetic surfaces, two of them here at Keeneland, and Dominican is a troubling 0 for 4 on dirt, which happens to be the surface at Churchill Downs.</p>
        <p>No one could blame Curlin's trainer, Steve Asmussen, for arguing that he has the horse to beat on May 5.</p>
        <p>''I would think that Curlin will be the favorite in the Derby,'' he said. ''I've seen all the Derby preps, and I haven't seen a more impressive horse. He's beating them easy, and everybody loves that.''</p>
        <p>Curlin, the son of Smart Strike, has, indeed, looked untouchable in his three starts, which he has won by a combined 28 1/2 lengths. Beyond the question of the quality of competition that the colt has faced in his brief career, there is the matter of some foreboding history. Curlin did not race as a 2-year-old, and the last Derby winner not to race as a 2-year-old was Apollo in 1882. The last horse to win the Derby after only three starts was the filly Regret in 1915.</p>
        <p>''He has question marks,'' Asmussen said. ''But I have run horses in the Derby. They had plenty of experience and no superstitions against them, but they just weren't fast enough. I would rather take the one that doesn't have the experience but is fast enough.''</p>
        <p>He is not the only trainer bringing a horse perceived to be flawed or vulnerable to Churchill Downs. Street Sense was game in the stretch of the Blue Grass, but his trainer, Carl Nafzger, confessed he was concerned about how the colt showed his inexperience in those final yards.</p>
        <p>''Every time he ran straight he would get the lead, then he would duck in and lose the lead, and then he would get the lead and lose it again,'' Nafzger said. ''We made mistakes.''</p>
        <p>When Nobiz Like Shobiz gawked and dawdled down the lane en route to a third-place finish in the Fountain of Youth in March, his trainer, Barclay Tagg, fitted the colt with blinkers to close off his peripheral vision and provide better focus. Nobiz Like Shobiz won the Wood Memorial in his next start.</p>
        <p>Nafzger does not have time to tinker. He said it was too late to gamble on blinkers for the Derby, and now Nafzger, along with the colt's backers, may wonder if it was a mistake to race Street Sense only twice as a 3-year-old considering the last horse to wear the blanket of roses with a similar schedule was Sunny's Halo in 1983.</p>
        <p>Tagg is hardly ensured a victory for following a traditional path to the Derby: Nobiz Like Shobiz had three races as a 2-year-old and an equal number this spring, but he pulls into the Derby with knocks of his own. The blinkers helped him focus down the stretch of the Wood, but they may have made him rank and hard to control in the beginning of the race.</p>
        <p>''He hasn't quite put it all together,'' Tagg said.</p>
        <p>Many of the Derby contenders have taken turns beating each other. Scat Daddy, the Florida Derby winner, has two victories over Nobiz Like Shobiz against one defeat. Street Sense and Great Hunter, the Robert B. Lewis champion, have traded decisions.</p>
        <p>''It's very spotty,'' said Darrin Miller, the trainer of Dominican. ''Everyone has beaten each other.''</p>
        <p>While the Blue Grass Stakes was the rare Triple Crown prep race this spring in which Todd Pletcher did not have a horse, he was on the rail for the race, keenly watching the competition.</p>
        <p>His horses are likely to fill a quarter of the Derby starting gate, but that guarantees him only a busy time saddling horses in the paddock. Besides Scat Daddy, there is the Louisiana Derby winner, Circular Quay, a colt who will be coming off an eight-week layoff and has not run beyond a mile and a sixteenth.</p>
        <p>There is Cowtown Cat, who won the Illinois Derby; Any Given Saturday; and Sam P.</p>
        <p>Pletcher has a lot of hope, but not a great deal of expectations.</p>
        <p>''You can make a case for horses, or you can make a case against them,'' he said. ''There is not a right way to do any of this. You just lead the horses over there, and every year one of them comes back a winner. You hope someday it will be your horse.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
