<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting the C.E.O. Treatment: CONVENIENCE; What's Cooking in First Class?</title>
    <meta content="16eats" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business Travel" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16eats.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070510T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840800"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E2DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting the C.E.O. Treatment: CONVENIENCE; What's Cooking in First Class?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What’s Cooking in First Class?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIM SEVERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Severson, Kim</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to food, airlines seem to be going all out for the well-paid business traveler.</p>
        <p>Charlie Trotter, the Chicago chef, will soon introduce dishes created for premier United Airlines passengers. (Mr. Trotter's personal tip? Try the short ribs spiced with Thai-style barbecue sauce.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eating light or indulging, you can bet it’s not peanuts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to food, airlines seem to be going all out for the well-paid business traveler.</p>
        <p>Charlie Trotter, the Chicago chef, will soon introduce dishes created for premier United Airlines passengers. (Mr. Trotter's personal tip? Try the short ribs spiced with Thai-style barbecue sauce.)</p>
        <p>And on Emirates, chefs from nine luxury Jumeirah hotels recently began cooking airline meals, adding to a menu that included roasted lobster and veal with pumpkin bathed in coconut cream.</p>
        <p>While the masses packed into economy continue to suffer through meals that seem to taste worse, cost extra or don't exist at all, a resurgence in the excesses of airline dining is swirling through first- and some business-class cabins. But is a parade of caviar, foie-gras-stuffed chicken breast and molten chocolate cake really what the elite business traveler wants?</p>
        <p>Hardly.</p>
        <p>''I can always tell when I'm traveling who is a frequent flier and who isn't by the amount of food they eat,'' said Niki Leondakis, chief operating officer of Kimpton Hotels and Restaurants. ''The newbies are trying everything, from the Champagne to the ice cream with Baileys. I always think, 'My God, do you know what you are going to feel like tomorrow?' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Leondakis, who is on and off planes more than two dozen times a year for Kimpton's San Francisco-based chain of 42 boutique hotels and 43 restaurants, has noticed the increased attention to food. She's not thrilled.</p>
        <p>''You don't want a five-course meal on an airplane,'' she said. ''It's almost an intrusion, the amount of courses that are being served.'' When she travels, she wants to step off the plane ready for a meeting, not a nap. So she agrees only to courses that are light and prepared without frills or heavy sauces.</p>
        <p>That means she might go for the shrimp cocktail and the salad course. She says no to the offerings of cocktails and wine, and yes to water. For dessert, she takes her own citrus-chamomile tea so she doesn't feel deprived when the chocolate tray and cordials come by.</p>
        <p>The best innovation she has seen lately is simple: United keeps a bowl of fresh fruit out at all times.</p>
        <p>''I get off the plane feeling infinitely better than the people who decided to act like they were at a restaurant,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But some airlines say elite travelers are demanding better food than ever, and they feel the pressure to keep up. Among certain carriers, the game is to outdo one another, with flavors from different countries, innovative dishes, richer desserts and better cocktails and wines.</p>
        <p>Still, airlines also say they try to balance the food race in the air with demands of frequent business travelers like Ms. Leondakis. On many airlines, first- and business-class meals are now served whenever travelers want them. And snacking is being given more thought.</p>
        <p>On Emirates, which runs 500 different menus a month, diners can browse through a selection of snacks that features a cheese soufflé created to puff up nicely in the airplane oven, grilled vegetable sandwiches or roast salmon with linguine, ginger relish and asparagus. Fresh espresso can be ordered at any time.</p>
        <p>''Passengers are becoming more in control when they fly,'' said Bob Ferguson, who has been with Emirates for 15 years. ''They want to have maximum flexibility. They prefer something more like a grazing meal, so they can get off feeling more refreshed than they would if they had more of a banquet-style meal.''</p>
        <p>To determine what travelers want, the airline collects food after some flights to see what hasn't been eaten. It is taken back to the office to be weighed and studied. Was there too much served? Was it the wrong sort of food? Did it simply not taste right?</p>
        <p>''We're still quite big on portions, though, because our view is if they don't want to eat it, fine,'' Mr. Ferguson said. ''But you still want to give the passenger the choice.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trotter, who was part of the United celebrity chef program, which was discontinued after 9/11, has also noticed a change in how passengers want to eat. He and a team of his cooks have designed 35 dishes for passengers in business and first class, as well as United's premium transcontinental service. Although elaborate, the new menus, which make their debut this summer, are lighter than the food he was preparing for passengers six years ago.</p>
        <p>''The key to airline foods is to come up with things that are very forgiving,'' he said. ''People want to eat healthfully, but they want something interesting.''</p>
        <p>His food is also prepared so that travelers can eat when they want to eat, whether it's soon after takeoff or three hours into the flight.</p>
        <p>''Things are much more customized,'' Mr. Trotter said. Instead of creating entrees that have to be cooked six at a time, the chef has developed a series of one-offs -- meals that can be cooked in a shorter period of time, then sauced and put on a plate individually.</p>
        <p>Food experts at Eos Airlines, a New York-based airline specializing in trans-Atlantic business travel, have a different point of view. Although they offer lighter, healthier choices like seasonal greens topped with grilled beef or a British-style afternoon tea, they have found that their customers actually want to indulge. Travelers increasingly treat themselves with food because travel in general has become so difficult, said Hector Adler, senior vice president for customer experience.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot of hype and literature and articles about people wanting healthier and lighter food,'' he added. ''It is an absolute lie.''</p>
        <p>On Eos, planes designed for 220 people have been reconfigured to hold only 48, and tickets start at just over $3,000. Dinner might start with a chilled Bellini cocktail, then segue into beef filet with potato purée studded with truffles -- a dish that works well with the airline's favorite Bordeaux. And naturally, a cheese course follows.</p>
        <p>The menus rotate every six weeks to keep frequent travelers happy. Flight attendants are given a one-day course on presentation at the Culinary Institute of America in Hyde Park, N.Y., and have a meal at a top-shelf restaurant to study service.</p>
        <p>Private jets take a similar approach, said Jack Gentile, who started New York Aviation 30 years ago. His company has made a name flying corporate executives, celebrities, politicians and members of the British royal family. In each case, the menu is dictated by the customer.</p>
        <p>''We'll go into the city and get dinner at Le Cirque if people want it,'' Mr. Adler said.</p>
        <p>Although corporate travelers might be eating a little healthier, he doesn't see that much has changed.</p>
        <p>''As long as there's booze on board, they're happy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 10, 2007, Thursday  Because of an editing error, an article on April 16 about airline food in the special Business Travel section incorrectly attributed comments about a private-jet company, New York Aviation, and about business travelers in general. The comments, ''We'll go into the city and get dinner at Le Cirque if people want it,'' about the services New York Aviation provides, and ''As long as there's booze on board, they're happy,'' referring to business travelers, were by Jack Gentile, founder of New York Aviation -- not by Hector Adler, senior vice president for customer experience at Eos Airlines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 10, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article on April 16 about airline food in the special Business Travel section incorrectly attributed comments about a private-jet company, New York Aviation, and about business travelers in general. The comments, ''We'll go into the city and get dinner at Le Cirque if people want it,'' about the services New York Aviation provides, and ''As long as there's booze on board, they're happy,'' referring to business travelers, were by Jack Gentile, founder of New York Aviation -- not by Hector Adler, senior vice president for customer experience at Eos Airlines.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
