<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nigeria's Governing Party Takes Lead in State Elections</title>
    <meta content="16nigeria" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/world/africa/16nigeria.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nigeria</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Polgreen, Lydia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abubakar, Atiku (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obasanjo, Olusegun (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Nigeria</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6DE113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nigeria's Governing Party Takes Lead in State Elections</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nigeria’s Governing Party Takes Lead in Elections</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYDIA POLGREEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Polgreen, Lydia</byline>
      <dateline>ADO EKITI, Nigeria, April 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Partial results from Nigeria's highly contested state elections appear to hand most victories to governing People's Democratic Party, prompting violent protests to break out in several of country's 36 states; allegations of vote rigging, ballot stealing and intimidation in several states raise fears that presidential voting, to be held later this week, could fail; People's Democratic Party has struggled to retain its dominance as infighting rages over who will replace Olusegun Obasanjo; there are two dozen candidates; Atiku Abubakar, current vice president who fell out with Obasanjo, has been barred from running because he was indicted on corruption charges by government panel; he is fighting that decision in court; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Violent protests broke out in several of Nigeria's 36 states on Sunday as partial results from highly contested state elections appeared to hand most of the victories to the governing People's Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>The police said 21 people had died in election violence, but local newspapers estimated that the toll was at least twice that number.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The police said 21 people died in election violence, but newspapers estimated that the toll was at least twice that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Violent protests broke out in several of Nigeria's 36 states on Sunday as partial results from highly contested state elections appeared to hand most of the victories to the governing People's Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>The police said 21 people had died in election violence, but local newspapers estimated that the toll was at least twice that number.</p>
        <p>Allegations of vote rigging, ballot stealing and intimidation in several states in the first round of Nigeria's landmark elections set off violence and raised fears that the country's presidential voting, to be held later this week, could fail, according to candidates and independent observers. Of the 10 state governor races for which results were available, the People's Democratic Party was leading in 8.</p>
        <p>''It is a complete disaster,'' said Chris Albin-Lackey, a researcher for Human Rights Watch, who spent election day on Saturday searching, largely in vain, for voters in the troubled, oil-rich Niger Delta region in the south. ''Watching the run-up to these elections, I suppose it shouldn't be a surprise, but the scale of it is astonishing.''</p>
        <p>Government and electoral officials said they were satisfied with the voting across the country, saying it had been largely free and fair. International observers have yet to publicly assess the election.</p>
        <p>But as election results and accounts of the voting emerged from states across the country, in many crucial races a picture of widespread incompetence, ballot stuffing, intimidation and fraud emerged.</p>
        <p>The problems are likely to intensify as Nigeria hurtles toward the presidential election, to be held Saturday, to choose the successor to Olusegun Obasanjo, the former general who has led the country since it emerged from three decades of nearly continuous military rule in 1999. Nigeria is the most populous nation in Africa and its largest oil producer.</p>
        <p>The People's Democratic Party has struggled to retain its dominance as infighting has raged over who will replace Mr. Obasanjo.</p>
        <p>There are two dozen candidates, but the main ones are Umaru Yar'Adua of the People's Democratic Party; Muhammadu Buhari, a former military ruler with a reputation for honesty; and Atiku Abubakar, the current vice president, who fell out with Mr. Obasanjo last year. Mr. Abubakar, the candidate of a new coalition of opposition parties, has been barred from running because he was indicted on corruption charges by a government panel. He is fighting that decision in court, and the proceedings may delay the presidential voting.</p>
        <p>If the election is successful, it will be the first time in Nigeria that one elected government has handed power to another without military interference, a milestone in a nation plagued by coups, despotism and civil strife.</p>
        <p>The state elections were in some ways a dry run for the presidential election, and the picture emerging from them was decidedly mixed. While they went smoothly in many states, there were problems in others.</p>
        <p>In several states across the Niger Delta, voting did not take place at all in many communities, either because materials never arrived or voters were scared away by armed gangs. In the southwestern state of Enugu, candidates said that essentially no election had taken place because ballots and boxes never arrived.</p>
        <p>Here in Ekiti, another southwestern state, where the People's Democratic Party was struggling to hold on to the governorship after a corruption scandal that forced the incumbent from power last year, the declaration that the party had won the governorship by a wide margin drew immediate protest.</p>
        <p>''They have stolen the Ekiti mandate,'' said Kayode Fayemi, the main opposition candidate. ''I am disappointed, but I am not surprised. We predicted this would happen. It was preordained that the ruling party should win.''</p>
        <p>Election day in Ekiti was marred by violent confrontations between supporters of candidates. In the town of Oye, supporters of Mr. Fayemi dragged from a car several people who were suspected of stealing a ballot box, beating one until he briefly lost consciousness. A search of the car's trunk turned up only old clothes.</p>
        <p>At another polling station in Oye, supporters of the People's Democratic Party carted off a ballot box as foreign journalists watched. The box was full of neat stacks of ballots that looked as if they had been stuffed in at the same time, not one by one by voters. At other polling stations in Oye, youths menaced voters. The official tally in Oye, according to election officials, gave twice as many votes to the governing party candidate as to the second-place candidate.</p>
        <p>In Enugu, Ken Nnamani, president of Nigeria's Senate and a member of the governing party, told Reuters that the election might as well have not taken place.</p>
        <p>''If people impose themselves on the electorate, it's no better than military rule,'' he said. ''The erosion of our democracy is horrendous.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
