<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Trophy Mag Wears Camouflage</title>
    <meta content="16carr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/media/16carr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070417T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA EQUATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Magazine Award</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Field &amp; Stream (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Yorker (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlantic Monthly</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Esquire (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Sid</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Magazine Awards</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EEDF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Trophy Mag Wears Camouflage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Trophy Mag Wears Camouflage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CARR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carr, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Field &amp; Stream ranks among top magazines despite its focus on hunting and other outdoor sports; is nominated for four National Magazine Awards, grouping publication in field that includes New Yorker, Atlantic Monthly and Esquire; editor Sid Evans says magazine fills niche that used to be more widely accepted across America (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sid Evans, the editor of Field &amp; Stream, is hardly the only editor in the ferocious world of Manhattan publishing with a reputation for taking no prisoners. But he is the only one with the temerity to actually hang the heads on the wall.</p>
        <p>Walking around the magazine's offices on Park Avenue in Midtown Manhattan, you see an oryx, a weird-looking critter with long straight horns that make a kind of inferred peace sign, a symbol that had no effect on its fate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Field &amp; Stream received four nominations in the National Magazine Awards, putting it in the front ranks of magazine journalism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sid Evans, the editor of Field &amp; Stream, is hardly the only editor in the ferocious world of Manhattan publishing with a reputation for taking no prisoners. But he is the only one with the temerity to actually hang the heads on the wall.</p>
        <p>Walking around the magazine's offices on Park Avenue in Midtown Manhattan, you see an oryx, a weird-looking critter with long straight horns that make a kind of inferred peace sign, a symbol that had no effect on its fate.</p>
        <p>The oryx was felled by Mr. Evans on a hunting trip in South Africa in 2003, as was the kudu, which has spiral horns and weighed 700 pounds when the rest of his body remained attached. And that little guy over in the photo department? Why that's an unlucky impala.</p>
        <p>The trophies all wear the stunned look that, at any other magazine, you find on editorial assistants. Clearly, they never saw it coming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans, who is a bit reticent about the display (he is more given to the quiet glories of fly fishing), is on another hunt, this time for Ellies, the elephant-shaped sculptures that represent a kill in the National Magazine Awards.</p>
        <p>At this year's awards on May 4, there will be the usual perennials, including The New Yorker, The Atlantic Monthly and Esquire, but then there is Field &amp; Stream, with four nominations, including one for general excellence. The burst of nominations puts Field &amp; Stream in the company of magazines with far more Manhattan cachet, like Gourmet and Martha Stewart Living.</p>
        <p>''How many people out there who read Gourmet or Martha Stewart Living know what it is like to shoot a quail or wring the neck of a chicken?'' Mr. Evans asked.</p>
        <p>Ummm, the answer is probably none, other than some rustic expatriate French chefs. It may seem odd that Field &amp; Stream, which promises to help its readers ''call ducks like a pro,'' is in the front ranks of magazine journalism. But Mr. Evans, 36, points out that they aim well beyond the easy editorial targets.</p>
        <p>When Vice President Dick Cheney accidentally shot one of his hunting buddies, Field &amp; Stream did a deconstruction on the topic of hunters gone bad. In the last year, the magazine published work by Howell Raines, former executive editor of The New York Times, C. J. Chivers, a Times correspondent in Afghanistan, and Phil Caputo, who has a Pulitzer Prize to his credit.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy that the judges were able to overcome any negative feelings that they may have about hunting to see our magazine for what it is,'' he said. ''We cover a subject that our peers don't interact with very often, but I think that they recognize that our writers are doing amazing work.''</p>
        <p>It's not as if the fashion-obsessed world of New York magazining is against the killing of animals. It's just that its members would prefer that someone else do the killing so that they can wear or eat the vanquished.</p>
        <p>''So much of the media is concentrated around the cities,'' he said. ''Our magazine goes to every state in the union, and we are very evenly spread among them. I don't think that is true of most men's magazines, which are more about grooming and shopping.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans, who grew up hunting and fishing in Tennessee, pointed out that the outdoor lifestyle used to be in the dead center of the American narrative. Three New Yorker covers from the '50s, each with a hunting theme, hang on his office wall, suggesting that there was a time when shotguns or bait used to be part of polite conversation, even in New York.</p>
        <p>Since joining Field &amp; Stream in 2002, Mr. Evans has become the editorial director of Salt Water Sportsman, which also received a general excellence nomination this year. Between the two publications' five nominations, their performance put them on par with all of Time Inc., which sold the two magazines, along with 16 other enthusiast magazines, to the Bonnier Magazine Group, a Swedish publisher, at the beginning of the year for about $220 million.</p>
        <p>Given the general state of the magazine industry -- serving the general interest is challenging when Paris Hilton and ''American Idol'' seem to be the only things we have in common -- being a niche player does not seem like a bad place to be.</p>
        <p>''Special interest magazines may not be high profile, but they make a lot of money,'' said Reed Phillips, managing partner of DeSilva &amp; Phillips, a media investment bank. ''The magazines that serve a niche and serve it well have a bright future, in part because they attract enthusiasts that will go to the brand on the Web. And it's pretty impressive that a magazine without a lot of profile in the editorial and publishing community is getting that kind of recognition.''</p>
        <p>Part of the reason that the judges were willing to look at a magazine that explores the business end of the food chain is that Mr. Evans, a veteran of general interest magazines, was able to bring real freshness to the hunting and fishing genre.</p>
        <p>The award in the personal service category generally revolves around persuading readers to show up for colonoscopies, but Mr. Evans came up with a package of how to avoid more aggressive threats, like lightning, animal attacks and the like.</p>
        <p>For a magazine where just about everything comes with a big old side of macho, a long treatise by Susan Casey on her first elk hunt has a surprise ending. Field &amp; Stream also has its own camouflage version of a ''green issue,'' including a column by Hal Herring about how unchecked development is threatening all sorts of species, including one that runs around on two legs.</p>
        <p>''It may not matter to the average 23-year-old media planner, but we are covering America,'' Mr. Evans said. ''There are 40 million people out there who see hunting and fishing as a vital part of their lives. Anybody who ever leaves the bubble of Manhattan knows that there is a big country out there.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA EQUATION</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 17, 2007, Tuesday  The Media Equation column in Business Day yesterday, about Field &amp; Stream magazine and its four nominations for National Magazine Awards, misstated the date the 2007 awards will be presented. It is May 1, not May 4.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 17, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>The Media Equation column in Business Day yesterday, about Field &amp; Stream magazine and its four nominations for National Magazine Awards, misstated the date the 2007 awards will be presented. It is May 1, not May 4.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
