<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Late Run Gives Nets Hope for a Better Seed</title>
    <meta content="16nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Late Run Gives Nets Hope for a Better Seed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even when the stakes were at their highest this season, and nothing was guaranteed, the Nets often had a difficult time kindling their inner fire. Now, with a postseason pass in hand, there was a question of how seriously the Nets would approach the one thing left to be had: the sixth seed in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>Against the Indiana Pacers on Sunday, the Nets displayed the type of endgame execution that would serve them well in the playoffs. The Nets' 111-107 victory at Conseco Fieldhouse moved them to a game behind the Washington Wizards for the sixth seed. The Nets (39-41) play the Knicks on Monday night and finish the regular season Wednesday at home against the Chicago Bulls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even when the stakes were at their highest this season, and nothing was guaranteed, the Nets often had a difficult time kindling their inner fire. Now, with a postseason pass in hand, there was a question of how seriously the Nets would approach the one thing left to be had: the sixth seed in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>Against the Indiana Pacers on Sunday, the Nets displayed the type of endgame execution that would serve them well in the playoffs. The Nets' 111-107 victory at Conseco Fieldhouse moved them to a game behind the Washington Wizards for the sixth seed. The Nets (39-41) play the Knicks on Monday night and finish the regular season Wednesday at home against the Chicago Bulls.</p>
        <p>''We're going to play to the end, try to get that sixth spot,'' Nets forward Bostjan Nachbar said.</p>
        <p>If they do, the Nets will play the Toronto Raptors in the first round of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Nachbar certainly showed he had something to play for. He made all six of his 3-point attempts and finished with 25 points.</p>
        <p>Vince Carter scored 35 points, making him the first player in the Nets' N.B.A. history to reach 2,000 points in a season. The rookie point guard Marcus Williams broke out of an offensive funk by scoring 11 points and making 5 of 9 shots.</p>
        <p>Carter said he did not realize he had surpassed 2,000 points.</p>
        <p>''It's a great accomplishment to beat my own record, I guess,'' he said.</p>
        <p>If Carter's nonchalance was a sincere indication that he was focused on team goals, the Nets could be in a good spot entering the postseason. Carter and Nachbar essentially carried the Nets late in the game.</p>
        <p>After the Pacers tied the score at 92-92 midway through the fourth quarter, the Nets used smart offense to take control with a 13-4 run.</p>
        <p>Nachbar hit a 3-pointer from the corner, Mikki Moore made two free throws and Carter had a 3-pointer and a jumper on consecutive possessions. Nachbar capped the spurt by giving a head fake behind the 3-point line and driving to the basket for a two-handed dunk and a foul on Mike Dunleavy. Nachbar's free throw gave the Nets a 105-96 advantage with 2 minutes 55 seconds remaining.</p>
        <p>''Once you make five, six 3's, they're going to start running at you hard, and that's where it really opens up drives,'' Nachbar said. ''Just trying to be smart about it, to make good decisions at good times. That's the most important thing.''</p>
        <p>Although he refused to mention positioning for the postseason, Nets Coach Lawrence Frank indicated that his team had no intention of letting up.</p>
        <p>''Our aspirations are to try to get as many wins as possible and, when it's over, go from there,'' he said before Sunday's game. ''Big picture, we understand what's at stake. We're focused and we know what needs to be done.''</p>
        <p>The defeat of the Pacers (35-45), combined with Orlando's victory over Boston, eliminated Indiana from playoff contention. It was another chapter in the Pacers' sudden and drastic tumble.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 21, they were five games above .500 (29-24). They lost 17 of their next 19 games.</p>
        <p>Pacers Coach Rick Carlisle sounded resigned when he delivered what sounded like a eulogy.</p>
        <p>''The last two games are on the schedule, and we're wearing a uniform that says Indiana Pacers,'' he said. ''So that's important, whether the last two games mean anything or not. We've had moments where it has been difficult, but the fight has never left these guys.''</p>
        <p>It has been an especially trying season for center Jermaine O'Neal, who had a team-high 20 points Sunday. He has missed 11 games because of a knee injury and has been hampered during many more. .</p>
        <p>O'Neal and some of his teammates lost a large chunk of the 2004-5 season because of the brawl during a game against the Detroit Pistons that spilled into the stands at the Palace of Auburn Hills. O'Neal had to endure the distraction that Ron Artest brought to the Pacers before Artest was traded to the Sacramento Kings last season. And O'Neal had to adjust to a revamped roster in the middle of this season when the Pacers made an eight-player trade with the Golden State Warriors.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Nets will play in their sixth consecutive postseason. They are just one of four teams to have qualified for each of the past six playoffs. The others are the Pistons, the San Antonio Spurs and the Dallas Mavericks.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
