<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Lady Magazine, a Ruthless Chick-Eat-Chick World</title>
    <meta content="16masl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/books/16masl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Little Pink Slips (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E1DF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Lady Magazine, a Ruthless Chick-Eat-Chick World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Lady Magazine, a Ruthless Chick-Eat-Chick World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Little Pink Slips  By Sally Koslow  370 pages. G. P. Putnam's Sons. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Sally Koslow was editor in chief of McCall's until it was transformed into a celebrity vehicle with Rosie O'Donnell at the helm. To the extent that Ms. Koslow's ''Little Pink Slips'' features an embattled editor named Magnolia Gold and does not have a character named Sally Koslow, it qualifies as a work of fiction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sally Koslow’s roman à clef clearly falls into the chicks-who-snitch category, populated by disgruntled, shoe-obsessed office underlings and nannies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Little Pink Slips  By Sally Koslow  370 pages. G. P. Putnam's Sons. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Sally Koslow was editor in chief of McCall's until it was transformed into a celebrity vehicle with Rosie O'Donnell at the helm. To the extent that Ms. Koslow's ''Little Pink Slips'' features an embattled editor named Magnolia Gold and does not have a character named Sally Koslow, it qualifies as a work of fiction.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Koslow's roman à clef clearly falls into the chicks-who-snitch category, populated by disgruntled, shoe-obsessed office underlings and nannies. What's different and moderately interesting about this book is that its main character is in a position of power and knows a lot about the magazine business. Certainly she knows more than that divas are apt to throw their coats on the desks of lower-level employees, although, as in ''The Devil Wears Prada,'' that actually happens.</p>
        <p>''Little Pink Slips'' also benefits from the incongruity between the magazine it describes -- ''everyone's favorite dowager,'' a frumpy thing called Lady -- and the smug young cupcakes who put it together. It takes a certain lively cynicism for the book's ''Sex and the City''-cloned characters to package articles about the secrets of getting a good night's sleep and aim them at a readership in which ''no one ever admitted to having, liking or being the least bit curious about sex.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Koslow, who did not work with Ms. O'Donnell but has said she picked up shock waves from members of the remaining McCall's staff, wastes little time before sending a character called Bebe Blake blasting onto the scene. ''It's clever the way you do the product endorsement thing, your seal of approval,'' Bebe says to Magnolia, apparently under the impression that she has taken over Good Housekeeping. She cements this first impression by referring to Magnolia as Gardenia.</p>
        <p>Soon Bebe is conducting meetings and offering to pose on the cover of her first issue in a tubful of bubbles, to show ''that I'm all about fun.'' She's offering to wear her own bicycle shorts when the clothes supplied by the magazine are all too tight. She's forgetting to invite the staff to the magazine's elaborate launch party. She's also trying to put type on the right side of the cover instead of the left. ''Perhaps it would sell well to the dyslexic,'' Magnolia cattily thinks, ''or in Tel Aviv.''</p>
        <p>However much comic potential there is in this caricature (the overbearing Bebe has ''a smile that stopped short of her eyes''), it's not enough to sustain ''Little Pink Slips.'' Ms. Koslow can't decide whether to demonize or enjoy Bebe, and so she remains a large, improbable presence. Although Bebe is a bull in Lady's china shop, and although the issue of her destructive influence on Lady eventually winds up in court (''I miss their recipes,'' says the wistful judge), this mess isn't compelling enough to yield a real story.</p>
        <p>So Ms. Koslow falls back on the usual chick-book tricks, starting with brand names. (''Her new Jimmy Choos could pass muster here. The question was, could she?'' ''You can kiss those Manolos goodbye, Magnolia said to herself.'') Then there are the manicures and pedicures and the fashion critiques (''She looked like a homeless woman who'd robbed a jewelry store'') and the endless perks. One of those perks is having a best friend who is a jewelry designer and likes to give her free samples. Another is Hugh Grant as birthday gift, courtesy of Bebe.</p>
        <p>Hot and cold running boyfriends are also obligatory, though Ms. Koslow outdoes the genre's norm by giving Magnolia an old flame who is a hot-blooded, married North Dakota minister. When these encounters threaten to become steamy, Magnolia's trusty BlackBerry is around to remind her that work comes first, and that there's work to be done.</p>
        <p>Until there isn't. As its coy title indicates, Magnolia's job security doesn't count for much after Bebe begins edging her out. Ms. Koslow's description of a corporate comedown is one of the book's non-generic ingredients. Just as she knows that for a cover photograph, ''it didn't matter if the star had lettuce in her teeth, as long as readers recognized her,'' she knows that becoming an editor at large ''translated to editor who's small.''</p>
        <p>And she knows that ''Manhattan was littered with UK roadkill who snatched New York jobs when their Fleet Street careers stalled.'' She knows when the sharks begin circling her, and she knows when the business in which she is involved is headed for disaster. ''Anyone who can start a fire, it seems, can start a magazine,'' Ms. Koslow has Larry King say, in one of the book's numerous unconvincing cameos. ''And usually all that happens is they burn a lot of money.''</p>
        <p>In the realm of pampered-heroine escapist reading, ''Little Pink Slips'' is a semi-success. ''Bergdorf Blondes'' and ''The Nanny Diaries'' are much funnier, but this is higher up the designer-brand totem pole than ''The Devil Wears Prada.'' And if Ms. Koslow is self-serving about her heroine, the book also makes her sound like a smart, gimlet-eyed professional who deserves better than what she gets, until she gets a bona fide Hollywood ending.</p>
        <p>Magnolia is blessed with her own celebrity rag to edit (''Hadn't Anne Frank had photographs of celebrities in her hiding place?'' she asks herself) and a big night at the Oscars. ''If celebrity worship were religion,'' Ms. Koslow writes, ''this was Jerusalem.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
