<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer Learns His Job Comes At a Cost</title>
    <meta content="16empire-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE EMPIRE ZONE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E1DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer Learns His Job Comes At a Cost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer has taken some lumps in the press during his first 105 days in office, while Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo has been riding a wave of positive publicity about his investigation into student loan practices.</p>
        <p>In a Quinnipiac University poll this month, Mr. Cuomo even surpassed the governor's still solid job approval numbers for the first time, a development that did not go unnoticed in the capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer has taken some lumps in the press during his first 105 days in office, while Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo has been riding a wave of positive publicity about his investigation into student loan practices.</p>
        <p>In a Quinnipiac University poll this month, Mr. Cuomo even surpassed the governor's still solid job approval numbers for the first time, a development that did not go unnoticed in the capital.</p>
        <p>''As attorney general, there are a series of binary choices between right and wrong and good and evil,'' Mr. Spitzer said in an interview last week when asked about the difference between the public perception of his current and previous jobs.</p>
        <p>''As governor, one is always making very difficult allocations, decisions in a zero-sum context, and necessarily there are winners and losers.''</p>
        <p>And as attorney general? As Mr. Spitzer put it, ''One is always on the side of righteousness.''</p>
        <p>In other words, it is often easier for the public and the press to extrapolate good guys and bad guys in investigations brought by an attorney general, as compared with, say, the dueling budget proposals being wrangled over by the governor and the Legislature.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo's latest investigation has revealed that top officials at several universities had lucrative financial ties to a major student lender.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer and his aides, in the meantime, have been trying to explain why they compromised with Senate Republicans in budget negotiations more than some observers had expected.</p>
        <p>How does the governor feel about his first 105 days?</p>
        <p>''It has been a remarkably successful stretch,'' he said. ''I don't mean to suggest successful in terms of the governor versus the Legislature. I think successful in terms of showing that we can govern the state, that Albany need not be dysfunctional.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer ticked off a number of previously intractable issues that he forged consensus on, including major agreements on the workers' compensation system and the civil confinement of sex offenders.</p>
        <p>The governor also has insisted that he achieved his major goals in the budget, winning substantial increases in education aid and property tax relief and $1 billion worth of Medicaid cuts.</p>
        <p>The Legislature returns today after a two-week vacation, and top items on the agenda include negotiating campaign-finance reform legislation and wrapping up leftovers from the budget, including a bill delineating capital projects.</p>
        <p>''Doing the job of governor properly necessarily means losing friends, saying no to supporters and making decisions that will have political costs,'' Mr. Spitzer said. ''Life is much more complicated.''</p>
        <p>THE EMPIRE ZONE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
