<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Imus Fracas Becomes a Draw in Play's Revival</title>
    <meta content="16talk" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/media/16talk.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840750"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bogosian, Eric</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schreiber, Liev</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7DE113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Imus Fracas Becomes a Draw in Play's Revival</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Imus Fracas Becomes a Draw in Play’s Revival</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ADAM NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andrew Adam</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Don Imus was being removed last week over an on-air racial slur, the producers of ''Talk Radio,'' the Broadway play by Eric Bogosian in which Liev Schreiber stars as shock D.J. Barry Champlain, had a sense of life imitating art.</p>
        <p>They also had an idea: use the controversy to sell more tickets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The producers of “Talk Radio,” the Broadway play, are using the Don Imus controvery to sell more tickets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Don Imus was being removed last week over an on-air racial slur, the producers of ''Talk Radio,'' the Broadway play by Eric Bogosian in which Liev Schreiber stars as shock D.J. Barry Champlain, had a sense of life imitating art.</p>
        <p>They also had an idea: use the controversy to sell more tickets.</p>
        <p>On Friday, right after Mr. Imus was dropped from WFAN and MSNBC, print ads for ''Talk Radio'' placed in The New York Times and Time Out New York magazine said, ''Before There Was Imus, There Was Barry Champlain.'' Mr. Bogosian wrote and staged the play in the mid-1980s; Mr. Imus's show began in the early 1970s.</p>
        <p>In the new version, Mr. Schreiber plays a Cleveland talk-show host giving a powder-keg broadcast. His show is on the brink of being picked up by a national network, and executives are listening to make sure that he is not too much of a loose cannon. As the play progresses, Mr. Schreiber's character swills whiskey and becomes so strident about not toning down the show that he becomes even more provocative, at one point calling an African-American caller ''Uncle Tom.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bogosian said he thought his script was never as offensive as Mr. Imus's remark mocking the Rutgers women's basketball team, but he said he did see parallels.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of weird that this is going down right now,'' said Mr. Bogosian, who played Barry Champlain Off Broadway in 1987 and in a film adaptation the next year. ''About 12 hours into the Imus fracas, I realized that what was happening had a lot to do with what I was writing about in the play: At what price do you raise your ratings? What are you willing to say?''</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Richards, one of the show's producers, said, ''Our business has increased. What's happened has fueled interest in talk radio and shock jocks in general, so I think we've been a beneficiary of that.''</p>
        <p>Postperformance discussions with actual radio hosts were scheduled before the Imus affair, but are being promoted more aggressively in its wake, Mr. Richards said. Tomorrow, Bob Grant, a former host on WOR and WABC, who years ago also drew heat for racially charged remarks, will take the stage.</p>
        <p>Offstage, meanwhile, the play's marketers found that ads for a provocative play about radio can actually be too strong to air on the radio. In February, a 60-second spot that featured Mr. Schreiber's character discussing ''your pet's orgasms'' was banned by WINS, WOR and WWFS and WCBS, according to Greg Corradetti of the ad agency Serino Coyne.</p>
        <p>''We have certain standards and practices'' for commercial content, said Crys Quimby, program director for WCBS. ''We did work with the advertiser and subsequently did run their other ads.'' WCBS is owned by CBS, the parent company of the radio station that dropped Mr. Imus.</p>
        <p>ANDREW ADAM NEWMAN</p>
        <p>MEDIA TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
