<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Good and the Bad of Leading a King From a Doubleton</title>
    <meta content="16card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/xword/16card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E1DF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Good and the Bad of Leading a King From a Doubleton</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Good and the Bad of Leading a King From a Doubleton</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alder, Phillip</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When would you lead the king from king-doubleton in an unbid side suit against a trump contract?</p>
        <p>The White House Teams ran in Amsterdam Feb. 23 to 25. The junior team tournament took place March 19 to 23, with the victory going to Norway, represented by Ivar Berg, Erik Eide, Tor Ove Reistad and Fredrik Simonsen. Second was the Poland Under-20 team: Karol Galazka, Bartek Igla, Piotr Kruszewski and Artur Machno.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When would you lead the king from king-doubleton in an unbid side suit against a trump contract?.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When would you lead the king from king-doubleton in an unbid side suit against a trump contract?</p>
        <p>The White House Teams ran in Amsterdam Feb. 23 to 25. The junior team tournament took place March 19 to 23, with the victory going to Norway, represented by Ivar Berg, Erik Eide, Tor Ove Reistad and Fredrik Simonsen. Second was the Poland Under-20 team: Karol Galazka, Bartek Igla, Piotr Kruszewski and Artur Machno.</p>
        <p>There was a four-day round robin for the 20 teams from 15 countries, which was won by Poland Under-20 ahead of Norway, Italy and Poland Juniors. (Poland had two teams playing.) In the 20-board semifinals, Norway defeated Italy, and Poland Under-20 beat Poland Juniors.</p>
        <p>Norway won the 20-board final by 64 international match points to 20, aided by the diagramed deal.</p>
        <p>At both tables South was in four hearts. In the other room Kruszewski for Poland (South) opened two diamonds, showing a weak two-bid in either major. This gave Galazka (North) a chance to be the declarer, which would have made the defense harder. But North responded four diamonds, asking his partner to bid game in his suit.</p>
        <p>In the given auction Reistad (South) opened three hearts, trading on the favorable vulnerability and trying to make it harder for his opponents to reach spades -- not that Berg (North) was worried about that.</p>
        <p>Against four hearts, both Wests, Eide and Igla, led the club king.</p>
        <p>The Norwegian East, Simonsen, using upside-down signals, encouraged with his club three. In desperation, declarer threw his queen under the king, but West continued with a second club, East winning the trick and taking two diamonds for down one.</p>
        <p>At the other table, Machno (East) thought he had matters under control. Trying to avoid an accident he overtook partner's club king with his ace. He then cashed two diamond tricks before returning a club. One can imagine his pain when declarer won with the queen and claimed, giving 10 imps to Norway.</p>
        <p>It is rarely right to lead the king from king-doubleton, especially when playing in a pair event, where conceding unnecessary overtricks is expensive. But when declarer is known to hold a weak, one-suited hand, the lead has greater appeal.</p>
        <p>Many years ago Eugenie and Lew Mathe were playing in a mixed pairs event. Lew, one of the best American players ever, was an excitable character. On an early deal Genie led the king from king-doubleton in an unbid side suit. It was a disaster, giving the Mathes a near bottom. Lew told his wife never to do that again.</p>
        <p>A few boards later Genie led the king from king-doubleton in an unbid side suit, resulting in another poor score. Lew's comments gained decibels.</p>
        <p>Then -- you guessed it -- Genie tried the same opening lead for a third time and a third catastrophe. Now Lew was almost having a conniption.</p>
        <p>After he calmed down. Genie said, ''You might not agree with my bridge, but you have to admit one thing.''</p>
        <p>''What's that?''</p>
        <p>''I've got chutzpah.''</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
