<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Are Still Putting All Their Pieces in Place</title>
    <meta content="16mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E6DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Are Still Putting All Their Pieces in Place</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Courtesy of Aaron Heilman, the first song that blared over the clubhouse speakers yesterday morning was ''The Long and Winding Road'' by the Beatles. If that selection was a tongue-in-cheek reminder of how early in the season it was, then the next Beatles number -- ''Come Together'' -- could have been a message of its own.</p>
        <p>Like many teams around the league, the Mets have been searching for an identity through the first 11 games. Since romping to four consecutive victories to begin the season, outscoring the Cardinals and the Braves, 31-3, the Mets are 3-4 and a game behind first-place Atlanta in the National League East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Courtesy of Aaron Heilman, the first song that blared over the clubhouse speakers yesterday morning was ''The Long and Winding Road'' by the Beatles. If that selection was a tongue-in-cheek reminder of how early in the season it was, then the next Beatles number -- ''Come Together'' -- could have been a message of its own.</p>
        <p>Like many teams around the league, the Mets have been searching for an identity through the first 11 games. Since romping to four consecutive victories to begin the season, outscoring the Cardinals and the Braves, 31-3, the Mets are 3-4 and a game behind first-place Atlanta in the National League East.</p>
        <p>With few exceptions, their starting pitching has been strong, their bullpen excellent and no one has been hurt. But to show how significantly things can change, at this point last season, Kazuo Matsui was still the second baseman, Víctor Zambrano was the No. 4 starter and John Maine had yet to throw a pitch.</p>
        <p>''This isn't going to be like it was last year,'' José Valentín said a few hours after the Mets' game against the Washington Nationals at Shea Stadium was rained out. (No need for Heilman to play ''Here Comes the Sun.'') ''There's plenty of time for us to figure out who we are.''</p>
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph knows his personnel; he is just sorting out how and when to use everyone. With the addition of Mike Pelfrey as the fifth starter, the rotation is settled. The lineup is, too, now that Shawn Green has shaken free from his spring training doldrums.</p>
        <p>The bullpen, one of the team's main uncertainties leaving camp in Florida, has withstood the absences of the right-handers Duaner Sánchez (shoulder surgery) and Guillermo Mota (50-game suspension) to post the majors' third-lowest earned run average, 1.82, entering yesterday's games.</p>
        <p>The relievers have allowed seven runs in 34 2/3 innings, and they were not scattered, either; they came over three consecutive games last week. Heilman allowed two runs last Sunday in Atlanta, Ambiorix Burgos gave up a three-run homer to the Phillies' Ryan Howard on Monday, and Aaron Sele allowed two runs during his four and a third innings in relief of Oliver Pérez on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''Everyone's like, 'What's my role?' '' the pitching coach Rick Peterson said. ''And the answer to that is, 'Well, how are you going to pitch?' ''</p>
        <p>In assembling the bullpen, General Manager Omar Minaya wanted relievers who could be used interchangeably. So far, the rookie right-hander Joe Smith has come into games twice with the bases loaded, in every inning from the sixth on and to face right-handers and left-handers. Heilman has been used as a situational right-hander as well as in his normal setup role.</p>
        <p>''The pieces are there for a great bullpen,'' said Scott Schoeneweis, who, as a member of the 2002 World Series champion Angels, was part of one of the better ones this decade. ''In Anaheim, it was let the starters pitch five innings, six as a bonus, and then we'd take care of the rest. That's how we feel here.''</p>
        <p>Led by Tom Glavine and Orlando Hernández, Mets starters have made it into the sixth inning in 9 of 11 games and, despite a recent rough turn, have compiled the fourth-best E.R.A. (3.18) in the N.L. before yesterday's games.</p>
        <p>For the most part, they have been supported by a lineup ignited, as usual, by José Reyes, who leads the N.L. in triples (3), stolen bases (6) and runs (13), and is batting .311 to go with a .415 on-base percentage. The only members of the Mets' lineup not hitting .289 or above are Carlos Delgado (.244) and Valentín (.206). David Wright (.333) is one game from tying the franchise mark for longest hitting streak (24 games). But the high averages mask a conspicuous teamwide lack of power.</p>
        <p>The Mets have only six home runs -- none in their five games at Shea Stadium -- and none by Moises Alou and Delgado, whose 45 at-bats without a home run to begin the season is the longest streak of his career, according to the Elias Sports Bureau. As much as anything, the void of home runs is a reflection of the nasty weather that has plagued the season's first two weeks.</p>
        <p>The rain is expected to continue through today in Philadelphia, raising the possibility of another rainout -- and costing the Mets another chance to begin developing their identity. As Maine said of the weather, ''Who knows what's going to happen?''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>No makeup date has been determined for yesterday's rainout, but the Mets have moved the Jackie Robinson Day festivities to Friday, before their game against the Braves.  Fans holding tickets for yesterday's game have the option of exchanging them for same-priced seats or toward the price of a higher-priced ticket for Friday's game or holding them for the rescheduled game against the Nationals.  John Maine, yesterday's scheduled starter, is scheduled to face Philadelphia's Freddy García tonight. Tom Glavine is scheduled to oppose Jamie Moyer for the second time in five days tomorrow. Oliver Pérez and Mike Pelfrey are scheduled to start Wednesday and Thursday in Florida.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
