<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sallie Mae, Mired in Controversy Over Loans, Is Under Siege</title>
    <meta content="16sallie" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/16sallie.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Slm Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sallie Mae</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1483" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sallie Mae, Mired in Controversy Over Loans, Is Under Siege</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sallie Mae, Mired in Controversy Over Loans, Is Under Siege</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH; Peter Edmonston contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>SLM Corporation, known as Sallie Mae, is under siege as lawmakers and President Bush threaten to cut federal subsidy guarantees that have allowed business to thrive for years; faces scrutiny over deceptive sales practices regarding high-interest private loans for students, its most lucrative business; private equity buyers discuss possible acquisition of company in deal that could be worth $20 billion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Standing before a group of student lending executives in late 2005, Representative John A. Boehner, then chairman of the House Education Committee, vowed he would keep their interests in mind as legislation made its way though Congress.</p>
        <p>''Know that I have all of you in my two trusted hands,'' Mr. Boehner, now the House minority leader, said in a widely reported speech.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nation’s largest provider of student loans is under siege on the political and economic fronts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Standing before a group of student lending executives in late 2005, Representative John A. Boehner, then chairman of the House Education Committee, vowed he would keep their interests in mind as legislation made its way though Congress.</p>
        <p>''Know that I have all of you in my two trusted hands,'' Mr. Boehner, now the House minority leader, said in a widely reported speech.</p>
        <p>Today, the student loan industry needs all the trusted hands it can find. And no lender needs them more than one of Mr. Boehner's biggest political supporters: the SLM Corporation, known as Sallie Mae.</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae, the nation's largest provider of student loans, is under siege on several fronts. Democratic lawmakers and President Bush are threatening to cut the federal subsidies and guarantees that have allowed its core loan business to thrive for years.</p>
        <p>Investigations and media scrutiny over deceptive sales practices are casting a harsh light on its newest and most lucrative business -- high-interest private loans that bridge the gap between tuition costs and federal aid. And a deteriorating credit environment for all financial institutions could soon put pressure on the company's bottom line.</p>
        <p>All the while, the political and economic uncertainty caused Sallie Mae's stock to plunge more than 20 percent over the last year, and made it a takeover target. At least two private equity buyers -- the Blackstone Group and a group consisting of J. C. Flowers and JPMorgan Chase -- are in talks to acquire the company, which is based in Reston, Va., according to people close to the situation. It could fetch $20 billion or more.</p>
        <p>''This is in some ways a perfect storm,'' said Kevin Bruns, the executive director of America's Student Loan Providers, an industry lobbying group. ''Sallie Mae's interests in what is going on in Congress and with the investigations is really what is going on in the overall student loan industry: the economics are changing, and they are concerned.''</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae has long known that its fortunes follow the course of Washington politics, even though it no longer has a quasi-government status, as many people still believe.</p>
        <p>''Much as Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac use their role in home ownership as a political asset for leverage, Sallie uses its historical role in providing student loans as a political asset,'' notes Jonathan G. S. Koppell, a Yale University professor who studies the politics of government-sponsored enterprises.</p>
        <p>The company, for example, has its own foundation, the Sallie Mae Fund, which offers money for education projects. Several of its former executives now hold top posts in the Education Department.</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae has also been a major political contributor, more often to Republicans than Democrats. And while it has not gotten much public attention until recently, its lobbyists have long been active on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>Even in the face of intense legislative and regulatory pressure, the company said that its growth as student lender remained compelling. ''We are providing better prices, better service and better technology,'' said Tom Joyce, a Sallie Mae spokesman. ''I think the facts will win out.''</p>
        <p>When the government established the company in 1972, a special charter allowed Sallie Mae to use low-cost debt, backed by the federal government, to buy existing student loans from banks. It pocketed the difference between the cost of the funds and the interest payments the students made. But as a government-sponsored enterprise, it was barred from directly lending to students.</p>
        <p>By the mid-1990s, however, Sallie Mae was struggling. As more students consolidated their debts at lower rates and a new government program cut private lenders out of the process, making student loans became far more profitable than packaging them. In 1997, Sallie Mae's new management team severed its government ties, allowing it to lend directly to students for the first time.</p>
        <p>Student lending had long been a little-noticed but lucrative niche. To encourage banks to lend to college students, who typically had little credit history and no collateral or predictable income, Congress has since the mid-1960s provided subsidies to banks and other private lenders.</p>
        <p>First, the government provided insurance to reimburse lenders in the event a student defaulted. Second, it agreed to guarantee the lenders a certain level of profit so long they adhered to an interest rate cap.</p>
        <p>While these terms were aimed at helping student borrowers, critics say the incentives are no longer necessary as the student loan business has matured, and have become little more than corporate handouts.</p>
        <p>As it snapped up smaller rivals, Sallie Mae quickly became the industry's biggest player. Today, it originates nearly 23 percent of all student loans, and carries about $142 billion, or 27 percent of all student loans, on its books.</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae also entered the debt collection business, which now contributes about 20 percent of its earnings. But so-called private loans ignited the company's growth.</p>
        <p>With tuition costs soaring and financial aid budgets remaining flat, students increasingly turned to banks and other lenders to bridge the gap. Because these loans did not receive government subsidies, Sallie Mae and other private lenders could issue them at a higher interest rate. At an average rate of 10.5 percent, more one and half times the guaranteed loan cap, they were far more profitable, even if the potential losses could be larger.</p>
        <p>A decade ago, Sallie Mae had no private loans. Today, it is the industry's largest player with as much as 40 percent of the market. While private loans make up about 15 percent of the company's portfolio, analysts say they generate 25 to 40 percent of its profits.</p>
        <p>As a result, Sallie Mae's stock price surged. Since 1997, Sallie Mae shares have delivered a 435 percent total return, nearly three and a half times the 126 percent growth of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index during the same period.</p>
        <p>But recently, Sallie Mae's lending success has become a major liability. With the federal budget stretched, both Congress and the White House are looking to cut back the subsidies of guaranteed loan programs. Proposed legislation would probably reduce costs for student borrowers but would also chip away at lenders' profits.</p>
        <p>In the House, Democratic lawmakers, led by Representative George Miller of California, voted to cut the federal loan interest rates in half over the next five years and force lenders to cover more of their losses.</p>
        <p>In the Senate, Edward M. Kennedy, the influential Education Committee chairman, is expected to introduce similar legislation as part of a broader plan to steer more students to direct federal loans, which avoid private lenders altogether.</p>
        <p>Even Republican support is fading. In February, President Bush sided with the Democrats when he called for a sharp reduction of federal loan subsidies. The news sent Sallie Mae's shares down from $46.46 to as low as $40.75 until they rebounded last Friday on reports of a possible buyout.</p>
        <p>And Senator Michael Enzi, the ranking Republican on the Education Committee, openly criticized Albert L. Lord, Sallie Mae's chairman, for selling more than $18.3 million of company stock just days before the president called for subsidy cuts. ''While the timing looked unfortunate, it was completely coincidental,'' said Mr. Joyce, the Sallie Mae spokesman.</p>
        <p>The recent investigation by the New York State attorney general into Sallie Mae's financial relationships with colleges and universities has been a rallying call for the company's critics.</p>
        <p>Last week, Sallie Mae agreed to pay $2 million and adopt a series of new practices, including barring gifts to university financial aid administrators and shutting down call centers that it runs for 19 colleges, to end the inquiry. A similar inquiry by the Education Department's inspector general in 2003 found that Sallie Mae made questionable inducements to get on a list of preferred lenders at one university.</p>
        <p>Although the inquiries were limited to Sallie Mae's private loan business, it is ''creating momentum for reform of the entire system,'' said Luke Swarthout, a student aid advocate for the Public Interest Research Group, a watchdog organization.</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae, meanwhile, is battling back. While it has long supported Republicans, there are signs that its allegiances are changing.</p>
        <p>During the 2006 election cycle, donations of $589,500 were split evenly between the two major parties, according to PoliticalMoneyLine. Now Sallie Mae's political spending is weighted heavily toward Democrats.</p>
        <p>Given the financial and political uncertainty, several analysts suggest that Sallie Mae could ultimately win by losing the government's assistance.</p>
        <p>If the government takes away part of its subsidies, Sallie Mae's lower operating costs still give it an advantage over smaller rivals. It also could move even further into the lucrative private loan market, which does not depend on federal support. These factors may be what the buyout groups are banking on with their bids.</p>
        <p>''Whatever Congress ends up passing will reduce profitability for lenders, but Sallie Mae will end up taking market share from smaller competitors,'' said Sameer Gokhale, an analyst for Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
