<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Rangers' Relief, Shanahan Seems Back to Normal At the Right Time</title>
    <meta content="16rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/sports/hockey/16rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Shanahan, Brendan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E3DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Rangers' Relief, Shanahan Seems Back to Normal At the Right Time</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To Rangers’ Relief, Shanahan Seems Back to Normal at the Right Time</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His signature fist-pump made its debut in the Rangers' postseason as forward Brendan Shanahan flashed a gap-toothed smile after scoring the winning goal. It was a window into the skills that Shanahan has displayed for 19 N.H.L. seasons: he got open in a shooting lane, called for a pass from Sean Avery and snapped a shot for a clutch goal.</p>
        <p>As easy as he made it look in that instant, Shanahan has battled to carry those skills back to the ice since his return March 21 after missing a month because of a concussion. Shanahan has only recently begun playing like his usual self, the man with 627 career goals in the regular season and 54 in the playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brendan Shanahan has only recently begun playing like his usual self, the man with 627 career goals in the regular season and 54 in the playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His signature fist-pump made its debut in the Rangers' postseason as forward Brendan Shanahan flashed a gap-toothed smile after scoring the winning goal. It was a window into the skills that Shanahan has displayed for 19 N.H.L. seasons: he got open in a shooting lane, called for a pass from Sean Avery and snapped a shot for a clutch goal.</p>
        <p>As easy as he made it look in that instant, Shanahan has battled to carry those skills back to the ice since his return March 21 after missing a month because of a concussion. Shanahan has only recently begun playing like his usual self, the man with 627 career goals in the regular season and 54 in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>It is not only a missing front tooth that has changed the way he looks. His goal Saturday was only his second since returning to the Rangers' lineup.</p>
        <p>The goal could not have come at a bigger time. It broke a tie late in the third period, pushing the Rangers to a 2-1 victory and a 2-0 lead over Atlanta in their Eastern Conference first-round series. Games 3 and 4 will be at Madison Square Garden on Tuesday and Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''It felt great,'' Shanahan said. ''I was going to the net, had a couple good scoring chances coming on the wing, and one rebound in the second period when their goalie made a great save on a one-time shot.</p>
        <p>''You just kind of say: 'Stick with it; you're doing the right thing, going to the right places, things are happening.' But it's a lot nicer to get rewarded for doing those things than to say it's coming.''</p>
        <p>Shanahan had been saying ''it's coming'' frequently in recent weeks, betraying no concern at the slow pace of his recovery. He said he had been warned by doctors that it would take time to return to form. His shot did not have its usual sting. He was a step slower getting to a shooting lane, and he battled for the puck with less than his trademark tenacity.</p>
        <p>He had seven assists in his first eight games back, but only one goal. He scored short-handed April 3, when his shot from behind the net banked off Islanders goalie Wade Dubielewicz.</p>
        <p>''I kind of take it upon myself that I've got to get Shanny the puck,'' said Avery, who plays on a line with Shanahan and center Martin Straka. ''That's what he does -- he gets open and he scores. If he's not scoring, it's kind of on my shoulders, more than anyone's, and Marty's. We have to get him the puck because when you get it to him, he usually scores.''</p>
        <p>The top line of Jaromir Jagr, Michael Nylander and Marcel Hossa led the Rangers to victory in Game 1. Shanahan's line got together afterward and talked about wanting to improve. Shanahan, Avery and Straka agreed that they had played solidly but had not created enough scoring chances. They vowed to communicate more, to work harder to get open for passes.</p>
        <p>Then they went out and dominated Game 2. Avery and Shanahan combined for 17 of the Rangers' 39 shots. Avery had two breakaways and Shanahan had a terrific shot on a rebound, but Thrashers goalie Johan Hedberg was able to stop them.</p>
        <p>Avery set up the winning goal by sending a pass across the crease to Shanahan, who had an open net because Hedberg was in position for a shot from Avery. Shanahan had called for the pass and Avery spotted him at the last instant.</p>
        <p>Shanahan also exhibited more of his usual snarl. Several times officials had to pull him from a shoving match with Atlanta players. He was called for two penalties, for high-sticking and for boarding, and he continually stuck up for Avery, who was being pounded by the Thrashers.</p>
        <p>The Rangers signed Shanahan in the off-season for just this kind of playoff presence, something they lacked last year, and for his knack for scoring big goals.</p>
        <p>''Our winning goal was a great goal,'' center Matt Cullen said. ''It was a great play by Aves to get it to Shanny, and Shanny's got one of the best releases in the history of the game, and it's in the back of the net. That's playoff hockey.''</p>
        <p>And that is the old Shanahan.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
