<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Goodness Gracious, That's Why He's a Mess</title>
    <meta content="16reas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/theater/reviews/16reas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Theater Workshop</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fugelsang, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">All the Wrong Reasons (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Theater Workshop</org>
        <object.title class="online_producer">All the Wrong Reasons (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1DF113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Goodness Gracious, That's Why He's a Mess</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Goodness Gracious, That’s Why He’s a Mess</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood reviews New York Theater Workshop production of John Fugelsang solo show All the Wrong Reasons: A True Story of Neo-Nazis, Drug Smuggling and Undying Love; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here it is halfway through April, and the slippery grip of winter hasn't quite relaxed its hold on the city. But New York Theater Workshop clearly is ready for summertime. This Off Broadway company, normally among the city's most adventurous, concludes its season with a solo show that is the stage version of a beach read: John Fugelsang's stand-up memoir ''All the Wrong Reasons.''</p>
        <p>Directed by Pam MacKinnon, Mr. Fugelsang's show is subtitled ''A True Story of Neo-Nazis, Drug Smuggling and Undying Love,'' a breathless string of phrases that conjures images of rampaging skinheads, terrifying scrapes with the law and heart-wrenching partings. Its tabloid flash is meant satirically, I suspect. Amiable and ingratiating, like the handsome Mr. Fugelsang, and sprinkled with comic zingers, ''All the Wrong Reasons'' is anything but melodramatic. By beach-read standards, it's pretty tame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York Theater Workshop, normally among the city’s most adventurous companies, concludes its season with a solo show that is the stage version of a beach read.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here it is halfway through April, and the slippery grip of winter hasn't quite relaxed its hold on the city. But New York Theater Workshop clearly is ready for summertime. This Off Broadway company, normally among the city's most adventurous, concludes its season with a solo show that is the stage version of a beach read: John Fugelsang's stand-up memoir ''All the Wrong Reasons.''</p>
        <p>Directed by Pam MacKinnon, Mr. Fugelsang's show is subtitled ''A True Story of Neo-Nazis, Drug Smuggling and Undying Love,'' a breathless string of phrases that conjures images of rampaging skinheads, terrifying scrapes with the law and heart-wrenching partings. Its tabloid flash is meant satirically, I suspect. Amiable and ingratiating, like the handsome Mr. Fugelsang, and sprinkled with comic zingers, ''All the Wrong Reasons'' is anything but melodramatic. By beach-read standards, it's pretty tame.</p>
        <p>An actor, writer, comedian and sometime television personality (he was the host of ''America's Funniest Home Videos'' for a few seasons, but don't hold that against him), Mr. Fugelsang spritzes the audience with stand-up for the show's first minutes. Theme: religion. ''I have come to view Jesus the way I view Elvis,'' he says. ''I love the guy, but a lot of the fan clubs really freak me out.''</p>
        <p>Other theme: politics. ''I was working on a book I'm self-publishing this summer. It's a self-help book for the troops about George W. Bush. It's called 'He's Just Not That Into You.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fugelsang has nice timing, and the jokes are generally worthy of Jay Leno or David Letterman, but it's a relief when he settles into memoir mode. If New York Theater Workshop wants to get into the stand-up comedy business, it should begin serving cocktails.</p>
        <p>The monologue circles back to the promised subjects of neo-Nazis and drugs, but is essentially a half-wry, half-heartfelt story of family, faith and Catholic guilt. Mr. Fugelsang's parents met when she was a nun and he a Franciscan brother; both left their orders to marry. As the offspring of this duo, Mr. Fugelsang was naturally more than usually susceptible to emotional blackmail trimmed in theology.</p>
        <p>With his father dying of heart disease, Mr. Fugelsang's mother gently suggests that a wedding date might give him something to hang on for. Mr. Fugelsang had been living with his girlfriend for 11 years at that point. Would it kill him to buy her a ring and sanctify the union in the eyes of the Lord?</p>
        <p>Broke and unhappy, he resisted the maternal campaign, at least long enough for the show to take a detour into a previous parent-son conflict. This one was occasioned by an appearance on Bill Maher's ''Politically Incorrect,'' on which Mr. Fugelsang sparred with David Duke, the neo-Nazi of the subtitle. Mom and Dad were no fans of this politician, but was it necessary for John to make that joke about sodomy on national television?</p>
        <p>The drug-smuggling episode comes toward the close of this 100-minute evening. Mr. Fugelsang was bringing a small amount of marijuana back from California for an ailing friend and was nearly nabbed while visiting his parents in Florida en route to New York. Again, what would Mom and Dad say?</p>
        <p>''All the Wrong Reasons'' is a pleasant, often amusing compendium of Mr. Fugelsang's best anecdotes and jokes. The general theme is his struggle to please his family and keep his own skeptical conscience free of hypocritical concessions to religious orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>But the show is loosely assembled, saggy in bits and heavy on comic digressions, as when Mr. Fugelsang reimagines, in contemporary slang, God's testing of Abraham's faith. (''Take that brat out in the fields and whack him.'') Some are quite funny; others feel like padding.</p>
        <p>I was most intrigued by the love story of his parents, who wed at 34, having spent years in religious orders, and embarked on a new life together. ''It was a first love, and a second marriage for them both,'' as Mr. Fugelsang says. Without punch lines, their story would seem to warrant a show unto itself.</p>
        <p>All the Wrong Reasons  A True Story of Neo-Nazis, Drug Smuggling and Undying Love</p>
        <p>Written and performed by John Fugelsang; directed by Pam MacKinnon; sets and costumes by Kaye Voyce; lighting by Mark Barton; sound by Jeremy J. Lee; production stage manager, Odessa (Niki) Spruill; assistant stage manager, Richard A. Hodge. Presented by the New York Theater Workshop, James C. Nicola, artistic director; Lynn Moffat, managing director. At the New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, between Second Avenue and Bowery; (212) 239-6200. Running time: 1 hour, 40 minutes.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
