<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dropped Duke Charges Renew Hope in Georgia</title>
    <meta content="16rape" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/us/16rape.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Georgia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4DE113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dropped Duke Charges Renew Hope in Georgia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dropped Duke Charges Renew Hope in Georgia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When North Carolina's attorney general said last week that an overreaching prosecutor lacked the evidence to support charges of rape against three former Duke University lacrosse players, some in this neighboring state hoped that tremors from his pronouncement would help free a former star high school football player.</p>
        <p>But as Georgia's legislative session neared a close, the odds were against them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some people in Georgia hoped that the decision in the case against three former Duke University lacrosse players might help free a former star high school football player.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When North Carolina's attorney general said last week that an overreaching prosecutor lacked the evidence to support charges of rape against three former Duke University lacrosse players, some in this neighboring state hoped that tremors from his pronouncement would help free a former star high school football player.</p>
        <p>But as Georgia's legislative session neared a close, the odds were against them.</p>
        <p>The former football player, Genarlow Wilson, is serving 10 years without parole for having consensual oral sex with a 15-year-old girl at a New Year's Eve party, an offense that constituted aggravated child molesting even though he was 17 at the time.</p>
        <p>The mandatory sentence shocked even the jury that convicted him. State law has since been changed to make most consensual sex between teenagers a misdemeanor.</p>
        <p>But the courts have ruled that the new law does not apply to Mr. Wilson, and the district attorney in his case, David McDade of Douglas County, has opposed efforts this session to pass a law that would allow judges to review earlier cases and to revise sentences.</p>
        <p>''Six young men basically gang-raped a 17-year-old and had repeated sex acts with a 15-year-old,'' Mr. McDade, told Channel 11, the local NBC affiliate, in March. ''There's no member of the legislature that I think would condone that behavior.''</p>
        <p>But the jury in Mr. Wilson's case disagreed with Mr. McDade's depiction. After being repeatedly shown a home videotape of sex, drugs and alcohol at the New Year's Eve party in a hotel room in Douglas County, they acquitted Mr. Wilson of rape. The five other young men at the party have pleaded guilty to lesser charges. None have been convicted of rape.</p>
        <p>''This is the same thing that happened in the Duke rape case, where some prosecutor exaggerated the facts out of self-interest,'' said B. J. Bernstein, Mr. Wilson's lawyer. The attorney general in North Carolina, Roy A. Cooper, called the prosecutor there, Michael B. Nifong, a ''rogue.'' Ms. Bernstein has called on Georgia's attorney general, Thurbert E. Baker, to review the Wilson case and not to oppose a habeas corpus petition she filed last week.</p>
        <p>State Senator Emanuel D. Jones, a Democrat who sponsored the bill to help Mr. Wilson, now 21, said that the legislature's intent with the first law had been to help Mr. Wilson. Although the new bill had been approved by the Judiciary Committee, it was deliberately put near the end of a list of legislation that had to be taken up by a certain day in order to be considered by the House in this session, Mr. Jones said, a common tactic for avoiding votes on controversial issues.</p>
        <p>The Senate adjourned before taking up that bill and one that would have kept employers from forbidding workers to leave guns in their cars at work.</p>
        <p>The judicial review bill was opposed by the Senate president pro tem, Eric Johnson, a Republican. ''These predators violated the law,'' Mr. Johnson wrote in a column in The Atlanta Journal-Constitution. ''Police arrested them. District attorneys chose to prosecute them. Juries convicted them. The legislature should not second-guess the process.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson's column continued a back-and-forth between the courts and the legislature, with each essentially blaming the other for the young man's continued imprisonment. Mr. Wilson, who was also an honor student and homecoming king, has served more than two years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones said in a telephone interview on Friday that he had been prepared to amend the bill to address some of Mr. Johnson's concerns, including narrowing the number of cases that could be reviewed. There are 92 people in Georgia serving sentences for child molesting they committed when they and their victims were teenagers, Mr. Jones said, and under the bill it would have been up to judges to determine if the encounters were consensual and merited new sentences.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones said he was troubled by comments that legislators briefed by Mr. McDade had made about the case. ''Their comments are selective -- it's like they're trying to try this kid all over again,'' he said. ''The reason he isn't out of prison is because he's black.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McDade, a regular presence in the Capitol as a representative for Georgia's prosecutors, did not return a call to his office late Friday afternoon. But he spoke to The New York Times in December, when the Georgia Supreme Court declined to hear Mr. Wilson's appeal. He maintained that what happened in the hotel room was worse than supporters of Mr. Wilson had led the public to believe: ''This isn't just a case of consensual teenagers petting each other and their moms found out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McDade said that Mr. Wilson had been ill advised by people who ''have their own agenda,'' and who had encouraged him not to plead guilty to a lesser crime. But he acknowledged that the deals offered would have left Mr. Wilson a registered sex offender.</p>
        <p>He also objected to accusations that race played a role in Mr. Wilson's predicament. ''How can it be racist to prosecute for raping and attacking African-American victims?'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
