<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Embattled Sallie Mae to Be Sold For $25 Billion, Negotiators Say</title>
    <meta content="16deals" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/16deals.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840858"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bank of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SLM Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Flowers, J C, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Friedman Fleischer &amp; Lowe</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Jennifer 8</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sallie Mae</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bank of America Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EFDC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Embattled Sallie Mae to Be Sold For $25 Billion, Negotiators Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Negotiators Say Sallie Mae to Be Sold for $25 Billion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and JENNIFER 8. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; Lee, Jennifer 8</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sallie Mae, nation's largest education lender, reportedly agrees to be sold to JP Morgan Chase, Bank of America and two private equity firms for $25 billion, moving it into private control amid increasing turmoil for company; two private buyers, J C Flowers &amp; Co and Friedman Fleischer &amp; Lowe, will control 50.2 percent of SLM Corp, Sallie Mae's real name, while banks will own rest; under terms of deal, two banks will provide Sallie Mae with up to $200 billion of backup financing to guarantee company can continue making low-cost loans in event its access to capital becomes limited through federal government or private markets; buyers will pay $60 a share in cash, almost 50 percent premium over Sallie Mae's share price before news of merger became public; deal may be salvation for Sallie Mae at time when its business model has been under attack from several directions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sallie Mae agreed late last night to be sold to JP Morgan Chase, Bank of America and two private equity firms for $25 billion, people involved in the negotiations said.</p>
        <p>The deal would move the nation's largest education lender, officially known as the SLM Corporation, into private control amid increasing turmoil for the company. The deal is expected to be announced today, these people said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nation’s largest education lender agreed to be sold to JP Morgan Chase, Bank of America and two private equity firms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sallie Mae agreed late last night to be sold to JP Morgan Chase, Bank of America and two private equity firms for $25 billion, people involved in the negotiations said.</p>
        <p>The deal would move the nation's largest education lender, officially known as the SLM Corporation, into private control amid increasing turmoil for the company. The deal is expected to be announced today, these people said.</p>
        <p>The other two private buyers are New York-based firms which have until now have kept a relatively low profile: J.C. Flowers &amp; Company and Friedman Fleischer &amp; Lowe. Together, the two firms will control 50.2 percent of the company, while the banks will own the rest.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the agreement, the two banks are going to provide Sallie Mae with up to $200 billion of backup financing to guarantee that the company can continue to make low-cost loans in the event that its access to capital, whether through the federal government or through private markets, becomes limited.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the deal, they said, the buyers will pay $60 a share in cash, which represents almost a 50 percent premium over Sallie Mae's battered share price before news of a potential buyout was reported in The New York Times last week. The share price has surged nearly 15 percent on the prospect that the company could be bought out.</p>
        <p>For Sallie Mae, which originates nearly 23 percent of student loans, this deal may be a salvation at a time when its business model has been under attack from several directions. All the uncertainty has caused Sallie Mae's stock to plunge more than 20 percent over the last year, making it a takeover target.</p>
        <p>The purchase of Sallie Mae represents the increasing willingness of private equity firms to step into highly regulated and scrutinized industries as they clamor for larger deals. Earlier this year, TXU, the largest power producer in Texas, agreed to be sold to a group of private equity firms in a deal valued at $45 billion. That deal, which faces significant government hurdles in Texas, is seen a test for how traditionally free-wheeling private equity firms are able to maneuver the tight corners of government regulation. The purchase of Sallie Mae is likely to raise similar scrutiny from legislators and consumer advocacy groups.</p>
        <p>Sallie Mae is both a lender and a debt collector, making profits on both sides of its loans. Last year, the company earned $1.2 billion and generated a lot of cash that makes it attractive to private equity buyers. Even so, some Wall Street analysts believe that it is a poor candidate to be saddled with debt because its business relies on razor-thin interest margins and the use of derivatives to manage its exposure to interest-rate swings.</p>
        <p>The private equity firms are essentially placing a bet that the legislative debates will ultimately fall in Sallie Mae's favor, even if the outcome is likely to mean reduced federal subsidies. The theory is that Sallie Mae's larger scale and lower operating costs will still give it an advantage over its competitors. Currently, the company is carrying $142 billion in private and guaranteed loans on its books, about 27 percent of American student loans in the United States.</p>
        <p>While 85 percent of its business is currently federally guaranteed, the company could also shift into the higher-interest and faster-growing market for private loans, which unlike guaranteed loans, is not subsidized by the government.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
