<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting the C.E.O. Treatment: INFORMATION, PLEASE; Diversions for the Jet Set</title>
    <meta content="16tech" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business Travel" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16tech.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting the C.E.O. Treatment: INFORMATION, PLEASE; Diversions for the Jet Set</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Diversions for the Jet Set</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharkey, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU wouldn't know it from that distant blurry movie on your airline's old overhead screen, but a major revolution is going on with in-flight entertainment.</p>
        <p>Behind the revolt is a global surge in business-class and first-class flying, but so far it is mostly limited to foreign carriers who have money to buy state-of-the-art cabin amenities. These include systems that offer hundreds of on-demand movies that can play on individual seatbacks, on screens that pull up from armrests or even on portable monitors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The quality of entertainment is a factor in choosing an airline, and sophisticated distractions can make a long haul feel like the good life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU wouldn't know it from that distant blurry movie on your airline's old overhead screen, but a major revolution is going on with in-flight entertainment.</p>
        <p>Behind the revolt is a global surge in business-class and first-class flying, but so far it is mostly limited to foreign carriers who have money to buy state-of-the-art cabin amenities. These include systems that offer hundreds of on-demand movies that can play on individual seatbacks, on screens that pull up from armrests or even on portable monitors.</p>
        <p>While many financially pressed domestic carriers have been making do with entertainment technology that is more state of the '70s than state of the art, even that is changing. Some major domestic carriers are actually spending money, or planning to, on upgrading entertainment systems to attract the industry's most profitable segment -- business travelers.</p>
        <p>American Airlines, for example, is rushing to install new personal audiovisual entertainment devices in business-class cabins on its 58 Boeing 767-300 aircraft. These planes are primarily used for trans-Atlantic flights, where competition for business-class passengers is fierce and intensifying. But some are also used on transcontinental domestic flights, which are also competitive. The installation had been tied to an overall upgrade of the business-class cabins, including new seats that lie flat with niches to house the portable entertainment appliances, called Peas. But once customers got a taste of the new offering, American decided it could not wait.</p>
        <p>The entertainment units have 10.6-inch monitors and offer 14 feature films. IMS, the developer of the units, worked with major film studios to ensure quick accessibility to released movies. The devices also provide 15 hours of television and news programs, which are updated daily, as well as music CDs, games and even language courses. The programming is on-demand, meaning that a passenger can pause or rewind a selection. Next month, American's scheduled features include ''The Painted Veil,'' ''Children of Men,'' ''Bridge to Terabithia'' and ''Stomp the Yard.''</p>
        <p>''The customers liked the device so much that there wasn't a good reason to wait, other than that the new seat is designed to accommodate the unit,'' said Lauri Curtis, American's vice president for onboard service. ''We had to do a little bit of a workaround with the existing seats, and it's just not quite as cool as it will be. But we didn't want to wait till we were done with the seat rollout, just for the sake of cool.''</p>
        <p>American's push to get the system running reflects a growing awareness that at least for business-class and first-class travelers, the quality of entertainment is a factor in choosing an airline. ''We see the domestic space as absolutely a developing market,'' said Joseph Renton, the chief executive of IMS, a California technology company.</p>
        <p>In the domestic market, JetBlue Airways redefined in-flight entertainment when it began operating in 2000 with personal monitors installed in each seatback, offering dozens of channels of live television. Frontier Airlines also put in a DirecTV system. Delta Air Lines began offering in-seat, on-demand programming on the 757s formerly operated by its defunct subsidiary, Song, and has placed monitors in seatbacks on other long-haul planes.</p>
        <p>In general, however, the major innovations have come from foreign airlines with lucrative long routes, like Singapore Airlines, British Airways, Emirates, Virgin Atlantic and Cathay. Last year, British Airways upgraded its Club World business-class cabins with a system offering 100 on-demand films and television programs.</p>
        <p>Over all, ''Singapore, Emirates and the others are at the top of the heap,'' Mr. Renton of IMS said. ''The amount of money that Emirates spends a year on buying content has to be phenomenal. These airlines are way out at the edge.''</p>
        <p>Singapore Airlines, for example, recently upgraded its on-demand system to offer more than 1,000 programming choices in 23 languages in all three cabins in its long-haul fleet. ''Because we're flying these ultralong-haul routes, we have to give you more of a sense of control, which means more options,'' said James Boyd, a Singapore spokesman.</p>
        <p>Singapore's seat units are also individual computers with the capacity to interact with personal electronic devices like BlackBerries. ''People are increasingly traveling without their laptops, and carrying BlackBerries and other devices,'' he said. ''If you're going to, say, Singapore to do a presentation, it's obviously hard to handle that with a BlackBerry. What we've done is equip the unit with U.S.B. drives, and for the first time a suite of office applications -- word processing, a spreadsheet, presentation software. You can download your presentation onto a thumb drive at your office, bring the thumb drive on board and plug in to create or modify the presentation using the 23-inch monitor and a keyboard on the control unit.''</p>
        <p>At Lufthansa, in-seat screens with audiovisual on-demand programming will soon be standard in all three classes of international service, said Reinhold Huber, the airline's head of product management and innovation. Lufthansa is putting seatback monitors in coach cabins on its long-haul fleet and refurbishing its business-class cabins. ''We are in the midst of developing, together with some partners, a new product that has all the communication technology on board, including Internet and mobile text messaging, and it will integrate with the audiovisual on-demand product,'' Mr. Huber said.</p>
        <p>With all this integration and innovation, airlines are also looking at ways to make money from the technologically sophisticated in-flight systems and their huge storage capacities.</p>
        <p>Most airlines remain wary of in-flight advertising and provide it only in small doses. But Virgin America, a new domestic airline that plans to start service this summer, has an entertainment system called Red that will incorporate marketing partnerships into the overall entertainment menu, which includes on-demand movies, TV programs, and even ways for passengers to ask, ''Are we almost there?''</p>
        <p>The Red system will offer interactive video aimed at business travelers who can choose to watch a detailed ad for products and services they are already interested in. One of Virgin America's first marketing partners is Land Rover.</p>
        <p>Kris Stevens, the chief executive of CoKinetic Systems, the technology company behind Red's software, said the ads would be incorporated into in-flight menus without being invasive.</p>
        <p>It may require investment in technology, he said, but it will be worth it. As to that familiar flap-down overhead screen, he said, ''the only thing you can do with that has to be done with a hammer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
