<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rope Climbing? Passé. Treasure Hunts? Cool.</title>
    <meta content="16active" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business Travel" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16active.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEETINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E2DD113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rope Climbing? Passé. Treasure Hunts? Cool.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New Kind of Business Conference Bonding</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY TRUCCO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Trucco, Terry</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CALL it the business conference bonbon, the afternoon activity in which colleagues bond, polish their team skills and kill a couple of hours after the day's heavy-duty meetings. For years, golf ruled, but golf is so 20th century.</p>
        <p>How about sending people on a treasure hunt instead? Is the meeting in Italy? Offer a pasta-making lesson. Participants work together, experience the local culture, learn a talent and can eat the results.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, colleagues bonded over golf, but golf is so 20th century. Now paint ball is cool.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CALL it the business conference bonbon, the afternoon activity in which colleagues bond, polish their team skills and kill a couple of hours after the day's heavy-duty meetings. For years, golf ruled, but golf is so 20th century.</p>
        <p>How about sending people on a treasure hunt instead? Is the meeting in Italy? Offer a pasta-making lesson. Participants work together, experience the local culture, learn a talent and can eat the results.</p>
        <p>Better yet, how about an afternoon assembling bicycles for kids? With a dash of philanthropy, the finished products are donated to charity.</p>
        <p>Everything gets a makeover eventually, even business conference downtime. In the last five years, more companies have bypassed mainstay activities like organized sports and rope courses in favor of less traditional events, often tied closely to the meeting's purpose. They are meant to promote active participation, impart new skills, offer a sense of surprise and entertain even the most jaded employees.</p>
        <p>The change comes partly from the increased financial accountability many companies are feeling, said Kurt Paben, vice president for business development at Carlson Marketing, a conference planner.</p>
        <p>''A good investment,'' he said, ''is seen as an event that moves the company towards its objective instead of a frivolous social activity.'' About a quarter of all the conferences Carlson plans include a nontraditional event, he said, ''and the trend is growing.''</p>
        <p>Since the Sept. 11 attacks, some companies have blended philanthropy with conference activities. ''If one of the goals is to promote camaraderie and team building, then bike building or working with Habitat for Humanity does all that and also gives back to the community,'' Mr. Paben said.</p>
        <p>The ideal is an event that swings both ways.</p>
        <p>For example, when Best Buy was introducing new digital video cameras, it held a training meeting, and invited families who had relatives overseas in the military to dinner at a hotel, Mr. Paben said.</p>
        <p>After dinner, people from the company showed the family members how to use the cameras. The businesspeople honed their demonstration skills, and the families created videos that were sent to their relatives stationed overseas.</p>
        <p>Sometimes business isn't on the agenda at all. ''Most conference organizers we deal with want something that entertains,'' said Nicholas Tommarello, president of Urban Interactive, a Boston company that organizes scavenger hunts with puzzles that lead to local landmarks.</p>
        <p>To play, a group of three to five players is given a mystery to solve and a cellphone to provide clues and guidance. As the players move through the city, actors appear with more clues. The group typically visits 10 sites to solve the riddle. In one game, players hunt down a John Singleton Copley portrait that has supposedly been stolen. The quest leads the players through Copley Plaza, the Prudential building and the Boston Public Library.</p>
        <p>Participants are kept on their toes by a blurring of fiction and reality. The actors in the game are not in obvious costume, so players often don't know if the vagrant offering advice is part of the drill or ''just some guy on the street,'' Mr. Tommarello said. Meanwhile, a facilitator evaluates leadership, team building, creativity and performance after the game.</p>
        <p>''If the activity is planned correctly, it's usually well received,'' Mr. Paben said of conference events. Planners keep in mind participants' ages and sex, but most of all, they watch the clock. ''Beyond two hours,'' Mr. Tommarello said, ''it's not much fun.''</p>
        <p>MEETINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
