<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israeli and Palestinian Leaders Open Regular Peace Talks</title>
    <meta content="16mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/16/world/middleeast/16mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Olmert, Ehud</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Abbas, Mahmoud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DC113FF935A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israeli and Palestinian Leaders Open Regular Peace Talks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Israeli and Palestinian Leaders Open Regular Peace Talks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL KERSHNER; Jennifer Medina contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershner, Isabel</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Olmert of Israel and Mahmoud Abbas, the Palestinian president, met here on Sunday, resulting in some mixed messages regarding a resumption of their long-dormant peace efforts.</p>
        <p>The meeting was the first of a series of biweekly sessions, agreed to by Mr. Olmert and Mr. Abbas during the last visit to the region by Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice. Israeli officials, in describing the meeting, emphasized the aspects that dealt with immediate, practical issues, while the Palestinian chief negotiator, Saeb Erekat, highlighted the part that he said focused on finding a far-reaching political solution to the conflict.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first of a series of meetings resulted in mixed messages about the resumption of the long-dormant peace process.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Olmert of Israel and Mahmoud Abbas, the Palestinian president, met here on Sunday, resulting in some mixed messages regarding a resumption of their long-dormant peace efforts.</p>
        <p>The meeting was the first of a series of biweekly sessions, agreed to by Mr. Olmert and Mr. Abbas during the last visit to the region by Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice. Israeli officials, in describing the meeting, emphasized the aspects that dealt with immediate, practical issues, while the Palestinian chief negotiator, Saeb Erekat, highlighted the part that he said focused on finding a far-reaching political solution to the conflict.</p>
        <p>The first half of the two-hour meeting dealt with security, the easing of restrictions on the movement of Palestinian people and goods, and macroeconomic issues, Israeli and Palestinian officials said. Israel's foreign minister, Tzipi Livni, and defense minister, Amir Peretz, also attended those talks. The Palestinian delegation included Mr. Erekat; Rafik al-Husseini, a senior aide to Mr. Abbas; and his economic adviser, Muhammad Mustafa. During the second hour, Mr. Olmert and Mr. Abbas met in private.</p>
        <p>Miri Eisin, a spokeswoman for Mr. Olmert, said Israel had agreed to keep the Karni commercial crossing between the Gaza Strip and Israel open until 11 every night, instead of 7 p.m., and to keep the Rafah passenger crossing between Gaza and Egypt, which has been closed for long periods, open ''for several days every week.'' She added that the mandate of the European monitors at the border was renewed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abbas presented a plan for reconstructing the Palestinian security forces and for building up his office's elite Presidential Guard, which the Israelis said was based on the recommendations by Gen. Keith Dayton, the American security coordinator to the Palestinians. Ms. Eisin also said that the sides discussed ways to contend with the continuing rocket fire from Gaza into Israel, and weapons smuggling across the Egyptian border into Gaza.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials had stated before the meeting that core ''final status'' issues of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, like borders, the future of Jerusalem and the fate of millions of Palestinian refugees, would not be on the agenda. Ms. Eisin specified that no final status issues had been addressed in the first hour, and gave no details about the second hour.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Erekat said in a telephone interview that the second hour was the ''most significant,'' and focused on ''the political horizon -- how to probe the possibility of implementing President Bush's vision for a two-state solution, and how to get there.'' It was the first time since January 2001, he said, that an Israeli prime minister and a Palestinian president had addressed fundamental issues.</p>
        <p>The two sides have agreed to meet in two weeks in the West Bank city of Jericho.</p>
        <p>Earlier on Sunday, Mr. Olmert told the Israeli cabinet that Israel would make ''every effort to find a comprehensive solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.'' Israeli officials have also indicated that Israel would be willing to discuss an Arab peace initiative with a working committee of the Arab League, if invited.</p>
        <p>''Israel has never blacklisted the Arab League -- it was the other way around,'' said Mark Regev, a spokesman for the Israeli Foreign Ministry.</p>
        <p>Israel rejected the Arab peace initiative when it was first raised in 2002. Based on a Saudi proposal, it calls for a full Israeli withdrawal to its pre-1967 boundaries in return for full relations with the Arab world. Mr. Olmert has said there are positive elements in the initiative and others that Israel finds unacceptable. In particular, Israel objects to a clause about the refugees, which it interprets as demanding the right of return for the refugees of 1948 and their descendants to their original homes in what is now Israel.</p>
        <p>Despite the positive signals, Israeli commentators remained skeptical about the potential for real, imminent progress. Mr. Olmert and Mr. Abbas are both in weak positions at home. Mr. Olmert is also said to be nervously awaiting the interim conclusions of a committee headed by a retired judge, Eliyahu Winograd, on the government's performance during last summer's war in Lebanon. The report is due at the end of April.</p>
        <p>''Nothing significant will happen before Winograd, and I think the Palestinians understand that,'' said Shlomo Brom, a retired general and senior researcher at the Institute for National Security Studies in Tel Aviv. But he noted a ''positive change'' in Israel's approach to the Arab initiative and said that if Mr. Olmert ''survives Winograd,'' everything could change.</p>
        <p>Also on Sunday, the Vatican's ambassador to Israel, Archbishop Antonio France, attended the Remembrance Day ceremony at the Holocaust Museum, reversing his earlier decision to skip the event in protest over the museum's depiction of Pope Pius XII as not doing enough to help stop the killings of Jews during World War II. The archbishop's office did not respond to a telephone call seeking comment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
