<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="15lilistingsLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDB123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Nassau and Suffolk Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to lical@nytimes.com, or by mail to Long Island Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>Comedy</p>
        <p>Levittown Jeff Dunham, stand-up and ventriloquism. April 15 at 6:15 and 8:45 p.m. $28 plus two drink minimum. Governor's Comedy Club, 90 A Division Avenue. (516) 731-3358.</p>
        <p>Westbury Bob Saget, stand-up. Friday at 8 p.m. $37.50. Kathy Griffin, stand-up. April 22 at 7 p.m. $41.50 to $51.50. North Fork Theater, 960 Brush Hollow Road. (516) 334-0800.</p>
        <p>Film</p>
        <p>Huntington ''The Healing Gardens of New York,'' a documentary directed by Alexandra Isles, guest speaker. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $12; members, $8; reservations recommended and includes reception. Cinema Arts Center, 423 Park Avenue. (631) 423-7611.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''The Heart of the Game,'' directed by Ward Serrill. Monday at 7 p.m. Charles B. Wang Center, Stony Brook University,. (631) 632-4400.</p>
        <p>Westhampton Beach Finest in World Cinema Series: ''The Italian,'' directed by Andrei Kravchuk, in Russian with English subtitles. April 15 at 1 p.m. and 4 p.m. $3 to $10. ''The Lives of Others,'' directed by Florian Henckel von Donnersmarck. Friday through April 22. Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center, 76 Main Street. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''A Children's Craft,'' create a ''Save the Whales'' banner. Ages 6 to 12. April 15 at 1 p.m. $7; members, $2.50; reservations required. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''Velveteen Rabbit,'' adapted from the story by Margery Williams. Through May 27. $8. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Beauty and the Beast,'' children's play followed by tea party. Saturdays through May 5. $8; $20 for show and tea party. BayWay Arts Center, 265 East Main Street. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Garden City ''Magical Musical Art.'' Explore the work of DeKooning and Duchamp and learn how music influenced their action paintings. Ages 6 to 12. April 15 at 12:30 and 2:30 p.m. $3 with museum admission, $2 for members. ''El Louie Show,'' presented by Louie Miranda. Ages 2 and up. April 14 and April 15 at 1 p.m. and 3 p.m. $5; $3 with museum admission. Long Island Children's Museum, 11 Davis Avenue. (516) 224-5800.</p>
        <p>Lindenhurst ''Aladdin,'' children's theater followed by a tea party. Saturdays through May 19. $8; $20 for show and tea party. Studio Theater, 141 South Wellwood Avenue. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Oyster Bay ''Reptiles.'' Learn about reptiles and create a craft. Ages 4 to 10. April 15 at 1:30 p.m. $8; members, $5. Theodore Roosevelt Sanctuary and Audubon Center, 134 Cove Road. (516) 922-3200.</p>
        <p>Patchogue ''Bam Percussion!'' Family program with comedy and drumming. April 15 at 3 p.m. $9. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Riverhead Arbor Day. Count tree rings, identify local trees and make leaf rubbings. April 15, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. $2; children, $5. ''Earth Day.'' Learn about environmental methods including recycling and alternative energy. April 22, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. $2; children, $5. Long Island Science Center, 11 West Main Street. (631) 208-8000.</p>
        <p>Smithtown ''World in a Bottle.'' Make a terrarium; bring two-liter bottle with screw top. All ages. April 15 at 1:30 p.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Caleb Smith State Park Preserve, Jericho Turnpike. (631) 265-1054.</p>
        <p>Westhampton Beach ''Amelia Earhart: First Lady of Flight,'' presented by the Seem-to-Be-Players of Kansas. Ages 7 to 13. Tuesday at 10 a.m. and 12:30 p.m. $8. Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center, 76 Main Street. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>Music and Dance</p>
        <p>Bay Shore Portland Taiko Drummers, Japanese drums. Friday at 8 p.m. $15. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>Brookville Vladimir Feltsman, piano; works by Beethoven and Mussorgsky. April 15 at 3 p.m. $45 to $90. C. W. Post Orchestra, conducted by Ching Juhl. Monday at 8:15 p.m. $8; seniors and students, $5. ''The River,'' ''Urban Folk Dance'' and other works, presented by Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater. Friday and April 21 at 8 p.m. $37 to $75. ''Revelations'' and ''Love Stories,'' presented by Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater. April 21 at 2 p.m. $22 and $35. The Shanghai Quartet; works by Schumann and Schubert. April 22 at 3 p.m. $40. Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, 720 Northern Boulevard, C. W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale Kittie with Walls of Jericho, In This Moment and others, hard rock. April 22 at 3 p.m. $15 and $17. Crazy Donkey, 1058 Route 110. (631) 753-1975.</p>
        <p>Hempstead ''Swing Into Spring!'' presented by Tavern on the Green All-Star Big Band with Lou Watson, Cynthia Crane and Laura Hull, guest vocalists. April 15 at 2 p.m. $10 to $18. Monroe Lecture Center Theater, California Avenue, Hofstra University, South Campus. (516) 463-6644.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Open Mic Jazz Jam.'' Individuals and jazz groups invited to perform. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Huntington Public Library, 338 Main Street. (631) 427-5165.</p>
        <p>Huntington The Jupiter String Quartet; works by Beethoven, Britten and Haydn; presented by Ridotto Concerts. April 15 at 4 p.m. $10 to $20. Old First Church, Route 25A. (631) 385-0373.</p>
        <p>Oceanside ''A World of Dance,'' presented by Dance Visions. April 15 at 2 p.m. Free; tickets required. Oceanside Library, 30 Davison Avenue. (516) 766-2360.</p>
        <p>Old Westbury Kate Beckman, vocalist. April 15 at 3 p.m. Free. Salten Hall, New York Institute of Technology, Old Westbury Campus, Northern Boulevard. (516) 686-7640.</p>
        <p>Oyster Bay ''Voices of Spring,'' presented by the Long Island Baroque Ensemble; works by Dowland, Marenzio and others. April 15 at 3 p.m. $20; seniors, $15; students; $10. Christ Episcopal Church, 61 East Main Street. (631) 724-7386.</p>
        <p>Patchogue ''Canta Libre,'' trio which blends the flute, harp and strings. April 22 at 3 p.m. $5. O'Connor Hall, St. Joseph's College, Suffolk Campus. (631) 447-7434.</p>
        <p>Patchogue Peter Tork and Shoe Suede Blues, Aura 3 and the Three Graces, rock. April 21 at 8 p.m. $25 to $35. The Nelson Riddle Orchestra. April 22 at 3 p.m. $25 to $40. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Sag Harbor Portland Taiko. Japanese drummers. April 22 at 11 a.m. and 1 p.m. $12. Bay Street Theater, Main and Bay Streets. (631) 725-9500.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''Music of the Carriage Era,'' performed by musicians from Stony Brook University. April 15 at 2 p.m. Free with admission: $7 for adults, $3 for students. Long Island Museum of American Art, History and Carriages, 1200 Route 25A. (631) 751-0066.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Hindemith's ''Alto Horn Sonata,'' Tan Dun's ''Snow in June for Cello and Percussion'' and other works, presented by Colin Carr, cello, Christina Dahl, piano, and others. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $32. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Classical Spring Chorale, featuring Rachel Schutz, soprano, and Deanna Muro, organ. April 22 at 4 p.m. $10 and $12. Stony Brook Community Church, 216 Christian Avenue. (631) 751-0574.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Rod Picott and Jory Nash, singer-songwriters. April 15 at 2 p.m. $15 to $20. University Cafe, Stony Brook Union Building, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-1093.</p>
        <p>Westbury Average White Band and Tower of Power, soul. Thursday at 8 p.m. $40 to $50. The Machine, tribute to Pink Floyd. April 21 at 8 p.m. $35. North Fork Theater, 960 Brush Hollow Road. (516) 334-0800.</p>
        <p>Outdoors</p>
        <p>Captree Island Historic Area Lighthouse Trek. April 21 at 8 a.m. $10; reservations required. Guided bird walk followed by lecture. April 22 at 10 a.m. $5; reservations required. Fire Island Lighthouse Preservation Society, 4640 Captree Island. (631) 661-4876.</p>
        <p>Cutchogue Winemaker's Walk, guided tour and wine tasting. April 21 at 1 p.m. $15. Castello di Borghese Vineyard, County Road 48 and Alvah's Lane. (631) 734-5111.</p>
        <p>Huntington Nature on the Move (Western Section), moderate adult nature hike along four-mile trail. April 15 at 10:30 a.m. $3; reservations required. ''Spring Seasonal Stroll,'' adult nature walk. April 22 at 1 p.m. $3; reservations required. Caumsett State Historic Park, 25 Lloyd Harbor Road. (631) 423-1770.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor Monica Randall, author of ''Mansions of the Gold Coast.'' Monday at 7 p.m. Free; registration required. Cold Spring Harbor Library, 95 Harbor Road. (631) 692-6820.</p>
        <p>Cutchogue Ann Marie Borghese, author of ''Great Tastes of Long Island.'' April 15 at 1 p.m. Free. Castello di Borghese Vineyard, County Road 48 and Alvah's Lane. (631) 734-5111.</p>
        <p>Garden City ''Last Child in the Woods: What Is Nature Deficit Disorder?'' Parenting workshop based on Richard Louv's book. Tuesday, 6:30 p.m. to 8 p.m. $10 and $12. Long Island Children's Museum, 11 Davis Avenue. (516) 224-5800.</p>
        <p>Garden City ''Bearing Witness,'' a lecture presented by Robert Mosley, author. Monday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Ruth S. Harley University Center , 1 South Avenue, Adelphi University. (516) 877-4555.</p>
        <p>Hempstead Lorrie Moore, author of ''Like Life.'' Wednesday at 7 p.m. Free. Guthart Cultural Center Theater, Axinn Library, Hofstra University, South Campus. (516) 463-5410.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Old Time Baseball: Then and Now,'' lecture by Gary Monti, advisor for Bethpage Village's Old Time Baseball Program. April 15 at noon. $15; includes refreshment. David Conklin Farmhouse, 2 High Street. (631) 427-7045, Extension 401.</p>
        <p>Lawrence ''George Washington Didn't Sleep at Rock Hall and Other Tales of Long Island Travelers.'' Presentation about old Long Island by Prof. Natalie Naylor. April 22 at 1:30 p.m. Free. Rock Hall Museum, 199 Broadway. (516) 239-1157.</p>
        <p>Oceanside ''Art Words: The Poetry of Michelangelo.'' Bob Spiotto, actor, presents a one-man tribute to the artist. Wednesday at 2 p.m. Free, but tickets required. Oceanside Library, 30 Davison Avenue. (516) 766-2360.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''This Is Our Youth'' by Kenneth Lonergan. Through April 22. $18 to $22. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Lovers and Other Strangers,'' comedy by Renee Taylor and Joseph Bologna. Through April 22. $14 to $22. BayWay Arts Center, 265 East Main Street. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Lindenhurst ''Beau Jest,'' comedy by James Sherman, presented by BroadHollow Theater Company. Through April 15. $22; seniors, $20; children under 16, $14. Studio Theater, 141 South Wellwood Avenue. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Monteverdi's ''L'Orfeo,'' presented by the Stony Brook Opera and Stony Brook Baroque Ensemble. April 15 at 2 p.m. $20; seniors and students, $10. Shakespeare's ''As You Like It,'' Directed by Valeri Lantz-Gefroh. Wednesday through April 29. $7 and $12. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>Museums and Galleries</p>
        <p>Bellport ''Spring 2007 Exhibition,'' paintings by various artists. Through April 30. Free. Hours: Saturdays, 1 to 5 p.m. Ratio Gallery, 10 Bell Street. (631) 286-4020.</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''Toys, Kids and Boats,'' exhibition of children's toys from the whaling era. Through Aug. 31. $4; seniors and students, $3; children under 5, free. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.</p>
        <p>East Hampton ''Two Painters: Two Perspectives,'' landscape paintings by Eileen Dawn Skretch and Dru Frederick. April 15, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Ashawagh Hall, Springs Fireplace Road at Old Stone Highway. (516) 380-7032.</p>
        <p>East Hampton ''Early Spring Show,'' works by nine furniture makers. Through May 22. Free. Pritam and Eames, 29 Race Lane. (631) 324-7111.</p>
        <p>East Hampton Paintings and mixed media works by Peter Dayton, Robert Kelly, Rex Lau, Alan Shields and Kelly Spalding. Through April 30. Free. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. The Drawing Room, 16R Newtown Lane. (631) 324-5016.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Surface Impressions,'' works by artists exploring the idea of surface in canvas, sculpture and mixed media. Wednesday through June 3. Reception: April 15, 2 to 4 p.m. Donation: $3. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Islip Art Museum, 50 Irish Lane. (631) 224-5402.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Oaxacan Wood Carvings Show.'' Through April 15. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Adobe Artes, 26 Gerard Street. (631) 385-8410.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Unlikely Materials,'' works by various artists. Through April 28. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Alpan Gallery, 2 West Carver Street. (631) 423-4433.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Dolls, Trains and Other Toys,'' historical collection from the mid-1800s. Check dates. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. David Conklin Farmhouse, 2 High Street. (631) 427-7045, Extension 401.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Bebe Identity,'' photographs by Richard Gardner. Through April 29. Free. Hours: Fridays, 5 to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 9 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fotofoto Gallery, 372 New York Avenue. (631) 549-0448.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Long Island's Best: Young Artists at the Heckscher,'' works by high school students. April 21 through May 6. Reception: April 22, 5 to 7 p.m. $5; seniors, $3; children ages 5 to 12, $1; under 5, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 8:30 p.m. Heckscher Museum of Art, 2 Prime Avenue. (631) 351-3250.</p>
        <p>Melville ''Fresh Air,'' works by Sanford Forrester, Barbara Gruber, Donald Thiergard, and M. Ellen Winter. Through June 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 7 a.m. to 7 p.m. Art-trium, 25 Melville Park Road. (631) 271-8423.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''The Living Classroom: Now Present at this Moment,'' multimedia installations by Ahn Pil Yun. Through April 29. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Anthony Giordano Gallery, Dowling College, Idle Hour Boulevard. (631) 244-3016.</p>
        <p>Quogue ''Local Color,'' works by Carolyn Munoco Haines and Meryl Spiegel. Through April 30. Hours: Sundays and Mondays, noon to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Quogue Library Art Gallery, 90 Quogue Street. (631) 653-4224.</p>
        <p>Riverhead Caroline M. Bell and the Peconic Bay Impressionists. Through April 30. Suffolk County Historical Society, 300 West Main Street. (631) 727-2881.</p>
        <p>Rockville Centre Pen and pencil drawings of Victorian architecture by Erin McCauley. April 15 through June 3. Reception: April 15, 1 p.m. to 4 p.m. with refreshments. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Phillips House, 28 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 764-7459.</p>
        <p>Roslyn Harbor ''Rembrandt to Rosenquist: The Masters of Printmaking.'' Through May 13. Admission: $4 to $10; children under 5 and members, free. ''Twenty-First Century Prints,'' works by Elizabeth Peyton, John Currin and other contemporary printmakers. Through May 13. Admission: $4 to $10; children under 5 and members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4:45 p.m. Nassau County Museum of Art, 1 Museum Drive. (516) 484-9337.</p>
        <p>Sag Harbor ''Erotic Art Show,'' works by Alberta Elia, William Negron and others. Through May 24. Free. Hours: Mondays and Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 7 p.m. Winter Tree Gallery, 125 Main Street. (631) 725-0097.</p>
        <p>Southampton Works by Irene Zevon. Through April 30. Free. Hours: Daily, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Bravura Art and Objects, 22 Nugent Street. (631) 259-2605.</p>
        <p>Southampton ''Raymond Loewy: Designs for a Consumer Culture,'' works by the 20th-century industrial designer. Through May 27. $7; seniors and students, $5; children under 18, free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Parrish Art Museum, 25 Job's Lane. (631) 283-2118, Extension 32.</p>
        <p>St. James ''28th Annual Juried Photography Exhibition.'' Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Mills Pond House Gallery, 660 Route 25A. (631) 862-6575.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''Living the American Dream: Levittown and the Suburban Boom,'' exhibition exploring the history of suburbanization on Long Island. Through July 8. ''William Sidney Mount: The Eduation of an Artist,'' Mount paintings are paired with works that inspired them. Through Sept. 30. $7; seniors, $6; students, $3. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Long Island Museum of American Art, History and Carriages, 1200 Route 25A. (631) 751-0066.</p>
        <p>Uniondale ''Paper Tapestries,'' works made of woven paper by Sage Reynolds. Through April 30. Reception: April 15, 2 to 4 p.m. Free. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Fridays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Uniondale Public Library, 400 Uniondale Avenue. (516) 489-2220.</p>
        <p>West Hills Photographs by George Mallis. Through April 15. $3. Walt Whitman Birthplace State Historic Site and Interpretive Center, 246 Old Walt Whitman Road. (631) 427-5240.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Nassau and Suffolk Counties this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to lical@nytimes.com, or by mail to Long Island Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>Comedy</p>
        <p>Levittown Jeff Dunham, stand-up and ventriloquism. April 15 at 6:15 and 8:45 p.m. $28 plus two drink minimum. Governor's Comedy Club, 90 A Division Avenue. (516) 731-3358.</p>
        <p>Westbury Bob Saget, stand-up. Friday at 8 p.m. $37.50. Kathy Griffin, stand-up. April 22 at 7 p.m. $41.50 to $51.50. North Fork Theater, 960 Brush Hollow Road. (516) 334-0800.</p>
        <p>Film</p>
        <p>Huntington ''The Healing Gardens of New York,'' a documentary directed by Alexandra Isles, guest speaker. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $12; members, $8; reservations recommended and includes reception. Cinema Arts Center, 423 Park Avenue. (631) 423-7611.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''The Heart of the Game,'' directed by Ward Serrill. Monday at 7 p.m. Charles B. Wang Center, Stony Brook University,. (631) 632-4400.</p>
        <p>Westhampton Beach Finest in World Cinema Series: ''The Italian,'' directed by Andrei Kravchuk, in Russian with English subtitles. April 15 at 1 p.m. and 4 p.m. $3 to $10. ''The Lives of Others,'' directed by Florian Henckel von Donnersmarck. Friday through April 22. Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center, 76 Main Street. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''A Children's Craft,'' create a ''Save the Whales'' banner. Ages 6 to 12. April 15 at 1 p.m. $7; members, $2.50; reservations required. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''Velveteen Rabbit,'' adapted from the story by Margery Williams. Through May 27. $8. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Beauty and the Beast,'' children's play followed by tea party. Saturdays through May 5. $8; $20 for show and tea party. BayWay Arts Center, 265 East Main Street. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Garden City ''Magical Musical Art.'' Explore the work of DeKooning and Duchamp and learn how music influenced their action paintings. Ages 6 to 12. April 15 at 12:30 and 2:30 p.m. $3 with museum admission, $2 for members. ''El Louie Show,'' presented by Louie Miranda. Ages 2 and up. April 14 and April 15 at 1 p.m. and 3 p.m. $5; $3 with museum admission. Long Island Children's Museum, 11 Davis Avenue. (516) 224-5800.</p>
        <p>Lindenhurst ''Aladdin,'' children's theater followed by a tea party. Saturdays through May 19. $8; $20 for show and tea party. Studio Theater, 141 South Wellwood Avenue. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Oyster Bay ''Reptiles.'' Learn about reptiles and create a craft. Ages 4 to 10. April 15 at 1:30 p.m. $8; members, $5. Theodore Roosevelt Sanctuary and Audubon Center, 134 Cove Road. (516) 922-3200.</p>
        <p>Patchogue ''Bam Percussion!'' Family program with comedy and drumming. April 15 at 3 p.m. $9. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Riverhead Arbor Day. Count tree rings, identify local trees and make leaf rubbings. April 15, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. $2; children, $5. ''Earth Day.'' Learn about environmental methods including recycling and alternative energy. April 22, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. $2; children, $5. Long Island Science Center, 11 West Main Street. (631) 208-8000.</p>
        <p>Smithtown ''World in a Bottle.'' Make a terrarium; bring two-liter bottle with screw top. All ages. April 15 at 1:30 p.m. $3; children, $2; reservations required. Caleb Smith State Park Preserve, Jericho Turnpike. (631) 265-1054.</p>
        <p>Westhampton Beach ''Amelia Earhart: First Lady of Flight,'' presented by the Seem-to-Be-Players of Kansas. Ages 7 to 13. Tuesday at 10 a.m. and 12:30 p.m. $8. Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center, 76 Main Street. (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>Music and Dance</p>
        <p>Bay Shore Portland Taiko Drummers, Japanese drums. Friday at 8 p.m. $15. Boulton Center for the Performing Arts, 37 West Main Street. (631) 969-1101.</p>
        <p>Brookville Vladimir Feltsman, piano; works by Beethoven and Mussorgsky. April 15 at 3 p.m. $45 to $90. C. W. Post Orchestra, conducted by Ching Juhl. Monday at 8:15 p.m. $8; seniors and students, $5. ''The River,'' ''Urban Folk Dance'' and other works, presented by Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater. Friday and April 21 at 8 p.m. $37 to $75. ''Revelations'' and ''Love Stories,'' presented by Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater. April 21 at 2 p.m. $22 and $35. The Shanghai Quartet; works by Schumann and Schubert. April 22 at 3 p.m. $40. Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, 720 Northern Boulevard, C. W. Post Campus, Long Island University. (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale Kittie with Walls of Jericho, In This Moment and others, hard rock. April 22 at 3 p.m. $15 and $17. Crazy Donkey, 1058 Route 110. (631) 753-1975.</p>
        <p>Hempstead ''Swing Into Spring!'' presented by Tavern on the Green All-Star Big Band with Lou Watson, Cynthia Crane and Laura Hull, guest vocalists. April 15 at 2 p.m. $10 to $18. Monroe Lecture Center Theater, California Avenue, Hofstra University, South Campus. (516) 463-6644.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Open Mic Jazz Jam.'' Individuals and jazz groups invited to perform. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Huntington Public Library, 338 Main Street. (631) 427-5165.</p>
        <p>Huntington The Jupiter String Quartet; works by Beethoven, Britten and Haydn; presented by Ridotto Concerts. April 15 at 4 p.m. $10 to $20. Old First Church, Route 25A. (631) 385-0373.</p>
        <p>Oceanside ''A World of Dance,'' presented by Dance Visions. April 15 at 2 p.m. Free; tickets required. Oceanside Library, 30 Davison Avenue. (516) 766-2360.</p>
        <p>Old Westbury Kate Beckman, vocalist. April 15 at 3 p.m. Free. Salten Hall, New York Institute of Technology, Old Westbury Campus, Northern Boulevard. (516) 686-7640.</p>
        <p>Oyster Bay ''Voices of Spring,'' presented by the Long Island Baroque Ensemble; works by Dowland, Marenzio and others. April 15 at 3 p.m. $20; seniors, $15; students; $10. Christ Episcopal Church, 61 East Main Street. (631) 724-7386.</p>
        <p>Patchogue ''Canta Libre,'' trio which blends the flute, harp and strings. April 22 at 3 p.m. $5. O'Connor Hall, St. Joseph's College, Suffolk Campus. (631) 447-7434.</p>
        <p>Patchogue Peter Tork and Shoe Suede Blues, Aura 3 and the Three Graces, rock. April 21 at 8 p.m. $25 to $35. The Nelson Riddle Orchestra. April 22 at 3 p.m. $25 to $40. Patchogue Theater for the Performing Arts, 71 East Main Street. (631) 207-1313.</p>
        <p>Sag Harbor Portland Taiko. Japanese drummers. April 22 at 11 a.m. and 1 p.m. $12. Bay Street Theater, Main and Bay Streets. (631) 725-9500.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''Music of the Carriage Era,'' performed by musicians from Stony Brook University. April 15 at 2 p.m. Free with admission: $7 for adults, $3 for students. Long Island Museum of American Art, History and Carriages, 1200 Route 25A. (631) 751-0066.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Hindemith's ''Alto Horn Sonata,'' Tan Dun's ''Snow in June for Cello and Percussion'' and other works, presented by Colin Carr, cello, Christina Dahl, piano, and others. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $32. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Classical Spring Chorale, featuring Rachel Schutz, soprano, and Deanna Muro, organ. April 22 at 4 p.m. $10 and $12. Stony Brook Community Church, 216 Christian Avenue. (631) 751-0574.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Rod Picott and Jory Nash, singer-songwriters. April 15 at 2 p.m. $15 to $20. University Cafe, Stony Brook Union Building, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-1093.</p>
        <p>Westbury Average White Band and Tower of Power, soul. Thursday at 8 p.m. $40 to $50. The Machine, tribute to Pink Floyd. April 21 at 8 p.m. $35. North Fork Theater, 960 Brush Hollow Road. (516) 334-0800.</p>
        <p>Outdoors</p>
        <p>Captree Island Historic Area Lighthouse Trek. April 21 at 8 a.m. $10; reservations required. Guided bird walk followed by lecture. April 22 at 10 a.m. $5; reservations required. Fire Island Lighthouse Preservation Society, 4640 Captree Island. (631) 661-4876.</p>
        <p>Cutchogue Winemaker's Walk, guided tour and wine tasting. April 21 at 1 p.m. $15. Castello di Borghese Vineyard, County Road 48 and Alvah's Lane. (631) 734-5111.</p>
        <p>Huntington Nature on the Move (Western Section), moderate adult nature hike along four-mile trail. April 15 at 10:30 a.m. $3; reservations required. ''Spring Seasonal Stroll,'' adult nature walk. April 22 at 1 p.m. $3; reservations required. Caumsett State Historic Park, 25 Lloyd Harbor Road. (631) 423-1770.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor Monica Randall, author of ''Mansions of the Gold Coast.'' Monday at 7 p.m. Free; registration required. Cold Spring Harbor Library, 95 Harbor Road. (631) 692-6820.</p>
        <p>Cutchogue Ann Marie Borghese, author of ''Great Tastes of Long Island.'' April 15 at 1 p.m. Free. Castello di Borghese Vineyard, County Road 48 and Alvah's Lane. (631) 734-5111.</p>
        <p>Garden City ''Last Child in the Woods: What Is Nature Deficit Disorder?'' Parenting workshop based on Richard Louv's book. Tuesday, 6:30 p.m. to 8 p.m. $10 and $12. Long Island Children's Museum, 11 Davis Avenue. (516) 224-5800.</p>
        <p>Garden City ''Bearing Witness,'' a lecture presented by Robert Mosley, author. Monday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Ruth S. Harley University Center , 1 South Avenue, Adelphi University. (516) 877-4555.</p>
        <p>Hempstead Lorrie Moore, author of ''Like Life.'' Wednesday at 7 p.m. Free. Guthart Cultural Center Theater, Axinn Library, Hofstra University, South Campus. (516) 463-5410.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Old Time Baseball: Then and Now,'' lecture by Gary Monti, advisor for Bethpage Village's Old Time Baseball Program. April 15 at noon. $15; includes refreshment. David Conklin Farmhouse, 2 High Street. (631) 427-7045, Extension 401.</p>
        <p>Lawrence ''George Washington Didn't Sleep at Rock Hall and Other Tales of Long Island Travelers.'' Presentation about old Long Island by Prof. Natalie Naylor. April 22 at 1:30 p.m. Free. Rock Hall Museum, 199 Broadway. (516) 239-1157.</p>
        <p>Oceanside ''Art Words: The Poetry of Michelangelo.'' Bob Spiotto, actor, presents a one-man tribute to the artist. Wednesday at 2 p.m. Free, but tickets required. Oceanside Library, 30 Davison Avenue. (516) 766-2360.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale ''This Is Our Youth'' by Kenneth Lonergan. Through April 22. $18 to $22. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Lovers and Other Strangers,'' comedy by Renee Taylor and Joseph Bologna. Through April 22. $14 to $22. BayWay Arts Center, 265 East Main Street. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Lindenhurst ''Beau Jest,'' comedy by James Sherman, presented by BroadHollow Theater Company. Through April 15. $22; seniors, $20; children under 16, $14. Studio Theater, 141 South Wellwood Avenue. (631) 581-2700.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Monteverdi's ''L'Orfeo,'' presented by the Stony Brook Opera and Stony Brook Baroque Ensemble. April 15 at 2 p.m. $20; seniors and students, $10. Shakespeare's ''As You Like It,'' Directed by Valeri Lantz-Gefroh. Wednesday through April 29. $7 and $12. Staller Center for the Arts, Stony Brook University. (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>Museums and Galleries</p>
        <p>Bellport ''Spring 2007 Exhibition,'' paintings by various artists. Through April 30. Free. Hours: Saturdays, 1 to 5 p.m. Ratio Gallery, 10 Bell Street. (631) 286-4020.</p>
        <p>Cold Spring Harbor ''Toys, Kids and Boats,'' exhibition of children's toys from the whaling era. Through Aug. 31. $4; seniors and students, $3; children under 5, free. Whaling Museum, Route 25A. (631) 367-3418.</p>
        <p>East Hampton ''Two Painters: Two Perspectives,'' landscape paintings by Eileen Dawn Skretch and Dru Frederick. April 15, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Ashawagh Hall, Springs Fireplace Road at Old Stone Highway. (516) 380-7032.</p>
        <p>East Hampton ''Early Spring Show,'' works by nine furniture makers. Through May 22. Free. Pritam and Eames, 29 Race Lane. (631) 324-7111.</p>
        <p>East Hampton Paintings and mixed media works by Peter Dayton, Robert Kelly, Rex Lau, Alan Shields and Kelly Spalding. Through April 30. Free. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. The Drawing Room, 16R Newtown Lane. (631) 324-5016.</p>
        <p>East Islip ''Surface Impressions,'' works by artists exploring the idea of surface in canvas, sculpture and mixed media. Wednesday through June 3. Reception: April 15, 2 to 4 p.m. Donation: $3. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Islip Art Museum, 50 Irish Lane. (631) 224-5402.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Oaxacan Wood Carvings Show.'' Through April 15. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Adobe Artes, 26 Gerard Street. (631) 385-8410.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Unlikely Materials,'' works by various artists. Through April 28. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Alpan Gallery, 2 West Carver Street. (631) 423-4433.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Dolls, Trains and Other Toys,'' historical collection from the mid-1800s. Check dates. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. David Conklin Farmhouse, 2 High Street. (631) 427-7045, Extension 401.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Bebe Identity,'' photographs by Richard Gardner. Through April 29. Free. Hours: Fridays, 5 to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 9 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fotofoto Gallery, 372 New York Avenue. (631) 549-0448.</p>
        <p>Huntington ''Long Island's Best: Young Artists at the Heckscher,'' works by high school students. April 21 through May 6. Reception: April 22, 5 to 7 p.m. $5; seniors, $3; children ages 5 to 12, $1; under 5, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 8:30 p.m. Heckscher Museum of Art, 2 Prime Avenue. (631) 351-3250.</p>
        <p>Melville ''Fresh Air,'' works by Sanford Forrester, Barbara Gruber, Donald Thiergard, and M. Ellen Winter. Through June 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 7 a.m. to 7 p.m. Art-trium, 25 Melville Park Road. (631) 271-8423.</p>
        <p>Oakdale ''The Living Classroom: Now Present at this Moment,'' multimedia installations by Ahn Pil Yun. Through April 29. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Anthony Giordano Gallery, Dowling College, Idle Hour Boulevard. (631) 244-3016.</p>
        <p>Quogue ''Local Color,'' works by Carolyn Munoco Haines and Meryl Spiegel. Through April 30. Hours: Sundays and Mondays, noon to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Quogue Library Art Gallery, 90 Quogue Street. (631) 653-4224.</p>
        <p>Riverhead Caroline M. Bell and the Peconic Bay Impressionists. Through April 30. Suffolk County Historical Society, 300 West Main Street. (631) 727-2881.</p>
        <p>Rockville Centre Pen and pencil drawings of Victorian architecture by Erin McCauley. April 15 through June 3. Reception: April 15, 1 p.m. to 4 p.m. with refreshments. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Phillips House, 28 Hempstead Avenue. (516) 764-7459.</p>
        <p>Roslyn Harbor ''Rembrandt to Rosenquist: The Masters of Printmaking.'' Through May 13. Admission: $4 to $10; children under 5 and members, free. ''Twenty-First Century Prints,'' works by Elizabeth Peyton, John Currin and other contemporary printmakers. Through May 13. Admission: $4 to $10; children under 5 and members, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 4:45 p.m. Nassau County Museum of Art, 1 Museum Drive. (516) 484-9337.</p>
        <p>Sag Harbor ''Erotic Art Show,'' works by Alberta Elia, William Negron and others. Through May 24. Free. Hours: Mondays and Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 7 p.m. Winter Tree Gallery, 125 Main Street. (631) 725-0097.</p>
        <p>Southampton Works by Irene Zevon. Through April 30. Free. Hours: Daily, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Bravura Art and Objects, 22 Nugent Street. (631) 259-2605.</p>
        <p>Southampton ''Raymond Loewy: Designs for a Consumer Culture,'' works by the 20th-century industrial designer. Through May 27. $7; seniors and students, $5; children under 18, free. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Parrish Art Museum, 25 Job's Lane. (631) 283-2118, Extension 32.</p>
        <p>St. James ''28th Annual Juried Photography Exhibition.'' Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Mills Pond House Gallery, 660 Route 25A. (631) 862-6575.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook ''Living the American Dream: Levittown and the Suburban Boom,'' exhibition exploring the history of suburbanization on Long Island. Through July 8. ''William Sidney Mount: The Eduation of an Artist,'' Mount paintings are paired with works that inspired them. Through Sept. 30. $7; seniors, $6; students, $3. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Long Island Museum of American Art, History and Carriages, 1200 Route 25A. (631) 751-0066.</p>
        <p>Uniondale ''Paper Tapestries,'' works made of woven paper by Sage Reynolds. Through April 30. Reception: April 15, 2 to 4 p.m. Free. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 9 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Fridays, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Uniondale Public Library, 400 Uniondale Avenue. (516) 489-2220.</p>
        <p>West Hills Photographs by George Mallis. Through April 15. $3. Walt Whitman Birthplace State Historic Site and Interpretive Center, 246 Old Walt Whitman Road. (631) 427-5240.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
