<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chance to Have Olympics Is a Balm for a Troubled City</title>
    <meta content="15cities" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/othersports/15cities.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United States Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Daley, Richard M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chance to Have Olympics Is a Balm for a Troubled City</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chance to Have Olympics Is a Balm for a Troubled City</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC FERKENHOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ferkenhoff, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This city's image could use a little lift.</p>
        <p>Battered by scandal on many fronts, including the resignation this month of its top police official and the indictment of an aide close to Mayor Richard M. Daley, Chicago has needed some good news.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Olympic committee picked Chicago for its ability to “recreate a certain magic,” according to the committee’s international vice president, Bob Ctvrtlik.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This city's image could use a little lift.</p>
        <p>Battered by scandal on many fronts, including the resignation this month of its top police official and the indictment of an aide close to Mayor Richard M. Daley, Chicago has needed some good news.</p>
        <p>And that came, in large measure, on Saturday, when the United States Olympic Committee announced that Chicago had beat out Los Angeles in the United States bid to serve as host of the 2016 Summer Games.</p>
        <p>In making its choice, the committee ended a yearlong tug-of-war of money and ego that started with five cities, including Philadelphia, San Francisco and Houston, and granted Chicago a world stage perhaps bigger than any since the Columbian Exposition of 1893.</p>
        <p>''It's certainly as historic as that to be in the running,'' said Laurence Msall, president of the Civic Federation, which promotes Chicago to the world.</p>
        <p>''We hit a low point in 2000, when The Wall Street Journal said we -- not even Illinois -- was on the map of tech hot-spots in the country,'' Msall said. ''We've come a long way since then, and this reinforces that and says we're not only on the map, but a big point on it.''</p>
        <p>The Olympic committee selected Chicago for its ability to ''re-create a certain magic,'' according to Bob Ctvrtlik, chairman of the U.S.O.C.'s city evaluation committee, with its miles of lakefront, its record of guiding a rusty city through vast environmental initiatives and its economic success.</p>
        <p>Even if Chicago does not win the international competition, which is expected to be decided in October 2009, a huge push is already under way to polish Washington Park in the South Side. The neighborhood and its vast park would be the site of the main stadium for the Games, but it is largely distressed despite its proximity to the well-to-do Hyde Park neighborhood and the University of Chicago.</p>
        <p>Michael Dunbar, 47, who was at the park on Saturday, sounded almost ecstatic at the news of the committee's choice. Having just finished walking his dog through the park -- whose tennis courts are tattered and signs are marred by graffiti -- he voiced hope that the development of Washington Park would not push out too many residents as businesses move into empty lots and the wealthy make it home.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going anywhere,'' said Dunbar, who has been a driver for Pepsi for 30 years. ''This will be my space, and maybe the riffraff will go away.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Sure the rent will go up, the condos are already coming. But me, hopefully I can retire early and maybe take in some of these Games.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone was rooting. On WGN radio, the host of ''Sports Central'' said Chicago did not need the Summer Games -- and the ''congestion'' and ''headache'' they would bring -- to prove the city was world class. But for others, the Games would be an important step for the city. ''We might get to represent the United States, and I'm happy that we were chosen,'' said David Wildman, a 10-year-old from the South Side who was walking with his mother on Saturday. ''My dad says -- I don't know if he's right -- the world hates us, and we probably won't be chosen. But I think we will. We're a nice city.''</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
