<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Credit Unions: The Silent Source</title>
    <meta content="15mort" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/realestate/15mort.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MORTGAGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit Unions</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tedeschi, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DC133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Credit Unions: The Silent Source</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Credit Unions: The Silent Source</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB TEDESCHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tedeschi, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mortgages column on offerings from credit unions, particularly low-interest Home Loan Payment Relief mortgages, intended for borrowers with household incomes at or below their area's median income (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS a result of the subprime lending crisis, even borrowers with good credit are struggling to find lenders willing to give them mortgages. Those with less-than-stellar credit scores face even more difficult times.</p>
        <p>But if borrowers look in unexpected places, their efforts can yield pleasant returns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If borrowers with less-than-stellar credit scores look in unexpected places, their efforts can yield pleasant returns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS a result of the subprime lending crisis, even borrowers with good credit are struggling to find lenders willing to give them mortgages. Those with less-than-stellar credit scores face even more difficult times.</p>
        <p>But if borrowers look in unexpected places, their efforts can yield pleasant returns.</p>
        <p>Take credit unions, for example. These institutions, which are run as nonprofit cooperatives, typically do not have enough money to market their mortgage offerings, and their mortgages are not offered through outside brokers. So consumers often overlook some highly useful alternatives that credit unions offer.</p>
        <p>About 200 credit unions affiliated with the Credit Union National Association have offered a low-interest Home Loan Payment Relief mortgage since late 2005. The program is limited, with some exceptions, to borrowers with household incomes at or below their area's median income.</p>
        <p>In specific high-cost areas like New York and northern New Jersey, credit unions will make loans to people whose incomes exceed the median. In the New York City area, for example, those earning 165 percent of the median household income of $70,900 can qualify, so the loans are available to households earning $116,985 or less.</p>
        <p>The loans, available at seven New York credit unions and one each in New Jersey and Connecticut, carry initial interest rates one percentage point below those of mainstream lenders. Only credit union members may apply; joining usually requires a minimum deposit of $25 or so.</p>
        <p>The payment-relief loans are available with both fixed and adjustable rates. The rate for the 30-year payment-relief mortgage earlier this month was 5.25 percent, with the rate increasing to 6.25 percent after three years, regardless of how high rates have climbed in the interim.</p>
        <p>The adjustable-rate payment-relief loan works in a similar fashion. The introductory rate earlier this month stood at 5.25 percent. Those who qualify for the mortgage will retain that rate for three years, when the rate can increase by one percentage point per year, depending on short-term interest rate fluctuations.</p>
        <p>The adjustable-rate payment-relief loan has a lifetime interest rate cap five percentage points higher than the initial rate. More information, including a list of participating institutions, is at the Web site cuna.org/initiatives/hlpr/.</p>
        <p>Bill Hampel, the chief economist at the Credit Union National Association, said credit unions could make such loans because they were forsaking the profit that mainstream institutions make.</p>
        <p>''Since credit unions are nonprofit cooperatives, they don't have to pay federal income taxes or pay dividends to stockholders, so they can offer better deals,'' Mr. Hampel said. ''That's also why they don't have any incentive to talk someone into taking out a shaky loan.''</p>
        <p>Gianni and Christine Trivigno financed the house they bought in December in Babylon, on Long Island, with a credit-union mortgage. Mr. Trivigno said the couple's credit score was ''in the 640-650 range.'' At that level, lenders often charge higher interest rates than for those with higher scores.</p>
        <p>Through the Bethpage Federal Credit Union, Mr. Trivigno found an adjustable-rate payment-relief mortgage for a full percentage point lower than those offered by two banks and a mortgage broker.</p>
        <p>Compared with those other mortgages, Mr. Trivigno said, the credit union loan for his two-bedroom $352,000 house saved him $900 to $1,200 in his monthly payments, and closing costs were also lower.</p>
        <p>''It was a really great experience all around, because it wasn't like they were trying to get us into a loan that might not be good for us,'' Mr. Trivigno said. ''I don't know if I'd have known about it if I wasn't a credit union member. How would you know? It's not like they're putting ads in the newspaper every day.''</p>
        <p>MORTGAGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
