<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indian Point 3 Reactors To Stay Closed for Repairs</title>
    <meta content="15weweekWC-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buchanan (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Entergy Nuclear Northeast</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steets, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charkes, Juli Steadman</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indian Point 3 Reactors To Stay Closed for Repairs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULI S. CHARKES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Charkes, Juli Steadman</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Entergy spokesman Jim Steets says Indian Point 3 will remain closed for at least another two weeks as repairs are made to nuclear reactor's two transformers, which were damaged in April 6 fire (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Indian Point 3 will remain closed for at least another two weeks as repairs are made to the nuclear reactor's two transformers, which were damaged by a fire on April 6, according to Jim Steets, a spokesman for Entergy, the company that owns and operates the plant in Buchanan. Mr. Steets said that the fire was probably caused by a worn-out bushing -- a type of porcelain insulator -- located on top of the transformer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steets said one of the transformers will need to be replaced, having sustained considerable damage from the fire. He estimated the cost of a new transformer as $2 million to $3 million. The second transformer was ''slightly damaged'' and will not need to be replaced, according to Mr. Steets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Indian Point 3 will remain closed for at least another two weeks as repairs are made to the nuclear reactor's two transformers, which were damaged by a fire on April 6, according to Jim Steets, a spokesman for Entergy, the company that owns and operates the plant in Buchanan. Mr. Steets said that the fire was probably caused by a worn-out bushing -- a type of porcelain insulator -- located on top of the transformer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steets said one of the transformers will need to be replaced, having sustained considerable damage from the fire. He estimated the cost of a new transformer as $2 million to $3 million. The second transformer was ''slightly damaged'' and will not need to be replaced, according to Mr. Steets.</p>
        <p>The fire, which was quickly brought under control by an on-site fire brigade, was the second unplanned shutdown within a week for Indian Point 3 and the fourth shutdown since July 1. County officials said there was no release of radiation as a result of the fire.</p>
        <p>In response to the shutdown, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission downgraded the safety assessment of the plant from green to white, the second highest rating out of a possible four safety levels.</p>
        <p>''We have an oversight program in place, and once you cross the threshold of more than three unplanned shutdowns over 7,000 hours, you will automatically have a change in status,'' said Neil Sheehan, spokesman for the commission. He added that the commission was in the process of setting up an inspection of the plant sometime within the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>But opponents of Indian Point said they remained unsatisfied with the response and called for an independent inspection of the site, separate from that of the commission.</p>
        <p>''I don't consider the N.R.C.'s inspection to be an objective one,'' said Representative John Hall, a Democrat whose district includes parts of Westchester. ''They are in the business of promoting all nuclear energy plants.'' The congressman, who was the host of a forum in Beacon last Monday on wind power, the first in a planned series on alternative energy sources, said that he would continue to push for an independent inspection of Indian Point, particularly as Entergy is in the process of seeking renewal of their operating license.</p>
        <p>Testing of a new emergency siren system at Indian Point continued throughout the last few weeks in order to meet an April 15 deadline required by the N.R.C. Previous testing had indicated a failure of some of the sirens, a result that Mr. Steets said was not unusual when bringing a new system into service.</p>
        <p>''People were a little hasty to draw an opinion on the operability of this new system based on some of the testing we conducted,'' he said. ''With each round, we gather data and make progress. The fact that not all of the sirens were sounding throughout the course of routine testing is not indicative of a failure, and we fully expect to meet our deadline.''</p>
        <p>JULI S. CHARKES</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
