<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Odds Are He Will Live on Disc Tomorrow</title>
    <meta content="15cosg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/arts/television/15cosg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DVD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cosgrove, Vincent</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgoohan, Patrick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Danger Man (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">McGoohan, Patrick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0D7153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Odds Are He Will Live on Disc Tomorrow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Odds Are He Will Live on Disc Tomorrow</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT COSGROVE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cosgrove, Vincent</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>All 86 episodes of 1960s TV series Danger Man starring Patrick McGoohan, later called Secret Agent, have been released on DVD; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE James Bond, John Drake is tall and handsome. Beautiful women swarm him. He regularly uses his self-defense skills. And he circumnavigates the globe with the sophistication that the British secret service apparently grants its more esteemed -- and fictional -- operatives.</p>
        <p>Beyond those similarities, though, Drake is the anti-Bond. Where Bond routinely invokes his double-O license to kill, Drake, the hero of a '60s television show, abhors extreme violence and rarely packs a gun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A “secret agent” comparable to James Bond comes out of hiding in a new 18-DVD set.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE James Bond, John Drake is tall and handsome. Beautiful women swarm him. He regularly uses his self-defense skills. And he circumnavigates the globe with the sophistication that the British secret service apparently grants its more esteemed -- and fictional -- operatives.</p>
        <p>Beyond those similarities, though, Drake is the anti-Bond. Where Bond routinely invokes his double-O license to kill, Drake, the hero of a '60s television show, abhors extreme violence and rarely packs a gun.</p>
        <p>Nor does he bed any of the willing femme fatales who pop up in the exotic places his adventures take him. Bond famously drives a gadget-laden Aston Martin, while Drake tools around London in an Austin Cooper S, ancestor to today's Mini Cooper.</p>
        <p>As Patrick McGoohan, the gifted actor who played Drake, told The New York Times in 1966: ''Drake is moral. He's all business. Ladies might show an interest, for example, but he doesn't reciprocate.'' In a fight, Mr. McGoohan maintained, Drake would best Bond.</p>
        <p>Perhaps one day some software whiz will create a computer game pitting Bond against Drake. Until then fans will have to compare the Bond films to ''Secret Agent A K A Danger Man: The Complete Collection,'' the 86 episodes of Mr. McGoohan's series, recently gathered in an 18-DVD set.</p>
        <p>''Danger Man'' was the name of the 30-minute black-and-white series that had its debut in Britain in 1960. Drake works for NATO in these early episodes, accepting assignments usually triggered by the cold war: uncovering traitors, foiling assassinations, tracking microdots. His pursuits lead him to locales like Jamaica, Sofia, Baghdad, Hong Kong and most European capitals, all convincingly rendered by clever use of stock footage, evocative sets and the English countryside.</p>
        <p>Given the time constraints, the emphasis is on action, with supporting characters skillfully sketched by a telling comment here, a revealing look there. While Eric Ambler's shady, suspenseful world of intrigue seems an inspiration, there's also an occasional hint of Somerset Maugham and Graham Greene.</p>
        <p>''Danger Man'' ended after 39 episodes. (The series ran briefly on CBS in 1961.) Three years later the show was resurrected in an hourlong format. These episodes grant Drake more depth and the scriptwriters more time to flesh out characters and plotlines. Drake now works for M9, a branch of British intelligence.</p>
        <p>In America the series was retitled ''Secret Agent'' and again found a home on CBS. A lively theme sung by Johnny Rivers accompanied the opening credits. ( ''Secret Agent Man. They've given you a number and taken away your name.'')</p>
        <p>Drake remains a knight in lightly tarnished armor. He shows more surliness toward his superiors, at one point refusing an order to eliminate an opponent. Unlike Bond, who rarely went undercover, Drake lives in a nether world where his identity is almost never his own.</p>
        <p>After shooting two color episodes of what was to be the fourth season, Mr. McGoohan decided the series was running out of inspiration. He quit, a wise move since Bond's popularity finally crept into the series. In the last episode Drake pursues a secret organization in Japan, skulking around the villains' island lair like 007 in a low-budget version of ''You Only Live Twice.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McGoohan had another reason to leave. He had an idea for a show about a disgruntled intelligence officer who resigns, only to find himself kidnapped and taken to a mysterious place known as the Village. This was the premise for the enigmatic cult classic ''The Prisoner.''</p>
        <p>For decades fans of the two series have debated whether John Drake is No. 6, the prisoner. Certainly, there are resemblances. And in ''The Prisoner'' they really did give Mr. McGoohan's character a number while taking away his name.</p>
        <p>VINCENT COSGROVE</p>
        <p>DVD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
