<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's the One Thing Big Business and the Left Have In Common?</title>
    <meta content="15letters.t-2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohn, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">meacham, michael r</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fein, Oliver (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">rodberg, leonard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">butterfield, mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5DD123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's the One Thing Big Business and the Left Have In Common?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>April 1 article on growing corporate support for universal health care prompts letters from Michael R Meacham, Oliver Fein and Leonard Rodberg and Mike Butterfield</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jonathan Cohn's article (April 1) gives us reason to be optimistic, but lest we become prematurely giddy about the possibility that the left and right can unite in a common cause for universal health care, we need to remember there are 1,001 trapdoors in Congress through which any proposal may fall. And there will still be plenty of special-interest groups around to pull the levers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jonathan Cohn's article (April 1) gives us reason to be optimistic, but lest we become prematurely giddy about the possibility that the left and right can unite in a common cause for universal health care, we need to remember there are 1,001 trapdoors in Congress through which any proposal may fall. And there will still be plenty of special-interest groups around to pull the levers.</p>
        <p>What Cohn doesn't detail is the momentum in the states. While he references the proposal in California and the current law in Massachusetts, readers should note that Maine and Vermont have some form of universal coverage in place; and Illinois and Pennsylvania have proposals to expand coverage. Other states are developing proposals.</p>
        <p>For good or ill, the federalist system is still vibrant; the gridlock of the federal government, the ever-increasing challenge of costs in the health-care system and the contribution of the uninsured to that problem have led to significant potential remedies by the states. While this may create an even more inefficient system of care in the United States, it will reflect the old adage that health care, like politics, is local. And a large number of states will have systems in place before a federal solution can clear a committee.</p>
        <p>Michael R. Meacham</p>
        <p>Associate Professor</p>
        <p>Department of Health Policy</p>
        <p>and Administration</p>
        <p>The Pennsylvania State University</p>
        <p>University Park, Pa.</p>
        <p>Is this what our country has come to? Leading C.E.O.'s, despairing of their ability to limit rising health-care costs and unwilling to bear these costs themselves any longer, will now back legislation that would place every individual and family at the mercy of private insurance companies like UnitedHealth, Wellpoint and the other insurance giants. Do they think John and Jane Doe can achieve what Safeway and General Motors cannot, namely, affordable health care for all of us?</p>
        <p>Instead of moving backward to the time before there was employer-based or group health insurance, when people were on their own to get health care any way they could, we should be moving forward, recognizing that health care is a necessary public good that should be treated as a public responsibility. We should be expanding and improving the Medicare program, which we know provides reliable, cost-effective coverage and has been doing so for more than 40 years. Public Medicare-for-All, not private for-profit insurance, is the only path to a future that will truly provide access to health care for all Americans.</p>
        <p>Oliver Fein, M.D.</p>
        <p>New York</p>
        <p>Leonard Rodberg</p>
        <p>Flushing, N.Y.</p>
        <p>(The authors are, respectively, chairman and research director of the New York chapter of Physicians for a National Health Program)</p>
        <p>Toward the end of his article, Jonathan Cohn suggests that, under a single-payer system, the government would ''assume direct responsibility for providing most Americans with health care.'' Actually a single-payer system refers to government financing of health care, leaving the provision of services largely in the hands of independent providers. The differences between this and a state-operated system like Britain's National Health Service are vast, and the two should not be conflated. This is an elementary yet important point to make, given the dearth of informative coverage and the surfeit of criticism single-payer plans receive.</p>
        <p>Mike Butterfield</p>
        <p>Rochester, Minn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
