<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Terrorism Fronts | April 8-14</title>
    <meta content="15week" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070422T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDE103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Terrorism Fronts | April 8-14</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOROCCO</p>
        <p>The News -- Three terrorism suspects implicated in the bombing of an Internet cafe in Casablanca blew themselves up on Tuesday as the police closed in, and a fourth suspect was shot as he tried to detonate a bomb.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The police said its investigation into the March 11 cafe bombing, which killed the bomber and four others, led them to the four men and to a wider plot to attack the port in Casablanca, as well as the police and tourist sites. The bombing rattled the country, which in 2003 was hit by five suicide bombings that killed 45 people. The police responded then by arresting thousands of reputed militants, including some accused of conspiring with Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>The News -- The European Union is considering expanding the powers of Europol, its law enforcement agency, to enhance its ability to fight terrorism.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The proposals, taken up at a hearing of the European Parliament last week, would extend the agency's mandate to criminal issues that are not strictly related to organized crime, and grant it greater access to data on people under investigation. The hearing coincided with the release of a report by Europol, which said that more than 700 people were arrested for terrorism-related offenses in the union's 27 nations in 2006, with half of those arrests involving threats from Islamic extremists.</p>
        <p>ALGERIA</p>
        <p>The News -- Two bombs targeting the Algerian prime minister's office and a police station killed at least 33 people and injured more than 200 on Wednesday. Al Qaeda's wing in North Africa claimed responsibility.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The suicide attacks in Algiers, the capital, were the deadliest in more than a decade and followed warnings by officials in the United States and Europe that Algeria was becoming a center for terrorism that could threaten Europe and North America. The group claiming responsibility, Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb, is North Africa's most active terrorist group and seeks to establish an Islamic theocracy throughout the region.</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN</p>
        <p>The News -- With fears of a new Taliban offensive, officials from the United States and allied countries met in Canada to discuss a long-term strategy for Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The United States, with about 26,000 troops there, hopes to clear southern Afghan regions of fighters for the Taliban and Al Qaeda and follow with rapid investments in infrastructure in what is expected to be a long struggle to stabilize the country. Military officials were preparing for an offensive by Taliban and Al Qaeda forces that is likely to focus on hit-and-run attacks, suicide bombings and roadside explosives that have been used with such punishing effect in Iraq.</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN</p>
        <p>The News -- Pakistan's generals say they have reclaimed some control of tribal areas bordering Afghanistan from foreign militants aligned with Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- President Pervez Musharraf of Pakistan said the army had joined tribal leaders in the fighting and had killed nearly 300 militants, though other officials say the number was much lower. Pakistan has been under heavy pressure from the United States to clear the tribal areas of militants -- mainly Uzbeks and other Central Asians who have been waging an insurgency in Afghanistan. Officials acknowledged that hundreds of foreign militants remain, probably including Osama bin Laden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOROCCO</p>
        <p>The News -- Three terrorism suspects implicated in the bombing of an Internet cafe in Casablanca blew themselves up on Tuesday as the police closed in, and a fourth suspect was shot as he tried to detonate a bomb.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The police said its investigation into the March 11 cafe bombing, which killed the bomber and four others, led them to the four men and to a wider plot to attack the port in Casablanca, as well as the police and tourist sites. The bombing rattled the country, which in 2003 was hit by five suicide bombings that killed 45 people. The police responded then by arresting thousands of reputed militants, including some accused of conspiring with Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>The News -- The European Union is considering expanding the powers of Europol, its law enforcement agency, to enhance its ability to fight terrorism.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The proposals, taken up at a hearing of the European Parliament last week, would extend the agency's mandate to criminal issues that are not strictly related to organized crime, and grant it greater access to data on people under investigation. The hearing coincided with the release of a report by Europol, which said that more than 700 people were arrested for terrorism-related offenses in the union's 27 nations in 2006, with half of those arrests involving threats from Islamic extremists.</p>
        <p>ALGERIA</p>
        <p>The News -- Two bombs targeting the Algerian prime minister's office and a police station killed at least 33 people and injured more than 200 on Wednesday. Al Qaeda's wing in North Africa claimed responsibility.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The suicide attacks in Algiers, the capital, were the deadliest in more than a decade and followed warnings by officials in the United States and Europe that Algeria was becoming a center for terrorism that could threaten Europe and North America. The group claiming responsibility, Al Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb, is North Africa's most active terrorist group and seeks to establish an Islamic theocracy throughout the region.</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN</p>
        <p>The News -- With fears of a new Taliban offensive, officials from the United States and allied countries met in Canada to discuss a long-term strategy for Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- The United States, with about 26,000 troops there, hopes to clear southern Afghan regions of fighters for the Taliban and Al Qaeda and follow with rapid investments in infrastructure in what is expected to be a long struggle to stabilize the country. Military officials were preparing for an offensive by Taliban and Al Qaeda forces that is likely to focus on hit-and-run attacks, suicide bombings and roadside explosives that have been used with such punishing effect in Iraq.</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN</p>
        <p>The News -- Pakistan's generals say they have reclaimed some control of tribal areas bordering Afghanistan from foreign militants aligned with Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>Behind the News -- President Pervez Musharraf of Pakistan said the army had joined tribal leaders in the fighting and had killed nearly 300 militants, though other officials say the number was much lower. Pakistan has been under heavy pressure from the United States to clear the tribal areas of militants -- mainly Uzbeks and other Central Asians who have been waging an insurgency in Afghanistan. Officials acknowledged that hundreds of foreign militants remain, probably including Osama bin Laden.  THE WEEK</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 22, 2007, Sunday  A graphic last Sunday about developments in the war on terror reversed the pictures above two brief news reports. The photograph of a soldier standing with a rifle should have appeared with the report about a meeting of allied countries in Canada to discuss strategy for Afghanistan. The photograph of a soldier's face should have appeared with the report about an assertion by Pakistani generals that they had reclaimed some control of tribal areas bordering Afghanistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 22, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>A graphic last Sunday about developments in the war on terror reversed the pictures above two brief news reports. The photograph of a soldier standing with a rifle should have appeared with the report about a meeting of allied countries in Canada to discuss strategy for Afghanistan. The photograph of a soldier's face should have appeared with the report about an assertion by Pakistani generals that they had reclaimed some control of tribal areas bordering Afghanistan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
