<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baby on Board, and a Photography Business, Too</title>
    <meta content="15cameras" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/business/yourmoney/15cameras.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: EARNING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cameras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D6133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baby on Board, and a Photography Business, Too</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Baby on Board, and a Photography Business, Too</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HANNAH FAIRFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fairfield, Hannah</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER Natasha Cuevas's daughter, Dakotah, was born in 2003, she wanted to capture every moment of her babyhood on film. A year and many hundreds of prints later, Mrs. Cuevas decided that it was time to invest in the new high-end digital camera she had been coveting.</p>
        <p>The pictures were luminous -- so detailed that she could count Dakotah's long eyelashes in them. Soon, women in her moms group in Fort Myers, Fla., were asking if she could take pictures of their children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As digital single-lens-reflex cameras have become more affordable, more people  overwhelmingly women  are starting photography businesses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER Natasha Cuevas's daughter, Dakotah, was born in 2003, she wanted to capture every moment of her babyhood on film. A year and many hundreds of prints later, Mrs. Cuevas decided that it was time to invest in the new high-end digital camera she had been coveting.</p>
        <p>The pictures were luminous -- so detailed that she could count Dakotah's long eyelashes in them. Soon, women in her moms group in Fort Myers, Fla., were asking if she could take pictures of their children.</p>
        <p>''I realized that I could actually get paid doing what I loved -- photographing babies and newborns,'' she said. So when her daughter was 18 months old, Natasha Cuevas Photography was born.</p>
        <p>As digital single-lens-reflex cameras have become more affordable, more people -- overwhelmingly women, according to the Professional Photographers of America -- are starting photography businesses. They often begin as part-time ventures, sometimes on top of full-time employment elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Sales of digital cameras, especially the higher-end S.L.R.'s, have skyrocketed. High-resolution cameras with more than six megapixels are the fastest-growing segment of the camera industry, jumping to 36 percent of the market in 2006 from 21 percent in 2005, according to the Consumer Electronics Association.</p>
        <p>Almost all the buyers already own digital cameras, but the new S.L.R.'s, with their quick auto focus, lighter weight and cheaper-than-last-year price, prove too tempting.</p>
        <p>And buyers can use the money-making potential of their new businesses to justify their purchases. Acquiring a name for the business seems simple; many women just tack the word ''photography'' after their own names. Many have no need for a studio, because most of the pictures are shot in natural light outside, or at the client's home.</p>
        <p>Marketing is often by word of mouth. When Jodie Otte (of J. Otte Photography) started her full-time business two years ago, she printed business cards after every photo session, knowing that her clients would pass them along if the cards featured pictures of their own children.</p>
        <p>Other women have engineered portrait parties, where several families get together and the budding photographer snaps portraits of the children at play. If the parents like the results, they tell their friends and playgroups, and the photographer's phone starts ringing.</p>
        <p>The rise of photography start-ups is helping other businesses as well. BluDomain, a company that designs Web site templates specifically for photographers, introduces about 100 new sites for clients each month. For $800, a new photographer can have her portfolio designed as a flash-driven, fully editable site with proofing galleries and video.</p>
        <p>Laura Brophy (of Laura Brophy Photography) started her part-time business last year in Canandaigua, N.Y., with a Canon EOS 20D and a Web site from BigBlackBag.com, which cost her $25 a month. Now, with brisk business in high school senior portraits, thanks mostly to friends of her teenage children spreading the word on MySpace.com, she is upgrading to a BluDomain site this month.</p>
        <p>Although there are no figures tracking start-up photography businesses, Dana Groves, director of marketing and communications at the Professional Photographers of America, says the industry has expanded rapidly in recent years. In response, the association in 2004 created a retreat called ''Chicks Who Click;'' this June, about 250 women will meet at the event in the Bahamas.</p>
        <p>Some past participants, discussing the retreats on an online forum, have said that there was too much emphasis on photographing children. But tapping into the children's portrait market was exactly what Lauren Dawson (of Lauren Dawson Photography), who had a part-time photo business in Dallas for five years, wanted to do last fall when she moved to Boston with her husband. ''I heard the market was wide open for children's photographers, so I really wanted to get in with moms groups,'' Ms. Dawson said. ''Sometimes all you need is one person, that one person who knows everyone, to help you spread the word.''</p>
        <p>Because the overhead can be minimal -- some business cards and a lot of chatting on playgrounds -- and because many new photographers have either a full-time job or a husband with one, they can afford to charge less than professional photographers. The professionals, who assert that they offer better quality because of their experience and studio equipment, may charge from $50 to several hundred dollars for an 8-by-10-inch print.</p>
        <p>Some large studios and old-guard photographers are feeling undercut; the backlash is apparent on many photography message boards, where ''MWAC'' means Mom With a Camera.</p>
        <p>''It's the established portrait studio guy who is scared that moms are taking cool photographs and selling them for $10 for an 8-by-10,'' said Kirk Voclain, a portrait studio photographer in Louisiana who owns Pro4uM, a professional photographers message board that has been host for some battles between the old guard and moms new to the business.</p>
        <p>''The people who buy photographs are women,'' he said. ''A man only comes to my studio when a woman decides that she wants a picture of him. So if moms are driving all the photo sales, then it makes sense that all these new photographers armed with digital cameras are moms.''</p>
        <p>SETTING prices for children's portraits can be daunting for people who are just starting in the business. Some feel that building relationships with their clients is more important than immediate profit.</p>
        <p>The new crop of photographers also tends to shy away from shooting weddings, even though they are lucrative jobs. Many cite a lack of creativity in posed wedding portraits and the pressure to document every moment of the big day. These photographers prefer the informal, low-pressure setting of snapping pictures while babies sleep or teenagers preen.</p>
        <p>''The biggest challenge facing women in the industry is business education,'' said Ms. Groves of the Professional Photographers of America. ''They tend to see themselves as artists before small-business owners, so they don't set their prices or invest with profit in mind.''</p>
        <p>Many women try to fit photography around full-time jobs and full-time parenting.</p>
        <p>''Lots of mom-with-a-camera businesses fail because they try to do it around the edges,'' said Mrs. Brophy, who has a preschool-age daughter and two teenagers and works as director of external relations at the Warner School of the University of Rochester in addition to running her weekend photography business. ''Plus, women face a business dilemma when they have to ask their husbands if they can buy a new camera.''</p>
        <p>Unlike some women who have a casual relationship with the business side of photography, Mrs. Brophy has a marketing plan and has reinvested all her earnings in lenses, lights, backdrops for her home studio, brochures and her new BluDomain Web site. She also has her eye on a new Canon.</p>
        <p>As new digital cameras come to market, with lower prices and more features than last year's models, new photographers cannot help yearning for the latest versions. Still, many are quick to say that the photographer's eye matters much more than the camera, and that the ability to use technology and respond to light is what makes an image come to life.</p>
        <p>That is why they smile when some owners of fancy S.L.R.'s put their camera on automatic settings and then complain that their pictures look like ordinary snapshots, albeit with very high resolution.</p>
        <p>''Good photography is more about the photographer than the camera,'' said Ms. Dawson, who has just started her business in Boston. ''It's about making people comfortable and finding the emotion in their faces. The camera is just a tool.''</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: EARNING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
