<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Memoirs of a Geisha's Sister</title>
    <meta content="Harrison2.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/review/Harrison2.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kirino, Natsuo</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Grotesque (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1303" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Memoirs of a Geisha's Sister</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Memoirs of a Geisha’s Sister</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIE HARRISON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harrison, Sophie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GROTESQUE</p>
        <p>By Natsuo Kirino.</p>
        <p>Translated by Rebecca Copeland.</p>
        <p>467 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Natsuo Kirino’s novel, the narrator’s sister and a classmate both become prostitutes and are murdered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GROTESQUE</p>
        <p>By Natsuo Kirino.</p>
        <p>Translated by Rebecca Copeland.</p>
        <p>467 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $24.95.</p>
        <p>AMERICA likes to invent images of Japan that suit itself, as nations do when they're more formally than familiarly acquainted. Despite manga and Murakami, Kurosawa and Oe, our own images of the culture -- ''Memoirs of a Geisha,'' ''Lost in Translation'' -- still seem obsessed with the whimsical or the coy: cherry blossoms, overplayed politeness, schoolgirls in long socks.</p>
        <p>''Grotesque'' is full of schoolgirls in long socks but blanchingly free of cuteness, a combination we might call Uh-Oh Kitty. Natsuo Kirino started out as a romance novelist before turning to crime fiction, which seems to suit her rather better. She has written 4 story collections and 16 novels, of which this is the second to be translated into English. The first, ''Out,'' was the cheerful tale of a factory worker who colludes with co-workers to murder her husband; they cut him up and distribute pieces of him around Tokyo. In ''Grotesque,'' she dismembers the detective novel instead, hacking off suspense, glamour, mystery and horror to leave a disconcerting stump of a book that fulfills no conventional expectations. The crime part is straightforward enough: two middle-aged prostitutes have been found strangled in apartments in central Tokyo. But the novel greets these acts with a laconic ''So?'' and approaches the business of crime-solving with the eye-rolling ennui of a teenager asked to do the washing-up. The family of at least one of the victims couldn't care less. The detectives barely figure. One murder is left unsolved, and the perpetrator of the other confesses promptly and volubly and with an unseemly hint of pride, offering a touching account of an impoverished Chinese childhood that makes him briefly more sympathetic than his victim.</p>
        <p>The story is told by a nameless narrator, the dowdy older sister of one of the murdered women and a former schoolmate of the other. She patches together an account of all their lives, here and there including extracts from the other women's letters and journals -- at which points the plot gets denser rather than thicker, as Kirino flirts naughtily with the notion of prostitution as feminism. (''My armor during the day was a flowing cape; at night it became Superman's cape. By day a businesswoman; by night a whore. ... I was capable of using both my brains and my body to make money. Ha!'' -- a declaration that might have more philosophical heft if the prostitute who makes it weren't murdered shortly after.) The narrator's reminiscences promise an explanation that is never really forthcoming, dragging out the pleasurable deferral of the detective story until it chafes. We learn what has happened, and to whom, and what they all thought of one another (not much). But no one ever seems to really get to grips with why.</p>
        <p>As young women, the narrator, her sister Yuriko (who was outlandishly pretty) and their schoolmate Kazue (who was not) attended an elite Tokyo institution the narrator calls the ''Q High School for Young Women,'' where status was everything, and to be poor or ugly was bad news. The narrator lives with her grandfather in shabby government housing in an unfashionable part of the city. Worse, she's ''half,'' as she puts it -- her mother is Japanese; her father is a Swiss of Polish descent. Without beauty to smooth her way, banished from the ''in'' crowd, she settles for honing her malevolent otherness. In the icy biosphere of Q School the caste system is subtle and total. Everything from hem lengths to handbags is scrutinized: those long knee socks, needless to say, matter beyond reason. (Kazue embroiders one of hers with red thread ''to make it look like the Ralph Lauren logo,'' an act that nicely crisps up the narrator's already boundless scorn for her.) The school is sharply drawn and sadly convincing; but although the narrator is an insightful chronicler of the cruelties of young women, she remains a puzzlingly useless guide to her own psychology.</p>
        <p>Which matters, because the schoolgirls may be horrid but the narrator is worse. She hates everything, inside of school and out, with an intensity that is at first brilliant but becomes exhausting, like staring for too long at an unshaded lightbulb. She despises her mother (''a born loser'' and ''not particulary attractive even for a Japanese''), her father (''miserly''), the opposite sex (''I can't think of any creature more disgusting than a man'') and the way men and women interact (''the lengths stupid people will go to for love!''). Most of all, she tells us, she ''truly hated'' her sister, whom she calls ''diabolically beautiful.'' Yuriko's loveliness (''even her fingers were gorgeous'') is the blight of the narrator's life.</p>
        <p>What began as jealousy is sharpened and darkened by the narrator's genetic determinism. How can someone so extraordinary have possibly issued from such ho-hum parents? Yuriko, she concludes, is an anomaly, a ''monster.'' Trapped in the rigid mesh of school society, the narrator has become a kind of insane biologist, intent on classifying the people she meets into her own peculiar system: people are likened to trees, or to squirrels or -- somewhat awkwardly -- to gymnosperms, which a science teacher later helpfully explains are a type of plants whose seeds are formed in exposed ovaries: relying on wind dispersal for reproduction, they resemble the narrator in their separateness from the ordinary mess of sexual life. Looking at a diagram of the Burgess Shale, the narrator compares her beautiful sister to the Anomalocaris, an ancestor to the crustacean, ''one of those animals that devours all others.'' As for herself: ''Without a doubt I'd be the Hallucigenia, the thing that crawls through the mud of the ocean floor covered in seven sets of quills, looking for all the world like a hairbrush.''</p>
        <p>But this still doesn't seem enough to account for the narrator's enormous resentment. She greets the suicide of her mother and the death of her sister with a kind of elaborately extended shrug. ''Did I hate her murderer? No,'' she says, which makes him almost the only person she doesn't dislike.</p>
        <p>The murders themselves are dealt with only obliquely, through hearsay and court reports: the narrative concentrates instead on the victims' school days and their subsequent murky careers with a thoroughness that promises explanation but instead provides mere information. Yuriko's diaries document her transformation from teenage nymphomaniac to haggard streetwalker in the most matter-of-fact way; Kazue's journals detail her life as an office worker and prostitute, but again we're given little understanding of why her life took this turn.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Copeland's translation of this bitter tale is respectable, without ever quite dispelling the odd sensation that translated fiction can sometimes produce: that of reading a book with your gloves still on. There are some tonal difficulties, especially in the slang, which gets a little hokey in places, although it's hard to say if the fault lies with Copeland or Kirino, who is a few decades past her school days. I don't know if Tokyo prostitutes typically address their clients as ''Mister,'' but it's odd to hear beggars saying folksy things like ''She was a nice lady too. Real kind.'' The women's language is also uneven, their habitual cool factuality sometimes veering startlingly into B-movie melodrama: ''So why the hell had I been standing on the corner night after night?'' Kazue reflects at one point (a question we wouldn't mind seeing better answered, too). Occasionally, words and phrases jump out, suggesting some difficult concept in the original that isn't being captured. When the narrator contemplates a pair of lovers and observes that ''passion hovered in the air between them like a massive lump,'' we can only imagine what this could possibly have meant in Japanese. Although perhaps it meant just that. Love is not the narrator's strong point, after all.</p>
        <p>Sophie Harrison is a contributing editor at Granta.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Sophie Harrison is a contributing editor at Granta.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
