<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking The Hits For Your Team</title>
    <meta content="15hockey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/hockey/15hockey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E5D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking The Hits For Your Team</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Taking the Hits for Your Team</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF Z. KLEIN and KARL-ERIC REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Jeff Z; Reif, Karl-Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the maxims of hockey, both in the regular season and in the playoffs, is that to win a team must be physical and dish out punishment.</p>
        <p>But upon examination, that does not necessarily hold up. In Game 1 of their series against Atlanta, the Rangers were outhit, 24-10, according to the official scoresheet, yet won, 4-3. And in Game 1 of the San Jose-Nashville series, the Sharks were outhit, 31-18, yet prevailed in overtime, 5-4.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the truisms of hockey is that to win a team must be physical and dish out punishment. But upon examination, that truism does not necessarily hold up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the maxims of hockey, both in the regular season and in the playoffs, is that to win a team must be physical and dish out punishment.</p>
        <p>But upon examination, that does not necessarily hold up. In Game 1 of their series against Atlanta, the Rangers were outhit, 24-10, according to the official scoresheet, yet won, 4-3. And in Game 1 of the San Jose-Nashville series, the Sharks were outhit, 31-18, yet prevailed in overtime, 5-4.</p>
        <p>Dishing out punishment may be entirely beside the point when it comes to winning hockey games.</p>
        <p>One statistical hockey blog has found evidence that being outhit could actually help teams win. The blog On the Forecheck measured 2005-6 totals for N.H.L. teams in both hits for and hits against. It said that teams that were outhit tended to excel in the regular season and the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Detroit was outhit in 2005-6 by 11 percent, the 24th-worst rate in the league, but finished first. Carolina, also outhit by 11 percent, won the Stanley Cup. Buffalo, outhit by 16 percent, came one period from reaching the final. The team with the best hitting ratio, Boston (44 percent more hits given than received), finished 26th over all and missed the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The statistic is a highly subjective one; hits are credited far more often in some cities than in others. Still, the blog, written from Nolensville, Tenn., by Dirk Hoag, found that the statistical correlation between winning and being outhit in 2005-6 was a fairly significant minus-0.40 (minus-1 is a perfect correlation). In the just-concluded 2006-7 regular season, Hoag reported it dropped to a weaker but still suggestive minus-0.23.</p>
        <p>So as you watch the playoffs this spring, bear in mind that the team that accepts punishment to make a play tends to do better. Ask the 1983 Edmonton Oilers, who were inspired to greater things by a beaten-up Islanders team that had defeated them for the Stanley Cup. Or the battered but victorious 1999 Dallas Stars, or the always outhit Soviet teams of the '70s and '80s.</p>
        <p>Statistical Roundup</p>
        <p>The regular-season statistics are in for the unofficial categories discussed in this space in the past few months. Here's a look at the top three finishers in each of those categories.</p>
        <p>MINUTES PER POINT -- He not only led the N.H.L. in scoring -- the youngest player to take the scoring crown -- but Sidney Crosby was also the most productive offensive force on a minutes-per-point basis. He scored a point for every 13 minutes 40 seconds he was on the ice.</p>
        <p>1. Crosby, Pittsburgh, 13:40. 2. Joe Thornton, San Jose, 14:36. 3. Jason Spezza, Ottawa, 14:51.</p>
        <p>ADJUSTED PLUS -- Adjusted plus/minus corrects raw plus/minus statistics to reflect how well or poorly a player performed, relative to his team's overall plus/minus mark.</p>
        <p>1. Thomas Vanek, Buffalo, plus-34.6. 2. Daniel Alfredsson, Ottawa, plus-30.2. 3. Marek Malik, Rangers, plus-29.6.</p>
        <p>ADJUSTED MINUS 1. Andrej Meszaros, Ottawa, minus-26.8. 2. Sheldon Souray, Montreal, minus-22.2. 3. Vaclav Prospal, Tampa Bay; and Kirk Maltby, Detroit, minus-20.2.</p>
        <p>GOALIE PERSEVERANCE -- The perseverance index ranks goaltenders on the twin scales of efficiency and workload, in a formula combining save percentage and average number of shots faced. Chris Mason of Nashville, with a .925 save percentage while facing 31.9 shots per 60 minutes, won the perseverance title with a mark of 978.</p>
        <p>1. Mason, Nashville, .925, 31.9 shots, 978 perseverance. 2. Niklas Backstrom, Minnesota, .929, 27.7, 975. 3) Rick DiPietro, Islanders, .919, 31.7, 972.</p>
        <p>Issues Come and Go</p>
        <p>In the long winter dog days of every hockey season, issues and controversies arise that are completely forgotten once the playoffs arrive. Remember slew-footing? The outrage of the 1997-98 season, it prompted calls for harsh rules to deal with the practice of kicking the feet out from under a player -- and was quickly forgotten. All the more reason to revisit the important issues worth remembering from this season. The N.H.L.'s competition committee will probably be considering each of these over the summer.</p>
        <p>HEAD INJURIES -- An alarming number of concussions were sustained this season by players of every description -- from tough-guy enforcers to ethereal playmakers to goaltenders -- as the result of both clean and dirty hits, stand-up fights and sucker punches. The Ontario Hockey League, a major feeder system for the N.H.L., outlawed all hits to the head last season and put in a system of stiff penalties to deal with such incidents. Will the N.H.L. follow suit, and will it re-examine the battering-ram quality of shoulder pads and other protective gear?</p>
        <p>CONFUSING STANDINGS -- The current standings formula, 2 points for any kind of victory -- regulation, overtime or shootout -- and a bonus point for losing in overtime or a shootout, actually made the race for the last Western Conference playoff spot a near runaway. Under the less-confusing formula favored by many fans -- 3 points for a regulation win, 2 points for an overtime or shootout win and 1 point for an overtime or shootout loss -- the Western race would have been razor-close throughout the entire season.</p>
        <p>INSTIGATION RULES -- General managers have recommended allowing enforcers to instigate five fights before getting an automatic suspension, up from the current three, so they could more easily protect skilled players. But after the recommendation, several enforcers were involved in ugly incidents that resulted in serious injuries and embarrassed the league. Will the N.H.L. ease instigation rules -- and will it continue to look to general managers for advice?</p>
        <p>Tight Schedule</p>
        <p>The Rangers, the Devils and the Islanders are playing most of their first-round games at roughly the same times, and the N.H.L. has taken criticism for it. Frank Brown, the N.H.L.'s vice president for media relations, said in an e-mail message that the league had to fit 56 playoff games into 14 dates and tried to stagger the games of the three New York-area teams to make ''as fan friendly a schedule as possible.''</p>
        <p>But, he said, issues arose because N.B.A. games and other events were already scheduled in some of the buildings involved, and because teams refused to play on consecutive days or nights at certain points in a series. ''Based on those realities, there are times when the schedule gets affected,'' Brown said. ''When 3 of the 16 playoff teams compete within a 40-mile radius, the likelihood of conflicting game times or game dates is greater.''</p>
        <p>Over There</p>
        <p>Last Friday, Metallurg Magnitogorsk upset the reigning Russian and European champion, Ak Bars Kazan, in the deciding fifth game of the Superliga final. Apparently Magnitka did not miss Evgeni Malkin, who left the team for Pittsburgh last summer and whom Magnitka unsuccessfully sued in United States federal court in an attempt to retain him.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
