<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parsing the Truths About Visas for Tech Workers</title>
    <meta content="15view" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/business/yourmoney/15view.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic View</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Visas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Gates, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2D6133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1138" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parsing the Truths About Visas for Tech Workers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Parsing the Truths About Visas for Tech Workers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR; Anand Giridharadas contributed reporting from Mumbai, India.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lohr, Steve</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE United States has benefited immensely from its role as a magnet for the best and brightest workers from around the world, especially in innovative fields like high technology. Bill Gates, the chairman of Microsoft, sounded precisely that theme in Senate testimony last month when asked about the visa program for skilled workers, the H-1B.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said that these workers are ''uniquely talented'' and highly paid -- ''taking jobs that pay over $100,000 a year'' -- and that America should ''welcome as many of those people as we can get.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Requesting the coveted H-1B visa, from India to Silicon Valley.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE United States has benefited immensely from its role as a magnet for the best and brightest workers from around the world, especially in innovative fields like high technology. Bill Gates, the chairman of Microsoft, sounded precisely that theme in Senate testimony last month when asked about the visa program for skilled workers, the H-1B.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said that these workers are ''uniquely talented'' and highly paid -- ''taking jobs that pay over $100,000 a year'' -- and that America should ''welcome as many of those people as we can get.''</p>
        <p>But that is not how the H-1B visa program as a whole is working these days, according to an analysis by Ronil Hira, an assistant professor of public policy at the Rochester Institute of Technology. The median salary for new H-1B holders in the information technology industry is actually about $50,000, based on the most recent data filed by companies with the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services agency. That wage level, Mr. Hira says, is the same as starting salaries for graduating computer science majors with bachelor's degrees.</p>
        <p>Yet salaries, according to Mr. Hira, are only part of the story. He says that while Microsoft may be paying its H-1B visa holders well and recruiting people with hard-to-find talents, other companies have a different agenda. The H-1B visa program, Mr. Hira asserts, has become a vehicle for accelerating the pace of offshore outsourcing of computing work, sending more jobs abroad. Holders of H-1B visas, he says, do the on-site work of understanding a client's needs and specifications -- and then most of the software coding is done back in India.</p>
        <p>''Information technology offshore outsourcing has just swamped the H-1B program in recent years,'' he said. The list of the top 10 companies requesting H-1B visas in fiscal 2006, the most recent government data available, was dominated by Indian-based technology outsourcing companies like Infosys Technologies, Wipro Technologies and Tata Consultancy Services, and a few other companies that offer outsourced services and have sizable operations in India like Cognizant Technology Solutions, Accenture and Deloitte &amp; Touche, according to a paper last month by Mr. Hira, which was published by the Economic Policy Institute, a liberal research group.</p>
        <p>Over the years, the H-1B visa, which allows a person to work in the United States for three years and can be renewed for an additional three, has been used by many people as a steppingstone to becoming a permanent resident. Traditionally, about half of all H-1B holders eventually get green cards, immigration experts say.</p>
        <p>Yet the major outsourcing companies, while seeking thousands of H-1B visas, are asking for relative handfuls of green cards, according to government figures.</p>
        <p>The statistics marshaled by Mr. Hira are not absolutely conclusive. The reported company-by-company numbers are for H-1B visas requested, not granted, but that is because the government does not publish visa counts by company. Since the visas are granted on a first-come-first-served basis, it seems reasonable that the companies seeking the most visas would, proportionately, get the most.</p>
        <p>It is not just critics like Mr. Hira who point to the crucial role that the H-1B visa program plays in the fast-growing global outsourcing industry. ''It has become the outsourcing visa,'' said Kamal Nath, the commerce minister of India.</p>
        <p>But is that a bad thing? Many economists say that paving the way for more efficient global trade in technology services should be a policy goal, and that the American economy will be more competitive and create more jobs as a result. Technology services like software programming and maintenance, they say, are an ''input,'' in economic terms, in industries from banking to manufacturing.</p>
        <p>It used to be that all the parts in a car or a computer were made in a single country; now they are manufactured wherever it is most efficient. The same thing is happening in technology services. ''We're seeing this growing international division of labor in services just as we saw in manufacturing decades ago,'' said Aaditya Mattoo, an economist at the World Bank.</p>
        <p>Still, the issue behind the H-1B controversy is how a nation devises a policy to benefit from global trade in technology services while treating its own workers fairly. The proposals before Congress range from significantly expanding the visa quota to tightening rules to protect American workers.</p>
        <p>This month, the government announced that it had received more petitions for H-1B visas in one day than it could grant in the entire fiscal year that begins in October. It received 150,000 petitions; the current visa cap is 65,000. Technology lobbying groups declared that the immediate overflow demand for H-1B visas was proof of the skills shortage in the United States and the need for a sharply higher visa limit. But some immigration policy experts and economists say that this argument fails a simple test of economics. It is not surprising, they say, that global companies -- including I.B.M., Microsoft and Oracle -- that benefit from the H-1B program would like to see it enlarged. ''There is no labor market test, using technically sound criteria, to determine whether or not there is a shortage,'' said David M. Hart, an associate professor of public policy at George Mason University. The measures, Mr. Hart suggests, would include recent wage trends and unemployment rates in specific professions.</p>
        <p>Other suggested changes include phasing out caps but holding auctions for H-1B visas in, say, lots of 30,000. After the first auction, the bidding for the next batch would begin at the high end of the initial sale's prices. In 1994, a commission appointed by Congress recommended letting companies hire skilled foreign workers easily if the employers paid a $10,000-a-person fee that would go into a fund to train domestic workers. And there might be a limit on the number of visas that any one company can get.</p>
        <p>''How to match policies to people in this emerging global labor market is something we really haven't thought through yet,'' said B. Lindsay Lowell, director of policy studies at the Institute for the Study of International Migration at Georgetown University. The current system, he said, tends to depend too much on the companies and how they use the complicated work-visa program.</p>
        <p>Microsoft, it seems, is paying its H-1B holders quite well -- a median salary of $82,500 for new visa applicants, whose wages over the subsequent three to six years could well rise to about the $100,000 Mr. Gates mentioned. And in fiscal 2006, Microsoft applied for 1,181 green cards and 4,471 H-1B's, a ratio of more than 26 percent. For the leading Indian outsourcing companies, the ratio was less than 1 percent.</p>
        <p>''Microsoft may well be using the program to bring in the best and the brightest,'' Mr. Hira said. ''But it's definitely not representative of how the H-1B program is being used today.''</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
