<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sidewalk Sheds: How Long Is Too Long?</title>
    <meta content="15qa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Q &amp; A"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E4DC133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sidewalk Sheds: How Long Is Too Long?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. The building next to ours erected a sidewalk shed that partly extends in front of our building. It would not bother us were it not for the fact that it has been up since 2004 and no work has been done since it went up. The owner has dutifully renewed the permit for the shed with the New York City Buildings Department every year.</p>
        <p>Is the permit renewable by right? Can we protest the next renewal? We think that the work for which the shed was erected should have been completed a long time ago.</p>
        <p>A. Kate Lindquist, a spokeswoman for the Buildings Department, said a property owner has the right to leave a sidewalk shed up for as long as the permit allows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. The building next to ours erected a sidewalk shed that partly extends in front of our building. It would not bother us were it not for the fact that it has been up since 2004 and no work has been done since it went up. The owner has dutifully renewed the permit for the shed with the New York City Buildings Department every year.</p>
        <p>Is the permit renewable by right? Can we protest the next renewal? We think that the work for which the shed was erected should have been completed a long time ago.</p>
        <p>A. Kate Lindquist, a spokeswoman for the Buildings Department, said a property owner has the right to leave a sidewalk shed up for as long as the permit allows.</p>
        <p>''Generally speaking, a permit for a sidewalk shed expires one year after the date it is issued,'' Ms. Lindquist said, adding that when the permit expires, the owner can apply for a renewal.</p>
        <p>''Some applications to renew a shed permit are reviewed by the Department of Buildings,'' she said. ''In some cases, the applicant would have to submit a timetable for the completion of the work and the removal of the sidewalk shed.''</p>
        <p>So, she said, if the residents in the letter writer's building believe the shed next door has been up too long, they can voice their concerns with the Buildings Department.</p>
        <p>''Passers-by may wonder why a sidewalk shed is installed if they don't see construction work being conducted,'' Ms. Lindquist said. ''But it's important to remember that a shed may be required during work on the building's interior, work that might not be immediately visible from the street.''</p>
        <p>Can a Stabilized Apartment Be Rented at Market Rates?</p>
        <p>Q. I live in a three-bedroom rent-stabilized apartment. I currently pay about $800 a month. Can I sublet my apartment for the market rate (currently about $2,500) and pay a fee to the landlord?</p>
        <p>A. ''A rent-stabilized tenant is not permitted to charge more than the stabilized rent for an unfurnished sublet,'' said Steve Dobkin, a Manhattan lawyer who represents tenants. ''If the apartment is furnished, a 10 percent surcharge over the legal regulated rent is permitted.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dobkin said the courts have held that profiteering by tenants is an evictable offense. ''And be wary of an owner who consents to this arrangement,'' he said. ''Recent appellate decisions have held that an owner cannot waive his rights under the rent laws.''</p>
        <p>Even if the landlord doesn't attempt to enforce the laws against profiteering, Mr. Dobkin said, the subtenant can.</p>
        <p>''The subtenant can go into court and sue for treble damages plus attorney fees,'' he said. That means that the subtenant can demand as much as three times the amount of the overcharge.</p>
        <p>''The courts hate to see a tenant making a profit on a rent-regulated apartment,'' Mr. Dobkin said. ''And they always enforce the law very strictly.''</p>
        <p>JAY ROMANO</p>
        <p>Q &amp; A</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
