<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Magical Thinking</title>
    <meta content="Schmidt.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/review/Schmidt.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Story of the Cannibal Woman, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Magical Thinking</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Magical Thinking</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH SCHMIDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmidt, Elizabeth</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Story of the Cannibal Woman</p>
        <p>By Maryse Condé.</p>
        <p>Translated by Richard Philcox.</p>
        <p>311 pp. Atria Books. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After her longtime partner’s murder, a woman goes into business as a fortune-teller.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Story of the Cannibal Woman</p>
        <p>By Maryse Condé.</p>
        <p>Translated by Richard Philcox.</p>
        <p>311 pp. Atria Books. $24.</p>
        <p>Maryse Condé's latest novel, her 12th, is a highly, sometimes unbearably realistic psychological portrait of one woman's grief after the unsolved murder of her partner of 20 years. ''The Story of the Cannibal Woman'' opens three months after the crime, and Rosélie Thibaudin, a 50-year-old painter, still finds it hard to get out of bed. She can't sleep, or eat or paint, and is mired in a state of semi-wakeful numbness -- that ''hour of lead,'' when ''the feet, mechanical, go round,'' that Emily Dickinson wrote follows ''great pain.''</p>
        <p>Such a state, while well suited to a short lyric poem, challenges the progress we expect from a traditional narrative, and the book's essential question is outlined from the start: What happens when a woman who feels she can't get out of bed must get out of bed? What happens when a black, childless woman, from Guadeloupe originally, with no source of income, finds herself stranded in a rich white neighborhood in Cape Town?</p>
        <p>Rosélie's deceased lover, Stephen, a British scholar and professor of some renown, had never persuaded her to marry him (she thought his proposals too perfunctory). Now she has no legal right to his assets, save their Victorian house, bought in ''both their names, so nobody could evict her.'' Without Stephen as buffer, she's at the mercy of her scandalized neighbors: ''As far as they could remember, pre- or post-apartheid, the only blacks spotted this side of Table Mountain were domestics.''</p>
        <p>Condé uses flashbacks to tell of Rosélie's childhood in Guadeloupe, her parents' unhappy marriage, her unsuccessful attempt at studying law in Paris (where she gets picked up in a cafe by a reggae singer, taken back to his family compound in Africa and dumped when he becomes his country's minister of culture and marries one of the president's daughters). Rosélie reflects dejectedly on her peripatetic life with Stephen in New York, Japan and Cape Town and on her lack of development as an artist. As she views her past through the dark lens of her depression, the author demonstrates how one's entire sense of self gets swallowed up by trauma and its dislocating aftermath.</p>
        <p>Condé gives shape and depth to Rosélie's story by interrupting these flashbacks with tales featuring vivid and humorous supporting characters, who try to make Rosélie snap out of her languor and get on with her life. And Richard Philcox's translation ably conveys the contrast between Rosélie's flat, desultory reflections and the lively voices surrounding her.</p>
        <p>There's Dido, Rosélie's servant turned best friend, who bustles into Rosélie's room each morning, newspaper and sludgy coffee in hand. She wakes Rosélie up by reading accounts of the horrendous crimes that fill the local paper: ''A father had raped his daughter; a brother his younger sister; some intruders a chubby 8-month-old baby in its stroller. A man had slit his concubine's throat. Masked thieves had robbed four streets of houses.''</p>
        <p>Dido also comes up with an idea to make practical use of Rosélie's reputation as a clairvoyant and healer, drumming up clients, printing business cards and helping Rosélie dress for the role. Business booms. South Africa's public face of Truth and Reconciliation, Condé suggests, has driven discontent underground, engendering a host of menacing psychological disorders and an atmosphere ''of danger which could sweep down from anywhere.''</p>
        <p>The detective assigned to investigate Stephen's case doesn't believe he was a victim of one of the random acts of violence that fill the papers, and he urges Rosélie to take an active role in the investigation. Here, Condé plays with two opposed fictional modes -- the fragmented inner monologue and the psychological thriller. And the novel's greatest pleasure comes from the author's defiance of narrative expectation. Rosélie does, reluctantly, begin to ask questions and, in fact, uncovers key evidence that leads to solving Stephen's murder. But action alone will not liberate her from depression.</p>
        <p>More important to Rosélie's recovery are the doubts that arise as she reviews what she'd believed was an essentially happy relationship with Stephen: old friends who insisted that he wasn't good for her, times when he disappeared without warning, the way his paternalistic encouragement of her painting and even his financial support undermined her autonomy as an artist, and how their particular dynamic as a mixed-race couple distanced her from understanding and experiencing the South Africa in which they lived. What helps her finally move through her wall of grief is not finding out who pulled the trigger, but her deeper awareness of the undercurrent of repressed rage leading up to the act.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Schmidt, a contributing editor at the literary magazine Open City, is working on a book about the American poets laureate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Schmidt, a contributing editor at the literary magazine Open City, is working on a book about the American poets laureate.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
