<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>America's Cup Draws Haves and the Have-Yachts</title>
    <meta content="15cup" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/othersports/15cup.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840619"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YACHTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>America's Cup Draws Haves and the Have-Yachts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">America’s Cup Draws the Haves and the Have-Yachts to Spain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The America's Cup has returned to the continent if not quite the time zone from whence it came, as can be confirmed by a long panoramic look at the huge amphitheater formed by the refurbished port in Valencia, Spain.</p>
        <p>Even when it was in American waters for more than 140 years, the Cup never had this grand a stage, and the question worth asking, with the challengers set to begin racing tomorrow, is if it is still America's cup at all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even when it was in American waters for more than 140 years, the America’s Cup never had this grand a stage, and the question worth asking is if it is still America’s cup at all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The America's Cup has returned to the continent if not quite the time zone from whence it came, as can be confirmed by a long panoramic look at the huge amphitheater formed by the refurbished port in Valencia, Spain.</p>
        <p>Even when it was in American waters for more than 140 years, the Cup never had this grand a stage, and the question worth asking, with the challengers set to begin racing tomorrow, is if it is still America's cup at all.</p>
        <p>The defender is the Swiss-based Alinghi, whose multinational roster reads like a staff list from a United Nations organization. Three of the 11 challengers are Italian, and for the first time there are syndicates from China, South Africa and Germany.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the American presence is shrinking. There are more sailors competing here from New Zealand, Italy and France than from the United States. The only American challenger, the powerful BMW Oracle Racing team, is proudly emphasizing its cosmopolitan character with its sailors wearing patches on their clothing that depict their own national flags, be they Danish, Japanese, Australian or, in the majority of cases, New Zealand.</p>
        <p>The flag flying most prominently from the team's remarkably well-appointed base during a visit last month was not an American flag but a BMW Oracle flag.</p>
        <p>''These aren't national teams; these are private sports teams,'' said Chris Dickson, the former enfant terrible from New Zealand who is now BMW Oracle's skipper and chief executive.</p>
        <p>But Dickson's boss is still American: the software impresario Larry Ellison, one of the world's wealthiest individuals, who intends to take the Cup to the San Francisco Bay Area if he succeeds. He failed in his first attempt, in 2003 in Auckland, New Zealand.</p>
        <p>That last campaign featured some quick shifts in management direction, with Ellison abandoning plans to drive the boat and Dickson being banished from the team at one stage before returning to the helm to lead the syndicate to the final of the Vuitton Cup, where it lost to Alinghi.</p>
        <p>Tommaso Chieffi, a tactician with Oracle in 2003 who is now sports director with South Africa's Shosholoza team, said that part of Oracle's problems was an excess of riches. ''We did too many experiments last time,'' Chieffi said. ''There is such a thing as having too much money.''</p>
        <p>There has been more stability this time with Dickson in place from the start in 2003. ''We figured out a direction, a clear direction, and we've had four and a half years to get on with it, so there hasn't been chopping and changing,'' Dickson said.</p>
        <p>Dickson said Ellison had been deeply involved and would be on board for much of the racing as part of the afterguard, the sailing term for the team's brain trust.</p>
        <p>The team's budget, estimated by some of its rivals at $200 million, dwarfs the opposition's resources, except for Alinghi. BMW Oracle is able to operate a racing team of 36 sailors -- more than two full 17-man crews. Such depth could prove useful in this more compact racing format. There are two sessions of round-robin races each day in the early stages and less than three months between the start of the challengers series, known as the Vuitton Cup, and the latest possible finish for the America's Cup in early July.</p>
        <p>BMW Oracle produced consistently strong results in the preliminary racing series. Those races, dubbed Acts, were staged in various American and European cities and were one of several major changes implemented for this Cup, which is the first in European waters since the competition began off the English coast in 1851 at the Isle of Wight with the schooner America trumping all British opposition in a fleet race.</p>
        <p>This will be the first Cup in the Mediterranean, the first in a country where English is not the primary language and the first in a country that is not the defender's. Landlocked Switzerland lacked the ocean access required by Cup rules. Alinghi took the opportunity to conduct an Olympic-style bidding process, which Valencia, spurred by the Spanish royal family's enthusiasm for yachting, won at no small cost over Marseille, France; Naples, Italy; and Lisbon.</p>
        <p>Michel Bonnefous, the head of America's Cup Management, said Valencia paid about $121.7 million for the right to stage the event, and nearly $1.35 billion more has been invested by the local and national governments in infrastructure linked to the Cup.</p>
        <p>The larger goal was to promote Valencia, even though most of the population would not know a racing yacht from a pleasure cruiser. While taxi drivers in Auckland would sometimes exchange opinions on sailing tactics with their clients during the last two Cups, that will not be happening in Spain.</p>
        <p>''Certainly not,'' said Peter Isler, BMW Oracle's navigator. ''Their reaction is, 'Copa de América?' But I sense there's a lot of pride in the community with the Cup being here.''</p>
        <p>Bonnefous is convinced that the best way to generate local enthusiasm is for the Spanish team, Desafio Español, to succeed. But the competition in the Vuitton Cup should be fierce this year, with the challenger field being cut from 11 to 4 by May 7.</p>
        <p>The Acts have allowed more teams the opportunity to improve, and the end of the nationality requirements has allowed more teams access to more talent. The fact that this is the fifth Cup in this class of boats also lengthens the odds of generating a big speed difference.</p>
        <p>''There is a point of diminishing returns,'' Isler said. ''So the difference between a first- and second-generation boat was maybe three or four minutes around the race course. Then it was two minutes. Then it was one and a half, and then maybe one minute last time. Now, it's maybe 30 seconds. The boats are going to be closer in speed, so that puts more importance on match-racing skills.''</p>
        <p>With Isler, Dickson and the Frenchman Bertrand Pace, BMW Oracle has acquired plenty. The question now is whether Ellison's team of all-stars will equal the sum of its expensive parts.</p>
        <p>YACHTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
