<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recipe Redux; 1939: Ceylon Curry of Oysters</title>
    <meta content="15food.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="65" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/magazine/15food.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Food: Recipe Redux"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Renaud, Cyril</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oysters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seafood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recipe Redux; 1939: Ceylon Curry of Oysters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">1939: Ceylon Curry of Oysters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Amanda Hesser</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recipe for Ceylon curry of oysters that appeared in Times in 1939 is reprinted with some minor alterations and also given complete makeover by Cyril Renaud, chef at Fleur de Sel; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just as Germany was preparing to invade Poland and America was wondering whether it would have to go to war, New Yorkers, according The Times, were dabbling in Indian cuisine, with new restaurants opening and hotels putting Indian dishes on their menus. As Charlotte Hughes, then a reporter for the paper, none-too-definitively declared, ''Everybody in India, apparently, eats curry.'' And although she noted that curries were complicated to prepare, ''nevertheless, American cooks with a pioneering spirit can master curry dishes.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the brink of the Second World War, New Yorkers opened their palates and kitchens to Indian cuisine; here, a recipe from East 57th Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just as Germany was preparing to invade Poland and America was wondering whether it would have to go to war, New Yorkers, according The Times, were dabbling in Indian cuisine, with new restaurants opening and hotels putting Indian dishes on their menus. As Charlotte Hughes, then a reporter for the paper, none-too-definitively declared, ''Everybody in India, apparently, eats curry.'' And although she noted that curries were complicated to prepare, ''nevertheless, American cooks with a pioneering spirit can master curry dishes.''</p>
        <p>And yet, 68 years later, we have not. But there is still time. A Ceylonese curry of oysters -- one of several vaguely composed recipes included in Hughes's article -- would be a fine place to start.</p>
        <p>First, a few disclaimers. Oyster curry, according to Andrew F. Smith, the author of ''The Oxford Companion to American Food and Drink,'' was a popular dish in the 19th century, particularly in England -- so popular that mixes for it were sold. By the time Hughes revisited it, the recipe was well established and westernized. Back then, food writers didn't often travel in order to better understand foreign cuisines, so some of the ingredients in Hughes's recipes were odd adaptations. In place of chilies, for instance, Hughes called for a green pepper, which would make for a meek derivative of a typically fiery Ceylonese curry.</p>
        <p>But even Hughes knew where to draw a line. Using good curry powder, however westernized, is imperative, she wrote, adding, ''One cannot just make a white sauce and stir in a little curry powder.''</p>
        <p>She got her recipe for the oyster curry from someone named Darmadasa at the East India Curry Shop on East 57th Street. The recipe begins with sautéing shallots, garlic and green pepper. Next it is seasoned with turmeric, curry powder, cinnamon, cloves and bay leaves and simmered in coconut milk. At the end, oysters and their liquor are slipped in, and the curry is seasoned with lemon juice. The whole process takes about 10 minutes, and the payoff lasts years, because you'll want to make it again and again.</p>
        <p>Hughes suggested serving the curry with rice. ''Dry, fluffy rice, each particle as separate from the next as a grain of sand on a sunbaked dune, is important to the excellence of a curry dish,'' she wrote. Everybody in India, apparently, also eats rice.</p>
        <p>Although the recipe has maintained its grace over the decades, I gave it to Cyril Renaud, the chef and owner of Fleur de Sel, who spent years at La Caravelle perfecting pike quenelles and other French fish dishes, to see how he would make it his own. He retooled the dish, refining what is a delicious but essentially lumpy sauce and separating the seasonings into discrete components. Out went the homely oysters. In came pristine fillets of wild striped bass, which were steamed with the cinnamon and cloves. The coconut milk became the cooking liquid for the rice. And the turmeric and curry powder were used to color and season an apple-banana chutney. It's about as Ceylonese as Darmadasa's curry, but does authenticity really matter when it comes to taste?</p>
        <p>1939: Ceylon Curry of Oysters</p>
        <p>This recipe appeared in The Times in an article by Charlotte Hughes. In Hughes's original recipe, she called for three bay leaves; I used only one. And since chilies are now commonly available, I used a serrano rather than the sweet green pepper that Hughes suggested.</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons butter or coconut oil</p>
        <p>4 small shallots, finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 clove garlic, minced</p>
        <p>1/2 serrano or Thai chili, seeded and minced</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon curry powder</p>
        <p>1 large pinch turmeric</p>
        <p>1 cinnamon stick</p>
        <p>3 cloves</p>
        <p>1 bay leaf</p>
        <p>1 cup coconut milk</p>
        <p>Salt</p>
        <p>12 oysters, shucked, liquor reserved</p>
        <p>Juice of 1/2 lemon.</p>
        <p>1. In a medium saucepan over medium heat, melt the butter. Add the shallots, garlic and chili, and sauté until softened and starting to brown, 2 to 3 minutes. Stir in the curry powder, turmeric, cinnamon stick, cloves and bay leaf and cook for 1 minute.</p>
        <p>2. Reduce heat to low and add the coconut milk and 1/2 teaspoon salt. Simmer for 3 minutes. Add the oysters and their liquor; simmer until the oysters are just firm, 3 to 4 minutes. Take the pan off the heat and add lemon juice and salt to taste. Serve over rice -- the rice in the fish recipe that follows would go well -- or on hoppers (see the recipe at nytimes.com/magazine). Serves 2.</p>
        <p>2007: Steamed Wild Striped Bass With Coconut Rice and Apple-Banana Chutney</p>
        <p>By Cyril Renaud, chef at Fleur de Sel in New York</p>
        <p>4 6-ounce pieces wild striped bass</p>
        <p>5 tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>Kosher salt and pepper</p>
        <p>4 cloves garlic, thinly sliced</p>
        <p>4 pinches ground cinnamon</p>
        <p>4 pinches ground cloves</p>
        <p>2 cups basmati rice</p>
        <p>4 cups rice milk</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons coconut cream (or coconut milk)</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons shredded unsweetened coconut</p>
        <p>2 bay leaves</p>
        <p>1/4 serrano chili, seeded and minced, more if desired</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons thinly sliced chives</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons butter</p>
        <p>1 small onion, finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon curry powder</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon turmeric</p>
        <p>2 cups diced (1/4 -inch) tart apple</p>
        <p>1/2 banana, diced (1/4 -inch).</p>
        <p>1. Cut 4 to 6 shallow slits into the skin side of each fish fillet. Place 4 large squares of plastic wrap on a flat surface and sprinkle the center of each with 1/2 tablespoon of olive oil. Lay a piece of fish, skin-side up, on each square. Top each with another 1/2 tablespoon oil. Season with salt and pepper. Divide the garlic among the fish, pressing into the slits. Sprinkle each piece with a pinch of cinnamon and cloves. Loosely wrap the fish in the plastic and refrigerate.</p>
        <p>2. In a large pan with a lid, combine the rice, rice milk, coconut cream, shredded coconut, bay leaves, chili and 2 teaspoons coarse kosher salt (or 1 teaspoon regular salt). Let sit for 30 minutes, then cover the pan, bring to a boil, reduce the heat to low and simmer for 17 minutes. Turn off the heat and let sit for 5 to 10 minutes. Stir in the chives.</p>
        <p>3. Meanwhile, to make the chutney, add the remaining 1 tablespoon olive oil and the butter to a sauté pan. Place over medium heat and, when hot, add the onion, curry powder and turmeric. Cook, stirring, until the onion is translucent, 5 minutes. Season with salt and pepper. Add the apple and banana and cook 2 minutes longer, until the apple is soft around the edges but still crisp. Transfer the chutney to a serving bowl.</p>
        <p>4. Fill a saucepan large enough to hold a steamer basket with 1 inch of water. Bring to a simmer. Place the wrapped fish in the basket. Lower the basket into the pan and cover. Steam the fish for 5 minutes, turn the pieces and steam until just cooked through, about 5 minutes more.</p>
        <p>5. To serve, remove the plastic from the fish. Spread the rice on a large platter, top with the fish and its cooking juices and serve with the chutney on the side. Serves 4.</p>
        <p>Food: Recipe Redux</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
