<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Players Vying for Awards Get a Creative Assist</title>
    <meta content="15glass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/basketball/15glass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFF THE GLASS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McGrady, Tracy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Arenas, Gilbert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3DC103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Players Vying for Awards Get a Creative Assist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Players Vying for Awards Get a Creative Assist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the N.B.A., players do not directly campaign for postseason awards like most valuable player, rookie of the year or sixth man of the year. Rather, they rely on creative communications staffs to generate tools that will get voters thinking and talking.</p>
        <p>This season, the results have included a rookie of the year campaign brochure in the form of an airplane ticket that promotes the Memphis Grizzlies' Rudy Gay. The Houston Rockets sent out a card in the form of a hamburger (the ''Mac Attack'') to promote Tracy McGrady for M.V.P. The Washington Wizards sent out a 2-by-3-foot movie-themed poster publicizing Gilbert Arenas for M.V.P. And the Portland Trail Blazers sent out a custom-made utility pocket tool to promote Brandon Roy for rookie of the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the N.B.A., players rely on creative communications staffs to generate tools that will get voters thinking and talking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the N.B.A., players do not directly campaign for postseason awards like most valuable player, rookie of the year or sixth man of the year. Rather, they rely on creative communications staffs to generate tools that will get voters thinking and talking.</p>
        <p>This season, the results have included a rookie of the year campaign brochure in the form of an airplane ticket that promotes the Memphis Grizzlies' Rudy Gay. The Houston Rockets sent out a card in the form of a hamburger (the ''Mac Attack'') to promote Tracy McGrady for M.V.P. The Washington Wizards sent out a 2-by-3-foot movie-themed poster publicizing Gilbert Arenas for M.V.P. And the Portland Trail Blazers sent out a custom-made utility pocket tool to promote Brandon Roy for rookie of the year.</p>
        <p>Items like these are sent to countless news media members and league officials, some of whom vote for the awards.</p>
        <p>''I think these materials are important to provide the media and to provide the voters with as much info as possible on that individual and their accomplishments,'' Zack Bolno, the Wizards' director of public relations, said during a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The Grizzlies have seen the results of their promotions. All three of their past items have resulted in victories -- Hubie Brown for coach of the year, Pau Gasol for rookie of the year and Mike Miller for sixth man of the year.</p>
        <p>Gay's plane ticket uses word play like Class R for rookie, Row 22 for his jersey number and Seat G for Gay. The ticket came in a barf bag with an attached wing pendant that reads, ''Rudy Air; Taking Flight Every Night.''</p>
        <p>''I think it's definitely a way to have fun, but I do think they work to get people talking,'' said Stacey Mitch, the Grizzlies' director of media relations.</p>
        <p>In a statement released by the team, Gay said: ''It was cool to see everything organized and put together. I was surprised. I mean, I know I was playing well, but I didn't realize people were thinking of me as being one of the best rookies.''</p>
        <p>Included with the utility tool promoting Roy is a leaflet that compares him to the tool. At one point it reads, ''This handy tool can be your sidekick that holds the power and versatility you need in day-to-day situations  just like Brandon, a versatile and reliable go-to guy for the Portland Trail Blazers.''</p>
        <p>The tool was part of a campaign the Blazers launched with a news conference in Roy, Ore.</p>
        <p>These things do not come cheap. Mitch said the Gay campaign cost around $2,500. Past campaigns have cost up to $4,000. But teams find them to be worthwhile.</p>
        <p>''When you've got a player like Brandon, our excitement about him is he may be the next premier league player,'' said Sarah Mensah, the Blazers' senior vice president for marketing and sales. ''And him getting the attention he has due is make or break for a franchise like ours.''</p>
        <p>OFF THE GLASS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
