<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Most Exclusive Club</title>
    <meta content="15Deal1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/realestate/15Deal1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BIG DEAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbanel, Josh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guillemot, Gerard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bartiromo, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lourd, Bryan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Big Deal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DC133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Most Exclusive Club</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Most Exclusive Club</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH BARBANEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barbanel, Josh</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ubisoft founder Gerard Guillemot buys $7.75 million apartment at 151 East 79th Street; unidentified hedge fund trader pays $6.55 million for duplex at 50 Bond Street; CNBC correspondent Maria Bartiromo and husband Jonathan Steinberg buy town house on East 62nd Street for $6.5 million; Hollywood agent Bryan Lourd buys one-bedroom condominium unit adjoining his penthouse at 59 West 12th Street for $4.25 million and plans to combine apartments; photos (Big Deal column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LET us now praise the unsung heroes of the effervescent Manhattan real estate market, where prices are pushing upward as they teeter or fall in much of the rest of the country: the buyers.</p>
        <p>In the last week or two, city property records recorded the names of people -- or in some cases of the trusts and limited liability corporations -- mainly from the worlds of technology, law and finance, who have been willing to step up and buy increasingly expensive real estate, despite these uncertain times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Let us now praise the unsung heroes of the effervescent Manhattan real estate market: the buyers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LET us now praise the unsung heroes of the effervescent Manhattan real estate market, where prices are pushing upward as they teeter or fall in much of the rest of the country: the buyers.</p>
        <p>In the last week or two, city property records recorded the names of people -- or in some cases of the trusts and limited liability corporations -- mainly from the worlds of technology, law and finance, who have been willing to step up and buy increasingly expensive real estate, despite these uncertain times.</p>
        <p>There was Gérard Guillemot, a co-founder of Ubisoft, the French interactive-game company, who spent $7.75 million for an eighth-floor apartment at 151 East 79th Street, at Lexington Avenue. There are just 16 units in the 15-story building. In 2003, Mr. Guillemot founded Longtail Studios, which designs games and entertainment for mobile phones.</p>
        <p>Then there was the trader at Millennium Partners, a hedge fund. He paid $6.55 million for an apartment, the last unsold unit at 50 Bond Street, a turn-of-the-last-century loft building with Greek Revival details in NoHo that was converted to condominiums a few years ago. The trader asked that his name not be used because the building has only six apartments and no doorman. The apartment is a duplex that includes 2,600 square feet on the seventh floor, a 770-square-foot eighth-floor penthouse and 2,000 square feet of terraces, according to property records.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Maria Bartiromo, a CNBC business correspondent, and her husband, Jonathan Steinberg, a hedge fund executive and a son of the financier Saul P. Steinberg, bought an 18.5-foot-wide town house on East 62nd Street. Ms. Bartiromo has been buffeted by questions in the business media lately over her relationship with sources. So what could be more comforting than the ritual of closing and getting the keys to a new house? The price was $6.5 million, according to property records, and the seller was Michael Slocum, a banker with Wachovia Bank, who was transferred out of the city.</p>
        <p>But unfortunately, not all New Yorkers can contribute to this high end of the real estate market. A study released last week by New York University's Furman Center for Real Estate and Urban Policy found that at recent sale prices, almost all apartments in Manhattan and most apartments across the city are beyond the means of typical New York households.</p>
        <p>The study estimated that fewer than 5 percent of New York City homes sold in 2005 were affordable to New Yorkers earning the city's median household income ($43,000 in 2005), down from 11 percent in 2000.</p>
        <p>In Manhattan, only 2.1 percent of all apartments sold were affordable to such households and 4.6 percent affordable to households earning 160 percent of the median income, or $64,500 in 2005. This number was down from 10.1 percent in 2000.</p>
        <p>A Hollywood Agent's Oscar-Worthy Deal</p>
        <p>BRYAN LOURD, the co-director of the Creative Artists Agency and one of the most powerful agents in Hollywood, knows how to do a deal. In 2004, Mr. Lourd, who holds one of the more celebrated pre-Oscar parties at his house in Los Angeles, bought an apartment in Greenwich Village, one of the two duplex penthouses atop 59 West 12th Street, a prewar apartment building developed by Bing &amp; Bing, whose apartments are known for their spaciousness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lourd's condo has south-facing views, a fireplace, two landscaped terraces and a living room with arched windows and 14-foot ceilings, according to the listing at the time by John Venekamp, a broker with Brown Harris Stevens.</p>
        <p>It has 2,760 square feet, not including the 840 square feet of terrace space, the condo documents show. Mr. Lourd paid $4.9 million for it. But it seems it was not quite big enough.</p>
        <p>Outside Hollywood, Mr. Lourd may be best known for his relationship with the actress and authorfor his relationship with Carrie Fisher. Mr. Lourd and Ms. Fisher have a daughter.</p>
        <p>In the Village, Mr. Lourd began negotiations over the last several months to buy the condo of his next-door neighbor, Hall Cannon, who owned a much smaller one-bedroom, at 1,082 square feet, facing north and without a terrace. Mr. Cannon paid $1.3 million for the apartment in November 2001, according to city records.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cannon, who worked for several years in real estate development in Manhattan, decided on an abrupt change in direction, and with his partner, Miles Refo, who worked in publishing, moved to New Zealand, where they bought and began renovating the historic Otahuna Lodge, which had fallen into receivership.</p>
        <p>The lodge, which has a spa and seven guest suites, caters to British and American guests. But it is also a working farm with chickens, sheep and pigs, a huge change from West 12th Street. They no longer needed the New York apartment and decided to sell, Mr. Cannon said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lourd's final offer was so high that it was accepted before a broker was hired and the apartment was listed. City records show a price of $4.25 million for the one-bedroom, which works out to $3,900 a square foot, more than double the average price per square foot in Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>But several brokers said that Mr. Lourd may have nonetheless made a wise deal since, in this strong luxury market, the combined apartments will probably command a much higher price per square foot as a single unit than they would if resold separately.</p>
        <p>BIG DEAL E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: bigdeal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
