<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Men in Uniform</title>
    <meta content="15inte" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/thecity/15inte.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CITY PEOPLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lamm, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vasquez, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harriott, Kwacha Denord</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McCann, Jimmy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santiago, Jose</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cintron, Rodney</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Upper West Side (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D6133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Men in Uniform</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Our Men in Uniform</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB LAMM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lamm, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brief sketches of some men who work at Hopkins, condominium on Upper West Side, part of Bob Lamm's 172 Interview Project; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I'VE spent most of my life, including the first eight years of my childhood, living at 172 West 79th Street, an apartment house at Amsterdam Avenue on the Upper West Side. It's now a condominium called the Hopkins, with 95 apartments and eight full-time employees.</p>
        <p>In an effort to help residents learn more about our staff, I created the 172 Interview Project. Over the last nine months, I've interviewed most of the people who work in the building and written short profiles of each, copies of which have been left in front of residents' doors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A project helps residents in a condominium on the Upper West Side learn about the people who work in their building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I'VE spent most of my life, including the first eight years of my childhood, living at 172 West 79th Street, an apartment house at Amsterdam Avenue on the Upper West Side. It's now a condominium called the Hopkins, with 95 apartments and eight full-time employees.</p>
        <p>In an effort to help residents learn more about our staff, I created the 172 Interview Project. Over the last nine months, I've interviewed most of the people who work in the building and written short profiles of each, copies of which have been left in front of residents' doors.</p>
        <p>The 172 Interview Project seems to have had a positive impact on our little community. Many residents have been eager to read about the building workers they see every day, while the staff members interviewed have been enthusiastic about sharing their stories. After talking for an hour with an employee named Kwacha Denord Harriott, for example, I had more than enough material. But Mr. Harriott said, ''I don't feel like stopping.''</p>
        <p>BOB LAMM</p>
        <p>FRANK VASQUEZ, 37  Daytime concierge  Eight years on the job</p>
        <p>The son of Ecuadorean immigrants, he grew up in Astoria, Queens.</p>
        <p>''I went to LaSalle Academy, an all-boys school in the East Village run by Franciscan priests. I love heavy-metal music, but to my classmates I was not Spanish, not even of Spanish descent. They considered me a 'white boy' because of the music. That helped me to realize how people can be so narrow-minded.''</p>
        <p>When he was a 20-year-old student at Queensborough Community College, his girlfriend became pregnant. ''The birth of my son saved me, because until he was born I did not know that I was going to live beyond 21. He basically gave me a life. God knows what would have happened to me if he hadn't been born.''</p>
        <p>KWACHA DENORD HARRIOTT, 34  Porter and nighttime concierge One year on the job</p>
        <p>He grew up on the island of Jamaica and has relatives who come from China, India, Africa and England.</p>
        <p>''As a little boy, I lived with my mother, but instead of going to school, I used to run off to work on a garbage truck with my grandfather. One afternoon my stepmother saw me and told my father, who came to get me. I tried to hide underneath the garbage truck, but my father loved me so much he laid down in the middle of the street so the truck wouldn't pass. After that, I lived with my father and stepmother.''</p>
        <p>JIMMY McCANN, 57  Concierge and porter  Four years on the job</p>
        <p>The son of an Italian-American mother and an Irish-American father who was a New York police officer, he grew up in the Bronx near Fordham Road.</p>
        <p>''I worked for Con Edison for 22 years, mainly in field operations. It was dangerous. You're going into a manhole with thousands of volts of electricity all around you. You hear all the time about manholes blowing up.''</p>
        <p>Four years ago, he met his wife, Laura, on a blind date. ''We knew very quickly that we were meant to be together. She has three grown children, but they took me in with no problem, like I was always part of the family. Now my wife and I share a three-story home in a very quiet part of north Flushing with Laura's mother, her sister and brother-in-law, and their two daughters.''</p>
        <p>JOSE SANTIAGO, 60  Handyman  Five years on the job</p>
        <p>He came to New York from Puerto Rico at age 10.</p>
        <p>''We were among the first Puerto Ricans to live in western Harlem. My new school was 90 percent black, and at first I found it intimidating. But once I made one friend, it was so easy to make a second and a third and a fourth.''</p>
        <p>He met his wife, Tania, when he was in a bowling league and she was working as a waitress at Stadium Lanes near Yankee Stadium. ''Without knowing that Tania was Cuban, I asked for some soda in a Cuban accent. She wouldn't say anything, but it was love at first sight for me. When she found out that I wasn't Cuban, she just laughed, then called her mother and said: 'Ma, I met this Puerto Rican who says he's Cuban. I'm mixed up.' ''</p>
        <p>RODNEY CINTRON, 28  Porter and maintenance man  Five years on the job</p>
        <p>The son of Puerto Ricans who met in New York, he grew up in Marble Hill, in Upper Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''When I was 10, 11, 12, 13, I had a lot of problems because I'm light-skinned and I've got red hair and blue eyes. It's hard when you don't look like you're supposed to. I was small and was bullied a lot till my older brother taught me karate and kick boxing.''</p>
        <p>He and his wife, Ines, recently had their third child and may leave New York because of the high cost of living. ''I want my children to grow up in a house just like I did, to have their freedom, to have a backyard where I know they're going to be safe. As a parent, your first priority is to be sure your kids are all right for the future.''</p>
        <p>CITY PEOPLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
