<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alternative Tax Hits Home the Hardest</title>
    <meta content="15RAMTWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alternative Minimum Tax</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">St James (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greco, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fessenden, Ford</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E0D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1238" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alternative Tax Hits Home the Hardest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FORD FESSENDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fessenden, Ford</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on adverse impact of alternative minimum tax on increasing number of households in New York metropolitan area; Joe Greco of St James, NY, for instance, says that while he makes about $150,000 annually, his property taxes are well into five figures; he is unable to use many federal tax deductions he has long relied upon; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOE GRECO lives with his wife, Karla, and their two children in a recently built four-bedroom home in a small hamlet in Suffolk County. Although he does not consider himself a wealthy man, Mr. Greco has joined a growing number of taxpayers across the region who find themselves paying the alternative minimum tax, which was created almost 40 years ago to make sure the nation's millionaires paid their fair share.</p>
        <p>''So, I earn a decent salary,'' said Mr. Greco, 41, of St. James, who makes about $150,000 a year running a ready-mix concrete business with his father and brother. ''But my property taxes are astronomical, well into five figures. And my state income taxes are also five figures. But if you make enough to pay them, you can't deduct them.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOE GRECO lives with his wife, Karla, and their two children in a recently built four-bedroom home in a small hamlet in Suffolk County. Although he does not consider himself a wealthy man, Mr. Greco has joined a growing number of taxpayers across the region who find themselves paying the alternative minimum tax, which was created almost 40 years ago to make sure the nation's millionaires paid their fair share.</p>
        <p>''So, I earn a decent salary,'' said Mr. Greco, 41, of St. James, who makes about $150,000 a year running a ready-mix concrete business with his father and brother. ''But my property taxes are astronomical, well into five figures. And my state income taxes are also five figures. But if you make enough to pay them, you can't deduct them.''</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Greco was required to do a second calculation when filling out his 2006 federal returns, unable to claim either those deductions or the child tax credit. Since the tax owed under that formula was higher than the amount of tax that would be paid with the deductions, he had to pay the higher amount.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Greco, that meant paying $5,000 to $6,000 more in taxes using the alternative minimum tax calculation. Households affected by it pay the equivalent of a flat tax of 26 or 28 percent.</p>
        <p>And because the A.M.T. has never been adjusted for inflation, more and more people are finding themselves unable to use many deductions they have long relied on.</p>
        <p>The alternative tax takes a disproportionate bite from the metropolitan area: One in every four of the households that pay it are in New York, New Jersey or Connecticut, according to an analysis prepared by Citizens for Tax Justice, a liberal research group based in Washington.</p>
        <p>Starting early next year, the number of households paying the A.M.T. within the region, and around the country, will skyrocket if Congress does not change the tax code. Citizens for Tax Justice projects that number will climb to 3 million from 870,000 in the region early next year, and to 23 million nationwide, up from 3.4 million last year.</p>
        <p>''The dilemma for suburban New Yorkers is that you have to have two jobs to pay your high mortgage, to pay your high property tax, to pay your gas to go to work,'' said Representative Steve Israel, Democrat of Huntington, N.Y. ''And then the federal government tells you, 'You're so rich, you have to give back your deductions.' ''</p>
        <p>The prospect of facing higher bills with the alternative minimum tax begins for most households when their adjusted gross income exceeds $125,000. But some making less can also get hit, based on the total amount of deductions.</p>
        <p>By early next year, people earning substantially less would see their tax bills rise, including almost everyone earning more than $100,000 and about half of those making $75,000 to $100,000. The impact of the additional tax would vary from a few dollars to thousands more.</p>
        <p>The average household reporting between $100,000 and $200,000 would pay $2,800 in additional federal taxes next year using the calculation for the alternative minimum tax, according to the Congressional Joint Committee on Taxation.</p>
        <p>The prospect of millions of their constituents suddenly seeing a sudden and substantial tax increase has members of Congress, especially those from the metropolitan region, focused on fixing the problem.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to have to answer to constituents in my own district if we don't do something,'' said Representative William J. Pascrell Jr., Democrat of Paterson, N.J., who is a member of the House Ways and Means Committee.</p>
        <p>''In 2005, there were 18,116 people eligible for the A.M.T.,'' he said, citing a study prepared for committee members on the impact of the tax in their districts. ''This year, there are 122,500-plus people in my district eligible. You don't have to be a mathematical wizard to figure this out.''</p>
        <p>Some members of Congress said it was unfair to consider income alone given the cost of living in the region. Can a taxpayer in the metropolitan area -- with its expensive housing, high energy costs, heavy state and local tax burden and long, costly commutes -- be regarded as wealthy because his or her income is in the five figures?</p>
        <p>''It is wrong that hard-working families in our community, who are struggling to keep up with large mortgages, increasing property taxes and the skyrocketing cost of sending children to college, must pay this exorbitant tax,'' said Representative Nita M. Lowey, Democrat of Westchester.</p>
        <p>Jim Isaacs, 60, who sells commercial carpet, said that he paid more under the alternative minimum tax but did not consider himself affluent.</p>
        <p>''I would be considered rich if I lived in Tuscaloosa, Ala.,'' said Mr. Isaacs, who lives in Maplewood, N.J., with his wife, Kerstin, a public relations manager for a New York City law firm.</p>
        <p>''When your real estate taxes are $19,000, and when prices of homes, just because you live in the New York area, go up and up and up, you're not wealthy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The New York Times examined 2004 data from the Internal Revenue Service that shows what households paid in federal tax and what was claimed in deductions, by ZIP code around the region.</p>
        <p>The data showed that the households in ZIP codes whose residents had average adjusted gross income of between $140,000 and $160,000 in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut paid an average of $14,800 in state and local taxes. This compares with $8,000 in state and local taxes paid on average by households earning similar income in ZIP codes elsewhere in the country.</p>
        <p>Without being able to deduct those local and state taxes under the alternative minimum tax rules, the overall federal tax burden is higher for those living within ZIP codes in the metropolitan area where the average adjusted gross income was between $140,000 and $160,000. The average federal tax bill was $30,900 in those ZIP codes, compared with $29,600 for households in comparable neighborhoods elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''Some of that is probably caused by the A.M.T.,'' said Gerald Prante, an analyst with the Tax Foundation, an organization based in Washington that favors lower taxes.</p>
        <p>The alternative minimum tax was approved in 1969 to make sure the most affluent Americans were not using loopholes to lower their bills. It disallowed a list of deductions, including shelters like accelerated depreciation and stock options that were being used by people with very high incomes.</p>
        <p>''It used to be that everyone was in these tax shelters, because the top tax rate was 70 percent,'' said Mitchell R. Zachary, head of the tax department for Grassi &amp; Company, in Lake Success, N.Y., and Mr. Greco's accountant. ''But there were lots of loopholes.''</p>
        <p>Congress has put off changing the alternative minimum tax for the last several years, instead choosing temporary fixes that have kept millions from paying more when they do the second calculation.</p>
        <p>Representative Charles B. Rangel, the New York Democrat who is chairman of the Ways and Means Committee, said there was discussion about making the alternative minimum tax apply only to the highest income earners, especially, he said, those who have done well under the Bush administration's tax cuts.</p>
        <p>''We don't know whether we can do any of these, but we are talking about it,'' Mr. Rangel said. ''We can kick this can down the road another year, but it is my hope we can deal with the A.M.T. this year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
