<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children's Books</title>
    <meta content="Long.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/review/Long.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840242"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children's Books</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Children’s Books</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNA RUDGE LONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Long, Joanna Rudge</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not a Box</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated by Antoinette Portis.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. HarperCollins Publishers.</p>
        <p>$12.99. (Ages 2 to 6)</p>
        <p>The Birthday Box</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated by Leslie Patricelli.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. Candlewick Press.</p>
        <p>$15.99. (Ages 2 to 5)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A lot of new picture books seem to reflect the concern that creative play is becoming a thing of the past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not a Box</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated by Antoinette Portis.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. HarperCollins Publishers.</p>
        <p>$12.99. (Ages 2 to 6)</p>
        <p>The Birthday Box</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated by Leslie Patricelli.</p>
        <p>Unpaged. Candlewick Press.</p>
        <p>$15.99. (Ages 2 to 5)</p>
        <p>Do children still know how to play? The flourishing market for picture books that promote playing as worthwhile (and, yes, fun) suggests that many of us aren't confident that they do, or that parents do enough to encourage them. Still, the impulse to ''make believe'' is strong at a very young age. Imagination animates toys, turns pots into drums, gives nature a role. As Dylan Thomas remembered in ''Fern Hill'': ''I was prince of the apple towns / ... I lordly had the trees and leaves / Trail with daisies and barley / Down the rivers of the windfall light.''</p>
        <p>Children's books have long celebrated that kind of creative play. A. A. Milne's ''Winnie-the-Pooh'' still satisfies children who dream of toys coming alive. From the same era, the children in Arthur Ransome's 1930 tale ''Swallows and Amazons'' turn an island camping trip into a spirited free-for-all between pirates and a shipshape crew. A generation later, John Burningham used delicious irony in ''Come Away From the Water, Shirley'' to present a small girl's lushly painted fantasy life in counterpoint with her sketchily drawn parents, who sit in beach chairs issuing the warnings that inspire her wild scenarios.</p>
        <p>While Shirley's parents haven't an inkling of her thrilling make-believe, the parents in ''Swallows and Amazons'' sympathize with their children's plans for adult-free sailing and island life. Daddy's cabled permission is classic: ''Better drowned than duffers if not duffers won't drown.'' Such books depict the kind of free-wheeling play we fondly remember. They're also exciting stories with memorable characters.</p>
        <p>A lot of new picture books seem to reflect the concern that creative play is becoming a thing of the past. Some merely portray imaginative activities, as if children might not think to invent them. Antoinette Portis's ''Not a Box'' (an ''Honor Book'' for the 2007 Geisel Award, given by the American Library Association for ''the most distinguished book for beginning readers'') is one of these. Portis enlivens it, though, with a developing argument between her rabbit character and an annoying offstage voice: ''Why are you sitting in a box? ... What are you doing on top of that box?'' ''It's not a box!'' retorts the rabbit, in words emblazoned on a full page of primary red. And, later, ''It's not not not not a box!''</p>
        <p>The square book, seemingly made of brown cardboard, itself looks amusingly like a box, from its ''11.5 oz.'' net weight to its admonitory ''this side up.'' Also, those offstage questions are set on box-brown pages, which, like the rabbit's increasingly exasperated replies, appear on the left. Meanwhile, in the illustrations on the right, sober black-and-white reality alternates with the rabbit's fantasies, which are boldly drawn in brilliant red against jubilant yellow; the actual rabbit and box are evoked by just a few broad, black, lightly feathered lines. The unquenchable hero perches atop ''Rabbit Peak,'' hoses a burning building, blasts off into space. The graphics are handsome, the debate authentically childlike. Still, there's just the one idea: imagination transforms. And the conclusion lacks punch. Asked, finally, ''Well, what is it then?'' the best the rabbit can come up with is: ''It's my Not-a-Box!''</p>
        <p>In ''The Birthday Box,'' Leslie Patricelli offers a similar riff on the same idea. Once it's unwrapped, the box of the title turns out to contain a doggy playmate, Oscar; the box itself becomes a plane, a ship, a sled and, at last (in good picture book tradition), the bed where the two characters curl up for a nap. Patricelli's several board books feature the same round-faced, diaper-clad tot, who looks barely a year old -- an age when children are less likely to engage in dramatic play than to have fun simply putting something into a box and taking it out again, like Eeyore. Certainly no preschooler will be capable of snipping holes in sturdy cardboard, as shown. But babies will relate to the bright colors, clear drawings and toddler-proven activities: ripping off gift wrap, climbing onto a box and sharing stories. ''I am very lucky,'' the tot tells Oscar as they snuggle down in their cardboard bed. ''Today is my birthday, and I got a box!''</p>
        <p>Both of these books are well worth a few readings, and they'll remind parents what play can be. Still, they don't offer the kind of story that draws children back, over and over, to relive events, visit beloved characters and pore over details -- the kind that sparks spontaneous, creative and independent play.</p>
        <p>Joanna Rudge Long, a former editor at Kirkus Reviews, writes and lectures about children's books.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joanna Rudge Long, a former editor at Kirkus Reviews, writes and lectures about children's books.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
