<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese and Chinese Fare, In a Lakefront Setting</title>
    <meta content="15wedineWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15wedine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/CARMEL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toro (Carmel, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Putnam County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese and Chinese Fare, In a Lakefront Setting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Japanese and Chinese Fare, in a Lakefront Setting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Toro restaurant in Carmel, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASICALLY, Toro is just another neighborhood restaurant, but it comes with a twist. The view from the dining room is of pretty Lake Gleneida. Route 6 and a small parking space separate the restaurant from the lake, but the intrusion is minor. While the restaurant is hardly a destination in itself, if the recreation the lake offers happens to bring hungry diners to its glittery shores, Toro is worth keeping in mind.</p>
        <p>Toro is really two restaurants in one -- a pairing of Japanese and Chinese. The combination is not entirely successful, but in Carmel -- a small, laid-back Putnam County town where dining options are few -- it may be necessary. Presentations were as casual as the restaurant itself, with taste winning over artistry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Toro, in Carmel, pairs Japanese and Chinese cuisines but the more appealing dishes come from the Chinese side of the menu.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASICALLY, Toro is just another neighborhood restaurant, but it comes with a twist. The view from the dining room is of pretty Lake Gleneida. Route 6 and a small parking space separate the restaurant from the lake, but the intrusion is minor. While the restaurant is hardly a destination in itself, if the recreation the lake offers happens to bring hungry diners to its glittery shores, Toro is worth keeping in mind.</p>
        <p>Toro is really two restaurants in one -- a pairing of Japanese and Chinese. The combination is not entirely successful, but in Carmel -- a small, laid-back Putnam County town where dining options are few -- it may be necessary. Presentations were as casual as the restaurant itself, with taste winning over artistry.</p>
        <p>The more appealing dishes came largely from the Chinese side of the menu. The usual basic dishes and the ''specialties'' proved equally good; the only difference was in the quantity of the featured meat or seafood. At only $10, shredded beef with scallion and sweet onion was a flavorful mating -- as, for a dollar less, was juicy moo shu pork, the savory vegetable julienne crunchy and fresh and the pancake wrappings thin and supple.</p>
        <p>Careful not to offend its customers' palates, the kitchen keeps spicy heat to an almost imperceptible minimum but will honor a diner's request for more fiery seasoning. Shrimp with spicy tea sauce could have used some.</p>
        <p>Among the house specialties, whole deep-fried fish made a fine choice, good for a group to share. The frying oil tasted fresh, and the fish -- a sizable sea bass -- was crispy without and juicy within. Shrimp and scallops starred in mala seafood; but the Sichuanese mala sauce lacked spiciness, and the dish in general was bland. Belying its name, another dish called house special bean curd came in a clay pot overflowing with steamed pork, chicken, shrimp, mushrooms and bamboo shoot and, yes, bean curd -- a ''good, and good for you'' selection.</p>
        <p>A menu note says that ''our Peking duck is outstanding.'' And, indeed, the rich meat was tender, but we would have preferred assembling our own rolls; the wait staff, which wants to please, rolled these (and the moo shu rolls) much too loosely and they tended to fall apart. Ask to roll your own. Spread a pancake with a bit of hoisin sauce, add strips of cucumber and scallions and both duck skin and meat. Roll tightly turning up one end to prevent spillage and enjoy the lusciousness of crunchy, crisp, tender and sweet all at the same time.</p>
        <p>Bridging the cuisines, on the Japanese side, shogayaki was reminiscent of Chinese dishes. The chicken sautéed with an intense ginger sauce was refreshing. Other offerings on the Japanese side of the menu were less impressive.</p>
        <p>An entree portion of grilled eel (unaju) was too much and too rich under a thick sweet sauce. That heavy sweet sauce also flooded the house special teriyaki. Beef negimaki was a tad tough, gyoza and shumai came with dipping sauce too sweet and too cold, and dry tuna tartare seemed to be made too far in advance.</p>
        <p>The roll of most interest was the ichiban, made without rice, the center of salmon, tuna and avocado held together by a ribbon of cucumber. However, this ribbon was too thick to enclose the center, and the roll fell apart at the touch of a chopstick. In general, items from the sushi bar were fresh enough, but they lacked the elegance and careful cutting of a professional. Some salmon still contained strings of inedible white gristle.</p>
        <p>After dark, the main dining room becomes dramatic with illuminated blue insets in the wall facing the ribbon of windows and that view of Lake Gleneida. Right now the lake is between seasons, done with winter's ice fishermen and waiting for summer's boaters.</p>
        <p>Toro  1679 Route 6  Carmel  (845) 228-1700  www.torocarmel.com</p>
        <p>SATISFACTORY</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- A neighborhood Chinese-Japanese restaurant made a little special by its location -- across from pretty Lake Gleneida -- and by its dramatic lighting after dark. The small back room is plain, but booths, some of which have lake views, make the main room cozy. The tables are too small for more than two people sharing dishes. Wheelchair accessible.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Casually dressed multigenerational couples and groups. Attentive, friendly service, out to please.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Small bar beyond the sushi counter.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Lunch specials (Chinese and Japanese dishes), $6 to $13. Dinner: Japanese entrees, $11 to $24; sushi rolls, $3 to $12; Chinese entrees, $8 to $16; Peking duck, $28.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Moo shu pork (chicken, shrimp or vegetables), spicy beef with scallion and onion, Peking duck, whole crispy fish, mala seafood, chicken shogayaki.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Open Monday to Thursday, 11:30 a.m. to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 11:30 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Sunday, 12:30 to 10 p.m. Lunch specials available Monday to Saturday, 11:30 a.m. to 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 15, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/CARMEL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
