<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>La Ring Bearer</title>
    <meta content="05well.victoire.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="93" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/style/tmagazine/15tbearer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris (France)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>La Ring Bearer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">La Ring Bearer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Cathy Horyn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In appearance, Victoire de Castellane is the classic Fifi, a girl swimming nude in a giant martini glass, and you can imagine the number of dreadful ''spectaculaire''s and ''fantastique''s that have been spilled in her honor. She has been on the Paris fashion scene so long, since her teen years in the early '80s, that her bric-a-brac features -- the large doe eyes, high cheekbones, fine equine nose and blunt bangs -- seem as engraved in the Paris mind as a Ladurée macaroon or the chic facades of the Avenue Montaigne.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Victoire de Castellane is the Queen of French bling. And the Queen takes her rocks enorme. Cathy Horyn is dazzled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In appearance, Victoire de Castellane is the classic Fifi, a girl swimming nude in a giant martini glass, and you can imagine the number of dreadful ''spectaculaire''s and ''fantastique''s that have been spilled in her honor. She has been on the Paris fashion scene so long, since her teen years in the early '80s, that her bric-a-brac features -- the large doe eyes, high cheekbones, fine equine nose and blunt bangs -- seem as engraved in the Paris mind as a Ladurée macaroon or the chic facades of the Avenue Montaigne.</p>
        <p>Yet in the best sense of the phrase, Castellane knows her place in the world, and doesn't care how it regards her. She likes going to work at Dior, where she creates enormous baubles of fly-catching diamonds and African opals, as much as she likes being at home with her four young children. She wears little, if any, makeup. ''I'm so happy to be a girl every day because I can wear clothes,'' she said. ''But, in my head, I'm like a boy. Everything has to be quick!'' And like any number of Frenchwomen with a dramatic history, she has the ability to wear it lightly on her sleeve. She says with a laugh that her mother and father, who met in a nightclub and divorced when she was a toddler, cost her a small fortune in analyst bills.</p>
        <p>On the first day of the fall shows, in late February, Castellane was having lunch in her usual spot, the bar at the HÃ$(4$)tel Plaza Athénée. The hotel is two skips from Dior. She had on a black sweater, an Alaïa denim circle skirt, black stockings and high heels. Castellane had a busy week ahead of her: for the first time in three years, she was showing a collection of new jewels before they disappeared into private safes. The 17-piece collection of fiery opals, rubies and other stones set in green-enameled gold is as exotic as its name: ''Belladone Island.'' Fairy-tale proportions and colors have been a Castellane specialty since she came to Dior, in 1998, and this collection delights with its movable parts (rings that pop open to reveal a small ruby) as well as its childlike fascination with pretty but deadly plants and bugs.</p>
        <p>''I like real jewelry that has a fake look to it,'' Castellane said. ''When I was young, all the best jewelry was in musical comedies of Hollywood. Of course, it was completely fake and it looked fake, but for me it was the most beautiful thing in the world.'' Perhaps because Castellane was initiated into costume jewelry at Chanel, where she worked with Karl Lagerfeld on runway accessories for 14 years, her touchstone isn't Cartier. It's Tony Duquette, the California set designer who created pieces of luminous volume. ''It's a very special look,'' she said. ''So exotic and free. Crazy!''</p>
        <p>The same could be said of Castellane. Her life, her ultrafeminine shape, has influenced her jewelry as much as anything else. She describes her father, Antoine de Castellane, as a sweet man who never wanted to grow up. ''What was important to him was to be with friends and go out at night,'' she said. Barbara Hutton, the American heiress, was his godmother. Among Castellane's relatives are Emilio Terry, the designer and decorator who died in 1969, and Kilian Hennessy, of the Cognac Hennessys, who recently turned 100 and was married to her paternal grandmother. Castellane was raised by her other grandmother, in the 16th Arrondissement of Paris. Also in the home was an uncle, Gilles Dufour, who later worked for Lagerfeld. As Castellane said, demonstrating that she got her money's worth at the shrink, ''It was like a Tennessee Williams story -- something really strange.''</p>
        <p>Today, Castellane lives with Thomas Lenthal, the creative director of Numéro magazine and a co-founder of a new publication for men called Paradis. They live in the 16th, in an apartment with pieces by Terry and Jean-Michel Frank, with their 4-year-old daughter, ZoÃdegrees, and Castellane's sons, Stanislas, Boniface and Jules, from a former marriage. ''I'm a girl of the 16th Arrondissement,'' Castellane said as she ate her salad. ''I've never changed. It's a very bourgeois district, with many old people. And very boring. But I'm so happy, because it's like Switzerland. It's peaceful and not as expensive as people might think.''</p>
        <p>You wonder, though, how a woman built like a brick house has coped in a thin-obsessed world. Castellane admits it was difficult as a teenager. ''I had my shapey look when I was 12,'' she said. ''I hated my look.'' It was her uncle who pointed out the advantages and also taught her about proportion. ''Gilles used to say to me, 'Men love a woman with shape,' '' Castellane recalled. ''I said, 'O.K.,' and I saw that it was true.''</p>
        <p>She laughed and, sounding more sanguine, added: ''That's why I always prefer to dress for myself and then for the men that I love. Of course, I'm only speaking about a heterosexual man, but I've never seen one that loves Marni. You know?'' At the thought, Castellane seemed to sit up straighter in her seat. ''If I'm in Alaïa, I can tell you, it's good in the street.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
