<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suicide Bomber in Karbala Kills 36 Near Bus Terminal</title>
    <meta content="15iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/world/middleeast/15iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Karbala (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Alissa J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khazali, Akhil (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suicide Bomber in Karbala Kills 36 Near Bus Terminal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Suicide Bomber in Karbala Kills 36 Near Bus Terminal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISSA J. RUBIN; Iraqi employees of The New York Times contributed reporting from Karbala and Kirkuk.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubin, Alissa J</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Suicide car bomber near bus station in Karbala, Iraq, kills 36 people and wounds 168 others; furious local residents besiege police and burn two vehicles; crowd of more than 200 people throws stones at provincial government building; Karbala's Gov Akhil Khazali says Interior Ministry turned down his request for more security; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A suicide car bomber struck Saturday morning near a bus station in Karbala, the holy city that is one of the main pilgrimage destinations for Shiites, killing 36 people, including several children, according to the governor and security officials.</p>
        <p>The bombing wounded 168, according to hospital officials, including 44 women and 11 children. The explosion created a scene of carnage that left some people unable to speak when approached by a reporter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A suicide car bomber struck near a bus station in Karbala, a holy city that is a main destination for Shiite pilgrims.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A suicide car bomber struck Saturday morning near a bus station in Karbala, the holy city that is one of the main pilgrimage destinations for Shiites, killing 36 people, including several children, according to the governor and security officials.</p>
        <p>The bombing wounded 168, according to hospital officials, including 44 women and 11 children. The explosion created a scene of carnage that left some people unable to speak when approached by a reporter.</p>
        <p>The market area had been busy because it was mid-morning and many families were out shopping, said Abu Haider, 45, who described how he had made his way out of the smoke-filled market after the blast.</p>
        <p>''At the market exit, I found human parts and wounded people. I saw bodies eaten by fire,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I noticed many dead bodies of women and children, including a totally burned body of a child. He was no more than 5 years old.''</p>
        <p>In two other attacks on Saturday, a bomber in Baghdad detonated his car on the Jadriya bridge, killing 11 people, and in Kirkuk, a man's explosive vest was apparently set off accidentally, killing everyone in the vehicle in which he was riding, police reports said. Karbala has repeatedly been a target for large-scale attacks because it draws Shiite pilgrims to holy sites like the Imam Abbas and Imam Hussain shrines in the city.</p>
        <p>In March 2004, three bombers wearing suicide vests killed 140 worshipers on Ashura, a Shiite holiday, as they made their way to the city's famous shrines, the police estimated. Another suicide bombing in January 2006 killed more than 40.</p>
        <p>Karbala's Al Hussain hospital, to which police and families ferried most of the wounded on Saturday, was overwhelmed by relatives who scoured posted lists of the wounded for familiar names.</p>
        <p>More than two hours after the explosion, ambulances and security forces were still evacuating the wounded. The entire city was closed to traffic.</p>
        <p>Furious local residents besieged the police, burning two police vehicles. A crowd of more than 200 quickly gathered and threw stones at the provincial government building.</p>
        <p>Karbala's governor, Akhil Khazali, said that he had asked for more security but that he had been turned down by the Interior Ministry. He said he also wanted the help of the American military.</p>
        <p>''We also demand the occupation forces provide support and on-ground backup for the Iraqi security forces,'' the governor said.</p>
        <p>He added that seven of the wounded were suffering from severe burns, which are difficult to treat given the lack of equipment and supplies for such special care.</p>
        <p>The bombing in Kirkuk was one more sign of growing unrest in that city, in which assassinations and bombings have become almost daily events in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>In Rayaad, a city about 25 miles west of Kirkuk, armed groups threw leaflets earlier in the week threatening to kill anyone who worked for the government.</p>
        <p>In response, the Iraqi and American militaries closed the city. Despite those efforts, at least one medical assistant was killed by armed men there.</p>
        <p>There have been reports that several Iraqi insurgent groups have broken with Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia and other jihadist organizations.</p>
        <p>Reports from different areas of the country suggested a rift between insurgent organizations with a more secular approach and those that shared Al Qaeda's aspiration of creating a state ruled by Islamic religious law.</p>
        <p>However, as the bombs on Saturday demonstrated, the rift did not seem to have weakened the Qaeda-linked groups, which are thought to be the ones most involved in carrying out attacks that use suicide bombs.</p>
        <p>The rift seems to have alarmed the community of militant Islamist groups.</p>
        <p>Many of the groups have posted open letters on militant Web sites urging the Iraqi insurgency to reunite, according to the SITE Institute, which tracks and translates radical Islamist messages posted on the Internet.</p>
        <p>In Baghdad, three roadside bombs exploded in Baghdad, killing three people and wounding several more. Nineteen bodies were found around the city, according to the Ministry of the Interior.</p>
        <p>Gunmen attacked the Baghdad home of Adnan Dulaimi, the leader of the National Accord Front, which is made up of the three main Sunni parties. He was not at home, but six of his guards were wounded.</p>
        <p>In Diyala Province, five Iraqi police officers were wounded in a clash with gunmen. Two people were killed in separate roadside bombings in the province, and a car bomb attack on an American military convoy killed one civilian and wounded eight.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
