<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bundling</title>
    <meta content="15wwln--safire.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/magazine/15wwlnsafire.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-15-07: ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Israel Public Affairs Committee</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE0DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bundling</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bundling</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire column on term 'bundling' as applied to campaign fund-raising; praises headline written by Rob Pollock of Wall Street Journal for article questioning FBI sting operation involving Pentagon analyst and two staff members at American Israel Public Affairs Committee; headline read, 'First They Came for the Jews' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When New York City was still New Amsterdam a quarter-millennium ago, the teenage children of the Dutch settlers were allowed to enjoy a physical intimacy known as bundling, a word related to ''binding.'' The great Dictionary of American Regional English (DARE) defines the verb to bundle as ''to share a bed with a person of the opposite sex while fully clothed (or with some other impediment to sexual intercourse).'' That impediment was a bundling board, a long plank of wood set between the courting youths to guarantee at least the appearance of chastity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Separating lovers, gathering givers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When New York City was still New Amsterdam a quarter-millennium ago, the teenage children of the Dutch settlers were allowed to enjoy a physical intimacy known as bundling, a word related to ''binding.'' The great Dictionary of American Regional English (DARE) defines the verb to bundle as ''to share a bed with a person of the opposite sex while fully clothed (or with some other impediment to sexual intercourse).'' That impediment was a bundling board, a long plank of wood set between the courting youths to guarantee at least the appearance of chastity.</p>
        <p>This precursor to parallel parking shocked Washington Irving, who in his 1824 ''History of New York'' called the challenging nocturnal contact of the snuggling youths a ''hideous'' custom ''which the Dutch lasses . . . seemed very well inclined to follow.'' A year later, another bluenose chronicler tut-tutted about ''the very 'bundling' of the Dutch settlers; that mischievous, wicked habit, which is now spreading through the frontier settlements.''</p>
        <p>The hideous custom now goes by a collocation beginning with ''dry'' and is regarded as a quaint version of the safest sex, but the word bundling is still spreading, this time through political settlements. Though its meaning has changed, reformers, ethicists, strait-laced pundits and other goo-goos regard the new method of fund-raising as an equally ''mischievous, wicked habit.''</p>
        <p>The laws since the Watergate scandals have made it perilous to slip a candidate some money under the table or to corral potential donors who don't want their largess revealed publicly. This would have appalled the Ohio Republican boss and later senator Mark Hanna; he pioneered modern political solicitation in 1896 in aid of William (''front porch campaign'') McKinley, who outspent the Democrat William Jennings (''Cross of Gold speech'') Bryan 10 dollars to 1. A year before, Hanna set forth his priorities in reaching the pinnacle of power: ''There are two things that are important in politics. The first is money, and I can't remember what the second one is.''</p>
        <p>Bundling is a way to get around the spirit of the law to curtail undue influence of fat cats on candidates by limiting individual contributions to $2,300 in primary or general elections. Candidates of both parties are outsourcing their fund-raising to key supporters who are willing to act as conduits for the contributions of their like-minded friends and contacts.</p>
        <p>These human conduits -- who were called Rangers by George W. Bush and are now called ''Hill-raisers'' by Hillary Clinton -- pledge to raise, say, $100,000 from about 50 people, but are careful not to break the law by touching any of the checks. The individuals, however, mark their checks with a tracking number to show that they are part of the ''bundle,'' and the conduit, or channel, or bundler gets credit from the candidate's campaign for raising that big bundle of boodle. To their credit, today's Big Six -- the firm of Clinton, Obama &amp; Edwards versus the firm of McCain, Giuliani &amp; Romney -- have agreed to identify their bundlers, taking some of the mystery out of the confidential outsources.</p>
        <p>An unsolved mystery: Who coined the term? Rick Bielke of Public Campaign tracks it to a 1972 letter to The Washington Post, and if the reader can beat that, channel the earlier citation my way and I'll bundle it up and get appointed ambassador to the O.E.D.</p>
        <p>Headline of the Year</p>
        <p>Writers of headlines -- their words cabin'd, cribb'd and confined in capturing the gist of an article -- on rare occasion break through with an inspiring turn of phrase. My nomination for Headline of the Year appeared early this month above a full-page commentary infused with original reporting by the Pulitzer-winning Dorothy Rabinowitz of The Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>Her subject was a largely downplayed instance of the current campaign to undermine the First Amendment by Justice Department prosecutors and their F.B.I. satraps of entrapment. Having failed for years to find the ''mole'' inside the F.B.I. who sold out to the Russians, the agent sought to salvage his reputation by running a ''sting'' operation. The F.B.I. found a Pentagon analyst who had foolishly taken home papers and -- by threatening him with prosecution -- induced the analyst to type a supposedly classified document about policy toward Iran and fax a ''leak'' of it to two staff members he knew in the American Israel Public Affairs Committee. F.B.I. agents then wired him for sound and further drew the unsuspecting targets -- whose jobs were to stay in touch with analysts and known journalists -- into the trap.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon analyst pleaded guilty to keeping classified documents at home, for which big shots draw a fine. He is trying to reduce his 12-year sentence by testifying in June, as Rabinowitz reported, in ''the first ever attempt by government prosecutors to convict private citizens under the 1919 Espionage Act.'' That F.B.I. bell tolls for thee and me.</p>
        <p>Here is the headline in the Journal that Rob Pollock, who grasped the universal civil-libertarian point of her article, put across the top of the page: ''First They Came for the Jews.''</p>
        <p>Those words are from an approximation of what Martin Niemoeller, the German pastor who outspokenly opposed the Nazis and suffered through concentration camps, said to a seminary audience in Georgia in 1959: ''First they came for the Jews, and I did not speak out because I was not a Jew. Then they came for the Communists, and I did not speak out because I was not a Communist. Then they came for the trade unionists, and I did not speak out because I was not a trade unionist. Then they came for me, and there was no one left to speak out for me.''</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-15-07: ON LANGUAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
