<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/Westchester; Green Before It Had a Name</title>
    <meta content="15wczo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/realestate/15wczo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | Westchester"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mount Pleasant (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Studio, The (Pleasantville, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Frank Lloyd (1867-1959)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, Frank Lloyd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2DC133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/Westchester; Green Before It Had a Name</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Green Before It Had a Name</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT PLEASANT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Usonia, development of 47 homes on 100 acres in Mount Pleasant, NY, began as experimental housing community designed by group of architects headed by Frank Lloyd Wright; houses were designed to be affordable, to blend in with rural landscape and to be environmentally friendly; retrospective chronicling 60-year existence of Usonia opens May 5 at Studio, alternative art space in Pleasantville, NY; photos (In the Region/Westchester) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROLAND REISLEY remembers the crisp fall afternoon in 1950 when he and his wife, Ronnie, drove north in their three-year-old Chrysler convertible to search for a new home in Westchester's suburbs. On the hourlong car ride from their apartment on West 85th Street in Manhattan to check out what was then considered a radical housing development, he said, the couple talked about their eagerness to set down roots and start a family.</p>
        <p>The Reisleys' quest for a home 57 years ago focused on finding a New York City suburb that would best suit their lifestyle, offer a high-performing public school system and be within their financial reach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Usonia, a development of 47 homes on a 100-acre wooded site, was designed by a group of architectural idealists headed by Frank Lloyd Wright.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROLAND REISLEY remembers the crisp fall afternoon in 1950 when he and his wife, Ronnie, drove north in their three-year-old Chrysler convertible to search for a new home in Westchester's suburbs. On the hourlong car ride from their apartment on West 85th Street in Manhattan to check out what was then considered a radical housing development, he said, the couple talked about their eagerness to set down roots and start a family.</p>
        <p>The Reisleys' quest for a home 57 years ago focused on finding a New York City suburb that would best suit their lifestyle, offer a high-performing public school system and be within their financial reach.</p>
        <p>At that time, not many years after World War II, environmentally friendly houses, preservation of open space and cooperative ownership of property were almost unheard of, but those were some of the attractions of Usonia, a development of 47 homes on a 100-acre wooded site here.</p>
        <p>The community was designed by a group of architectural idealists headed by Frank Lloyd Wright, and Mr. and Mrs. Reisley, who came of age during the Depression, felt drawn to it.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't your typical American house or neighborhood that we were looking for,'' Mr. Reisley said during an interview in his home. Mrs. Reisley died last year.</p>
        <p>Beginning on May 5, a retrospective titled ''Frank Lloyd Wright and Usonia: an Experiment in Living,'' will be on display at the Studio, an alternative space for contemporary art in Pleasantville. The exhibit, curated by Johanna Cooper, a resident of Usonia since 1971, chronicles the 60-year existence of the community where three of the houses, including Mr. Reisley's, were designed by Wright, who was 80 when it started in 1947.</p>
        <p>Usonian-style houses, which the architect first started building in the 1930s, were designed not only to be affordable but also to blend in with the local landscape. The architectural exhibit includes original drawings and site plans of the houses and recorded statements by founding members of Usonia.</p>
        <p>The development originally had a cooperative form of ownership, but that changed during the 1950s, and now only some of the land, including a pool, tennis courts and private roads, is owned in common, by a homeowner's association.</p>
        <p>''One of the main points of the exhibit is that Wright was a very early environmentalist,'' Mrs. Cooper said. The architect used the term Usonian -- he is said to have coined it as short for the United States of North America -- to describe houses that echo the natural forms of the surrounding land and use glass and stone to reduce the sense of separation from the outside.</p>
        <p>The Reisleys spent $20,000 to $30,000 on their new three-bedroom home, where they raised three children. ''I remember coming upon an enclave in the woods and liking what we saw,'' said Mr. Reisley, a retired physicist, ''and for the time, it was relatively affordable.'' They ultimately expanded the house to 3,200 square feet.</p>
        <p>When the cooperative community began, the least expensive houses cost $10,000 and the most expensive were $85,000. Each lot is 1.25 acres.</p>
        <p>In 1971, Mrs. Cooper, the exhibit curator, and her husband, Marvin, a doctor, bought their four-level three-bedroom house, designed by a Wright apprentice, for $100,000.</p>
        <p>The most recent sale in Usonia, according to the Westchester-Putnam Multiple Listing Service, was a five-bedroom, four-bath home that went for $900,000 last fall after one year on the market. The asking price had originally been $1.095 million.</p>
        <p>Houses in Usonia tend to appeal to a narrow market, said Helene Miller, a sales associate for Prudential Holmes &amp; Kennedy. ''They're not for the buyer who wants the most square footage in a house, or a conventional-styled home,'' Ms. Miller said, describing them as the antithesis of McMansions.</p>
        <p>Many of the houses in Usonia -- like the four-bedroom house bought in 1997 for about $450,000 by Leigh Mesh and Nancy Wu, both musicians with the New York Metropolitan Opera Orchestra -- were quite small to begin with and have been expanded over the years.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wu, a violinist, explained that she and her husband, who plays the double bass, were seeking a house that was part of a close-knit community and at the same time offered a sense of privacy.</p>
        <p>''It's a neat compromise between having privacy and not being isolated,'' she said. Additionally, the couple, who have a son, 5, and a daughter, 9, were attracted to the highly rated Byram Hills Central School District.</p>
        <p>The architectural control exercised by the Usonia board of directors is seen as a plus by most residents, said Dara Meyers-Kingsley, who lives in a house built in 1951 and added onto twice.</p>
        <p>Ms. Meyers-Kingsley, a board member, explained that all additions ''must be sympathetic'' in style to the existing home. Any home built to replace one that has been torn down must be Usonian in style. ''You can't take down a house and build a center-hall colonial,'' she said. ''But why would anyone who was attracted to Usonia even want to do that?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Meyers-Kingsley, an art curator, and her husband, Evan, a museum administrator, are among what she described as ''a whole new generation of Usonians who have arrived in the past 5 or 10 years.'' The couple moved to Usonia from Park Slope three years ago with their daughters, Elizabeth, 9, and Ava, 11. According to Ms. Meyers-Kingsley, three other Brooklyn families have also come to Usonia in recent years.</p>
        <p>''We use the word organic now to describe what Wright did,'' said Ms. Cooper, the curator of the Usonia exhibit, citing as examples the architect's use of passive solar energy and concrete floors with radiant heat. ''Sixty years ago, he was considered a radical, but in many ways his ideas have stood the test of time. Now we take them for granted.''</p>
        <p>In the Region | Westchester</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
