<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Trucks, Gunshot Victims and a Famous Patient On the Mend</title>
    <meta content="15surgery" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/15surgery.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CORZINE'S CRASH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Camden (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fahim, Kareem</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ostrum, Robert F (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Back (Human Body Part)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Back (Human Body Part)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFD9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Trucks, Gunshot Victims and a Famous Patient On the Mend</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">N.J. Governor Undergoes Another Operation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREEM FAHIM and DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David; Fahim, Kareem</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov Jon S Corzine undergoes second operation at Cooper University Hospital in Camden, NJ, to clean wound around thigh bone that was broken in car accident; is semiconscious because of pain medications and remains in intensive care on ventilator; Dr Robert F Ostrum, hospital's director of orthopedic surgery, says Corzine is doing better than expected and should make full recovery; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gunshot wounds, stab wounds and other perils of urban life keep the trauma surgeons at Cooper University Hospital here busy. Of the roughly 2,500 patients that the trauma center treats every year, hospital officials say, 10 percent to 15 percent are crime victims.</p>
        <p>Loudspeaker announcements mark patients' arrivals: ''Trauma alert to admitting, trauma alert to admitting.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though Gov. Jon S. Corzine remained in intensive care and on a ventilator, semiconscious because of pain medication, doctors said his vital signs were improving.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gunshot wounds, stab wounds and other perils of urban life keep the trauma surgeons at Cooper University Hospital here busy. Of the roughly 2,500 patients that the trauma center treats every year, hospital officials say, 10 percent to 15 percent are crime victims.</p>
        <p>Loudspeaker announcements mark patients' arrivals: ''Trauma alert to admitting, trauma alert to admitting.''</p>
        <p>On Thursday evening, the loudspeaker marked the arrival of Gov. Jon S. Corzine, who was flown by helicopter to a gray helipad on the hospital's roof, which overlooks Philadelphia and southern New Jersey. He was wheeled down a long ramp, then through two wide doors into a receiving room filled with equipment and beds and decorated with a street sign that reads, ''Chopper Boulevard.''</p>
        <p>Governor Corzine underwent a second operation here Saturday morning, an hourlong procedure to clean the wound around his badly broken thigh bone. The hospital's director of orthopedic trauma, Dr. Robert F. Ostrum, declared the surgery to be ''routine and uneventful.''</p>
        <p>''He's doing better than we had expected,'' Dr. Ostrum said, adding that he believed the governor would recover fully.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Corzine remained in intensive care and on a ventilator, semiconscious because of pain medication, doctors said his vital signs were improving and that his movements bolstered their confidence that he had escaped any brain or spinal injury.</p>
        <p>Dr. Steven E. Ross, head of the hospital's trauma unit, said Saturday that it appeared the governor had not even suffered a concussion.</p>
        <p>''He has been awakened, answers simple yes-or-no answers about pain and will perform things for us to demonstrate that his brain is working properly,'' Dr. Ross said.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he added, the medication has kept Mr. Corzine in a state in which ''he is not aware of his surroundings.''</p>
        <p>The governor, who apparently was not wearing a seat belt while riding in the front passenger seat of a Chevrolet Suburban, broke his left femur in two places, as well as ribs, his breastbone, collarbone and a lower vertebra.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ross said that while Mr. Corzine fractured the outer portion of the vertebra and had a serious bruise near his spine, there was no risk of nerve damage because the break occurred in a spot where the bone attached to muscle and was far from the spinal cord.</p>
        <p>''Other than the pain, it is of no clinical significance,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's three children and his companion, Sharon Elghanayan, visited him on the third floor here before and after he underwent surgery on Saturday.</p>
        <p>It is unclear when he will be able to resume his duties, but the governor's chief of staff, Tom Shea, acknowledged Saturday that his earlier estimate -- that Mr. Corzine would be able to conduct state business from his hospital bed within a week -- was ''a hope.''</p>
        <p>If the governor is among Cooper's most famous patients, hospital staff took pains to make clear that he received the same standard of care as, say, a gunshot victim who lives in Camden.</p>
        <p>Or, for that matter, the same standard of care as Maria Centron's pregnant daughter, whose blood pressure shot up on Friday, sending her to the emergency room.</p>
        <p>''I heard the governor is here,'' Ms. Centron said as she stood in the cold outside the hospital.</p>
        <p>''He's not in good shape,'' she added, forgetting her family's problems for a moment. ''I just hope he feels better.''</p>
        <p>Still, it was clear that the governor was not just another patient. A caravan of television trucks snaked around the front of the hospital, some of them parking on sidewalks near boarded-up row houses. Extra security guards roamed the entrance, and the trauma center's intensive care unit was watched over by an extra guard, in addition to the governor's state police detail.</p>
        <p>But for the doctors, there were plenty of other emergencies, with patients on gurneys that lined the hallway near the hospital's crowded emergency room: someone injured in a fall, three people who were in car accidents, an assault victim.</p>
        <p>''It's Camden,'' said Danielle Orlando, who waited with two other hospital employees for a shuttle bus to the parking lot. ''It's always busy.''</p>
        <p>Cooper's trauma center treats patients from all over the state, said Dr. Simon J. Samaha, the chief medical officer. A majority are victims of car crashes, many on major highways like the Atlantic City Expressway, the New Jersey Turnpike or, in the governor's case, the Garden State Parkway.</p>
        <p>The trauma center is one of only three in the state designated Level 1. These centers -- the others are Robert Wood Johnson University Hospital in New Brunswick and University Hospital in Newark -- are required to treat at least 600 critically injured patients a year.</p>
        <p>Dr. Samaha and his team would not discuss the details of the governor's treatment but spoke generally about their preparations for a trauma patient. The doctor on duty -- on Thursday, it happened to be Dr. Ross -- communicates with the medical technicians who bring in the patient and then mobilizes a medical team of 20 to 30 members.</p>
        <p>''There is a whole procedure that is almost a reflex,'' Dr. Samaha said. When a patient is flown in by helicopter, as Mr. Corzine and the state trooper who was driving him were, a doctor from the hospital has command of the in-flight care.</p>
        <p>Sometime after Mr. Corzine arrived at the hospital on Thursday, a memorandum went around to staff members, reiterating rules about patient confidentiality.</p>
        <p>The hospital, Camden's largest employer, has tried to provide a lift for the blighted city, but it is a tall task. Racheed Long, 32, a security guard who lives near Cooper, walked Friday afternoon near the Cooper Plaza Commons, a weedy square of graffiti and discarded lighters that is decorated with a plaque that describes a ''landscaped oasis of beauty.'' A chunk of a burned house sat on the pavement near not far from the plaque.</p>
        <p>Mr. Long said his wife had had a baby at Cooper, and that in his neighborhood, with ''drug dealers on every corner,'' it was good to have a hospital so close.</p>
        <p>In March, the Camden Police Department credited the hospital with cutting into a problem that the city has struggled with for years: the homicide rate. For 69 days this year, no homicides were recorded in Camden, in part because the trauma unit's doctors kept wounded people alive, the Police Department said. One of them was a 19-year-old man who had been shot five times. ''He had a 10 percent chance of living,'' said Teresa Sicard Archambeault, a spokeswoman for the police.</p>
        <p>On Friday afternoon, two of Mr. Corzine's children, Jeffrey and Jennifer, wandered through the hospital's lobby almost unnoticed as a flat-screen television nearby broadcast a speech by their father's temporary replacement, Richard J. Codey, the president of the State Senate.</p>
        <p>A few feet away from the Corzines, Kim Santana wheeled a dolly crowded with bouquets. The flowers had been sent to the governor, but his family decided to give them to patients who had no visitors. The sunflowers, roses and white lilies brought smiles, Ms. Santana said. She kept the cards for the governor.</p>
        <p>CORZINE'S CRASH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
