<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting Older? Don't Despair; You Can Still Lift Your Game</title>
    <meta content="15chess" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/crosswords/chess/15chess.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kraai, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nakamura, Hikaru</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcclain, Dylan Loeb</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE4DA103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting Older? Don't Despair; You Can Still Lift Your Game</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Getting Older? Don’t Despair; You Can Still Lift Your Game</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dylan Loeb McClain</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcclain, Dylan Loeb</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chess column on players who are considered past their prime chess years; says using wisdom that comes with age can be critical in achieving goals that eluded them earlier; cites recent victory by Jesse Kraai, 34, over Hikaru Nakamura, 19, former US champion; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Can players get better after 30? Yes, but it requires commitment.</p>
        <p>In general, chess has become a young person's game, with a number of players achieving grandmaster and international master titles in their teens. But not everyone peaks before gaining the right to vote, and there is no reason they should.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In general, chess has become a young person’s game. But not everyone peaks before gaining the right to vote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Can players get better after 30? Yes, but it requires commitment.</p>
        <p>In general, chess has become a young person's game, with a number of players achieving grandmaster and international master titles in their teens. But not everyone peaks before gaining the right to vote, and there is no reason they should.</p>
        <p>Studies at the National Institute on Aging and other research centers have shown that the mind does not lose its abilities as it ages. Rather, disease, which often comes with aging, seems to cause mental impairment.</p>
        <p>For players who are considered past their prime chess years, the wisdom that comes with age can be critical in achieving goals that eluded them earlier.</p>
        <p>In 1993, Paul Van der Sterren, a Dutch grandmaster who had never been among the world's elite, qualified for the first and only time for the candidates matches for the world championship. He was 37.</p>
        <p>More recently, Emory Tate of the United States earned the international master title at 48.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, Jesse Kraai, an international master from New Mexico, tied for fifth at the Foxwoods Open, fulfilling the requirements for the grandmaster title. Gata Kamsky, a grandmaster from Brooklyn, took first on a tiebreak.</p>
        <p>Kraai is 34 -- not exactly old. But only recently, he said, has he been able to raise his level of play.</p>
        <p>''I have spent a lot of time analyzing my own games,'' Kraai said. ''When you are older, it is not like you are going to make all kinds of leaps and bounds by memorizing openings. But as an older player, we can really reflect on the decision-making process.''</p>
        <p>Kraai, who has a Ph.D. in philosophy from the University of Heidelberg, said he had learned to be less impetuous and laughed as he recalled that five years ago the headline on Robert Byrne's chess column in The New York Times about one of his losses was ''An Itchy Trigger Finger Draws Lethal Return Fire.''</p>
        <p>His newfound patience served him well in his seventh-round victory over Hikaru Nakamura, 19, a former United States champion.</p>
        <p>It is rare that a game between high-level players produces a position that does not appear in online databases by Move 7, but that is what happened. Kraai was trying to restrain Nakamura, an aggressive player, without taking undue risks.</p>
        <p>In years past, Kraai said, he would have played 12 e4 to open up the center. With his new self-awareness, he realized that would be premature. ''I had to pull out and not do it,'' he said, so he played 12 a3 instead, a move he said he was proud of.</p>
        <p>Nakamura may have grown frustrated by White's patience, which may explain why he played 14  g5, an attempt to start an attack and create an unbalanced position. But instead of creating play for himself, the move opened weaknesses in his position.</p>
        <p>His 18  b5 was a horrible positional concession to try to prevent c4, but it created other problems. Then, weakened on the queenside, he had to launch a kingside attack.</p>
        <p>But Kraai played carefully and allowed no counterplay. Nakamura fought on, but in the end, facing heavy material losses, he gave up.</p>
        <p>CHESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
