<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lego Picks Up the Pieces After Layoffs and Moves</title>
    <meta content="15ctmainCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15ctmain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="INDUSTRY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Enfield (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lego Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laursen, Soren Torp</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Lego Group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE3D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lego Picks Up the Pieces After Layoffs and Moves</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lego Picks Up the Pieces After Layoffs and Moves</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA WOLFE BOYNTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</byline>
      <dateline>ENFIELD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lego Americas president Soren Torp Laursen, says toy company, which has laid off 300 employees at its complex in Enfield, Conn, and plans to sell 230-acre campus and move production south, says worldwide operations have been remolded to go 'back to the basics'; says company will no longer try to create products to compete with electronic gaming companies; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OUTDOOR stacks of oversize red, blue and yellow Legos make the building block company's North American headquarters look like a fun place. But after laying off 300 employees, selling its 230-acre campus and moving production south, the Danish company has shown that it knows how to play rough when it has to.</p>
        <p>Faced with financial losses and losing the battle for children's attention spans to Game Boys and other electronic gadgets, Lego operations worldwide have been remolded to go ''back to the basics,'' said Soren Torp Laursen, 43, president of Lego Americas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faced with financial losses, Lego has had to lay off employees at its North American headquarters, sell its 230-acre campus and move production to Mexico.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OUTDOOR stacks of oversize red, blue and yellow Legos make the building block company's North American headquarters look like a fun place. But after laying off 300 employees, selling its 230-acre campus and moving production south, the Danish company has shown that it knows how to play rough when it has to.</p>
        <p>Faced with financial losses and losing the battle for children's attention spans to Game Boys and other electronic gadgets, Lego operations worldwide have been remolded to go ''back to the basics,'' said Soren Torp Laursen, 43, president of Lego Americas.</p>
        <p>That has meant laying off 1,200 employees worldwide, refocusing on the building bricks that made Lego a household name and no longer trying to create products to compete with electronic gaming companies like Nintendo and Sony -- a mistake Lego made in the late 1990s, Mr. Laursen said.</p>
        <p>For the Enfield campus, which until earlier this year consisted of five buildings totaling nearly 1.1 million square feet, it has meant moving warehousing and packaging to Mexico, distribution to Texas and order fulfillment to Tennessee -- areas where costs are significantly lower, Mr. Laursen said.</p>
        <p>Most laid-off employees and the last pieces of equipment left the plant at the end of March. What remain are Lego's North American sales, marketing and administrative offices, housed in two buildings that have been leased back from Equity Industrial Partners, which bought the campus in January.</p>
        <p>''We've tried to underscore the fact that we're not leaving Connecticut, but changing the way we do business,'' said Mr. Laursen, who often plays with loose Lego bricks he keeps in a bowl on his desk. ''Moving production and manufacturing was necessary for us to stay competitive, but there are still 500 people who work here in Enfield on the corporate side.''</p>
        <p>Enfield officials, however, have mixed emotions about Lego's new configuration, the town manager, Matthew W. Coppler, said.</p>
        <p>As the town's largest employer and taxpayer since opening in 1975, Lego has long been a source of pride for the community, Mr. Coppler said. Most of the town's business development materials feature Lego as Enfield's leading industry. Life-size Lego ghosts, police officers and other building-block creations around the campus also attract visitors who might not otherwise come to Enfield, which is 15 miles north of Hartford, close to the Massachusetts border.</p>
        <p>Lego will still be among Enfield's top employers, and the campus's purchase means the town will not lose any property tax dollars.</p>
        <p>But the loss of 300 jobs is not easy to get over.</p>
        <p>''The job loss hurts,'' said Mr. Coppler, who was appointed town manager last June, shortly before Lego announced its downsizing plan. ''Any time a large business closes or relocates, the impact on people and families is what matters most.''</p>
        <p>Over the past nine months, those receiving pink slips have been offered skills training, résumé help and emotional support to cope with the change, said Julie Stern, a company spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>The majority of employees stayed to help the company break down operations, she said. One of those who stayed is Peter Uricchio, an Enfield resident who was a warehouse manager for 11 years and is now part of the transition team tying up loose ends before departing.</p>
        <p>''There's a real sense of loyalty among a lot of the people who work here,'' Mr. Uricchio said. ''That doesn't mean the layoffs were easy. Many of the guys on the production floor were people who came here straight from high school and worked here all their adult life. They seemed to have the hardest time.''</p>
        <p>They should have been the people least surprised by Lego's decision to downsize, Mr. Laursen said. Lego experienced its first financial loss in 1998, and two years later, Enfield employees watched as brick-molding operations were moved to Denmark. Until then, Enfield was the only plant in the United States where bricks had been made.</p>
        <p>''None of the changes we've made over the past several years were easy,'' Mr. Laursen said. ''But because of them, Lego can reconfirm its plans to stay both in Connecticut and the toy industry. Despite an overwhelming interest today in cellphones and joysticks, there are still Lego kids out there -- kids who want to build, construct and role-play.''</p>
        <p>Eighth graders at Tomlinson Middle School in Fairfield sure do, said their technology teacher, Catherine Audet. For more than 12 years, Ms. Audet has used Lego bricks to teach engineering and problem-solving. She also runs a Lego Club for middle schoolers on Monday afternoons.</p>
        <p>''Legos are great teaching tools, because students who create with them don't see what they're doing as learning; they see it as play,'' Ms. Audet said. ''That goes for children, as well as adults.''</p>
        <p>While the playfulness that employees used to feel at the Enfield plant is gone, there is no bitterness, said a former supply manager, Robert Motykav, of Springfield, Mass., which is about 10 miles north of Enfield.</p>
        <p>''Anyone who's been through layoffs before knows that business is business,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Even when the company was having some really bad years, they were always good to me. So I can't complain. Not everyone feels this way, but I do.''</p>
        <p>INDUSTRY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
