<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stung by a Fraud Indictment, A Power Broker Punches Back</title>
    <meta content="15stockman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/business/15stockman.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Collins &amp; Aikman Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Landon Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stockman, David A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Collins &amp; Aikman Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stockman, David A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stung by a Fraud Indictment, A Power Broker Punches Back</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stung by a Fraud Indictment, a Power Broker Punches Back</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LANDON THOMAS Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thomas, Landon Jr</byline>
      <dateline>ASPEN, Colo.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>President Reagan's budget director David A Stockman faces trial on fraud charges after his attempt to save auto parts maker Collins &amp; Aikman from bankruptcy failed; company's board fired Stockman as chief executive over financial disclosure irregularities; government intends to make case that Stockman engaged in deceptions and sham transactions to save company and his investment in it; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David A. Stockman is trying to unwind at his second home here after another long day spent scouring legal documents. Dinner at a restaurant with his wife, Jennifer, has been a balm, to say nothing of the big glass of scotch he has nursed throughout the evening.</p>
        <p>He has much to brood over. Mr. Stockman, President Ronald Reagan's budget director, is facing a trial next year on fraud charges after his attempt to save an auto parts maker from bankruptcy had failed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>David A. Stockman, President Ronald Reagan’s budget director, is facing a trial on fraud charges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David A. Stockman is trying to unwind at his second home here after another long day spent scouring legal documents. Dinner at a restaurant with his wife, Jennifer, has been a balm, to say nothing of the big glass of scotch he has nursed throughout the evening.</p>
        <p>He has much to brood over. Mr. Stockman, President Ronald Reagan's budget director, is facing a trial next year on fraud charges after his attempt to save an auto parts maker from bankruptcy had failed.</p>
        <p>''How can you end up losing $13 million of your own money and $350 million of your fund's and still end up with 30 years in jail?'' he asks.</p>
        <p>His anger builds. ''It's wrong. It's sick. I had an honorable career in public and private life and now this prosecutor goes after me as if I were a -- ''</p>
        <p>''Criminal,'' his wife breaks in, saying what Mr. Stockman could not.</p>
        <p>Since his days as a Marxist firebrand in the 1960s, Mr. Stockman, now 60, has pursued ideas that fired his ambitions. As budget chief in 1981, he advocated tax cuts and blamed congressmen, lobbyists and Pentagon bureaucrats for his failure to manage the Reagan budget.</p>
        <p>Now having been ousted as chief executive of the auto parts maker Collins &amp; Aikman by his handpicked board over financial disclosure irregularities, he is casting his fraud indictment as a similarly wrongheaded action by regulators, prosecutors and lawyers. In an earlier time, Mr. Stockman had mere scorn for such people. Now it is anger as he copes with the blow to his reputation, the loss of the fund company he founded and the looming prospect of spending his retirement years in a federal prison. A pretrial hearing is set for tomorrow.</p>
        <p>''The idea that there was this conspiracy does not connect in the remotest to the facts of life,'' he said. ''I had no motive. This is crazy. This case is a dangerous criminalization of a business failure fueled by Sarbanes-Oxley vendors.''</p>
        <p>This suffer-no-fools disposition harks back to an early embrace of the writings of Theodore J. Lowi, the political scientist who argued that the art of making policy should be the preserve of sophisticated practitioners like Mr. Stockman. It now shapes Mr. Stockman's attitude toward his current tormentors.</p>
        <p>''It's amateur hour,'' Mr. Stockman said, speaking of Helen V. Cantwell, the lead prosecutor on the case. ''The prosecutors don't seem to understand bank covenants, accounting and even basic business operations.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the United States attorney's office in Manhattan said that Ms. Cantwell would have no comment. But the government intends to make the case that Mr. Stockman engaged in a conspiracy of deceptions and sham transactions to save not just the company but the significant investment he had in it.</p>
        <p>Being dismissive of bureaucrats, lawyers and regulators may make for good politics in Washington, but in today's world, with heightened levels of regulatory and legal scrutiny brought on by Sarbanes-Oxley legislation, such an approach can have dangerous repercussions. In March, a federal grand jury in Manhattan indicted Mr. Stockman on charges including bank fraud, conspiracy and obstruction of justice.</p>
        <p>There is a frantic aspect to Mr. Stockman these days. The big-framed glasses that defined his brash, whiz-kid demeanor in the 1980s have been traded for a tortoise-shell look. But his searing, unblinking stare remains the same and the prospect of a life spent in prison has brought fear and a bit of panic to his notorious workaholic ways.</p>
        <p>His hands shake as he leafs through piles of Collins &amp; Aikman spreadsheets, rattling off reams of arcane data and ratios to support his claim that he never booked an inappropriate rebate, fudged liquidity levels or exaggerated cash flow forecasts, as the prosecution maintains.</p>
        <p>A day's growth of stubble gives him an air of distraction. His wife is concerned about his health.</p>
        <p>''This could destroy your life,'' he said. ''I have to think how I keep my life and family going.''</p>
        <p>The life of an indicted former chief executive can be a lonely one. There is no more office to go to, no around-the-world trips on corporate jets, and aside from calls from lawyers -- Mr. Stockman has two law firms working for him -- the phone rings less often. With one daughter away at college and another beginning a new job, the big rambling house in Greenwich, Conn., can seem empty.</p>
        <p>Mr. and Ms. Stockman, who is co-chairwoman of the Republican Majority for Choice, an abortion-rights group, say that friends have reached out to them. And while he has friends on Wall Street, in the current glare, just a few have spoken up.</p>
        <p>He is a ''very good boy scout,'' said James S. Tisch, the chief executive of the Loews Corporation. Warren B. Rudman, the former New Hampshire senator who is a longtime director of Collins &amp; Aikman and has known Mr. Stockman since his Washington days, said: ''You feel badly when someone gets into that kind of trouble.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stockman does make brief stabs at black humor. He chuckles that he has a brother who is a corrections officer and notes the odd fate of spending his first day in court at the Daniel Patrick Moynihan courthouse, named for the late New York senator who gave him his entree into politics.</p>
        <p>Some who have worked with Mr. Stockman on Wall Street, where he was an early partner of the private equity firm Blackstone Group, say that he was known for having a devotion to his own numbers and analysis that could blind his judgment.</p>
        <p>''David is often messianic,'' said Roger C. Altman, a former partner at Blackstone. ''But the David I know is not one I would associate with criminal intent.''</p>
        <p>Many remember his rapid rise in Washington from an aide to a House member to the youngest cabinet officer of the last century.</p>
        <p>''He is truly, truly ambitious in the non-flattering sense,'' said Arthur B. Laffer, the supply-side economist and adviser to President Reagan who still fumes over the critical comments Mr. Stockman made about the president's tax cuts in an article in The Atlantic Monthly in 1981. ''I don't wish him evil or pain; all I know is what I saw gave me a window into his character.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stockman's involvement with Collins &amp; Aikman dates to 1988, when he first invested in the company while at Blackstone. In 2001, having started his own buyout firm, Heartland Industrial Partners, he snapped up a majority share.</p>
        <p>Collins &amp; Aikman, once a flagging 1970s-era conglomerate, was a mish-mash of business from which Mr. Stockman, in the 1990s, carved out one that supplied interior parts to the major automobile manufacturers. Cheap oil would prompt continuing demand for S.U.V.'s and trucks made by the Big Three automakers in Detroit. Like his other grand notions, this one was bold, contrarian and, this time, disastrously wrong.</p>
        <p>Aiming to make Collins &amp; Aikman the dominant supplier, Mr. Stockman went on an acquisition spree, buying up competitors and saddling the company with additional debt.</p>
        <p>After the Sept. 11, 2001, attacks, the automobile industry came under increased pressure. With Collins &amp; Aikman's stock plummeting and investors becoming antsy, Mr. Stockman assumed leadership of the company in summer 2003, moving to Troy, Mich., from Greenwich.</p>
        <p>But business got worse. It was during this period that prosecutors say Mr. Stockman conspired to inflate the firm's cash flow by aggressively booking rebates from his suppliers and lying to his banks about his cash position.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stockman and his lawyers argue that there was no conspiracy. According to their account, meetings were held in the open and his bankers were also his investors and well aware of his cash reserves. More important, they say, Mr. Stockman never sold any stock during this time. From 2002 to 2004, he and Heartland invested $25 million more. The government says Mr. Stockman's fund collected $45 million in fees, half of which went to Mr. Stockman.</p>
        <p>''No crime was committed,'' said Elkan Abramowitz, the lead lawyer for Mr. Stockman. ''He has nothing to hide and we think the government will have a very hard time cross-examining him.''</p>
        <p>It is not clear that Mr. Stockman's public defense will pay off. ''The problem is that the court of public opinion is not the court that will hear the case,'' said Mark F. Pomerantz, a senior white-collar defense lawyer and former prosecutor. ''The notion that you can help persuade a jury now is sheer fancy and you certainly will not persuade the government.''</p>
        <p>In March 2005, the board's auditor, KPMG, raised questions about the accounting of rebates; KPMG then hired the law firm Davis Polk.</p>
        <p>Rumors had begun to spread that Collins &amp; Aikman was experiencing a liquidity crisis. On March 17, Mr. Stockman presented preliminary year-end results to investors. Badgered on the call by analysts about the firm's cash position, Mr. Stockman did his best to stay upbeat, while also laying out the challenges ahead.</p>
        <p>On May 9, Mr. Stockman made a last bid to save his company, securing, he says, a promise from Chrysler, Collins &amp; Aikman's largest customer, to give the company better pricing. Mr. Stockman was ecstatic.</p>
        <p>However, on that very afternoon, Mr. Stockman got a call from Dennis E. Glazer, a partner at Davis Polk. The law firm was now questioning whether Mr. Stockman gave overly optimistic forecasts during the March conference call.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stockman defended himself, saying that he had provided sufficient caveats. But Mr. Glazer was not convinced. In its indictment, the government would charge that Mr. Stockman drafted the materials and made ''at least three material misstatements or omissions.''</p>
        <p>Late the next night, Mr. Stockman received a call in his Troy, Mich., hotel room from Daniel P. Tredwell, his partner at Heartland. The board would ask for his resignation the next day. Mr. Stockman could not believe it. ''The audit committee had taken over the company and delegated authority to a lawyer from New York wearing suspenders,'' he says now. That night, he would add a third Klonopin anti-anxiety pill to the two he was taking each night to bring on sleep quickly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glazer declined to comment on the case, citing confidentiality.</p>
        <p>The next day the board demanded his resignation.</p>
        <p>''Leave your office now and don't take anything with you,'' Mr. Stockman recalled Mr. Glazer as saying.</p>
        <p>It had happened so quickly that he could not even call a lawyer.</p>
        <p>''I was in shock,'' he said. ''I had been with the company for 14 years -- I mean I had put this whole thing together. I had put these guys on the board, invested the money, owned the shares and they stabbed me in the back. It was like a Stalinist show trial.''</p>
        <p>A week later, on May 17, Collins &amp; Aikman filed for bankruptcy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
