<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine's Near-Deadly Crash Puts New Jersey Politics on an Uncertain Path</title>
    <meta content="15corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/15corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CORZINE'S CRASH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1548" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine's Near-Deadly Crash Puts New Jersey Politics on an Uncertain Path</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Crash Adds Uncertainty to New Jersey Politics</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER; David W. Chen and Mary Williams Walsh contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aides to New Jersey Gov Jon S Corzine say it could take week to 10 days before he is well enough to resume his duties after being in near-fatal car crash on Garden State Parkway on April 12; his injuries could sideline him at crucial time in his second year in office, when he is trying to gain favor with voters and make inroads with Trenton's political establishment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Members of the staff of Gov. Jon S. Corzine say it could take a week to 10 days before he is well enough to resume his duties as the governor of New Jersey. His doctor said it could be ''days or weeks.'' Six months may pass before he can get around by himself.</p>
        <p>No matter how long the recuperation, the incapacitating injuries that Mr. Corzine suffered Thursday evening, when his Chevrolet Suburban crashed on the Garden State Parkway near Atlantic City, come at an important moment both in state government and in the life of his young administration, politicians and analysts said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Gov. Jon S. Corzine’s convalescence is lengthy, the crash could define his first term and lead the state into murky waters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Members of the staff of Gov. Jon S. Corzine say it could take a week to 10 days before he is well enough to resume his duties as the governor of New Jersey. His doctor said it could be ''days or weeks.'' Six months may pass before he can get around by himself.</p>
        <p>No matter how long the recuperation, the incapacitating injuries that Mr. Corzine suffered Thursday evening, when his Chevrolet Suburban crashed on the Garden State Parkway near Atlantic City, come at an important moment both in state government and in the life of his young administration, politicians and analysts said.</p>
        <p>If his convalescence proves a lengthy one, they said, the crash could define his first term and lead the state into murky political waters.</p>
        <p>''From every point of view, this is not a fortuitous time for him or for the state,'' said Thomas H. Kean, a former governor of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine underwent another operation yesterday morning at Cooper University Hospital in Camden, N.J., as doctors tried to repair the injuries to his left leg. The doctors called the surgery ''uneventful'' and said that Mr. Corzine was improving.</p>
        <p>The crash comes as Mr. Corzine, 60, a former co-chairman of Goldman Sachs who has pledged to use his business acumen to shore up New Jersey's finances, was heading into his second budget battle with the State Legislature.</p>
        <p>Last year's epic fight was a test of stamina and brinksmanship. Mr. Corzine slept on a cot in his office for three nights in a row and shut down state government in order to win an agreement from lawmakers to raise the state sales tax.</p>
        <p>This year, the governor may have to negotiate the budget from a bed or a wheelchair. And while the next budget is not likely to be as contentious as the last -- it is an election year for lawmakers, and Mr. Corzine's proposal contained fewer politically difficult measures -- many challenges lie ahead.</p>
        <p>Among them is the state's crushing debt load. Many homeowners still complain about high property taxes, though they were granted some relief in last year's budget package. And for years, the state has put too little money in its pension system, casting doubt on whether it can meet its obligation to retirees.</p>
        <p>The financial outlook is so bleak that Mr. Corzine has proposed selling off state assets like the New Jersey Turnpike and the parkway on which he was injured.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's injuries could sideline him at a crucial time in his second year in office, when he is still trying to gain favor with voters and make inroads with Trenton's political establishment. He has also been asked to answer questions about his gifts to a former companion who is the president of a powerful state employees union.</p>
        <p>''It comes at a point where he's about to make the most critical decisions of his governorship,'' said Peter J. Woolley, a political scientist who is executive director of the Public Mind poll of Fairleigh Dickinson University. ''Are his injuries going to be so extensive that it's going to deter him physically and mentally from pushing his own agenda to fix the financial woes, or will he recover enough with enough determination and still enough political latitude that he'll be able to be effective?''</p>
        <p>The president of the State Senate, Richard J. Codey, became the acting governor this week for the third time -- he took over after Gov. James E. McGreevey resigned amid scandal in 2004 -- pledging to work to carry out the Corzine administration's agenda. ''It's their administration, not mine,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's chief of staff, Tom Shea, said on Friday that it was unclear exactly when Mr. Corzine would be able to resume his duties.</p>
        <p>''You know, he certainly needs the ability to concentrate and focus and communicate in order to effectively carry out the duties of his office,'' he said. ''And I think only time will tell how long that takes for us for him to be able to do that again.''</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Corzine's convalescence takes longer than expected, or if he should suffer setbacks that keep him from governing as the July 1 start of the fiscal year nears, the state could find itself in a peculiar situation: Mr. Codey, a fellow Democrat who has had political tensions with Mr. Corzine in recent years, would have to represent both the administration and the Senate in budget negotiations.</p>
        <p>''It's an outrageous conflict of interest,'' said Mr. Kean, a Republican.</p>
        <p>New Jersey voters agreed in 2005 to create the position of a lieutenant governor who would serve if a governor stepped down or could not serve, but the position will not be created until 2009.</p>
        <p>The accident comes a little more than a year after Mr. Corzine took office with the résumé of an outsider. As a former business executive and as a United States senator for five years, he has never had to forge the kind of direct, close connection with voters that people like to have with their governors.</p>
        <p>As a politician, Mr. Corzine can come across as a bit aloof, analysts said. He never toiled in the vineyards of local politics. He is not a natural glad-hander, or a stirring speaker, and he cuts an unconventional figure on the political scene with his scholarly-looking gray beard and trademark blue sweater vest.</p>
        <p>As former Gov. Brendan T. Byrne said: ''Governor Corzine is respected, I think, in virtually all quarters. He's not the warm and fuzzy type Codey is. But I think he is well respected and listened to.''</p>
        <p>A February poll from Quinnipiac University suggested that voters were willing to give him the benefit of the doubt, but not with a lot of enthusiasm. Fifty percent of those polled approved of his performance, while 34 percent disapproved, his highest ratings yet; but only 20 percent said that things had improved under his watch, while 15 percent said the opposite.</p>
        <p>And while several political analysts said that Mr. Corzine had been working to forge closer connections with voters -- by going to town meetings, dinners and fund-raisers for local officeholders -- injuries that limit his mobility could hinder those efforts. They could also limit his ability to campaign for legislative allies who face re-election this year.</p>
        <p>But some political analysts said that his accident and injuries would most likely engender sympathy for him as well. And they noted that the next election for governor is more than two years away.</p>
        <p>Of more pressing concern, analysts said, are the grave problems facing the state.</p>
        <p>The second year is critical in any governor's four-year term, political scientists said. The first year is often spent assembling an administration and learning how state government works. By the third and fourth years, political capital has a habit of eroding, and a re-election campaign can distract politicians from governing. So the second year is prime time for attempting ambitious, politically risky measures.</p>
        <p>''I think this comes at a particularly unfortunate time,'' said Ross K. Baker, a political scientist at Rutgers University. ''The problems with the state pension fund were only just revealed, and he had resolved to see that it was set right. And he was in a unique position to try to find some way out of this problem for a state that was already bogged down in serious debt, and his background in finance made him uniquely suited to do it.''</p>
        <p>The pension fund's problems are staggering. The state failed for years to make the required annual contributions, and used questionable accounting methods to hide the true condition of the funds. And just as a few late credit card payments can cause anindividual's debt to balloon, the missing pension contributions have made the state's pension shortfall soar.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine tried to break with the past, ordering the first significant pension contributions in a decade. But because of the years of neglect, even that has not been able to keep up with the required amounts. That is one reason he has been weighing the sale of state assets.</p>
        <p>Joseph R. Marbach, the acting dean of the College of Arts and Sciences at Seton Hall University, said a lengthy convalescence could place Mr. Corzine's proposals to sell assets like the toll roads and the lottery on the back burner. ''That may be taken off the table entirely, while the state applies a Band-Aid approach,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Eric Shuffler, who was a top aide to Mr. Codey and Mr. McGreevey, and who has written speeches for Mr. Corzine, said he expected Mr. Corzine to be able to resume his duties soon. ''I think the biggest thing for the governor is that there is so much he wants to do, and so much he is trying to do, and this is a loss of time for an agenda that is quite ambitious,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Professor Baker, of Rutgers, noted how strange it was that Mr. Corzine was critically injured while on his way to broker a meeting between the Rutgers women's basketball team and Don Imus, the talk-show host who was fired for making racist and sexist comments about them.</p>
        <p>''It would be treated as bad fiction if this had appeared between two covers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>CORZINE'S CRASH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
