<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chicago Wins U.S.O.C. Bid For 2016 Summer Games</title>
    <meta content="15usoc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070417T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EED9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chicago Wins U.S.O.C. Bid For 2016 Summer Games</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moments after Chicago beat out Los Angeles on Saturday to be the United States' bid city for the 2016 Summer Olympics, representatives from Chicago's Olympic bid stopped floating and got serious.</p>
        <p>''We're going to go to work, probably tonight, maybe tomorrow, certainly no later than tomorrow,'' said Pat Ryan, chairman of the city's bid committee. ''It's just the beginning. It's a long road.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moments after Chicago beat out Los Angeles on Saturday to be the United States' bid city for the 2016 Summer Olympics, representatives from Chicago's Olympic bid stopped floating and got serious.</p>
        <p>''We're going to go to work, probably tonight, maybe tomorrow, certainly no later than tomorrow,'' said Pat Ryan, chairman of the city's bid committee. ''It's just the beginning. It's a long road.''</p>
        <p>Winning the bid means Chicago is now in competition again, this time with several international cities, to win the 2016 Summer Games. The goal is to win at least 60 votes from the International Olympic Committee in the final stage of voting, which will take place in October 2009. Madrid, Prague, Rio de Janeiro, Rome and Tokyo are expected to be in the mix.</p>
        <p>The 11-member United States Olympic Committee board took about two hours Saturday before announcing that Chicago was the city that would advance to that final cut. The vote, which U.S.O.C. Chairman Peter V. Ueberroth called ''a very tough decision,'' left Los Angeles's representatives stunned as the Chicago contingent erupted in cheers.</p>
        <p>Chicago has never played host to an Olympics, while Los Angeles has had two Games, in 1932 and 1984; the 1984 Olympics was the first to end with a profit.</p>
        <p>Mayor Richard M. Daley of Chicago was among those who jumped to his feet Saturday. It was, ''like a kid watching the Olympics,'' he said. Mayor Antonio Villaraigosa of Los Angeles rushed to congratulate Daley.</p>
        <p>''This is a proud moment for every Chicagoan, but it's also a proud moment for all of us,'' said Villaraigosa, insisting that he would support Chicago's bid because he would like to see the Olympics come to the United States.</p>
        <p>In the early afternoon Saturday, representatives from Chicago and Los Angeles gave their final 40-minute presentations to the U.S.O.C. board. Each group said it felt confident that it had offered the best package for the Olympics, with the financing, the strategy and the enthusiasm to be a perfect host.</p>
        <p>Two hours later, after a closed vote, U.S.O.C. officials said both cities offered bids strong enough to have the Games.</p>
        <p>Bob Ctvrtlik, chairman of the U.S.O.C.'s candidate city evaluation committee, said Chicago won partly because of its financial guarantees and its plan for new facilities, particularly a $1.1 billion athletes village on Lake Michigan, south of downtown, and an 80,000-seat, temporary Olympic stadium costing $366 million. He said that the waterfront area would ''recreate a certain magic'' that the Olympics needed to succeed.</p>
        <p>U.S.O.C. officials had a specific list of requirements for success in the bidding process. They asked for a carefully crafted financial plan and an Olympic stadium built or already approved. They also asked that the governments of the cities promise to guarantee to pay for any overruns if private financing failed to pay the cost of the Games.</p>
        <p>Chicago's pitch included $500 million in taxpayer-backed financial guarantees from the city council and more than $32 million from the private sector.</p>
        <p>The requirements show that the U.S.O.C. approached this selection differently than it had in the past, particularly in light of the failed New York City bid for the 2012 Games. In 2005, New York City went into the I.O.C.'s final vote on those Games without an Olympic stadium plan. The proposal for the West Side stadium had been defeated one month before.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 17, 2007, Tuesday  A sports article in some copies on Sunday about Chicago's selection as the United States' candidate for the 2016 Summer Olympics referred incorrectly to New York City's failed bid for the 2012 Olympics. The city's proposal included plans to build a stadium in Flushing in conjunction with the Mets; the bid was not submitted without plans for a stadium. (The NYC2012 group turned to the Flushing alternative late in the process, after plans fell apart for a West Side stadium in Manhattan.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 17, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A sports article in some copies on Sunday about Chicago's selection as the United States' candidate for the 2016 Summer Olympics referred incorrectly to New York City's failed bid for the 2012 Olympics. The city's proposal included plans to build a stadium in Flushing in conjunction with the Mets; the bid was not submitted without plans for a stadium. (The NYC2012 group turned to the Flushing alternative late in the process, after plans fell apart for a West Side stadium in Manhattan.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
