<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Delivery Is a Mainstay, a Rebellion Over Pay</title>
    <meta content="15delivery" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/15delivery.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delivery Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Picketing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saigon Grill (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ollie's (NYC Retsaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Delivery Is a Mainstay, a Rebellion Over Pay</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Delivery Is a Mainstay, a Rebellion Over Pay</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Restaurant deliverymen in Manhattan, most of them immigrants from China, are picketing restaurants like Saigon Grill and Ollie's, accusing them of paying as little as $1.40 an hour; have filed federal wage lawsuits against these companies, and their advocates say they will soon sue a dozen other restaurants in city; state law requires that deliverymen receive at least $4.85 an hour before tips; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They can usually be seen pedaling madly on Manhattan streets, often against traffic, rushing to satisfy New Yorkers' capacious appetites for cold sesame noodles and General Tso's chicken.</p>
        <p>But nowadays these restaurant deliverymen can increasingly be seen standing defiantly on the city's sidewalks, hoisting protest signs and shouting that they should be paid the minimum wage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Delivery workers have picketed New York restaurants and filed lawsuits claiming their pay falls far below the state’s minimum wage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They can usually be seen pedaling madly on Manhattan streets, often against traffic, rushing to satisfy New Yorkers' capacious appetites for cold sesame noodles and General Tso's chicken.</p>
        <p>But nowadays these restaurant deliverymen can increasingly be seen standing defiantly on the city's sidewalks, hoisting protest signs and shouting that they should be paid the minimum wage.</p>
        <p>Call it the deliverymen's rebellion. These workers, almost all of them immigrants from China, have picketed several Saigon Grill, Ollie's and Our Place outlets, accusing these well-known Asian restaurants of paying them as little as $1.40 an hour, far less than the federal and state minimum wage. The workers have filed federal wage lawsuits in Manhattan against those restaurant companies, and their advocates say they will soon sue a dozen other restaurants in the city.</p>
        <p>''The conditions are pretty bad in all the restaurants, so there's no real advantage to switch to another restaurant,'' said Yu Guan Ke, a deliveryman who said Saigon Grill usually paid him just $120 in wages for his 75-hour weeks. ''Before we would accept whatever wages they would give us, but now we see we should stand up for what we're entitled to under the law.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ke, one of the plaintiffs, said his pay came to $1.60 an hour before tips; New York State law requires that deliverymen receive at least $4.85 an hour before tips. He said he worked 10:30 a.m. to 11:30 p.m. six days a week and often received $100 a day in tips, making 20 to 30 deliveries a day. (The state minimum wage is $7.15 an hour for non-tipped workers, $2 higher than the federal minimum.)</p>
        <p>The deliverymen's movement has picked up steam for numerous reasons, among them that many of the workers hail from the same towns in Fujian Province and often compare notes. And they have been emboldened by strikes and lawsuits that improved wages at some restaurants in Chinatown, giving them hope of obtaining similar raises at restaurants uptown.</p>
        <p>In one lawsuit, against New Silver Palace, one of Chinatown's largest restaurants, a judge awarded $2.9 million in back wages to 17 workers in late 2003; the restaurant, now closed, also reached a $500,000 settlement with other workers.</p>
        <p>And in February, a federal judge ordered 88 Palace, another Chinatown restaurant, to pay 11 workers $700,000 in back wages and punitive damages after finding that managers had illegally taken part of their tips. The restaurant's lawyer said it was considering whether to appeal.</p>
        <p>''Restaurants in Chinatown are really in trouble because of high rents and because they're not attracting many tourists,'' said Peter Kwong, a Hunter College professor and an author of ''Chinese America: The Untold Story of America's Oldest New Community.''</p>
        <p>''As a result, many Chinese restaurants are moving uptown,'' he added. ''In Chinatown the restaurants play hardball with their workers, and the same attitude prevails in these new restaurants. They squeeze their workers real hard. And they feel they can do that because many of the workers just got off the boat.''</p>
        <p>But now the workers are pushing back, fed up with what they say is restaurants' failing to pay minimum wage, making improper deductions, taking from the tip pool, not reimbursing them for expenses like bicycles and not paying for medical care when deliverymen are hit by cars.</p>
        <p>''People see that conditions are getting worse unless they stand up,'' said Nelson Mar, president of the 318 Restaurant Workers Union, which represents waiters, busboys and deliverymen at more than a dozen Asian restaurants. ''The rents and the cost of doing business are going up.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''There's more pressure on bosses, and instead of trying to bargain with landlords for better rents, they cheat their workers. Workers don't have any options except to accept it or fight.''</p>
        <p>The fiercest dispute revolves around Saigon Grill, which has locked out 30 delivery workers and suspended delivery at its branches at Amsterdam Avenue and 90th Street on the Upper West Side and on University Place in Greenwich Village. Outside both restaurants, a dozen deliverymen protest several times a week, urging a boycott.</p>
        <p>According to the workers, the owner got wind of their pending lawsuit and told the deliverymen that they could not work unless they signed statements saying that Saigon Grill had always paid them at least the minimum wage.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't sign it,'' said Mr. Ke, 36, who began working at Saigon Grill a decade ago. ''We couldn't lie about the conditions that were taking place.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ke and other deliverymen said in the lawsuit that Saigon Grill fined them $200 if a customer complained about a late delivery and $50 if they shut the restaurant's door too loudly on their way out.</p>
        <p>He has been locked out for a month, and his wife, a restaurant worker, is out of work after giving birth four months ago. They are in such financial straits, he said, that they borrowed money to fly their infant daughter home to China so his mother could care for her.</p>
        <p>Simon Nget, Saigon Grill's owner, did not respond to several telephone calls seeking comment, but in a letter to customers, he said: ''I have always paid my deliverymen what is required by law, paid their taxes and paid their benefits. They have no legitimate complaint.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nget added, ''These deliverymen behave like thugs and gangsters and have threatened me, my family and my inside workers.''</p>
        <p>At lunchtime one recent day, whenever someone approached the front door of the Saigon Grill on Amsterdam Avenue, those on the picket line thundered, ''Boycott Saigon Grill.'' One picket sign read, ''Don't support the illegal lockout.''</p>
        <p>People inside peered out uneasily, trying to figure out what was happening.</p>
        <p>''It's very sad what's going on,'' said June Choi, a customer who had walked into the restaurant before the protesters gathered on the sidewalk. ''We totally forgot about the dispute. I feel really bad for them. I wouldn't have gone in if I had seen them.''</p>
        <p>Another customer, Michelle Gewirtz, an art conservator, said she knew little about the dispute. ''Saigon Grill is a favorite restaurant of ours, and I hope they try to resolve it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Jim Cifelli, a teacher at the Trinity School on the Upper West Side, stopped by to chat with some of the picketing workers. He said he had stopped patronizing Saigon Grill once the lockout began.</p>
        <p>''The law is the law, and if you don't pay the minimum wage, then you shouldn't even be in business,'' Mr. Cifelli said.</p>
        <p>The Chinese are by no means the only ethnic group working low-wage restaurant jobs, but they have pushed harder for their rights than others because of their sheer numbers and because they are backed by some forceful advocacy groups.</p>
        <p>One major backer is the Chinese Staff and Workers' Association, a Chinatown group that helped spawn the 318 union and has spent decades battling for sweatshop workers. That association and the union have created a campaign called Justice Will Be Served, which is fighting on behalf of immigrant restaurant and grocery workers, with an eye to helping nail salon workers next.</p>
        <p>The deliverymen also have some powerful legal backing, including the Asian American Legal Defense and Education Fund, the Urban Justice Center and prestigious law firms like Shearman and Sterling.</p>
        <p>''We encouraged workers to contact friends or co-workers, and then those friends and co-workers go to 10 other restaurant workers,'' said Wing Lam, 57, the founder of the Chinese Staff and Workers' Association. Mr. Lam has spent years collecting employees' stories as ammunition for lawsuits, unionization efforts and enforcement actions by the state.</p>
        <p>While minimum wage laws cover both legal and illegal immigrants, employers are not supposed to hire immigrants who do not have valid work documents. So illegal immigrants from China often find themselves in a vise, sometimes trying to pay off $50,000 or more in smugglers' fees while worrying that they may be fired at any time.</p>
        <p>''The bosses sow divisions between undocumented and documented workers,'' said Josephine Lee, a 27-year-old daughter of immigrant restaurant workers and the campaign coordinator for Justice Will Be Served, who organizes picket lines and news conferences when not working as a waitress at Zen Palate. ''The boss makes documented workers fear that they will lose their jobs to undocumenteds, and they use that threat to worsen conditions for undocumented and documented workers.''</p>
        <p>Besides complaints about low pay, the deliverymen for Saigon Grill and Ollie's said in their lawsuits that if they were robbed, their employers deducted half or all the stolen money from their paychecks.</p>
        <p>''It's horribly unfair,'' said Guo Ping Li, a former Ollie's deliveryman. ''I was robbed of $300 at gunpoint on 93rd Street, and Ollie's made me pay them $150. That's three or four days' pay.''</p>
        <p>The lawsuit against Ollie's asserts that such deductions are illegal because they pull workers' pay below the minimum wage. The suit involves three of the five Ollie's restaurants in Manhattan: those on West 44th Street and on Broadway at 68th and 84th Streets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Li said he was fired after he missed work to attend his brother's wedding. He cleared the absence in advance with the restaurant, he said, but was told later that he had not followed proper procedure. He said he suspected his protests about low pay were the real reason for his firing.</p>
        <p>Gui Ming Li, another deliveryman at Ollie's, who said he worked 70 hours a week and received $165 a week in wages, said: ''We went to the State Department of Labor a year ago to complain, but they work very slowly. That's why we brought a lawsuit.''</p>
        <p>M. Patricia Smith, the state's new labor commissioner, has vowed to speed up efforts and conduct a full investigation.</p>
        <p>Tsu Yue Wang, the owner of Ollie's, did not return several telephone calls for comment, but Tommy Chu, the manager of Ollie's on West 44th Street, denied that many employees worked 11-hour days, saying they received several hours of breaks each day.</p>
        <p>Dawn Cardi, a lawyer for Our Place on Third Avenue at 82nd Street, the third restaurant being sued, said the owner, Kong Ping Chen, ''is a hardworking immigrant, and he's trying to do the right thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
