<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Look at the Roots From Which Pop Art Sprang</title>
    <meta content="15njartsNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15njarts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840432"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Princeton University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Princeton University Art Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E5DE133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Look at the Roots From Which Pop Art Sprang</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Look at the Roots of Pop Art</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews Pop art exhibit at Princeton University; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is something sneakily powerful about Pop Art, the movement that flourished in the 1960s and 70s, drawing its inspiration from popular culture, the news media and advertising imagery. Perhaps that is why it appeals to art audiences almost a half century later. It generally doesn't overstimulate the brain with ideas.</p>
        <p>''Pop Art at Princeton: Permanent and Promised,'' at the Princeton University Art Museum, feels like a refresher class in art history. That is appropriate, for like many exhibitions here it is designed to augment the university's art history programs. It also coincides with the publication of a handsome book, a monograph on the museum's deep and wide Pop Art collection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pop Art, the movement that flourished in the 1960s and 70s, generally doesn’t overstimulate the brain with ideas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is something sneakily powerful about Pop Art, the movement that flourished in the 1960s and 70s, drawing its inspiration from popular culture, the news media and advertising imagery. Perhaps that is why it appeals to art audiences almost a half century later. It generally doesn't overstimulate the brain with ideas.</p>
        <p>''Pop Art at Princeton: Permanent and Promised,'' at the Princeton University Art Museum, feels like a refresher class in art history. That is appropriate, for like many exhibitions here it is designed to augment the university's art history programs. It also coincides with the publication of a handsome book, a monograph on the museum's deep and wide Pop Art collection.</p>
        <p>While the monograph is philosophically ambitious and periodically absorbing, the same cannot be said for the show. Conventionally hung in rough chronological order, the selection is restricted to a narrow band of well-known and celebrated Pop artists and their precursors. No individual works by women are included, though in fairness Pop Art was primarily a men's movement.</p>
        <p>Princeton's collection bears some of the responsibility for the show's shortcomings, for although the collection contains many outstanding works of Pop Art, it is by no means comprehensive. Even so, you have to question the merits of assembling an exhibition largely for teaching purposes that provides such a limited view of art history.</p>
        <p>The show is made up of more than 80 paintings, prints, drawings and sculptures, filling the museum's temporary exhibition galleries. Some of them are old favorites, hanging regularly in the permanent collection rooms, like Andy Warhol's ''Brillo Box'' (1964) and ''Blue Marilyn'' (1962), but much of the work is seldom shown. This gives the exhibition a certain curiosity value.</p>
        <p>The opening room looks at the range of issues and art-making techniques from which Pop Art sprang. Major experimental prints by Robert Rauschenberg, with layered illustrations appropriated from newspapers, open the display, followed by colorful prints and sculptures by Robert Indiana, Alex Katz, Allan D'Arcangelo, Jasper Johns and Jim Dine. The selection reminds us that Pop Art was primarily a sculpture and printmaking movement.</p>
        <p>One of the show's better qualities is that it provides a range of works by individual artists. In one room, for instance, there is a group of more than a dozen works by Tom Wesselmann, among them treatments of the same subject. An especially interesting pairing is the juxtaposition of his early molded-plastic wall sculpture ''Still Life No. 54'' (1965) with his later, laser-cut steel assemblage ''Still Life With Orange and Tulip'' (1986-92).</p>
        <p>Mr. Wesselmann's ''Still Life No. 54'' is among the highlights of the exhibition. It is inspired by illuminated, vacuum-formed plastic gas station signs, the color fused onto the back of a molded transparent sheet producing a flat surface devoid of visible brushwork. Here the artist uses the same technology to create a still-life image of an old-fashioned radio and a juicy red apple on a kitchen shelf. It's funny.</p>
        <p>A range of finished works, drawings and models relating to this piece helps give the viewer a sense of how the work evolved out of his incorporation of real objects and collage elements into early still-life paintings and sculpture. But what is especially radical is the choice of such an unorthodox material.</p>
        <p>The rest of the room combines selected works from the museum's collection by George Segal, James Rosenquist and Edward Ruscha, with some new promised gifts of work by Mr. Wesselmann, Roy Lichtenstein, Warhol and Claes Oldenburg, who in recent years has begun collaborating with his wife, Coosje van Bruggen. Several of those collaborations are included here.</p>
        <p>A good deal of the material from the university's collection is work from the 1980s and 90s. It is great to see it here, for it is rarely on display in the museum, but its presence further complicates the basic art historical story the exhibition is trying to tell; not only is it out of historical sequence, but it is also not the work for which the artists are best known.</p>
        <p>Some famous and colorful prints -- several of them by Warhol, others by Lichtenstein -- round out the exhibition. There are Warhol's screen prints of Campbell's soup cans and portraits of Marilyn Monroe and Mao Zedong. Then there are Warhol prints based on appropriated media images of the assassination of President John F. Kennedy, race riots in Birmingham, Ala., and the electric chair.</p>
        <p>Although Warhol's source images for these darker prints are fairly crude, the images are fascinating, both for their sociological qualities and as a kind of exposé of popular culture. They make a bold statement about cultural attitudes during the period. Perhaps Pop Art was not so flaky after all.</p>
        <p>''Pop Art at Princeton: Permanent and Promised,'' Princeton University Art Museum, through Aug. 12. Information: www.princetonartmuseum.org or (609) 258-3788.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
