<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lost Coins? Dime a Dozen. How About a Cannonball?</title>
    <meta content="15njtopicNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15njtopic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DISCOVERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Revolutionary War, American (1775-83)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Toms River (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DeGroot, Sean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holl, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDE133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lost Coins? Dime a Dozen. How About a Cannonball?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lost Coins? Dime a Dozen. How About a Cannonball?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holl, John</byline>
      <dateline>SOUTH TOMS RIVER</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Sean DeGroot of Seaside Park, NJ, who found active cannonball from Revolutionary War at park in South Toms River, NJ; other unexpected items that have been found while digging in New Jersey described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS common as the colorful towels, ice-filled coolers, anglers and playful yells along the state's shorelines during warm months are the beachcombers with metal detectors searching for treasure in the sand.</p>
        <p>Most find some loose change or the occasional piece of jewelry. Then there is Sean DeGroot, a Seaside Park man who found an active cannonball from the Revolutionary War in a park here in early March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stick a shovel in the ground and you might find a piece of history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS common as the colorful towels, ice-filled coolers, anglers and playful yells along the state's shorelines during warm months are the beachcombers with metal detectors searching for treasure in the sand.</p>
        <p>Most find some loose change or the occasional piece of jewelry. Then there is Sean DeGroot, a Seaside Park man who found an active cannonball from the Revolutionary War in a park here in early March.</p>
        <p>After digging through two feet of sand, he unearthed the cannonball, placed it in a bucket of water and took it back to his apartment, where he began to scrape away centuries of rust and dirt with a butter knife, police officials said. Then he discovered a fuse hole that began leaking gunpowder.</p>
        <p>''It was quite something,'' said Judy Appleby, Mr. DeGroot's landlord. ''It's a real piece of the past, something that belongs in a museum.''</p>
        <p>It is just another reminder of New Jersey's rich past and why it is possible to stick a shovel in the ground just about anywhere -- from the Pine Barrens to High Point -- and unearth history.</p>
        <p>''We have at least 12,000 years of human history in the state, and when you begin to start poking around and digging in New Jersey, you find unexpected things,'' said Maxine N. Lurie, a history professor at Seton Hall University. ''Sometimes you find a musket ball, but sometimes you find chemical waste.''</p>
        <p>Sandra DeGeneste of Orange found more than 200 logbooks from the White Star cruise ship line, placed in her house's walls as insulation, during a recent remodeling project. And several World War II military fuses were found in the sand at Surf City on Long Beach Island, unearthed during an Army Corps of Engineers project this spring.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeGroot, who declined several interview requests, uncovered ''an exciting, rare find,'' said Joe DeMarco, the owner of a metal detector shop in Millville and president of the South Jersey Metal Detecting Club.</p>
        <p>''Most people don't know what's under their feet as they walk along,'' Mr. DeMarco said, ''but we do.''</p>
        <p>For those building transportation projects or housing developments, construction sometimes takes a macabre turn.</p>
        <p>Four years ago, while excavating in Secaucus for the new 15X exit ramp for the New Jersey Turnpike, workers had to relocate a potter's field. Initially the workers expected to move 600 bodies, but they uncovered 4,571 remains and a trove of artifacts from the 1860s to the 1940s.</p>
        <p>''There were medals from World War I and the Civil War, coins, perfume and whiskey bottles, smoking pipes, a lot of stuff,'' said John M. Keller, a Turnpike Authority project supervisor. After hundreds of photos and careful documentation, the remains were reburied in Hackensack with their possessions.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeGroot told police officials he hoped to give the cannonball to a local museum, but any hopes of preservation were squashed by the New Jersey State Police, which deemed it unstable and ordered it destroyed.</p>
        <p>''We didn't want to take any chances,'' said Lt. Bill Lundon, director of the State Police Technical Response Bureau.</p>
        <p>He said the bomb squad is called out dozens of times a year to handle ordnance like the cannonball and old munitions uncovered by people clearing out a relative's house.</p>
        <p>As for the riverfront area where Mr. DeGroot found the cannonball, Andrew Izatt, chief of the South Toms River Police Department, said it was later searched by a bomb-detecting dog that turned up nothing. But Chief Izatt said he expected that as the weather gets warmer, people will start combing the park looking for their own piece of history.</p>
        <p>''We had the area checked,'' he said. ''It looks clear, but anything is possible.''</p>
        <p>DISCOVERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
