<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.R.A. Covers Bloomberg, And Results Aren't Pretty</title>
    <meta content="15nra" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/15nra.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Rifle Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">America's 1st Freedom (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mayors Against Illegal Guns</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardwell, Diane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Rifle Association</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEED9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.R.A. Covers Bloomberg, And Results Aren't Pretty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">N.R.A. Covers Bloomberg, and Results Aren’t Pretty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE CARDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cardwell, Diane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Rifle Association news magazine, America's 1st Freedom, depicts New York City Mayor Michael R Bloomberg as giant octopus on its April cover, and article and column inside are devoted to idea that he is extending his reach in his campaign against illegal guns; Bloomberg's coalition, Mayors Against Illegal Guns, just launched Web site and announced media campaign urging Congress to drop provision, supported by NRA, that limits release of data about guns recovered in crimes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg was looking for evidence that his campaign against illegal guns had caught the notice of the National Rifle Association, he would need to look no further than the current cover of America's 1st Freedom, the group's news magazine.</p>
        <p>''Tentacles!'' shouts the headline over a cartoon illustration of Mr. Bloomberg depicting him as a giant octopus, looking fierce and slightly insane, with serpentine arms swirling behind him. Inside are a main article, two sidebars and a column devoted to the idea that Mr. Bloomberg, as the cover puts it, is extending ''his reach, and his illegal antigun tactics, across America.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Articles in the magazine of the National Rifle Association argue that Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg is waging war on legal gun ownership.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg was looking for evidence that his campaign against illegal guns had caught the notice of the National Rifle Association, he would need to look no further than the current cover of America's 1st Freedom, the group's news magazine.</p>
        <p>''Tentacles!'' shouts the headline over a cartoon illustration of Mr. Bloomberg depicting him as a giant octopus, looking fierce and slightly insane, with serpentine arms swirling behind him. Inside are a main article, two sidebars and a column devoted to the idea that Mr. Bloomberg, as the cover puts it, is extending ''his reach, and his illegal antigun tactics, across America.''</p>
        <p>The issue, dated this month, was sent to as many as 600,000 of the N.R.A.'s 4 million members at a time when Mr. Bloomberg has been intensifying his efforts and as mayors across the country continue to sign on to the fight. On Thursday, Mr. Bloomberg and his coalition, Mayors Against Illegal Guns, launched a Web site, protectpolice.org, and announced a media campaign urging Congress to drop a provision, supported by the N.R.A., that limits the release of data about guns recovered in crimes.</p>
        <p>Nestled among ads in America's 1st Freedom for cigars, concealed gun holsters and imitation diamond rings are articles focusing on that provision and the Bloomberg administration's undercover sting operations to catch gun dealers outside the city who had been improperly selling their merchandise and whose guns had been linked to crimes in New York. Bloomberg officials have used those investigations in lawsuits to pressure the dealers into submitting to monitoring by a court-appointed special master.</p>
        <p>The cover article, which labels Mr. Bloomberg ''a billionaire, Boston-grown evangelist for the nanny state,'' argues that despite the mayor's carefully chosen words about keeping firearms out of the hands of criminals, he was actually waging war on legal gun ownership.</p>
        <p>''Beholden to nothing except his own ambitions, the mayor has established himself as a kind of national gun-control vigilante,'' writes James O. E. Norell, identified as a contributing editor. Calling the national coalition a ''cabal,'' Mr. Norell adds: ''Bloomberg's tentacles reach throughout the country to foist N.Y.C.-style gun control on you, your friends and neighbors.''</p>
        <p>Accompanying the article are two sidebars, one about a letter from the Justice Department warning Mr. Bloomberg's office that the sting operations may have crossed a legal line. The other profiles a couple, Joanne and Dino Longueira, who run a Staten Island gun shop, casting them as lonely holdouts against a hostile administration.</p>
        <p>Wayne LaPierre, executive vice president of the rifle association, said that Mr. Bloomberg was a natural subject for the publication, given the organization's focus on preserving the Second Amendment.</p>
        <p>''He's become the poster boy for gun bans in America,'' Mr. LaPierre said from St. Louis, where the group is holding its annual meeting, which ends today. ''Why wouldn't we put him on the cover?''</p>
        <p>For their part, Bloomberg administration officials, who emphasize that their fight is against criminal possession and use of guns and has nothing to do with Second Amendment protections, are taking the criticism as something of a compliment.</p>
        <p>''I think it's fair to say we have gotten their attention,'' said Edward Skyler, the deputy mayor overseeing the gun effort. ''It really shows how they talk out of both sides of their mouth, claiming to be against illegal guns while doing everything possible to undermine efforts to crack down on them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
