<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Calling All Jocks and Brainiacs Onstage</title>
    <meta content="15RweMusicalWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">La Gorce, Tammy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">High School Musical (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">High School Musical (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2207" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Calling All Jocks and Brainiacs Onstage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAMMY LA GORCE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">La Gorce, Tammy</byline>
      <dateline>MONTCLAIR, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on huge popularity of Disney's TV movie High School Musical, which is being staged at schools worldwide, including more than 100 elementary, middle and high schools in New York metropolitan area suburbs; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE dance routines have lost some of their Hollywood gloss, and occasionally a hormone-hijacked voice threatens to derail a duet. But herds of young actors have been saying the same thing since last fall, when Disney's ''High School Musical'' started hurtling into school drama departments: The show is unstoppable.</p>
        <p>The TV movie that set off a million adolescent singalongs before its soundtrack went on to become the biggest-selling album of last year is currently rah-rah-ing its way across more than 1,300 school stages worldwide, according to Disney officials; more than 100 of them are in elementary, middle and high schools in the suburbs around New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE dance routines have lost some of their Hollywood gloss, and occasionally a hormone-hijacked voice threatens to derail a duet. But herds of young actors have been saying the same thing since last fall, when Disney's ''High School Musical'' started hurtling into school drama departments: The show is unstoppable.</p>
        <p>The TV movie that set off a million adolescent singalongs before its soundtrack went on to become the biggest-selling album of last year is currently rah-rah-ing its way across more than 1,300 school stages worldwide, according to Disney officials; more than 100 of them are in elementary, middle and high schools in the suburbs around New York.</p>
        <p>The reason for its popularity is simple: ''It's a nice, big cupcake of a story,'' said David Simpatico, who wrote the book for the stage version. He attended a performance in late March by fourth and fifth graders at the Hillside Gifted and Talented Elementary School here, one he wanted to see because its actors were among the youngest to tackle the show.</p>
        <p>''For a lot of kids, 'High School Musical' is their first experience with a story they can really relate to,'' Mr. Simpatico said. ''The message is, 'You can be whatever you want to be,' and it thrills me that I'm able to be a part of it.''</p>
        <p>The story line is an inventive, poppy tapestry incorporating elements of ''West Side Story,'' ''Romeo and Juliet'' and ''Grease.'' The one- and two-act stage versions were concocted by Mr. Simpatico with Bryan Louiselle, who adapted the music in just four months after the movie's release in January of last year.</p>
        <p>''High School Musical'' charts the struggles of two teenagers, the basketball hero Troy and the eggheaded new girl Gabriella. Both want to play parts in the spring play, ''Juliet and Romeo'' (''a feminist reworking of 'Romeo and Juliet,' '' Mr. Simpatico said) at the fictional East High School. Peer pressure from their respective cliques, the Brainiacs and the Jocks, keeps them from auditioning. A hypercompetitive drama club queen, Sharpay, also works hard to stymie their ambitions.</p>
        <p>Where the movie had a flaky drama teacher, the play has a caring one -- a reflection of Mr. Simpatico's experience with his own drama teacher, Dorothy McLernon, who still teaches English at Palisades Park High School, as she has for 35 years. ''We felt the drama teacher wasn't taken seriously enough'' in the film version, Mr. Simpatico said. ''We wanted to show that she cares deeply about her students.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McLernon recalled Mr. Simpatico well but had never heard of ''High School Musical'' until she was contacted by a reporter last week. ''I'm pleased by all means,'' she said in a telephone interview about having influenced the stage version, ''but I never would have imagined it.''</p>
        <p>Where the movie had mostly duets, the theatrical version has some full choruses. For the one-act, 60-minute version at Hillside, 76 students aged 9 and 10 crammed the stage for a few big numbers. All had the chance to sing one of nine songs backed by a quartet of pit musicians.</p>
        <p>''Normally we'd do something like 'The Sound of Music,' '' said Deborah McHugh, who directed the play and has taught drama at Hillside for 18 years. ''But one day my colleagues and I were talking, and we decided we didn't want to do 'West Side Story' because there's too much violence. So we floated the idea of 'High School Musical.' The moment you say it to the kids, they're screaming. When I was a kid we screamed over the Beatles; this is what they're screaming for.</p>
        <p>''After I talked to my students, there was no way we couldn't do it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>At Fairfield Woods Middle School in Fairfield, Conn., Jeff McHugh, dean of students and co-director of three performances of the show there in late March, said, ''It speaks to middle school students really well.''</p>
        <p>It may speak to middle school students best of all, actually: ''Kids are walking around reciting the lines in their own personal lives, that's how well they fit,'' said Edward Tholl Jr., a teacher at Memorial Junior High School in Valley Stream, N.Y., who is directing the show with seventh through ninth graders for performances on April 20 and 21.</p>
        <p>Usually, adults can be counted on to get it wrong when it comes to accounting for what makes a hit among teenagers and those approaching adolescence. But the teachers and directors who shepherded hundreds of area students through performances of ''High School Musical'' this spring weren't completely off the mark when they ventured that the peer-pressure message struck a nerve.</p>
        <p>''Kids can really relate to the part about wanting to keep your friends but wanting to try something new and different,'' said Catherine Luciani, a 14-year-old eighth grader at Fairfield Woods who played Mrs. Darbus, the drama teacher, in the show. ''Kids can also relate to the little love story, and how that can make things hard with your friends.''</p>
        <p>Mostly, though, the screaming in the hallways reported by several teacher-directors when they announced the play would be staged owes itself to the TV movie's music and razor-sharp dialogue. ''People can connect to it because the music is so good,'' said Dylan Levinson, 12, who played Ryan, the brother of Sharpay, in the Fairfield Woods production. ''There hasn't been anything realistic like it. There's hip-hop in it and Broadway-type stuff. It really fits together well.''</p>
        <p>Johnny Shea, a Fairfield Woods seventh grader who played Troy, said he also loved the music, but mostly savored a zingy line he delivered to his Jock friends about seeing Gabriella over a winter-break ski trip: '' 'She was so hot the slopes turned to slush,' '' he said. ''Saying that was awesome.''</p>
        <p>Steve Fickinger, vice president of theatrical licensing at Disney, based in New York, said that ''High School Musical'' was being licensed faster than any other movie adaptation in history, but he acknowledged that many high school students were turning up their noses at it.</p>
        <p>''They love it, they know every lyric and every line, but they're not going to let you know they love it,'' he said. ''Disney characters are often aspirational. And who wants to be a 9th or 10th grader? A fourth or fifth grader. That's why it's working so well for the younger kids.''</p>
        <p>Lisa Larsen, chorale director at Coginchaug Regional High School in Durham, Conn., said her 30-member cast of 9th through 12th graders, rehearsing for performances on May 20 and 21, tells her it's ''babyish and silly.''</p>
        <p>''But then it comes out they've all seen it like 16 times,'' she said.</p>
        <p>At Trinity Elementary School in New Rochelle, the Brainiacs are struggling with fractions and the cheerleaders have yet to wear training bras. But the third, fourth and fifth graders putting on three performances at the school on April 19 to 21 have never been more gung-ho about giving a show, according to Janine Penta, a fourth-grade teacher and one of four directors. ''This is huge for them,'' she said. ''Some of them have even gone to audition for Broadway shows because of this experience.''</p>
        <p>Shows have ranged from elaborate to bare bones, depending in part on a school's resources. At Coleytown Middle School in Westport, Conn., which put on three performances in late March, Donna Molesworth, the parent producer, oversaw 20 committees of parent volunteers, who helped with everything from props to costuming to ticket sales.</p>
        <p>''At our school, we have kids who are so into theater they have agents,'' she said. ''They take this very seriously. Everybody pays a tremendous amount of attention.''</p>
        <p>Coleytown's ''High School Musical,'' with a cast of 100 students, sold out faster than any other performance in the school's history, Ms. Molesworth said. Auditions for the show started in November; by the last curtain, it had raised $30,000 for the school.</p>
        <p>At West Side Middle School in Waterbury, Conn., where the play will be performed May 18 and 19, circumstances have been very different. ''We hadn't had a play in quite a few years,'' said Michael Cappiello, the drama teacher, who joined the faculty in September. ''We don't have a large stage or even a backstage, so we had to go about it creatively,'' he said, using coasters to change scenery, for instance.</p>
        <p>''But I was committed to doing whatever we needed to do to get a show here -- some of these kids haven't even seen 'Wizard of Oz,' '' Mr. Cappiello said. ''It's a low-income, inner-city area. I wanted to open their eyes. That means we wear our own clothes for costumes, and we have to scramble to get kids rides home so they don't have to drop out. But they're committed. 'High School Musical' has created a lot of school spirit for us.''</p>
        <p>Putting on the show has demanded sacrifices. At Hillside in Montclair, students gave up lunch hours to squeeze in rehearsals, Ms. McHugh said; at Fairfield Woods, at least a few students' test scores suffered. ''We do 25 rehearsals in all,'' said Mr. McHugh of Fairfield Woods. ''But when it gets near to showtime, the rehearsals increase in intensity -- the first 10 rehearsals or so are two hours Monday, Thursday and Friday. But a week prior to the show, we go every day from 3 until around 6:30.''</p>
        <p>For this year's show, he said, his cast was especially eager to put in the time to get it together. For Dylan Levinson of Fairfield Woods, that meant a grade on a math test that he was less than proud of. ''I'm going to retake it,'' he said. Johnny Shea said he, too, would be retaking a test that fell on the day of the show's premiere.</p>
        <p>But at least one young actor managed to translate the hectic pace before the performances into improved study habits. ''I'm really upset now that it's over,'' said Mackenzie Dancho, 13, who played Gabriella in Fairfield Woods' late March production. ''When we had rehearsals and were getting ready there was so much to do all the time. It was good for me, because I'm a procrastinator, and I'd have to go right home and do my homework before soccer and religious school. There was no time for IM-ing and talking on the phone with my friends.</p>
        <p>''It's surprising,'' she said. ''I figured I'd be upset that I had no time to hang out with my friends. But it's the opposite. I really miss being in the show.''</p>
        <p>Whether ''High School Musical'' will be as popular with the next generation is still up for debate. Bill Ullman, drama director at Emerson Junior-Senior High School in Emerson, N.J., had to think hard before suggesting that the show, which 50 of his students will perform at the school through April 21, will outlast the hype. ''The music -- could it get to the point where it's just too 2007?'' he asked. ''Will we look at it as nostalgic? I don't know. I assume it'll be like 'Grease.' I think it'll live a long time.''</p>
        <p>A professional production that will kick off in Pittsburgh in June and tour the country through next spring will help. So will the play's timeless message of friendship.</p>
        <p>At Hillside in Montclair, Mr. Louiselle, who adapted the music for ''High School Musical,'' and Ken Cerniglia, the show's Disney dramaturge, clapped heartily on opening day and stayed to talk with a few student actors afterward. They had joined Mr. Simpatico for a firsthand look at how the show was translating to younger audiences.</p>
        <p>It was clear the feel-good spirit had affected Ayanda Thusi, 11, and Olivia Converse, 10. Ayanda, cast as Gabriella, was unable to play her role during the school-day matinee because of an illness. Olivia, her understudy, stepped up.</p>
        <p>''I think I did O.K., even though I messed up on the harmony two times and forgot a costume change,'' said Olivia, glancing at Ayanda. ''It was nerve-racking. Ayanda is the real Gabriella.''</p>
        <p>''I'm a little sad,'' said Ayanda, who played a bit role while Olivia grabbed the spotlight before reclaiming the role of Gabriella the next night. ''But I'm also so excited for Olivia. I'm glad I got sick in a way. Because she does deserve it.''</p>
        <p>Where This Play's the Thing</p>
        <p>These are some of the schools scheduled to present Disney's ''High School Musical'' in coming weeks:</p>
        <p>Connecticut</p>
        <p>DURHAM -- Coginchaug Regional High School, May 20 and 21.</p>
        <p>GREENWICH -- Greenwich Catholic School, May 18.</p>
        <p>SEYMOUR -- Seymour Middle School, May 24 and 25.</p>
        <p>SHELTON -- Shelton High School, May 17 to 19.</p>
        <p>STAMFORD -- Scofield Magnet Middle School, April 27 and 28.</p>
        <p>STAMFORD -- Rippowam Middle School, May 2.</p>
        <p>WATERBURY -- West Side Middle School, May 18 and 19.</p>
        <p>Westchester County</p>
        <p>NEW ROCHELLE -- Trinity Elementary School, April 19 to 21.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
        <p>LINDENHURST -- Lindenhurst Middle School, April 20 and 21.</p>
        <p>NORTH MERRICK -- Joint performance by three elementary schools at Brookside School, April 18 to 21.</p>
        <p>OCEANSIDE -- Walter S. Boardman Elementary School, April 19.</p>
        <p>VALLEY STREAM -- Memorial Junior High School, April 20 and 21.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
