<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Internet, A Video Showcase for Poets</title>
    <meta content="15lipoetsLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15lipoets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Poetryvlog.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotroneo, Nicole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DB123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Internet, A Video Showcase for Poets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On the Internet, a Video Showcase for Poets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLE COTRONEO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotroneo, Nicole</byline>
      <dateline>SETAUKET</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on year-old poetryvlog.com, Web site that introduces new video of poet reading about five minutes' worth of his or her work each Saturday; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DUANE ESPOSITO had just been introduced to the crowd at Setauket Neighborhood House as a college professor and a ''new daddy,'' an image that didn't quite seem to fit with his military cap and his tattoo-covered arms. The contrast definitely added interest to the poetry he began to read:</p>
        <p>When the moon's in sky and we listen</p>
        <p>to a loon on a lake, we never cry for long.</p>
        <p>We witness a smaller planet, circles on water,</p>
        <p>the sky above our wild and physical world.</p>
        <p>Seeing and hearing a poet speak his own words is what attracts audiences to live poetry readings. But the more than 60 poetry lovers gathered at the Neighborhood House last weekend were not only appreciating the live poets, they were also celebrating the first anniversary of poetryvlog.com, a Web site that has taken poetry reading to a 21st-century level.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Poetryvlog.com, a Web site that has taken poetry reading to a 21st-century level, recently celebrated its first anniversary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DUANE ESPOSITO had just been introduced to the crowd at Setauket Neighborhood House as a college professor and a ''new daddy,'' an image that didn't quite seem to fit with his military cap and his tattoo-covered arms. The contrast definitely added interest to the poetry he began to read:</p>
        <p>When the moon's in sky and we listen</p>
        <p>to a loon on a lake, we never cry for long.</p>
        <p>We witness a smaller planet, circles on water,</p>
        <p>the sky above our wild and physical world.</p>
        <p>Seeing and hearing a poet speak his own words is what attracts audiences to live poetry readings. But the more than 60 poetry lovers gathered at the Neighborhood House last weekend were not only appreciating the live poets, they were also celebrating the first anniversary of poetryvlog.com, a Web site that has taken poetry reading to a 21st-century level.</p>
        <p>Each Saturday, poetryvlog.com introduces a new video of a poet reading about five minutes' worth of his or her work. While many of those featured have been Long Islanders, others have been from Connecticut, Rhode Island, Ireland and Iceland. The videos are filmed and archived by the Web site's creator, Michael Mart of St. James, and the poets are chosen by George Wallace, of Huntington, who was named Suffolk County's first poet laureate in 2003.</p>
        <p>The inception of poetryvlog.com was largely a result of a physical space problem. Mr. Mart, a contemporary poetry enthusiast and the owner for more than 30 years of the tiny Good Times Bookshop in Port Jefferson, never had room there for readings, he said. But a few months before he closed the shop last July, he said, he realized that virtual space was the solution.</p>
        <p>Inspired by Rocketboom, a New York City-based videoblog, Mr. Mart discovered he could start a Web site for very little money. ''It helps everyone,'' he said. ''The poet gets noticed, and it expands the audience to whomever might have an interest and an Internet connection.''</p>
        <p>A year later, Mr. Mart said, the poetry site receives an average of 17,000 visits a month. ''That's more attention than any poet would've gotten in our bookshop,'' he noted.</p>
        <p>Exposure has increased primarily through word of mouth, according to Mr. Mart. Neither he nor Mr. Wallace makes money from the site, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wallace, who met Mr. Mart as a customer at Good Times, is also well connected to the Long Island poetry community. He organizes poetry readings in Manhattan and Long Island and publishes an online poetry magazine at www.poetrybay.com.</p>
        <p>As a Web-based publisher, Mr. Wallace said he understood the power and potential of the Internet when Mr. Mart approached him with his idea. ''The Internet is really the downtown of the 21st century,'' Mr. Wallace said at the anniversary party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wallace said he does not choose the featured poets based on their performance ability. ''I've tried to be as inclusive as possible while maintaining the quality,'' he said. ''I also want to present different voices.''</p>
        <p>Among those voices has been that of Mr. Esposito, who lives in South Huntington and teaches in the English department at Nassau Community College in Garden City. Another is that of Adam D. Fisher, a retired rabbi from Stony Brook, who was also one of more than two dozen guests to read at the poetryvlog.com party, which was sponsored by the Greater Port Jefferson-Northern Brookhaven Arts Council.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Wallace said he did not know of any poets who had been discovered by agents or publishers as a result of the site, it has helped the writers in other ways. Marcia Slatkin, a poet from Shoreham, said her video helped her publicize a scheduled reading of her work. Others said the site introduced them to the local poetry community.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wallace said that with all the poets he now knows on Long Island alone, he could fill two or three years' worth of the site's weekly slots.</p>
        <p>''For quality of poets,'' he said, ''Long Island can compete with any region pound for pound.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
