<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stacy Rosenberg, Samuel Kashy</title>
    <meta content="15rosenberg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/fashion/weddings/15rosenberg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Stacy Beth (Stacy Beth Kashy)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kashy, Samuel Marc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0D9133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stacy Rosenberg, Samuel Kashy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stacy Rosenberg, Samuel Kashy</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stacy Beth Rosenberg and Samuel Marc Kashy were married last evening by Rabbi Stephen Hart at the InterContinental Chicago hotel.</p>
        <p>The bride, 36, is the director of online marketing at FinanSure, a Chicago company that makes student loans. She graduated from the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and received a master's degree in integrated marketing from Northwestern.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stacy Beth Rosenberg and Samuel Marc Kashy were married last evening by Rabbi Stephen Hart at the InterContinental Chicago hotel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stacy Beth Rosenberg and Samuel Marc Kashy were married last evening by Rabbi Stephen Hart at the InterContinental Chicago hotel.</p>
        <p>The bride, 36, is the director of online marketing at FinanSure, a Chicago company that makes student loans. She graduated from the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and received a master's degree in integrated marketing from Northwestern.</p>
        <p>She is the daughter of Renée and Charles Rosenberg of Arlington Heights, Ill. Her father retired as an owner of Keroff &amp; Rosenberg, a former advertising agency in Chicago. The bride's mother retired as the agency's office manager.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 40, is the vice president for new business development for PayNet, a company in Skokie, Ill., that provides credit history reports on businesses. He graduated from Michigan State University and received a master's degree in industrial management from Carnegie Mellon.</p>
        <p>He is a son of Marilyn and Edwin Kashy of Haslett, Mich. The bridegroom's mother, who is retired, worked in Lansing, Mich., as an information systems analyst for the State Department of Management and Budget. His father, also retired, was a professor of nuclear physics at Michigan State University.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosenberg and Mr. Kashy met through an online site in October 2005. Ms. Rosenberg said she contacted Mr. Kashy because she thought his screen name, ''Hippity Hop,'' which referred to his love of dancing, was funny. (She said she chose the screen name ''Spacey'' because it rhymed with her first name, not because it referred to any of her personal characteristics.)</p>
        <p>The pair conversed through instant messaging every few days for a couple of weeks and found they had much in common: a love of family, an affinity for blues music and a penchant for what Mr. Kashy called ''mischief'' -- for example, crashing V.I.P. rooms at nightclubs and concerts.</p>
        <p>Their first date on Nov. 1 at an Italian restaurant in Chicago went well. A couple of days later, he invited her out to see ''700 Sundays,'' a one-man play in which Billy Crystal reminisces about his father, which was playing in Chicago at the time.</p>
        <p>There was one catch to the invitation: Mr. Kashy's parents would be attending the performance.</p>
        <p>''She would be thrown into the boiling kettle of a date chaperoned by my parents,'' Mr. Kashy said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rosenberg accepted the challenge. But when she arrived at the restaurant where she was to meet Mr. Kashy and his parents before the show, she realized she didn't know the family's last name. Before making the embarrassing admission to the headwaiter, however, she spotted Mr. Kashy, who was seated at the bar.</p>
        <p>The rest of the evening went well, and in August last year things had progressed to the point where Mr. Kashy wanted to introduce her to other members of his family. Specifically, 50 relatives who had arranged to get together in Houston.</p>
        <p>The morning after the couple arrived at the reunion, Ms. Rosenberg met the family matriarch, Mr. Kashy's maternal grandmother, Sarah Orr, who was then 94.</p>
        <p>Ms. Orr, who Mr. Kashy said often forgets the names of her 13 grandchildren and 22 great-grandchildren, was sharp as a tack when the family sat down with her at the breakfast table that first morning.</p>
        <p>''You're not one of mine,'' Mr. Kashy recalled his grandmother saying, as she directed her gaze at Ms. Rosenberg.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kashy said he replied, ''She's not one of yours now, but she soon will be.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
