<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recycling Opulence and Helping a Good Cause</title>
    <meta content="15ctcolCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15ctcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bridgeport (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Measure for Measure (Orgn)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Demolitions (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">All Addicts Anonymous (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hirshey, Gerri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recycling Opulence and Helping a Good Cause</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recycling Opulence and Helping a Good Cause</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERRI HIRSHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hirshey, Gerri</byline>
      <dateline>BRIDGEPORT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerri Hirshey column on Measure for Measure in Bridgeport, Conn, which has teamed with Green Demolitions to sell donated recycled materials, including high-end home fixtures and appliances; proceeds benefit nonprofit addiction-recovery program, All Addicts Anonymous; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMEONE'S dream kitchen sits waiting in an industrial space in the Black Rock section of Bridgeport. Its custom-milled cabinets and marble countertops embrace high-end faucets, hardware and appliances -- Sub-Zero refrigerator, Miele dishwasher, a handsome French-made Lacanche stove. Here at Measure for Measure, a store that also sells ''green'' building and cleaning supplies, you can buy this recycled splendor to perk up your own center-hall Shangri-La for about half what a hedge-fund baron may spend to install it brand-new in a waterfront manse.</p>
        <p>Often, such elegant domestic design gets mashed into landfill when homes change ownership. This kitchen, only gently used and impeccably, professionally restored, was trucked here from Greenwich, Connecticut's teardown capital. New homeowners planning to demolish their home and rebuild to their own tastes were delighted to have it removed at no cost. The store has teamed with a company called Green Demolitions to sell these donated recycled materials, with the proceeds going to a nonprofit addiction-recovery program, All Addicts Anonymous, which does not charge for its treatment and outreach services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At Measure for Measure, all proceeds go to a nonprofit addiction-recovery program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMEONE'S dream kitchen sits waiting in an industrial space in the Black Rock section of Bridgeport. Its custom-milled cabinets and marble countertops embrace high-end faucets, hardware and appliances -- Sub-Zero refrigerator, Miele dishwasher, a handsome French-made Lacanche stove. Here at Measure for Measure, a store that also sells ''green'' building and cleaning supplies, you can buy this recycled splendor to perk up your own center-hall Shangri-La for about half what a hedge-fund baron may spend to install it brand-new in a waterfront manse.</p>
        <p>Often, such elegant domestic design gets mashed into landfill when homes change ownership. This kitchen, only gently used and impeccably, professionally restored, was trucked here from Greenwich, Connecticut's teardown capital. New homeowners planning to demolish their home and rebuild to their own tastes were delighted to have it removed at no cost. The store has teamed with a company called Green Demolitions to sell these donated recycled materials, with the proceeds going to a nonprofit addiction-recovery program, All Addicts Anonymous, which does not charge for its treatment and outreach services.</p>
        <p>An architect is circling the goods on the kitchen's first day in Measure for Measure's main showroom. An interior designer is taking digital photos of mantelpieces and marble-topped bathroom vanities. Word of mouth in the design and construction industries has sent most savvy shoppers to this Fairfield Avenue store. Two other stores, in Bethel, N.Y., and Honesdale, Pa., also sell Green Demolitions goods. Homeowners, interior designers, architects and contractors can locate and buy donated goods on the Web at greendemolitions.org.</p>
        <p>The president of Green Demolitions, Steve Feldman, a former radio D.J. and marketing manager -- and a recovered addict -- is responsible for this synergy of excesses, which strives to curb chemical indulgence with the resale of discarded opulence. He calls it ''green luxury.''</p>
        <p>The idea came to him six years ago as he drove past a teardown in Greenwich that once belonged to the last empress of Iran, Farah Pahlavi. ''She lived in a 10,000-square-foot, former Rockefeller estate mansion,'' Mr. Feldman recalled. ''But when I drove down the driveway, it was just a hole in the ground. I stood there thinking that there must have been wonderful treasures in that house. I was looking for new ways to raise money for this charity. And I thought, why not start a demolition-donation program?''</p>
        <p>It is his goal to raise enough money to sustain and expand the 45-year-old addiction treatment and prevention program, based at a retreat center in the Catskill Mountains. Funds from the sales of home fixtures go to a nonprofit organization registered as Recovery Unlimited, which issues I.R.S.-accepted tax credits equal to the final sale price of donated items.</p>
        <p>''Everyone on my core staff is either a recovered addict or a family member of one,'' Mr. Feldman said. ''Some of my partners in the construction company that removes and restores the material are children of recovered addicts. Their parents went through the program, and they did the prevention program as teens.''</p>
        <p>It took him more than four years to start the program, which is ''green,'' he said, in a few ways. ''First off, it is the color of money. Donors receive tax savings and cut labor and dump fees. They get free pickup. Consumers can buy a kitchen at 50 to 75 percent off retail. It saves the cost and energy of total demolition, as well as space in a landfill.''</p>
        <p>Andy Smith, a contractor working with his wife, Alissa, inspects, removes, restores and transports the donated items from homes in the tristate area; most donors are in Westchester and Fairfield. ''We provide guilt relief,'' he said, joking. And to buyers, he brings honed granite and glee. The previous day, Mr. Smith, hauling a year-old, $100,000 kitchen from Greenwich, pulled his truck up to a Long Island home. ''The buyer and his contractor met me in the driveway with ecstatic grins,'' he said. ''For $26,000, this nice, average home was getting a gorgeous new room. And we left the Greenwich contractor smiling, too. His guys were able to demo the rest of the room in about a third the time, with about two less dumpsters.''</p>
        <p>Earlier in the week, Mr. Feldman and Mr. Smith went to an apartment high over Fifth Avenue to inspect the goods in a growing new donation pool: the high-turnover Manhattan luxury market. Mr. Smith said that soon the company would probably be dismantling and selling fixtures from that apartment, which was a former home of Jacqueline Onassis. Thus the kitchen sink of Camelot royalty may one day adorn a modest Cape in Teaneck, N.J.</p>
        <p>Improbability is exactly what Mr. Smith loves about his job, which, like the recovery program it supports, unfolds one day at a time. ''I just never know what I'm going to find,'' he said. ''What I know for sure is that wherever I pull up with our biggest 26-foot truck -- empty or full -- they're always glad to see us.''</p>
        <p>E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
