<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Designed For Living</title>
    <meta content="05well.art.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="74" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/style/tmagazine/15tlouise.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Nevelson, Louise</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Designed For Living</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Designed for Living</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Camhi</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Camhi, Leslie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The artist Louise Nevelson said she didn't believe in reincarnation, but late in life, when an interviewer asked her whom she would like to come back as, she answered without hesitation, herself. ''The Sculpture of Louise Nevelson: Constructing a Legend,'' opening May 5 at New York's Jewish Museum, showcases her monumental assemblages and pioneering, room-size environments made of found wooden objects, painted black, white or gold, and rendered infinitely mysterious.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In creating a dazzling persona, Louise Nevelson fused her art and her life. Leslie Camhi wonders if an artist can still look like one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The artist Louise Nevelson said she didn't believe in reincarnation, but late in life, when an interviewer asked her whom she would like to come back as, she answered without hesitation, herself. ''The Sculpture of Louise Nevelson: Constructing a Legend,'' opening May 5 at New York's Jewish Museum, showcases her monumental assemblages and pioneering, room-size environments made of found wooden objects, painted black, white or gold, and rendered infinitely mysterious.</p>
        <p>But the artist was in many ways her own greatest creation.</p>
        <p>Fame came to her belatedly. She was 60 when the 1959 Museum of Modern Art exhibition ''Sixteen Americans'' enshrined her along with rising stars like Jasper Johns, Robert Rauschenberg and Frank Stella (all younger than her by at least a quarter-century). Most women, as they age, cling tenaciously to a few well-honed looks. Nevelson made old age the stage for a fashion revolution. Gradually, her full-blown style emerged, an immense collage whose elements were subject to miraculous transformations -- the head scarves and multiple pairs of false eyelashes, the ethnographic jewels and enormous furs, the couture garments layered under and over peasant clothing.</p>
        <p>There's the sculptor, at 81, smoking cigars with her dealer Arne Glimcher on the roof of her Spring Street home. She's wearing a voluminous, ruffled and spangled robe made for her by the couturier Arnold Scaasi. She sports an Inca-style necklace; two enormous disks hang from her earlobes, and her entire ensemble is topped off with a jockey cap. (What is that rule of good taste? Before leaving the house, you remove one thing?)</p>
        <p>In most photographs, it's impossible to tell exactly what she's wearing -- the layering of glimmering bits of exotic fabrics and utilitarian garments, the unexpected juxtapositions, create a sense of utter uniqueness, an indefinable luxury. It's a look that's at once out of time and uncannily of this moment -- furs over jeans, pants under dresses, riots of pattern and color. Nevelson ''wanted to look dazzling at all times,'' Scaasi remembers. ''I'd show her a blue-and-silver brocade with big gold birds all over it,'' the designer recalls, ''and she'd say, 'Oh, that's perfect for Miss America' -- meaning herself. We'd make the suit, thinking it would be for evening, but then she'd be giving lectures in it at 10 a.m.'' Glimcher told me recently that ''she used to say, 'I'm an atmospheric dresser,' '' as if by piling on the clothes she could invent her own personal weather.</p>
        <p>It must be somehow comforting to move about, suspended in an aura of your own creation. An ex-boyfriend of mine, a prominent European artist, was convinced he'd never make it into the major leagues because of his unprepossessing appearance. ''Look at Duchamp and Picasso,'' he'd say mournfully. ''So handsome, both of them!'' Of course, he'd neglected to mention the original peintre maudit, Modigliani, whose beauty and way with a neck scarf were legendary, as well as a host of subsidiary dandies, like Foujita, the Japanese painter who, inspired by Isadora Duncan's brother Raymond, wandered the streets of bohemian Montparnasse in a Greek tunic he had woven himself; or DalÃ (ferally attractive in his youth, before he turned to self-caricature), who almost suffocated from the deep-sea diving suit he wore during a 1936 lecture in London. And in our own day, I can remember artists grumbling at the almost instant success of Matthew Barney, whose early videos showed the fetching young creator elaborately made up as a cloven-foot, nub-horned satyr. ''You know,'' they'd say, ''he was a J. Crew model.''</p>
        <p>I was fond of my artist, short and squat as he was. But I suspected he was onto something. Nevelson, too, believed that ''the physical is the geography of the being.'' Early on and for decades, she grew accustomed to the tributes that a beautiful and charismatic woman receives as her due -- so that, when fame finally came, she was ready for it.</p>
        <p>''Miss America'' was born Leah Berliawsky in Kiev, Ukraine, to upper-middle-class Jews with ties to the lumber industry. In her memoir, ''Dawns and Dusks,'' she claims to have known that she was an artist from her earliest childhood. She emigrated with her family at age 5, following her father to Rockland, Me.; they were wearing Persian lamb hats and coats, which must have made these rare Jews seem terribly outré in small-town, Puritan New England.</p>
        <p>Charles Nevelson, a New York Jew who with his brothers made a fortune in shipping, was her ticket out of Rockland; they married, and their son Mike was born in 1922, but her artistic ambitions soon clashed with the demands of domestic life. An exhibition of Japanese Noh robes at the Metropolitan Museum of Art broke through her depression, convincing her that ''life is worth living if a civilization can give us this great weave of gold and pattern.''</p>
        <p>So she shook off her marriage, left her son with family in Maine and set off for Munich, where she studied art with Hans Hofmann. Returning to New York, she worked briefly as an assistant for the muralist Diego Rivera, admiring both his wife Frida Kahlo's paintings and the Mexican folk dress and jewelry that Kahlo wore while entertaining ''princesses and . . . laborers'' in the couple's West 13th Street salon.</p>
        <p>The record of Nevelson's clothes during those years of struggle is mixed: a burlap sack, a hot-pink ensemble, secondhand ethnic costumes and bits of old lace alongside sleek suits and fashionable hats. She knew poverty, but she rejected the look, which other American artists embraced as a seal of authenticity. And she never remarried, despite hordes of male admirers. (How did she manage to dress so wonderfully, her fellow artist Alice Neel asked her, on her limited W.P.A. stipend in the 1930s? Nevelson's answer is unprintable in a family newspaper.)</p>
        <p>Nevelson paid a price for her stylishness -- other artists mistook her for a bourgeois girl who was slumming, neglecting her almost preternatural energy for work in the years when she regularly woke before dawn to enter her studio, pausing only to dine on sardines and stale bread. In fact, her talent for self-dramatization seems both a reflection of the intensity of her drive and a cover for the deep vulnerability that went with it. Eventually her mature look (photographed by everyone from Cecil Beaton to Robert Mapplethorpe) became a public brand, as much as Warhol's helmet of white hair and affectless demeanor. ''She was a real innovator,'' observes Brooke Kamin Rapaport, the guest curator of the Jewish Museum's retrospective, ''not just in creating her work but in her understanding of artistic celebrity.''</p>
        <p>A girl with artistic inclinations growing up in the 1970s might have looked to Nevelson or to Georgia O'Keeffe as a role model.</p>
        <p>(As a style icon, O'Keeffe was the anti-Nevelson, with her tailored blacks and whites and intensely weathered skin that was almost part of her costume.) For Laurie Simmons, who always knew she wanted to be an artist, there were no visual clues in suburbia for what a woman artist should look like. ''Nevelson was one of the first to penetrate my awareness in that way,'' she recalls. Simmons, best known for her photographs of eerily animated ventriloquists' dummies, currently favors little black dresses by Lanvin and Narciso Rodriguez. ''All my strangeness is channeled into my work,'' she explains. ''But I've always admired the idea that an artist's persona could be seamlessly at one with her creations.''</p>
        <p>Male artists can pull it off with a single uniform, like Carl Andre's overalls or Joseph Beuys's fishing vest and fedora, which they exercise ad infinitum. For women artists, negotiating the fraught terrain of appearance requires considerably more work. (I knew a painter who spent inordinate amounts of time trying to maintain the illusion that she never gave her clothes a second thought.) When the wacky post-minimalist Andrea Zittel faced the problem of maintaining art-world chic on an emerging artist's budget, she created personal ''uniforms'' that she wore for months on end around her desert compound near Joshua Tree National Park: they evolved from Comme des Garconish sheaths to wild, organic-looking, felted dresses. The sculptor Chakaia Booker says she begins each morning by collaging her appearance, using head wraps, neckwear, found objects and pieces of rubber to get the creative energy flowing from one medium -- herself -- into another.</p>
        <p>Then there are the performance artists whose looks are vehicles for their oeuvre, like Orlan, who sculpts her own body with cosmetic surgery; Colette, who religiously clothed herself in pink for nearly a year; or Carolee Schneeman and Hannah Wilke, beautiful women who took off their clothes and turned the art world upside down. Marina Abramovic, a statuesque Slav, still endures intense physical trials in the service of her art, but has recently confessed a weak spot for glamour. Three hundred people filed into the Guggenheim Museum to celebrate her 60th birthday in February (dress code: outrageously elegant); we watched a film in which she cut and whipped herself and lay naked on a cross of ice, then we went upstairs and toasted the artist, who was attired in Givenchy.</p>
        <p>The sculptor Kiki Smith was there, wearing some flowing white garment that set off her long, gray tresses; with her tattoos, multiple piercings and ankle bracelets, Smith's flower-child-meets-emergency-medical-technician persona seems entirely of a piece with her uncannily corporeal oeuvre. So do the looks of the film installation artist Shirin Neshat, a tiny, Iran-born woman of birdlike slenderness, whose fiercely kohl-rimmed eyes and heavy Persian jewelry seem drawn, like her work, from a deep well of exoticism and strength. These women, in their appearance, deliver what, on some level, we long for -- the vision of an artistic ideal permeating every corner of an artist's life.</p>
        <p>That ideal, it seems to me, is waning. More artists (preoccupied with their career, perhaps?) appear to be playing it safe. Fashionistas like the painters/sculptors Hope Atherton (a Vogue ''Girl of the Moment'') and Rachel Feinstein (a muse to Marc Jacobs), when not toiling in their studios, appear fabulously garbed in the party pages of magazines. Which is not the same thing as embodying an artistic ideal.</p>
        <p>That, on Nevelson's terms, requires another half-century of ripening; maybe it requires time spent in the artistic wilderness of neglect, where an individual's creative will is forged. Nevelson, after all, did dress for success, but success has never looked like that before or since.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
