<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Regional Ambience, Global Cuisine</title>
    <meta content="15ctdineCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15ctdine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/STONINGTON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Water Street Cafe (Stonington, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyness, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Mystic and the Southeastern Coast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Stonington (Conn)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Water Street Cafe</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Regional Ambience, Global Cuisine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Regional Ambience, Global Cuisine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE LYNESS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyness, Stephanie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephanie Lyness reviews Water Street Cafe in Stonington, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE thing I like best about the Water Street Cafe in Stonington is the specificity of the atmosphere. It's a pleasantly funky New England seacoast tavern of indeterminate age, clothed with an assortment of objects and memorabilia. Despite a dominant maritime theme, the collection is diverse and intriguing enough that one imagines it to have simply accrued gradually over the life of the restaurant, through a variety of means, the way a life story develops over time.</p>
        <p>This regional ambience is so potent and palpable, so well expressed in the nautical décor, dim lighting and New England hospitality, that I assumed the menu would follow suit. I expected a variant of New England cuisine -- straightforward, hearty and oriented toward the coast. I was wrong, on almost all counts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the Water Street Cafe in Stonington, the menu could be simpler and more focused but the seafood is stellar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE thing I like best about the Water Street Cafe in Stonington is the specificity of the atmosphere. It's a pleasantly funky New England seacoast tavern of indeterminate age, clothed with an assortment of objects and memorabilia. Despite a dominant maritime theme, the collection is diverse and intriguing enough that one imagines it to have simply accrued gradually over the life of the restaurant, through a variety of means, the way a life story develops over time.</p>
        <p>This regional ambience is so potent and palpable, so well expressed in the nautical décor, dim lighting and New England hospitality, that I assumed the menu would follow suit. I expected a variant of New England cuisine -- straightforward, hearty and oriented toward the coast. I was wrong, on almost all counts.</p>
        <p>Seafood is certainly well represented, from the platter of oysters we sampled one night to steamed mussels and clams and a nice selection of finfish that changes daily. (There was, in fact, a New England clam chowder on the list of specials that we turned down in favor of a shrimp and corn chowder.) But the cuisine is global, not regional, and ambitiously so. One evening, the list of 23 specials encompassed the cuisines of 10 different cultures. Italian dishes, which often appear relentlessly as defaults on other American menus, play a lesser role here.</p>
        <p>The quality of nearly all the seafood we had was impeccable (and my sole complaint is a small one -- the shrimp one night, in both the above-mentioned chowder and a shrimp appetizer with seaweed salad, were curiously devoid of taste). Raw oysters sparkled, the finfish was pristine, and one seasoned dining companion, a professional in the food business, declared several times without prompting that his plump steamed mussels were the best he had ever eaten.</p>
        <p>It is precisely the excellence of the raw ingredients that makes me yearn for a cuisine that is a little simpler, and a little more focused. The food is well cooked, but the preparation often seems to get in the way of it.</p>
        <p>So, for example, a lovely piece of wild striped bass, served on top of a bed of sautéed vegetables, was blanketed with a strong-tasting, wet miso ''crust'' that obscured the taste of the fish to no good purpose. Grilled hanger steak, accompanied by fine mashed potatoes and sautéed spinach, was sliced and coated with a red-wine-and- blue-cheese sauce: one struggled to taste the meat beneath.</p>
        <p>Better choices were the swordfish, grilled and served on a bed of rice and vegetables; a yellowfin tuna steak, seared and served with a wasabi dipping sauce; a spiced, blackened salmon garnished with guacamole (though the salmon was salty and the rice cold); and an enormous pork chop topped with fresh pear and green tomato chutney.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the food just needs to be seasoned correctly. A tuna tartare appetizer combined small chunks of glistening raw tuna and thin ribbons of fresh cucumber, pressed into a mold. The ingredients were beautiful, but the tuna needed a sprinkling of salt and pepper to bring out its flavor.</p>
        <p>The small dessert menus are charming in their individual picture frames, and sweets are fairly traditional and quite good. Most successful one evening was a wedge of warm coconut-walnut wafer cake; its buttery, nutty taste was irresistible. Another night we compared a slab of warm, flourless chocolate cake to the chocolate layer cake, finding a mild preference for the intense, bitter chocolate taste of the former.</p>
        <p>It appears that cooking a global menu is a difficult task: It requires a great deal of culinary expertise and may result in a lack of focus in a restaurant. Water Street Cafe does not entirely avoid these dangers, and I suspect that the excellent ingredients might speak better with simpler preparations. However, should you find yourself in this lovely coastal town this summer, there are good things to eat here, along with a truly great bar.</p>
        <p>Water Street Cafe</p>
        <p>142 Water Street  Stonington  (860) 535-2122</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Cozy tavern with a comfortable, dark, cavelike feel. Lovely bar fills the back of the restaurant. Chalkboard list of daily specials. Seating for smaller parties, some with banquettes, and a table for large parties in the back of the restaurant. Wheelchair accessibility.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Local crowd, very casual. Restaurant gets noisy when full, particularly if there is live music (acoustic guitar on Wednesday and Thursday evenings). No reservations accepted, so there may be a wait.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Full bar and a small, reasonable wine list. Beer in bottles and on tap.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Entrees, $7 to $26. American Express not accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Raw oyster bar, steamed mussels, nachos, warm duck salad, smoked salmon; tuna with wasabi dipping sauce, grilled swordfish with sautéed vegetables, roast pork chop, hamburger, blackened salmon; coconut-walnut wafer cake, flourless chocolate cake, chocolate layer cake, double-crust raspberry pie.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Breakfast: Friday and Monday, 8 a.m. to 2:30 p.m. Brunch: Saturday and Sunday, 8 a.m. to 2:30 p.m. Lunch: Monday to Friday, 11:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m. Dinner: Sunday to Thursday, 5 to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 4 to 11 p.m.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 15, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/STONINGTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
