<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="15njlistingsNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3DE133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2270" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Hasbrouck Heights Joe Starr, stand-up. Friday and April 21. $12 to $15. Bananas Comedy Club, 283 Route 17 South. (201) 727-1090.</p>
        <p>Morristown Colin Mochrie and Brad Sherwood, improv. April 21 at 8 p.m. $47 to $57. The Community Theater, 100 South Street. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>Red Bank Bob Saget, standup. Thursday at 8 p.m. $20 to $50. Count Basie Theater, 99 Monmouth Street. (732) 842-9000.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>New Brunswick The New Jersey Film Festival, Spring 2007. Schedule and information: njfilmfest.com. Through April 15. $4 to $10. New Jersey Media Arts Center, 72 Lipman Drive. (732) 932-8482.</p>
        <p>SOUTH ORANGE Screenings of works from the annual Black Maria Film and Video Festival. Tuesday at 7 p.m. Free. South Orange Public Library, 65 Scotland Road. (973) 762-0230.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Morristown The Dirty Sock Funtime Band, family concert. April 22 at 1:30 and 4 p.m. $12. The Community Theater, 100 South Street. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>Newark Center Family Time: Shakespeare's ''Romeo and Juliet,'' family production by Aquila Theater Company. Ages 12 and up. April 21 at 2 p.m. Sold out. New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>Princeton ''Ralph's World,'' one-man children's musical by Ralph Covert. Ages 2 to 8. April 21 at 11 a.m. $16. McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>South Orange ''Ralph's World,'' one-man children's musical by Ralph Covert. Ages 2 to 8. April 15 at 11 a.m. and 3 p.m. $15. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Boonton ''When You Wish Upon a Song: A Magical Musical Revue,'' presented by the Boonton Parks and Recreation Theater Company. Through April 15. $9 to $12. Boonton High School, 306 Lanthrop Avenue. (973) 335-9700.</p>
        <p>Cape May Annual Cape May Jazz Festival, ''A Tribute to Wes Montgomery,'' with workshops and performances . Friday through April 22. $25 to $190 (weekend pass with reserved seats); workshops, free. Cape May Convention Hall, 720 Beach Drive at Stockton Avenue. (609) 884-5404.</p>
        <p>Englewood Itzhak Perlman, violinist. April 15 at 3 p.m. $35 to $125. ''Cinderella,'' performed by the Russian National Ballet. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $25 to $50. Emanuel Ax, pianist, and Edgar Meyer, bassist. Thursday at 8 p.m. $35 to $75. Michael Franks and the Rippingtons, jazz. April 22 at 7 p.m. $28 to $85. Bergen Performing Arts Center, 30 North Van Brunt Street. (201) 227-1030.</p>
        <p>Morristown Geoff Kaufman, with Elin and Edward, folk. Friday at 8:30 p.m. $7. Minstrel Coffeehouse, Morristown Unitarian Fellowship, 21 Normandy Heights Road. (973) 335-9489.</p>
        <p>Morristown The Warren Vaché Group, jazz. April 15 at 3 p.m. $15. The Rippingtons, jazz. Thursday at 8 p.m. $37 to $47. The Community Theater, 100 South Street. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick Rutgers Brass; Renaissance to contemporary music. April 15 at 6:30 p.m. Free. Christ Church Episcopal, 5 Paterson Street. (732) 545-6262.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick ''Falsettos,'' musical by William Finn and James Lapine. Through May 6. $28 to 64. George Street Playhouse, 9 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7717.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick Handel's ''Athalia,'' performed by Opera at Rutgers and Musica Raritana. Through April 15. Free. Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, Douglass Campus, Rutgers University, 85 George Street. (732) 932-7511.</p>
        <p>Newark Johnny Mathis. Friday at 8 p.m. $24 to $88. Peter, Paul &amp; Mary, folk. April 21 at 8 p.m. $22 to $78. John Legend, with Corinne Bailey Rae, rhythm and blues. April 22 at 7:30 p.m. Sold out. New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>Princeton Tchaikovsky's ''The Sleeping Beauty,'' with choreography by Marius Petipa, performed by the Moscow Festival Ballet. April 15 at 3 p.m. $15 to $44. John Williams and John Etheridge, classical and jazz guitar. Thursday at 8 p.m. $32 to $38. Friday Night Magic, magicians. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $15 to $35. Salif Keita, Malian composer and singer, with Vieux Farka Touré. Friday at 8 p.m. $32 to $43. Barbara Cook, singer. April 21 at 8 p.m. $15 to $50. McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>Red Bank Pat Metheny and Brad Mehldau, with Larry Grendier and Jeff Ballard, jazz. April 15 at 7:30 p.m. $30 to $75. American Big Band, with music, dance and narration. Tuesday at 2 p.m. $20 to $40. Peter, Paul &amp; Mary, folk. Friday at 8 p.m. $38.50 to $100. ''The Led Zeppelin Experience,'' performed by Hammer of the Gods. April 21 at 8 p.m. $25 to $50. Gordon Lightfoot, folk. April 22 at 7 p.m. $38 to $88. Count Basie Theater, 99 Monmouth Street. (732) 842-9000.</p>
        <p>Ridgewood Moe-tion Dance Theater, modern dance. April 15 at 5 p.m. $25, including a dinner reception after the performance; children under 6, free. Art of Motion, the Performing Arts Building, 17 Chestnut Street. (862) 485-2436.</p>
        <p>Teaneck Graham Parker and the Latest Clowns, folk. Thursday at 9 p.m. $25. Reid Genauer and the Assembly of Dust, rock. April 21 at 9 p.m. $15 and $20. Mexicali Blues Cafe, 1409 Queen Anne Road. (201) 833-0011.</p>
        <p>Watchung The Sanctuary Concerts Sunday Night Music Club: Dan Friedman, folk. April 22 at 7 p.m. $15. Watchung Arts Center, 18 Stirling Road. (908) 753-0190.</p>
        <p>Wayne The Machine, multimedia tribute to the music of Pink Floyd. Friday at 8 p.m. $15 to $35. Shea Center for Performing Arts, William Paterson University, 300 Pompton Road. (973) 720-2371.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Atlantic Highlands ''Miss Witherspoon,'' comedy by Christopher Durang. Through April 28. $15 to $20. First Avenue Playhouse, 123 First Avenue. (732) 291-7552.</p>
        <p>Cranford ''Open Admissions,'' drama by Shirley Lauro, presented by the Theater Project. Through April 28. $10 to $20. Union County College, 1033 Springfield Avenue. (908) 659-5189.</p>
        <p>Eatontown ''The Lion in Winter,'' drama by James Goldman, presented by Over the Rainbow. Through April 28. $17 to $22. Eatontown Playhouse, Tower Market Shopping Center, 3713 Route 35 North. (732) 460-0100.</p>
        <p>Hoboken ''The Miracle Worker,'' drama by William Gibson, presented by the Hudson Theater Ensemble. Through April 15. $8 to $15. Hudson School, 601 Park Avenue. (201) 377-7014.</p>
        <p>Lawrenceville ''The Heidi Chronicles,'' drama by Wendy Wasserstein, presented by Rider University student actors. Through April 21. $4 to $10. Rider University, Yvonne Theater, 2083 Lawrenceville Road. (609) 896-5303.</p>
        <p>Long Branch ''Love and Murder,'' drama by Arthur Giron; world premiere. Through May 6. $25 to $40. New Jersey Repertory Company, 179 Broadway. (732) 229-3166.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick ''In the Sawtooths,'' drama by Dano Madden, presented by the Rutgers Theater Company. Friday through April 28. $15 to $25. ''Derby Day,'' premiere of the dark comedy by Samuel Brett Williams, presented by the Rutgers Theater Company. April 21 through 29. $15 to $25. Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, Douglass Campus, Rutgers University, 85 George Street. (732) 932-7511.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick Chinese Golden Dragon Acrobats. April 22 at 2 and 5 p.m. $20 to $50. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>Nutley ''I Hate Hamlet,'' comedy by Paul Rudnick. Through April 28. $12. Nutley Little Theater, 47 Erie Place (off Brookfield Avenue). (973) 667-0374.</p>
        <p>Oaklyn ''Much Ado About Nothing,'' William Shakespeare's comedy; directed by Denise George. Through April 15. $17 to $30. Ritz Theater, 915 White Horse Pike. (856) 858-5230.</p>
        <p>Oradell ''Angels in America: Millennium Approaches,'' drama by Tony Kushner, presented by the Bergen County Players. Through April 21. $15 and $18. Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road. (201) 261-4200.</p>
        <p>South Orange ''Dead Man Walking,'' drama by Tim Robbins, adapted from the book by Sister Helen Prejean. Friday through April 22. $8 to $15. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.</p>
        <p>Sussex Shakespeare's ''Twelfth Night,'' presented by the Tri-State Actors Theater. Thursday through May 6. $17 to $27. Crescent Theater, 74 Main Street. (973) 875-2950.</p>
        <p>Wayne ''Quilters,'' musical by Molly Newman and Barbara Damashek. Tuesday through April 22. $8 and $10. Hunziker Theater, William Paterson University, 300 Pompton Road. (973) 720-2371.</p>
        <p>Wayne ''Seussical,'' musical by Stephen Flaherty and Lynn Ahrens, adapted from the books by Dr. Seuss; presented by the William Paterson University Pioneer Players. Through April 22. $3 to $7. YM-YWHA of North Jersey, 1 Pike Drive. (973) 595-0100.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Clinton ''Barbara Klein: New Marks,'' abstract paintings, and ''How American Women Artists Invented Post Modernism,'' group show presented by the Feminist Art Project. Through June 3. Reception: April 15, 2 to 4 p.m. Donation: $3. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Hunterdon Museum of Art, 7 Lower Center Street. (908) 735-8415.</p>
        <p>Cranford ''Memories and Mountains,'' mixed-media by Carole Wong Chesak. Through Friday. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m. Additional hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 6 to 9 p.m. Tomasulo Gallery, Union County College, 1033 Springfield Avenue. (908) 709-7155.</p>
        <p>Hopewell ''The Intimacy of Flowers,'' photography by Tasha O'Neill. Through April 15. ''Double Take: Two Photographers, Two Coney Islands,'' works by Joanna Tully and Marty Schwartz. Friday through May 27. Reception: Friday, 6 to 9 p.m. Artist talk: April 22, 1 to 3 p.m. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Gallery 14, 14 Mercer Street. (609) 333-8511.</p>
        <p>Lambertville ''Constructions and Reconstructions,'' mixed media and photography by Nancy Shill and John Treichler. Through April 29. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m., or by appointment. Artists' Gallery, 32 Coryell Street. (609) 397-4588.</p>
        <p>Lincroft Photographs from the collection of Brookdale Community College, including works from prominent 20th-century documentary and fine art photographers. Through April 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Monmouth Museum, Brookdale Community College, Newman Springs Road. (732) 747-2266.</p>
        <p>Maplewood ''Raw Spirits: A Survey of Contemporary Folk and Outsider Art in America,'' group show. April 15 through May 27. Reception: April 15, 2 to 5 p.m. 1978 Arts Center, 1978 Springfield Avenue. (973) 275-9855.</p>
        <p>Maplewood ''Lisa Pressman: Mixed Media, Transitions and Processes.'' Through April 28. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, noon to 8 p.m. Classic Design Framing, 168 Maplewood Avenue. (973) 762-5588.</p>
        <p>Montclair ''Dreaming of a Speech Without Words: the Painting and Early Objects of H. C. Westermann.'' Through May 27. $6 to $8; free for members and children 12 and under; free for everyone on Fridays from 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Montclair Art Museum, 3 South Mountain Avenue. (973) 746-5555.</p>
        <p>Morristown ''Oil on Linen,'' paintings by David Moore. Through April 21. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Simon Gallery, 48 Bank Street. (973) 538-5456.</p>
        <p>Newark ''Mi Puerto Rico: Master Painters of the Island,'' paintings by José Campeche, Francisco Oller and Miguel Pou. Through April 15. $3 and $7. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., October through June; noon to 5 p.m., July through September. The Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street. (973) 596-6493.</p>
        <p>Oceanville ''Spinning Worlds: Emerging Artists,'' works by Paul Santoleri and Carla Falb. ''Surface Rhythms,'' work by Bennett Bean and Barbara Bullock. Both through April 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays noon to 5 p.m. Noyes Museum of Art, 733 Lily Lake Road. (609) 652-8848.</p>
        <p>Princeton '' History, Identity or None of the Above: Regarding African American Art,'' mixed-media exhibit. Through May 13. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Princeton University Art Museum, Nassau and Witherspoon Streets. (609) 258-3788.</p>
        <p>Rahway ''High Fiber Content,'' mixed-media group show. Through Friday. Hours: Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 1 to 3 p.m. and 5 to 7 p.m. Arts Guild of Rahway, 1670 Irving Street. (732) 381-7511.</p>
        <p>Skillman Group show by the A-Team Artists of Trenton. Through May 6. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Montgomery Center for the Arts, 124 Montgomery Road. (609) 921-3272.</p>
        <p>Springfield ''Structures,'' photographs by Sue Zwick. Through April 26. Hours: Mondays, Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Tuesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 3:30 p.m. Donald B. Palmer Museum, 66 Mountain Avenue. (973) 376-4930.</p>
        <p>Summit ''Wes Sherman: Recent Works,'' paintings. Thursday through May 19. Reception: Friday, 7 to 9 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Domo Gallery, 447 Springfield Avenue. (908) 608-0079.</p>
        <p>Trenton ''Friends for the Marsh 2007,'' photography exhibition. Through April 21. Free. Wood fired ceramics and handmade paper and printmaking, by Peter Callas and Margaret Kennard Johnson. Through April 22. Suggested admission $2 to $5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. The Trenton City Museum, Cadwalader Park. (609) 989-3632.</p>
        <p>Washington Township ''In the Shadows of Manhattan,'' mixed-media group show. Through April 22. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 6 a.m. to 10 p.m.; Fridays, 6 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 8 a.m. to 5 p.m. Atrium Gallery, Bergen County Y, 605 Pascack Road. (201) 666-6610, Extension 222.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Hasbrouck Heights Joe Starr, stand-up. Friday and April 21. $12 to $15. Bananas Comedy Club, 283 Route 17 South. (201) 727-1090.</p>
        <p>Morristown Colin Mochrie and Brad Sherwood, improv. April 21 at 8 p.m. $47 to $57. The Community Theater, 100 South Street. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>Red Bank Bob Saget, standup. Thursday at 8 p.m. $20 to $50. Count Basie Theater, 99 Monmouth Street. (732) 842-9000.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>New Brunswick The New Jersey Film Festival, Spring 2007. Schedule and information: njfilmfest.com. Through April 15. $4 to $10. New Jersey Media Arts Center, 72 Lipman Drive. (732) 932-8482.</p>
        <p>SOUTH ORANGE Screenings of works from the annual Black Maria Film and Video Festival. Tuesday at 7 p.m. Free. South Orange Public Library, 65 Scotland Road. (973) 762-0230.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Morristown The Dirty Sock Funtime Band, family concert. April 22 at 1:30 and 4 p.m. $12. The Community Theater, 100 South Street. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>Newark Center Family Time: Shakespeare's ''Romeo and Juliet,'' family production by Aquila Theater Company. Ages 12 and up. April 21 at 2 p.m. Sold out. New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>Princeton ''Ralph's World,'' one-man children's musical by Ralph Covert. Ages 2 to 8. April 21 at 11 a.m. $16. McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>South Orange ''Ralph's World,'' one-man children's musical by Ralph Covert. Ages 2 to 8. April 15 at 11 a.m. and 3 p.m. $15. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Boonton ''When You Wish Upon a Song: A Magical Musical Revue,'' presented by the Boonton Parks and Recreation Theater Company. Through April 15. $9 to $12. Boonton High School, 306 Lanthrop Avenue. (973) 335-9700.</p>
        <p>Cape May Annual Cape May Jazz Festival, ''A Tribute to Wes Montgomery,'' with workshops and performances . Friday through April 22. $25 to $190 (weekend pass with reserved seats); workshops, free. Cape May Convention Hall, 720 Beach Drive at Stockton Avenue. (609) 884-5404.</p>
        <p>Englewood Itzhak Perlman, violinist. April 15 at 3 p.m. $35 to $125. ''Cinderella,'' performed by the Russian National Ballet. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $25 to $50. Emanuel Ax, pianist, and Edgar Meyer, bassist. Thursday at 8 p.m. $35 to $75. Michael Franks and the Rippingtons, jazz. April 22 at 7 p.m. $28 to $85. Bergen Performing Arts Center, 30 North Van Brunt Street. (201) 227-1030.</p>
        <p>Morristown Geoff Kaufman, with Elin and Edward, folk. Friday at 8:30 p.m. $7. Minstrel Coffeehouse, Morristown Unitarian Fellowship, 21 Normandy Heights Road. (973) 335-9489.</p>
        <p>Morristown The Warren Vaché Group, jazz. April 15 at 3 p.m. $15. The Rippingtons, jazz. Thursday at 8 p.m. $37 to $47. The Community Theater, 100 South Street. (973) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick Rutgers Brass; Renaissance to contemporary music. April 15 at 6:30 p.m. Free. Christ Church Episcopal, 5 Paterson Street. (732) 545-6262.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick ''Falsettos,'' musical by William Finn and James Lapine. Through May 6. $28 to 64. George Street Playhouse, 9 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7717.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick Handel's ''Athalia,'' performed by Opera at Rutgers and Musica Raritana. Through April 15. Free. Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, Douglass Campus, Rutgers University, 85 George Street. (732) 932-7511.</p>
        <p>Newark Johnny Mathis. Friday at 8 p.m. $24 to $88. Peter, Paul &amp; Mary, folk. April 21 at 8 p.m. $22 to $78. John Legend, with Corinne Bailey Rae, rhythm and blues. April 22 at 7:30 p.m. Sold out. New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>Princeton Tchaikovsky's ''The Sleeping Beauty,'' with choreography by Marius Petipa, performed by the Moscow Festival Ballet. April 15 at 3 p.m. $15 to $44. John Williams and John Etheridge, classical and jazz guitar. Thursday at 8 p.m. $32 to $38. Friday Night Magic, magicians. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $15 to $35. Salif Keita, Malian composer and singer, with Vieux Farka Touré. Friday at 8 p.m. $32 to $43. Barbara Cook, singer. April 21 at 8 p.m. $15 to $50. McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place. (609) 258-2787.</p>
        <p>Red Bank Pat Metheny and Brad Mehldau, with Larry Grendier and Jeff Ballard, jazz. April 15 at 7:30 p.m. $30 to $75. American Big Band, with music, dance and narration. Tuesday at 2 p.m. $20 to $40. Peter, Paul &amp; Mary, folk. Friday at 8 p.m. $38.50 to $100. ''The Led Zeppelin Experience,'' performed by Hammer of the Gods. April 21 at 8 p.m. $25 to $50. Gordon Lightfoot, folk. April 22 at 7 p.m. $38 to $88. Count Basie Theater, 99 Monmouth Street. (732) 842-9000.</p>
        <p>Ridgewood Moe-tion Dance Theater, modern dance. April 15 at 5 p.m. $25, including a dinner reception after the performance; children under 6, free. Art of Motion, the Performing Arts Building, 17 Chestnut Street. (862) 485-2436.</p>
        <p>Teaneck Graham Parker and the Latest Clowns, folk. Thursday at 9 p.m. $25. Reid Genauer and the Assembly of Dust, rock. April 21 at 9 p.m. $15 and $20. Mexicali Blues Cafe, 1409 Queen Anne Road. (201) 833-0011.</p>
        <p>Watchung The Sanctuary Concerts Sunday Night Music Club: Dan Friedman, folk. April 22 at 7 p.m. $15. Watchung Arts Center, 18 Stirling Road. (908) 753-0190.</p>
        <p>Wayne The Machine, multimedia tribute to the music of Pink Floyd. Friday at 8 p.m. $15 to $35. Shea Center for Performing Arts, William Paterson University, 300 Pompton Road. (973) 720-2371.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Atlantic Highlands ''Miss Witherspoon,'' comedy by Christopher Durang. Through April 28. $15 to $20. First Avenue Playhouse, 123 First Avenue. (732) 291-7552.</p>
        <p>Cranford ''Open Admissions,'' drama by Shirley Lauro, presented by the Theater Project. Through April 28. $10 to $20. Union County College, 1033 Springfield Avenue. (908) 659-5189.</p>
        <p>Eatontown ''The Lion in Winter,'' drama by James Goldman, presented by Over the Rainbow. Through April 28. $17 to $22. Eatontown Playhouse, Tower Market Shopping Center, 3713 Route 35 North. (732) 460-0100.</p>
        <p>Hoboken ''The Miracle Worker,'' drama by William Gibson, presented by the Hudson Theater Ensemble. Through April 15. $8 to $15. Hudson School, 601 Park Avenue. (201) 377-7014.</p>
        <p>Lawrenceville ''The Heidi Chronicles,'' drama by Wendy Wasserstein, presented by Rider University student actors. Through April 21. $4 to $10. Rider University, Yvonne Theater, 2083 Lawrenceville Road. (609) 896-5303.</p>
        <p>Long Branch ''Love and Murder,'' drama by Arthur Giron; world premiere. Through May 6. $25 to $40. New Jersey Repertory Company, 179 Broadway. (732) 229-3166.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick ''In the Sawtooths,'' drama by Dano Madden, presented by the Rutgers Theater Company. Friday through April 28. $15 to $25. ''Derby Day,'' premiere of the dark comedy by Samuel Brett Williams, presented by the Rutgers Theater Company. April 21 through 29. $15 to $25. Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, Douglass Campus, Rutgers University, 85 George Street. (732) 932-7511.</p>
        <p>New Brunswick Chinese Golden Dragon Acrobats. April 22 at 2 and 5 p.m. $20 to $50. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>Nutley ''I Hate Hamlet,'' comedy by Paul Rudnick. Through April 28. $12. Nutley Little Theater, 47 Erie Place (off Brookfield Avenue). (973) 667-0374.</p>
        <p>Oaklyn ''Much Ado About Nothing,'' William Shakespeare's comedy; directed by Denise George. Through April 15. $17 to $30. Ritz Theater, 915 White Horse Pike. (856) 858-5230.</p>
        <p>Oradell ''Angels in America: Millennium Approaches,'' drama by Tony Kushner, presented by the Bergen County Players. Through April 21. $15 and $18. Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road. (201) 261-4200.</p>
        <p>South Orange ''Dead Man Walking,'' drama by Tim Robbins, adapted from the book by Sister Helen Prejean. Friday through April 22. $8 to $15. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.</p>
        <p>Sussex Shakespeare's ''Twelfth Night,'' presented by the Tri-State Actors Theater. Thursday through May 6. $17 to $27. Crescent Theater, 74 Main Street. (973) 875-2950.</p>
        <p>Wayne ''Quilters,'' musical by Molly Newman and Barbara Damashek. Tuesday through April 22. $8 and $10. Hunziker Theater, William Paterson University, 300 Pompton Road. (973) 720-2371.</p>
        <p>Wayne ''Seussical,'' musical by Stephen Flaherty and Lynn Ahrens, adapted from the books by Dr. Seuss; presented by the William Paterson University Pioneer Players. Through April 22. $3 to $7. YM-YWHA of North Jersey, 1 Pike Drive. (973) 595-0100.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Clinton ''Barbara Klein: New Marks,'' abstract paintings, and ''How American Women Artists Invented Post Modernism,'' group show presented by the Feminist Art Project. Through June 3. Reception: April 15, 2 to 4 p.m. Donation: $3. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Hunterdon Museum of Art, 7 Lower Center Street. (908) 735-8415.</p>
        <p>Cranford ''Memories and Mountains,'' mixed-media by Carole Wong Chesak. Through Friday. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m. Additional hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 6 to 9 p.m. Tomasulo Gallery, Union County College, 1033 Springfield Avenue. (908) 709-7155.</p>
        <p>Hopewell ''The Intimacy of Flowers,'' photography by Tasha O'Neill. Through April 15. ''Double Take: Two Photographers, Two Coney Islands,'' works by Joanna Tully and Marty Schwartz. Friday through May 27. Reception: Friday, 6 to 9 p.m. Artist talk: April 22, 1 to 3 p.m. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Gallery 14, 14 Mercer Street. (609) 333-8511.</p>
        <p>Lambertville ''Constructions and Reconstructions,'' mixed media and photography by Nancy Shill and John Treichler. Through April 29. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m., or by appointment. Artists' Gallery, 32 Coryell Street. (609) 397-4588.</p>
        <p>Lincroft Photographs from the collection of Brookdale Community College, including works from prominent 20th-century documentary and fine art photographers. Through April 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Monmouth Museum, Brookdale Community College, Newman Springs Road. (732) 747-2266.</p>
        <p>Maplewood ''Raw Spirits: A Survey of Contemporary Folk and Outsider Art in America,'' group show. April 15 through May 27. Reception: April 15, 2 to 5 p.m. 1978 Arts Center, 1978 Springfield Avenue. (973) 275-9855.</p>
        <p>Maplewood ''Lisa Pressman: Mixed Media, Transitions and Processes.'' Through April 28. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, noon to 8 p.m. Classic Design Framing, 168 Maplewood Avenue. (973) 762-5588.</p>
        <p>Montclair ''Dreaming of a Speech Without Words: the Painting and Early Objects of H. C. Westermann.'' Through May 27. $6 to $8; free for members and children 12 and under; free for everyone on Fridays from 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Montclair Art Museum, 3 South Mountain Avenue. (973) 746-5555.</p>
        <p>Morristown ''Oil on Linen,'' paintings by David Moore. Through April 21. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Simon Gallery, 48 Bank Street. (973) 538-5456.</p>
        <p>Newark ''Mi Puerto Rico: Master Painters of the Island,'' paintings by José Campeche, Francisco Oller and Miguel Pou. Through April 15. $3 and $7. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., October through June; noon to 5 p.m., July through September. The Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street. (973) 596-6493.</p>
        <p>Oceanville ''Spinning Worlds: Emerging Artists,'' works by Paul Santoleri and Carla Falb. ''Surface Rhythms,'' work by Bennett Bean and Barbara Bullock. Both through April 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays noon to 5 p.m. Noyes Museum of Art, 733 Lily Lake Road. (609) 652-8848.</p>
        <p>Princeton '' History, Identity or None of the Above: Regarding African American Art,'' mixed-media exhibit. Through May 13. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Princeton University Art Museum, Nassau and Witherspoon Streets. (609) 258-3788.</p>
        <p>Rahway ''High Fiber Content,'' mixed-media group show. Through Friday. Hours: Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 1 to 3 p.m. and 5 to 7 p.m. Arts Guild of Rahway, 1670 Irving Street. (732) 381-7511.</p>
        <p>Skillman Group show by the A-Team Artists of Trenton. Through May 6. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Montgomery Center for the Arts, 124 Montgomery Road. (609) 921-3272.</p>
        <p>Springfield ''Structures,'' photographs by Sue Zwick. Through April 26. Hours: Mondays, Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Tuesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 3:30 p.m. Donald B. Palmer Museum, 66 Mountain Avenue. (973) 376-4930.</p>
        <p>Summit ''Wes Sherman: Recent Works,'' paintings. Thursday through May 19. Reception: Friday, 7 to 9 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Domo Gallery, 447 Springfield Avenue. (908) 608-0079.</p>
        <p>Trenton ''Friends for the Marsh 2007,'' photography exhibition. Through April 21. Free. Wood fired ceramics and handmade paper and printmaking, by Peter Callas and Margaret Kennard Johnson. Through April 22. Suggested admission $2 to $5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. The Trenton City Museum, Cadwalader Park. (609) 989-3632.</p>
        <p>Washington Township ''In the Shadows of Manhattan,'' mixed-media group show. Through April 22. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 6 a.m. to 10 p.m.; Fridays, 6 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 8 a.m. to 5 p.m. Atrium Gallery, Bergen County Y, 605 Pascack Road. (201) 666-6610, Extension 222.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
