<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HABITATS/Chelsea; Downsizing By Moving Downstairs</title>
    <meta content="15habi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/realestate/15habi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Habitats | Chelsea"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Stephen P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winter, Lewis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winter, Harriet</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Active Adult</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Brownstones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brownstones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chelsea (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3DC133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1215" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HABITATS/Chelsea; Downsizing By Moving Downstairs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Downsizing by Moving Downstairs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN P. WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Stephen P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Habitats column on Lewis Winter and wife Harriet, who have lived in triplex on West 20th Street for more than 40 years; couple plans to move into duplex they are creating in cellar of town house and rent out triplex for $16,000 per month; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SITTING at the dining-room table on the parlor floor of their town house in Chelsea, Harriet and Lewis Winter hear the whirring of a circular saw downstairs. The sound is reassuring evidence that the crew below them is busy creating a sleek duplex out of their once-dank cellar and the one-bedroom rental on the garden floor.</p>
        <p>But it's also a disconcerting reminder that sometime around May 1, when the saws stop and the workers leave, the Winters will vacate the triplex they have inhabited for more than 40 years and move downstairs. They hope to rent out the well-lived-in triplex for $16,000 a month after painting, installing new appliances and making repairs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A couple find a novel way to remain in their longtimeChelsea home while minimizing physical challenges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SITTING at the dining-room table on the parlor floor of their town house in Chelsea, Harriet and Lewis Winter hear the whirring of a circular saw downstairs. The sound is reassuring evidence that the crew below them is busy creating a sleek duplex out of their once-dank cellar and the one-bedroom rental on the garden floor.</p>
        <p>But it's also a disconcerting reminder that sometime around May 1, when the saws stop and the workers leave, the Winters will vacate the triplex they have inhabited for more than 40 years and move downstairs. They hope to rent out the well-lived-in triplex for $16,000 a month after painting, installing new appliances and making repairs.</p>
        <p>''We decided to build our own nursing home with a little park out back,'' said Mrs. Winter, who at 80 is finding it too challenging to climb the stairs to her third-floor bedroom, ''because I most certainly was not going to move to Florida.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Winter won't give his age, but the couple have been a fixture on West 20th Street since 1965, when they motored down from the Upper East Side to tour a different four-story brownstone that was for sale. They had been married for two years and wanted a home to replace the two-bedroom apartment they had been living in with Mrs. Winter's two daughters from a previous marriage.</p>
        <p>At just 12 feet across, the brownstone almost seemed narrow enough for Mr. Winter, who is more than six feet tall, to reach out and touch both walls.</p>
        <p>They said no thanks to the brownstone and headed for the door. As they stepped onto the stoop, Mrs. Winter was mesmerized by the 18-foot-wide brick house across the street.</p>
        <p>''The place just beckoned to me, saying, 'Buy me, buy me,' '' Mrs. Winter recalled. ''So I said, 'There's my house.' ''</p>
        <p>''Funny you should say that,'' the broker said, ''because that house is going to come on the market in a few months.''</p>
        <p>''We basically bought this house without seeing the interior,'' Mr. Winter said, looking around the parlor floor with its high ceilings, original plaster moldings and the new deck they built to help entice new tenants, whoever they'll be.</p>
        <p>The couple were drawn to the area by the sky, which was -- and still is -- huge, because most of the buildings in the neighborhood are low-rise. The surrounding blocks were lined with rooming houses for itinerant sailors.</p>
        <p>But where the Winters saw beauty, their friends and family saw peril.</p>
        <p>''Chelsea was a rapidly improving slum at the time -- how rapidly depended on your point of view,'' Mr. Winter said.</p>
        <p>His uncle, a lawyer, offered to donate his services for their closing until he heard the address. He backed out, telling them it was a horrible investment, and the Winters used another lawyer.</p>
        <p>In the end, they paid about $30,000 for the house, which was about the same price as the eight-room apartments they had been looking at on Central Park West. Michelle Barshay, of Barshay Brokerage, who is listing the Winters' triplex for rent and has found tenants for them for years, estimates that the house could now sell for about $5 million.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to have lived here and know that we didn't make a big mistake,'' Mrs. Winter said.</p>
        <p>But the couple saw the house as more of a home for her two daughters, Andrea and Joanna, and their son, Alex, who was born after they moved in, than as an investment.</p>
        <p>''As far as I was concerned, this was the most exciting place I had ever lived,'' Mrs. Winter said. ''There were guitars playing everywhere, and men playing dominoes on the streets. It was a surprising life I never thought I'd have.''</p>
        <p>For instance, not long after they moved in, she came across Joanna on her hands and knees on the sidewalk on Eighth Avenue, surrounded by strange men. She ran to rescue her, but her daughter just looked up and said, ''Aren't these guys great -- they're helping me find my contact lens.''</p>
        <p>Chelsea was clearly a long way from Long Island, where Mrs. Winter grew up in Woodmere and where the neighborhood kids would sometimes gather in front of the house waiting for Bob Hope to arrive to play cards with her father, a theatrical agent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Winter grew up nearby, but on the wrong side of the tracks, he said. They met only once when they were young, on a skating pond at the country club.</p>
        <p>''He was sweet, but he was a very tall raincoat-type guy,'' Mrs. Winter said. ''He wore the coat to hide his fat. I wouldn't have gone out with him.''</p>
        <p>Decades passed. When Mrs. Winter was 35, at the end of a long divorce, her daughters put a huge stuffed green frog in her bedroom and told her that it would turn into her handsome prince. Then one day she ran into Mr. Winter at a bar mitzvah on Long Island, and they hit it off.</p>
        <p>''When he first came to the house,'' she recalled, ''the kids said: 'It's him. The frog prince is here.' You can't see it now, but in those days he did look a bit like a human frog, with big eyes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Winter had lost weight, moved to New York and developed a strong interest in art. They were married within a year.</p>
        <p>In time, they went into business together, opening a store selling vintage clothing. After four years in the house on 20th Street, they started a clothing company called Mrs. H. Winter, with Mrs. Winter as the designer.</p>
        <p>After one of her shows, a vice president of Henri Bendel called her ''our own little Balenciaga,'' Mrs. Winter said.</p>
        <p>The Winters worked. They bought a country house. The children grew up and left.</p>
        <p>Then they started spending parts of each winter in Venice. When she was about 70, Mrs. Winter turned her passion for clothing into a passion for making complex needlepoint portraits of women. Turn them over and the knots and loose threads on the reverse side seem to deepen the character study in unimagined ways.</p>
        <p>As they got older, some things got harder. So a little over a year ago they decided to move downstairs. They had the cellar dug a couple of feet deeper, and the water heaters, furnaces and other mechanical equipment moved into a narrow space along one wall. They added rear windows that look out onto a trough dug out of the garden that will let light and air into the space.</p>
        <p>Guests -- children and grandchildren, primarily -- will stay here, along with the Winters' television set. Up a flight of stairs, they have extended the back wall of the house to make the deck above and are installing huge windows looking out onto the garden.</p>
        <p>''I plan to sew and grow old gracefully out there,'' Mrs. Winter said.</p>
        <p>She won't be the first. Some years after moving to Chelsea, the Winters discovered a plaque on the Episcopal church a few doors down.</p>
        <p>''It was dedicated to Harriet Winter, a local dressmaker who died two years before I was born,'' Mrs. Winter said.</p>
        <p>Although she's never learned which building the earlier Harriet Winter lived in, she wouldn't be at all surprised if it was her own.</p>
        <p>Habitats | Chelsea</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
