<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'For Sale' May Mean 'You Lose'</title>
    <meta content="15gret" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/business/yourmoney/15gret.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FAIR GAME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE2D6133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'For Sale' May Mean 'You Lose'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘For Sale’ May Mean ‘You Lose’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are quiet fire sales occurring inside the corporate bankruptcy world that hurt bondholders and other creditors while, in many cases, enriching insiders at failed companies.</p>
        <p>That is the message of a comprehensive and troubling new study by Lynn M. LoPucki, a bankruptcy expert who is a professor at the law school of the University of California, Los Angeles, and Joseph W. Doherty, director of the law school's Empirical Research Group. The study, titled ''Bankruptcy Fire Sales,'' examined 54 large companies that were going through the bankruptcy process from 2000 through 2004. It compared how much money creditors received when companies were sold during bankruptcy proceedings with how much they received when the companies emerged from bankruptcy, reorganized and got a fresh start.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Auctions make money, but how much goes to shareholders?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are quiet fire sales occurring inside the corporate bankruptcy world that hurt bondholders and other creditors while, in many cases, enriching insiders at failed companies.</p>
        <p>That is the message of a comprehensive and troubling new study by Lynn M. LoPucki, a bankruptcy expert who is a professor at the law school of the University of California, Los Angeles, and Joseph W. Doherty, director of the law school's Empirical Research Group. The study, titled ''Bankruptcy Fire Sales,'' examined 54 large companies that were going through the bankruptcy process from 2000 through 2004. It compared how much money creditors received when companies were sold during bankruptcy proceedings with how much they received when the companies emerged from bankruptcy, reorganized and got a fresh start.</p>
        <p>The study found that bankrupt companies whose managers chose to sell them -- an increasingly popular route in recent years, according to Mr. LoPucki -- received roughly half what was generated at companies that decided to reorganize. This suggests that creditors and shareholders can nearly double their recoveries by pushing their companies to reorganize rather than to sell, the authors said.</p>
        <p>Management also appears to be using the veil of bankruptcy to cash in, according to the study. In 11 of 30 bankruptcy sales examined, the chief executives involved received specific benefits associated with the decision to sell. These benefits included severance payments generated by the sales or job offers from buyers after C.E.O.'s sell their companies. In other cases, chief executives became paid consultants to companies buying the assets.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, creditors and shareholders are often helpless bystanders in the bankruptcy process, at the mercy of insiders and their legal and financial advisers. Even so, the study comes at a time when investors are not much interested in what Mr. LoPucki calls a deeply biased bankruptcy process. Mergers, takeovers and hot initial public offerings are so much more compelling.</p>
        <p>But investors should pay closer attention to the bankruptcy process, given how many formerly highflying subprime mortgage lenders are teetering on the edge of collapse or are already falling apart.</p>
        <p>According to the study, companies that sold out during the bankruptcy process received an average of 35 percent of their book value, or net worth. Conversely, companies that reorganized did so at a value of 80 percent of book value. That's some spread. And it was found across industries as diverse as retailing, energy, airlines, entertainment and technology.</p>
        <p>''Companies that file bankruptcy have internal incentive types of problems that make them willing to sell their property for less than it's worth,'' Mr. LoPucki said in an interview last week. ''The judges are supposed to control it. But they are making rulings that are favorable to the people that bring them cases, so they will continue to bring them cases.''</p>
        <p>Big bankruptcy cases, of course, generate enormous fees and revenues for the court system. And judges are increasingly willing to let companies and their lawyers call the shots in these proceedings, Mr. LoPucki said.</p>
        <p>This phenomenon was explored extensively in Mr. LoPucki's 2005 book, ''Courting Failure: How Competition for Big Cases Is Corrupting the Bankruptcy Courts.'' He said competition has been pursued most aggressively in the bankruptcy courts in Delaware and New York City.</p>
        <p>In filing for bankruptcies, companies can choose the court where their case will be heard. New Century Financial, a subprime lender that filed for bankruptcy protection earlier this month, is a case in point. Based in California and incorporated in Maryland, New Century chose to file its case in Delaware, where a subsidiary is incorporated. A company spokeswoman did not respond to an interview request inquiring about their choice of venue for their bankruptcy filing.</p>
        <p>''This is a very sophisticated game,'' Mr. LoPucki said. ''The judges are not blatantly favoring one party over another; it's very subtle. But when you see the pattern -- and I see them in the cases -- then you realize there is something very wrong going on. The parties who bring them the cases are getting what they want.'' The LoPucki-Doherty study is a compelling rebuttal to academics who have argued in recent years that auctions were more effective than reorganizations at extracting value from a bankrupt company. Trust in the market's ability to price assets rationally was behind that view; not surprisingly, bankruptcy sales have grown considerably.</p>
        <p>Especially popular, Mr. LoPucki said, are sales under Section 363 of the federal bankruptcy code, which allows managers to sell a company quickly without giving creditors the chance to vote on the deal or providing a detailed disclosure statement required under reorganization law. Compounding the problem is that once a judge approves a sale, appeals are not available.</p>
        <p>As it turns out, ''the market'' that is entrusted to price a bankrupt company may also be subject to what economists call an ''agency problem'' -- characterized by managers and other parties putting their own interests ahead of those of owners or creditors in bankruptcy cases.</p>
        <p>Consider the October 2001 bankruptcy of Polaroid. In April 2002, its co-chief executives sold the company to the sole private bidder for approximately $465 million, a price widely criticized as too low and far below the $1.8 billion in assets that Polaroid had listed in its bankruptcy petition.</p>
        <p>The creditors raised their objections to the judge overseeing the case in Delaware, arguing that the company would be worth more in reorganization. The judge approved the deal nonetheless. After the sale closed, Polaroid disclosed that the co-chiefs had each received stock in the acquiring company valued at $3 million to $4 million. Ka-ching!</p>
        <p>Mr. LoPucki argues that investment bankers hired to sell a company have few incentives to maximize the bids they receive. Investment bankers may not think it worth their while to curry favor with the sellers who hired them because the companies are going out of business, he speculates. Furthermore, underpricing an asset creates value for the buyer, who may then compensate the banker with future business, he says.</p>
        <p>While bankers often receive ''success'' fees totaling 1 percent of a company's sale price, Mr. LoPucki said a fee resulting from a higher price is often not worth the extra effort required to achieve it. Better to go on to the next deal.</p>
        <p>THAT leaves creditors and judges to make sure the process is effective, Mr. LoPucki said. Too often the creditors are powerless and the judges passive or eager to please.</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. LoPucki said, bankruptcy courts are not fulfilling their obligation to ensure that the best interests of the debtor's estate are being served, the study concluded. ''There are billions of dollars being pulled out of this system,'' he said. The Michigan Law Review plans to publish the LoPucki-Doherty study in November. A copy is at www.law.ucla.edu/docs/lopuckidohertyfire--4-11-07.pdf.</p>
        <p>That creditors would be treated like steerage passengers on the S.S. Bankruptcy is not really surprising. The practices described in the study and the results they bring are completely in keeping with the treatment that many public company shareholders receive today from me-first managers. Whether the company is thriving or diving, being an insider has never been better.</p>
        <p>FAIR GAME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
