<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Packing on the Pollution</title>
    <meta content="15WEsells" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delivery Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sells, Mimi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Packing on the Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mimi Sells</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sells, Mimi</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by former public relations executive Mimi Sells on her discovery that e-commerce is not necessarily greener way to shop; says overnight air shipment, fueled by instant consumer gratification, is serious carbon polluter; offers ways to become more conscientious consumer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN ''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire'' came out in July 2000, Amazon and FedEx collaborated on shipping 250,000 books overnight to Potter fans around the world, myself included. A few weeks ago, Amazon e-mailed its customers to offer first-day (and bargain-priced) acquisition of this summer's must read, ''Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows,'' the seventh and last in the series. As a result, Amazon reported that advance orders were 547 percent higher than for Book 6, published in 2005. Like millions of others, I signed up for mine.</p>
        <p>But now, I'm having second thoughts. While researching the environmental effects of online shopping, I discovered that e-commerce isn't necessarily a greener way to shop. Indeed, a trip to the local bookstore might be ''cleaner'' than shopping online.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN ''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire'' came out in July 2000, Amazon and FedEx collaborated on shipping 250,000 books overnight to Potter fans around the world, myself included. A few weeks ago, Amazon e-mailed its customers to offer first-day (and bargain-priced) acquisition of this summer's must read, ''Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows,'' the seventh and last in the series. As a result, Amazon reported that advance orders were 547 percent higher than for Book 6, published in 2005. Like millions of others, I signed up for mine.</p>
        <p>But now, I'm having second thoughts. While researching the environmental effects of online shopping, I discovered that e-commerce isn't necessarily a greener way to shop. Indeed, a trip to the local bookstore might be ''cleaner'' than shopping online.</p>
        <p>The really scary thing about my research is that there is so little information about the environmental costs of online shopping and none of it current. Salon published an article seven years ago that clued me in to the great Harry Potter mail drop of 2000. The article said: ''It's easy to imagine how good shopping online could be for the environment. After all, retail space with its hardwood floors, heating and cooling costs and huge parking lots can be a bigger drain on natural resources than warehouse space.''</p>
        <p>But the article also pointed out that although we might buy products online in what appears an efficient trade-off from driving, if we ship them back for returns or exchanges we create a double shipping impact. And when we order a single book on a whim rather than bundling several book or other purchases into one shipment, we create excess trips.</p>
        <p>Moreover, in 2000, people were mostly buying books and CD's online; today they're purchasing big items like plasma TVs, computers and home appliances that weigh a whole lot more and require a lot more packaging.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the biggest anti-green factor is the seductive power of the Internet to provide instant consumer gratification: If you want something, order it now! Have it shipped overnight! Why wait? Back in 2000, few people were talking about carbon footprints. We were worried about the price of the fuel, not the cost of the fumes. But now we know air transport is a serious carbon polluter.</p>
        <p>What's worse is that overnight shipping is an even dirtier business. Research has shown that nighttime air transport produces twice the pollution of day flights because of condensation trails that trap heat. These trails create a greater warming effect in the dark because there is no sunlight to reflect them back into space.</p>
        <p>The Internet seduces you with access to millions and millions of products that you can instantly click and order and see miraculously appear on your doorstep the next morning. You can shop day or night. And, there are thousands of merchants that will gladly give you free shipping for the privilege of feeding your retail appetite.</p>
        <p>How big is that appetite? According to eMarketer.com, a digital market research firm, online shopping increased to more than $102 billion in 2006 from just $60 billion in 2000.</p>
        <p>I know women who swear by Zappos shoes. They will buy several pairs and simply return the ones they don't like. Free shipping and free returns are the bait that turn us into restless consumers. But all this shipping back and forth can't be good for the environment.</p>
        <p>I'm not suggesting that we don't shop online. I love comparison and product-review shopping sites that help me find the best stuff at the lowest prices. But I think we all need to be more conscientious consumers to avoid increasing environmental (and personal) pollution with things we don't really need. Never order overnight delivery unless it's a true emergency (the latest Manolo Blahnik shoes are not an emergency). Avoid compulsive click-shopping. To reduce shipping returns, do your research online to be sure that what you order is what you really want. Indeed, wait 24 hours before placing an order. If you still have to have it a day later, then buy it.</p>
        <p>We also need to encourage retailers to observe clean shipping practices like using recycled shipping materials, eliminating excess packaging and discouraging excess customer returns by charging a small restocking fee. We don't need fancy boxes arriving by mail (unless it's a Tiffany box, of course) so let merchants know you'd like the most environmentally friendly packaging and shipping method for your purchases.</p>
        <p>Harry Potter transported through the fireplace to Diagon Alley for his shopping needs. Shopping online can be just as magical and be far more environmentally gentle if we simply think before we click.</p>
        <p>Mimi Sells is a former public relations executive for an online comparison shopping company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mimi Sells is a former public relations executive for an online comparison shopping company.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
