<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With DiPietro Back in the Islanders' Crease, Buffalo Folds</title>
    <meta content="15isles" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/hockey/15isles.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dipietro, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With DiPietro Back in the Islanders' Crease, Buffalo Folds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With DiPietro Back in the Islanders’ Crease, Buffalo Folds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY MATT HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO, N.Y., April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With their franchise goaltender, Rick DiPietro, healthy again, the Islanders have a new outlook for their Eastern Conference playoff series against the Buffalo Sabres.</p>
        <p>DiPietro had not played since March 25 because of postconcussion symptoms, but he appeared in top form Saturday night, stopping 32 shots in the Islanders' 3-2 victory. Their first-round series is now tied at one game apiece, with Game 3 on Monday at Nassau Coliseum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a stellar performance for Rick DiPietro, who had missed 10 games with postconcussion symptoms. DiPietro made 32 saves in victory that evened their quarterfinal series, 1-1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With their franchise goaltender, Rick DiPietro, healthy again, the Islanders have a new outlook for their Eastern Conference playoff series against the Buffalo Sabres.</p>
        <p>DiPietro had not played since March 25 because of postconcussion symptoms, but he appeared in top form Saturday night, stopping 32 shots in the Islanders' 3-2 victory. Their first-round series is now tied at one game apiece, with Game 3 on Monday at Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>DiPietro, who missed 10 games, showed no ill effects from his time off and the Islanders played better in front of him than they had in Game 1 for Wade Dubielewicz, his replacement.</p>
        <p>Six minutes after the Sabres tied the score at 2-2 in the third period, defenseman Marc-André Bergeron scored the winner on a power play 8 minutes 37 seconds into the period. He took a pass from defenseman Tom Poti and fired a slap shot past Sabres goalie Ryan Miller.</p>
        <p>''Obviously Ricky was outstanding,'' Islanders forward Jason Blake said. ''Anytime you've got him in the lineup, he definitely gives your club a boost, and certainly a better chance of winning.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''He played a great game and it's a testament to his character being out for so long and coming into a playoff game of this magnitude. The way he played was unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>In DiPietro's last start, March 25 against the Rangers, he sustained his second concussion in two weeks. The Islanders played well enough in his absence to clinch the eighth and final playoff seed in the conference.</p>
        <p>But they appeared overmatched in Game 1 against the top-seeded Sabres, who finished the regular season with the best record in the league. Buffalo dominated in a 4-1 victory Thursday.</p>
        <p>But from the opening face-off Saturday, it was clear the Islanders were a different team with DiPietro. They scored on their third shot of the game, 3:07 into the game, for a 1-0 lead.</p>
        <p>A shot by Mike Sillinger glanced off Trent Hunter's skate past Miller. Poti set up the play, finding Sillinger unguarded in the left face-off circle. Sillinger faked a shot before unloading the puck into a crowd in front of Miller.</p>
        <p>The Islanders continued to apply pressure and grabbed a 2-0 lead at 11:03.</p>
        <p>With the teams playing four on four, Miroslav Satan beat Sabres forward Daniel Brière cleanly on a face-off. The puck went directly to defenseman Bruno Gervais at the point, and his wrist shot sneaked between Miller's pads.</p>
        <p>But the Sabres had come back from two goals to win 10 times this season, a franchise record. And for a time they threatened to do so again.</p>
        <p>Buffalo would pull to 2-1 with a minute remaining in the first period on a shot through traffic by defenseman Toni Lydman.</p>
        <p>Thomas Vanek carried the puck from behind the net into the slot and dished to Lydman, who beat DiPietro with a wrist shot.</p>
        <p>And the regular season's highest scoring team would continue to pour on offensive pressure.</p>
        <p>The Sabres tied the game at 2:12 of the third on a goal by defenseman Dmitri Kalinin. DiPietro made two saves before Kalinin scored on a rebound from a scramble.</p>
        <p>But DiPietro would be sterling down the stretch to preserve the win. His presence has clearly changed the tenor of the series for Buffalo.</p>
        <p>''There are no easy games,'' Lydman said. ''It's only going to get harder. This was our last chance to learn that lesson.''</p>
        <p>PENGUINS 4, SENATORS 3 -- Sidney Crosby scored his second goal of the playoffs midway through the third period for visiting Pittsburgh, which evened its first-round Eastern Conference series with Ottawa. Game 3 is today in Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>The Penguins tied the score twice in the third period before Crosby scored the winner at 11:44. Crosby, at 19 the league's youngest winner of the Art Ross Trophy, which is given to the league's scoring champion, redirected a cross-ice pass from Mark Recchi past goalie Ray Emery.</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh outshot the Senators, 37-21. (AP)</p>
        <p>PREDATORS' RADULOV SUSPENDED -- The National Hockey League suspended Nashville forward Alexander Radulov for one game for his hit from behind of San Jose forward Steve Bernier on Friday in Game 2 of their first-round Western Conference playoff series. Radulov will miss tomorrow's game at San Jose. (AP)</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
