<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children's Books / Young Adult</title>
    <meta content="Hearn.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/review/Hearn.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children's Books / Young Adult</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Children’s Books / Young Adult</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL PATRICK HEARN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hearn, Michael Patrick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Navigator</p>
        <p>By Eoin McNamee.</p>
        <p>342 pp. Wendy Lamb Books/</p>
        <p>Random House. $15.99.</p>
        <p>(Ages 10 to 13)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An adventure tale combining fantasy, medieval romance, science fiction and World War II movies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Navigator</p>
        <p>By Eoin McNamee.</p>
        <p>342 pp. Wendy Lamb Books/</p>
        <p>Random House. $15.99.</p>
        <p>(Ages 10 to 13)</p>
        <p>Owen is unlike other boys. He does not know why people look at him so strangely. His father is dead, perhaps a suicide, and the child lives alone with his depressive mother. He also suffers from hydrophobia, and he seeks solace in the Den, his secret room dug into the hillside near the deserted Workhouse. A chance meeting with an odd little man called the Sub-Commandant, who is barely taller than Owen himself, leads the boy to his destiny as the Navigator in the struggle between the Resisters and their enemies, the Harsh.</p>
        <p>A dark flash in the sky turns to total blackness, and the world as the boy knows it vanishes. The Workhouse is suddenly teeming with activity, for the Resisters, now awakened from the Sleep, have set up their headquarters there.</p>
        <p>The Sub-Commandant's daughter, Cati, is assigned to look after Owen, but some of the other warriors are suspicious of the new recruit. Who exactly is this boy who, like the Harsh, fears water? Was his father really a traitor? Did he steal the Mortmain, a mysterious instrument that will turn off the Great Machine of the Puissance, the vortex? Owen, the young outsider, must prove his valor and loyalty to the cause.</p>
        <p>Like so many other contemporary Anglo-Irish fantasies, ''The Navigator'' echoes ''The Chronicles of Narnia,'' ''The Lord of the Rings'' and the Harry Potter books, which in turn all look back to the legends of King Arthur. Here, Owen the Navigator is the innocent chosen to save the world. There is also a good dose of ''Star Wars'' thrown in. The Harsh are the dark side, Cati is like Princess Leia, and the enemy leader, Johnston, substitutes for Darth Vader. All the marvelous gadgets and vehicles that Owen discovers, like magno guns and Q-cars (with wheels nearly as high as a three-story building), could have come out of George Lucas's storehouse. The eccentric inventor Dr. Diamond, who sometimes speaks backward, is a combination of Obi-Wan Kenobi and Yoda. Instead of ''May the Force be with you,'' he tells Owen, ''Magno is the force that binds.'' He is the one who explains the true fate of Owen's father.</p>
        <p>The novel is a strange amalgamation of fantasy, medieval romance, science fiction and World War II movies. The setting is pre-nuclear: warriors bear knives, crossbows, lances and bayonets along with ingenious, scientifically advanced mechanical devices. A great ship propels itself on long, thin oars across the water like an insect on a lake. Deadly birdlike airplanes raid the Resisters and the Raggies, an irregular force of abandoned children. This is also a 21st-century adventure story in which men and women engage equally in deadly combat.</p>
        <p>The Harsh are haunting figures. These vaporous, faceless beings, all in white, glide effortlessly across the landscape, an almost unstoppable ecological force determined to push back time to an ice age before there were any men and women. Their very breath nearly freezes Cati to death, and Owen is ''hit by a frozen blast of what felt like the coldest sleet he had ever experienced -- sleet like frozen knives, cutting through his clothes with a noise like the howling of a terrible wind.''</p>
        <p>This is the first children's book by Eoin McNamee, the Northern Irish writer of political thrillers who is best known for his debut novel, ''Resurrection Man,'' set amid the violence of Belfast in the 1980s. It may be too easy to interpret the war in ''The Navigator'' as a metaphor for the conflict between the Irish (the Resisters) and the British (the Harsh) in Northern Ireland. The imagery could apply to tyranny anywhere. But the novel goes beyond tiresome allegory and becomes a riveting tale of good and evil.</p>
        <p>McNamee's style is refreshingly taut and spare, full of active verbs. He does not describe what his energetic characters are doing. He just lets them do it. Like the best pulp fiction, the story zips along as swiftly as a film treatment. There are enough twists and turns in the lightning plot to fill half a dozen B movies (no surprise, this is Book 1 in a projected series). It splits into parallel adventures on land and at sea when Owen and Cati are briefly separated, then reunites them for the tense climax.</p>
        <p>One quibble: The book contains handsome illustrations by Jon Goodell -- oddly, he is credited only on the copyright page -- but they are few and far between. The story would have benefited from more of these atmospheric drawings.</p>
        <p>Michael Patrick Hearn's many books include ''The Annotated Wizard of Oz.'' His study of Russian children's book illustration will be published in Moscow in the fall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Patrick Hearn's many books include ''The Annotated Wizard of Oz.'' His study of Russian children's book illustration will be published in Moscow in the fall.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
