<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Avery Makes Own Luck, and the Difference</title>
    <meta content="15rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/hockey/15rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Thrashers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Shanahan, Brendan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Avery, Sean</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Avery Makes Own Luck, and the Difference</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers’ Avery Makes His Luck and the Difference</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a still-open cut swelling his left eye and an ice pack strapped to his left wrist, Rangers forward Sean Avery stood in the visitors' locker room at Philips Arena on Saturday and wore his scars proudly.</p>
        <p>Avery had taken hit after hit from the Atlanta Thrashers and yet was largely responsible for both goals in a 2-1 victory that gave the Rangers a 2-0 lead in their Eastern Conference first-round playoff series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sean Avery scored a goal on a weird bounce off the glass in the first period, then sent a sharp pass across the crease to Brendan Shanahan for the winning goal with 4 minutes 1 second left.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a still-open cut swelling his left eye and an ice pack strapped to his left wrist, Rangers forward Sean Avery stood in the visitors' locker room at Philips Arena on Saturday and wore his scars proudly.</p>
        <p>Avery had taken hit after hit from the Atlanta Thrashers and yet was largely responsible for both goals in a 2-1 victory that gave the Rangers a 2-0 lead in their Eastern Conference first-round playoff series.</p>
        <p>The series now heads to Madison Square Garden for Games 3 and 4, starting Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''Pound for pound, I don't know if there is a tougher, more engaging player in the game than that guy right there,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said.</p>
        <p>''He got opened up in the game, but it was almost a badge of honor, not just for him, but for his teammates, to see the blood coming down his face.''</p>
        <p>Avery scored a goal on a weird bounce off the glass in the first period, then sent a sharp pass across the crease to a wide-open Brendan Shanahan for the winning goal with 4 minutes 1 second left in the third.</p>
        <p>It was vintage Avery. His tough, agitating ways had drawn angry Thrashers to him all game. Several defensemen were trying to tie him up in front of the net when he found Shanahan for a clear shot.</p>
        <p>''The more attention on me, the less there is on my teammates and the better I play,'' Avery said. ''It keeps me on my toes.''</p>
        <p>For Shanahan, it was only his second goal since his return to the lineup March 21 after missing a month with a concussion. He said that he, Avery and center Martin Straka had talked before the game about being patient in front of the net and finding each other.</p>
        <p>''I yelled for it,'' Shanahan said. ''You just kind of hope it's coming. It's one thing to get open, but to play with a player that recognizes that you've got a good lane to the net, that's a great hockey player. Sean made a great pass on the play.''</p>
        <p>For the second game in a row, the Rangers skated into a raucous atmosphere here and did not let it rattle them. They won Game 1 on Thursday by scoring early and forcing the Thrashers to play catch-up. Game 2 quickly became a defensive battle.</p>
        <p>Atlanta Coach Bob Hartley tried to jump-start his team by switching goalies, benching Kari Lehtonen and starting the veteran Johan Hedberg. And the Thrashers tried to wear down the Rangers by hitting them at every opportunity.</p>
        <p>Avery was their prime target. As the Rangers' feistiest player, Avery does a masterly job of drawing penalties, but also often collects penalties himself. In this game, Avery took the hits -- some cheap, some clean -- and did not retaliate.</p>
        <p>''You've got to take it for the team and it's the time of year when the team's always first,'' Avery said. ''It's tough at times, but I think the team that does that more is the team that succeeds.''</p>
        <p>Despite the pounding, Avery and his linemates continually got free for scoring chances, but Hedberg was playing a strong game and went on to stop 37 shots.</p>
        <p>The Rangers' first goal had nothing to do with Hedberg's ability and little to do with Avery's. He was merely dumping the puck deep when it caromed off a partition in the glass to the left of the goal and slid toward the net. Hedberg was waiting behind his net for the dump-in and could not scramble back in time to save it. With 11:52 left in the first, the Rangers had an unlikely 1-0 lead.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen a puck go like that,'' Hedberg said. ''It just came flying. The glass has been good all year.''</p>
        <p>The teams played a tight game through the second and Atlanta tied the score, 1-1, 5:35 into the third on a great give-and-go play between Ilya Kovalchuk and Keith Tkachuk. Kovalchuk passed to Tkachuk behind the net, skated to an open spot in front of it and collected Tkachuk's pass for a wrist shot that beat Henrik Lundqvist to the top left corner.</p>
        <p>That sent the crowd into new frenzy, but it failed to unnerve the Rangers, who responded with a half-dozen scoring chances that culminated in Shanahan's goal.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't nervous at all,'' forward Jaromir Jagr said. ''I had a good feeling about it. You never know, but I felt 80 percent we're going to win it. I don't know why. Sometimes you just have to feel it.''</p>
        <p>Shanahan said, ''Until you win four, you haven't accomplished anything.''</p>
        <p>But the Rangers' bruises feel a lot better cushioned by two victories.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>The Rangers made no lineup changes for Game 2. Center Blair Betts played about nine minutes after missing practice Friday with what was described as various ''bumps and bruises.''  After being called for two penalties in Game 1, the Rangers were called for three in the first period and another two each in the second and third.  Rangers Coach Tom Renney said it was possible that defenseman Karel Rachunek could return for Game 3.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
