<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Waste Lead, but This Time Can't Recover</title>
    <meta content="15devilsxx" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/hockey/15devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Lightning</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Holmqvist, Johan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Louis, Martin St.</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brodeur, Martin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lecavalier, Vincent</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Waste Lead, but This Time Can't Recover</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Devils Waste Lead, but This Time Can’t Recover</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils got away with giving up three goals Thursday because Tampa Bay Lightning goaltender Johan Holmqvist gave up five. The Devils did not exploit a weakness as much as Holmqvist sprang a leak.</p>
        <p>Game 2 of this playoff series was different. Tampa Bay's Martin St. Louis and Vincent Lecavalier, placed on separate lines midway through the game, scored on consecutive shots to beat the Devils, 3-2, Saturday night before a crowd of 18,231 at Continental Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martin St. Louis and Vincent Lecavalier, placed on separate lines midway through the game, scored on consecutive shots to beat the Devils on Saturday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils got away with giving up three goals Thursday because Tampa Bay Lightning goaltender Johan Holmqvist gave up five. The Devils did not exploit a weakness as much as Holmqvist sprang a leak.</p>
        <p>Game 2 of this playoff series was different. Tampa Bay's Martin St. Louis and Vincent Lecavalier, placed on separate lines midway through the game, scored on consecutive shots to beat the Devils, 3-2, Saturday night before a crowd of 18,231 at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>''They're excellent players, and they took advantage of their opportunities,'' Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' general manager and interim coach, said of St. Louis and Lecavalier. ''Our best players have to step up and get the job done, too.''</p>
        <p>Holmqvist stopped 34 shots, some with flair, to help the Lightning tie the best-of-seven series at 1-1. The next two games are to be played Monday and Wednesday at the St. Pete Times Forum in Tampa, Fla.</p>
        <p>''He's had his struggles throughout the year at certain times and always seems to bounce back, sometimes within a game, sometimes the next game,'' Tampa Bay Coach John Tortorella said of Holmqvist.</p>
        <p>After St. Louis's goal tied the score at 2-2 in the final minute of a second period that the Devils dominated until the last two shifts, Lecavalier gave Tampa Bay the lead for good 1 minute 42 seconds into the third.</p>
        <p>As Lightning defenseman Paul Ranger collected a pass near the blue line, Lecavalier found room in front of Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur. Ranger sent a strong wrist shot bouncing toward the goal, and Lecavalier deflected it in.</p>
        <p>''He's such a big player, and he's physical,'' Brodeur said of Lecavalier. ''He creates his own space out there.''</p>
        <p>St. Louis's goal tied the score at 19:11 of the second period, less than three minutes after the Devils took a 2-1 lead. After a Devils' turnover, St. Louis charged to a spot to the far left of Brodeur, took a pass and walloped a slap shot from a severe angle.</p>
        <p>The shot, Brodeur said, hit his left wrist, then his pants, then went in.</p>
        <p>The same fans who whipped up a din moments earlier, when Jamie Langenbrunner scored a power-play goal for the Devils, groaned after St. Louis's goal.</p>
        <p>''They do not need many chances to score a goal,'' Devils left wing Jay Pandolfo said.</p>
        <p>Yielding a goal in the final minute of any period is a downer, but the Devils had amassed an 18-5 edge in shots in the second period and had Tampa Bay scrambling for most of the period.</p>
        <p>At 14:45 of the second, the Lightning received a penalty for having too many men on the ice, and Filip Kuba was called for a holding penalty 47 seconds later when he tackled Patrik Elias in front of the goal. Less than a minute after that second penalty, Langenbrunner scored on an assist from Brian Gionta.</p>
        <p>Zach Parise had tied the score, 1-1, at 18:11 of the first period with his third goal in two games, this one with the Devils on a power play. Kuba polished off a 3-on-2 rush by scoring a short-handed goal 9:02 into the game.</p>
        <p>The Devils' top line of Elias, Scott Gomez and Gionta floundered. They took 10 shots and did not score. Gionta hit a goalpost on one shot and shook his head in dismay. Lamoriello said he was unimpressed with all three players. They were, too.</p>
        <p>''Now, it's our turn to respond,'' Gomez said, referring to the team as a whole. ''We had our chances. The difference was, we didn't score on any of them.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
