<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patient Privilege</title>
    <meta content="15WWLN--Ethicist.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/magazine/15WWLNEthicist.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-15-07: THE ETHICIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hepatitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/The Ethicist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hepatitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hepatitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patient Privilege</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Patient Privilege</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Cohen Ethicist column comments on whether patients should allow residents to sit in when their doctors are examining them; also comments on how far volunteer firefighter should go to alert other rescue workers that bloodied woman they are removing from wrecked automobile is infected with hepatitis C if they refuse to put on protective gloves (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When I went for an examination, my surgeon asked if two residents could be present. I felt uncomfortable being undressed in front of extra people, and so I declined. My surgeon scolded me, saying I was preventing the next generation of doctors from being trained. Why is it my responsibility to provide training for medical students?</p>
        <p>name withheld, Beit Shemesh, Israel</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dilemmas concerning privacy, tested and respected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When I went for an examination, my surgeon asked if two residents could be present. I felt uncomfortable being undressed in front of extra people, and so I declined. My surgeon scolded me, saying I was preventing the next generation of doctors from being trained. Why is it my responsibility to provide training for medical students?</p>
        <p>name withheld, Beit Shemesh, Israel</p>
        <p>Your surgeon's request was reasonable; her brow-beating you was not. She's right that a new physician's education must include work with actual patients, under the supervision of a wily veteran like herself. Because you, like all of us, rely on the skills of physicians trained in this way, you have a general obligation to reciprocate, to assist the next generation of patients as the past generation of patients has assisted you.</p>
        <p>Happily for you, this training needs the participation of many patients but not all. Some are profoundly uncomfortable when being examined, particularly by strangers, particularly when those extra docs are not medically necessary. Feeling as you do, you may decline your surgeon's request, a decision she must accept graciously: no scolding, no eye-rolling. Her primary obligation is the well-being of her current patient, not the training of her future colleagues.</p>
        <p>But if you demur, you should find another way to do your fair share for the health-care community of which you are a member and from which you benefit. Give blood, sign your organ-donor card, arrange to donate your body to science, give money to your hospital. There are many ways to contribute; I'm sure that your physician herself can suggest some.</p>
        <p>I am a volunteer firefighter. I responded to an accident involving someone I knew to be infected with hepatitis C, a contagious disease. As we cut the roof off her car to remove this injured and bleeding woman, two police officers approached to administer first aid. They were not wearing protective gloves, so I offered each a pair; they declined. Should I have revealed her medical condition? Should I inform those officers now so they can be tested and perhaps treated?</p>
        <p>Ryan Thomas, Oakland County, Mich.</p>
        <p>Your concern for the privacy of your injured acquaintance is admirable, but yes, you should have alerted those police officers to their serious, imminent danger. Their peril superseded her claims to confidentiality.</p>
        <p>These officers were -- what's the word? knuckleheads! -- not to have donned their gloves already. Surely they were trained to. Had they observed this protocol for administering first aid, they would have shielded themselves from the blood-borne diseases any victim might carry and dodged a clash between their safety and a victim's privacy.</p>
        <p>You should have warned them (avoiding the word ''knucklehead'') by offering the minimum information necessary, i.e., by declaring that you knew her to have an infectious disease. If those doofuses still eschewed protective gear, you could then have said that she's a vampire. O.K., not a vampire, but you could have progressed gradually but swiftly from the general to the particular, mentioning her specific condition only as a last resort.</p>
        <p>Having failed to do that, you must now urge them to get tested, which means revealing what they must be tested for.</p>
        <p>UPDATE: Thomas spoke to the victim, who volunteered to notify the rescue workers herself.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-15-07: THE ETHICIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
