<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kimberly Young, Stefano Rivella</title>
    <meta content="15young" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Young, Kimberly Marie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivella, Stefano</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFD9133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kimberly Young, Stefano Rivella</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kimberly Marie Young, the daughter of Ada Ortúzar-Young and Roger Young of Cedar Knolls, N.J., was married last evening to Stefano Rivella, the son of Liliana Perta Curtis of Cervaro, Italy, and Attilio Rivella of Turin, Italy. Mary Beaty, a chaplain of the American Humanist Association, officiated at the Angel Orensanz Foundation in New York.</p>
        <p>Ms. Young, 26, is keeping her name. She is a member of a group that structures and underwrites leveraged loans in the New York investment banking unit of the Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce. She graduated cum laude from George Washington University and received a master's degree in economics from Boston University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kimberly Marie Young, the daughter of Ada Ortúzar-Young and Roger Young of Cedar Knolls, N.J., was married last evening to Stefano Rivella, the son of Liliana Perta Curtis of Cervaro, Italy, and Attilio Rivella of Turin, Italy. Mary Beaty, a chaplain of the American Humanist Association, officiated at the Angel Orensanz Foundation in New York.</p>
        <p>Ms. Young, 26, is keeping her name. She is a member of a group that structures and underwrites leveraged loans in the New York investment banking unit of the Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce. She graduated cum laude from George Washington University and received a master's degree in economics from Boston University.</p>
        <p>Her father retired as a senior member of the technical staff in Clifton, N.J., for ITT Avionics, the military aviation electronics division of ITT Industries; he designed software, mainly for Air Force radar jammers. Her mother is a Spanish literature professor at Drew University in Madison, N.J.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rivella, 40, is an assistant professor of genetic medicine at Weill Medical College of Cornell University in New York, researching genetic cures for diseases of the blood. He graduated from University of Pavia in Italy, where he also received a Ph.D. in applied genetics.</p>
        <p>His mother is a museum administrator providing clerical and office support to a variety of programs at the National Archaeological Museum of Cassino in Italy. His father is the owner of Abi, a firm that designs and renovates commercial properties in Turin.</p>
        <p>The couple's first contact came three years ago at DanceSport, a studio in New York: they exchanged meaningful glances at a tango dance called a milonga, where the stylized rituals of tango are observed.</p>
        <p>''In Argentina, you often go to the milonga by yourself and look for ladies to dance with there,'' Dr. Rivella said. ''You communicate by looking at each other. If the other person smiles back, you approach them and clarify that you want to dance with her.''</p>
        <p>That look -- officially called the cabaceo -- was successful and when she saw it, Ms. Young responded with an affirmative nod.</p>
        <p>After that first dance, which included several numbers, they went on to other partners, but the bride said, ''When we were rotating partners, I noticed that he was trying to cut in line and maneuver his last partner closer to me. Then we started talking by the wine counter, and he walked me home.''</p>
        <p>They began going to more milongas, at first by themselves and then together. ''It was good that we were both beginners; we would practice together,'' said Ms. Young, who had been an exchange student in Argentina during high school and college, but had taken only one lesson there.</p>
        <p>On Valentine's day two years ago, Dr. Rivella told Ms. Young to get her passport and suitcase for the weekend and meet him at the subway station from which they went to Kennedy Airport.</p>
        <p>''When we passed through customs, she realized we were going to Paris,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''After dinner at the Eiffel Tower, I proposed. The Italians don't have the tradition of diamond rings, so I proposed with a photocopy of a ring to be sure she liked it.''</p>
        <p>Her reaction: ''I thought, 'Great, now I can choose my own ring,' '' she said.</p>
        <p>Last September, the couple began practicing a special tango that they planned to do at the wedding, despite slight shyness on Dr. Rivella's part. ''I am a professor who presents talks,'' he said, ''I am more comfortable with that than something artistic.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
