<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chic? Hmm</title>
    <meta content="05remix.royal.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/style/tmagazine/15tchic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REMIX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chic? Hmm</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chic? Hmm</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Natasha Fraser-Cavassoni</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is Ségolene Royal a gazelle, air hostess or France's next Joan of Arc? Since this 53-year-old became the presidential candidate for France's Socialist Party, opinions have remained divided. ''She just looks so bourgeois for someone left-wing,'' says Marisa Berenson. The designer Martine Sitbon, on the other hand, finds her ''pretty well dressed.'' She adds, ''By wearing a skirt, she's avoiding that frumpy trouser-suit look so prevalent amongst female politicians.'' The shoe designer Christian Louboutin describes Royal as ''physically, great'' and someone whose appearance has ''dramatically evolved since working for Mitterrand in the 1980s.'' Pictures show a rounder person with big glasses and hair untidily tied back. Now it's cheekbones, chiseled jaw, perfectly coiffed hair and contact lenses. ''And two years ago, she replaced her Dracula fangs with caps,'' says Lucien Pellat-Finet, the cashmere expert. ''In France, we call it the presidential smile.'' Terry de Gunzburg, the creator of By Terry cosmetics, is impressed by her ''naturally perfect'' complexion and how ''she never looks tired.'' The hairstylist Odile Gilbert refers to her do as ''classic,'' but because her hair is fine, he says she has no choice. Still, in terms of clothes, Gilbert thinks she could be ''more jeans and cool, à la Hillary.'' (Hillary cool?) Pellat-Finet is horrified that she favors Paule Ka, the staid French label inspired by Jackie O. He criticizes her red jackets, knee-length skirts and white coats for their ''terrible'' proportions. Louboutin likens her round-toed shoes to Minnie Mouse's but appreciates her ''terrific legs and ankles.'' And apparently the mother of four is a fantasy figure for certain French men, says Louboutin: ''They dream of having Ségo as a mother.''</p>
        <p>Natasha Fraser-Cavassoni</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is Ségolene Royal a gazelle, air hostess or France’s next Joan of Arc? Since this 53-year-old became the presidential candidate for France’s Socialist Party, opinions have remained divided. “She just looks so bourgeois for someone left-wing,” says Marisa Berenson. The designer Martine Sitbon, on the other hand, finds her “pretty well dressed.” She adds, “By wearing a skirt, she’s avoiding that frumpy trouser-suit look so prevalent amongst female politicians.” The shoe designer Christian Louboutin describes Royal as “physically, great” and someone whose appearance has “dramatically evolved since working for Mitterrand in the 1980s.” Pictures show a rounder person with big glasses and hair untidily tied back. Now it’s cheekbones, chiseled jaw, perfectly coiffed hair and contact lenses. “And two years ago, she replaced her Dracula fangs with caps,” says Lucien Pellat-Finet, the cashmere expert. “In France, we call it the presidential smile.” Terry de Gunzburg, the creator of By Terry cosmetics, is impressed by her “naturally perfect” complexion and how “she never looks tired.” The hairstylist Odile Gilbert refers to her do as “classic,” but because her hair is fine, he says she has no choice. Still, in terms of clothes, Gilbert thinks she could be “more jeans and cool, à la Hillary.” (Hillary cool?) Pellat-Finet is horrified that she favors Paule Ka, the staid French label inspired by Jackie O. He criticizes her red jackets, knee-length skirts and white coats for their “terrible” proportions. Louboutin likens her round-toed shoes to Minnie Mouse’s but appreciates her “terrific legs and ankles.” And apparently the mother of four is a fantasy figure for certain French men, says Louboutin: “They dream of having Ségo as a mother.” [?][?][?]Natasha Fraser</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is Ségolene Royal a gazelle, air hostess or France's next Joan of Arc? Since this 53-year-old became the presidential candidate for France's Socialist Party, opinions have remained divided. ''She just looks so bourgeois for someone left-wing,'' says Marisa Berenson. The designer Martine Sitbon, on the other hand, finds her ''pretty well dressed.'' She adds, ''By wearing a skirt, she's avoiding that frumpy trouser-suit look so prevalent amongst female politicians.'' The shoe designer Christian Louboutin describes Royal as ''physically, great'' and someone whose appearance has ''dramatically evolved since working for Mitterrand in the 1980s.'' Pictures show a rounder person with big glasses and hair untidily tied back. Now it's cheekbones, chiseled jaw, perfectly coiffed hair and contact lenses. ''And two years ago, she replaced her Dracula fangs with caps,'' says Lucien Pellat-Finet, the cashmere expert. ''In France, we call it the presidential smile.'' Terry de Gunzburg, the creator of By Terry cosmetics, is impressed by her ''naturally perfect'' complexion and how ''she never looks tired.'' The hairstylist Odile Gilbert refers to her do as ''classic,'' but because her hair is fine, he says she has no choice. Still, in terms of clothes, Gilbert thinks she could be ''more jeans and cool, à la Hillary.'' (Hillary cool?) Pellat-Finet is horrified that she favors Paule Ka, the staid French label inspired by Jackie O. He criticizes her red jackets, knee-length skirts and white coats for their ''terrible'' proportions. Louboutin likens her round-toed shoes to Minnie Mouse's but appreciates her ''terrific legs and ankles.'' And apparently the mother of four is a fantasy figure for certain French men, says Louboutin: ''They dream of having Ségo as a mother.''</p>
        <p>Natasha Fraser-Cavassoni  THE REMIX</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
