<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
    <meta content="05contributors.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONTRIBUTORS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LESLIE CAMHI: ''As a journalist, you want to focus on the other, so I spent a lot of my youth dressing to be invisible,'' says Leslie Camhi (near right, with her son, Asher), the photography critic for the Village Voice, who wrote about the artist Louise Nevelson (far right) in ''Designed for Living'' (Page 74). With her magpie array of couture, furs, jewels and turbans, Nevelson was hardly a minimalist -- but Camhi, who also writes about culture, found plenty to relate to. ''Nevelson never accepted that women should blend into the woodwork and become invisible with age,'' she says. ''I haven't gone for a head wrap yet, but when my son was born, I did buy myself a chartreuse Burberry coat.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LESLIE CAMHI: ''As a journalist, you want to focus on the other, so I spent a lot of my youth dressing to be invisible,'' says Leslie Camhi (near right, with her son, Asher), the photography critic for the Village Voice, who wrote about the artist Louise Nevelson (far right) in ''Designed for Living'' (Page 74). With her magpie array of couture, furs, jewels and turbans, Nevelson was hardly a minimalist -- but Camhi, who also writes about culture, found plenty to relate to. ''Nevelson never accepted that women should blend into the woodwork and become invisible with age,'' she says. ''I haven't gone for a head wrap yet, but when my son was born, I did buy myself a chartreuse Burberry coat.''</p>
        <p>MILES ALDRIDGE: It's a good thing that the British photographer Miles Aldridge, who shot ''2007: A Face Odyssey'' (Page 84), has always loved sci-fi movies. ''There was a lot of '60s- and '70s-style futurism in the spring collections,'' he says. ''So all I had to do was go back to my childhood memories and films like 'Forbidden Planet' [center] and 'Solaris.' '' Before his shoots, he often sketches out ideas (far left), turning the studio into a cinematic fanstasyland. He also recently published ''The Cabinet'' (Reflex Gallery), a compilation of his editorial work of the past five years. ''It's a fractured story of expressionless women in various states of jeopardy, ecstasy and crisis,'' he says with a laugh.</p>
        <p>NATASHA SINGER: There's a good reason why Natasha Singer, the New York Times beauty reporter, did not submit a contributor's picture. ''I try to be anonymous when I report on salons,'' she explains. Singer didn't need to go undercover, however, to dissect our obsession with aging (''Defy Another Day,'' Page 40). ''When the word 'anti-aging' was first used, it was associated with dubious marketing, and now people think it connotes high-tech products,'' Singer says. ''But the real question is, should growing old be treated as a disease?'' With such weighty topics to ponder, it's hardly surprising that two of Singer's favorite resources are ''The Picture of Dorian Gray,'' by Oscar Wilde, and ''The Body,'' by Hanif Kureishi.</p>
        <p>ALICE RAWSTHORN: Though fashion photography is not her main beat, the International Herald Tribune design critic and T columnist Alice Rawsthorn was delighted to profile Nick Knight, an old friend (''Vision Quest,'' Page 80). ''I first met Nick through the designer Peter Saville and helped him out in the late '90s with some of the text for SHOWstudio, his Web site,'' she says. Rawsthorn saw her article as an opportunity to rediscover Knight's work (center), including his famous ''Skinhead'' images. ''Nick is a technical virtuoso, always pushing the boundaries of photography with the newest technology,'' she says. ''But he also has a great intellectual vigor. His images comment on contemporary culture and say something salient about what it's like to live now.''</p>
        <p>HEW LOCKE: Although the peppy floral T that the British artist Hew Locke created (Page 61) seems perfectly innocuous at first, there is more to it than meets the eye. ''On the surface are things like surface-to-air missiles, animal heads and machine guns, but there is even more underneath,'' he says. ''It's a colorful apocalypse.'' Layering fake flowers with toy soldiers is second nature to Locke, who published a self-titled monograph in 2005 (center). ''I source a lot of stuff at the Brixton market in London [far right], near where I live,'' he says. ''I'm interested in objects that aspire to be more than they are, like cheap plastic jewelry. Thanks to globalization, it's now very easy to find them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
