<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grown-Up Chorus Boy's Big Leap Forward</title>
    <meta content="15gree" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/theater/15gree.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Jerry</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Legally Blonde (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, Jerry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFD7153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grown-Up Chorus Boy's Big Leap Forward</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Grown-Up Chorus Boy’s Big Leap Forward</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE GREEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Green, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles chorus boy-turned-choreographer/director Jerry Mitchell; he will soon be making his Broadway directorial debut with musical Legally Blonde; former career enables Mitchell to make everything dance for a purpose; Mitchell's kind treatment of actors described; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME directors treat an actor's performance as a sacred mystery: something to be unlocked with an occult key. Some just say, ''Move over there.'' Others say nothing at all, but glower from the back of the theater and send passive-aggressive notes via assistants.</p>
        <p>Then there's Jerry Mitchell. At a brush-up rehearsal a few days before the February press opening of ''Legally Blonde'' in San Francisco, where that musical was trying out before its Broadway opening on April 29, he matter-of-factly worked through a dozen changes he wanted to make, based on the previous evening's show: an added beat in the opening number, a revised line of dialogue, a new take on a character's motivation. Ping-ponging from the auditorium to the stage, he tried to deploy the actors (and the props, lights and scenery) according to his precise mental picture, so that every story point would be legible, apparently even to viewers on Mars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jerry Mitchell, the latest choreographer to turn director, knows how to make everything dance for a purpose.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME directors treat an actor's performance as a sacred mystery: something to be unlocked with an occult key. Some just say, ''Move over there.'' Others say nothing at all, but glower from the back of the theater and send passive-aggressive notes via assistants.</p>
        <p>Then there's Jerry Mitchell. At a brush-up rehearsal a few days before the February press opening of ''Legally Blonde'' in San Francisco, where that musical was trying out before its Broadway opening on April 29, he matter-of-factly worked through a dozen changes he wanted to make, based on the previous evening's show: an added beat in the opening number, a revised line of dialogue, a new take on a character's motivation. Ping-ponging from the auditorium to the stage, he tried to deploy the actors (and the props, lights and scenery) according to his precise mental picture, so that every story point would be legible, apparently even to viewers on Mars.</p>
        <p>Sometimes this required only oral instruction: ''Hands up so they catch the light,'' or ''If you're saying something serious, don't flip your hair.'' When that didn't produce the desired result, he simply stepped into the performer's place and said, ''Let me be you,'' then played the part: attitude, expression, pirouettes and all.</p>
        <p>During the course of the rehearsal Mr. Mitchell did his ''Let me be you'' act over and over, on several occasions even pretending to be a piece of scenery. (''We're moving, we're moving, we're there.'') By the time he got down on the floor to demonstrate the role of Bruiser -- a Chihuahua who accompanies the seemingly ditzy sorority girl Elle Woods to Harvard Law School in a matching pink outfit -- it was clear that Mr. Mitchell could have performed the whole show himself, if only there were enough of him.</p>
        <p>The cast was by then used to his ''Let me be you'' technique; Laura Bell Bundy, who plays Elle when Mr. Mitchell doesn't, had the phrase emblazoned on a souvenir T-shirt.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Mitchell, though, it's just how he was trained. Choreographers ''set'' dances on dancers, bodily, and his career until now has been spent on one side or the other of that push-me-pull-you relationship. In the last eight years he has choreographed nine Broadway musicals, most notably ''The Full Monty,'' ''Hairspray,'' ''Never Gonna Dance'' and the revival of ''La Cage aux Folles,'' for which he won a Tony Award after five nominations.</p>
        <p>Though he staged dozens of dances in those shows -- all accurate to the characters and to their period -- Mr. Mitchell was never really a step man; his job didn't start with the gypsies in the studio but with his collaborators and the script. Especially while working with the director Jack O'Brien, he devised key storytelling concepts for productions he nominally only choreographed, including the stupendous Act I curtain number in ''Monty'' and the bird's-eye bedroom at the beginning of ''Hairspray.''</p>
        <p>Despite this training, ''Legally Blonde'' is a big and risky step forward. Not only is it the first Broadway show he's directed, it's also a ridiculously high-profile property: the $13 million jewel in the crown of MGM's musicalizable film catalog.</p>
        <p>That didn't seem to alter Mr. Mitchell's methods or cow him even a little. Even after the joyful San Francisco reviews appeared, he assembled the cast members almost every day -- ''No sightseeing for you,'' he told them -- and kept tightening the show, one detail at a time. Many directors with a far less encouraging out-of-town reception do little or nothing during this period, citing their shows' need to breathe; those shows tend to arrive in New York gasping. During Mr. Mitchell's last week in California, he made 37 cuts.</p>
        <p>''I'm a bit anal,'' he acknowledged over an austere egg-white breakfast back in New York a few days before Broadway previews began. He works late, wakes up with ideas and spends the rest of his time methodically beheading his endless to-do lists. He hasn't danced professionally in 15 years, but at 47 maintains his discipline and lean physique (he's 6 foot 4) by going to the gym every day and keeping to a diet whose main food groups seem to be caffeine and whey.</p>
        <p>Still, his career path -- dancer to choreographer to director -- is riddled with potholes a control freak can't always avoid. Ask Twyla Tharp. The jury is out on a younger generation of hopefuls, including Susan Stroman, Kathleen Marshall, Casey Nicholaw and now Mr. Mitchell. Even in the golden age of the director-choreographer, only five men -- Gower Champion, Jerome Robbins, Bob Fosse, Michael Bennett and Tommy Tune -- excelled at the job, and the most recent of their major works are now long in the past: ''Jerome Robbins' Broadway'' in 1989 and Mr. Tune's ''Will Rogers Follies'' in 1991.</p>
        <p>As it happens, Mr. Mitchell was Robbins's assistant on the former and danced nearly naked on a drum in the latter. Earlier he had assisted Bennett on the reputedly brilliant but unproduced ''Scandal''; in the 1980 revival of ''Brigadoon,'' he even danced for Agnes de Mille. If he was lucky enough to witness the tail end of such greatness (''Brigadoon'' was his first Broadway job, at the age of 20), he was also, in a way, lucky to have missed its heyday in the '50s, '60s and '70s. The near disappearance of dance from Broadway in the next decades, thanks to turgid pop operas and also to AIDS, left him free to develop his own sense of how movement should function in musicals. For models he was forced to study not only choreographers but also directors, who taught very different lessons.</p>
        <p>''Story, story, story'' is how Mr. Mitchell summarized those lessons. ''The dance step may be amazing, and maybe I can do it beautifully, but if the actor can't, then it won't tell the story, so it's no good and has to go.'' The same was true, he said, of lines, costumes, scenery, songs. No matter how brilliant in the abstract, they had to earn their place.</p>
        <p>This is a different standard from the one traditionally governing Broadway narrative. Even in ''Oklahoma!'' -- a musical often heralded for its integration of dance and story -- there was room for an ''in one'' comedy number that mostly masked a scene change, and for a 15-minute de Mille dream ballet that told audiences something about the characters' demons but not what choices they'd make. In a contemporary rendering of the same tale, such diversions would surely be cut after the first workshop.</p>
        <p>Storytelling now means only plot advancement; whether this represents a gain or a loss, or a bit of both, it's what audiences trained on the rhythms of film and television seem to require. In any case Mr. Mitchell has mastered the Bennett trick of making everything dance for a purpose. In ''Legally Blonde'' the big Act I production number is Elle's admission essay, transformed from a videotape in the movie to a live demonstration of her assets. Working with the designer David Rockwell (who also provided the sets for ''Dirty Rotten Scoundrels'' and ''Hairspray''), he has even made scene changes part of the choreography. Sorority sisters pop out of windows in the pink facade of Delta Nu, which then flies away, revealing the interior, which then disappears as a boutique assembles itself -- on and on, with never a standstill moment.</p>
        <p>''The motion is the story,'' Mr. Mitchell said, announcing a precept especially apt for ''Legally Blonde.'' It is after all a show about a girl who manages, despite allobstacles, to get from one place to another.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell understands that: ''I've lived her life,'' he said. He was raised in Paw Paw, Mich., the kind of village with a dance studio above the drugstore and ''everyone in your business.'' His childhood there was ''A Chorus Line'' meets Wally Cleaver: following a neighbor girl to tap class (and recreating the steps for her afterward) but also playing football, lettering in high jump, becoming class president.</p>
        <p>''I knew I was gay since I was 8,'' he said, ''and though I wasn't out, I was confident it would all be O.K.'' Still, that knowledge started him on a lifetime habit of filling every moment with challenges, ''so no one would catch up with me.''</p>
        <p>And despite ''major sex in the cornfields,'' no one did. At the beginning of his senior year of high school, his prayers (''Please take me away from here and get me into a show'') were answered when, on the spur of the moment, he auditioned to replace an injured dancer in a bus-and-truck tour of ''West Side Story'' and got the part. With his parents' tearful blessing and his principal's wise permission (''We all know where you're headed,'' Mr. Mitchell recalled the principal saying, ''so you might as well go''), he was gone. ''One-night performances in 230 cities in 42 states,'' Mr. Mitchell crowed. ''It was heaven.''</p>
        <p>The road from there was fast, and if it included some familiar gypsy signposts -- Equity card (''My Fair Lady'' with Anita Gillette), first residual check (a dancing Dr Pepper commercial) -- Mr. Mitchell often found himself veering outside the lanes. When he saw ''The Wiz,'' he was annoyed by the ''lazy, out-of-sync'' ensemble: that was a choreographer's perspective. When he saw ''A Chorus Line,'' he ''didn't notice the choreography, only the structure'': that was a director's.</p>
        <p>Though he was still only a dancer -- that residual check paid for his first solo trip to New York, where he auditioned for de Mille and got the job in ''Brigadoon'' -- he already knew he wanted to be what he calls, reversing the usual order, a choreographer-director.</p>
        <p>''I have exacting standards,'' he said, ''and unlike most dancers always knew what everyone else was supposed to be doing. I'm mathematical. I can't spell my own name but I can see where everyone is now and where they will be a moment later. I was always'' -- he paused to find the right phrase -- ''outside the box.''</p>
        <p>He was also ahead of himself. No one entrusted the choreography (let alone the direction) of expensive shows to chorus boys. In this there was logic but also prejudice: ''The condescension in the culture toward male dancers is extreme,'' Mr. Mitchell said. ''Just as it is to supposedly dumb blondes like Elle Woods. 'Stand in the corner, do what you're told, have nothing to say.' Which is why 'Legally Blonde' was clearly the right story for me to tell my first time as a director. Elle exists in the space between feminism and Britney Spears, and speaks directly to the problem of girls who dumb themselves down to be attractive to boys. Girls still need to be told it's O.K. to be beautiful and smart. Or more importantly, it's O.K. to be smart.''</p>
        <p>Whether or not the 2001 movie intended to make this point, it was why the show's lead producer, Hal Luftig, who optioned the rights from MGM, felt the story was worth musicalizing. Having approached several A-list directors who didn't share his vision, he was relieved, and perhaps a little alarmed, when he ran into Mr. Mitchell one day in 2003 and raised the subject.</p>
        <p>''He literally jumped on me and said, 'I love that story,' '' Mr. Luftig recalled. ''He had respect for this character and understood the trajectory of her growth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Luftig knew that Mr. Mitchell would be a hard sell at MGM, which was hoping for an established name. But he also knew that Mr. Mitchell had by that point proved his director's eye in his dances and his showbiz acumen in the annual ''Broadway Bares'' benefit, which he created in 1992. The first edition, at the gay bar Splash, netted $8,000 in a beer-soaked pillowcase for Broadway Cares/Equity Fights AIDS; the latest, at Roseland last June, brought in more than $650,000. In between, before handing over the day-to-day reins of the big strip-show operation, Mr. Mitchell had 12 years to develop his narrative and executive skills supported by ''a completely cushioned safety net'' of good will.</p>
        <p>And so, asking MGM to join him in a ''leap of faith,'' Mr. Luftig gave Mr. Mitchell his chance. But what kind of leader would he turn out to be? On one side were models like Robbins and Bennett, famous for their sadistic rehearsal-room antics. ''I saw Jerry tear down a girl over a period of six months to the point she could have killed herself,'' Mr. Mitchell recalled. ''And Michael once said to me that the problem with theater today was that human rights were creeping in.''</p>
        <p>On the other side were figures like Mr. O'Brien, whose famous kindness was a beacon; but he was only a director. Was kindness somehow at odds with the emotional and historical essence of choreography?</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell didn't think so. ''You have a choice,'' he said. ''You can collaborate by being nice, or by dictating. Either will work. The difference is, are you going to have dinner with anyone afterwards? The way Jerry treated people, I don't want to have that around me. It's a musical, for God's sake. If you want to go it alone, good luck.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell and his partner, Erik Sherr, an actor, have been together for six years. Perhaps because he is not tortured about his sexuality, as both Bennett and Robbins were, he is not torturing either. Mr. Luftig, who came to San Francisco to keep an eye on his novice director, said there were no prima donna meltdowns; tech rehearsals, when shows often hemorrhage cash because of a director's disorganization, finished ahead of schedule.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen him flapped or flummoxed,'' Mr. Luftig added. ''When he couldn't get the stage to rehearse, he'd just work upstairs. I've had directors in that situation say, 'I'm going to the movies' and walk off. I mean, when was the last time you heard of a happy creative team? If I had known he was such a great leader, I'd have stayed home.''</p>
        <p>It's not that Mr. Mitchell is mother-hennish or nicey-nicey; he's a bit remote behind his lopsided smile, and too kinetic to get stuck for long in personality mires. Nell Benjamin, who with her husband, Laurence O'Keefe, wrote the songs for ''Legally Blonde,'' called him a ''kinder, gentler autocrat,'' unthreatened by other people's ideas because he has so many of his own.</p>
        <p>''Many of us have been taught that every idea has to be challenged, taken apart,'' she said. ''Jerry is no anti-intellectual, but he doesn't pre-criticize. Every idea is the most exciting idea he's ever had. He puts it up there and gives it a try. If it doesn't work, he's got another. I'm pretty much in awe of that kind of assurance.''</p>
        <p>Can a kinder, gentler dictator achieve the brilliant results in our era that Robbins and Bennett and the others did in theirs? Do today's musical subjects even warrant such brilliance? ''Legally Blonde'' isn't about pogroms or gangs or even the pain of being a dancer. But to Mr. Mitchell its themes are just as important, if expressed quite differently: ''We're a big, pink snowball,'' he told his cast in San Francisco. ''But we want to pack that snowball as tight and hard as we can and chuck it at New York.''</p>
        <p>And who knows? The blonde with the lap dog may be a great jurist someday. And the willowy boy at the barre may have a better arm than you think.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
