<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Biblio File; Starved to Perfection</title>
    <meta content="05talk.brubach.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Anorexia Nervosa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Eating Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Models (Professional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anorexia Nervosa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eating Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Biblio File; Starved to Perfection</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Holly Brubach</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brubach, Holly</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The recent controversy over allowing severely emaciated girls to walk the fashion runways was mostly played out in letters to the editor and in designer caucuses behind closed doors. The public greeted the news with a shrug, revealing the extent to which most people now regard anorexia nervosa as just another occupational hazard. Models starve themselves the way football players take steroids, jeopardizing their health and longevity for celebrity and wealth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The recent controversy over allowing severely emaciated girls to walk the fashion runways was mostly played out in letters to the editor and in designer caucuses behind closed doors. The public greeted the news with a shrug, revealing the extent to which most people now regard anorexia nervosa as just another occupational hazard. Models starve themselves the way football players take steroids, jeopardizing their health and longevity for celebrity and wealth.</p>
        <p>More surprising, perhaps -- and certainly no less alarming -- is the realization that dieting has become so commonplace that the skeletons on the catwalk simply strike us as more expert at it than the rest of us. We're the amateurs, skipping lunch and taking the tops off our sandwiches, and we're the ones Courtney E. Martin is addressing in ''Perfect Girls, Starving Daughters: The Frightening New Normalcy of Hating Your Body'' (Free Press), a smart and spirited rant that makes for thought-provoking reading. She opens with some sobering statistics: seven million American girls and women with eating disorders, and up to 70 million people worldwide. ''Ninety-one percent of women recently surveyed on a college campus reported dieting; 22 percent of them dieted 'always' or 'often.' In 1995, 34 percent of high-school-age girls in the United States thought they were overweight. Today, 90 percent do.</p>
        <p>''We eat healthy portions in social situations or out on dates,'' Martin adds, ''but when we are home, we feel relief that we can go back to our skimpy dinners without feeling observed . . . a bowl of spinach and a piece of dry toast, a chicken breast plain and cold. 'Everybody does it,' a friend tells me. 'It's just normal now.' But does that means it's O.K.?'' Martin wonders. ''Does that mean I should watch a generation of promising young women devote the better part of their intellects to scheduling visits to the gym and their next meal? . . . Is this really what it means to be a woman?''</p>
        <p>Martin asks more questions than she answers, and what information she does provide is mostly culled from interviews. Speaking for the women of her generation, now in their mid-20s, she contends that their distorted attitudes when it comes to food are the byproduct of their mothers' revolutionary zeal. ''We are the daughters of feminists who said, 'You can be anything,' and we heard, 'You have to be everything,' '' she writes.</p>
        <p>The conclusions Martin comes to in the course of her rambling investigation rarely venture onto medical ground. That territory is best explored in the company of the late Dr. Hilde Bruch, who first charted it nearly 30 years ago in ''The Golden Cage: The Enigma of Anorexia Nervosa'' (Harvard University Press). It is still an extraordinary achievement. A professor of psychiatry at Baylor College of Medicine, Bruch wrote with clarity, insight and compassion of her cases during the anorexia outbreak of the early '70s, an epidemic that seemed to arise out of nowhere, with no official diagnosis. (Anorexia didn't make its debut in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders until 1980.) It was, Bruch remarked in retrospect, a time when ''no anorexic patient had ever heard of such a condition'' and each invented the illness for herself -- a situation that strikes us as unthinkable today, when sufferers trade starvation tips on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Whatever early hopes Bruch's lucid analysis may have inspired, the prospect of a cure through greater understanding has been confounded by the intractability of the anorexic mind. Citing research on war prisoners, Bruch attributed some of anorexia's most severe symptoms, like splitting of the ego and depersonalization, directly to the effects of sustained malnutrition. Her prescription, then, begins with eating.</p>
        <p>Eating is what Martin would have us do, too -- or, rather, more eating and less thinking about it when we're not. But how to achieve this? It's one thing to decide that we're going to reclaim the time we spend thinking about a doughnut and devote it to reading Proust instead, but no sooner are we deep into the details of his insomnia than a voice in the back of our heads whispers, ''Doughnut!'' and the argument with ourselves starts all over again.</p>
        <p>Martin suggests spiritual solutions. She urges us to recognize that ''we are not our bodies,'' ''that how we feel about our bodies does not have to be indicative of how we feel about ourselves.'' And yet, surely one of the more bewildering paradoxes here is the fact that anorexics, while closely identified with their bodies' appearance, are completely divorced from their bodies' experience, refusing to acknowledge hunger and fatigue, imposing their iron wills on flesh and bone.</p>
        <p>The force of the cultural riptide is not to be underestimated. The anorexic, Bruch wrote, ''has lost her belief in her right to take up space in the world.'' Over the course of the past three decades, men have been pursuing unnatural bulk and women exaggerated thinness, as if the world were such a small and symbiotic place that the weight they gain is the weight that we must lose, as if we need to minimize ourselves to make room for them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
