<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A West End Name, A Broadway Debut</title>
    <meta content="15ryzi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/theater/15ryzi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ryzik, Melena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grandage, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgan, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Frost/nixon (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Frost, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nixon, Richard Milhous</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EED7153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A West End Name, A Broadway Debut</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A West End Name, a Broadway Debut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELENA RYZIK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ryzik, Melena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles British director Michael Grandage; whose direction of Peter Morgan's play Frost/Nixon on Broadway will mark his American debut; Grandage has reputation as one of most prolific and respected British directors working today; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE director Michael Grandage has no time for small talk; even his elevator chitchat is meaningful.</p>
        <p>''We don't have rehearsal space like this in London,'' he said the other day, as he oohed and aahed over a building on 42nd Street in Manhattan. For three weeks he had been holed up there, fine-tuning the American version of the West End sensation ''Frost/Nixon,'' a dramatization of David Frost's seminal 1977 television interview with Richard M. Nixon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael Grandage has arrived in New York to fine-tune the American version of the West End sensation “Frost/Nixon.” What took him so long?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE director Michael Grandage has no time for small talk; even his elevator chitchat is meaningful.</p>
        <p>''We don't have rehearsal space like this in London,'' he said the other day, as he oohed and aahed over a building on 42nd Street in Manhattan. For three weeks he had been holed up there, fine-tuning the American version of the West End sensation ''Frost/Nixon,'' a dramatization of David Frost's seminal 1977 television interview with Richard M. Nixon.</p>
        <p>''We're up on the sixth floor,'' Mr. Grandage continued, in a truly gleeful tone, ''so we have a view of the city. But we have to keep the blinds closed during rehearsal because what's happening outside is so interesting.''</p>
        <p>Bing! The doors opened, and Mr. Grandage, in an army-green jacket, with a messenger bag slung across his shoulder and the excitable air of a grad student still years away from his dissertation, bounded out. The view, he explained later, was his lodestar.</p>
        <p>''The view represented that I could only be in one place: rehearsing,'' he said. ''I just looked out of the window and knew we could only be in New York, and that I was making my debut. And that was rather exciting.'' He was so enthusiastic that he chose an apartment blocks away, in a Times Square high-rise (against the advice of all his friends, who urged him to stay in the meatpacking district). His two-month foray here is the longest he has been away from home, and he didn't want to miss anything.</p>
        <p>Since 1995, when he abandoned a successful acting career in favor of creating offstage, Mr. Grandage, 44, has secured a reputation as one of the most prolific and respected British directors working today. He has won or been nominated for dozens of awards, mostly for work that originated at the Donmar Warehouse, the small theater known as a London hit maker. Since he succeeded Sam Mendes as artistic director there in 2002, his triumphs have included ''Guys and Dolls,'' with Ewan McGregor and Jane Krakowski; ''The Cut,'' a new play by the provocative writer Mark Ravenhill, starring Ian McKellen; and adaptations of Strindberg, Ibsen and Tennessee Williams. In The New York Times Ben Brantley called his version of Peter Nichols's ''Passion Play'' ''one of those benchmark interpretations that brought out the magnificence in something previously regarded as smart and brittle.''</p>
        <p>On the West End he is a marquee name. ''Frost/Nixon,'' which stars Michael Sheen as the interviewer and Frank Langella as the former president, marks Mr. Grandage's American debut; it is set to open on April 22 at the Bernard B. Jacobs Theater (which is trying him out on the marquee). Given the velocity of the career -- and the man, who does everything at double-time pace -- theatergoers, colleagues and friends like Mr. Mendes are wondering: What took him so long? Why now?</p>
        <p>Mr. Grandage's answer: It's all in the timing. ''There's a lot of planets coming into alignment on this one,'' he said, including the stellar reputation of the first-time playwright, Peter Morgan -- better known as the screenwriter of ''The Queen'' and ''The Last King of Scotland'' -- and the political climate.</p>
        <p>''The heat under 'Frost/Nixon' was as intense as anything I've ever seen in England,'' Mr. Grandage said. ''And if it resonates in England, it's certainly going to resonate here as you start a new presidential campaign. When you see Nixon in the chair being interviewed by Frost, the questions that he gets asked are the questions you want to ask any politician. So there simply was a demand for that.''</p>
        <p>Already on track to become a film by Ron Howard, ''Frost/Nixon'' depicts the historic, much-watched television special, and the lead-up to it -- the personalities behind the camera, the negotiations over what could be discussed -- as a competition for prestige between mismatched underdogs. In one corner is the heavy, the former president, grappling to regain some of his reputation. In the other is the comparatively lightweight British TV presenter, a famous playboy with (onstage, at least) good hair, a glossy smile and a preternatural understanding of the value of both. By the time Nixon expresses regret for his role in Watergate, the lasting winner is clear.</p>
        <p>Framing it all is a grid of 36 vintage television screens, which hang over the set like a third eye, broadcasting the action onstage in a live closed-circuit loop. There's no laugh track, but there is plenty of humor to smooth out the history; it's political theater as intellectual game show, complete with boppy '70s-style music. There's even a host of sorts, the author and Frost adviser Jim Reston, played by Stephen Kunken. (The character is based on James Reston Jr., the son of James Reston, a former columnist, Washington correspondent and executive editor of The New York Times.) Mr. Langella, Mr. Sheen and Corey Johnson -- as Nixon's chief of staff, Jack Brennan -- reprise their London roles; the rest of the actors are new.</p>
        <p>The TV sets were actually cast before any of the other performers. By convention, habit or bad seats, audience members often wind up watching the televised version instead of the live action before them, which Mr. Grandage relishes. ''I see people flicking between the two, and that's exactly what I wanted because I think the play is about how TV distorts reality,'' he said. ''It's part of the story of the way the '70s changed us all completely. This one political televisual event was a cornerstone moment. It led somehow to where we are now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grandage's own life is full of those axis-changing flashes, like deciding to transition from acting to directing. In his 30s, he said, the quality and size of the roles he was being offered began to decline. ''With that came frustration, and with frustration came panic,'' he said. ''And then a really wonderful realization that -- control is a terrible word and it gets misused, but the idea and thrill of being able to control something big in its entirety, like a whole piece as opposed to just your individual part as an actor, is something I knew I wanted to try.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I had no idea whether I would be any good at it, and I had no idea whether I would enjoy it. But the truth is, that first time I did it was an absolute burning-bush moment. I just thought, 'I don't know why I've waited so long.' ''</p>
        <p>But his timing was perfect. ''He had this weird thing of an enormous amount of theatrical know-how, but the enthusiasm of a newcomer, which is very infectious,'' said Mr. Mendes, who groomed Mr. Grandage as a successor at the Donmar. ''He's fast talking, fast thinking, enthusiastic, sharp as a tack. You can see it onstage; there's such pace and élan. That's what he's like. It's unusual that the characteristics of a theater director are mirrored in the work that he does so clearly.''</p>
        <p>Though he's found his calling as a director, Mr. Grandage still retains some actorly traits, like terrific body language -- his hands are constantly moving: tunneling, cupping, squeezing or smoothing out his thoughts -- and a charisma that Mr. Morgan, the playwright, referred to as ''the lighthouse beam of his attention.''</p>
        <p>''He's just an extraordinarily dynamic individual,'' Mr. Morgan said. ''He works astonishingly hard, and is a sort of force of nature.''</p>
        <p>Given his work ethic -- last year he directed five back-to-back shows; this year he will stage several more, in addition to running the Donmar and planning next year's slate -- there is another question that reverberates for Mr. Grandage: When is he going to do a movie?</p>
        <p>''Actually I don't feel I've got to the place yet where I've finished theater,'' he said, though he acknowledged that film and perhaps even television were on his agenda. And he is always entertaining new challenges: around 2010, expect an opera.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, though, Mr. Grandage sees no point in slowing down.</p>
        <p>''I started directing in order to find myself, and re-find myself, in terms of knowing why I'm here, why I'm doing what I do,'' he said, as his hands danced. ''And last year made me feel completely alive.'' This year, he said, his momentum is even better: ''I feel like I'm in the peak time now.''</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
