<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Feist. Just Wait.</title>
    <meta content="15pare" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/arts/music/15pare.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feist, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Feist, Leslie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD7153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Feist. Just Wait.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Just Feist. Just Wait.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles article profiles singer Leslie Feist, known professionally as Feist, whose new album will be released May 1; says album should transform her from darling of indie-rock to full-fledged star; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the way to the video shoot for a song named ''1 2 3 4,'' Leslie Feist called her father on her cellphone, urging him to drop by the studio. ''I'm going to dance like in 'Fame,' '' bubbled Feist, a petite 31-year-old brunette who uses her last name for her solo recording career. ''I'm going to be carried around on the shoulders of 50 people, like Madonna in 'Material Girl,' only minus the pearls and the back muscles.''</p>
        <p>She wasn't exaggerating. ''1 2 3 4,'' which appears on her new album, ''The Reminder'' (Cherry Tree/Interscope), is an easy-swinging tune, almost like a nursery rhyme, that grows into a mass chorus. Tucked into it are lyrics that celebrate the intensity of teenage bonds and feelings: ''Money can't buy you back the love that you had then.'' The video clip, to be completed in just two days of rehearsals and one of shooting, would be a big live production number: an uninterrupted, uneditable one-camera take.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a decade of wandering, an indie darling is ready to become pop’s new one-name wonder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the way to the video shoot for a song named ''1 2 3 4,'' Leslie Feist called her father on her cellphone, urging him to drop by the studio. ''I'm going to dance like in 'Fame,' '' bubbled Feist, a petite 31-year-old brunette who uses her last name for her solo recording career. ''I'm going to be carried around on the shoulders of 50 people, like Madonna in 'Material Girl,' only minus the pearls and the back muscles.''</p>
        <p>She wasn't exaggerating. ''1 2 3 4,'' which appears on her new album, ''The Reminder'' (Cherry Tree/Interscope), is an easy-swinging tune, almost like a nursery rhyme, that grows into a mass chorus. Tucked into it are lyrics that celebrate the intensity of teenage bonds and feelings: ''Money can't buy you back the love that you had then.'' The video clip, to be completed in just two days of rehearsals and one of shooting, would be a big live production number: an uninterrupted, uneditable one-camera take.</p>
        <p>Four dozen dancers in color-coordinated thrift-store clothes surrounded Feist, raising her overhead and, at one point, flipping her. The camera swooped around, amid and above them, revealing geometric patterns like a Busby Berkeley sequence. Feist had traded her usual T-shirt and jeans for a flashy blue-sequined pantsuit and pointy golden high heels, which pinched her feet. ''It's not the most pleasant sensation,'' she said after dancing in them through take after take. ''But it's for the razzle-dazzle.''</p>
        <p>What's a nice indie-rocker doing in a scene like this? Courting a potential mainstream audience while offering something as substantial as it is catchy.</p>
        <p>Feist's third album of new material, ''The Reminder'' is due for release May 1. It's the album that should transform her from the darling of the indie-rock circuit to a full-fledged star, and do it without compromises. ''The Reminder'' is a modestly scaled but quietly profound pop gem: sometimes intimate, sometimes exuberant, filled with love songs and hints of mystery.</p>
        <p>This album is all Feist, unlike her 2004 album, ''Let It Die.'' She wrote or collaborated on every song except the traditional ''Sea Lion Woman.'' ''The Reminder'' is also her first album to arrive facing sizable expectations. ''Let It Die'' sold 400,000 copies worldwide, 118,000 of them in the United States, and earned Feist a devoted audience among musicians, critics and concertgoers. When she tours this time around, Feist will have a luxury: a seated audience in theaters rather than her former circuit of rock clubs. She is booked at Massey Hall, Toronto's equivalent of Carnegie Hall, and she comes to Town Hall in Manhattan on June 11.</p>
        <p>As an album ''The Reminder'' has some echoes of ''Let It Die.'' It too starts with a kind of bossa nova, ''So Sorry,'' and eases through folk-rock, ballads and electronica. Feist's voice, clear and sustained with sultry flickers of vibrato, stays serenely in the foreground, and the music takes its time, even in upbeat songs like the first single, ''My Moon My Man,'' powered by a few thumping piano notes.</p>
        <p>Yet where ''Let It Die'' dipped into private melancholy, then backed off with a final string of other people's songs, ''The Reminder'' reaches deeper. Feist, whose conversation is often a stream of poetic imagery, said over a cup of tea, ''I'm on the archaeological dig to find the place where my heart ended up.''</p>
        <p>In her new love songs Feist apologizes, confesses to longing, hints at betrayals and misunderstandings and wonders what might have been. Her voice is self-possessed yet unguarded, and it hovers in arrangements that are often modest -- just a handful of musicians playing together in a room -- but can also proffer gleaming instrumental hooks and nonsense syllables that invite singalongs. The songs find equipoise within heartache.</p>
        <p>Feist named the album ''The Reminder'' as ''a pivotable riddle: something that could change and feed in and didn't necessarily have a concrete point to it,'' she more or less explained. ''It just felt vague enough and open-ended enough to be able to encapsulate all the things I hoped the record would morph into.''</p>
        <p>While making the album she tried not to feel commercial pressure. ''I wasn't thinking about the reaction to 'Let It Die,' '' she said. ''My mind decided to create a benevolent blank slate on the whole making of the album. I saw a bunch of faces on all my touring, and they had moved their bodies from their homes to the gig, and that was a certain amount of trust. And now I'm just going to trust them.''</p>
        <p>Jason Charles Beck, a Canadian keyboardist better known as Gonzales, was a producer for both ''Let It Die'' and ''The Reminder.'' The thought of making a hit album was ''the elephant in the room,'' he said by telephone from Studio Ferber in Paris. ''Feist comes from an indie-rock world, where it's sacrilege to admit any kind of ambition. But I had 100 percent in my mind the idea that we should have as much material as possible that could be played on the radio or resonate with a huge bunch of people. We already have the built-in reflex not to get behind anything that's going to be hollow. And when you have an artist with this kind of credibility, the idea is to communicate to as many people as possible without doing something ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Until she had an unlikely hit with ''Mushaboom,'' a jovial folk-rock tune from ''Let It Die'' that imagined living in the Canadian boondocks, Feist was primarily known in Canada and Europe, and there as a perky part of other people's projects. She grew up in Calgary and sang for five years with a punk band that started in high school. In the mid-1990s she moved to Toronto, working quietly on her own songs while the city's homegrown bohemian culture welcomed her.</p>
        <p>''She's really great at meeting people, and she's a very outgoing person,'' said Gonzales. ''Every musician I knew had had some kind of run-in with her. She was playing drums with this band or guitar with another band, or jamming with somebody, or setting up an evening of music somewhere. She was really in a rush to get in as much experience as she could. And when we got together, I noticed that she had a burning ambition to master her craft, and also insisted on goofing around at every turn. I remember thinking, 'Wow, if this girl ever gets her focus together she'll be unstoppable.' ''</p>
        <p>Feist went on to a decade of touring and collaborating, racking up experience as an indie-rock trouper. She played guitar in By Divine Right, a rock band that opened a stadium tour for the Canadian favorites the Tragically Hip, and she released her own promising but unexceptional debut album, ''Monarch,'' in 1999, without much impact. She joined her roommate, the conceptually bawdy rapper Peaches, as singer, rapper, dancer and sock puppeteer (billing herself as Bitch Lap Lap), and went on to tour Europe with Peaches's keyboardist, Gonzales, in his own comically glam mode. A video circulating on YouTube shows him rapping with Feist, who is in a unitard, singing backup and pretending to tap-dance. ''I have experimented with my limits of cheese,'' she said. ''And all those things educated me when I came to Feist.''</p>
        <p>The difference in the exchange rate between the euros she earned while touring and the Canadian dollar helped her get by. She also worked temp jobs, including stints at a sandwich shop, at a Salvation Army warehouse and at a flower company, ''dethorning roses.'' She moved to Paris to live in a place without ''all the signposts of my past'' but decided there that for a girl from Calgary, ''trying to be cool is too exhausting.''</p>
        <p>Back in Toronto (although she still has a Paris apartment) Feist found herself among the group of friends that evolved into the large, ever-changing band Broken Social Scene, and she went on to tour with them, singing and sometimes stage-diving. Broken Social Scene's main songwriter, Kevin Drew, is now her boyfriend.</p>
        <p>Feist has a gift for drawing supportive collaborators. ''With Broken Social Scene there's the chicken-or-the-egg question,'' she said. ''Was it because we're all musicians, or was it because we were all friends, or was it because we were all friends who played music and wanted to play together, or was it because. ''</p>
        <p>She laughed. ''As time passes and that becomes a more and more elastic project, it feels to me that it was the friendships.''</p>
        <p>But she's selective too. ''Most of the people I've ended up playing with, it's kind of love first, a friendship first,'' she said. ''But I have a lot of friends who I don't play with.''</p>
        <p>Amid her other gigs Feist was writing her own more introspective songs. A handful of them made their way onto the Internet as ''The Red Demos,'' including an early version of ''The Water,'' which she would refine on ''The Reminder.'' When she was struggling to finish songs, Gonzales urged her to try recording other people's material. As he recalled it, he suggested, ''Do some covers, you'll get over your songwriting complex.''</p>
        <p>Without any particular plan they worked in a small Paris studio in 2002 and 2003, recording a dozen songs by the likes of the Bee Gees and the celebrated Canadian songwriter Ron Sexsmith. (Mr. Sexsmith would go on to collaborate with Feist on a song for ''The Reminder'' called ''Brandy Alexander.'')</p>
        <p>Gradually Feist and Gonzales added some of Feist's own songs to their project, including ''Mushaboom,'' and they realized that what they had could become an album. ''Let It Die'' (Cherry Tree/Interscope) revealed a singer who understood the impact of quiet, utterly exposed performances. The album put Feist on the radio internationally, and steady touring made her a headliner until, eventually, she was eager to record again.</p>
        <p>''Being on tour, singing the same songs -- there are certain notes that are always being hit and intervals that are always being threaded together and chords that always come in succession of each other,'' she said. ''And after a while every cell in my body was lunging toward new stuff.''</p>
        <p>She says she has never been able to write on a schedule. Songwriting is ''like any romance,'' she said. ''You can't decide when your first kiss is going to be. The whole point is the anticipation.''</p>
        <p>She constantly records musical fragments, on a Dictaphone or her computer's Garageband software. ''I've collected a lot of little shreds, quivering little pink spinal cords,'' she said. ''The backbone without the bone, just the embryo. Mostly I was just writing about this and that, reading a lot of books, underlining things, remembering what concepts felt like they resonated. I was just on the lookout for what felt like it might go into the sponge and then be able to be squeezed out again.''</p>
        <p>In a brief break between tour dates Feist decided to rent a place in Berlin and concentrate on songwriting. A few months later she gathered her touring band and producers in a mansion outside Paris for two and a half weeks. There the musicians were recorded playing in a room together, often without headphones -- an old-fashioned setup that's almost radical in the era of infinite computerized tweaking and multitracking. The album's four most haunting songs -- ''I'm Sorry,'' ''The Water,'' ''The Park'' and ''Intuition'' -- are essentially live takes.</p>
        <p>Others, like ''1 2 3 4,'' took on additional layers in Paris and Toronto studios. For ''Honey Honey,'' a minimalistic concoction of electric keyboards and an overdubbed chorus of Feists, she booked a harpist and instructed her: ''You're the mermaid 40 feet down under the raft, you're in the doldrums, there's all complete silence, but the guy on the raft hasn't had anything to drink or eat for two weeks, and he doesn't know if he's hearing things or if it's real. And that's you.''</p>
        <p>Loneliness pervades the songs on ''The Reminder.'' ''By nature of me being the one singing it and writing it there is always an innate bit of autobiography there,'' Feist said. ''But I think I learned years ago that you don't get songs that have that long stride and that pivot-hinge ability if it's too much diary entry.''</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, to all appearances Feist is surrounded by affection. As the video shoot continued past sunset and the studio curfew loomed, Feist's father showed up. So did her brother Ben with his family. Mr. Drew was there along with friends, former housemates and members of Feist's band. In the last hours and minutes of available studio time, Feist beamed through her steps, and the dancers burst into applause every time they completed the entire song. The takes got better and better until time finally ran out, and Feist was surrounded by dancers eager to embrace her. There was no hipster irony or professional cool; the pop production had turned into a community musical, one more of Feist's ad hoc social scenes.</p>
        <p>''She really poured it on,'' Mr. Drew said afterward. ''She always pours it on. That's Feist.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
