<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Retail Sales Could Set The Tone On Wall St.</title>
    <meta content="15mark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/business/yourmoney/15mark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840538"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D6133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Retail Sales Could Set The Tone On Wall St.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Retail Sales Could Set the Tone on Wall St.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De Aenlle, Conrad</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE facet of economic activity after another will have its moment under the microscope this week. Reports are expected on home construction, inflation, manufacturing and leading indicators, but one measure of consumers' willingness to keep spending may matter most on Wall Street, in one economist's opinion.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of pieces of information to sift through, and the most important probably is retail sales,'' said Robert MacIntosh, chief economist at Eaton Vance, the Boston fund manager. As other pillars of growth have begun to look shaky, consumer spending has taken on a more crucial role in supporting the economy, he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“How the consumer acts is how the economy will act,” an analyst says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE facet of economic activity after another will have its moment under the microscope this week. Reports are expected on home construction, inflation, manufacturing and leading indicators, but one measure of consumers' willingness to keep spending may matter most on Wall Street, in one economist's opinion.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of pieces of information to sift through, and the most important probably is retail sales,'' said Robert MacIntosh, chief economist at Eaton Vance, the Boston fund manager. As other pillars of growth have begun to look shaky, consumer spending has taken on a more crucial role in supporting the economy, he said.</p>
        <p>''Business investment has really tailed off, and with government spending unable to grow very much, it kind of leaves you with consumers,'' Mr. MacIntosh explained. ''How the consumer acts is how the economy will act, and retail sales are a good indicator of that.''</p>
        <p>A Bloomberg News poll of economists expects the report, to be released Monday, to show a 0.8 percent increase in retail sales for March, excluding cars.</p>
        <p>Mr. MacIntosh prefers to focus on the ''ultracore retail sales'' figure, which also excludes gasoline. A climb in gas prices adds to retail sales, but not in a desirable way; factoring it out provides a truer reading, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. MacIntosh expects a 0.3 percent increase after a 0.3 percent decline in February.</p>
        <p>Traders would respond well to a number ''significantly higher'' than a 0.3 percent gain, he predicted, while a smaller reading could send stocks lower.</p>
        <p>''People are a little afraid that the economy is getting a little too weak,'' he said. With a Federal Reserve rate increase apparently off the table, equity investors, he said, ''are looking for a little more growth.''</p>
        <p>The construction industry could do with some growth, but the March housing data, to be released Tuesday, may not be the place to find it.</p>
        <p>Building permits are expected to show a decline to an annual rate of 1.510 million units from 1.532 million in February.</p>
        <p>A fall in housing starts is also anticipated, to 1.498 million units a year from 1.525 million.</p>
        <p>At this point, the housing numbers may not be that significant, though, Mr. MacIntosh said.</p>
        <p>''Housing is tertiary,'' he said. ''People on the margin are now unable to borrow against their house, but it's still a very small part of the overall economy.''</p>
        <p>DATA WATCH -- The same could be said about manufacturing, so the weakness expected in numbers scheduled for Tuesday is unlikely to move the stock market, Mr. MacIntosh said.</p>
        <p>The Bloomberg survey estimates that the nation's factories operated at 81.9 percent of capacity in March, compared with 82 percent the previous month.</p>
        <p>No rise is foreseen in industrial production after a 1 percent gain in February.</p>
        <p>The core Consumer Price Index, which excludes food and energy, is expected to rise 0.2 percent in March, the same gain as in the previous month. And the Conference Board's index of leading indicators, due Thursday, is expected to show a gain of 0.1 percent in March, after a 0.5 percent drop in February.</p>
        <p>MARKET WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
