<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS: Campaign 2008; The Unsure Bet of the Heir Presumptive</title>
    <meta content="15nagourney" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/weekinreview/15nagourney.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Campaign 2008"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mondale, Walter</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dole, Bob</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerry, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Edwards, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6DC103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1198" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS: Campaign 2008; The Unsure Bet of the Heir Presumptive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Unsure Bet of the Heir Presumptive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>DES MOINES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was never too hard to figure out a big part of the presidential campaign strategies of John McCain and Hillary Rodham Clinton. They sought to portray their party nominations as inevitable, and so create a stampede of support from donors, delegates, elected officials, opinion leaders and -- the idea is -- actual voters.</p>
        <p>Such a strategy has proved reliable over the last 30 years. It rocketed George W. Bush over the Republican field in 2000, and was central to the nomination strategies of Walter Mondale, Bob Dole, John Kerry and another president named Bush, to name a few.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After watching John McCain and Hillary Rodham Clinton take campaign hits, it seems fair to ask whether the era of the inevitable candidate has now passed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was never too hard to figure out a big part of the presidential campaign strategies of John McCain and Hillary Rodham Clinton. They sought to portray their party nominations as inevitable, and so create a stampede of support from donors, delegates, elected officials, opinion leaders and -- the idea is -- actual voters.</p>
        <p>Such a strategy has proved reliable over the last 30 years. It rocketed George W. Bush over the Republican field in 2000, and was central to the nomination strategies of Walter Mondale, Bob Dole, John Kerry and another president named Bush, to name a few.</p>
        <p>But not, it seems, this time.</p>
        <p>By the time Senator McCain, Republican of Arizona, delivered his speech on Iraq in Virginia last week, he was as likely to be described by many in his own party, fairly or not, as a long shot, rather than inevitable. For Senator Clinton, Democrat of New York, the situation is not so seemingly dire, but any hope she had of Democrats embracing her candidacy as inevitable has been dashed by the rise of Senator Barack Obama of Illinois, the continued strength of John Edwards of North Carolina, and obvious discomfort in some Democratic quarters of putting another Clinton in the White House.</p>
        <p>After watching Mr. McCain and Mrs. Clinton take their hits, it seems fair to ask whether the era of the inevitable candidate has now passed, the victim of an increasingly chaotic campaign environment that defies management by even the most expert campaign. Indeed, the real question may be, why would any candidate even want to be viewed as inevitable today?</p>
        <p>If the strategy works, as it did for George W. Bush in 2000, the lure is obvious. It scares off, or at least crowds out, competitors, particularly when it comes to drawing media attention. Politicians and voters love a winner. The aura of success allows campaigns to recruit donors, talent, endorsements and key constituency groups.</p>
        <p>''People want to be in the herd,'' said John Weaver, a senior campaign adviser for Mr. McCain, describing the all-aboard strategy. ''And we're in the herd-growing business.''</p>
        <p>Even when a strategy of inevitability works, though, it is nearly always painful for the candidate who embraces it. Historically, the pain has paid off; the inevitable candidate tends to be the nominee. But these days, the clatter of blogs, talk radio and a 24-hour news cycle of often unfiltered information has made the strategy more difficult to execute, and the costs now might be greater.</p>
        <p>Presidential campaigns have always been a ritual of candidates' being built up and torn down, and nothing invites a tear-down more than being perceived as the front-runner. Being on top makes you a big target for your opponents and the news media, and sets you up for buyer's remorse, a common phenomenon in the nomination process, even before the sale is done. Even the inevitable Mr. Bush had to endure a defeat in his first primary, in New Hampshire (by, appropriately enough, Mr. McCain).</p>
        <p>''As they say on Long Island, the further up you are on the flagpole, the more people can see your rear end,'' said Richard Bond, a former Republican National Committee chairman who got his start in Nassau County politics.</p>
        <p>A campaign that tells the world it is inevitable comes -- inevitably -- to believe it. An inevitable candidate is a complacent one, sitting comfortably atop a campaign so busy lining up endorsements and planning for its convention that it doesn't take chances or react to signs of decay.</p>
        <p>Tony Fabrizio, a Republican who was the pollster for Mr. Dole when he ran for president in 1996, said their campaign chose not to broadcast television ads early, despite polls showing Mr. Dole slipping, out of fear that doing so would undercut Mr. Dole's effort to present his nomination as foregone.</p>
        <p>''That's the problem with overplaying inevitability,'' Mr. Fabrizio said. ''Eventually, someone is going to pass you.''</p>
        <p>Jim Jordan, a Democratic strategist and a onetime manager of Mr. Kerry's campaign, said: ''It's psychologically extremely damaging, even dangerous, for a campaign. It leads to an excess of caution. It leads to a flattening of message. It's a disincentive to risk taking and expressions of convictions, which are all important to voters.''</p>
        <p>In the past, the pain might have been worth the gain. Mr. Dole won his party's nomination, after all. Mr. Kerry went through two months of being written off as his party's nominee in 2004 but ended up nearly running the table once the voting began. Mr. Mondale got a scare from Gary Hart in 1984, but went on to be nominated.</p>
        <p>But there is a growing feeling in political circles, particularly watching Mr. McCain, that this may no longer be the case.</p>
        <p>The tear-down-the-leader mentality appears to have reached screeching levels because of the proliferation of media outlets, where there is a premium on getting heard. And what better way of getting heard than attacking a big target?</p>
        <p>Also, there are many more players looking to dig up disqualifying information about a front-runner, and a lot more forums for getting such information before the public. The early intensity of the 2008 campaign also means that candidates have been elevated -- either by themselves or by the news media -- to the inevitable level a lot earlier than they once were, leaving them sitting on top of the flagpole that much longer. From the Clinton and McCain campaigns, there was a long stream of announcements about this endorsement or that poll, as well as a not-subtle get-on-the-train message delivered behind closed doors to potential contributors.</p>
        <p>The Internet also makes it more plausible for a later-emerging candidate to overcome the inevitable one. Think Al Gore this time, as compared with Mr. Hart in 1984. Chris Lehane, a consultant to Mr. Gore in 2000 who has advised the Clintons over the years, suggested that the outcome might have been different for Mr. Hart: ''If Gary Hart had the Internet available to him in 1984, could he have overcome Mondale's considerable institutional advantages -- primarily his war chest and institutional support?''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton and Mr. McCain might not be the ideal tests for this strategy, given some Democrats' reservations about her and some Republicans' reservations about him. There was crystal evidence of that for Mr. McCain when the balloon of his inevitability burst -- punctured by weak first-quarter fund-raising and various polls showing him trailing. Inevitable candidates cannot trail in polls, no matter how early they are.</p>
        <p>The candidates presumably have time to try to hang the inevitability banner again, assuming they want to, and can figure out how to put Humpty Dumpty back together. But take it from those who have been there, the best way to do it is to stop telling people you are going to win.</p>
        <p>''The challenge is going to be to say something to the voters more than just inevitability,'' said Peter Hart, the pollster who advised Mr. Mondale when he employed that strategy. ''Inevitability is not a message. Mondale learned that, and I think every other candidate who runs on inevitability learns it. There needs to be something to grab on to. Inevitability is not a tune that people can march to.''</p>
        <p>Campaign 2008</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
