<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Main Street Mainstay Keeps Thai Fans Satisfied</title>
    <meta content="15njdineNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15njdine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/HACKENSACK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bangkok Garden (Hackensack, NJ, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corcoran, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Thailand</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5DE133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Main Street Mainstay Keeps Thai Fans Satisfied</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Main Street Mainstay Keeps Thai Fans Satisfied</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CORCORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corcoran, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Corcoran reviews Bangkok Garden restaurant in Hackensack, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN I was writing an article last fall about restaurants where New Jersey chefs like to eat on their night off, I called Zod Arifai, chef and owner of Blu, the terrific New American place in Montclair. He didn't hesitate.</p>
        <p>''Bangkok Garden in Hackensack,'' he replied. ''And every time I go, I get the roasted duck salad.'' He proceeded to recite the ingredients from memory: duck, chilies, red onion, scallion, ginger, coriander, lime juice, fermented fish paste, sugar cane, chunks of orange.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What sets Hackensack’s Bangkok Garden apart is the care with which the ingredients are selected, prepared and served.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN I was writing an article last fall about restaurants where New Jersey chefs like to eat on their night off, I called Zod Arifai, chef and owner of Blu, the terrific New American place in Montclair. He didn't hesitate.</p>
        <p>''Bangkok Garden in Hackensack,'' he replied. ''And every time I go, I get the roasted duck salad.'' He proceeded to recite the ingredients from memory: duck, chilies, red onion, scallion, ginger, coriander, lime juice, fermented fish paste, sugar cane, chunks of orange.</p>
        <p>So when the time came to visit this 17-year-old restaurant, the duck salad was the first thing I ordered. It did not disappoint.</p>
        <p>Listed as yum ped yarng (more often spelled yum ped yang), it costs all of $10.95. Like much else on the 120-item menu, it demands earnest concentration. The bits of roasted, shredded duck give the salad its rich, mellow bass notes, but they don't predominate: what catch your attention are the brilliant high notes of ginger, coriander and chili. While those flavors settle in, the other ingredients each take a moment in the spotlight -- by turns sweet, sour and sharp -- and this entree-size dish is gone before you know it.</p>
        <p>But don't fill up because there is plenty more to like. Bangkok Garden is the life's work of an extended family from central Thailand, about 100 miles northwest of Bangkok. The owner, Suramitr Suwanarusk, 54, settled in Bergen County after graduating from Rutgers. He can barely cook, his niece and manager, Nikki Sillpsitte, told me; the chef is her aunt Chureerat Lolak, the owner's sister.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lolak, 48, doesn't cook in a dazzlingly original style. Dishes like duck salad can be found in dozens of Thai restaurants. And even a $20.95 special like pla lui suan -- whole deep-fried tilapia -- uses largely the same ingredients, once you substitute fish for fowl. What sets Bangkok Garden apart is the care with which the ingredients are selected, prepared and served.</p>
        <p>While some staff members are more fluent than others, the language barrier is not high, and the explanations of unfamiliar dishes are patient. Servers will ask you how spicy you want your food, on a scale of 1 to 10; Ms. Sillpsitte says that in recent years the average has edged up to 6 or 7 -- which is how they like it in Thailand, she added.</p>
        <p>Nonspicy offerings did prove less interesting than spicy ones. Those takeout standbys pad Thai and mee krob were bland and ordinary, and in other pasta dishes the profusion of noodles tended to blot out the flavors of the featured ingredients -- large shrimp cooked in curry with a haystack of thin noodles, for instance. In the kitchen's only serious miscue over two visits, deep-fried duck with basil leaves was seriously underspiced, clocking in at 2 or 3 instead of the 6 we asked for. Desserts ignited no fireworks, though bananas fried in wonton wrappers were crisp and pleasant.</p>
        <p>But an entree soup called po-tek was a revelation. It came in a tubular pan meant to evoke a Thai steamboat, over a candle flame. This boat was Noah's ark, seafood division: mussels, squid, shrimp, scallops and an unspecified white fish, all accurately cooked, in a clear chicken broth charged with kaffir lime and basil leaves, ginger, red pepper and the Thai herb galangal. Another special, called seafood madness, had many of the same ingredients, minus the broth but plus two intriguing seasonings, green peppercorns and lesser ginger, also called rhizome.</p>
        <p>An outsized clay pot was filled with impeccable mussels steamed in a mustard-colored sauce of white wine, coconut milk, lemon grass and basil. Other appetizers included a lively green papaya salad and a fine, forceful accounting of the traditional spicy chicken soup called tom yum goong.</p>
        <p>Seventeen years is a long time to prosper in Hackensack, a county seat that has seen its commercial fortunes ebb in competition with the malls of Paramus. Bangkok Garden has a homey, lived-in feeling, enlivened by touches like Thai dragon statues, banks of artificial geraniums and, on each table, a real orchid. Presiding benignly over the 95-seat main dining room are smiling portraits of Thailand's monarchs, King Bhumibol Adulyadej and Queen Sirikit. They might well smile: if they're ever in Hackensack, they'll like this place.</p>
        <p>Bangkok Garden  261 Main Street  Hackensack  (201) 487-2620  www.bangkokgarden-nj.com</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- A downtown storefront with pleasant if generic Thai décor. Ninety-five seats in the main dining room, 30 in a back room. Wheelchair-accessible.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Casual; the staff is accommodating to large groups.</p>
        <p>THE STAFF -- Amiable and efficient.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- A short but adequate wine and beer list, with a surprise: two light, inexpensive wines, a red and a white, made in Thailand and sold under the Monsoon Valley label.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Lunch combinations, $6.95 and $7.95. Dinner entrees, $8.95 to $22.95. Credit cards: American Express, MasterCard, Visa.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Roasted duck salad, chicken satay, steamed mussels, green papaya salad, tom yum goong (spicy chicken soup); po-tek (seafood soup), whole deep-fried fish, ''seafood madness''; fried bananas.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Open daily. Sunday through Thursday, 11 a.m. to 10 p.m. Friday and Saturday, 11 a.m. to 11 p.m. (The kitchen closes one hour before the restaurant.) Reservations are recommended on Friday, Saturday and Sunday. Parking is available on the street or in a rear lot.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 15, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/HACKENSACK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
