<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Whole Foods, Rejection and Invitation</title>
    <meta content="15cttopicCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15cttopic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RETAIL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Darien (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whole Foods Market Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bonanno, Christine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spiegel, Jan Ellen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Whole Foods Market Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Whole Foods, Rejection and Invitation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Whole Foods, Rejection and Invitation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN ELLEN SPIEGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spiegel, Jan Ellen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Officials in Darien, Conn, reject proposal to open Whole Foods store on site of old Howard Johnson's off Interstate 95; Christine Bonanno, deputy economic development administrator in New Haven, comments on efforts to persuade Whole Foods to open store there; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER months of meetings and two and a half years of planning, Darien has said no to a proposed Whole Foods store on the site of an old Howard Johnson's off Interstate 95.</p>
        <p>While the issue is zoning -- and may yet be resolved -- Whole Foods's difficulties in Darien are sending another ripple of anxiety through New Haven, which has all but begged the natural-foods chain to open a store there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After months of meetings and two and a half years of planning, Darien has said no to a proposed Whole Foods store off Interstate 95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER months of meetings and two and a half years of planning, Darien has said no to a proposed Whole Foods store on the site of an old Howard Johnson's off Interstate 95.</p>
        <p>While the issue is zoning -- and may yet be resolved -- Whole Foods's difficulties in Darien are sending another ripple of anxiety through New Haven, which has all but begged the natural-foods chain to open a store there.</p>
        <p>''We have been reaching out to them,'' said Christine Bonanno, New Haven's deputy economic development administrator. ''We definitely feel we have a market that is ready for a Whole Foods in New Haven.''</p>
        <p>While there had been some opposition to the Darien location by residents of a neighboring condominium complex, the main question was whether the location was zoned for a grocery store. On March 27, the Darien Planning and Zoning Commission ruled that it was not. Whole Foods can appeal that ruling in court or seek a zoning change.</p>
        <p>New Haven officials have met with Whole Foods executives several times in the last few years, but in the last two new-store announcements, the New Haven area was left out again. In addition to Darien, proposals included a store in Glastonbury and a 60,000-square foot store -- the largest Whole Foods in the state -- in Fairfield. Currently, there are stores in Greenwich and West Hartford.</p>
        <p>Even Wild Oats, a rival natural-foods chain that is being bought by Whole Foods, has left New Haven out of its plans. It has stores in Westport and West Hartford, and began construction of a Milford store last year.</p>
        <p>Still, for the first time there is word that Whole Foods has New Haven in its sights.</p>
        <p>''Eventually, we'll definitely be there,'' said Christina Minardi, Whole Foods's Northeast regional president. ''You can see the pattern of what we're doing is, we're working our way up the coast.''</p>
        <p>The Darien situation, Ms. Minardi said, is by no means the toughest the chain has faced: Getting a store into White Plains took eight years.</p>
        <p>First among the criteria Whole Foods uses to determine store placement is population density, which Ms. Minardi said was more critical than the wealth of an area. Other factors are the concentration of college graduates; parking availability (a 60,000-square-foot store requires 350 spaces); visibility; and how badly an area wants a store.</p>
        <p>On that score, New Haven excels.</p>
        <p>''They write letters, they call, they come to mayor's night in, they come to mayor's night out,'' Ms. Bonanno said.</p>
        <p>Neighboring Orange has also inquired about getting a store (it was turned down), and nearby Branford plans to contact Whole Foods about building there.</p>
        <p>It was unclear what impact the acquisition of Wild Oats would have on that chain's 110 stores nationwide, but Ms. Minardi indicated that even if the new store in Milford were converted to a Whole Foods, being 15 miles from New Haven would most likely have no bearing on whether New Haven got its own Whole Foods.</p>
        <p>All good news as far as New Haven is concerned.</p>
        <p>''We're hopeful it's sooner rather than later,'' Ms. Bonanno said. ''And we'll be working hard to make sure we can get them here.''</p>
        <p>RETAIL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
