<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giving the Lawn What It Needs</title>
    <meta content="15Home" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/realestate/15Home.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lawns</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Consumer Reports</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cornell University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DC133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giving the Lawn What It Needs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giving the Lawn What It Needs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your Home column on spring preparations for healthy lawn; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE days are longer, the air is warmer, and the forsythia is about to bloom. ''Now is the time to get your lawn ready for summer,'' said A. Martin Petrovic, a professor of turf grass science at Cornell University.</p>
        <p>Dr. Petrovic said the first thing a homeowner should do is to clean off any leaves, brush or twigs that have accumulated over the winter. After that, he said, it is wise to test the soil to find out what it may, or may not, need.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many counties in New York have a cooperative extension office that can test soil samples for homeowners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE days are longer, the air is warmer, and the forsythia is about to bloom. ''Now is the time to get your lawn ready for summer,'' said A. Martin Petrovic, a professor of turf grass science at Cornell University.</p>
        <p>Dr. Petrovic said the first thing a homeowner should do is to clean off any leaves, brush or twigs that have accumulated over the winter. After that, he said, it is wise to test the soil to find out what it may, or may not, need.</p>
        <p>''If you don't test the soil, you're going to be guessing about what to put down,'' he said, adding that many counties have a cooperative extension office that will provide a soil test kit for a nominal fee.</p>
        <p>The homeowner takes a soil sample and sends it in, and within a week or two the results will be returned, in some cases with advice about remedial steps.</p>
        <p>Peter Sawchuck, the program leader for lawns and lawn products at Consumer Reports in Yonkers, said that while waiting for the results, homeowners might want to rent a ''de-thatching'' machine to clean out the layer of organic debris that settles at the base of the grass. ''If you have a half inch or more, now is a real good time to do it,'' he said. ''But you have to make sure you clean up all the stuff you're pulling out.''</p>
        <p>The test results will list the pH level of the soil, and for growing grass, neutral or slightly acidic conditions are best. ''The pH should be between 6.5 and 7,'' Mr. Sawchuck said.</p>
        <p>Lime is often used to neutralize acidic soil. If lime is called for, Mr. Sawchuck recommends the pelletized type, as opposed to the powdery kind, because it is less messy. ''Just follow the directions on the package for spreading it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The next decision is when to fertilize and whether to apply a herbicide for weed control.</p>
        <p>Dr. Petrovic said it was better not to fertilize too early. ''You don't want to fertilize until after you get the first natural flush of growth,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the New York metropolitan area, Dr. Petrovic said, that will probably occur over the next two weeks or so, so the best time to fertilize will probably be the first week of May.</p>
        <p>If a lawn had a problem with crabgrass last year, the next couple of weeks will also be the best time to deal with that. ''You want to put down your herbicide before the forsythia blooms,'' Dr. Petrovic said. ''And that's the dilemma: most consumer herbicides come combined with fertilizer.''</p>
        <p>Herbicides used for crabgrass control, Dr. Petrovic said, are ''pre-emergents'' designed to kill the crabgrass just as it begins to grow. As a result, it is necessary to apply them before the seeds start germinating. The problem, though, is that applying a product that is a combination of crabgrass control and fertilizer may result in fertilizing just a little too early.</p>
        <p>''You might want to find a product that has a slow-release fertilizer so you don't force too much growth too soon,'' Dr. Petrovic said.</p>
        <p>It may also make sense to use the herbicide-fertilizer combination only in areas of the lawn where crabgrass has been a problem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sawchuck of Consumer Reports says that if parts of the lawn have to be reseeded, it is better to use high-quality perennial seed than less expensive seed, which is usually an ''annual'' type.</p>
        <p>''And if you are seeding in a heavily shaded area, you want a shade mix that has slower-growing grass,'' he said, adding that grass seed generally will not germinate until the soil warms up, probably not until the beginning of May. ''So don't put the seed down too early or it will just sit there and rot.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Petrovic cautioned that it was also important to avoid using a pre-emergent herbicide in any areas of the lawn that will be reseeded. The herbicide, he said, will kill germinating grass seed just as effectively as it will kill crabgrass.</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
