<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paste on the Brush, Not on the Sink</title>
    <meta content="15goods" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/business/yourmoney/15goods.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OPENERS: THE GOODS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Goods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Teeth and Dentistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teeth and Dentistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E0D6133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paste on the Brush, Not on the Sink</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Paste on the Brush, Not on the Sink</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENDAN I. KOERNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Koerner, Brendan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST people try their best to avoid being considered tedious. But Stewart Robertson, a product designer in Scotland, actually enjoys killing conversations with his logorrheic ramblings. ''If you're not boring the pants off people,'' Mr. Robertson said, ''you don't have enough passion.''</p>
        <p>For the last four years, the object of his passion -- and the chief topic of his dull lectures -- has been the X-Paste, a toothpaste dispenser meant to keep bathrooms free of gunk. A user simply presses the toothbrush against a plastic lever, and a good-size dollop of paste or gel plops down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The X-Paste was inspired by Stewart Robertson’s children, who would leave half-squeezed toothpaste tubes uncapped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST people try their best to avoid being considered tedious. But Stewart Robertson, a product designer in Scotland, actually enjoys killing conversations with his logorrheic ramblings. ''If you're not boring the pants off people,'' Mr. Robertson said, ''you don't have enough passion.''</p>
        <p>For the last four years, the object of his passion -- and the chief topic of his dull lectures -- has been the X-Paste, a toothpaste dispenser meant to keep bathrooms free of gunk. A user simply presses the toothbrush against a plastic lever, and a good-size dollop of paste or gel plops down.</p>
        <p>It was the messiness of Mr. Robertson's children that inspired the X-Paste. They would leave half-squeezed toothpaste tubes uncapped, resulting in sticky gobs dripping onto the porcelain sink.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robertson, who lives in Kilmacolm, near Glasgow, experimented with several upright toothpaste pumps, but was disappointed with their performance.</p>
        <p>''They all used a medical syringe type of approach,'' he said, referring to the pumps' use of pistons. The pistons, he said, were quickly worn down by the abrasive paste, causing the pumps ''to come to a sad stop.''</p>
        <p>Having previously designed a machine for cleaning circuit boards, Mr. Robertson went to work on creating an alternative toothpaste pump. He knew that his dispenser couldn't use pistons, and he wanted to avoid battery power, too. ''I did not want to be labeled as having made a gadget,'' he said. ''I wanted to be known for designing a serious solution for toothpaste mess.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Robertson settled on a modified version of a vacuum pump. The toothpaste tube is positioned with its nozzle facing the floor; the nozzle is then wedged into the dispenser's airtight, flexible membrane. When the dispenser's lever is pressed, toothpaste is sucked out of the tube.</p>
        <p>After cobbling together a prototype from off-the-shelf components, Mr. Robertson stopped to consider whether the X-Paste could really sell. ''There were a lot of hard questions to ask, such as, 'Are people really going to need this?' '' he said.</p>
        <p>His doubts vanished after he took the prototype to the Glasgow Science Center, a tourist attraction. According to Mr. Robertson, visitors responded enthusiastically to his demonstration of the X-Paste and said they would buy one if it ever came to market.</p>
        <p>Heartened, he created 20 more prototypes of varying shape, using a three-dimensional printing process called stereolithography. Eventually, he chose to encase the pump in a cylindrical, stainless steel cover. And two steel discs on the back of the X-Paste conceal suction cups that attach it to a tile wall.</p>
        <p>The dispenser went on sale last November through X-Paste.com; the price is £29.95, or around $59. Mr. Robertson said he could have brought down the price by having all production done in Asia, where some of the parts are made, but he chose instead to have the X-Paste's key mechanism made by a Scottish medical appliances company.</p>
        <p>''This is not a nasty, low-end foreign import,'' said Mr. Robertson, who estimates that he has sold 3,000 X-Pastes so far. ''It's a quality product.''</p>
        <p>After using an X-Paste for two weeks, I can vouch for that quality. Inserting a tube's nozzle into the pump's membrane is easier than I expected, and a soft touch is all that's needed to get a suitable ribbon of paste. Some gunk collects around the dispenser after a while, but it can be removed by soaking the X-Paste in warm water.</p>
        <p>As promised, there is no extraneous toothpaste on my sink. But then again, there never really was. Unlike Mr. Robertson's children, I've always been a stickler for capping the tube.</p>
        <p>OPENERS: THE GOODS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
