<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Airstream: The Concept Travels Well</title>
    <meta content="15TRAILER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles; Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/automobiles/15TRAILER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recreational Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recreational Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mobile Homes and Trailers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Thor Industries Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E2DD133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Airstream: The Concept Travels Well</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Airstream: The Concept Travels Well</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHIL PATTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Patton, Phil</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS if abandoned by a misdirected camper who parked in the dark, a silver Airstream trailer sits these days in the lobby of the Museum of Modern Art. A model called the Bambi, designed in 1960 with Airstream's distinctive streamlined riveted skin, has been acquired for the museum's design collection.</p>
        <p>The first Airstream, the Clipper, arrived in 1936 amid a national craze for streamlining -- in cars, in buildings, in toasters -- as the brainchild of an inventor and travel promoter named Wally Byam. After World War II, as the highway system expanded, the economy boomed and Airstreams gained starring roles in Hollywood films, the trailer came to symbolize American-style travel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A house for the road, the sleek silver Airstream has long intrigued Americans as an ideal combination of their twin loves, vehicle and home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS if abandoned by a misdirected camper who parked in the dark, a silver Airstream trailer sits these days in the lobby of the Museum of Modern Art. A model called the Bambi, designed in 1960 with Airstream's distinctive streamlined riveted skin, has been acquired for the museum's design collection.</p>
        <p>The first Airstream, the Clipper, arrived in 1936 amid a national craze for streamlining -- in cars, in buildings, in toasters -- as the brainchild of an inventor and travel promoter named Wally Byam. After World War II, as the highway system expanded, the economy boomed and Airstreams gained starring roles in Hollywood films, the trailer came to symbolize American-style travel.</p>
        <p>Airstream's appeal seems to have few limits, and indeed a powerful world traveler recently provided proof of its persistent appeal. On a trip to Asia in February, Vice President Dick Cheney traveled in an Airstream -- inside an airplane.</p>
        <p>Mark Silva, chief of the Washington bureau of The Chicago Tribune, accompanied the vice president as the press corps' pool print reporter. The group flew on a huge gray C-17 cargo plane that the Air Force calls the Spirit of Strom Thurmond, in honor of the late senator. Mr. Silva said that when he boarded he noted the familiar outline of the Airstream roof inside the vast fuselage.</p>
        <p>''I crawled on the floor to look at the nameplate,'' Mr. Silva said, confirming that it read ''Airstream, Jackson Center, Ohio.'' Inside, Mr. Silva said in an interview, ''there were plush leather chairs, blue-gray carpet, wood paneling, recessed lighting and a TV and DVD player.'' He said the Airstream reminded him of one of the first he had seen, on the cover of a Ry Cooder record album from 1970. ''The Airstream is the symbol of taking it on the road with style,'' he added.</p>
        <p>A home for the road, the Airstream has long intrigued Americans as an ideal combination of their twin loves, vehicle and home. Its functionalism also let it be read as a symbol of the ideals of modern architecture. Christian Larsen, a curatorial assistant in MoMA's department of architecture and design, said, ''The Bambi is a machine for living and traveling, the sort of industrialized, rationalized vessel that had long been the dream object of modernist architects, from Le Corbusier to Buckminster Fuller.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Larsen also related the Airstream to the work of artists like Andrea Zittel, who builds trailerlike works, installed in galleries or outdoor installations.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the Airstream has attracted the attention of automakers, too.</p>
        <p>Nissan Design America, the California studio of the Japanese automaker, produced an Airstream trailer concept displayed at auto shows after its introduction at the New York International Contemporary Furniture Fair in 2003. Bryan Thompson, one of the designers, said Nissan's work with Airstream led to the BaseCamp, a $20,000 trailer with a pop-up Kelty tent. The BaseCamp, which is now sold by Airstream, is light enough to be towed by the average car.</p>
        <p>''Airstream is one of those companies that is part of the heart and soul of American design,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''The shape is timeless, the materials are modern and the fabrication is hands-on traditional. They have the ability to combine Old World handmade craftsmanship with cutting-edge technology.''</p>
        <p>More recently, Airstream, which is based in Jackson Center, Ohio, and now owned by Thor Industries, has collaborated with Ford. The automaker's Airstream design study, a crossover wagon theoretically powered by hydrogen fuel cells, was unveiled in Detroit in January and has been on display at the New York auto show, which closes today.</p>
        <p>The alliance grew out of a high-concept future study ordered by J Mays, the group vice president for design at Ford, to explore the American journey. The result was a concept vehicle of gleaming aluminum and orange window frames aimed at the growing number of baby boomers who are 55 and older -- a group that has historically accounted for a large percentage of trailer buyers.</p>
        <p>''The Ford Airstream concept captures the sense of optimism and adventure conveyed in American aircraft, spacecraft and the streamlined shape of Airstream trailers,'' Mr. Mays said.</p>
        <p>The Ford concept realizes Wally Byam's dream of eventually making the Airstream a self-propelled land yacht. (He foresaw a motorized portion that would detach from the mothership, like a dinghy.) It recalls the VW Microbus, and for that matter the Stout Scarab, a 1935 precursor to the minivan.</p>
        <p>Inside, the Ford concept car shifts its frame of reference to more distant travel. The materials and colors -- called ''cosmic red and white'' -- were inspired by the spacecraft in the 1968 film ''2001: A Space Odyssey.''</p>
        <p>Space buffs will recall another connection between space travel and Airstream. In 1969, upon their return from the moon, the Apollo 11 astronauts were quartered inside a modified Airstream called the mobile quarantine facility. They remained in the silver pod for three weeks; President Richard M. Nixon visited and waved at the astronauts through the window.</p>
        <p>More recently, the silver bullet Airstreams have attracted the attention of those who appreciate other aspects of 1950s modernism. Allison Arieff, the former editor of Dwell magazine, which celebrates prefab housing and modernist ideals, is an Airstream owner and fan. She and her husband, Bryan Burkhart, along with David Hunt, produced a book ''Airstream: The History of the Land Yacht'' (Chronicle Books, 2000). Other titles ministering to the faithful include ''Airstream Living'' by Bruce Littlefield and Simon Brown (Collins Design, 2005), a celebration of the many ways the trailers have been customized.</p>
        <p>If Airstreams are perceived as cool among 30-somethings, it is surely because mobile living is an idea with lingering appeal. In fact, the trailers have experienced a revival after suffering a slow decline from their peak of popularity in the '50s. Byam's monocoque aircraft torpedo trailer designs proved more expensive to build than trailers that were less durable and less visually exciting. Airstream was on the ropes when its creator died in 1962.</p>
        <p>The rediscovery took time. In 2000, Christopher C. Deam, an architect and designer, was hired to rebuild the inside of an Airstream to show off Wilsonart's plastic laminate. The trailer was so well received that Airstream began producing a line of similar products.</p>
        <p>There was more to Byam's vision than the trailer itself. In the 1950s he organized the Wally Byam Caravan Club International and led Airstream trips across America -- some 4,000 gathered in Jackson Center for homecomings -- and then around the world. The Airstreamers wore dark blue berets and loaded their land yachts into the holds of ships for dispatch across the seas, painted with proud owner labels like ''Don and Leta Hill, Corning, Iowa, USA.''</p>
        <p>Byam's caravaning creed was a stark statement of one American vision of travel. The goal of trailering, he declared, was ''to place the great wide world at your doorstep for you who yearn to travel with all the comforts of home.''</p>
        <p>Byam pledged in his book ''Trailer Travel Here and Abroad,'' to ''lead caravans wherever the four winds blowto the traveled and untraveled corners of the earth.''</p>
        <p>With his wife, Stella, and their dogs Penny and Chica, Byam led caravans that traversed the Oregon Trail, South America and Europe. The most ambitious trip went from Cape Town to Cairo. Along the way, he met a witch doctor in Uganda and Emperor Haile Selassie of Ethiopia.</p>
        <p>The journey culminated in the encampment in the famed wagon wheel circle of a vast fleet of Airstreams in the shadow of the Great Pyramid of Giza, like a congregation of silvery metal worshippers.</p>
        <p>Byam began by selling plans for building trailers. Soon he moved to offering kits, then finished trailers in aluminum. In 1936 he offered the Airstream Clipper, which borrowed its name and look from Pan Am Clipper seaplanes and Chrysler's Airflow and Airstream cars.</p>
        <p>But travel by Airstream can be limiting. The vastness of the globe can be confused with the compactness of the silver pod; one's view of the world can be restricted to the one out the trailer window. ''There are just too many Italians in Italy,'' Byam concluded after driving his Airstream through Europe.</p>
        <p>''None of us had ever met a red Russian before,'' he noted. ''We were surprised to discover that they were good looking and interesting, if a trifle serious people.''</p>
        <p>In Cuba in 1958, Fulgencio Batista greeted Byam and his caravan. The dictator arrived with armed guards and an entourage of mysterious black cars. But after all, Byam recalled in his book, ''that might have been expected considering the fact that he has a revolution in his backyard.''</p>
        <p>Byam saw the Airstream as a neutral vessel wherever it sailed. ''We never get involved in the internal politics of any country,'' he said. ''We concentrate on learning as much as we can, making friends on an unofficial, nonpolitical people-to-people basis.''</p>
        <p>The Airstream, like the covered wagon, suggested membership in a group of pioneers. Mr. Larsen of MoMA said, ''In California, having one in your backyard became a symbol for a lifestyle.''</p>
        <p>The iconic successor of the Conestoga wagon and the prairie schooner, the yacht and the private Pullman car, the Airstream can be seen as a symbol of the best and worst qualities of traveling Americans: the willingness to go anywhere tempered by the simultaneous wish never to leave home.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
