<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Passing The Baton: Be Bold, New York</title>
    <meta content="15tomm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070422T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salonen, Esa-Pekka</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEFD7153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Passing The Baton: Be Bold, New York</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini article on New York Philharmonic's search for new conductor; feels conductor must be young and active in community in order to attract young audience; success of Los Angeles Philarmonic's conductor Esa Pekka Salonen discussed; conductors chosen by other US orchestras noted; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICAN orchestras have historically been hidebound institutions afraid of alienating mainstream subscribers. Boards tend to hire the most renowned maestros they can attract and afford: sure bets, in other words, safe investments. And many orchestras are weighted down with the burden of having to be the public face of a city's higher cultural aspirations.</p>
        <p>In recent decades even some great conductors driven by lofty artistic principles have unwittingly contributed to the perception that orchestras are elitist. When Kurt Masur, during his tenure with the New York Philharmonic, faced criticism that the orchestra was loath to take risks, he often answered that, yes, yes, we should play new music and be more adventurous. But then he would grow misty-eyed and speak of the Philharmonic's sacred responsibility to maintain the timeless Germanic masterpieces from Mozart through Bruckner. It was impossible not to be affected by his passion. Sadly, it was also clear that such an Old World attitude was an impediment to change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMERICAN orchestras have historically been hidebound institutions afraid of alienating mainstream subscribers. Boards tend to hire the most renowned maestros they can attract and afford: sure bets, in other words, safe investments. And many orchestras are weighted down with the burden of having to be the public face of a city's higher cultural aspirations.</p>
        <p>In recent decades even some great conductors driven by lofty artistic principles have unwittingly contributed to the perception that orchestras are elitist. When Kurt Masur, during his tenure with the New York Philharmonic, faced criticism that the orchestra was loath to take risks, he often answered that, yes, yes, we should play new music and be more adventurous. But then he would grow misty-eyed and speak of the Philharmonic's sacred responsibility to maintain the timeless Germanic masterpieces from Mozart through Bruckner. It was impossible not to be affected by his passion. Sadly, it was also clear that such an Old World attitude was an impediment to change.</p>
        <p>Was it any surprise that so many young people found it hard to see the symphonic tradition as a living art form worth their interest? So why not turn things over to a new generation of music directors, young dynamos who would think outside the box, adventurous musicians with collegial connections to young composers, sympathy for pop music and unjaded enthusiasm for reaching out to new audiences?</p>
        <p>That was exactly what the Los Angeles Philharmonic did in 1989 when it stunned the music world with the news that its next music director would be a little-known 31-year-old Finnish composer and conductor with, to most Americans, a funny-sounding name: Esa-Pekka Salonen. Last week the orchestra did it again with the announcement that Mr. Salonen would step down at the end of the 2008-9 season to devote more time to composing. His successor is even younger and less well known than Mr. Salonen was when he got the job: Gustavo Dudamel, a 26-year-old Venezuelan sensation who made his professional conducting debut only three years ago.</p>
        <p>Music lovers in New York who want our own great but status-quo-hugging Philharmonic to lead the charge in propelling symphonic art through the 21st century can only hope that the Los Angeles move is resonating within the administrative offices at Avery Fisher Hall. The New York Philharmonic is poised to announce the successor as music director to Lorin Maazel, who leaves at the end of the 2008-9 season (the same time, intriguingly, that Mr. Salonen will be free). After Mr. Masur and Mr. Maazel -- two formidable but very Old World maestros whose combined tenures at the Philharmonic will have totaled 18 years -- it would surely seem time for a generational jolt.</p>
        <p>The example of Los Angeles bears looking at. In the late '80s the orchestra was generally considered a second-tier ensemble with unrealized potential. So it took a chance that Mr. Salonen could shake things up. But in interviews at the time he debunked the ''young dynamo'' label, saying that he thought of himself ''more as a provocateur.''</p>
        <p>He was. And it worked. Within a few years Mr. Salonen turned the orchestra into an athletic, urban, sometimes scrappy but always spirited ensemble. He helped persuade the city's corporate and civic leaders to build the Philharmonic a new home, Disney Hall, now America's hippest concert hall. New listeners have been drawn to his programs, which regularly include bracing doses of new and recent works. Today the Los Angeles Philharmonic is arguably the most adventurous and inviting orchestra in the United States, though its neighbor to the north, the San Francisco Symphony, conducted by that ageless dynamo Michael Tilson Thomas, is another strong contender.</p>
        <p>That Los Angeles is placing its trust in Mr. Dudamel is an audacious and inspiring move. Mr. Dudamel made his American debut just two years ago, conducting the Los Angeles Philharmonic at the Hollywood Bowl. Next season he will make his debuts with the New York, Berlin and Vienna philharmonics. Call it the one-two-three punch.</p>
        <p>As has been the case during the Salonen years the Los Angeles orchestra will continue to court renowned conductors as regular guests, to share their insights without the burden of running the shop.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, at the New York Philharmonic, the administration has been zealously keeping its deliberations secret. Still, among conductors who have appeared with the orchestra in recent years, the musicians are known to have been especially impressed by the fiery Italian Riccardo Chailly and the elegant young Frenchman Ludovic Merlot.</p>
        <p>The name that keeps slipping out, though, is Riccardo Muti. The Philharmonic plays splendidly for this exacting Italian maestro. But in assuming the post at 68, he would be the third elder eminence in a row, and he hardly seems the type of artist who could reach young audiences and foster relations among emerging composers. With classical music making real headway in the age of iTunes and digital communications, there are tantalizing signs that young people are newly curious about this art form. So outreach is a crucial component of the music director's job.</p>
        <p>Though a formidable conductor, Mr. Maazel has had essentially no impact as a cultural leader in New York, and his programming has been oddly uninspired. Take, for example, next season's token exploration of Berio and Beethoven, which amounts to performances of just three Berio works on three programs, and one work, the well-known ''Sinfonia,'' is paired not with a Beethoven but with a Brahms symphony.</p>
        <p>Among the new generation of conductors, the name that keeps popping up is Alan Gilbert, who would be a refreshing choice. Mr. Gilbert is a Philharmonic baby, born in New York in 1968 to two violinists in the orchestra. He has thrived as the conductor of the Royal Stockholm Philharmonic and presented imaginative festivals of music by John Adams, Henri Dutilleux and other living composers. With the New York Philharmonic he has given accomplished and exciting performances of varied repertory, including gnarly, complex scores by Dutilleux and Ligeti.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Mr. Salonen's success in Los Angeles may have emboldened a few American orchestras to make daring appointments in recent years. Next season the indomitable Marin Alsop becomes the first woman to head a major American orchestra when she takes charge of the Baltimore Symphony. She seems to have reached an understanding with a cadre of the musicians who initially protested her choice, asserting that they had had little role in the selection process and that they were underwhelmed by her talents. But the orchestra seems abuzz with optimism about Ms. Alsop now.</p>
        <p>David Robertson, the superlative California-born conductor who cut his teeth as the music director of Pierre Boulez's contemporary ensemble in Paris, has galvanized the players of the St. Louis Symphony, which had skirted bankruptcy just before he took the helm in 2005. St. Louis audiences are streaming into his concerts, and the orchestra sounded terrific during the typically invigorating Robertson program I heard last month at Carnegie Hall, with an atmospheric new work by George Benjamin, Bartok's propulsive First Piano Concerto and a freshly conceived account of Sibelius's Second Symphony.</p>
        <p>James Levine's immense success at the Boston Symphony is a cautionary tale for those us who beat the drum for younger dynamos. These days the low-key Mr. Levine, who at 63 conducts seated after years of health problems, hardly cuts the figure of a podium wizard. But the players revere him, and this historically great orchestra has been rejuvenated. He showed up for work with enough ideas for five seasons of innovative programs. And he fosters contemporary music not just by performing it but also through well-attended preconcert talks and regular radio appearances.</p>
        <p>The boldest choice of late has come from, of all places, Dallas. To succeed the feisty and erratic Andrew Litton, who left in 2006, the Dallas Symphony Orchestra has tapped the Dutch conductor Jaap van Zweden, virtually unknown in America, who assumes the post in 2008. Formerly the concertmaster of the renowned Royal Concertgebouw Orchestra in Amsterdam (a position he won at 19), he turned to full-time conducting in 1997. Last year he floored Dallas critics, audiences and players in his debut program with the orchestra.</p>
        <p>But so far Mr. van Zweden has had no substantive involvement with music by living composers. In a recent phone interview the orchestra's president, Fred Bronstein, said Mr. von Zweden ''has a keen interest in new music and is adding new pieces all the time.'' Mr. Bronstein added that Mr. von Zweden hopes to introduce Dallas audiences to works by Dutch composers. How about Dallas composers? If an orchestra does not champion deserving composers from its own region, who will?</p>
        <p>In Mr. Dudamel's case, though he is a comprehensive musician and a trained composer, he has won most of his acclaim for performances of staples, like Mahler's Fifth Symphony, which he conducted in his debut this month with the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, drawing rapturous reviews from critics there. His debut recording on the Deutsche Grammophon label offers incisive, fresh and urgent accounts of Beethoven's Fifth and Seventh Symphonies with the Simón Bolívar Youth Orchestra of Venezuela, an impressive training ensemble that he has conducted since 1999.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dudamel's devotion to education caught the attention of Deborah Borda, the president and chief executive officer of the Los Angeles Philharmonic, who followed him around the world, checking out performances to make sure he was the ''real thing,'' as Daniel Barenboim has called him. She was sold. Mr. Dudamel has signed a five-year contract.</p>
        <p>His Chicago program included a 1954 work by a Venezuelan composer, Evencio Castellanos. But how would he manage, say, the complex and mesmerizing Ligeti Violin Concerto, which Mr. Gilbert conducted recently at the New York Philharmonic, with Christian Tetzlaff as soloist? Or Mr. Salonen's bustling ''L.A. Variations,'' which has become a staple of the Los Angeles Philharmonic's repertory? On the other hand, as a South American Mr. Dudamel should be able to connect with the enormous Latino population of Los Angeles. He surely will bring his own outlook to concert life in the city. In any event, for a young artist Mr. Dudamel is about to endure a very public maturation.</p>
        <p>Maybe Los Angeles's courageous choice will jolt the New York Philharmonic. This is the orchestra, after all, that took a chance on the young Leonard Bernstein in 1957 by appointing him co-principal conductor with Dimitri Mitropoulos, whose tenure with the Philharmonic was winding down at the time. Of course Bernstein was becoming a household name, having composed ''West Side Story,'' which opened that same year in New York. But at the time his Broadway credentials were actually held against him in certain stuffy confines of the classical music establishment. Within one year the music directorship of the Philharmonic was all his, making Bernstein the first American to hold the post.</p>
        <p>That risk sure paid off.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 22, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about potential candidates for music director of the New York Philharmonic misspelled the surname of a guest conductor who has impressed the orchestra's musicians. He is Ludovic Morlot, not Merlot. The article also misidentified the work that Gustavo Dudamel, who will take over as music director of the Los Angeles Philharmonic in 2009, conducted in his debut with the Chicago Symphony Orchestra. It was Mahler's First Symphony, not his Fifth Symphony. The article also gave an incorrect surname in some references for a conductor who will lead the Dallas Symphony Orchestra. He is Jaap van Zweden, not von Zweden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 22, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about potential candidates for music director of the New York Philharmonic misspelled the surname of a guest conductor who has impressed the orchestra's musicians. He is Ludovic Morlot, not Merlot. The article also misidentified the work that Gustavo Dudamel, who will take over as music director of the Los Angeles Philharmonic in 2009, conducted in his debut with the Chicago Symphony Orchestra. It was Mahler's First Symphony, not his Fifth Symphony. The article also gave an incorrect surname in some references for a conductor who will lead the Dallas Symphony Orchestra. He is Jaap van Zweden, not von Zweden.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
