<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Find Pickup Driver Who Left Site</title>
    <meta content="15crash" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/15crash.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CORZINE'S CRASH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Garden State Parkway (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Potts, Kenneth Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Find Pickup Driver Who Left Site</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Police Find Pickup Driver Who Left Site</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI; David W. Chen contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey State Police say they have located driver of pickup truck that set off crash on Garden State Parkway that severely injured Gov Jon S Corzine; say they have no plans to charge man with leaving scene of accident because he said he was unaware his vehicle had been involved; investigators familiar with case identify man as Kenneth Potts Jr (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Jersey State Police said Saturday that they had located the driver of a pickup truck that set off the crash that severely injured Gov. Jon S. Corzine. But the police said they had no plans to charge the man with leaving the scene of the accident because he said he was unaware his vehicle had been involved.</p>
        <p>The driver had pulled to the side of the Garden State Parkway after seeing the flashing emergency lights of the governor's Chevrolet Suburban, according to a state police statement. But when the pickup slipped off the pavement, the driver overcorrected into traffic, causing the crash, the statement said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Police said they had no plans to charge the driver of a truck that set off the crash that severely injured Gov. Jon S. Corzine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New Jersey State Police said Saturday that they had located the driver of a pickup truck that set off the crash that severely injured Gov. Jon S. Corzine. But the police said they had no plans to charge the man with leaving the scene of the accident because he said he was unaware his vehicle had been involved.</p>
        <p>The driver had pulled to the side of the Garden State Parkway after seeing the flashing emergency lights of the governor's Chevrolet Suburban, according to a state police statement. But when the pickup slipped off the pavement, the driver overcorrected into traffic, causing the crash, the statement said.</p>
        <p>With evidence from police cameras and assistance from the police in Little Egg Harbor Township, troopers tracked down the driver and questioned him Friday at the Atlantic City casino where he works.</p>
        <p>Col. Joseph R. Fuentes, the state police superintendent, said that the driver said he did not stop because he did not realize he had started a chain of events that led Mr. Corzine's driver to hit a guardrail, critically injuring the governor. The police would identify the driver only as a 20-year-old man from Atlantic County, but investigators familiar with the case, who spoke on condition of anonymity, identified him as Kenneth Potts Jr. Attempts to reach Mr. Potts were unsuccessful.</p>
        <p>''He was unaware that he caused this accident which unfolded as the other two vehicles passed him,'' Colonel Fuentes said in a written statement.</p>
        <p>The state police said they had not determined whether the driver of the pickup truck would be cited for any traffic violations.</p>
        <p>Colonel Fuentes's statement provided the most complete description to date of the accident.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Corzine's motorcade approached milepost 43.4, the red Ford pickup pulled onto the shoulder from the right lane and slowed down. A white Dodge Ram pickup moved from the left to the right lane. But as the white Dodge approached the red Ford, the Ford's right front tire went off the paved shoulder and hit softer dirt, causing the truck to pull to the right. The driver turned the wheel to the left but overcompensated and partly entered the right lane.</p>
        <p>This led the driver of the white Dodge to pull sharply to the left and strike the passenger-side front fender of the governor's vehicle. The impact caused Mr. Corzine's Suburban to swerve onto the grass median off the left side of the roadway and smash into the end of a guardrail.</p>
        <p>One question that remained Saturday was how fast Mr. Corzine's car was traveling. One driver who said he was near Mr. Corzine's motorcade said that most cars were going about 65 to 70 miles per hour at the time.</p>
        <p>The motorist, Mark Richman, a professional magician from Rockaway, N.J., said that after the accident, he got out of his car and saw two ankles -- Mr. Corzine's, in shoes -- jutting out the back.</p>
        <p>''His feet were out there,'' Mr. Richman said.</p>
        <p>CORZINE'S CRASH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
