<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Had a Hammer</title>
    <meta content="Kalfus.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/review/Kalfus.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Ice (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Had a Hammer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">They Had a Hammer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN KALFUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kalfus, Ken</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ICE</p>
        <p>By Vladimir Sorokin.</p>
        <p>Translated by Jamey Gambrell.</p>
        <p>321 pp. New York Review Books. $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Vladimir Sorokin’s novel, cult members test people by banging on their chests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ICE</p>
        <p>By Vladimir Sorokin.</p>
        <p>Translated by Jamey Gambrell.</p>
        <p>321 pp. New York Review Books. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Controversy chases the Russian writer Vladimir Sorokin the way a dog chases a stick. His 1999 novel, ''Blue Lard,'' featuring some hot man-on-man love between Stalin and Khrushchev, provoked pornography charges and a public protest in Moscow, where copies of the book were dumped in a large mock toilet. His libretto for a Bolshoi Opera production earned the threat of an inquiry in the Duma in 2005. Despite the international publicity generated by all this, little of Sorokin's work has reached American audiences.</p>
        <p>The intellectual journal n+1 tried to increase awareness of Sorokin in 2004 with a characteristically indelicate excerpt from his novel ''The Norm,'' a Brezhnev-era fantasy in which every Soviet citizen is required to consume daily the brown, malodorous contents of mass-produced cellophane packets. After a few pages in which a series of ordinary individuals reluctantly ingest their rations, we come to understand that what they're eating is human excrement, an exquisite token of life's regimentation within and beyond Russian borders.</p>
        <p>Sorokin's new offering to English-language readers, ''Ice,'' is the first of a trilogy that has already been published in Russia. It also revolves around a symbolic essential substance: in this case, a crystalline icelike material, mined from a meteor, that can awaken the power of speech in selected human hearts. Unfortunately, this central conceit proves even harder to swallow than the one in ''The Norm.''</p>
        <p>''Ice'' opens like a crime thriller, with three familiar contemporary Russian characters: the student-slacker, the prostitute and the businessman. Each is kidnapped in a separate incident, bound and gagged by teams of blue-eyed, blond men and women who scour Moscow's streets for the similarly blue-eyed and blond. The kidnappers strike their victims' chests with hammers until they're killed or their hearts start to mumble and speak. When these hearts reveal their identities (with guttural Klingonish names like Ural, Diar and Mokho), the abducted are brought to a secret Moscow clinic where they're treated for their chest injuries, welcomed as brothers and sisters and invited to participate in some literally heart-to-heart chats with their hosts. The hammers' heads are made from the meteor's magic ice.</p>
        <p>These goings-on, brutal and strange even by Moscow standards, are explained by Khram, an elderly woman whose heart was ''awakened'' when she was a young girl sent to Germany. There she was selected for an ice thumping by members of a secret organization who taught her the truth about Creation: ''In the beginning there was only the Light. And the Light shone in the Absolute Emptiness. The Light Shone for Itself Alone. The Light consisted of 23,000 light-bearing rays. And we were those rays.'' Then the Light fell to Earth, bringing imperfection into the universe. But the 23,000 rays still radiate in the hearts of certain men and women, many of them unaware, every one of them icily blond and blue-eyed. Once they've been found and their hearts awakened, the 23,000 will chant the 23 ''heart words'' in unison, the Earth will dissolve and the Light will return to Eternity.</p>
        <p>That day will be a lousy one for the rest of us, but the founder of the cult explains: ''The absolute majority of people on this earth are walking dead. They are born dead, they marry the dead, they give birth to the dead and die; their dead children give birth to new dead -- and so on, from century to century.'' Unlike other conquering faiths, such as Christianity and Communism, the ice-centered ideology refuses redemption to humanity at large. The cult is looking only for its own, not for converts or slaves. After finding Ural, Diar and Mokho, the ice people indifferently leave behind the bodies of the ''empties.''</p>
        <p>The cosmology behind this novel is absurd, of course, but ''Ice'' lacks some of the elements that we associate with absurdist writing: humor, non sequiturs, a correlation with reality that reveals the real world's ludicrous particulars. The glib thing would be to declare ''Ice'' a spoof of Russia's recent totalitarian past, or of totalitarianism or ideology or religion in general, but Sorokin's ice cult hardly resonates with anything historical. ''Ice'' is much less a satire than a single monstrous vision: human beings are no more than ''meat machines,'' a race unable to communicate on a truly intimate scale and unworthy of continued existence. Purity lies in a universe without thought or language. In his frigid antihumanism, Sorokin parts company with Russian satirists like Gogol, Bulgakov, Yuri Olesha and, more recently, Viktor Pelevin.</p>
        <p>Jamey Gambrell, who has produced luminous translations of lyrical contemporary Russian writers like Tatyana Tolstaya, transforms Sorokin's staccato cadences into a hard-boiled English that suits the novel's brutality, especially in its violent early chapters. But even with help from a sensitive translator, American readers taking a whack at the novel with their own ice hammers may have trouble finding its heart, and even more trouble getting it to speak.</p>
        <p>Ken Kalfus's most recent novel is ''A Disorder Peculiar to the Country.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ken Kalfus's most recent novel is ''A Disorder Peculiar to the Country.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
