<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For New Mothers, a Priceless Dose of Community</title>
    <meta content="15wetopicWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15wetopic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SUPPORT SYSTEM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Full Circle Women's Health</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Werthamer, Cynthia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pregnancy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For New Mothers, a Priceless Dose of Community</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For New Mothers, a Priceless Dose of Community</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA WERTHAMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Werthamer, Cynthia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Full Circle Women's Health, clinic in White Plains, NY, that offers wide range of services to new mothers, including referrals to counselors for those suffering from postpartum depression; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Suzanne Blair discovered she was pregnant in 2005, she went to Full Circle Women's Health, a clinic in White Plains, where she was relieved to find ''someone who would listen, where I wasn't just another number.''</p>
        <p>Her first child, Thomas, was born in August 2005. He had ''terrible'' colic and would cry for up to eight hours a day. Ms. Blair, 32, said she was at her wit's end.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Suzanne Blair discovered she was pregnant in 2005, she went to Full Circle Women’s Health, a clinic in White Plains, where she was relieved to find “someone who would listen, where I wasn’t just another number.”.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Suzanne Blair discovered she was pregnant in 2005, she went to Full Circle Women's Health, a clinic in White Plains, where she was relieved to find ''someone who would listen, where I wasn't just another number.''</p>
        <p>Her first child, Thomas, was born in August 2005. He had ''terrible'' colic and would cry for up to eight hours a day. Ms. Blair, 32, said she was at her wit's end.</p>
        <p>''After years of waiting and waiting for a baby, I didn't think I could be a good mother,'' said Ms. Blair, of Croton-on-Hudson, who had had two miscarriages before Thomas was born and whose husband, Ryan, an airplane pilot, is away from home more than half the week. ''I just wept.''</p>
        <p>She's not alone. A recent study on psychiatric illness after childbirth found that postpartum depression is far more common than previously thought. New mothers, especially in the first three weeks after birth, are seven times as likely to be hospitalized with mental illness as women with older infants, the study found. The study, based on 2.3 million patients in Denmark, was reported by The Journal of the American Medical Association in December.</p>
        <p>Ms. Blair's midwife, Kathy Herron, referred her to a postpartum support group run by Carol Merle-Fishman, a member of the Hudson Valley Birth Network, a Westchester-based alliance of birth professionals. (Full Circle's midwives belong to the network.)</p>
        <p>''It's such a comfort to hear that what you're feeling isn't abnormal, and to be able to talk, not just about the joys of motherhood, but about the challenges,'' Ms. Blair said.</p>
        <p>The network's treasurer, Debbie Aglietti, who runs Northeast Doulas in Mahopac, said that in the last five years, she had seen an increase in postpartum depression. Ms. Aglietti, from her experience as a birth and postpartum doula (a coach or supporter) with more than 350 families, estimates that one family in five suffers from the phenomenon, which ranges from an inability to get out of bed to ''not liking their baby.''</p>
        <p>The birth network, founded in 2004, is unusual in the scope of its services and the interconnection of its practitioners, members say. More than 40 people, mostly women practicing in Westchester, Putnam, Rockland, Sullivan, Orange and Dutchess Counties, belong to the birth network, which is made up of birth educators, doulas, therapists, midwives, pediatricians, acupuncturists and specialists in lactation and breast-feeding, among others. The network holds bimonthly meetings, and because of their regular contact, practitioners can refer clients knowledgeably.</p>
        <p>''I feel very strongly that I want to know the person I'm referring people to,'' Ms. Herron said. ''At our network meetings, we really get to know each other and our backgrounds.''</p>
        <p>In 2006, the network's members saw more than 2,000 mothers and children, some 30 percent referred by other members of the network, according to Melissa Creighton, a co-president of the network and a doula training to be a midwife.</p>
        <p>The personal referral was important for Ms. Blair, who said she was ''not at a point in my life where I could have found the postpartum group myself, or done the research; I hadn't slept.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Merle-Fishman said that ''what's special is that all these disciplines are brought together, and we all know and help each other.''</p>
        <p>''It's networking in the modern age,'' she said. ''But unlike sitting down at a computer, these women are being personally supported.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Blair is expecting another child in October, and if her family hadn't moved to Cold Spring, she said she would be using the same midwifery group. ''There's no bigger change on earth than becoming a mother,'' she said. ''Not a lot of people know that this network for support exists.''</p>
        <p>SUPPORT SYSTEM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
