<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F. Y. I.</title>
    <meta content="15fyi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/thecity/15fyi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="F. Y. I."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rodents</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jamaica (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollak, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/F.Y.I.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFD7133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F. Y. I.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">And Forget the Tip</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL POLLAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollak, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions about lifting cab drivers' licenses, deteriorating church in Jamaica, Queens and 'multiplex rodent station' in Manhattan's financial district; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>And Forget the Tip</p>
        <p>Q. Just wondering, after a particularly unsatisfying taxi ride: How bad a driver does a cabby have to be before the city lifts his or her license?</p>
        <p>A. It's a matter of numbers.</p>
        <p>The Taxi and Limousine Commission uses two rating systems. One, the Critical Driver Program, uses state Motor Vehicle Department license points. (For instance, speeding means 3 to 11 points against your record, depending on how fast; reckless driving is 5 points; and so on.) Any cabdriver who accumulates 10 or more points in 15 months loses his or her taxi license. Racking up six or more points in 15 months means a 30-day suspension.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How bad a driver does a cabby have to be before the city lifts his or her license?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>And Forget the Tip</p>
        <p>Q. Just wondering, after a particularly unsatisfying taxi ride: How bad a driver does a cabby have to be before the city lifts his or her license?</p>
        <p>A. It's a matter of numbers.</p>
        <p>The Taxi and Limousine Commission uses two rating systems. One, the Critical Driver Program, uses state Motor Vehicle Department license points. (For instance, speeding means 3 to 11 points against your record, depending on how fast; reckless driving is 5 points; and so on.) Any cabdriver who accumulates 10 or more points in 15 months loses his or her taxi license. Racking up six or more points in 15 months means a 30-day suspension.</p>
        <p>Drivers can get a two-point reduction by taking a motor vehicle accident prevention course.</p>
        <p>The commission's other system, the Persistent Violator Program, takes passengers' complaints into account. It penalizes drivers for taxi commission violations like discourtesy (2 points), using a cellphone while driving (2 points), not using the shortest available route and other cabby infractions. The threshold for punishment is the same as for motor vehicle points.</p>
        <p>In the fiscal year ended 2006, there were 32 license revocations for motor vehicle violations and 122 suspensions, according to the taxi commission. For persistent violators (discourtesy and so on), there were 5 license revocations and 32 suspensions.</p>
        <p>From a Ruined Church</p>
        <p>Q. For years, I watched an old church deteriorate and then collapse just east of the Jamaica station on the Long Island Rail Road. In the last few years, part of the church has been rebuilt with a wall around it. Can you tell me its story?</p>
        <p>A. You were seeing the decline and transformation of St. Monica's Roman Catholic Church.</p>
        <p>The church was at 94-20 160th Street in Jamaica. Designated a city landmark in 1979, it was built in 1856-57 and is one of the earliest examples of Early Romanesque Revival architecture in New York. Mario Cuomo, the former governor, was an altar boy there.</p>
        <p>After World War II, parishioners moved away and downtown Jamaica declined, and in 1973, the diocese closed the church. The city took over the property but did not seal it, and vandalism and the elements took their toll. York College of the City University of New York became the owner, but the state delayed funds for remodeling or preservation. Eventually, the main part of the church collapsed in 1998, leaving only the front facade and tower.</p>
        <p>York College has incorporated those remnants into its child and family center, built on the site. The center provides free child care for students with children. There are many single parents who hold down jobs to go to York College, and this is a vital service for them, said Nate Moore, a York College spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mouse Movies?</p>
        <p>Q. Last month, I must admit, I was stumped when walking in the financial district after lunch and saw large, professionally executed metal plaque on the side of a building, reading: ''Multiplex Rodent Station Located Here.'' How on earth could there be a multiplex for rodents?</p>
        <p>A. Movie theaters are getting small, but not that small.</p>
        <p>A pest exterminator explained that a rodent station is a poison-bait box, tamper-resistant to protect children, set on the ground indoors or outdoors to kill rats and mice. ''Multiplex'' just means that it's a big one: multiple entrances, no waiting.</p>
        <p>The city's health and environmental agencies said the one you saw is a private commercial installation.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL POLLAK</p>
        <p>F. Y. I. E-mail: fyi@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: fyi@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
