<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fiction Chronicle</title>
    <meta content="McCulloch.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/review/McCulloch.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840243"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Soto, Sonia</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fiction Chronicle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fiction Chronicle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MCCULLOCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcculloch, Alison</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE WIND FROM THE EAST. By Almudena Grandes. Translated by Sonia Soto. (Seven Stories, $27.95.) The east wind that whips Spain's southwest coast can be so trying, explains one of the characters in this long and pleasantly meandering novel, that the courts allow it to be cited ''as an extenuating circumstance in cases of assault and battery, physical abuse, even murder.'' Juan, a doctor in his early 40s, and Sara, 53, a single woman of some means, become friends after settling in the same new beachfront development. For these emotional refugees from Madrid, the wind takes some getting used to. Why they each came to Andalusia are the mysteries that propel the narrative forward, and Grandes unravels them at a perfect pace, with just enough tension between the revealed and the hidden, the past and present. Sara's story, one of betrayal on many sides, reaches back to the Civil War, and the deal her impoverished parents struck with the devil, in the guise of a well-to-do woman who for a time was Sara's surrogate mother. Juan, who arrives with his 10-year-old niece and mentally disabled brother, has left behind a decade-long affair with his sister-in-law, now dead, and one terrible night he can't forget. The mix also includes an attractive single mother who cleans house for these two neighbors. It's all the ingredients for a sentimental daytime soap. But although she edges dangerously close, Grandes, whose book will appear next month, manages to keep this intricate story of flawed people engaging and fresh.</p>
        <p>PAPER TIGER. By Olivier Rolin. Translated by William Cloonan. (University of Nebraska, cloth, $40; paper, $17.95.) Martin, an aging French radical from the 60s, wonders where it all went and why. One night in 2000, when this rushing stream of a book is set, he broods out loud while driving around (and around and around) Paris with Marie, the 24-year-old daughter of his best friend from ''the Cause.'' Marie's father died in an unexplained fall from a church tower 20 years earlier, and the excuse for Martin's regurgitation of the past is to introduce Marie to her lost parent. At the same time, he is trying to understand his own father, a ''colonialist soldier'' killed carrying out ''France's civilizing mission'' in Indochina. Through these histories, Rolin philosophizes about Big Ideas like aging, lost idealism and the weight of past wars on future generations. It sounds like heavy going, and it is. Rolin's use of the second-person and the recurring shifts back and forth in time can be disorienting; but there are also treats that make the car ride worth taking, some serious (like Rolin's observations -- often pessimistic -- about the human condition) and others delightfully comic (like the young revolutionaries' many botched missions). When the journey to the end of the night is over, the impression left behind (at once comforting and disturbing) is that history will make a paper tiger of every high hope and feared foe alike, no matter how seemingly imperishable.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN VISA. By Juan de Recacoechea. Translated by Adrian Althoff. (Akashic, paper, $14.95.) Illicit drug use far outstrips terrorism as a killer of Americans, but the days when countries like Bolivia and Colombia were in our cross hairs in the war on drugs now seem almost innocent. Forty-year-old Mario Alvarez, a ''ruined petit bourgeois,'' has pinned his hopes on acquiring a visa that will get him from La Paz to Miami where his son, who made the move at 18, has found him a job at a House of Pancakes. But it's 1993, and as Mario's godfather warns him, the cocaine trade has made Americans very suspicious: ''They imagine that every one of us is carrying at least a hundred grams.'' Despite a new haircut, a good suit and a carefully assembled file of false documents, Mario fails at the consulate. Plan B involves a crime seemingly intended to evoke Raskolnikov's in many of its particulars and in all of its futility. Around the edges of this story line Recacoechea scatters characters sometimes too pointedly colorful (a ''famous ex-goalie-turned-shrewd-politician,'' a transvestite named Gardenia) and concocts, at least in translation, oddball turns of phrase (''I was as confused as a Saharan on the high seas,'' ''a strange dessert of chocolate and tropical fruit that looked like it could constipate a duck''). ''American Visa,'' which won Bolivia's National Book Prize in 1994 and was made into a movie in 2005, is both dark and quirky, a revealing excursion to a place over which ''the gringos'' to the north always loom.</p>
        <p>HUNTING AND GATHERING. By Anna Gavalda. Translated by Alison Anderson. (Riverhead, paper, $16.) Chocolate brownie ice cream or ''Hunting and Gathering''? Both taste pretty good at first, slip down easily and even contain the occasional chunky bits. But they share something else: after your third or fourth bite, you'll be reaching for the Pepto-Bismol. The latest offering from Gavalda, a very successful French novelist, reads as if it was written with its just-released French movie version in mind (starring Audrey Tautou of course). The protagonist, Camille, is a gorgeous, talented (''She was gifted. Very gifted. Too gifted''), lonely, misunderstood, near-death gamine who meets an odd assortment of other misunderstood young Parisians, all overcoming difficult childhoods (evil mothers are well represented). In the course of nearly 500 cloying pages, they help one another find lasting happiness (''For the first time, each and every one of them felt like they belonged to a real family''). And all this not in any scrubby old banlieue, but in an apartment next door to the Eiffel Tower. What movie director could resist? Take the ice cream.</p>
        <p>PIERCING. By Ryu Murakami. Translated by Ralph McCarthy. (Penguin Books, $13.) The gasp-with-horror scene that opens this perfectly titled book begins oh so innocently: a new father, awake in the middle of the night, gazes at his 4-month-old daughter, who lies asleep in her crib tucked beneath a pink blanket. But wait, what's that in Dad's hand? ''Gripping the ice pick lightly to minimize trembling, he placed the point of it next to the baby's cheek.'' The reader's palpitations continue well into this dense little novel, as the father, Kawashima Masayuki, hits upon a way of relieving his creeping desire to hurt the baby: ''There's only one way to overcome the fear: you've got to stab someone else with an ice pick.'' But that strategy goes awry -- the prostitute he selects as his victim is at least as disturbed as Kawashima, and their combined psychopathologies keep getting in the way. In the course of their sadistic dance with death, their histories as victims of child abuse are revealed. Murakami has a known predilection for shock, as in his ''Coin Locker Babies'' or ''In the Miso Soup,'' but in ''Piercing'' there is little else besides. The few other characters, among them Kawashima's wife, fade away as the story staggers through Tokyo from blood pool to blood pool. Depending on your fortitude, Murakami's penetrating forays into the minds of abused children may make the horror worth getting through, or may not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New books by Almudena Grandes, Olivier Rolin, Juan de Recacoechea, Anna Gavalda and Ryu Murakami.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE WIND FROM THE EAST. By Almudena Grandes. Translated by Sonia Soto. (Seven Stories, $27.95.) The east wind that whips Spain's southwest coast can be so trying, explains one of the characters in this long and pleasantly meandering novel, that the courts allow it to be cited ''as an extenuating circumstance in cases of assault and battery, physical abuse, even murder.'' Juan, a doctor in his early 40s, and Sara, 53, a single woman of some means, become friends after settling in the same new beachfront development. For these emotional refugees from Madrid, the wind takes some getting used to. Why they each came to Andalusia are the mysteries that propel the narrative forward, and Grandes unravels them at a perfect pace, with just enough tension between the revealed and the hidden, the past and present. Sara's story, one of betrayal on many sides, reaches back to the Civil War, and the deal her impoverished parents struck with the devil, in the guise of a well-to-do woman who for a time was Sara's surrogate mother. Juan, who arrives with his 10-year-old niece and mentally disabled brother, has left behind a decade-long affair with his sister-in-law, now dead, and one terrible night he can't forget. The mix also includes an attractive single mother who cleans house for these two neighbors. It's all the ingredients for a sentimental daytime soap. But although she edges dangerously close, Grandes, whose book will appear next month, manages to keep this intricate story of flawed people engaging and fresh.</p>
        <p>PAPER TIGER. By Olivier Rolin. Translated by William Cloonan. (University of Nebraska, cloth, $40; paper, $17.95.) Martin, an aging French radical from the 60s, wonders where it all went and why. One night in 2000, when this rushing stream of a book is set, he broods out loud while driving around (and around and around) Paris with Marie, the 24-year-old daughter of his best friend from ''the Cause.'' Marie's father died in an unexplained fall from a church tower 20 years earlier, and the excuse for Martin's regurgitation of the past is to introduce Marie to her lost parent. At the same time, he is trying to understand his own father, a ''colonialist soldier'' killed carrying out ''France's civilizing mission'' in Indochina. Through these histories, Rolin philosophizes about Big Ideas like aging, lost idealism and the weight of past wars on future generations. It sounds like heavy going, and it is. Rolin's use of the second-person and the recurring shifts back and forth in time can be disorienting; but there are also treats that make the car ride worth taking, some serious (like Rolin's observations -- often pessimistic -- about the human condition) and others delightfully comic (like the young revolutionaries' many botched missions). When the journey to the end of the night is over, the impression left behind (at once comforting and disturbing) is that history will make a paper tiger of every high hope and feared foe alike, no matter how seemingly imperishable.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN VISA. By Juan de Recacoechea. Translated by Adrian Althoff. (Akashic, paper, $14.95.) Illicit drug use far outstrips terrorism as a killer of Americans, but the days when countries like Bolivia and Colombia were in our cross hairs in the war on drugs now seem almost innocent. Forty-year-old Mario Alvarez, a ''ruined petit bourgeois,'' has pinned his hopes on acquiring a visa that will get him from La Paz to Miami where his son, who made the move at 18, has found him a job at a House of Pancakes. But it's 1993, and as Mario's godfather warns him, the cocaine trade has made Americans very suspicious: ''They imagine that every one of us is carrying at least a hundred grams.'' Despite a new haircut, a good suit and a carefully assembled file of false documents, Mario fails at the consulate. Plan B involves a crime seemingly intended to evoke Raskolnikov's in many of its particulars and in all of its futility. Around the edges of this story line Recacoechea scatters characters sometimes too pointedly colorful (a ''famous ex-goalie-turned-shrewd-politician,'' a transvestite named Gardenia) and concocts, at least in translation, oddball turns of phrase (''I was as confused as a Saharan on the high seas,'' ''a strange dessert of chocolate and tropical fruit that looked like it could constipate a duck''). ''American Visa,'' which won Bolivia's National Book Prize in 1994 and was made into a movie in 2005, is both dark and quirky, a revealing excursion to a place over which ''the gringos'' to the north always loom.</p>
        <p>HUNTING AND GATHERING. By Anna Gavalda. Translated by Alison Anderson. (Riverhead, paper, $16.) Chocolate brownie ice cream or ''Hunting and Gathering''? Both taste pretty good at first, slip down easily and even contain the occasional chunky bits. But they share something else: after your third or fourth bite, you'll be reaching for the Pepto-Bismol. The latest offering from Gavalda, a very successful French novelist, reads as if it was written with its just-released French movie version in mind (starring Audrey Tautou of course). The protagonist, Camille, is a gorgeous, talented (''She was gifted. Very gifted. Too gifted''), lonely, misunderstood, near-death gamine who meets an odd assortment of other misunderstood young Parisians, all overcoming difficult childhoods (evil mothers are well represented). In the course of nearly 500 cloying pages, they help one another find lasting happiness (''For the first time, each and every one of them felt like they belonged to a real family''). And all this not in any scrubby old banlieue, but in an apartment next door to the Eiffel Tower. What movie director could resist? Take the ice cream.</p>
        <p>PIERCING. By Ryu Murakami. Translated by Ralph McCarthy. (Penguin Books, $13.) The gasp-with-horror scene that opens this perfectly titled book begins oh so innocently: a new father, awake in the middle of the night, gazes at his 4-month-old daughter, who lies asleep in her crib tucked beneath a pink blanket. But wait, what's that in Dad's hand? ''Gripping the ice pick lightly to minimize trembling, he placed the point of it next to the baby's cheek.'' The reader's palpitations continue well into this dense little novel, as the father, Kawashima Masayuki, hits upon a way of relieving his creeping desire to hurt the baby: ''There's only one way to overcome the fear: you've got to stab someone else with an ice pick.'' But that strategy goes awry -- the prostitute he selects as his victim is at least as disturbed as Kawashima, and their combined psychopathologies keep getting in the way. In the course of their sadistic dance with death, their histories as victims of child abuse are revealed. Murakami has a known predilection for shock, as in his ''Coin Locker Babies'' or ''In the Miso Soup,'' but in ''Piercing'' there is little else besides. The few other characters, among them Kawashima's wife, fade away as the story staggers through Tokyo from blood pool to blood pool. Depending on your fortitude, Murakami's penetrating forays into the minds of abused children may make the horror worth getting through, or may not.</p>
        <p>Alison McCulloch is a former editor at the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alison McCulloch is a former editor at the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
