<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Digging Into His Past</title>
    <meta content="15LIfilmLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15LIfilm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Arts and Entertainment"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Clams</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shellfish</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marino, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Everitt, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Diggers (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0DB123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Digging Into His Past</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Digging Into His Past</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID EVERITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Everitt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on actor Ken Marino, whose first feature-length screenplay, for film Diggers, was inspired by his childhood in Moriches, on Long Island's South Shore, where his father was clam digger; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN writing his first feature-length script, the screenplay for the film ''Diggers,'' Ken Marino naturally turned to a familiar source of inspiration: his Long Island roots. The actor has appeared in a host of TV shows since the 1990s, including ''Reno 911,'' ''Dawson's Creek'' and ''Men Behaving Badly,'' and he has also written sketch material while performing on the MTV comedy series ''The State.''</p>
        <p>Like many other writers tackling their first major project, he decided to write about what he knew.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Family ties to Long Island’s faded shellfishing industry helped Ken Marino develop his first feature-length screenplay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN writing his first feature-length script, the screenplay for the film ''Diggers,'' Ken Marino naturally turned to a familiar source of inspiration: his Long Island roots. The actor has appeared in a host of TV shows since the 1990s, including ''Reno 911,'' ''Dawson's Creek'' and ''Men Behaving Badly,'' and he has also written sketch material while performing on the MTV comedy series ''The State.''</p>
        <p>Like many other writers tackling their first major project, he decided to write about what he knew.</p>
        <p>''I just wanted to write something that I remember fondly as a child, a time and a place that I remember fondly,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That time and place were the mid-1970s in Moriches, a hamlet in the Town of Brookhaven on Long Island's South Shore. Mr. Marino lived there until the fourth grade, when his family moved to West Islip, where he stayed until he began studying drama at New York University.</p>
        <p>In Moriches, his father made his living as a clam digger. Mr. Marino, 38 and now living in Los Angeles, used this setting for a serio-comic story about four clam-digger friends grappling with a time of change when their livelihood is disappearing. The movie is scheduled to be released by Magnolia Pictures on April 27.</p>
        <p>''Toward the end of the '70s, the beginning of the '80s, they'd say you could walk across the bay on all the clam boats,'' Mr. Marino said, ''but as time went on and the beds got depleted, nobody could make a living anymore.''</p>
        <p>Among the factors contributing to the problem, said Betty Arink, director of the Long Island Maritime Museum in West Sayville, were pollution, overharvesting and the emergence of large dredge-boat companies that leased parts of Moriches Bay and crowded out independent operators.</p>
        <p>The film based on Mr. Marino's screenplay is a mix of reminiscence and fiction, combining details from his childhood with characters based loosely on people he has known since leaving Long Island. The clam diggers do not seem to have a great deal in common other than their occupation and a shared background in the community: Paul Rudd plays a restless young man with artistic inclinations; Ron Eldard portrays a good-natured womanizer; and Josh Hamilton is a pot-smoking misfit.</p>
        <p>Each of the men responds to the time of transition on Long Island in his own way. The character played by Mr. Marino is a hot-tempered family man named Lozo who, like Mr. Marino's father, eventually leaves clam digging to become a plumber so he can support his family. It's tempting to assume this character is a fictional stand-in for Mr. Marino's real father, but the writer points out that only the superficial details are similar. ''My dad wasn't this screaming maniac that Lozo is,'' he said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>In a more general sense, though, his family life played a role in his script.</p>
        <p>''The inspiration for this movie was just life growing up and watching my dad and my mom struggle to keep our family comfortable and happy and put food on the table,'' Mr. Marino said. The movie, which he also co-produced, ''is basically a love letter to my parents.''</p>
        <p>Directed by Katherine Dieckmann, the film also features Sarah Paulson of ''Studio 60 on the Sunset Strip,'' Maura Tierney of ''E.R.'' and Lauren Ambrose of ''Six Feet Under.''</p>
        <p>Summoning his fond memories of his Moriches years, Mr. Marino remembers the area as a ''natural kind of playground'' where he could go exploring along the creek behind his parents' house and ''go out on the boat at night and shine flashlights in the water and scoop up crabs that were swimming on the top of the water.''</p>
        <p>Evidence of how much the area has changed could be found when trying to find locations for the film, he said.</p>
        <p>While settings by the bay in Moriches could still pass for scenes from Mr. Marino's childhood, footage of homes and the surrounding town had to be filmed elsewhere, in parts of Staten Island ''that seemed to be kind of stuck in time,'' as Mr. Marino put it. In contrast, said the film's co-producer, Jon Stern, who scouted locations for the movie, ''There's been more development in Moriches, both in housing and businesses, that would have made it difficult to make it seem like 1976.''</p>
        <p>In what Mr. Marino described as a reflection of his own decision to leave the South Shore, the character played by Mr. Rudd eventually leaves his hometown to pursue creative ambitions, but not, Mr. Marino emphasized, because he disapproves of the community.</p>
        <p>''I never wanted to make the town or the people in it seem like something he has to get away from,'' he said. ''They're good people and they have important points of view. It's just that he has to explore a world that he clearly needs to see.''</p>
        <p>Arts and Entertainment</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
