<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Night Train to Bucharest</title>
    <meta content="Schillinger3.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/review/Schillinger3.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840245"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Appelfeld, Aharon</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">All Whom I Have Loved (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Night Train to Bucharest</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Night Train to Bucharest</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIESL SCHILLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schillinger, Leslie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All Whom I Have Loved</p>
        <p>By Aharon Appelfeld.</p>
        <p>Translated by Aloma Halter.</p>
        <p>246 pp. Schocken Books. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The family drama of Aharon Appelfeld’s young protagonist is about to be subsumed in the Holocaust.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All Whom I Have Loved</p>
        <p>By Aharon Appelfeld.</p>
        <p>Translated by Aloma Halter.</p>
        <p>246 pp. Schocken Books. $23.</p>
        <p>LITERATURE is fond of the wise child. But what of the not-so-wise child, the ordinary boy who doesn't project greatness from the schoolyard and isn't the hero of the nursery? What if he's asthmatic and antisocial and throws a kicking, screaming temper tantrum when his mother goes to work? Can such a child be ennobled by the passage of time, his struggles granted retroactive gravitas and his childish confusions rearticulated with adult clarity? If the child grows up to be a wise man with a novelistic bent, perhaps. But there's no guarantee: not every unhappy child is a David Copperfield.</p>
        <p>In his new novel, ''All Whom I Have Loved,'' the Israeli writer Aharon Appelfeld tells the story of Paul Rosenfeld, a 9-year-old Jewish boy in Czernowitz, Romania (now Chernovtsy, Ukraine), whose family drama overshadows the political conflict building around him. His parents have divorced, and his mother has married a ''goy,'' a gym teacher named André -- a ''blond thug'' whom Paul hates -- and converted to Christianity. Out of jealousy, Paul has chosen to live with his father, Arthur, a self-centered, hot-tempered, alcoholic artist.</p>
        <p>In Czernowitz, on the eve of World War II, Arthur takes his young son to a tavern before they board the train to Bucharest, where a rich art patron has promised them shelter. Rowdy with drink, Arthur rails against the small-mindedness of Czernowitz, praises Bucharest and picks a fight with an acquaintance as his little boy looks on. ''Jews have no respect for their city, for their birthplace,'' the acquaintance argues. ''They're ready to go anywhere that will offer them more. A birthplace isn't a shop where you go in, buy something and leave!'' ''I'm leaving it gladly,'' Arthur shouts, ''and you, too.'' ''Now you know why Jews are hated,'' the man replies -- and Arthur hits him in the face, setting off a brawl.</p>
        <p>For the reader, who knows that this birthplace is soon to be overtaken by history and its Jewish population dispersed, murdered or sent to concentration camps, such an exchange has unusual force. But that grim future doesn't lie within the span of Appelfeld's book, and Paul is no prophet. He's just a child, a victim not of the Wehrmacht but of the flawed decisions of the adults he loves best. ''Father's face was covered in blood,'' Paul notices after the fight in the tavern. He doesn't judge; he simply records the scene, as if to say, ''This is what may happen in a tavern.'' His father offers no explanation. ''If you understand, you understand,'' he has told his son. ''Explanations are useless.''</p>
        <p>Appelfeld uses faith to add mystery to what would otherwise be a straightforward account of one boy's miserable childhood. Paul's father and mother, nonpracticing Jews, are both orphans, people who lack the habit of religion or family. The boy's father believes in God but is hostile to humanity. His mother, secular to the core, is friendly to strangers but hostile to belief. ''There is no life after death. We have to get this fact into our heads,'' she tells Paul. ''Believing in God is foolish.''</p>
        <p>Paul's mother recoils from pious men (''Those people darken the world with their primitive rituals'') yet Paul is nourished by the piety of his peasant nanny, Halina, a Christian who warns him that the bearded Jews in the next-door synagogue are dishonest thieves. Yet Halina is also moved to tears when she witnesses their reverent celebration of Yom Kippur. ''These Jews always amaze me,'' she says, and lights a lantern.</p>
        <p>Appelfeld threads his narrative with many sonorous, ingenuous lessons, like blunt precepts cross-stitched on a child's sampler. And yet we have the unavoidable impression that Paul's crisis is more Oedipal than scriptural. A formerly cosseted child who relishes simple pleasures like pies, cakes and halvah (which the book's translator, Aloma Halter, frequently describes with the sickly adjective ''tasty''), Paul is unmoored by his parents' divorce. He whips himself into a fury when his mother falls in love with André. ''Repulsed'' by her disloyalty, he rages, ''I had nothing but scorn for her, and I swore to myself that as soon as I grew up I would not see her face anymore.''</p>
        <p>Neglected by his father, Paul wanders Czernowitz and talks about God with his father's landlord, a Ruthenian peasant who tells him that ''the Jews no longer know who they are. ... They've forgotten that they're the sons of kings'' -- and that Paul himself is a ''little prince.'' This is all too deep for the boy, who replies, in perplexity, ''I'm only 9 years old.'' It's no crime that Paul isn't shrewder or more sophisticated, but Appelfeld blurs the boy's outline by swaddling him in homilies. Is Paul a troubled child or a signboard for interfaith doctrine? Every preacher knows that kids say the darndest things, but how much meaning can be ascribed to their epiphanies?</p>
        <p>In his unforgettable first novel, ''Wartime Lies,'' published in 1991, Louis Begley also chose an East European Jewish child as his protagonist. Striking in its historical and personal detail, its lack of sentimentality and its beautiful language, the book tells the story of Maciek and his aunt Tania -- Polish Jews who posed as an Aryan son and mother to elude Nazis and informers in wartime Poland. Maciek's experiences were inspired by Begley's own history; he and his mother survived the war by disguising themselves as Aryans. Without putting words in Maciek's mouth that would have been beyond the boy's intelligence or beneath his dignity (''I could not have borne to have the little boy address his father as 'Daddy,' '' Begley told an interviewer), the grown author brought decades of reflection to bear on Maciek's story.</p>
        <p>Like Maciek, the character of Paul Rosenberg has been created by a mature author whose own thoughts and images inform his portrait. But because Appelfeld relays his story in Paul's immature voice and with his stunted understanding, the book suffers from Paul's limitations. How can the reader analyze Paul's feelings and religious leanings when Paul can't do this and the author won't?</p>
        <p>Appelfeld might say that this isn't his concern; poetic in his instincts, he has an artfully spare writing style, pregnant in its imagery, intentionally coy in its resonance. His novels are set largely in the haunted pre-Holocaust era, skirting the catastrophe that defined the last century. In 2004, after the publication of his affecting memoir, ''The Story of a Life,'' Appelfeld told an interviewer he rejected the idea that he should or could write about collective misfortune rather than individual memory, and explained that the characters in his novels are ''a kind of projection of myself.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, Appelfeld shares significant biographical overlap with his protagonist. Like Paul, he was born in Czernowitz, though it was in 1932, and German was also his mother tongue. Here, however, their histories diverge. Appelfeld's mother was killed when the Nazis arrived, and the boy and his father were sent to a concentration camp, where they were separated. In 1946, Appelfeld arrived in Israel, alone. He adopted a new language, Hebrew, and that is the language of his many books.</p>
        <p>loma Halter has translated several of Appelfeld's works, including ''The Story of a Life,'' the late fruit of a long life. In ''All Whom I Have Loved'' she has the difficult task of translating intentionally unripe language -- the thoughts of a child -- for adult readers. Begley has described the trickiness of such an endeavor. In ''Wartime Lies,'' he explained, it enforces the ''simplicity of the narrative style.'' Also, he said, as he was writing, he imagined the boy's words in his own native tongue -- Polish. Translating them into another language (in his case, English) imposed a ''certain chastity of expression.''</p>
        <p>In ''All Whom I Have Loved,'' Halter faithfully conveys this chastity in Paul's words. It feels like a translation at a remove: a rendering of an author's own translation of words and thoughts it pains him to remember, in a language he no longer speaks. ''My childhood was cut off when I was 8 1/2,'' Appelfeld has said. ''All Whom I Have Loved'' ends before the tragedies that shaped the author's life began. Would Paul have grown up to be as wise as the man who tells his story today? It's hard to know. The child is doubly orphaned; his story ends without leaving a sense of the adult he might become.</p>
        <p>Liesl Schillinger is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Liesl Schillinger is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
