<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Director, and Mother, Confronts Infanticide</title>
    <meta content="15durb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/movies/15durb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durbin, Karen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brougher, Hilary</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Stephanie Daley (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Brougher, Hilary</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tamblyn, Amber</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Stephanie Daley (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1D7153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1234" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Director, and Mother, Confronts Infanticide</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Director, and Mother, Confronts Infanticide</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Karen Durbin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durbin, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karen Durbin interviews director Hilary Brougher about her new film Stephanie Daley; film deals with whether or not teenager killed her newborn child; controversial subject of film and influence of Brougher's children discussed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1997 Hilary Brougher made her writing and directing debut with a stylish science fiction noir, ''The Sticky Fingers of Time.'' In her new movie, ''Stephanie Daley,'' Ms. Brougher flirts with genre again, this time the murder mystery. Opening Friday, ''Stephanie Daley'' is also a dual character study, a snapshot of the current social climate and a piercing look at the way circumstances push people into places they shouldn't have to go. But almost from the first moments -- ski-booted feet trudging through snow, then faltering as blood seeps into the bootprints -- what drives the narrative is a single question: What has she done?</p>
        <p>She is Stephanie Daley (Amber Tamblyn), a shy, secretly pregnant teenager who goes into labor on a school ski trip and is accused of killing her premature baby. Shooting fast over 25 days in the rural landscapes of upstate New York where she grew up, Ms. Brougher layers the action around a series of tense meetings between Stephanie and Lydie Crane (Tilda Swinton), a pregnant forensic psychologist charged with discovering if the girl is lying in saying that the infant was stillborn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hilary Brougher, director of “Stephanie Daley,” talks with Karen Durbin about the hurdles and high points of making an award-winning movie with a hot-button subject.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1997 Hilary Brougher made her writing and directing debut with a stylish science fiction noir, ''The Sticky Fingers of Time.'' In her new movie, ''Stephanie Daley,'' Ms. Brougher flirts with genre again, this time the murder mystery. Opening Friday, ''Stephanie Daley'' is also a dual character study, a snapshot of the current social climate and a piercing look at the way circumstances push people into places they shouldn't have to go. But almost from the first moments -- ski-booted feet trudging through snow, then faltering as blood seeps into the bootprints -- what drives the narrative is a single question: What has she done?</p>
        <p>She is Stephanie Daley (Amber Tamblyn), a shy, secretly pregnant teenager who goes into labor on a school ski trip and is accused of killing her premature baby. Shooting fast over 25 days in the rural landscapes of upstate New York where she grew up, Ms. Brougher layers the action around a series of tense meetings between Stephanie and Lydie Crane (Tilda Swinton), a pregnant forensic psychologist charged with discovering if the girl is lying in saying that the infant was stillborn.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brougher, a sunny woman with two new movies in the works, explains the long gap between her first and second with a grin and the words ''5-year-old twins.'' One recent afternoon she talked to Karen Durbin about the hurdles and high points of making a multiple-award-winning movie whose hot-button subject made distributors hesitate for more than a year.</p>
        <p>Q. The film has an austere style you don't expect with that content. At times it almost feels black and white.</p>
        <p>A. Upstate winters almost are black and white. I wanted the simplicity of that landscape and, even in the interior scenes, a sense of nature beyond the windows. We were trying to refrain from sentimentality, button-pushing -- to let viewers bring their own associations to the story.</p>
        <p>Q. That includes the performances?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. Tilda brings a lot of intelligence to whatever she plays; you can see her thinking on screen. She's a very reserved actress, and yet she's vibrant. Lydie has her own secrets, but Tilda plays her as a woman who's going to make it all work. Amber is also strong. She doesn't play Stephanie like a victim; she's a girl who's still trying to get through the day.</p>
        <p>Q. Tilda Swinton is one of Britain's most admired actors, and in ''Joan of Arcadia'' Amber Tamblyn was wholly convincing as a high school girl to whom God appeared on a weekly basis. How did they come on board?</p>
        <p>A. It was kind of wonderful. Financing wasn't so easy, but Tilda, my first choice for Lydie, just responded to the material. She was passing through New York, so we had coffee in a diner in the Village and talked about our kids. She has twins too. Afterwards I thought I should have talked about the script in a more structured way. But actually it was perfect because it's how we made the movie -- very conversational, people bringing their process and their lives to it, and not a lot of rehearsal. It had a really nice, intimate feel. Amber and Tilda were very familial on set. They're both excruciatingly funny, and they'd be going back and forth, and then they'd stop and do this dark material on a dime. That gave us all the energy to access the dark stuff.</p>
        <p>Q. Sounds great. How did you get Amber Tamblyn?</p>
        <p>A. Our casting directors urged me to look at her show, so I watched it and flew out to L.A. for breakfast with her. What convinced me immediately about Amber, one, I looked at her and thought, O.K., you can play a 16-year-old without breaking out any kind of filters, and two, she's an incredibly forthright, down-to-earth person. I felt that here was someone who's not going to be afraid to do anything. Wow. I remember telling my producers, I'm really worried -- this is much too easy. It took years to develop the script and find the right producers, but when it started to move, there was tremendous momentum.</p>
        <p>Q. Why did it take so long?</p>
        <p>A. Well, first there was another script I worked on for a couple of years that finally just got written into the ground. And then, unexpectedly but happily, I got pregnant. Kids bring new ideas and energy into your life, and I feel there's a connection between the twins and the movie. I wrote the script before I had them, took the three-year break, and when it came time to direct it, I was really fresh. Even though it's a script that deals with fear, I wasn't fearful. I was overjoyed that my kids were here, and I made it when they were 3 1/2, so I could leave them with their father and they'd be fine with that.</p>
        <p>Q. Who's their father?</p>
        <p>A. Ethan Mass. He's a director of photography. He shot ''Sticky Fingers.'' But he didn't shoot this movie. He took care of the kids. He does a lot of television.</p>
        <p>Q. I want to ask you about filming a particularly daring scene -- --</p>
        <p>A. You mean the birth scene?</p>
        <p>Q. Yes, in the stall in the ladies' room, with other girls trekking in and out obliviously. It's one of those moments in a movie when you're watching the work, the way it comes together, and you think: This is why they do it. This is why I'm here.</p>
        <p>A. That's how I felt when we were filming it. And I have to hand it to Amber, I don't know how she prepared for that. Amber is someone who shows up ready, and you ask for variations and she's happy to play. She's a director's dream.</p>
        <p>Q. With a TV series you work really fast. It must be good training.</p>
        <p>A. She has an incredible amount of craft and the soul of a poet. The scene was late in our schedule, and there was a lot of trust built up. We did it in four hand-held shots. One of those shots was about 12 minutes long; it was kind of exploratory. We had a basic idea of the actions we were going to go through. But she came in and did this, and I remember thinking, there's the movie. Now this movie makes sense; now this character makes sense. Of course it always had, but everyone watching -- it was completely hushed. They were in the other room watching the monitor. Usually you hear people in there doing things, getting information, paper towels, whatever. But there was dead silence.</p>
        <p>People have fainted during that scene at festival screenings. I think the count is up to four. Which always, brrrr, makes me feel kind of terrible. But then I remember that we bring ourselves to this scene. Because everybody, whether they've had a baby or not, has experienced something very painful, and beyond a door life goes on, and you can't reach across to it, and you make yourself go silent and dissociate from that pain. Men get it, and women get it. That's something we can do: We can feel extreme pain and stand it. That's that moment, and we all have those moments in our lives.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
