<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Entertainment Complex Plans to Add Security</title>
    <meta content="15weweekWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840435"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Rochelle (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Roc City (New Rochelle, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bransom, Noam (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E0DE133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="528" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Entertainment Complex Plans to Add Security</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Noam Bransom of New Rochelle, NY, outlines security measures that will be instituted in wake of melee involving hundreds of youths that started at New Roc City entertainment center; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Noam Bransom of New Rochelle outlined the steps last week that city officials and representatives of New Roc City Associates were taking in response to the melee that started Sunday at the New Roc City entertainment center.Hundreds of youths, many from New York City, had clashed with the police on city streets after being ejected from New Roc, and more than 200 police officers, including some from other Westchester departments, were called in. At least seven youths were arrested.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bramson, describing the violent clash as an ''anomaly,'' said the city would accelerate the start of its summer security and youth outreach programs, increase the overall police presence in downtown, and improve communication with Metro-North, so that local police officials would be informed whenever a large group boards a train at another location with New Rochelle as its destination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Noam Bransom of New Rochelle outlined the steps last week that city officials and representatives of New Roc City Associates were taking in response to the melee that started Sunday at the New Roc City entertainment center.Hundreds of youths, many from New York City, had clashed with the police on city streets after being ejected from New Roc, and more than 200 police officers, including some from other Westchester departments, were called in. At least seven youths were arrested.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bramson, describing the violent clash as an ''anomaly,'' said the city would accelerate the start of its summer security and youth outreach programs, increase the overall police presence in downtown, and improve communication with Metro-North, so that local police officials would be informed whenever a large group boards a train at another location with New Rochelle as its destination.</p>
        <p>''This will become a matter of standard, ongoing operating procedure,'' Mr. Bramson said in a statement. Joseph V. Apicella, senior vice president of Cappelli Enterprises, which operates New Roc City, said the police presence at the entertainment center would be increased by hiring off-duty uniformed officers to provide security.</p>
        <p>According to the mayor's statement, New Roc will hire up to 10 officers at peak hours, starting this weekend. This would be in addition to the two police officers who have long been stationed at the New Roc police facility.</p>
        <p>''You will not be able to frequent New Roc City without coming upon a uniformed police officer,'' Mr. Apicella said, adding that the complex, which features an arcade, theaters, restaurants and activities like rock climbing and miniature golf, already has a mini police precinct as well as 200 closed circuit cameras monitoring the parking garage, corridors and businesses within the complex.</p>
        <p>Mr. Apicella also said the center was prepared to change its policies and procedures. As specified in the mayor's statement, people under the age of 18 would not be permitted to enter the New Street Atrium, including the New Roc funhouse, after 6 p.m. on weekends and holidays without a parent or guardian. Also, in an effort to discourage loitering, those under age 18 would need to purchase a $10 card to enter the entertainment center's Funhouse, Ice Arena or Speedway.</p>
        <p>Mayor Bramson also said that there was discussion before last Sunday about ''transitioning New Roc into a primarily retail facility.'' He said the area around the complex was undergoing major changes, with high-profile residential buildings under construction.</p>
        <p>''New Roc Associates understands the importance of accomplishing this objective and will work with us to achieve it, '' Mr. Bramson said.</p>
        <p>Though some residents said the rampage last weekend was something they had been predicting for years, Mr. Bramson and representatives of the center said it was the first major incident at the center in nine years of operation.</p>
        <p>''This was a perfect storm of anomalous events,'' Mr. Bramson said, noting that officials believed that the youths came to the center because it was one of the few entertainment venues open on Easter.</p>
        <p>''I take Sunday's event very seriously,'' Mr. Bramson said, ''as do we all, but my confidence in New Rochelle has never been stronger.''</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
