<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spotlight: N.B.A.; OFF THE DRIBBLE</title>
    <meta content="15nbarail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spotlight: N.B.A.; OFF THE DRIBBLE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED BIERMAN and BENJAMIN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Benjamin; Bierman, Fred</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Less Is More</p>
        <p>During Kobe Bryant's four-game streak of scoring 50 or more points, it seemed that he was proving the ''Wall Street'' antihero Gordon Gekko's theory that greed is good. The Lakers won all four games on the heels of a seven-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Since then, the Lakers have lost both of the games in which Bryant scored 50 or more, including 50 in a loss to the Clippers on Thursday. Outside the streak, they are 2-3 when he reaches 50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Less Is More</p>
        <p>During Kobe Bryant's four-game streak of scoring 50 or more points, it seemed that he was proving the ''Wall Street'' antihero Gordon Gekko's theory that greed is good. The Lakers won all four games on the heels of a seven-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Since then, the Lakers have lost both of the games in which Bryant scored 50 or more, including 50 in a loss to the Clippers on Thursday. Outside the streak, they are 2-3 when he reaches 50.</p>
        <p>The red-hot Clippers and the Warriors have a chance to take the No. 7 seed from the Lakers in the Western Conference.</p>
        <p>Draftology</p>
        <p>The race is on for the worst record in the N.B.A., and no team has as much to gain by losing as the Atlanta Hawks.</p>
        <p>Because of the sign-and-trade deal that sent Joe Johnson to Atlanta, the Phoenix Suns will get the Hawks' draft pick if it is lower than a top-three selection.</p>
        <p>If the season had ended before last night's games, the Hawks (29-50) -- who are playing without their two best offensive players, the injured Johnson and the suspended Josh Smith -- would have ended up with the fourth-worst record.</p>
        <p>The Memphis Grizzlies (19-60) would have finished with the worst record, followed by the Boston Celtics (23-56) and the Milwaukee Bucks (27-52).</p>
        <p>The teams with the worst records will have a better chance of landing the highly regarded scorer Kevin Durant, who is leaving Texas for the N.B.A., or a franchise center in Greg Oden, should he decide to leave Ohio State.</p>
        <p>Super-Sized</p>
        <p>On March 28, Warriors guard Baron Davis, above, spent an afternoon manning the drive-thru of a McDonald's in Oakland, Calif., for a feature that TNT showed during the next day's Warriors-Suns game.</p>
        <p>The video has surfaced on the Internet and can be found on YouTube.com. After butchering many of the motorists' orders, Davis gives everyone their food and tickets to the game.</p>
        <p>When one woman asks Davis what he is doing back there, he responds: ''They cut me from the team. I got to make a living somehow.'' Davis scored 21 points and had 12 assists the next day as the Warriors defeated the Suns, 124-119.</p>
        <p>FRED BIERMAN and BENJAMIN HOFFMAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
