<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Philadelphia Struggles to Quell An Epidemic of Gun Violence</title>
    <meta content="15philadelphia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/us/15philadelphia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hurdle, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2DC103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Philadelphia Struggles to Quell An Epidemic of Gun Violence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Philadelphia Struggles to Quell an Epidemic of Gun Violence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON HURDLE; Dan Barry's column, ''This Land,'' will resume next week.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hurdle, Jon</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Epidemic of gun violence in Philadelphia has left police struggling to preserve public safety and government officials renewing efforts to tighten state's gun control laws; number of homicides rose 22 percent from 2002 to 2006; combination of poverty, youth culture that increasingly settles minor disputes through violence and easy availability of guns all contribute to problem; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a hospital emergency room, a young man winces as doctors try to determine how badly he has been injured.</p>
        <p>His name is Karim Williams, he is 27, and he is this city's latest shooting victim. He says he was hit around 12:30 a.m. by a shot fired while he was walking from his girlfriend's car into a bar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rise in violence is evident at the University of Pennsylvania hospital, whose trauma unit saw a 15 percent increase in gunshot victims in 2006.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a hospital emergency room, a young man winces as doctors try to determine how badly he has been injured.</p>
        <p>His name is Karim Williams, he is 27, and he is this city's latest shooting victim. He says he was hit around 12:30 a.m. by a shot fired while he was walking from his girlfriend's car into a bar.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams was fortunate. The bullet went through his leg without hitting bone or major blood vessels, and after a shot of morphine and a few hours' observation, he will be discharged from the Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania back into the West Philadelphia night.</p>
        <p>In some ways, Mr. Williams is a typical patient at the trauma unit: young, mildly intoxicated and apparently with no idea why he was shot. What makes his case less common, doctors here say, is that he is neither seriously injured nor dead, since Philadelphia is in the midst of an epidemic of gun violence that has left the police struggling to preserve public safety and government officials renewing efforts to tighten the state's gun control laws.</p>
        <p>Last year, there were 406 homicides in Philadelphia, most of them by gunshot, the highest number in nine years, according to the Police Department. From 2004 to 2006, the number of homicides in the city rose 22 percent, more than twice as much as the aggregate increase recorded by 56 cities surveyed by the Police Executive Research Forum, a national law enforcement group.</p>
        <p>This year, the pace of the killings has worsened; as of Friday the death toll stood at 110, or 16 percent higher than at the same time last year. By comparison, in New York City, with six times the population, there were 102 homicides from Jan. 1 to April 8, a drop of almost 24.4 percent from the same period a year ago. The rise in violence is evident at the University of Pennsylvania hospital, whose trauma unit treated 479 gunshot victims last year, a 15 percent increase over 2005. Some 18 percent of the attacks were fatal, and 16 percent of the victims will suffer permanent disabilities, like paralysis from head or spinal injuries, amputations, or long-term damage to internal organs.</p>
        <p>Gun violence is becoming so common in some parts of the city that many people are no longer shocked by it, said Dr. Bill Schwab, chief of trauma and surgical critical care at the hospital.</p>
        <p>''Are people becoming numb to violence? The answer is yes,'' Dr. Schwab said. ''It's very common for them to be sitting on their porch and to hear gunshots in the night.''</p>
        <p>What sets Philadelphia apart from other cities, say the police, politicians and academic experts, is the combination of high poverty -- with 25 percent of the population living below the poverty line, the city has the highest rate among the 10 biggest cities, according to census data -- a youth culture that increasingly settles minor disputes through violence and the easy availability of guns.</p>
        <p>Pennsylvania's cities are forbidden by state law from making their own gun laws, and so must conform to the political will of a largely rural state that, according to the National Rifle Association, has around a quarter of a million gun owners.</p>
        <p>With about 85 percent of Philadelphia's homicides involving guns, gun control advocates are urging state lawmakers to limit handgun purchases to one per person per month. The goal is to choke off supply to so-called straw purchasers, who buy multiple guns on behalf of those who cannot legally acquire the guns themselves because they have criminal records.</p>
        <p>Supporters -- including Gov. Edward G. Rendell and Philadelphia's police chief, Sylvester Johnson -- say it would not curtail the right of gun owners to bear arms but would significantly reduce the number of illegal guns on the street.</p>
        <p>But many state lawmakers oppose the plan, which was introduced in February as part of a package of gun control measures, as an attempt to curb the Second Amendment right to bear arms. ''It's a constitutional infringement,'' said State Representative Bryan Cutler, a Republican from Lancaster County, at a recent seminar at Temple University Hospital here on the effects of gun violence.</p>
        <p>A similar measure was defeated in the Legislature last October, the day after a Lancaster County gunman carrying a mostly legal arsenal shot 10 Amish schoolgirls in their classroom, killing five of them.</p>
        <p>For Karim Williams, the explanation for Philadelphia's carnage is a lack of jobs.</p>
        <p>''You've got to have jobs for the people that need them,'' he said from his gurney. ''You have to keep people occupied. Without jobs, all you can do is resort to violence.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams said he recently became a licensed electrician and was looking for work after a past in which he served jail time for crimes including car theft and drug dealing.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Williams hopes to escape the violence of his West Philadelphia neighborhood, it is too late for Richard Johnson. He was killed in a South Philadelphia convenience store in July 2005 when he was 17.</p>
        <p>His mother, Catherine Young, said Richard -- who had won a full academic scholarship to a local university -- and his cousin were shot by a 16-year-old boy who claimed they were blocking the doorway in the store, and came back a short time later with a gun.</p>
        <p>''It's so easy for them to have a gun,'' Ms. Young said. ''Nobody should own a gun except the police.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
