<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Asking for Money Is So Appallingly American, Dahling</title>
    <meta content="15lyall" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/weekinreview/15lyall.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840589"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">England</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DC103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Asking for Money Is So Appallingly American, Dahling</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Asking for Money Is So Appallingly American, Dahling</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>EXETER, England</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE university development officer reviewed his approach. Do not cough dryly into your hand. Do not babble. When you have asked for the money, do not then blurt, ''Oh, sorry, was that too much?''</p>
        <p>But no sooner had he made his nervous pitch to the rich alumnus across the table -- ''We're sort of interested in maybe seeking your support, and I was actually wanting to ask you to consider a gift of £5 million '' -- than Neil Dryback, a professor brought along to help bolster the case, weighed in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Britain, the old alma mater is learning how to tap the shuddering alumni.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE university development officer reviewed his approach. Do not cough dryly into your hand. Do not babble. When you have asked for the money, do not then blurt, ''Oh, sorry, was that too much?''</p>
        <p>But no sooner had he made his nervous pitch to the rich alumnus across the table -- ''We're sort of interested in maybe seeking your support, and I was actually wanting to ask you to consider a gift of £5 million '' -- than Neil Dryback, a professor brought along to help bolster the case, weighed in.</p>
        <p>''You don't need to decide today,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Oops. But luckily, Professor Dryback is an actor and this was a role-playing exercise at a fund-raising seminar here, designed to help British educators learn how to extract money from their alumni. This is not something that comes naturally.</p>
        <p>''It's not quite so easy for a British person -- even if she believes passionately in something -- to just say, 'This is important; give me a large chunk of money for it,' '' said C. Duncan Rice, the principal and vice chancellor of the University of Aberdeen.</p>
        <p>Or, as Shaun Horan, the director of development and external affairs at the University of Reading, said, ''You have to get over the fear that if you ask, they'll scream, and blood will run from their ears.''</p>
        <p>Raising money is a pressing issue. British universities are poor compared to American ones. Harvard's endowment is $28 billion and Yale's is $18 billion; by contrast, Oxford has a $7.1 billion endowment and Cambridge's is about $5.9 billion. In a recent speech announcing the formation of a £200 million (or $396.5 million) matching fund for gifts to universities, Prime Minister Tony Blair said that the average American endowment was 14 times the size of that of a comparable British institution.</p>
        <p>As financing from the government decreases, British universities have begun in the last 10 to 15 years to regard charitable donations as an important potential resource. Still, some schools are further along than others.</p>
        <p>Since Peter Agar took his job as development director at Cambridge five years ago, the development office has expanded to 53 people, from 40. The university is in the middle of its most ambitious fund-raising campaign yet, to raise $1.9 billion by 2012 to commemorate its 800th anniversary. It has for the first time produced expensive brochures that set out its financial needs, and systematically approached all its alumni on a university level (in the past, most fund-raising was done through individual colleges). It spends about $15.8 million a year on fund-raising.</p>
        <p>But even a place like Cambridge has to overcome cultural hurdles in soliciting alumni donations. For one thing, there is no tradition of it. The average alumni participation rate for giving at most British universities is one percent, with the most successful universities, Oxford and Cambridge, at about 11 percent, said Joanna Motion, the vice president for international operations at the Council for Advancement and Support of Education.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the overall alumni participation rate for public and private universities in the United States is about 12.4 percent, according to the Council for Aid to Education. (The figures are higher for non-state institutions. The figure for Princeton last year was 43.1 percent, for Harvard 24 percent, and for Yale 33 percent, the council said).</p>
        <p>Until recently, many alumni here were rarely even approached by their schools.</p>
        <p>''There's a fear of being fund-raised,'' said Tania Jane Rawlinson, director of campaigns and alumni relations at the University of Bristol. ''They think: 'Telethons? How disgusting. How American.'''</p>
        <p>In addition, Britons give less money to charity than Americans -- .7 percent of the gross domestic product as compared to 1.8 percent, according to figures compiled by the London School of Economics in 2002 -- and give less of it to education, preferring causes like medical research and abandoned animals.</p>
        <p>American fund-raisers are helped, too, by the ineffable thing that is school spirit.</p>
        <p>Not so in Britain, where superiority is supposed to speak for itself and displaying unironic school pride is an embarrassing gaffe, akin to boasting about your I.Q. or your salary (the exception is the annual Oxford-Cambridge boat race, where emotional displays are acceptable, particularly if alcohol is involved).</p>
        <p>Indeed, the joke at Oxford is that the only students who wear school sweatshirts are the Rhodes scholars.</p>
        <p>Nor do British universities subscribe to the nostalgic ''best years of our lives'' mentality, encouraged in America through football games and lavish reunions in which alumni are wined and wooed.</p>
        <p>This all means that Britain has had a lot of catching up to do. The University of Bristol, for instance, did not even establish a database of alumni until the early 1990s, and for decades had little or no contact with most of its graduates.</p>
        <p>While it is difficult ''to ring someone up who's 54 years old and say, 'You haven't heard from the university for 30 years; how about giving some money now?''' said Eric Thomas, the vice chancellor, Bristol began doing just that three years ago. It now has up-to-date information on some 70 percent of its alumni, and has been working to engage them again with the life of the school; its annual giving rate is 4 percent.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rawlinson, the campaign's director, is American, and her foreignness is a plus, Mr. Thomas said, because she lacks the social antennae that can turn a Briton-to-Briton fund-raising appeal into a pas de deux of mortified evasion.</p>
        <p>''Americans are coming from left field completely,'' Mr. Thomas said. ''Because those nuances don't come into play with her, she's able to ask in a clearer way.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rawlinson, as it happened, was one of the three people conducting the seminar at Exeter, whose topic was how to identify and cultivate major potential donors. With the help of actors playing Professor Dryback and Paul Andrew, a rich fictional alumnus who had not heard from his university in 20 years, the participants were led from the initial approach to the climactic appeal.</p>
        <p>Some of the lessons were straight out of Fund-Raising 101.</p>
        <p>If you don't ask, no one will give you any money. Believe in the product. Be sure to tell prospective donors about new tax regulations that make giving more attractive financially. When met with rejection, don't apologize and scurry away, never to return.</p>
        <p>''No doesn't always mean no,'' said Mr. Horan, of Reading University. ''Sometimes it means not yet.''</p>
        <p>Don't beat around the bush. Always carry fund-raising forms and stamped, self-addressed envelopes. After you ask for money, let the request hang in the air, even as tension builds and every fiber of your upbringing cries out for you to break the silence.</p>
        <p>But in a nation where it is still considered rude to talk about money and ruder still to ask for it, the first step is often the most excruciating.</p>
        <p>''I haven't done it yet,'' said Martin Thornton, the lone development officer at the University of Wales at Swansea. ''I'm here to learn how to do it. I am looking forward to the receiving of money.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Karl Donert, a geography professor who doubles as the director of development at Liverpool Hope University, said the school was embarking on its most ambitious fund-raising project yet: a campaign to raise nearly $30 million for three new buildings.</p>
        <p>Some of that will naturally have to be raised by Mr. Donert, a prospect that does not fill him with delight.</p>
        <p>''Face-to-face asking is not something I would have done normally, but I'm trying to do it,'' he said. ''I don't mind asking for money. It's the thought of rejection that's hard.''</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
