<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hendrick Drivers Have Been Able to Hog the Road: Victory Lane</title>
    <meta content="15hendrick" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/othersports/15hendrick.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hendrick, Rick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Jimmie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Jeff</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Busch, Kyle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hendrick Drivers Have Been Able to Hog the Road: Victory Lane</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hendrick Drivers Have Been Able to Hog the Road: Victory Lane</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN DALEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Daley, Ken</byline>
      <dateline>FORT WORTH, April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The racing league that unveiled the Car of Tomorrow is at the same time revisiting a vestige of the good old days. Such is the state of Nascar as the Nextel Cup series resumes after its holiday hiatus.</p>
        <p>The Car of Tomorrow, being phased in over 16 races this season, is not being used in Sunday's Samsung 500 at Texas Motor Speedway. But that may not matter to the drivers and crews of Hendrick Motorsports, the powerhouse team threatening a streak of dominance unseen since Richard Petty ruled stock-car racing's premier circuit 36 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With four drivers in Sunday’s Samsung 500, Hendrick Motorsports can become the first team to win five consecutive races since 1971.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The racing league that unveiled the Car of Tomorrow is at the same time revisiting a vestige of the good old days. Such is the state of Nascar as the Nextel Cup series resumes after its holiday hiatus.</p>
        <p>The Car of Tomorrow, being phased in over 16 races this season, is not being used in Sunday's Samsung 500 at Texas Motor Speedway. But that may not matter to the drivers and crews of Hendrick Motorsports, the powerhouse team threatening a streak of dominance unseen since Richard Petty ruled stock-car racing's premier circuit 36 years ago.</p>
        <p>The first dozen Cup races at Texas Motor Speedway produced 12 different winners, and the Hendrick drivers Jimmie Johnson, Jeff Gordon, Kyle Busch and Casey Mears were not among them.</p>
        <p>But if any of the four wins Sunday, Hendrick would become the first team to win five consecutive races since Petty accomplished the feat from July 14 to Aug. 1, 1971. Such a streak has happened only five times in Nascar history.</p>
        <p>''They're a great organization and they run up front,'' said Kasey Kahne, a driver for Evernham Motorsports. ''They have great drivers, great crews, great crew chiefs; the whole system is really right. It's tough to keep up with those teams.''</p>
        <p>Qualifying was postponed Friday because of inclement weather, so the starting grid for Sunday was set based on points standings. Hendrick drivers will start in three of the first five spots, with Gordon being awarded the pole.</p>
        <p>Multicar teams are the modern norm in Nascar's top division. The extraordinary level of cooperation, cohesiveness and success under the Hendrick umbrella is not.</p>
        <p>''Rick's done a great job of putting together people that are really focused and dedicated,'' Johnson, the defending Cup champion, said of Rick Hendrick, the team owner. ''I'm happy and proud to be a part of it. It's just the way it all flows and works. It's hard to explain it, and I'm not sure we could recreate it. But Rick's worked a lot of years to put this company in this position.''</p>
        <p>Johnson's title defense has taken off with his victories in three of the past four races. He ranks third in the season standings, 60 points out of first, as he returns to the one-and-a-half-mile Texas speedway where he finished second last November.</p>
        <p>Atop the season standings is Gordon, a four-time series champion, who has four top-three finishes through six races. He has placed second three times, including a tense duel to the checkered flag with Johnson two weeks ago in Martinsville, Va.</p>
        <p>''It's good to be frustrated over finishing second,'' Gordon said. ''It's been a while since we've been in that position. Jimmie and I were bumping and banging pretty good at Martinsville, but we were able to laugh about it on the phone shortly after that. Having other teammates that run good only makes all of us stronger.''</p>
        <p>Busch won the first Car of Tomorrow race March 25 at Bristol, Tenn., and is fifth in the season standings. Only Mears, a newcomer to the Hendrick operation this season, has struggled, with one top-10 finish through six races. He will start 33rd in Sunday's field.</p>
        <p>The Hendrick drivers and crew chiefs are innately competitive, but appreciate the teamwork and cooperation they receive. They huddle each week before and after practice to share performance data gleaned from their various approaches to aerodynamic packages and chassis setups.</p>
        <p>''I can't tell you exactly what we've hit on this year,'' Gordon said. ''All I know is that the team and the guys building the cars have done a fantastic job just improving a little bit in all these different areas. The cars have been so much more comfortable to drive. And that's when the speed comes, when that comfort is there.''</p>
        <p>Busch, who two weeks before his 22nd birthday has four career victories, said competition between the Hendrick teams was fierce but friendly.</p>
        <p>''You're going to have complications between teams, but you just hope none of them ever get too overheated,'' he said. ''We tend to try to work as well as we can with each other, develop things together and just make it where we know we can be competitive each and every week.''</p>
        <p>Such an approach is not unique, of course.</p>
        <p>''Sharing information is only as good as the information is to share,'' said Matt Kenseth, one of Roush Racing's five drivers. ''If we're all running 15th and we're sharing information, great, we've all got 15th-place information. You still have to be figuring stuff out and making it better.''</p>
        <p>So far, the Hendrick teams have done just that, and now they find themselves on the verge of making some history.</p>
        <p>''It would be a great thing to accomplish, but we're not sitting back, saying, 'We've got to win five to keep the streak alive,' '' Johnson said. ''We're all coming in here with our agendas to run well and do well in the points. It's really business as usual, and if we're in a position to do it, we'll celebrate in victory lane.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
