<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Francine Whitney, Fernando Banhara</title>
    <meta content="15FWHITNEY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/fashion/weddings/15FWHITNEY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitney, Francine Douwes</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banhara, Fernando Soares</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0D9133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="472" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Francine Whitney, Fernando Banhara</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Francine Whitney, Fernando Banhara</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Francine Douwes Whitney and Fernando Soares Banhara were married yesterday at Beckwith Pointe, a club in New Rochelle, N.Y. The Rev. Thomas F. Pike, an Episcopal priest, officiated.</p>
        <p>The bride, 47, is keeping her name. She is the director of digital media at Wings WorldQuest in Manhattan, a nonprofit organization that promotes the work of female explorers. She graduated from Drexel and received a master's degree in screenwriting and directing from Columbia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Francine Douwes Whitney and Fernando Soares Banhara were married yesterday at Beckwith Pointe, a club in New Rochelle, N.Y. The Rev. Thomas F. Pike, an Episcopal priest, officiated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Francine Douwes Whitney and Fernando Soares Banhara were married yesterday at Beckwith Pointe, a club in New Rochelle, N.Y. The Rev. Thomas F. Pike, an Episcopal priest, officiated.</p>
        <p>The bride, 47, is keeping her name. She is the director of digital media at Wings WorldQuest in Manhattan, a nonprofit organization that promotes the work of female explorers. She graduated from Drexel and received a master's degree in screenwriting and directing from Columbia.</p>
        <p>The bride, a widow, was married to Gifford Whitney, a great-grandson of Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney, the founder of the Whitney Museum of American Art. She is a daughter of Françoise W. Douwes of Philadelphia and the late Dr. Karel Douwes. Her father was a general surgeon at Episcopal Hospital in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 40, is an independent painter and restorer of boats working at Consolidated Yachts in the Bronx. He graduated from Colégio Municipal in São Paulo, Brazil.</p>
        <p>He is the son of Marly Parreira Soares Banhara of Poços de Caldas, Brazil, and the late Fernando R. Banhara. His mother retired as a school administrator in Poços de Caldas. His father owned Transmop, a freight-trucking company in São Paulo.</p>
        <p>The couple met in March 2005, when Ms. Whitney was settling the estate of her first husband, who had died the previous November. Ms. Whitney encountered Mr. Banhara at Consolidated Yachts, a marina and boatyard in the City Island section of the Bronx, in which her late husband had had a financial interest and had kept a number of boats and dirt bikes.</p>
        <p>By July, the couple became friends when Mr. Banhara began teaching Ms. Whitney basic boating skills so that she could take her son Harry Payne Whitney III out on Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>''I had known Harry since he was about 6 years old,'' Mr. Banhara said. ''I could see that Francine was now struggling to do the things that Harry once did with his father, so I began to help whenever I could, and we began to get to know each other.''</p>
        <p>In December, when Mr. Banhara invited Ms. Whitney and Harry to his ski house at Hunter Mountain in New York to ride their dirt bikes, the relationship became serious.</p>
        <p>''There was kind of a vibe going on,'' Ms. Whitney recalled. ''I really appreciated the personal time he was taking with Harry, and Harry really liked him. I began realizing that Fernando was a solid person, and that I could count on him -- not for just boating advice, but for friendship.''</p>
        <p>By January 2006 they had begun dating. Ms. Whitney said she did not want to hide that fact from her son, who was 12. ''I turned to Harry and said: 'What do you think of Fernando. What if I dated him?' He just looked at me and said, 'C'mon mom, aren't you already dating him?' ''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
