<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Time, Rate Cuts May Not Work Magic on Stocks</title>
    <meta content="15rate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/business/yourmoney/15rate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5D6133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Time, Rate Cuts May Not Work Magic on Stocks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">This Time, Rate Cuts May Not Work Magic on Stocks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORM ALSTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alster, Norm</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOONER or later, the Federal Reserve will cut interest rates and buoy the stock market. That assumption -- that a rising market will follow a Fed rate cut as surely as night follows day -- is widely held.</p>
        <p>But John P. Hussman, manager of the Hussman Strategic Growth fund, argues that this assumption is wrong. Investors need to look at other factors for a realistic assessment of the state of the stock market, he and several other analysts say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Conditions in the bond market make the current prospects for the stock market worse than these figures suggest, an analyst said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOONER or later, the Federal Reserve will cut interest rates and buoy the stock market. That assumption -- that a rising market will follow a Fed rate cut as surely as night follows day -- is widely held.</p>
        <p>But John P. Hussman, manager of the Hussman Strategic Growth fund, argues that this assumption is wrong. Investors need to look at other factors for a realistic assessment of the state of the stock market, he and several other analysts say.</p>
        <p>''The idea that stocks will do particularly well if the Fed cuts rates is an idea that's not well supported by the data,'' Mr. Hussman said.</p>
        <p>Certainly, Fed rate cuts stimulate the stock market in certain periods -- ''after the economy is already clearly in a recession'' and stock values have already come down, he said. In such cases, ''by the time the Fed eases there's a great deal of room for price-to-earnings multiples to increase, he said.'' When P/E multiples climb, stock prices generally rise.</p>
        <p>But at the moment, stocks are already fairly expensive, Mr. Hussman said. He bases this assessment on the fact that the P/E ratio of the S.&amp; P. 500 index stands at 17 even as corporate earnings have risen to record levels. History shows that when the P/E ratio of the S.&amp; P. 500 is at least 17 -- and when overall corporate earnings have surpassed previous levels -- Fed rate cuts generally do not take the stock market higher. (Mr. Hussman calls the P/E in such times the ''price-to-peak-earnings ratio.'')</p>
        <p>In fact, in periods since 1955 when the P/E of the S.&amp; P. 500 has been 17 or more, stocks, on average, have declined by 2.3 percent, annualized, in the six months following the first Fed rate cut in a market cycle.</p>
        <p>After that initial decline, however, the market has generally recovered: stocks have returned 6.2 percent, annualized, over the 18 months after the first Fed rate cut.</p>
        <p>But don't relax just yet.</p>
        <p>Conditions in the bond market make the current prospects for the stock market worse than these figures suggest, Mr. Hussman said. At the moment, there is an inverted yield curve -- bond market terminology for a situation in which short-term interest rates are higher than longer-term rates.</p>
        <p>Historically, when all of these bond and stock market conditions are combined, as they were when the Fed first cut rates in 1968 and 2001, stocks have been especially weak. In the first six months after cuts in those years, they declined by an average of 6.8 percent, annualized. And over the 18 months after the first cuts, they lost an average of 9.3 percent, annualized.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hussman says he is not convinced that the Fed, still concerned about inflation, will ease interest rates anytime soon. And if it doesn't, he said, the outlook for stocks may be worse yet. ''In my view,'' he said, ''the stock market risk/reward ratio is not appealing at this time.'' But his bearish assessment of the stock market's prospects is not universally held.</p>
        <p>Laszlo Birinyi Jr., president of Birinyi Associates in Westport, Conn., for example, says he expects the stock market to rise this year, whether or not the Fed cuts rates. Private equity firms have accumulated a huge reservoir of capital that they will continue to deploy to acquire publicly traded companies, he said, and that should buoy the markets.</p>
        <p>''I think we're in a bull market,'' he said. ''It will continue for the rest of the year. The market is going to do well, with interruptions and bumps along the way.''</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that the growth rate for corporate earnings is declining, a development that has generally been a drag on the market. But he said that analysts' estimates had already ''come down so sharply'' that further bad news on that front wasn't likely to have much market impact.</p>
        <p>In early January, analysts tracked by Thomson Financial were forecasting an 8.7 percent increase in first-quarter earnings for the S.&amp; P. 500 companies.</p>
        <p>But since then, the aggregate forecast has been ratcheted all the way down to 3.4 percent, said David Dropsey, senior research analyst at Thomson. Since January, the forecast for full-year earnings growth has been trimmed to 6.2percent from 9.3 percent.</p>
        <p>David M. Jones, president of the economic consulting firm DMJ Advisors, says he believes that ''in the short run -- over the next month or two or three -- the bulls win out'' as hopes for a Fed rate cut overwhelm concern over falling profits.</p>
        <p>But three to six months out, Mr. Jones says, as the housing downturn proves ''longer and deeper than generally expected,'' growing evidence of a slowing economy and decelerating profit growth will prompt a correction, in his view.</p>
        <p>''The rate of profit growth will slow more than expected,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And what if the Fed defies market expectations and does not cut rates at all this year? In that case, Mr. Jones shares Mr. Hussman's bearishness.</p>
        <p>''If the Fed does nothing, it would mean an even bigger market decline,'' Mr. Jones said. ''Beware of too much bullish talk. You want to be careful with your investments and be aware of the possibility of a big correction.''</p>
        <p>JOE BATTIPAGLIA, chief investment officer at Ryan Beck &amp; Company, has a similar view. He is not sure that companies can match even the current earnings growth forecasts.</p>
        <p>''Earnings growth expectations for the S.&amp; P. 500 may be too high,'' Mr. Battipaglia said.</p>
        <p>Noting that net new borrowing by consumers was down 38 percent in the fourth quarter of 2006, versus the period a year earlier, he sees the prospect of a ''consumer-led pullback'' for the first time in 15 years.</p>
        <p>This would hurt the stock market, he said, with the S.&amp; P. dropping 5 percent or more.</p>
        <p>If Fed rate cuts won't necessarily signal a market upturn, where should investors focus?</p>
        <p>Corporate profit trends are a fairly reliable indicator, Mr. Battipaglia said. ''The first sign of a turn-up in the corporate profit growth rate,'' he said, is a bullish signal that has ''great predictive accuracy.''</p>
        <p>Such a turn-up, he added, could materialize toward year-end.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
