<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Visceral Realist</title>
    <meta content="woods15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0DD123EF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Visceral Realist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Wood</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Savage Detectives By Roberto Bolano. Translated by Natasha Wimmer.</p>
        <p>577 pp. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $27.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Savage Detectives By Roberto Bolano. Translated by Natasha Wimmer.</p>
        <p>577 pp. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $27.</p>
        <p>Over the last few years, Roberto Bolano's reputation, in English at least, has been spreading in a quiet contagion; the loud arrival of a long novel, ''The Savage Detectives,'' will ensure that few are now untouched. Until recently there was even something a little Masonic about the way Bolano's name was passed along between readers in this country; I owe my awareness of him to a friend who excitedly lent me a now never-to-be-returned copy of Bolano's extraordinary novella ''By Night in Chile.'' This wonderfully strange Chilean imaginer, at once a grounded realist and a lyricist of the speculative, who died in 2003 at the age of 50, has been acknowledged for a few years now in the Spanish-speaking world as one of the greatest and most influential modern writers. Those without Spanish have had to rely on the loyal intermittence of translation, beginning with ''By Night in Chile'' (2003), two more short novels -- ''Distant Star'' (2004) and ''Amulet'' (2007) -- and a book of stories, ''Last Evenings on Earth'' (2006), all translated by Chris Andrews and published by New Directions.</p>
        <p>The best way to offer a sense of this writer might be to take a scene, and a sentence, from ''By Night in Chile,'' still his greatest work. The book is narrated by Father Urrutia, a dying priest and conservative literary critic, a member of Opus Dei, who comes to emblematize, by the novella's end, the silent complicity of the Chilean literary establishment with the murderous Pinochet regime. In one episode, Father Urrutia is sent to Europe, by Opus Dei agents, to report on the preservation of the churches there.</p>
        <p>This is where Bolano's imagination suddenly expands into a magical diorama. Father Urrutia discovers</p>
        <p>that the chief threat to the churches comes from pigeon excrement, and that all over Europe churches have been using falcons to kill the pests. In Turin, Father Angelo has a fearsome falcon called Othello; in Strasbourg, Father Joseph has one named Xenophon; in Avignon, the murderous falcon is named Ta Gueule, and the narrator watches it in action:</p>
        <p>''Ta Gueule appeared again like a lightning bolt, or the abstract idea of a lightning bolt, and stooped on the huge flocks of starlings coming out of the west like swarms of flies, darkening the sky with their erratic fluttering, and after a few minutes the fluttering of the starlings was bloodied, scattered and bloodied, and afternoon on the outskirts of Avignon took on a deep red hue, like the color of sunsets seen from an airplane, or the color of dawns, when the passenger is woken gently by the engines whistling in his ears and lifts up the little blind and sees the horizon marked with a red line, like the planet's femoral artery, or the planet's aorta, gradually swelling, and I saw that swelling blood vessel in the sky over Avignon, the blood-stained flight of the starlings, Ta Guele splashing color like an Abstract Expressionist painter.''</p>
        <p>Much of the most successfully daring postwar fiction has been by writers committed to the long dramatic sentence (Bohumil Hrabal, Thomas Bernhard, W. G. Sebald, José Saramago). Bolano is in their company: the quotation here is broken off of a phrase that takes about a page in the book. The musical control is impeccable, and one is struck by Bolano's ability to nudge on his long, light, ethereal sentence -- impossibly, like someone punting a leaf -- image by image: the falcon, the red hue, the sunset, the dawn, the dawn seen from a plane, the femoral artery, the blood vessel, the abstract painter. It could so easily be too much, and somehow isn't, the flight of fancy anchored by precision and a just-suppressed comedy. (In Spain, amusingly, the falcons are too old or docile for killing, and the priests have none of the dangerous elegance of their French or Italian counterparts.) Likewise, this fantasia about falcons in every European city might have been thuddingly allegorical or irritatingly whimsical, and isn't. It is comically plausible, and concretely evoked; the surrealism lies in the systematic elaboration of the image. The Catholic Church is likened to a bird of prey, murderous and blood-red in its second capital, Avignon, and we are free to link this, without coercion, to the Chilean situation and the ethical somnolence of Father Urrutia.</p>
        <p>That long sentence is a poem, really, proceeding by foliation; in fact the entire novella is a poem of a kind. It will not surprise you to learn that Roberto Bolano wrote poetry before he wrote fiction. Even in a long novel like ''The Savage Detectives,'' his favorite unit is the discrete, Browning-like monologue, not the extended scene. He was born in Chile in 1953, but came of age in Mexico City, where his family had moved in 1968. Returning to Chile in 1973 to help with the socialist revolution as he saw it, he was caught in the Pinochet coup and briefly arrested. He went back to Mexico, where he published two books of verse, and then began a long period of displacement and travel and drug-taking and odd jobs in France and Spain. He died of liver failure, in Barcelona, a far violin among near balalaikas (to adapt Nabokov's words on a fellow exiled writer). He knew time was short: the fiction that is currently being translated -- there are more novellas to come, and a huge novel, ''2666,'' will appear in English next year -- was written in a spasm of activity in his last years.</p>
        <p>''The Savage Detectives'' was published in 1998, but its heart belongs to the Mexico City of the mid-1970s, when Bolano was an avant-garde poet bristling with mad agendas. Like much of his work, the novel is craftily autobiographical. Its first section is narrated in the form of a diary, by a 17-year-old poet named Juan Garcia Madero who is on the make, erotically and poetically, and who has been asked to join a gang of literary guerillas who have named themselves the ''visceral realists.'' The group is led by two young poets, Arturo Belano and Ulises Lima, a wild duo who appear elsewhere in Bolano's work (in ''Amulet,'' for instance). Lima is based on one of Bolano's friends, the poet Mario Santiago, and Belano is based on ... Bolano. Literature in Spanish and Portuguese, from Fernando Pessoa to Javier Cercas, from Cortazar to Borges, seems especially infatuated with alter egos. (José Saramago wrote an entire novel, and a great one too, ''The Year of the Death of Ricardo Reis,'' with one of Pessoa's authorial stand-ins, Ricardo Reis, as its protagonist.)</p>
        <p>A novel all about poetry and poets, one of whose heroes is a lightly disguised version of the author himself: how easily this could be nothing more than a precious lattice of ludic narcissism and unbearably ''literary'' adventures! Again, Bolano skirts danger and then gleefully accelerates away from it. The novel is wildly enjoyable (as well as, finally, full of lament), in part because Bolano, despite all the game-playing, has a worldly, literal sensibility. His atmospheres are solidly imagined, but the tone is breezy and colloquial and amazingly unliterary -- Gide's novel about writers, ''The Counterfeiters,'' comes to mind, or better, a kind of Latinized Stendhal, whose characters just happen to be writers (Bolano often warmly invoked Stendhal). He places usthere, in Mexico City, and reminds us of the excitement and boredom, the literary pretentiousness and ignorance, the erotic ambition and anxiety of being a young writer or reader in the company of like-minded friends. The juvenile diarist who is our guide can write things that made this reader, at least, wince in painful recognition: ''Depressed all day, but writing and reading like a steam engine.'' Or: ''Then I read William Burroughs until dawn.'' Or: ''Nothing happened today. And if anything did, I'd rather not talk about it, because I didn't understand it.'' One of his friends, a gay poet, grandly and absurdly classifies all literature as heterosexual, homosexual or bisexual: ''Novels, in general, were heterosexual, whereas poetry was completely homosexual; I guess short stories were bisexual, although he didn't say so.'' The same poet announces that at present poetry is enough for him, ''although sooner or later I'm bound to commit the vulgarity of writing stories.'' (The pleasure we take in this, as readers of English, owes everything, of course, to the book's talented translator, Natasha Wimmer, who repeatedly finds inspired English solutions for what must be a fiendishly chatty and slangy novel.)</p>
        <p>The visceral realists conduct ''purges,'' steal books (I particularly liked the sound of the Rebbeca Nodier Bookstore, whose owner is conveniently blind), write and read and have sex and attitudinize. Life is a heaven's kitchen, with everything simultaneously on the boil. ''It's incredible how much free time Mexicans have,'' one character claims. The young diarist falls in with a mad family and loses his virginity to one of the daughters, Maria Font. Meanwhile, Ulises Lima and Arturo Belano have become peculiarly obsessed with a poet from the 1920s named Cesarea Tinajero, a surrealist and modernist who belonged to the forerunners of the later visceral realists. Her work is revered by other writers from that period, but is nowhere to be found. She herself seems to have disappeared into the Sonoran Desert. Lima and Belano, accompanied by the young diarist and a prostitute, set out on a quixotic hunt for their equivalent of Quixote's Dulcinea.</p>
        <p>We are 120 pages in, and suddenly the book alters its form. The next 400 pages feature first-person interviews with scores of witnesses, friends, lovers, acquaintances and enemies of Lima and Belano. These are all people whose lives intersected, however briefly, with the two visceral realists, from 1976 to 1996. It is as if the novelist has taken a tape recorder and journeyed around the world, from Mexico City to San Diego to Barcelona to Tel Aviv, desperate to find out what became of the young, optimistic, but perhaps now doomed poets. Where did they go after the Sonoran Desert? What jobs did they have? What did they write? What became of all that ambition? Page by page, the novel begins to darken. An editor who met Lima and Belano before they set off for the desert says ''it was as if they were there but at the same time they weren't there,'' and the novel precisely mimics this poignant presence and absence.</p>
        <p>Again, it should be stressed that this is not just a postmodern game about the fictionality of novelistic characters (though it is that, too). Movingly, no one seems quite able to get the two young poets in focus; Lima and Belano flicker in and out of other people's lives, and the news is not good. They are dealing in drugs, they are often high, they drift from job to job. Lima is living in Paris for a while, desperately poor. He once found a 5,000-franc note on the sidewalk and now always walks with his head down. Belano is spotted near Perpignan, looking for a ''friend'' who has disappeared and who is about to commit suicide. A painter, interviewed in Mexico City in 1981, says that Belano and Lima weren't revolutionaries: ''They weren't writers. Sometimes they wrote poetry, but I don't think they were poets either.'' Belano moves to Barcelona, and works as a dishwasher in a restaurant. Lima goes to Nicaragua, and disappears there; two years later he has returned to Mexico City, and is glimpsed by the secretary of Octavio Paz. In a wonderfully sad scene, Lima approaches Paz, and the two sit on a bench, talking. The impeccably establishment Paz had been the great bete noire of the visceral realists, but Lima now seems emptied of revolt. He meekly shakes the hand of the Nobel laureate -- who has never heard of him, of course -- and disappears.</p>
        <p>''We poets in our youth begin in gladness; / But thereof come in the end despondency and madness,'' are Wordsworth's famous lines, precious to a generation of American poets like Lowell and Schwartz and Berryman, whose lives ended in suicide or bouts of insanity. Curiously, ''The Savage Detectives'' is both melancholy and fortifying; and it is both narrowly about poetry and broadly about the difficulty of sustaining the hopes of youth. Bolano beautifully manages to keep his comedy and his pathos in the same family. For instance, it is at once very funny and oddly appalling that not once does Bolano quote a single poem of Lima or Belano. We know their careers were not hoaxes (some of the witnesses speak of reading poems by the young men); but were they dreams? What kind of actual poetic talent inflated the ballooning ambition of these young writers?</p>
        <p>The terror of the MacGuffin always hangs over Bolano's work. In ''By Night in Chile,'' he tells the story of a rich shoemaker in the Austro-Hungarian empire who becomes obsessed with building a Heroes' Hill, a vast mausoleum dedicated to the heroes of the empire. When, decades later, Soviet troops storm the hill, all they find is a crypt containing the skeleton of the shoemaker, who gave up his life to the grand insanity of his dream. Ulises Lima and Arturo Belano, whose work we never see, drove off in 1975 in search of a poet whose own work was never published! Well, that's not quite accurate. The two men do eventually find a single poem by Cesarea Tinajero, published in a one-off magazine, and it's not even a poem but a hieroglyph. It is called ''Sion'' (i.e., Zion), and consists of three line-drawings. In the first, a square that looks a bit like a boat on a horizon, sits on a calm, straight line. In the second drawing, the line is wavy, undulating like a choppy sea, but the little boatlike square is gamely floating in the wave. In the third sketch, the line is stormily jagged, like a terrible EKG, and the little boat is barely clinging to the vertiginous wave.</p>
        <p>This ''poem'' might mean lots of things, but in the context of the novel, it surely evokes the difficult passage from the bathwater of youth and gladness to more treacherous adult waters. An Israeli friend of Ulises Lima's says that the importance of the poets' lives had nothing to do with visceral realism: ''It has to do with life, with what we lose without knowing it and what we can regain.'' He continues, and says that what we have lost we can regain, ''we can get it back intact.'' Can we? Minutes after delivering this wisdom this same man dies in a car accident. A Mexican academic, interviewed late in the novel, says that hardly anyone remembers the visceral realists anymore. Many are dead. Lima, he says, is living in Mexico City. ''About Arturo Belano,'' he says, ''I know nothing.'' This is finally how the novel makes good on its playful, postmodern impulses. Roberto Bolano's alter ego, Arturo Belano, whose life so closely shadows Bolano's own (night watchman and dishwasher, life in Paris and Barcelona, and so on), disappears from the story -- to re-emerge, of course, as the man willing to ''commit the vulgarity of writing stories,'' the man who triumphantly wrote this marvelous, sad, finally sustaining novel. Truly, it is as if he is there but at the same time isn't there.</p>
        <p>James Wood is a senior editor at The New Republic and a professor of the practice of literary criticism at Harvard University. His most recent work is a book of essays, ''The Irresponsible Self: On Laughter and the Novel.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Wood is a senior editor at The New Republic and a professor of the practice of literary criticism at Harvard University. His most recent work is a book of essays, ''The Irresponsible Self: On Laughter and the Novel.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
