<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Beachfront Home, Once Again</title>
    <meta content="15NJcolNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15NJcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Loch Arbour (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bubis, Sophie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kassin, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coyne, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sand and Gravel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sand and Gravel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDE133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Beachfront Home, Once Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Beachfront Home, Once Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kevin Coyne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Coyne, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>LOCH ARBOUR</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kevin Coyne Jersey column on lawsuit brought by beachfront homeowner Sophie Bubis, 83, against Jack Kassin of Loch Arbour, NJ; Bubis lost her ocean view when Kassin bought defunct beach club and had dune erected to shield his private beach; court has ruled that sand and vegetation must be removed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOPHIE BUBIS perched on the edge of the living-room couch that was once a front-row seat to sunrises over the ocean, mesmerized on this blustery morning by the most beautiful sight she could imagine: a backhoe lurching along across the street, scooping up sand.</p>
        <p>''Look, they're getting closer to my house,'' she said, pointing as it dug, swiveled and dumped, again and again. ''Every bucket is one bucket closer to seeing my beautiful view.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A battle over a 10-foot-tall pile of sand raises the question of how private a beach really can be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOPHIE BUBIS perched on the edge of the living-room couch that was once a front-row seat to sunrises over the ocean, mesmerized on this blustery morning by the most beautiful sight she could imagine: a backhoe lurching along across the street, scooping up sand.</p>
        <p>''Look, they're getting closer to my house,'' she said, pointing as it dug, swiveled and dumped, again and again. ''Every bucket is one bucket closer to seeing my beautiful view.''</p>
        <p>The backhoe had arrived two hours earlier -- and 12 years too late, in Ms. Bubis's view -- to start dismantling a 10-foot-tall pile of sand that she calls a berm and that its owner, Jack Kassin, calls a dune. Whatever its name, it has loomed like Everest at the center of the Jersey Shore's version of Jarndyce v. Jarndyce, the interminable lawsuit in Charles Dickens's ''Bleak House.''</p>
        <p>The matter of Bubis v. Kassin started in 1995, when Mr. Kassin bought a defunct beach club that a storm had all but washed away in this three-block-by-five-block village of 150 houses and barely 300 residents just north of Asbury Park. Across the street was the boxy yellow house of Ms. Bubis, a widowed bookkeeper who grew up behind her father's grocery in Passaic and who loves the beach, she said, ''more than anything else except my two children.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kassin loves the beach, too, and he bought the 650-foot stretch for $575,000 to use as a private one for his family and friends. Local zoning prohibits a residence; he maintains a cabana on the beach, and lives in nearby Deal.</p>
        <p>''I always had this view until Mr. Kassin came along and pushed up the sand,'' Ms. Bubis said, displaying a photograph taken through her window soon after she and her late husband, Samuel, bought their house in 1978. The beach is flat, the blue ocean shimmers.</p>
        <p>The pile of sand that Mr. Kassin built to shield his private beach -- but that also, he argued, protected the village in storms -- erased Ms. Bubis's view and spawned a dispute that quickly grew from a spat between neighbors into an epic court battle over a persistent, emotional question that has never been fully answered in New Jersey: Just how private can a beach really be?</p>
        <p>''You don't miss what you never had, but I had it once, and it became very dear to me,'' Ms. Bubis said about the ocean view she had for 17 years, and that she has spent ''very close to $250,000'' trying to get back. ''What right does he have to take it away from me? I said whatever it takes I'm going to do it, because it means so much to me.''</p>
        <p>She argued that the sand pile planted with trees and shrubs was an illegal fence, but for years she kept losing in court. She borrowed against her home equity, took in foreign students from nearby Monmouth University as boarders, worked at Macy's restocking the clothes left in dressing rooms. ''I would have been more than happy to throw in the towel a long time ago, but my client had faith in the rectitude of her position and she was willing to push it forward,'' said Leonard Needle, Ms. Bubis's lawyer.</p>
        <p>In 2005, the State Supreme Court finally agreed with her, and ordered the sand and vegetation removed. Mr. Kassin then applied to the Village of Loch Arbour for a variance to keep his dune but lower it to six feet. After eight months of planning board hearings, his request was denied by a 6-3 vote.</p>
        <p>Over the course of her long case, Ms. Bubis became an irresistible underdog, the 83-year-old widow fighting on behalf of all beach lovers who resent the barricading of oceanfront property. But in Loch Arbour itself, not everybody has been on her side. Mr. Kassin is regarded as a good neighbor, allowing the patrons of the neighboring village beach to spill over onto his property on busy summer days. He has been especially welcoming to surfers; a sandbar off his beach makes it a prime spot for good waves.</p>
        <p>And some village residents don't think it makes much sense to tear down a dune at a time when many other beach towns are building them for protection against storms and erosion. ''Witnesses showed how it would protect the village, and in my opinion that is much, much more important than the view itself,'' said Ed Lee, a member of the village Board of Trustees who voted in favor of the variance.</p>
        <p>The backhoe took another bite of the sand outside Ms. Bubis's window, slowly unveiling her quarter-million-dollar view, and a car pulled up on the otherwise empty street. ''This is it -- it's over,'' said Mr. Kassin, the owner of a textile business, as he watched his dune recede. ''And now that it's over, we're going to live in peace.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bubis didn't go out to see him, and he didn't go in to see her. The courts still have to resolve another case between them, and decide whether she can sit on any portion of his beach. A ruling is expected before summer, but that, of course, may not be the end of that.</p>
        <p>JERSEY E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: jersey@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
