<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEST SELLERS: April 15, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Besthard.nonfiction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1265" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEST SELLERS: April 15, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 31, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>SELECTED POEMS, by Derek Walcott. Edited by Edward Baugh. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $25.) The Nobel Prize winner Walcott, who was born on St. Lucia, is a long-serving poet of exile, caught between two races and two worlds.</p>
        <p>SEIZURE, by Erica Wagner. (Norton, $23.95.) A troubled young Englishwoman inherits a seaside cottage and takes an unexpected lover.</p>
        <p>KNOTS, by Nuruddin Farah. (Riverhead, $25.95.) After 20 years, a Somali woman returns home to Mogadishu from Canada, intent on reclaiming a family house from a warlord.</p>
        <p>CHANGING LIGHT, by Nora Gallagher. (Pantheon, $22.) The Manhattan project inspired this novel of love and guilt in 1940s New Mexico.</p>
        <p>EVOLUTION FOR EVERYONE: How Darwin's Theory Can Change the Way We Think About Our Lives, by David Sloan Wilson. (Delacorte, $24.) An absorbing study of cooperative behavior.</p>
        <p>THE MISTRESS'S DAUGHTER, by A. M. Homes. (Viking, $24.95.) Homes's dark memoir tells the story of her birth parents' re-entry into her life.</p>
        <p>CULTURAL AMNESIA: Necessary Memories From History and the Arts, by Clive James. (Norton, $35.) Essays on 20th-century luminaries by one of Britain's leading public intellectuals.</p>
        <p>SICK: The Untold Story of America's Health Care Crisis -- and the People Who Pay the Price, by Jonathan Cohn. (HarperCollins, $25.95.) The crisis seen through the experiences of ordinary people.</p>
        <p>THE LONG EXILE: A Tale of Inuit Betrayal and Survival in the High Arctic, by Melanie McGrath. (Knopf, $24.95.) Canada's forced relocation of a group of Inuit in 1953 is now seen as one of the country's worst human rights violations.</p>
        <p>THE ROAD TO DISUNION: Volume Two. Secessionists Triumphant: 1854-1861, by William W. Freehling. (Oxford University, $35.) This history of the origins of the Civil War stresses the South's distinct cultural and economic divisions.</p>
        <p>INVENTING HUMAN RIGHTS: A History, by Lynn Hunt. (Norton, $25.95.) Modern attitudes are traced to the 18th-century Enlightenment.</p>
        <p>The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 31, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>SELECTED POEMS, by Derek Walcott. Edited by Edward Baugh. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $25.) The Nobel Prize winner Walcott, who was born on St. Lucia, is a long-serving poet of exile, caught between two races and two worlds.</p>
        <p>SEIZURE, by Erica Wagner. (Norton, $23.95.) A troubled young Englishwoman inherits a seaside cottage and takes an unexpected lover.</p>
        <p>KNOTS, by Nuruddin Farah. (Riverhead, $25.95.) After 20 years, a Somali woman returns home to Mogadishu from Canada, intent on reclaiming a family house from a warlord.</p>
        <p>CHANGING LIGHT, by Nora Gallagher. (Pantheon, $22.) The Manhattan project inspired this novel of love and guilt in 1940s New Mexico.</p>
        <p>EVOLUTION FOR EVERYONE: How Darwin's Theory Can Change the Way We Think About Our Lives, by David Sloan Wilson. (Delacorte, $24.) An absorbing study of cooperative behavior.</p>
        <p>THE MISTRESS'S DAUGHTER, by A. M. Homes. (Viking, $24.95.) Homes's dark memoir tells the story of her birth parents' re-entry into her life.</p>
        <p>CULTURAL AMNESIA: Necessary Memories From History and the Arts, by Clive James. (Norton, $35.) Essays on 20th-century luminaries by one of Britain's leading public intellectuals.</p>
        <p>SICK: The Untold Story of America's Health Care Crisis -- and the People Who Pay the Price, by Jonathan Cohn. (HarperCollins, $25.95.) The crisis seen through the experiences of ordinary people.</p>
        <p>THE LONG EXILE: A Tale of Inuit Betrayal and Survival in the High Arctic, by Melanie McGrath. (Knopf, $24.95.) Canada's forced relocation of a group of Inuit in 1953 is now seen as one of the country's worst human rights violations.</p>
        <p>THE ROAD TO DISUNION: Volume Two. Secessionists Triumphant: 1854-1861, by William W. Freehling. (Oxford University, $35.) This history of the origins of the Civil War stresses the South's distinct cultural and economic divisions.</p>
        <p>INVENTING HUMAN RIGHTS: A History, by Lynn Hunt. (Norton, $25.95.) Modern attitudes are traced to the 18th-century Enlightenment.</p>
        <p>The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>FICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>NINETEEN MINUTES, by Jodi Picoult. (Atria, $26.95.) The aftermath of a high school shooting reveals the fault lines in a small New Hampshire town.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>OBSESSION, by Jonathan Kellerman. (Ballantine, $26.95.)The psychologist-detective Alex Delaware investigates what seems to be a deathbed confession of murder.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>THE ALIBI MAN, by Tami Hoag. (Bantam, $26.) A disgraced former policewoman investigates a murder linked to a group of wealthy Palm Beach men.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>WHITETHORN WOODS, by Maeve Binchy. (Knopf, $25.95.) A proposed highway threatens the existence of a religious shrine in a rural Irish village.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>FOR A FEW DEMONS MORE, by Kim Harrison. (Eos/HarperCollins, $21.95.) A witch owns an ancient artifact that may stop a serial killer or ignite a gang war.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>ABSOLUTE FEAR, by Lisa Jackson. (Kensington, $19.95.) A New Orleans detective tracks a serial killer somehow linked to an abandoned asylum.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>SHOPAHOLIC &amp; BABY, by Sophie Kinsella. (Dial, $24.) Becky is pregnant, and the obstetrician turns out to be her husband's ex-girlfriend.</p>
        <p>8*</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>STEP ON A CRACK, by James Patterson and Michael Ledwidge. (Little, Brown, $27.99.) A detective raising 10 children alone must rescue 34 high-level hostages.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>THE DOUBLE BIND, by Chris Bohjalian. (Shaye Areheart, $25.) A young woman who works at a homeless shelter struggles to understand the mysterious photographs taken by a recently deceased resident.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>SISTERS, by Danielle Steel. (Delacorte, $27.) After a family tragedy, four sisters with very different lives decide to share a Manhattan brownstone.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>DADDY'S GIRL, by Lisa Scottoline. (HarperCollins, $25.95.) A law professor caught in a prison riot must defend herself when she is unjustly accused of murder.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>BURNING BRIGHT, by Tracy Chevalier. (Dutton, $24.95.) In Georgian London, the poet William Blake befriends two neighborhood chldren.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>HUNTER'S MOON, by Randy Wayne White. (Putnam, $24.95.) Doc Ford helps a former president secretly investigate his wife's death in a suspicious accident.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>THE WATCHMAN, by Robert Crais. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.95.) A former Los Angeles police officer becomes the bodyguard of a troubled heiress marked for death.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>HEART-SHAPED BOX, by Joe Hill. (Morrow, $24.95.) An aging rock star who buys what's advertised as a ghost is stunned when it turns out to be the real thing.</p>
        <p>16*</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>THE BOOK OF AIR AND SHADOWS, by Michael Gruber. (Morrow, $24.95.) Letters found in a rare book set off a race to find an undiscovered Shakespeare play.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>A LONG WAY GONE, by Ishmael Beah. (Sarah Crichton/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) A former child soldier from Sierra Leone describes his drug-crazed killing spree and his return to humanity.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>GRACE (EVENTUALLY), by Anne Lamott. (Riverhead, $24.95.) Essays about faith and forgiveness.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>IN AN INSTANT, by Lee and Bob Woodruff. (Random House, $25.95.) The aftermath of the ABC co-anchor's traumatic brain injury in Iraq in 2006.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>HOW DOCTORS THINK, by Jerome Groopman. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) A doctor and New Yorker staff writer describes how doctors arrive at diagnoses.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>35</p>
        <p>I FEEL BAD ABOUT MY NECK, by Nora Ephron. (Knopf, $19.95.) A witty look at aging from a novelist and screenwriter (''When Harry Met Sally'').</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>INFIDEL, by Ayaan Hirsi Ali. (Free Press, $26.) A memoir by the Somali-born advocate for Muslim immigrant women.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>THE AUDACITY OF HOPE, by Barack Obama. (Crown, $25.) The Illinois junior senator proposes that Americans move beyond their political divisions.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>THE GOD DELUSION, by Richard Dawkins. (Houghton Mifflin, $27.) An Oxford scientist asserts that belief in God is irrational.</p>
        <p>9*</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>THE NEW AMERICAN STORY, by Bill Bradley. (Random House, $25.95.) The former Democratic senator and presidential candidate presents a liberal-centrist agenda.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>THE HARDCORE DIARIES, by Mick Foley. (World Wrestling Entertainment/Pocket, $24.) The former professional wrestling champion discusses his fame and his life at World Wrestling Entertainment.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>75</p>
        <p>MARLEY &amp; ME, by John Grogan. (Morrow, $29.95 and $21.95.) A newspaper columnist and his wife learn some life lessons from their neurotic dog.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>103</p>
        <p>THE WORLD IS FLAT, by Thomas L. Friedman. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $30.) A columnist for The Times analyzes 21st-century economics and foreign policy.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>SOMEBODY'S GOTTA SAY IT, by Neal Boortz (HC/HarperCollins, $25.95.) A radio talk-show host discusses government, povertyand other topics.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>SECOND CHANCE, by Zbigniew Brzezinski. (Basic, $26.95.) The former National Security adviser discusses how America can regain the global power and prestige squandered by its three post-cold-war presidents.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>RELIGIOUS LITERACY, by Stephen Prothero. (HarperSanFrancisco, $24.95.) What Americans need to know about the world's religions and their own.</p>
        <p>16*</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>BLACKWATER, by Jeremy Scahill. (Nation, $26.95.) An account of the private army that has been deployed by the government in Afghanistan and Iraq.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
