<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the South Bronx, Unlikely Allies Fight a Proposed Jail</title>
    <meta content="15jail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/15jail.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840677"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hunt's Point (Bronx)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rikers Island Prison Complex (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Correction Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Steven E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horn, Martin F (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the South Bronx, Unlikely Allies Fight a Proposed Jail</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the South Bronx, Unlikely Allies Fight a Proposed Jail</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Timothy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Proposal by New York City Dept of Corrections to build $375 million jail in Hunts Point section of South Bronx is arousing opposition from unlikely coalition of neighbors, environmentalists, advocates for prison reform and members of union that represent jail guards; Comr Martin F Horn says city needs 2,000-bed jail to relieve pressure on Rikers Island complex; union representing correction officers says money would be better spent on improving conditions at Rikers; environmentalists are concerned about possible toxic chemicals at site; politicians and residents say South Bronx has been dumping ground for city for too long and new jail might interrupt area's resurgence; Steven E Smith, owner of proposed jail site, who cooperated at first when smaller jail was proposed, now maintains that effort to condemn entire 27-acre parcel is preventing him from developing or selling land; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Residents of the South Bronx have long made the point that the area needs banks, restaurants, parkland and, most critically, jobs. The last thing the South Bronx needs, some of them say, is a new 2,040-inmate jail.</p>
        <p>A proposal by the city's Correction Department to build a $375 million jail in the Hunts Point section has aroused opposition from an unlikely coalition of neighbors, environmentalists, advocates for prison reform and members of the union that represents jail guards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A proposed $375 million jail in the Hunts Point section has aroused opposition from environmentalists, advocates for prison reform and members of the jail guards union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Residents of the South Bronx have long made the point that the area needs banks, restaurants, parkland and, most critically, jobs. The last thing the South Bronx needs, some of them say, is a new 2,040-inmate jail.</p>
        <p>A proposal by the city's Correction Department to build a $375 million jail in the Hunts Point section has aroused opposition from an unlikely coalition of neighbors, environmentalists, advocates for prison reform and members of the union that represents jail guards.</p>
        <p>''They're essentially trying to establish a penal colony in the South Bronx,'' said Elena Conte, the solid waste and energy coordinator for Sustainable South Bronx, an environmental group opposed to the jail plan.</p>
        <p>On Friday, opponents earned more time to continue their fight after Steven E. Smith, the owner of the proposed jail site, won a temporary restraining order in Federal Bankruptcy Court that delays the plan's first public hearing, which had been scheduled for tomorrow. (The court proceedings were held in bankruptcy court because Mr. Smith's company, Britestarr Homes, is in bankruptcy protection.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith, who had cooperated with the city when the Department of Correction had planned a smaller jail on the property, now maintains that the effort to condemn the entire 27-acre parcel is preventing him from developing or selling the land.</p>
        <p>''I have everything I own invested in this property,'' said Mr. Smith, who added that he believes he could sell the land for as much as $80 million.</p>
        <p>The tract is among the largest pieces of vacant land in the city that is controlled by a single owner. For years, the property had been used as an illegal dump for construction and demolition material, and it is still filled with debris. Mr. Smith originally sought to build a power plant there.</p>
        <p>The Department of Correction first proposed the jail -- which would be known as the Oak Point Detention Center -- last April.</p>
        <p>Martin F. Horn, commissioner of the Department of Correction, said during an interview last week that the city needed the 2,000-bed jail to relieve pressure on the dilapidated Rikers Island jail complex. The department has also proposed reopening and expanding capacity at the Brooklyn House of Detention, which is now closed, from 700 to 1,400 inmates within five years.</p>
        <p>In January, the Bronx House of Detention, which housed about 400 inmates, was demolished to make room for a $500 million mall. The city also operates a barge with 800 prisoners anchored off Hunts Point, not far from the proposed jail.</p>
        <p>''This is a citywide plan to overall reduce the size of the city's jail system and reduce the dependence on Rikers Island and its aging facilities,'' said Mr. Horn. ''Jails have to go somewhere.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Horn said that keeping so many inmates -- an average of about 14,000 each day -- on Rikers Island presented security problems, was a chore for family members and attorneys seeking to visit inmates and was a psychological burden for the prisoners.</p>
        <p>''Keeping all the city's inmates on Rikers Island is downright dangerous,'' he said. ''It stigmatizes and demonizes inmates. It is New York's version of Devil's Island.''</p>
        <p>But critics say the proposed Bronx jail, which would be the city's largest outside of Rikers Island, makes little sense.</p>
        <p>The union representing corrections officers has said the $375 million needed to build the jail would be better spent on improving conditions at Rikers.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say they are concerned about possible toxic chemicals at the Bronx site, including mercury, barium and lead. And politicians and residents say the South Bronx has been the dumping ground for the city for too long, and that a new jail might interrupt the area's resurgence.</p>
        <p>The South Bronx has one of the city's highest concentrations of waste transfer stations and sewage treatment plants. There is also a sprawling rail yard and a fertilizer pellet factory that residents say emits a foul odor.</p>
        <p>''I've heard every possible excuse to do something bad in the Bronx,'' said U.S. Rep. Jose E. Serrano, who represents the South Bronx and has been one of the jail's most outspoken opponents. ''The whole situation is people forgetting how far the South Bronx has come.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Horn bristles at the suggestion that a jail would taint the area.</p>
        <p>''These are the sons and daughters of the city,'' Mr. Horn said, referring to inmates. ''We are not noxious. We do not spew noxious fumes. It demeans the humanity of us.''</p>
        <p>In addition to housing 2,040 inmates, the proposed jail would have 600 parking spaces and a kitchen where meals for all of the city's jails would be prepared. Construction would start in 2009 and be finished in 2013.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horn said the jail would not hurt economic development in the South Bronx, and might even aid it by encouraging new restaurants and other businesses that would serve corrections officers and visitors. And no one, he said, lives within at least half a mile of the site.</p>
        <p>''There is no evidence that the location of a jail diminishes a community,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Faced with intense opposition, Mr. Horn has been like a man waging a political campaign.</p>
        <p>Before Monday's hearing was canceled, he had been scheduled to give reporters a bus tour of Rikers Island to point out the complex's dilapidated condition. (Some of the buildings on the island have been closed after a federal judge found them to be inadequate for holding inmates.) A spokesman said the tour would be rescheduled.</p>
        <p>Opponents may be united against the jail, but they are split about what they would like to have built at the site, which includes a stretch of East River waterfront.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith would still like to build a power plant, although that plan has failed to win either neighborhood or political support. Mr. Serrano said he would like to see at least part of the tract reserved for a park.</p>
        <p>Sustainable South Bronx has proposed building a recycling center that would create 300 to 500 jobs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horn said, however, that the jail plan ''is the last best chance for the city to be able to do the right thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
