<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing Along With Imus</title>
    <meta content="15tanenhaus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/weekinreview/15tanenhaus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">MSNBC</org>
        <org class="online_producer">WFAN-AM</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chambers, Whittaker</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hiss, Alger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lamb, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6DC103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing Along With Imus</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Playing Along With Imus</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM TANENHAUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tanenhaus, Sam</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The remarkable story of Don Imus's unraveling has inspired commentary from many quarters -- from the upper echelons of his employers, MSNBC and CBS, to the aggressive criticism of the Rev. Al Sharpton and the eloquent testimony of the Rutgers basketball players who described how wounded they were by the racial and sexual disparagement Mr. Imus had heaped on them in a mere three words.</p>
        <p>But there have been surprisingly muted signals from some of the most thoughtful people who have traveled in the curious orbit of the ''Imus in the Morning'' program, specifically the authors and journalists who at various times lent their voices to his program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The author measures his own culpability and complicity as a guest on Don Imus’s CBS radio show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The remarkable story of Don Imus's unraveling has inspired commentary from many quarters -- from the upper echelons of his employers, MSNBC and CBS, to the aggressive criticism of the Rev. Al Sharpton and the eloquent testimony of the Rutgers basketball players who described how wounded they were by the racial and sexual disparagement Mr. Imus had heaped on them in a mere three words.</p>
        <p>But there have been surprisingly muted signals from some of the most thoughtful people who have traveled in the curious orbit of the ''Imus in the Morning'' program, specifically the authors and journalists who at various times lent their voices to his program.</p>
        <p>One reason may be that they are sifting through the complex issue of their own culpability and complicity. For the guests on Mr. Imus's program knew they were also implicated as participants in his comic, and sometimes abrasive, act.</p>
        <p>I wrote ''they.'' I mean ''we.''</p>
        <p>For a period lasting many months I was one of Mr. Imus's collaborators, or enablers -- in fact one of the more conspicuous ones. In October 1997, when I was a freelance writer, a friend phoned with the news that Mr. Imus had begun talking up my book, ''Whittaker Chambers: A Biography.'' He did not succeed in making it a best seller, as he did in some other cases, but his efforts resulted, by my estimation, in an additional 10,000 sales, plenty for a densely footnoted biography with a $35 price tag.</p>
        <p>More gratifying still were the letters and phone calls from readers, not the presumed yahoos we've been hearing about in recent days, but civil and courteous people from all walks of life -- students, retirees, history buffs and, in some instances, professional authors -- who also were part of Mr. Imus's following.</p>
        <p>Mr. Imus's enthusiasm was unexpectedly long-lived. Months after his first mention of the book he was still obsessing, daily it seemed, about minutiae of the Chambers-Alger Hiss espionage confrontation, while his sidekicks histrionically greeted his recountings with a chorus of groans and protests of the ''not-again'' variety.</p>
        <p>All this, I knew, was ''good'' for me -- even the groaning. I was transcending the role of mere author and had become a bit player in the daily Imus comedy routine. I enjoyed all this, but knew it wouldn't last. I had listened closely enough to the show to realize that Mr. Imus was capricious, and regulars on the program often became the butt of jokes or abuse, some of it quite cruel.</p>
        <p>It was the price of admission. For all his self-assuredness, Mr. Imus often seemed perplexed by those who came from outside his own world. He had successfully remade himself into a quasi-establishment figure, but his roots were in the shock-jockery of the 1970s and 1980s.</p>
        <p>This accounted, I suspect, for the elaborate courtesies he showed new guests. When I began to get the occasional live phone call, I was treated with deference. Mr. Imus's second banana, Charles McCord, addressed me, with almost grave formality, as ''Mr. Tanenhaus,'' and the tone of respect was even more obvious to me when his guest was a woman, as though Mr. Imus wanted to atone for the lewdly misogynist fare he and his crew so often indulged in.</p>
        <p>On the one occasion when I was invited into the studio for a full-fledged interview, Mr. Imus diffidently showed off the rare first editions of literary classics arranged in his office and modestly accepted my praise of the accomplished photographs he had taken.</p>
        <p>The interview itself was a surprisingly sober affair of the C-Span variety: a direct, matter-of-fact, carefully paced tour through Chambers's life. Mr. Imus had thoroughly mastered the material; he told me he was an admirer of the ''Booknotes'' interviews Brian Lamb was then doing on C-Span. A few minutes into the session I realized the only expectation of cheap laughs had been my own: the humorous ''material'' I'd worked up, but mercifully was spared from testing out.</p>
        <p>By now, I was tuning in regularly. It had become part of my routine: waking up each morning to WFAN and the frisson of hearing my name broadcast on the radio. Of course, I was hearing other things, too, and they were disturbing at times: slurs against black athletes, an ''impersonation'' of Clarence Thomas that didn't sound like him at all (unlike the impersonations of white figures), but instead drew on the stalest of the ''here come de judge'' grotesqueries of a previous era; the almost continual soundtrack of leering sexual comments.</p>
        <p>Today, in the harsh light of Mr. Imus's disgrace, it is hard to explain why none of this bothered me very much. But the truth is I tuned it out. One reason, I think, is that my position seemed paradoxical. I was pleased to have been admitted into Mr. Imus's club -- alongside famous columnists and TV pundits and celebrated authors.</p>
        <p>But I also had been summoned into the exotic precinct of mass, or mob, culture, with its populism and prejudices, its bracing vulgarity, its base humor. And in America at least, all these characteristics are inseparable from broad popularity, the warts of our pluralism.</p>
        <p>Those who stand outside it can seem undemocratic. I remember my ambivalence in 1998 when Mr. Imus in a fit of outrage at ''the elitists'' who had not given my biography the National Book Award, announced his own Imus American Book Awards, which would include very large prizes (as much as $100,000) to winners selected by Mr. Imus and his listeners.</p>
        <p>Mr. Imus first said he ''was just kidding'' about dispensing his own book awards. But the next year, he went through with it anyway, although he appeared to be embarrassed by the spectacle, probably because he sensed that he had crossed from rebelliousness to philistinism.</p>
        <p>He committed a similar error nearly two weeks ago, and it cost him more dearly. Those of us who benefited from his attention can only feel saddened now, not only because we are indebted to him, but because we too played a part in the performance he carried too far.</p>
        <p>BOOKS Sam Tanenhaus is the editor of the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Sam Tanenhaus is the editor of the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
