<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Fantasy Sports, It Helps Being a Rocket Scientist</title>
    <meta content="15cheer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/baseball/15cheer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHEERING SECTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DC103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Fantasy Sports, It Helps Being a Rocket Scientist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Fantasy Sports, It Helps Being a Rocket Scientist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallozzi, Vincent M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One night last month, Clark Olson sat at his home computer and selected players in three different fantasy baseball drafts.</p>
        <p>''It took about three hours,'' said Olson, a 38-year-old Seattle Mariners fan. ''It was time-consuming, but I actually managed to cook dinner during the second draft.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clark Olson, one of the top fantasy sports players in the world, has a galactic edge. He is not only a knowledgeable sports fan, but also a rocket scientist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One night last month, Clark Olson sat at his home computer and selected players in three different fantasy baseball drafts.</p>
        <p>''It took about three hours,'' said Olson, a 38-year-old Seattle Mariners fan. ''It was time-consuming, but I actually managed to cook dinner during the second draft.''</p>
        <p>Olson is one of the top fantasy sports players in the world. Last year, he nickel-and-dimed his way to the top of ESPN's Über standings, which rank the online performance of everyone who plays fantasy games across multiple sports.</p>
        <p>''Clark is a bit of a legend on our message boards,'' said Matthew Berry, the senior director for fantasy leagues at ESPN. ''When you consider that 15 million people play fantasy sports, what he has done as a fantasy gamer has been unreal.''</p>
        <p>In a thinking-man's universe where success and failure are mostly a reflection of time spent doing statistical analysis and research, Olson has a galactic edge. He is not only a knowledgeable sports fan, but also a rocket scientist.</p>
        <p>Olson worked for five years at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., where he helped develop techniques for Mars rovers and other applications in which information is extracted from digital images.</p>
        <p>''The job required a lot of computational and algorithmic thinking,'' said Olson, who lives with his wife, Rebecca, in Seattle. ''That way of thinking and looking at numbers is a benefit when it comes to playing fantasy sports, which is heavily based on statistics.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, nearly every would-be general manager in cyberspace has had trouble staying in Olson's orbit. They have long since come to grips with a sobering reality: They cannot formulate lineups with the same kind of deft drafting, shrewd trading and waiver-wire finds made by a man whose former day job was out of this world.</p>
        <p>''Clark is a very impressive, high-skilled player,'' Berry said. ''He is the Albert Pujols of fantasy sports, a player who consistently produces, a player who is money in the bank.''</p>
        <p>Olson is an associate professor of computing and software systems at the University of Washington at Bothell. He graduated from the University of Washington at Seattle, where he also received a master's degree in electrical engineering, and he earned a doctorate in computer science from the University of California.</p>
        <p>He achieved his highest honors in fantasy land through years of studying statistical spreadsheets, newspaper and magazine articles, box scores and rosters. He finished third in the 2002 Über rankings, second in 2003, third in 2004, third again in 2005 and first last year.</p>
        <p>Olson has been consistently in the top 10 this year, running 16 teams in ESPN leagues: seven in baseball, five in basketball and four in hockey. He is pondering a return to fantasy bass fishing.</p>
        <p>''The key to most of these sports is knowing where to get good information to help determine which players might do well,'' said Olson, who lists the 2005 signing of Milwaukee Brewers pitcher Derrick Turnbow as one of his greatest steals.</p>
        <p>''Sure, I'm good at problem solving and using analytical skills. But like any other fantasy player, I need to be smart in other areas, like picking up free agents, studying current sports news and trends, paying attention to who's hot and who's not, and knowing the rules of each league that I belong to.''</p>
        <p>In addition to his ESPN teams, Olson spends about 10 hours a week handling the budgets of fantasy teams in high-stakes events. He competes in the National Fantasy Baseball Championship, which is made up of 375 teams. The entry fee is $1,300 and the top prize is $100,000.</p>
        <p>In the past three years, Olson has won two league titles in that event, collecting $5,000 for each. He and a partner also earned $5,000 for winning a league in the World Championship of Fantasy Football.</p>
        <p>Serious fantasy players are always eager to team with Olson. In fact, he joined forces with the singer Meat Loaf in the 2004 World Championship of Fantasy Baseball.</p>
        <p>''Meat Loaf is a huge fantasy sports fan,'' Olson said. ''We sat beside each other that year at the draft in Las Vegas. We finished third out of 15 teams in our league and won $1,000. But that didn't even cover our entrance fee.''</p>
        <p>Olson said that real-life general managers had made moves on paper that he would have never made online.</p>
        <p>''I would not have brought José Vidro to Seattle to be our designated hitter because we could have better used that money,'' he said. ''We also traded Rafael Soriano, a great setup man, to Atlanta for Horacio Ramirez, a starting pitcher who is often injured, another move I definitely would not have made.</p>
        <p>''And Gil Meche going from Seattle to Kansas City for $55 million, that really shocked me. To me, those numbers just didn't seem to add up.''</p>
        <p>CHEERING SECTION E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
