<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Raymond Carver Is Now Calling From</title>
    <meta content="15mcgr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/movies/15mcgr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgrath, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lawrence, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carver, Raymond (1939-88)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Robert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jindabyne (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Short Cuts (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Australia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Carver, Raymond</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E1D7153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Raymond Carver Is Now Calling From</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Raymond Carver Is Now Calling From</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES McGRATH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgrath, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on director Ray Lawrence's new film Jindabyne, based on Raymond Carver short story So Much Water So Close to Home; same story was adapted for one passage of Robert Altman's film Short Cuts; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE writer Raymond Carver is often said to be a minimalist, which isn't quite accurate. He's no more a minimalist than Chekhov, the writer he most resembles, and some of Carver's late stories, like ''Blackbird Pie,'' are almost lush in their texture. Carver is also like Hemingway, though, in the simplicity and clarity of his pared-down language, his precise descriptions, his use of dialogue to evoke complicated emotional situations. Not a lot happens in a typical Carver story -- or not a lot that goes on outside people's heads -- and this may explain why, though he is admired by many filmmakers (and probably even more screenwriters), not many Carver works have been turned into movies. There are only a handful of Carver-inspired films, most lasting less than half an hour.</p>
        <p>''Jindabyne,'' which opens April 27, an Australian film directed by Ray Lawrence and starring Gabriel Byrne and Laura Linney, is just the second full-length Carver feature -- or even the first if, like some hard-line Carver purists, you don't count Robert Altman's ''Short Cuts,'' which came out 14 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mr. Carver’s characters get transplanted from the Pacific Northwest to Australia for the film, “Jindabyne.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE writer Raymond Carver is often said to be a minimalist, which isn't quite accurate. He's no more a minimalist than Chekhov, the writer he most resembles, and some of Carver's late stories, like ''Blackbird Pie,'' are almost lush in their texture. Carver is also like Hemingway, though, in the simplicity and clarity of his pared-down language, his precise descriptions, his use of dialogue to evoke complicated emotional situations. Not a lot happens in a typical Carver story -- or not a lot that goes on outside people's heads -- and this may explain why, though he is admired by many filmmakers (and probably even more screenwriters), not many Carver works have been turned into movies. There are only a handful of Carver-inspired films, most lasting less than half an hour.</p>
        <p>''Jindabyne,'' which opens April 27, an Australian film directed by Ray Lawrence and starring Gabriel Byrne and Laura Linney, is just the second full-length Carver feature -- or even the first if, like some hard-line Carver purists, you don't count Robert Altman's ''Short Cuts,'' which came out 14 years ago.</p>
        <p>''Short Cuts'' is a masterpiece, one of the greatest feats of ensemble acting in American moviemaking, but die-hards still complain that there's too much Altman and not nearly enough Carver. Altman and his screenwriter, Frank Barhydt, took nine Carver stories, as well as one of his poems, and wove them together into a skein of looping, intertwined and overlapping Altmanesque narratives, adapting and altering many of the original characters and even making up brand-new ones. They also relocated these people to Los Angeles, where the movie famously begins with ''Medfly''-spraying helicopters looming on the horizon and ends with an earthquake.</p>
        <p>Most of Carver's stories, on the other hand, are set in the Pacific Northwest, where he spent most of his life. It's not an area he describes in a lot of detail, but it's nonetheless a defining circumstance for his characters, who tend to be blue-collar and down on their luck. Carver's Northwest is less a place, really, than a state of mind, and uprooting his people from there and plopping them down in hyper Los Angeles (where Altman uses a sun-drenched palette) is a little like moving Chekhov's to Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>Mapwise, ''Jindabyne'' performs an even more wrenching dislocation. The movie takes its name from the town where it's set, near the Snowy Mountains, in New South Wales. In the winter months Jindabyne is actually a ski town, but in the warmer weather, when the movie takes place, it's a sleepy, rough-edged place that may surprise American viewers by its close metaphorical resemblance to Carver's Northwest. Jindabyne is, among other things, the kind of town where the year-rounders take their hunting and fishing very seriously.</p>
        <p>The movie is based on Carver's classic story ''So Much Water So Close to Home,'' told from the point of view of a wife who gradually discovers that while on a fishing trip her husband and his buddies came upon a young woman's corpse floating in the water, and after debating what to do, tied the body to a tree and went on fishing for a couple of days before reporting their find to the authorities. ''She was dead,'' he explains. And his wife replies: ''That's the point. She was dead.  She needed help.''</p>
        <p>The same story is one of the central and most powerful threads in ''Short Cuts,'' and dramatizes perhaps more starkly than any of the others that movie's main preoccupation: the way that husbands and wives, men and women, simply fail to comprehend one another. The kind of fishing trip that in Carver and in ''Jindabyne'' takes on an almost ritualistic quality, though, is more nearly a novelty and a lark in Altman's Los Angeles; played by Buck Henry and Huey Lewis, the husband's two sidekicks (reduced from three in the original) are such bumptious indoor guys that it's hard to believe they wouldn't freak out from spending the night in a tent, let alone from coming upon a floating corpse, and their decision seems to stem in part from uncertainty and incompetence. A moral weight hangs much heavier over the Jindabyne campsite.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lawrence, whose previous movie was ''Lantana,'' an Altmanesque story of multiple strands about four unhappy couples, is the Ridley Scott of Australia, the country's most successful director of television commercials. He's picky about his film projects, and famous for filming them in natural light, often in single takes.</p>
        <p>''All that filmmaking paraphernalia just gets in the way,'' he said in a recent telephone interview. ''And all the time you spend setting up is renowned for sucking the energy out of actors. I try to counteract all that. If I could get rid of the camera, I would. On 'Jindabyne' we got on a roll after a while. Laura had worked with Clint Eastwood, who works that way -- without a lot of takes -- and she pretty much led the band. I remember saying after we'd finish a scene, 'Well, we could do it again, but I can't think of a good reason why.' So we'd just move on.''</p>
        <p>The result is a movie that doesn't quite look like a movie: so natural seeming it's a little bleached out, and so understated in its acting that it's the screen equivalent of Carver's transparent, vernacular prose style. On the other hand Mr. Lawrence and his screenwriter, Beatrix Christian, have fleshed out Carver's spare, elusive story to a degree that's almost novelistic.</p>
        <p>Claire (Ms. Linney), the troubled wife, turns out to have a history of postpartum depression that makes her sexually skittish. Played by Mr. Byrne, her husband, Stewart (this must be the Aussie spelling; he's Stuart in Carver and Altman), is an Irishman who runs a garage but dreams of being a race car driver, and his fishing buddies have back stories as well. Carl (John Howard) and his wife, Jude (Deborra-Lee Furness), have found themselves somewhat reluctantly in charge of their orphaned and possibly disturbed granddaughter. Rocco (Stelios Yakimis) is in the beginning stages of a complicated relationship with a local teacher who is part Aborigine. Billy (Simon Stone), the youngest and dumbest, is living in a van with a spaced-out hippie chick. Even the floating corpse is a character: She's a local Aboriginal girl, it turns out, whose angry family complains that the fishermen would never have ignored her had she been white.</p>
        <p>''I've always loved that story,'' Mr. Lawrence said, ''and what particularly interested me was the way it dramatized the moral dilemma of responsibility. I've always been interested in the male-female relationship and how difficult it is -- what makes you stay, what makes you leave.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Carver said once that he confronted his characters head-on, which has always been an inspiration to me. And this was a great opportunity to put myself in a situation where I had to do the same thing. It also enabled me to hang on to the film a lot of other things that interest me. I've always been interested in Aboriginal culture, for example, and as soon as we made the dead girl an Aboriginal, that began to speak volumes. And I wanted an Irishman because the Irish experience in Australia in some ways paralleled the Aboriginal one. Many of them came as convicts.''</p>
        <p>Speaking from Chicago, where she now lives, Ms. Christian, the screenwriter, said: ''Ray Lawrence is interested in the appeal of ordinary people. He's virtually allergic to any kind of story you could call aspirational.'' She added that when she and Mr. Lawrence first visited Jindabyne, where he himself had made a number of fishing trips, they just walked around, almost the way journalists would, incorporating things they saw -- a garage, a trailer camp -- into the story. The idea of making the dead girl an Aborigine, she said, was ''one of those things where you get 20 ideas and 19 are terrible.'' She continued, ''This was the one that stuck, and it was a way to implicate more people in the story.''</p>
        <p>She said that when Mr. Lawrence first approached her, she had by chance just finished adapting Chekhov's ''Three Sisters'' for the Sydney Opera House and had read a lot of Carver to prepare herself. ''Ray had been obsessed with 'So Much Water' for years, but couldn't get anyone to commit to it,'' she went on. ''But I just became fascinated by the other men in the story and this mysterious event. Did they behave differently because they were in a group? I tried to leave as much room around that as I could.''</p>
        <p>She said that in switching the story to Australia she was always aware that she and Mr. Lawrence were taking a risk, because Carver had set it so squarely in a particular place and time. ''Now that I'm living in America, there's a sense in which I understand the story better,'' she said. ''At first I couldn't relate to the female character and her degree of isolation. But driving through Midwestern towns now, I see a lot of that kind of isolation -- that sense she has of being submerged and half-asleep.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lawrence said: ''When I read the story in 1984, I thought right off that it could make a good film. Then, when Altman made it, I thought, 'Well, that's that.' He was such a great director, who put his stamp on everything he did.'' He went on to say that he got the rights to ''So Much Water,'' which Altman owned together with Carver's widow, Tess Gallagher, because Altman, who died last year, admired ''Lantana.'' ''Or so I've been told,'' he added, ''and I'm told that he gave permission only if he could be invited to the American premiere. So I suppose his ghost will be sitting right behind me.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Christian said: ''You know, it's terrible, but I've never seen the Altman version, and I'm a big fan. When I started on 'Jindabyne,' my first impulse was to go out and grab the DVD, but to this day I've been afraid to look. I suppose I should, but it feels like a kind of taboo.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
