<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Affordable Housing Would Stay Affordable</title>
    <meta content="15wemainWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15wemain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LAND TRUSTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spano, Andrew J (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, Caitlin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Affordable Housing Would Stay Affordable</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">This Affordable Housing Would Stay Affordable</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAITLIN KELLY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelly, Caitlin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Westchester County Executive Andrew Spano's proposed land trust, whose goal would be to preserve affordable housing in perpetuity; trust, which will establish bank of land, donated by towns, villages or cities, on which developers will be able to build affordable housing for rent or sale, is expected to be operating by July; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FINDING affordable housing in Westchester -- the nation's seventh-most expensive county, according to census data -- is never easy. Even long-term residents of properties built with county, state or federal subsidies inevitably face steeper housing costs when their homes eventually revert to market rates.</p>
        <p>Some 240 properties have already lost their price caps this year, and 4,000 more in 11 communities will soon follow suit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>FINDING affordable housing in Westchester  the nation’s seventh-most expensive county, according to census data  is never easy. Even long-term residents of properties built with county, state or federal subsidies inevitably face steeper housing costs when their homes eventually revert to market rates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FINDING affordable housing in Westchester -- the nation's seventh-most expensive county, according to census data -- is never easy. Even long-term residents of properties built with county, state or federal subsidies inevitably face steeper housing costs when their homes eventually revert to market rates.</p>
        <p>Some 240 properties have already lost their price caps this year, and 4,000 more in 11 communities will soon follow suit.</p>
        <p>Last month, County Executive Andrew J. Spano proposed the creation of a land trust whose goal would be to preserve affordable housing in perpetuity. A coalition of 15 developers, housing advocates, bankers, lenders and county officials served as advisers to create the trust, which is expected to be operating by July. The trust will set up a bank of land, donated by towns, villages or cities; developers will be able to build affordable housing for rent or sale on parcels from that bank, which will remain the property of the trust, rented out in 99-year leases.</p>
        <p>''There is not enough, and a decreasing amount, of subsidized housing in Yonkers,'' said Jon Shenk, executive director of the Cluster Housing Resource Center, a nonprofit housing advocacy group. ''It's a problem.'' Residents of subsidized housing who soon face higher market rates fear losing their homes, he said.</p>
        <p>Tanya Mahboob, a tenant at the Whitney Young apartment complex in Yonkers since 1999, has heard that her rent will probably rise $300 from the $1,300 a month (30 percent of her salary) she now pays for the affordable-housing three-bedroom, two-bathroom apartment she shares with her three sons. None of her sons, ages 18, 19 and 26, have full-time jobs, but all are now looking for work to help her financially, she said. ''It would be scary for me if they weren't here to help,'' she said. ''I'd have to look at moving or take on a second job.'' Ms. Mahboob, who works as a project manager for Starwood Hotels, called the rent increase ''a big change a lot of people weren't prepared for.''</p>
        <p>Norma Drummond, the county's deputy commissioner of planning, said: ''We felt like we were treading water. People want the government out of their lives.''</p>
        <p>Joseph Apicella, an executive vice-president with Cappelli Enterprises, a Westchester developer, said the trust was a smart way to deal with the business community. ''Any time we can deal with an agency that is less bureaucratic than established governments or agencies, it's less onerous,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Leasing land for 99 years, while developers or homeowners own only the buildings on the land, will require some education on behalf of lenders, buyers and developers.</p>
        <p>''It will be a new model for all of us to work with, which always adds a new level of complexity,'' said Rosemarie Noonan, executive director of the Housing Action Council, an advocacy group in Tarrytown that works to create affordable housing.</p>
        <p>Ms. Noonan, a coalition member, agreed that fresh thinking on a persistent problem -- creating housing that lower-income workers can afford, like homes that sell for $185,000 to $195,000 -- was badly needed. Families who make 80 percent or less of the county's median income can qualify for ''affordable'' units, requiring no more than 30 percent of their income, including utilities. For a family of four, that is an income of $77,200 and a rent or mortgage payment of no more than $1,930 a month.</p>
        <p>''I do hear it more and more: 'There's nothing affordable here for my children -- they'll never be able to buy a home here,' '' Ms. Noonan said.</p>
        <p>Westchester's municipal officials also increasingly see the value of making housing affordable for younger residents, the elderly and service personnel, she added.</p>
        <p>''This is the towns' own acknowledgement that diversity is important to the community,'' Ms. Noonan said.</p>
        <p>LAND TRUSTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
