<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>North Korea Takes No Apparent Action as Deadline Passes</title>
    <meta content="15korea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assets, Frozen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Macao</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Banco Delta Asia</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hill, Christopher R (Asst Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Macao</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Macao</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>North Korea Takes No Apparent Action as Deadline Passes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER; Thom Shanker contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>North Korea has made no apparent move to shut down and seal its main facility for manufacturing nuclear weapons ahead of deadline that expired; failure to act leaves Pres Bush vulnerable to criticism for returning $25 million in frozen funds to North Korea; Japan, South Korea and China have urged chief American negotiator Christopher R Hill to give North Korea more time; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first deadline for North Korea to shut down and seal its main facility for manufacturing nuclear weapons fuel expired Saturday, with no apparent move by the North to fulfill its commitments, while China asked angry officials in the Bush administration to show patience.</p>
        <p>The inaction leaves President Bush vulnerable to attacks from hawks in his own party, who have argued that it was a mistake to return $25 million in frozen funds to the North Koreans -- much of it believed to be from illicit sales of missiles and counterfeit currency -- and who doubt that the North Koreans will stop producing bomb fuel and give up their existing weapons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first deadline for North Korea to shut down and seal its main facility for manufacturing nuclear weapons fuel expired Saturday, with no apparent move by the North to fulfill its commitments, while China asked angry officials in the Bush administration to show patience.</p>
        <p>The inaction leaves President Bush vulnerable to attacks from hawks in his own party, who have argued that it was a mistake to return $25 million in frozen funds to the North Koreans -- much of it believed to be from illicit sales of missiles and counterfeit currency -- and who doubt that the North Koreans will stop producing bomb fuel and give up their existing weapons.</p>
        <p>Sean McCormack, the State Department spokesman, called on North Korea in a statement on Saturday ''to realize fully its commitments under the Feb. 13 agreement'' by inviting back inspectors from the International Atomic Energy Agency and beginning to close down its Yongbyon nuclear facility. And the chief American negotiator dealing with the North, Christopher R. Hill, told reporters in Beijing: ''We don't have a lot of momentum right now. That is for sure.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hill has traveled over the past week to Japan, South Korea and China, where officials urged him to allow the North Koreans a little time. But in Washington, officials said they did not know if the Chinese had any indications that compliance was forthcoming.</p>
        <p>A senior State Department official said in a telephone interview that it was ''prudent to give this thing a few more days.''</p>
        <p>North Korean officials told a visiting American delegation earlier in the week that they would begin shutting down the reactor at Yongbyon, where for years they have produced plutonium from spent nuclear fuel, as soon as the $25 million frozen at a bank in Macao was returned. The process has taken far longer than American officials expected, in part because the legal mechanisms for returning the money turned out to be enormously complicated, leading the Bush administration to give up its demand that all illicit funds had to be used for humanitarian purposes.</p>
        <p>But the agreement that Mr. Hill signed with North Korea on Feb. 13 -- in talks that also included China, Russia, Japan and South Korea -- gave the North 60 days to deactivate and seal its main plant at Yongbyon, invite back international inspectors and provide a preliminary accounting of how much plutonium it had produced. As of Saturday, the country had apparently taken none of those steps.</p>
        <p>The visiting delegation was led by Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico, who is seeking the Democratic nomination for president. Officials in Pyongyang told the Americans that they would fulfill their obligations within 30 days of receiving the funds.</p>
        <p>Investigators from the United States Treasury and American intelligence agencies had spent months poring through records of the frozen accounts, and mapped the banking activities of state-owned companies, arms traders and the leaders surrounding President Kim Jong-il.</p>
        <p>''This was the first thing we ever did that got the North Koreans' attention,'' a senior White House official said in an interview this week.</p>
        <p>Some administration officials acknowledge that they have few good options to enforce the deadline. With the money cleared for return, the Macao accounts no longer provide diplomatic leverage. That leaves the administration more dependent than ever on pressure from China, the North's main supplier of energy and aid, to force North Korea to live up to the agreement.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Eberstadt, a scholar at the American Enterprise Institute, said that turning over the money ''complicates the logic of the Proliferation Security Initiative,'' the administration's plan to stop countries from illicit shipments of weapons, because it allows the North to retrieve profits from those activities.</p>
        <p>''It also goes contrary to the Security Council resolution'' passed at Washington's urging after North Korea's nuclear test on Oct. 9, he said. The test was something of a fizzle, a subkiloton explosion, but it was enough to win unanimous passage of a resolution that imposed new economic sanctions.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Eberstadt said, ''the North Koreans can force the Bush administration into continuing, humiliating reversals of its policy.''</p>
        <p>But administration officials argue that Mr. Bush never reversed policy. They contend that he simply waited for the right moment to strike the deal, after the nuclear test angered China's leaders enough to move them from a neutral arbiter to a source of pressure on the North. North Korea reached the deal, they argue, because China and South Korea had cut aid.</p>
        <p>In public statements, both Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice and the national security adviser, Stephen J. Hadley, have defended the accord as far more effective than an agreement signed between North Korea and President Bill Clinton in 1994 to freeze the Yongbyon plant.</p>
        <p>''What you are hearing,'' one senior official said, ''are the complaints of a lot of people who simply don't think we should be dealing with the North Koreans at all.''</p>
        <p>Among those who have objected are former Bush administration officials who believe that the president has been so eager for a diplomatic coup that he has given up his principles -- and is perpetuating Mr. Kim's rule. Mr. Bush's former ambassador to the United Nations, John R. Bolton, recently expressed the hope that the North would violate the Feb. 13 agreement because it would give Mr. Bush an excuse to renounce the deal.</p>
        <p>Anticipating that the North would miss the deadline, Mr. Bolton said recently, ''One sign of whether we are in trouble is whether the administration will call this a 'violation' or use words like 'noncompliance.' '' Assuming that the North admits international inspectors and seals the Yongbyon plant and the nearby nuclear reprocessing facility, it would have to move on to ''disable'' the nuclear facilities, a term that the agreement does not define.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, it would have to account for and surrender all its nuclear weapons, an arsenal that American intelligence agencies believe has grown from enough fuel for one or two weapons when Mr. Bush took office, to fuel for somewhere between a half-dozen and a dozen weapons.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
