<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why 100 Pitches Don't Go as Far as They Used To</title>
    <meta content="15score" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/baseball/15score.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840629"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="KEEPING SCORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why 100 Pitches Don't Go as Far as They Used To</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Why 100 Pitches Don’t Go as Far as They Used To</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sheehan, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You can't open a newspaper, a magazine or a browser without reading a complaint about starting pitchers. Complete games are at a historic low, the quality-start statistic has purists up in arms and the idea of pitch counts sends many people into convulsions.</p>
        <p>Bert Blyleven, who won 287 games in a 22-year career that ended in 1992, falls into the camp that insists today's pitchers have been turned into lesser beings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Strikeouts and walks have increased as a percentage of plate appearances for 80 years, with a sharp uptick since the 1980s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You can't open a newspaper, a magazine or a browser without reading a complaint about starting pitchers. Complete games are at a historic low, the quality-start statistic has purists up in arms and the idea of pitch counts sends many people into convulsions.</p>
        <p>Bert Blyleven, who won 287 games in a 22-year career that ended in 1992, falls into the camp that insists today's pitchers have been turned into lesser beings.</p>
        <p>''It's because they put a pitch count in,'' said Blyleven, a right-hander best known for his big curve. ''When I came up, we got a chance to pitch nine innings at the minor league level.</p>
        <p>''I'm from the old school. The more you throw, the better off you are.''</p>
        <p>Is the evolution of a starting pitcher's role the result of overprotection, or a natural response to a changing game? After all, no one would argue that today's pitchers have it easy, not with smaller ballparks, smaller strike zones and bigger hitters with high-performance muscles who patiently look for the perfect pitch to drive.</p>
        <p>Strikeouts and walks have increased as a percentage of plate appearances for 80 years, with a sharp uptick since the 1980s. Even plate appearances that result in the ball being put in play take more pitches, as hitters work deep counts. If you've ever ridden the No. 4 train at 11:30 p.m. after a mere nine-inning Yankee game, you're familiar with this change.</p>
        <p>Since 1969, when Major League Baseball lowered the mound to 10 inches high and tightened the strike zone, the game has become more oriented toward offense and, within that, the power game.</p>
        <p>This evolution is most obviously manifested in the outsize home run numbers of modern players. Seven of the game's 20 500-home run hitters started playing after 1969, and that percentage will probably grow with Alex Rodriguez, Manny Ramírez, Frank Thomas and Jim Thome poised to cross that line in the next year or two. The top six single-season home run totals were posted between 1998 and 2001, the peak of the recent hitters' era.</p>
        <p>Of course, the game has always had prodigious power players. Even the offensive wasteland of the 1960s had Frank Howard and Willie McCovey. A key change now is that power is spread throughout the lineup. Whereas the game used to be divided into hitters' positions and fielders' positions, teams get power from seven, eight or nine lineup spots.</p>
        <p>Consider the change that has occurred since the start of Blyleven's career. In 1970, when he made his debut with the Minnesota Twins, the American League's second basemen had a slugging percentage of .332; the catchers .391; the shortstops .347. The league averages at those spots last year were .395, .417 and .412.</p>
        <p>There are no longer breaks in the lineup. Back in the 1960s and '70s, maybe half the hitters in any given lineup could hurt you with their power. Now, any player in most lineups can hit a ball a long way if you let him.</p>
        <p>Pitchers can't let up at any point in the game, lest their less-than-best offering end up on some bleacher creature's nightstand. The pennant-winning Detroit Tigers of 2006 had eight hitters with at least 13 home runs and at least a .437 slugging average -- while playing in a pitchers' park.</p>
        <p>If pitchers are having to use more pitches to get the same number of hitters out, that would explain why they face fewer batters, throw fewer innings and complete fewer games. If the average effort per pitch is higher, because pitchers live in constant fear of the long ball, that would be an argument in favor of not only fewer innings, but fewer pitches. With so few weak hitters in the game, there are no soft touches. Pitchers may be working just as hard as they did 40 years ago, but they are seeing fewer hitters simply because pitching is that much harder now.</p>
        <p>Blyleven, who stays close to the game as a popular analyst on Twins broadcasts, scoffs at the notion that pitchers were able to coast in his day.</p>
        <p>''I never took any hitter for granted,'' he said. ''Every hitter you faced, you had to go at him as the No. 3 hitter. It's still 60 feet 6 inches away. I can't see these pitchers today doing any different than they were in the '70s.''</p>
        <p>The evidence is compelling, though. In 1976, 101 regulars -- players with 400 or more plate appearances -- slugged below .400. In 1986, just 61 players slugged below .400. Last year, with four more teams and 40 more regulars added since 1986, only 52 players were below the .400 mark. In the modern game, every player with a bat in his hands is a threat to be giving the third-base coach a high-five a few seconds later.</p>
        <p>Pitching is a fundamentally different job than it was 30 or 40 years ago. The statistical lines of pitchers have changed, not because the pool is filled with lesser competitors, but because the same amount of effort simply does not go as far as it once did.</p>
        <p>To compare what Johan Santana has to do in 2007 with what Sandy Koufax faced in 1965 -- or Blyleven did a decade later -- is to compare vastly different jobs under different circumstances. That, and not some weakness of character or sinew, is why pitchers throw fewer innings than they used to.</p>
        <p>KEEPING SCORE E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
