<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/Long Island; A Prime Site for Cooking Classes</title>
    <meta content="15lizo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/realestate/15lizo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Riverhead (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Suffolk County Community College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotsalas, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2DD133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/Long Island; A Prime Site for Cooking Classes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Prime Site for Cooking Classes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE COTSALAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotsalas, Valerie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Riverhead, LI, welcomes pending addition of Suffolk County Community College Culinary Arts Center; school will offer both degree classes and continuing education for general public, space for catered events and cafe area; Riverhead officials hope state-of-the-art facility will have spillover effect for downtown retailers as efforts to revive town continue; photo (In the Region/Long Island) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN recent years, planners trying to spruce up aging downtown shopping districts on Long Island have turned to a variety of unusual properties as centerpieces: specialty food markets, ice rinks and refurbished performing arts theaters, for example. Now, downtown Riverhead is hoping to bring some of the bustle back to Main Street with a new culinary school.</p>
        <p>Suffolk County Community College will begin classes this fall in its new Culinary Arts Center, now under construction on a once-vacant lot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Downtown Riverhead is hoping to bring some of the bustle back to Main Street with a new culinary school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN recent years, planners trying to spruce up aging downtown shopping districts on Long Island have turned to a variety of unusual properties as centerpieces: specialty food markets, ice rinks and refurbished performing arts theaters, for example. Now, downtown Riverhead is hoping to bring some of the bustle back to Main Street with a new culinary school.</p>
        <p>Suffolk County Community College will begin classes this fall in its new Culinary Arts Center, now under construction on a once-vacant lot.</p>
        <p>The culinary center is the second project in which the school has expanded beyond its three main campuses -- Selden, Brentwood and the Eastern Campus, just across the Riverhead border in the town of Southampton -- to a downtown area. In 2005, the Center for Allied Health and Nursing opened in downtown Sayville, leasing space in an unused Sayville School District building.</p>
        <p>Riverhead officials say they expect the culinary center to provide a welcome economic stimulus to the downtown.</p>
        <p>''The activity at the school will extend beyond traditional retail hours,'' said Andrea Lohneiss, the director of Riverhead's community development agency, which had to approve the project before it could be built. ''There will be night classes and not just enrolled students, but classes that people can take for fun.''</p>
        <p>The 28,000-square-foot culinary school in Riverhead will also give the college's culinary arts program a chance to grow. In the last 15 years, the two-year degree program has been using the college's cafeteria at the Eastern Campus for a test kitchen, along with various classrooms for general instruction.</p>
        <p>But in recent years enrollment has increased about 25 percent each year, said Richard Freilich, the director of the culinary center. With the new school on Main Street, he said, it is expected that the number of students in the program will more than double, to about 190 in the next three or four years.</p>
        <p>In the fall, the school will also add two-year degrees in restaurant management and pastry arts to its culinary arts degree program.</p>
        <p>The new two-story building, designed by Baldassano Architecture of Ronkonkoma, will house a world of culinary equipment and accouterments, including a demonstration theater for presentations by visiting chefs and for televising cooking classes.</p>
        <p>The center will have a front entrance on Main Street, which will open on the Bakers Workshop Cafe and Bistro, where students will prepare and sell specialty breads, sandwiches, salads and other fare, and diners can sit at tables in an atrium, Mr. Freilich said.</p>
        <p>The rear entrance, on Roanoke Avenue, will provide access to a hotel lobby, with a concierge desk, built-in coatroom and lounge areas. This side of the building, which borders a park with a visitors' parking lot, would be used for catered events and for a future hotel and resort management degree program.</p>
        <p>The culinary lab and the baking and pastry arts lab will each have 16 cooking stations. The labs' up-to-date equipment includes four-burner stoves, overhead broilers, stainless steel work counters, 6- and 10-quart mixers, walk-in ''proofers'' (low-temperature roomlike ovens for racks of rising dough) and long pizza-style deck ovens.</p>
        <p>Four classrooms on the first floor will have retractable walls to create a banquet hall with space for 100. The kitchen in the 60-seat stadium-style demonstration theater will be outfitted with Wolf and Sub-Zero appliances, ''just like a Food Network set,'' Mr. Freilich said. There will be conventional classrooms and lockers on the second floor and, off the theme, a separate lab for nursing-school students.</p>
        <p>For the public, there will be continuing-education cooking classes, including Italian cuisine, ice sculpturing and cake decorating; wine tastings; a certificate program in professional wine studies; and a ''young chefs'' summer program for 9- to 13-year-old children. The school will also train non-degree students for food industry jobs, Mr. Freilich said.</p>
        <p>Students may also be able to take advantage of Riverhead's location, he added. The town starts roughly where Long Island splits into vineyard country on its North Fork and the Hamptons ocean hamlets on the South Fork, providing opportunities for internships at local vineyards, restaurants and hotels.</p>
        <p>Downtown Riverhead has been slowly reviving after storefronts were emptied with the gradual completion of the Long Island Expressway in the 1970s. The expressway terminated at a county highway that bypassed downtown and lured shoppers with its big-box strip malls. When the 165-store Tanger Outlet Center opened in 1994, directly off Exit 72 of the expressway, downtown Main Street died.</p>
        <p>Efforts to revitalize the downtown include a $121 million proposal, still in the planning stages, to create a park and a retail and condominium complex next to the Peconic River, which runs parallel to Main Street.</p>
        <p>Town officials say the Culinary Arts Center classes and events for the public will help bring more people downtown from the surrounding area. And ''those folks might go to the coffee shop or the restaurants,'' said Ms. Lohneiss, the community development director. ''There's a spillover effect from a culinary facility.''</p>
        <p>The school is investing about $1 million in the plan, along with $330,000 from Suffolk County and $250,000 from New York State for equipment.</p>
        <p>But following the model used at its downtown Sayville nursing school, the college will not own the building. The developer Ron Parr of the Ronkonkoma-based Parr Organization is building the $7.5 million facility and will lease it to the college.</p>
        <p>The leasing arrangement helped move the project quickly, said George Gatta, the vice president for planning and development at Suffolk County Community College. If the school had bought the lot and built the school using only public funds, he said, it would have taken much more than four years to propose and complete the culinary center.</p>
        <p>A new library planned for the college's Eastern Campus, for example, which is to be built with $6.8 million from Suffolk County and an equal amount from New York State, could take up to 10 years to complete, Mr. Gatta said.</p>
        <p>The compact scale of the off-campus schools in Riverhead and Sayville is part of their success, some planners say. Replacing an empty lot with a cooking school, or an empty school building with a nursing center, fills in the gaps in downtown areas.</p>
        <p>Vision Long Island, a nonprofit planning firm that focuses on ''smart growth'' development and publicizes projects that meet its development standards, extols the plan for the culinary center.</p>
        <p>''The concept is multiple uses,'' said Eric Alexander, executive director of Vision Long Island, of the addition of the culinary arts center to downtown Riverhead. ''As many different uses as you can have that complement each other'' will help bring in more people at different times of day.</p>
        <p>In the Region | Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
