<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/New Jersey; Adopting City Mannerisms</title>
    <meta content="15njzo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/realestate/15njzo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Englewood (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Antoinette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EEDD133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/New Jersey; Adopting City Mannerisms</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Adopting City Mannerisms</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTOINETTE MARTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Martin, Antoinette</byline>
      <dateline>ENGLEWOOD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Englewood, NJ, appeals to Manhattan commuters with close proximity to city and highly diverse housing stock; Town Centre at Englewood, featuring 188 extremely luxurious rental apartments opening in stages during spring of 2007, will compete with Manhattan luxury rental prices; Brownstones at Englewood, similar project, is underway on former 14-acre industrial site; photos (In the Region/New Jersey) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the early 20th century, when most of the mansions on East Hill here were being built, this small city was known as ''Wall Street's bedroom.'' Englewood's proximity to Manhattan -- only five minutes to the George Washington Bridge -- made it a perfect haven for New Yorkers looking to build a big house somewhere peaceful and quiet.</p>
        <p>Today Englewood has a population of 27,000. It remains appealing to commuters, and its housing stock, already highly diverse, is becoming even more so with a new development offering upscale apartments right over downtown shops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Englewood’s housing stock, already highly diverse, is becoming even more so with a new development offering upscale apartments right over downtown shops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the early 20th century, when most of the mansions on East Hill here were being built, this small city was known as ''Wall Street's bedroom.'' Englewood's proximity to Manhattan -- only five minutes to the George Washington Bridge -- made it a perfect haven for New Yorkers looking to build a big house somewhere peaceful and quiet.</p>
        <p>Today Englewood has a population of 27,000. It remains appealing to commuters, and its housing stock, already highly diverse, is becoming even more so with a new development offering upscale apartments right over downtown shops.</p>
        <p>Towne Centre at Englewood, a group of 188 pricey rental units, is opening in stages this spring amid the retail thicket on West Palisade Avenue, the heart of the city's downtown.</p>
        <p>''We are calling it apartment living reimagined,'' said Aida Lahood, leasing manager for the Towne Centre's apartments. ''This is something quite different for this community. Not only are the apartments extremely luxurious, but residents will be able to just walk downstairs to shop for anything they need.''</p>
        <p>The Towne Centre apartments are being built on the upper floors of two four-story buildings fronting on West Palisade, with retail and restaurant space at street level on West Palisade and along the building's rear facade on Englewood Avenue.</p>
        <p>The apartments are one-, two- and three-bedroom units, and some have additional loft spaces that can be used as home offices, guest suites or entertainment areas. All have terraces and nine-foot ceilings. They are being marketed at rents ranging from $1,995 to $3,700 per month -- steep by local standards, but not by Manhattan's.</p>
        <p>Rents in northern New Jersey, always a cheap alternative for New Yorkers, have been increasing in recent years, and the brokerage company Marcus &amp; Millichap predicts another rise in rates of about 3 percent this year, to an overall average of just under $1,400 a month.</p>
        <p>Apartment vacancy rates, meanwhile, are low -- under 4 percent -- as home-buying fever has cooled, brokers say, and the number of renters continues to rise.</p>
        <p>In Bergen County, where Englewood is situated, about a third of residents are renters, according to census figures. That number is higher than in Essex and Morris Counties, but far lower than in Hudson County, which includes Hoboken and Jersey City, and where about 66 percent of the residents rent as opposed to owning their homes.</p>
        <p>Englewood is set to gain a substantial number of new apartments this year and next. In addition to the Towne Centre, another 350 apartments are going up just north of Route 4, in a mixed-use project called the Brownstones at Englewood.</p>
        <p>That project, which has its own health club, is rising on a 14-acre site where an old manufacturing plant once stood; a 12-story office building is also planned.</p>
        <p>Rents at the Brownstones will start slightly below those at the Towne Centre -- $1,768 for a one-bedroom unit.</p>
        <p>At Towne Centre, about two dozen apartment units are already finished and occupied, as construction -- not to mention deconstruction -- proceeds on the site, between West Palisade and Englewood Avenues and South Van Brunt and Humphrey Streets.</p>
        <p>The two buildings were topped off a year ago, but then some alert residents noted that the Englewood Avenue side seemed to be a bit taller than the four stories that had been approved in 2002. They went to city officials to complain.</p>
        <p>City planners insisted that they had not approved a fifth story, and the developer, Fred Fish, insisted that they had.</p>
        <p>When the wrangling was over, it was agreed that Mr. Fish's company, Real Estate Equity, and its partner, the Atlantic Realty Development Corporation, would lop off the top of one of the buildings, and eliminate the lofts from some penthouse units. That work is under way now, according to the leasing manager; meanwhile, model apartments are open for viewing.</p>
        <p>Each Towne Centre apartment will be equipped with a washer and dryer, surround sound, recessed lighting and a security system.</p>
        <p>The Crowne Residences, the top-of-the-line units atop the northern building of the Towne Centre, are the largest available. Each has hardwood floors throughout and higher-end kitchen appliances.</p>
        <p>The complex will be staffed with a round-the-clock concierge and will have enclosed parking, a fitness center, a business center, a library with fireplaces, club rooms, a children's playroom and a movie theater. Housekeeping, laundry and transportation service can be arranged through the concierge.</p>
        <p>Several shops have already moved into ground-floor spaces at the Towne Centre. Meanwhile, other shopping opportunities are rife on West Palisade and the surrounding streets: chain stores to boutiques, and bodegas to kosher delis.</p>
        <p>A decade ago, the western end of Palisade Avenue was run-down and low-rent, compared with the eastern end, where retail has traditionally thrived, Ms. Lahood noted. Since a city redevelopment effort that began five years ago, however, there is now little distinction to be made.</p>
        <p>In the Region | New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
