<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Laura Shoop and David Milowitz</title>
    <meta content="15vows" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/fashion/weddings/15vows.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shoop, Laura (Laura Milowitz)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milowitz, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0D9133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Laura Shoop and David Milowitz</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Laura Shoop and David Milowitz</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVID MILOWITZ, a dancer who had hung up his shoes for a career as an event planner, wields a Rolodex with something for every conceivable occasion -- from a band for an opening night party on Broadway to a sword swallower for a corporate blowout in Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>But one category he resolutely left unfilled was that of a wife. ''I didn't really want a relationship, and I never really thought I was going to get married,'' said Mr. Milowitz, 32, a principal in ESP Productions in Albertson, N.Y. ''My parents being divorced made me lose total faith in the whole concept of marriage,'' he said. ''I was disillusioned in the whole idea that there's one person out there.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Watching Ms. Shoop perform in the Broadway revival of “Oklahoma!” made Mr. Milowitz want to pencil her in on his yellowing dance card.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVID MILOWITZ, a dancer who had hung up his shoes for a career as an event planner, wields a Rolodex with something for every conceivable occasion -- from a band for an opening night party on Broadway to a sword swallower for a corporate blowout in Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>But one category he resolutely left unfilled was that of a wife. ''I didn't really want a relationship, and I never really thought I was going to get married,'' said Mr. Milowitz, 32, a principal in ESP Productions in Albertson, N.Y. ''My parents being divorced made me lose total faith in the whole concept of marriage,'' he said. ''I was disillusioned in the whole idea that there's one person out there.''</p>
        <p>Then, in November 2002, he went to see his friend Jermaine Rembert dance in the Broadway revival of ''Oklahoma!'' Mr. Milowitz became entranced as he watched Mr. Rembert's dance partner, Laura Shoop, kick up her prairie skirt.</p>
        <p>It was enough to make Mr. Milowitz want to pencil her in on his yellowing dance card. Mr. Rembert, too, saw potential in a match with Mr. Milowitz and procured her number. But Mary Garrett-Turner, Mr. Milowitz's roommate, who also knew Ms. Shoop, wasn't so sure. '' 'Too pretty, too American, too tall and beautiful,' '' he recalled Ms. Garrett-Turner telling him. '' 'Definitely not your type.' ''</p>
        <p>Too pretty, too American, too tall and beautiful not to call, thought Mr. Milowitz, who decided Ms. Shoop was exactly his type.</p>
        <p>Ms. Shoop, a Juilliard-trained dancer, had plenty of experience twirling effortlessly through the arms of men. But offstage, she'd stumbled here and there. ''Jermaine set us up because he was so sick of my complaining that I couldn't find a good man,'' said Ms. Shoop, 31.</p>
        <p>So when Mr. Milowitz called to make a date, she accepted. It was ''all right, cool and fine,'' she said of that date and the one that followed. When a group of her friends asked her to join them at Joe's Pub, and Mr. Milowitz agreed to tag along, she was surprised at how easily he fit in.</p>
        <p>''He just walked into the midst of all my friends and took charge,'' she recalled. ''It takes a lot from somebody to walk into the lion's den on a third date, and yet he handled it so eloquently and with such charm.'' When she knocked her Cosmopolitan all over his tan pants and he good-naturedly mopped it up, he captivated her as well. ''David was so charming about it and made me feel completely at ease that I was literally like, 'He's so adorable, and he took the nervousness out of the moment.' That's why I fell in love with him. I saw that funny, charming side of him on the third date and I just knew.''</p>
        <p>Bewitched though they were, Mr. Milowitz's pesky issues eventually resurfaced. So he suggested therapy -- for both of them.</p>
        <p>''It was the fear of the loss of the relationship, of the breaking-up part, the fear of this nuclear family, like the one I grew up with, falling apart again,'' he said. ''Therapy was the key to breaking myself out of that, living in the present instead of thinking about the fear of the future.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shoop, who was raised in Chicago and whose parents were married for 37 years, harbored none of those fears. ''I knew marriage could work,'' she said. But there were religious differences her parents hadn't had to face. She had been raised Catholic; Mr. Milowitz is Jewish. Moreover, his mother and stepfather, a rabbi, were pushing for him to marry within the religion.</p>
        <p>Enter Ms. Shoop, stage right, in the role of Hodel in the 2004 Broadway revival of ''Fiddler on the Roof.'' '' 'She says Shabbat prayers better than anybody,' '' Mr. Milowitz recalled his mother and stepfather exclaiming when they saw her perform. '' 'She's in!' ''</p>
        <p>The following year he proposed to her on a pier at the South Street Seaport. But before their wedding plans could be settled, in the summer of 2006 Ms. Shoop discovered that her mother, Carol Shoop, was dying. Mr. Milowitz set aside everything to drive to Chicago to be with Laura, his cat riding along in his Mustang convertible. ''It was an incredible testament to who he is,'' she said.</p>
        <p>On April 1, they were married at dusk at the Lighthouse at Chelsea Piers amid a garden of white and pink cherry blossoms, hydrangea and roses chosen by Ms. Shoop's mother before her death last July. Rich Kieling, a psychotherapist who had counseled the couple and who became a minister of the Church of Spiritual Humanism for the occasion, officiated before 240 guests.</p>
        <p>Despite the moral and professional support, Mr. Milowitz bungled his lines amid waves of laughter. It wasn't a fear of commitment that rattled him, said Derek Shaffer, his best man.</p>
        <p>''I watched Laura perform this song in 'Fiddler' where she talks about going off to Siberia to live with this Bolshevik for the rest of her life,'' Mr. Shaffer said, recalling when he realized Mr. Milowitz's heart had been ensnared by a woman who, too, would travel great distances for him. ''She sang the song with such earnestness and passion that I had a conscious thought -- that she was going to marry my friend.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
