<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Listen Up, You Weeds and Twigs: It's April!</title>
    <meta content="15RHomeLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15RHome.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOME WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lawns</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Busch, Akiko</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7DA123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Listen Up, You Weeds and Twigs: It's April!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Listen Up, You Weeds and Twigs: It’s April!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AKIKO BUSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Busch, Akiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Akiko Bush Home Work essay on getting lawn into shape in April; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR a winter that took so long in coming, this one seems to have taken just as long to leave. Even after the snow and ice were gone, winter's residue could still be found spread across the grass in the powdery leaves and twigs, the dirt shoved by the snowplow up onto the lawn, and all the other bits of dust it left in its wake.</p>
        <p>Our lawn is an uneven place to begin with. It is a combination of the broad, deep-green blades of Kentucky bluegrass and the thinner blades of fine fescue, a typical mix in this region. From time to time, we have also let the grass go to meadow, so add to that the timothy, ryegrass and patches of clover, along with the knotweed, crabgrass and dandelion, and you've got the rough texture of the common Northeastern lawn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nourishing a little patch of earth brings an almost primal sense of fulfillment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR a winter that took so long in coming, this one seems to have taken just as long to leave. Even after the snow and ice were gone, winter's residue could still be found spread across the grass in the powdery leaves and twigs, the dirt shoved by the snowplow up onto the lawn, and all the other bits of dust it left in its wake.</p>
        <p>Our lawn is an uneven place to begin with. It is a combination of the broad, deep-green blades of Kentucky bluegrass and the thinner blades of fine fescue, a typical mix in this region. From time to time, we have also let the grass go to meadow, so add to that the timothy, ryegrass and patches of clover, along with the knotweed, crabgrass and dandelion, and you've got the rough texture of the common Northeastern lawn.</p>
        <p>At the beginning of April, though, you wouldn't know any of this. Then the lawn is a swath of brown and mottled dun, disrupted only by broad patches of a washed-out yellow. Even as the days grow longer and the lawn gets more light, it brightens in unpredictable and uneven spots. I am not much of a gardener and even less of a diagnostician. It could be snow mold that the grass suffers from, a deficiency of light, or assorted fungi, or mites and worms. I won't hazard a guess. Still, a glance out the window suggests that this is going to be one of those times when I try to take care of the problem without ever identifying exactly what it is.</p>
        <p>It's not that I aspire to live on a putting green, or want to transform the lawn into a sheet of emerald velvet. Nor am I especially susceptible to the news that April is National Lawn Care Month -- or so says the Professional Lawn Care Association of America.</p>
        <p>In his wide-reaching social and cultural analysis of our lawns and the industry they have spawned, ''American Green: The Obsessive Quest for the Perfect Lawn,'' Ted Steinberg attributes our lawn care mania to assorted factors like the economic imperatives of postwar consumerism, the cold war political climate, the needs of the American family, new understandings of outdoor and indoor space, and a new appreciation for bright colors.</p>
        <p>That may all be true, but there is something else at work here, some innate sense that this little piece of earth that my house -- my life -- rests on should be healthy. And making it so generates an almost primal sense of accomplishment. Or in the words of Jonathan Swift, ''whoever could make two ears of corn or two blades of grass to grow upon a spot of ground where only one grew before, would deserve better of mankind, and do more essential service to his country, than the whole race of politicians put together.''</p>
        <p>The first step toward that end is to rake the grass. This seems an act of faith more than anything else, as if it were possible to simply comb out all the mats and tangles of winter. But the raking sloughs off what is dead and aerates the grass as well, awakening it to the burgeoning light and warmth.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, though, putting the grass to rights is a complex enterprise. As so often in the garden, bringing something back to life necessarily demands a degree of brutality. The entire lawn care industry is there to assist, with its arsenal of pesticides, herbicides and fungicides, all the granules, pellets and powders to kill the rodents and insects, the weeds, the moss and whatever other intrusive agents there are, all of which arrive with a strategic timing that has a near-military precision. Dandelions and other broadleaf greens that thrive in warmer temperatures come up in May, after the crabgrass that is already upon us; each plant of crabgrass has some 10,000 seeds. That has to be the first to go.</p>
        <p>When was the last time you got rid of 10,000 of anything? Such an extravagance of extermination is daunting, and the temptation, of course, is to let it go. There are times when indifference pays off, when neglect can be a virtue.</p>
        <p>Like most people, I am prone to thinking too highly of my interventions. Rather than blanket the grass with a sea of chemicals, why not just recognize the hardy resilience of the grass? Can't it take care of itself? I've been told healthy grass can crowd out the weeds. Let the fine fescue, the knotweed, and the dandelions decide the matter in their own pastoral brawl. And who wouldn't welcome the occasional patch of clover interspersed with the bluegrass? Besides, wasn't it Emerson who asked: ''What is a weed? A plant whose virtues have not yet been discovered.''</p>
        <p>I know, too, that the grass can be renovated simply by overseeding -- that is, mowing the grass short and raking it clean, then scattering seed over what is already there in the hopes that the new seeding will germinate and fill out the sparse areas where the grass has thinned. My friend Jan Axel, who is a landscape designer in South Salem, N.Y., recommends this route, and it seems a gesture that offers greater hope than spreading a synthetic pesticide. ''Then mow high,'' she tells me. ''You're exposing less of the root system that way, so the grass needs less water.''</p>
        <p>In the end, though, I also acquiesce to something called Weed &amp; Feed; even its simple name, brilliant in its reduction, affirms its bipolar character. And while there is something vaguely irritating about its excess of ambition, I can see it is a product that recognizes the full complexity of the task at hand; while its herbicide attacks both the crabgrass and broadleaf weeds, it nonetheless manages to replenish the grass with nitrogen. Its yellow and green bag cheerfully announces that nurturing and destroying can be simultaneous acts, with a label affirming the little riot of horticultural multitasking it is capable of: ''Kills, Thickens, Prevents,'' it reads.</p>
        <p>I am reminded then that April, as well as being National Lawn Care Month, also happens to be National Poetry Month. Makes sense to me. It's not just the simple rhyming in the name of this lawn care product; it's that even in its promotional language, Weed &amp; Feed seems fully engaged with the inventive reach of imagination, the nuance of phrasing and all the subtle contradictions of thought and feeling that are expressed more routinely at the higher reaches of literature. It knows that our small patch of lawn, with its rough texture of the desired and the despised, asks at once for every part of your psyche -- generosity, indifference, ruthlessness. And that cultivating it is like taking care of anything or anyone else you love.</p>
        <p>HOME WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
