<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Talk; Let's Get Genetical</title>
    <meta content="05talk.science.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Talk; Let's Get Genetical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jennifer Kahn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Jennifer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is possible to get many things at the Four Seasons Hotel in Westlake Village, Calif., but a blood-and-urine panel that analyzes the condition of your DNA is a relatively new development. The panel, offered through the California WellBeing Institute as part of several luxury-lifestyle packages, including a $2,800 executive physical, is boomingly popular: about 50 people signed up in January, the first month it was available.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is possible to get many things at the Four Seasons Hotel in Westlake Village, Calif., but a blood-and-urine panel that analyzes the condition of your DNA is a relatively new development. The panel, offered through the California WellBeing Institute as part of several luxury-lifestyle packages, including a $2,800 executive physical, is boomingly popular: about 50 people signed up in January, the first month it was available.</p>
        <p>Four years out from the sequencing of the human genome, DNA has become like the rain forest. Rummage around enough, one suspects, and you can eventually find the source of anything, be it heart-disease risk or unflattering frown lines. But even as research scientists struggle to catalog this elaborate ecosystem, companies selling the promise of genetically customized treatments have rolled out the tent and set up shop.</p>
        <p>At spas, in particular -- where individual skin analyses and bespoke facials are already mandatory -- DNA has been seized upon as the ultimate, and most intimate, evolution in personalized care. In November, the MGM Grand in Las Vegas began offering cheek swabs courtesy of SpaGen, a program devised by a company called Salugen. SpaGen issues dietary recommendations (and hawks supplements) based on minor variations in six genes that have been linked to nutrient metabolism. Dermagenetics in New Jersey bases a genetically derived skin cream on a similar principle.</p>
        <p>There is little proof that such personalized products can make a difference for your health. But it makes sense that they might. Indeed, the general idea -- that thousands of subtle variations in our genetic functions affect both our health and how we age -- is broadly accepted. And while some of these variables may be innate -- about half of us carry a minor permutation that hampers our ability to metabolize folic acid, for instance -- others are simple wear and tear: the result of years of exposure to all the things that can cause DNA to break down, a long list that includes, but isn't limited to, cigarette smoke, sunburn, weed killer, coffee, antibiotics, neoprene and charcoal-grilled steak.</p>
        <p>In theory, knowing how these changes in genetic production affect our overall health could enable us to correct for them. The folic acid permutation, for instance (one of seven gene permutations that SpaGen tests for), cuts our ability to benefit from the vitamin threefold. The solution: triple the amount of folic acid in your vitamin pack.</p>
        <p>According to company literature, such genetically tailored supplements will create a welter of impressive (if not always very specific) benefits, like better bone density and enhanced mental performance. But intuitive as this seems, the biological leap is dodgy. Does taking a vitamin actually increase the amount of folic acid that we can use? Or is the mechanism itself terminally inefficient -- in which case tripling our intake is like dumping extra boxes on an assembly line with two employees? And what if we have another gene that somehow compensates for the first one?</p>
        <p>Dr. Andrew Conrad, who runs the WellBeing Institute, has a low opinion of the SpaGen approach. But he adds that complexities like these bedevil any attempt to link DNA biochemistry and health. ''We don't know how clinically relevant all of this is yet,'' he admits. Nonetheless, he remarks, ''there are consumers who are interested.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Conrad is more worried that the WellBeing Institute's test, which promises to ''link your lifestyle choices to the rate of your DNA damage,'' will be lumped in with companies that claim to create DNA-based diets and skin creams. ''What we do -- this is not Wacky McNut-Nut,'' Conrad explains. ''We have $6 million worth of equipment in the basement.''</p>
        <p>Located half an hour outside of L.A., the WellBeing Institute is a luxurious place to get blood drawn. Illuminated glass panes and botanical prints warm the halls, which are populated by doctors whose caseloads seem enviably light. (While I'm there, one wanders through the empty foyer and offers to fetch me a coffee.) Other amenities include valet parking, an on-site CT scanner and magnetic resonance imager, and private waiting rooms. ''We get a lot of famous people who may be creeped out by seeing other people,'' Conrad explains.</p>
        <p>In addition to overseeing the WellBeing Institute's foray into genetics, Conrad also co-founded the lab that analyzes the test results: the National Genetics Institute (NGI), a subsidiary of LabCorp. Blond and restless in a Southern California way (he surfs and drives a black Maserati), Conrad notes that the idea of attempting to measure a person's rate of genetic damage was inspired by the insurance giant WellPoint, which was looking for a way to motivate patients to adopt healthier lifestyles.</p>
        <p>NGI had previously analyzed results for the clinical trial of a hepatitis C drug with unpleasant side effects, and one thing researchers discovered was that when patients were allowed to track their viral load -- to see how it went up or down, based on their behavior -- they took their medication more reliably. Conrad dreamed up a corollary: if ordinary people could watch the genetic damage that accrues from eating Ho Hos, they would change how they ate.</p>
        <p>''It's like a bathtub,'' Conrad explains. ''The tub is your accumulated amount of DNA damage. So what controls that? There's the faucet: the rate of damage going in. That's stuff like smoking, sunbathing, eating pesticides.</p>
        <p>On the other end, there's the drain. That's your body's ability to repair the damage.'' There's also a third variable, sensitivity, or how likely one's DNA is to break under stress, which Conrad likens to the height of the tub. If your DNA breaks easily, your tub will fill -- and ultimately overflow, in the form of cancers and other ailments -- that much sooner.</p>
        <p>The interaction between these three results, he asserts, provides a snapshot of your genetic health: how much damage you're doing, and how easily you're able to bounce back. ''Everybody has that crazy uncle who smoked and sunbathed and lived to be 95,'' Conrad says. ''How'd he do it? He may have had a huge drain.''</p>
        <p>For anyone not endowed with a prodigious drain, presumably the only option is to turn down the faucet -- the amount of free radical damage. In the body, free radicals injure cells by reacting with guanine, one of the four basic components of DNA, and transforming it into 8-hydroxy-2-deoxyguanosine (8oxodg for short). According to Conrad, as the body's genetic repair system kicks in, it snips off the aberrant 8oxodg segment, which washes out in urine. The higher your 8oxodg count, in other words, the more oxidative damage your body is experiencing.</p>
        <p>What makes this measure so useful, Conrad believes, is that it's extraordinarily sensitive to various outside factors. Smoking a cigarette, for instance, will cause your 8oxodg rates to spike almost immediately. So does a bad sunburn. (''Whether you bake yourself inside or out, it's going to come out in your pee,'' Conrad remarks cheerfully.)</p>
        <p>Then there's what Conrad calls ''the Merry Christmas phenomenon.'' He flips to a pair of graphs that belong to a husband and wife</p>
        <p>who had their urine analyzed at least once a month for a year. Both have identical Christmas-tree-shaped spikes in their otherwise level charts. ''The holidays,'' Conrad says significantly. ''Eating sugary food really makes your 8oxodg shoot up.''</p>
        <p>Why pumpkin pie would have such an effect is unknown, though Conrad thinks that the insulin rush could spur activity in some genes and inhibit other ones -- and that the on-off action renders areas of the genome more vulnerable. (Dr. Jeff Albrecht, who handles the laboratory processing of the tests, puts it differently. He argues that junk food dramatically boosts metabolic activity, and thus free radical production, without supplying compensatory antioxidants, the way vegetables would.)</p>
        <p>Part of what makes the question confounding is that free radicals are produced in the body, naturally, all the time. (When mitochondria convert food to energy, for instance, free radicals are one of the main byproducts.) Externally, oxidative boosters include everything from obesity to over-exercise.</p>
        <p>This hints at a larger problem, which is significant: at present, no one has any idea what the normal range of 8oxodg is -- or even whether a high measure is necessarily bad.</p>
        <p>One theory holds that 8oxodg might actually be a positive byproduct, signaling an efficient repair system rather than an unusually high level of damage.</p>
        <p>''There's a long history of people measuring oxidative byproducts in urine,'' notes Dr. Bruce Demple, a Harvard University biochemist who studies free radical damage and repair. ''The upshot, so far, is that it's not very telling.''</p>
        <p>There are other mysteries as well. Conrad notes that if you exercise vigorously once -- running a marathon, say -- you'll get an 8oxodg spike. But if you exercise vigorously and consistently, the measure will level out. This is true for worse behaviors as well. Eat junk for a week, and your 8oxodg count will rise. Eat badly all the time, and eventually it will normalize.</p>
        <p>Why this happens is not clear. Conrad notes that the body may start operating at a chronically higher repair rate, to keep the cellular damage level in a normal range.</p>
        <p>This, in turn, could be bad -- a sign that the body is overtaxed. Or it might not be. There's even a possibility that free radicals themselves aren't as damaging as people think. A recent study on naked mole rats showed that they have naturally high levels of oxidative damage -- yet they remain one of the longest-lived rodents.</p>
        <p>Conrad acknowledges this, adding, ''That's exactly the kind of thing we're trying to find out.'' He notes that the Institute intends to launch a series of clinical trials that will evaluate the 8oxodg levels of tanning-bed users, smokers and people in radiation therapy. (Although the Institute doesn't advertise this widely, clients who wish to can skip the $2,800 executive physical and simply enroll in one of the trials as a control.)</p>
        <p>Until the results from those and more studies come in, the WellBeing Institute's test remains essentially a motivator: a genetic Santa that brings the gift of kale. ''Maybe you'll smoke a little less, or eat a little better,'' Conrad says hopefully. ''I can't say how much that will do, but I do know it won't hurt.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
