<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anna Nicole's Lawyer? Crooner? Yeah, Same Guy</title>
    <meta content="15licolLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15licol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Anna Nicole</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leeds, Lenard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDB123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anna Nicole's Lawyer? Crooner? Yeah, Same Guy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anna Nicole’s Lawyer? Crooner? Yeah, Same Guy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robin Finn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>CARLE PLACE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robin Finn The Island column on lawyer Lenard Leeds, 54, of Carle Place, NY, whose high-profile clients included Anna Nicole Smith, and who moonlights as crooner; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST think of him, if you get goose bumps from ''Cara Mia'' sung the old-fashioned way, as the singing lawyer who got Jay Black's mojo, and moniker, back for him.</p>
        <p>Looking cabaret-ready in his shiny blue shirt and Bulgari cufflinks, Lenard Leeds, 54 and fey about defying it, is a ringer for Regis around the eyes and a dead ringer for Manilow when he opens his mouth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lenard Leeds, a celebrity-friendly litigation lawyer whose prize client was Anna Nicole Smith, is a lounge lizard in the making.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST think of him, if you get goose bumps from ''Cara Mia'' sung the old-fashioned way, as the singing lawyer who got Jay Black's mojo, and moniker, back for him.</p>
        <p>Looking cabaret-ready in his shiny blue shirt and Bulgari cufflinks, Lenard Leeds, 54 and fey about defying it, is a ringer for Regis around the eyes and a dead ringer for Manilow when he opens his mouth.</p>
        <p>Which happens constantly, whether Mr. Leeds is in court (guess which infuriated Long Island lawyer sued Cablevision when it would not broadcast Yankees games, got Nassau County's assets frozen when it balked at paying damages to a gay police officer, and is mulling an age-discrimination suit against ''American Idol'') or on CD (his latest: ''Love Will See Us Through: From Lawsuits  to Love Songs'').</p>
        <p>Combine a celebrity-friendly litigation lawyer -- Anna Nicole Smith was Mr. Leeds's prize client; in recent weeks he has made the talk show rounds, commenting on the posthumous paternity suit shenanigans involving her -- with a lounge lizard in the making, and the rhetoric flows like, uh, music.</p>
        <p>Or Muzak. Mr. Leeds is a child of the Anka/Sedaka era; he insists that adoration, not audacity, moved him to record ''Len Leeds Sings Sinatra'' as his music business icebreaker. A logical midlife crisis maneuver. ''I didn't think I could be him, but if I think he's the best, why not sing his songs?'' Mr. Leeds reasons.</p>
        <p>He has been an opening act for veterans like Tony Bennett (his advice to the rookie from Old Westbury: ''Kid, keep on plugging''), Tony Orlando, Dionne Warwick and Neil Sedaka since reinventing himself as a singer at age 50 and moonlighting on whatever stage will have him. Best payday, $7,500, not that he's in this for the dough. His day job covers that.</p>
        <p>''Age Is Just a Number'' is Mr. Leeds's theme song; he wrote and is living it.</p>
        <p>''I run into people my age who are, say, plastic surgeons or dentists,'' he says, ''and they tell me, 'Gee, I've always wanted to be a ski instructor,' or whatever, and I tell them: 'Go for it! Life is short!' You never know how much time you have left.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leeds steps behind, but does not sit at, the capacious desk at Leeds Morelli &amp; Brown, his baronial law office on the busy northern fringe of the Roosevelt Field mall, and gives his throat a momentous clearing.</p>
        <p>Then he embarks -- tunefully, just the way he does in his act -- on the embellished tale of how he got Jay Black's stage name back. It happened just in time for Mr. Black, the Woodbury resident and '60s crooner whose real name is David Blatt and who inundated AM radio with hits like ''Cara Mia'' and ''This Magic Moment,'' to celebrate his 45th year in show business April 14 at the North Fork Theater at Westbury.</p>
        <p>''A year ago a man came into my office and told me this horrific story,'' Mr. Leeds says. ''He said, 'I'm involved in some litigation, and the court took away my name.' I said: 'That's impossible! How could a court take away the name of somebody who's had 23 hits, 5 No. 1's! You've been Jay Black for 30 years!'</p>
        <p>''Anyway, we went before the court and got to the summation, and I said, 'Judge, this case is so important, I'd like to do something unique: sing the summation.' She said, 'Mr. Leeds, where do you think you are, in a nightclub or in a courtroom?' ''</p>
        <p>Long story short: he belts out ''I've Gotta Be Me.''</p>
        <p>Real story: Last year, with Mr. Black's assets (including his stage name and the band's name, Jay and the Americans) tied up in bankruptcy proceedings, he was forced to bill himself only as ''Jay is Back!'' at Westbury, where he has been a headliner for decades. Belittling. Mr. Leeds learned of the singer's plight from an acquaintance of Mr. Black's while exercising at the gym, where he had lately removed 30 pounds (singers in tuxedos should be svelte).</p>
        <p>In December, with Mr. Leeds negotiating, Mr. Black, 68, bought back his professional name from the court for $214,000; the band name was purchased by a former bandmate who hired a different Jay as its front man. Mr. Leeds refers to that band as an impostor. ''Jay Black had all the hits,'' he says.</p>
        <p>The opener for Jay Black's band at Westbury? A no-brainer: my lawyer, my opening act.</p>
        <p>One last snippet from Mr. Leeds's act: ''There I was in Texas with my client, the Playmate of the Year, Anna Nicole Smith; her 90-year-old husband, Howard Marshall; and his son, Pierce,'' he says, ''and Pierce turned to me and said, 'Len, as long as I'm alive, Anna Nicole will never get one nickel from my father's estate,' and Mr. Marshall turned to me and said, 'Len, now that my life is drawing to a close, please Len, do me a favor,' '' he says, gearing up for his segue. ''And that's when I start singing, 'Take good care, of my, baaaaa-beeee!' Hopefully, it'll come off nicely.''</p>
        <p>If not, there's always that lien he filed for his share of Ms. Smith's estate. Law degrees have their upside.</p>
        <p>THE ISLAND E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
