<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Merchants Brace for a Local Big Dig</title>
    <meta content="15merc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/thecity/15merc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLUSHING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Flushing (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vandam, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7D6133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Merchants Brace for a Local Big Dig</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Merchants Brace for a Local Big Dig</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF VANDAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vandam, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Merchants on Union Street in Flushing, Queens, protest against Flushing Commons, $500 million commercial and residential development slated to replace municipal parking lot that they say could mean demise of their businesses; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the hair salons, sushi academies, travel agencies and driving schools stuffed into a densely occupied block of Union Street in Flushing, the eye nearly misses the maroon awning over Rim's Fine Jewelry, embossed with the image of a large diamond.</p>
        <p>The store, which houses a small family business more than three decades old, specializes in selling tiny gold rings that are given to Korean children. It is sandwiched between a noodle house and a Korean barbecue place, and it sits below Bethel Business Accounting, whose window also advertises the services of a tarot card reader.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the hair salons, sushi academies, travel agencies and driving schools stuffed into a densely occupied block of Union Street in Flushing, the eye nearly misses the maroon awning over Rim’s Fine Jewelry, embossed with the image of a large diamond.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among the hair salons, sushi academies, travel agencies and driving schools stuffed into a densely occupied block of Union Street in Flushing, the eye nearly misses the maroon awning over Rim's Fine Jewelry, embossed with the image of a large diamond.</p>
        <p>The store, which houses a small family business more than three decades old, specializes in selling tiny gold rings that are given to Korean children. It is sandwiched between a noodle house and a Korean barbecue place, and it sits below Bethel Business Accounting, whose window also advertises the services of a tarot card reader.</p>
        <p>Despite the jewelry store's size, its manager, a 35-year-old South Korean immigrant named Ikhwan Rim, is one of the local merchants protesting loudest about Flushing Commons, a $500 million commercial and residential development proposed for the neighborhood. The project, which will include a movie theater, a hotel, condominiums and new shops, will replace a 1,100-space municipal parking lot.</p>
        <p>Final approval from city commissions is still required, but the project has been praised by Mayor Bloomberg and other elected officials. Construction could start next year and is scheduled to take three years.</p>
        <p>And that, Mr. Rim said, will be a problem.</p>
        <p>''For three years while they're building, you're not going to have any parking lot,'' he said the other day. ''Nobody will come here to our restaurants. They won't come to our jewelry stores.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rim, whose monthly rent is $4,500, offers a grim prediction as to whether his store will survive. ''A lot of us will not make it,'' he said gloomily. ''Not even three months.''</p>
        <p>The blocklong stretch of Union Street where Mr. Rim's store is, between Northern Boulevard and 37th Avenue, is home to more than 100 tiny businesses, whose owners represent a United Nations of backgrounds. Many share space to survive; the sight of four or five shops crowded into a single storefront or two-story building is common. Though the developers of Flushing Commons have pledged to help get financial assistance for the affected stores during construction, many business owners are worried.</p>
        <p>Local officials acknowledge that even under the best circumstances, a rocky time lies ahead for the small merchants.</p>
        <p>''These are our best efforts,'' said City Councilman John Liu, who represents the area, ''but of course nothing could provide a scenario that simulates no construction.''</p>
        <p>Andrew Brent, a spokesman for the city's Economic Development Corporation, said residents of the future apartments in Flushing Commons would help nearby businesses, injecting money into the local economy. Details of an assistance program are not yet final, he said, but it will most likely involve alternative parking space and signs to help existing shops retain customers. Flushing Commons itself will contain 1,600 spaces, but some will be earmarked for businesses and residents in the complex.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rim has already begun exploring other ways to ensure his survival. He has started dabbling in gold coins and wholesale jewelry sales. But he remains worried about the health of his store and the dozens like it nearby.</p>
        <p>''Dynamic Koreans, Chinese, Indians -- this is what Flushing is about,'' he said. ''We built this. Now this big project with developers came in on this parking lot and they say, 'We're taking over now.' ''</p>
        <p>JEFF VANDAM</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: FLUSHING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
