<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Rest For a Russian Renegade</title>
    <meta content="15good" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/arts/dance/15good.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Elfman Ballet of St Petersburg</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodwin, Joy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elfman, Boris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Eifman, Boris</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1D7153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Rest For a Russian Renegade</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Rest for a Russian Renegade</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOY GOODWIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodwin, Joy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles Russian choreographer Boris Elfman, whose Elfman Ballet of St. Petersburg will perform at City Center; fights with Russian bureaucracy and changes that have taken place in Russia described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SOVIET-ERA film clip of a rehearsal of the Leningrad Ballet Ensemble shows the choreographer Boris Eifman at work on a duet for his 1987 ballet, ''The Master and Margarita.'' Dressed in black, his intense face framed by a shock of black curls and a dark beard, Mr. Eifman hovers over his two dancers, instructing and explaining with evident passion.</p>
        <p>''I would like some heavier poses,'' he says, dramatically bending his neck to one side to demonstrate. He urges the woman to hold the man's neck just so. ''You are carrying his life in the palm of your hand,'' he tells her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The battle over “Pink Floyd” and other war tales from Boris Eifman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SOVIET-ERA film clip of a rehearsal of the Leningrad Ballet Ensemble shows the choreographer Boris Eifman at work on a duet for his 1987 ballet, ''The Master and Margarita.'' Dressed in black, his intense face framed by a shock of black curls and a dark beard, Mr. Eifman hovers over his two dancers, instructing and explaining with evident passion.</p>
        <p>''I would like some heavier poses,'' he says, dramatically bending his neck to one side to demonstrate. He urges the woman to hold the man's neck just so. ''You are carrying his life in the palm of your hand,'' he tells her.</p>
        <p>This month in Midtown Manhattan Mr. Eifman again stood with his back to studio mirrors, rehearsing his dancers in one of the four ballets that the 45-member Eifman Ballet of St. Petersburg is performing during its two-and-a-half-week engagement at City Center, which opened on Friday. His distinctive locks and beard were gray, his body a bit stouter and less nimble. But his zeal was unmistakably the same.</p>
        <p>''You have to hold each pose,'' he shouted over the recorded music, propelling his 60-year-old body into action to indicate the phrasing he wanted. The dancers, leggy and rail-thin, watched intently. ''Don't rush,'' he warned as they began anew. ''It shouldn't be smudged.''</p>
        <p>Dramatic movements and clear-cut poses have always been hallmarks of Mr. Eifman's company, which celebrates its 30th anniversary this year. Theatrical glitter has been another constant: extravagant sets and costumes and an often spectacular use of lighting and stage effects.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eifman has also typically chosen tragic psychological narratives for his ballets, from tales of heroes and heroines trapped in asylums (''Red Giselle,'' ''Don Quixote,'' ''The Master and Margarita'') to sagas of characters crushed by their societies (''Anna Karenina,'' ''Tchaikovsky,'' ''Russian Hamlet''). And from the beginning his work has split audiences and critics into galvanized camps, those who adore his ballets and those who avoid them.</p>
        <p>The Siberian-born Mr. Eifman, a promising graduate of the Leningrad Conservatory, was appointed director of the little-known Leningrad Ballet Ensemble at 30, in 1977. And if much has remained constant over the last three decades, much has also changed.</p>
        <p>''The life of my company can really be divided into three decades,'' Mr. Eifman said one recent afternoon through an interpreter, ''the Soviet period, the perestroika era and the last 10 years.''</p>
        <p>Sitting at a cafe table, sipping a cappuccino, he spoke more softly than in rehearsal but with the same youthful earnestness. The timing of his career, Mr. Eifman acknowledged, had played a crucial part in his success. Unlike his mentor, the much-praised, much-censored experimental choreographer Leonid Jakobson, Mr. Eifman came along when the regime's cultural restrictions were beginning to loosen. ''It's my huge luck that I was born 40 years later than Jakobson,'' he said. ''Because Jakobson only fought. But I had the opportunity not only to fight but to win.''</p>
        <p>Yet in 1977 Mr. Eifman's prospects didn't look much brighter than Mr. Jakobson's had. Like his mentor Mr. Eifman managed to secure his own small Leningrad ballet company. But even before its first performance he found himself battling cultural bureaucrats over his choice of music for one dance on the program: Pink Floyd, ''then highly unwelcome,'' he said. Mr. Eifman threatened to cancel his sold-out concert if he couldn't perform the piece. Half an hour before curtain he received permission to do it -- once.</p>
        <p>Political gamesmanship demanded much of Mr. Eifman's energy in his company's first decade. State committees reviewed his ballets before they were shown to the public, often blocking or editing them. More than once officials threatened to close down the company. When his troupe went abroad, he was denied a travel visa.</p>
        <p>But he persisted in pursuing controversial subjects. He explored eroticism onstage and dared to create a ballet about life in the Soviet Army. Not surprisingly cultural authorities often called him into their offices.</p>
        <p>''I would be told that my kind of art was not Soviet art, that it was not choreography, that I was doing but pornography,'' Mr. Eifman said. ''They said that it would be best if I left, and that, as at that time Jews were being allowed to emigrate to the United States, they were ready to let me go at any moment.''</p>
        <p>Instead he stayed and built his company. Despite its lack of name-brand classics, his provocative young troupe packed big theaters in cities across the Soviet Union; one year it performed 150 tour dates. Touring was critical to shore up popular support and finance the fledgling company, which had minimal state support and no fixed rehearsal space. With the honorariums from tours Mr. Eifman paid his dancers and rented gymnasiums by the hour.</p>
        <p>He served as the troupe's sole choreographer, as well as administrator, teacher, recruiter, marketer and government liaison. ''A lot of his ballets are about the lonely creator,'' said Nina Alovert, a ballet photographer and journalist who met Mr. Eifman in the early 1970s, ''the artist who is a dreamer, who's not like everyone else. I think that's what Boris feels, that all his life he's been trying to do something against the grain.''</p>
        <p>By 1986, doubting that he could go on much longer, Mr. Eifman decided to create the ballet he assumed would destroy his theater, ''The Master and Margarita.''</p>
        <p>''I staged a very sincere ballet,'' he said. ''I showed the mental institution where the dissident is taken to have his thoughts suppressed. And there was no question in my mind, after that I wouldn't be allowed to continue working.''</p>
        <p>Yet at the exact moment that he finished it, in 1987, perestroika was taking root. ''When I showed my ballet to the commission,'' Mr. Eifman recalled with a wry smile, ''the panel said, 'Oh, it's a work of art of the new Russia.' '' He added, ''Overnight I went from dissident to people's hero.''</p>
        <p>That success ushered in a period of transformation that lasted through 1997. For the first time Mr. Eifman was able to create ballets freely, even on subjects previously off limits, like homosexuality (in ''Tchaikovsky,'' 1993). In 1988 the state granted the company its own rehearsal space, and state financing remained stable even after the collapse of the Soviet Union in 1991.</p>
        <p>A new generation of dancers arrived, and with them the Eifman style was forged. It was bold, psychological and highly theatrical, and its off-kilter classical movement was performed by expressive actor-dancers who transmitted what he called ''a new kind of emotional energy'' onstage.</p>
        <p>A phone call from the arts promoter Sergei Danilian in 1996 heralded a third era. The company had already been touring in Europe; now Mr. Danilian proposed to introduce Boris Eifman to the United States market.</p>
        <p>''I thought of the American model of companies led by one artist -- Paul Taylor, Martha Graham, '' Mr. Danilian said. ''So I asked him, could we call the company Eifman Ballet of St. Petersburg?''</p>
        <p>In 1998 the company began what would become a regular tour of American cities, presenting a series of evening-length ballets that more often than not pitted the individual against the system. If that theme remains dearer to Mr. Eifman's heart than it might to choreographers raised under different circumstances, it also resonates with the legions of Russian-born immigrants who are among his staunchest admirers. They have been known to arrive at his American concerts carrying programs from Eifman ballets they attended in the Soviet Union more than 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>The third decade, Mr. Eifman stressed, has brought its own pressures. Despite receiving more substantial state financing than in the past, the company maintains a heavy foreign touring schedule, to subsidize his lavish productions and to supplement his artists' salaries, ''relieving them,'' he said, ''of the necessity to emigrate.'' And he remains heavily involved with administrative duties, including the creation of two major new projects: a dance academy planned for 2009 and a home theater for the company, its first, to be built by 2012 as part of a major redevelopment project in St. Petersburg.</p>
        <p>But most daunting is the responsibility of creating new ballets. To celebrate the company's 30th anniversary Mr. Eifman decided to risk a Chekhov adaptation. His new ballet, ''The Seagull,'' with Chekhov's two clashing writers transformed into choreographers, will have its New York premiere on Wednesday. To Mr. Eifman it is one of his most experimental works.</p>
        <p>''I put so much of who I am in this work, of my life in theater for the last 30 years,'' he said. When he was starting out, he added, he was like the young writer Konstantin Treplev in Chekhov's play. ''I rebelled against the successful art of the Bolshoi and the Kirov, and I thought it was all up to me to bring new ideas and new forms that could move the art forward.''</p>
        <p>In the last few years, Mr. Eifman noted, as his company acquired more success, he had instead begun to identify with the play's older writer, Boris Trigorin. ''Because for me,'' Mr. Eifman said, ''Trigorin is not somebody who rested on his laurels but a person who's still a seeker. He's still looking for innovative forms of expression.''</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
