<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pedicure Junction</title>
    <meta content="05remix.feet.pedicure.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE REMIX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="381" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pedicure Junction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Fiorella Valdesolo</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Did you know that your feet have 500,000 sweat glands? No wonder they . . . well, you know . . .</p>
        <p>Fiorella Valdesolo</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Did you know that your feet have 500,000 sweat glands? No wonder they . . . well, you know . . .</p>
        <p>Fiorella Valdesolo</p>
        <p>To get rid of yellow nails (from red polish), make a paste out of hydrogen peroxide and baking soda, leave on a few minutes, then scrub and rinse off. -- Deborah Hardwick, founder of BuffSpa</p>
        <p>The best candidates for toe shortening are those with painful hammertoes, usually on the second and third toes, according to the podiatrist Dr. Suzanne Levine, who performs the procedure not only to allow for the wearing of stilettos but also to remove a source of horrible, shooting pain.</p>
        <p>''I think the primary cause of foot odor is poor diet. . . . High amounts of refined carbohydrates and fermented products. The second-most common cause is stress.'' -- Dr. Robert Kornfeld, integrative podiatrist</p>
        <p>Famous foot fetishists: Charles Baudelaire; Giacomo Casanova; F. Scott Fitzgerald; Johann Wolfgang von Goethe; King Ludwig I of Bavaria</p>
        <p>''Cracked heels are the most common foot issue we see. I always recommend Diamancel No. 11 Tough Buffer, which is an investment, because it's made of diamond dust and will last forever.'' -- Donna Perillo, owner of Sweet Lily Nail Spa and Boutique</p>
        <p>Nail-salon favorites: Hit Me With Your Best Shot (Lippman); Chinatown (NARS); Lincoln Park After Dark (Opi); Wicked (Essie); Black Satin (Chanel); Film Noir (Rescue)</p>
        <p>The ideal length of a bound foot was three inches. When, in 1911, the custom was ended, ''few realized that the pain of release would match what had been endured when the growing feet were first bound.'' -- ''The Chinese Century: The Photographic History of the Last Hundred Years''</p>
        <p>In Thailand and various Arab countries, exposing the sole of your foot can be considered offensive.</p>
        <p>''You never want your toenail to be longer than the edge of your toe.'' -- Deborah Lippmann, celebrity manicurist</p>
        <p>The sole is home to the body's thickest layers of skin and the least amount of pigment, and is one of only two body parts unable to grow hair. (The other? The palm.)</p>
        <p>A number of illnesses, including diabetes, arthritis and circulatory problems, can make their first appearance here.</p>
        <p>Since your feet swell throughout the course of the day, never shop for shoes in the morning.</p>
        <p>''Shrimping'' is slang for toe sucking.</p>
        <p>THE REMIX</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
