<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Motorists, Take Note: The Bike Path Is Complete</title>
    <meta content="15litopicLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15litopic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RECREATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DB123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Motorists, Take Note: The Bike Path Is Complete</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Motorists, Take Note: The Bike Path Is Complete</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Workers put final touches on 85-mile-long bike path along Route 25A and Route 25 between Cold Spring Harbor and Orient Point; path, proposed by former Gov George Pataki, is Long Island's first long-distance bike route; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AN 85-mile stretch of roads designated as a bicycle path has been in the works for two years. Now state workers have put up the last green and white signs to mark it, Long Island's first long-distance bike route.</p>
        <p>The route runs along the shoulders of 18 miles of Route 25A and 67 miles of Route 25 -- both state roads -- with periodic detours. The winding path runs between the Long Island Rail Road station at Cold Spring Harbor and the Orient Point ferry terminal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An 85-mile stretch of roads designated as a bicycle path, Long Island’s first long-distance bike route, is now complete.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AN 85-mile stretch of roads designated as a bicycle path has been in the works for two years. Now state workers have put up the last green and white signs to mark it, Long Island's first long-distance bike route.</p>
        <p>The route runs along the shoulders of 18 miles of Route 25A and 67 miles of Route 25 -- both state roads -- with periodic detours. The winding path runs between the Long Island Rail Road station at Cold Spring Harbor and the Orient Point ferry terminal.</p>
        <p>Eileen W. Peters, a spokeswoman for the State Department of Transportation, said the idea for a bike route on Long Island came from former Gov. George E. Pataki.</p>
        <p>''On the 10th anniversary of the opening of the bike route along Route 9 upstate, he pledged to move forward with a similar extensive bike route on Long Island,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peters said the route was projected as a safe path for recreational cyclists, who might detour to villages like Port Jefferson and Stony Brook, as well as for commuters.</p>
        <p>The signs, the last of which were put in place on Feb. 28, are posted every half-mile and have a bicycle icon that Ms. Peters said was designed ''to help protect bicyclists and alert motorists that they now have to share the road.''</p>
        <p>The signs include distances to communities along the route and point cyclists to train stations.</p>
        <p>''Cyclicts who want to ride only one way or who get tired and don't want to complete the route can carry their bikes on the train,'' Ms. Peters said, adding that an annual permit from the Department of Transportation's Bike and Ride program is available for $20.</p>
        <p>Richard Partenfelder, owner of the Cycle Company in Smithtown, which the path runs through, said the bike signs along the route are clear, well marked and easy to follow.</p>
        <p>But he was uncertain whether the route would encourage more Long Islanders to cycle.</p>
        <p>''I think the path will be helpful for recreational cyclists and may encourage more people to use their bikes,'' Mr. Partenfelder said. ''I doubt that it will make a big difference in getting people to commute by bike to work, but it can't hurt.''</p>
        <p>Bill Selsky, the president of the 700-member Long Island Bicycle Club, called the route ''a step in the right direction,'' even though it is ''not a real bike path through the woods or cut off from traffic.''</p>
        <p>''Many of us ride in groups and are visible to drivers,'' he said, ''but for those who ride alone, the signs will be a protection to warn motorists to watch out.''</p>
        <p>The only interruption along the route is a 1.5-mile gap in Smithtown, where state officials determined that traffic was too heavy or the road too narrow to allow bicyclists.</p>
        <p>''Safety was the prime factor in developing the route,'' Ms. Peters said. ''Along that stretch, cyclists can either walk their bikes or take their own paths.''</p>
        <p>There are also small detours along half the route to keep cyclists away from heavy traffic, she said.</p>
        <p>Additional bike routes are on the horizon.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peters said Nassau County was more of a challenge because it is more congested, but by the end of the summer, a separate path for cyclists, runners and skaters will be completed along Route 24, linking the Village of Hempstead's downtown with Hofstra University, Nassau Community College and Eisenhower Park.</p>
        <p>Also planned are an extension of the Bethpage bike route onto local roads, and a 16-mile Ocean Parkway route that will connect to the Wantagh bike path and run between Jones Beach and Captree State Park.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
