<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marines' Actions Called Excessive In Afghanistan</title>
    <meta content="15afghan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/world/asia/15afghan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nangarhar Province (Afghanistan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Afghan Independent Human Rights Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Marine Corps</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E3D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marines' Actions Called Excessive In Afghanistan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Marines’ Actions in Afghanistan Called Excessive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>KABUL, Afghanistan, April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report published by Afghan Independent Human Rights Commission says American marines reacted with excessive force to suicide bomb ambush in Nangarhar Province in March; says marines hit groups of bystanders and vehicles with machine gun fire in series of attacks over 10 miles of highway that left 12 civilians dead; report condemns suicide attack and acknowledges that there might have been small arms fire directed at marines' convoy; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American marines reacted to a bomb ambush with excessive force in eastern Afghanistan last month, hitting groups of bystanders and vehicles with machine-gun fire in a series of attacks that covered 10 miles of highway and left 12 civilians dead, including an infant and three elderly men, according to a report published by an Afghan human rights commission on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Families of the victims described in interviews this week the painful toll of the attacks, which took place on March 4 in Nangarhar Province. One victim, a 16-year-old newly married girl, was cut down while she was carrying a bundle of grass to her family's farmhouse, according to her family and the report. A 75-year-old man walking to his shop was hit by so many bullets that his son said he did not recognize the body when he came to the scene.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>American marines reacted to a bomb ambush with excessive force, shooting bystanders, a report said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American marines reacted to a bomb ambush with excessive force in eastern Afghanistan last month, hitting groups of bystanders and vehicles with machine-gun fire in a series of attacks that covered 10 miles of highway and left 12 civilians dead, including an infant and three elderly men, according to a report published by an Afghan human rights commission on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Families of the victims described in interviews this week the painful toll of the attacks, which took place on March 4 in Nangarhar Province. One victim, a 16-year-old newly married girl, was cut down while she was carrying a bundle of grass to her family's farmhouse, according to her family and the report. A 75-year-old man walking to his shop was hit by so many bullets that his son said he did not recognize the body when he came to the scene.</p>
        <p>In its report, the Afghan Independent Human Rights Commission condemned the suicide bomb attack that started the episode, striking a Marine Special Operations unit convoy and slightly wounding one American. And the report said there might also have been small arms fire directed at the convoy immediately after the blast. But it said the response was disproportionate, especially given the obviously nonmilitary nature of the marines' targets long after the ambush.</p>
        <p>''In failing to distinguish between civilians and legitimate military targets, the U.S. Marine Corps Special Forces employed indiscriminate force,'' the report said. ''Their actions thus constitute a serious violation of international humanitarian standards.''</p>
        <p>In the weeks immediately after the episode, the United States military began an investigation, and it is now exploring possible criminal charges, senior military officials said. The marines involved in the episode are being kept in Afghanistan, but the rest of their 120-man company has been pulled out of the country.</p>
        <p>[The Washington Post reported late Saturday that a preliminary United States investigation had found that the people who were killed and injured were civilians, and that there was no evidence that the marines involved had come under small arms fire after the bombing.</p>
        <p>[The preliminary findings were reported by Army Maj. Gen. Francis H. Kearney III, the commander of Special Operations troops in the Middle East and Central Asia, who ordered a formal investigation in March, The Post reported.]</p>
        <p>An American spokesman in Afghanistan, Lt. Col. David A. Accetta, said Saturday that the military was in the final stages of approving condolence payments for families of the wounded and dead in the shootings.</p>
        <p>The events have had the highest profile of a number of potential human rights violations by both sides, many by the Taliban and its allies, in the fighting in Afghanistan that were documented by the Afghan commission, which was established after the Taliban's ouster and is partly financed by Congress. The commission's report comes amid resurgent Taliban violence and coalition reprisals that are costing an increasing number of civilian lives and that have brought harsh criticism of international forces in the country.</p>
        <p>The deputy director of the human rights commission, Nader Nadery, warned that attacks like the highway shooting had greatly contributed to outrage in Afghanistan, contradicting efforts by coalition forces to win people's support away from the Taliban. ''This is not an isolated case'' he said. ''People are realizing more that they are a victim of the conflict from both sides, from the Taliban and from the international operations.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''What we identified throughout all our investigation is a high level of frustration among the public and among the civilians.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the United States Central Command said the Afghan commission's report had been forwarded to Adm. William J. Fallon, the senior American officer in the region, for review.</p>
        <p>In Washington, the chairman of the House subcommittee that oversees American Special Operations forces said Saturday that he was concerned by the information gathered so far, but that he had received assurances that a thorough military investigation was under way.</p>
        <p>''It is a very serious matter, and the evidence is troubling,'' said the chairman, Representative Adam Smith, Democrat of Washington.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview from his home in Tacoma, Wash., Mr. Smith added: ''There should be a full and complete investigation, and the military is doing that. That is the purpose of the report done by the Special Operations component of the Central Command.''</p>
        <p>Anger and frustration over the shooting was evident in Spinpul, where the attack happened, and in the whole province of Nangarhar. Still mourning, the families of the victims said this week that they had demanded from President Hamid Karzai and the American generals they had met that those responsible be punished. Some of them said the soldiers should be tried under Islamic law and face the death penalty if found guilty of the killings.</p>
        <p>''They committed a great cruelty; they should be punished,'' said Gharghashta, 65, whose daughter-in-law was killed at the door of their farmhouse compound, several hundred yards from the road and the scene of the blast. The American troops were firing from the road and raked the river bed where workers were digging a ditch and the surrounding fields with gunfire, he and other witnesses said.</p>
        <p>''She was cutting grass in the field and she was carrying the bundle of grass on her head back into the house for the animals,'' said his eldest son, Abdel Muhammad, 25.</p>
        <p>''There was a big blast and then I heard firing. I started walking toward my house,'' he said. ''When I reached the house, my sister called and said my sister-in-law had been killed,'' he said. The young woman, Yadwaro, 16, was shot in the back and fell dead across the threshold, he said. Her husband, Tera Gul, 18, sat listening silently to his brother and then got up and walked away.</p>
        <p>The suicide bomb attack happened 500 yards along the road from the bridge that gives the village its name, White Bridge, on the main highway 25 miles east of Jalalabad. A man driving a minibus in the opposite direction to the Marine unit exploded his vehicle as he passed the convoy of five or six Humvees, according to the commission's report, which was drawn from interviews with witnesses, police officers, community leaders and hospital officials. One marine was lightly wounded by shrapnel from the blast, it said.</p>
        <p>The convoy may then have come under small arms fire from one vehicle on the same side of the road as the bomber, Mr. Nadery said. In the days after the episode, the United States military said the convoy had come under a ''complex ambush from several directions,'' but the human rights panel questioned this.</p>
        <p>''If such an attack did indeed occur, as it is claimed by the U.S. military, it was almost certainly very limited in scope and restricted to the immediate site'' of the suicide bombing, it said in its report.</p>
        <p>The report's description continued: Two Humvees then moved forward 500 yards to the bridge and opened fire with roof-mounted machine-guns on a car that had stopped on a side road, some yards from the highway. The gunners then swung their weapons around and began firing on the nearby river bed and fields. They killed six people instantly and wounded at least another.</p>
        <p>The car's driver, a veteran mujahedeen fighter who goes by the name of Lewanai, 45, was wounded but survived the shooting by diving out of his door and scrambling behind a mound of earth. But the big guns shredded his car and the three people inside: his father, Hajji Zarpadshah, 80; his uncle, Hajji Shin Makhe, 75; and his nephew, Farid Gul, 16.</p>
        <p>''It was an illegal action,'' he said. ''I know the army rules, and when I heard the blast I stopped my car, I was thinking in case they shoot me,'' he said in an interview at his home nearby. ''They opened fire and were shooting for 10 minutes.''</p>
        <p>The car, now parked at a nearby gas station, is torn by gashes from the bullets over its hood, side and roof and the seats are shredded from the gunfire, the ceiling is smattered with debris and bits of blood and bone. Mr. Nadery said that the vehicle had been hit by 250 bullets.</p>
        <p>''Their insides were all coming out,'' said Noor Islam, 22, who saw the dead men in the car after the attack. ''We were very upset. Two of them were old men with white beards, and one was young,'' he said. ''They had no weapons.''</p>
        <p>Near the car was Shin Gul, 70, who was waiting for a ride to the nearby bazaar of Markoh where the family had a shop selling flour. He was cut down on the spot and his body so torn apart that his son, Muhammad Ayub, 35, said he could not recognize him at first. ''I saw a notebook in his pocket and then I knew it was him,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Nearby a 30-year-old shepherd named Farid was shot. He died two weeks later in the hospital.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ayub said he was with a group of workers digging a ditch in the river bed when they came under fire from the Humvees at the bridge. They all survived by taking cover in the ditch, but the bullets went over their heads. Those were the shots that killed the newlywed girl, Yadwaro, about 100 yards beyond.</p>
        <p>As the Humvees pulled away across the bridge they opened fire on a gas station and other vehicles, killing four people in a minibus, including a 1-year-old, the report said.</p>
        <p>In that attack and later ones along the 10-mile stretch of road from Spinpul, six people were killed and 25 were wounded.</p>
        <p>The report covered other civilian killings in recent weeks, including extensive human-rights violations by Taliban fighters and their allies that involved beheadings and the mutilation of victims.</p>
        <p>In other cases involving coalition troops in Afghanistan, the report detailed an airstrike in Kapisa Province in March that killed a family of nine people, including two pregnant women and four children younger than 5.</p>
        <p>The report also criticized continuing house raids by American forces, including one on the house of one of the human rights commission's staff members, who the report said was hooded and handcuffed to a detonator and told not to move in case it exploded.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
