<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Hopes for an Ambitious Newark Arena</title>
    <meta content="15njmainNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15njmain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DEVELOPMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prudential Center Arena (Newark)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vanderbeek, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0DE133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Hopes for an Ambitious Newark Arena</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">High Hopes for an Ambitious Newark Arena</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Jeffrey Vanderbeek, principal owner of New Jersey Devils hockey team, who comments on new Prudential Center Arena in downtown Newark, which is scheduled to open in October; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWENTY-THREE floors above the busy sidewalks, just after 9 a.m. on a recent Monday, Jeffrey Vanderbeek stood in the lobby of his quiet office and examined a row of chairs as if he were judging a beauty pageant or giving them a consumer rating.</p>
        <p>He was, in fact, doing both. They were samples of plush, padded seats that Mr. Vanderbeek, the principal owner of the New Jersey Devils hockey team, might choose to install in the $365 million, 17,625-seat arena being built here downtown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Newark’s Prudential Center is envisioned as a potent magnet for sports and entertainment events.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWENTY-THREE floors above the busy sidewalks, just after 9 a.m. on a recent Monday, Jeffrey Vanderbeek stood in the lobby of his quiet office and examined a row of chairs as if he were judging a beauty pageant or giving them a consumer rating.</p>
        <p>He was, in fact, doing both. They were samples of plush, padded seats that Mr. Vanderbeek, the principal owner of the New Jersey Devils hockey team, might choose to install in the $365 million, 17,625-seat arena being built here downtown.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vanderbeek wants the Prudential Center, which is scheduled to open in October for the Devils' 2007-8 opener, to be an attractive, comfortable site for hockey, basketball and indoor soccer games, concerts and other events.</p>
        <p>''The acoustics, the bells and whistles, it's going to be to die for,'' he said of the arena. ''When people actually see it, feel it, touch it, they'll be flabbergasted. They've never been to a place like this.''</p>
        <p>He also must meet a budget, which is why he wants durable seats. He scrutinizes details because so much is riding on this arena -- the future of his franchise and, to some extent, Newark itself.</p>
        <p>''I thought I was going into semi-retirement, but think again,'' said Mr. Vanderbeek, 49, who was on the executive committee at Lehman Brothers in New York before taking on the Devils three years ago.</p>
        <p>The goal is to use the arena more than 200 nights a year, not just the 41 days (plus dates of the Stanley Cup playoffs) the Devils will play there each season.</p>
        <p>City officials say they are confident that such activity will eventually lure businesses and development to downtown -- even Mayor Cory A. Booker, who was no fan of the project until Mr. Vanderbeek made some concessions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vanderbeek agreed to involve the community, particularly minority-owned businesses and trade unions, more heavily. Now Mr. Booker says, ''I think it's going to be a great spiritual asset for the city as we turn this corner.''</p>
        <p>Later the mayor added: ''The idea that this is just a hockey arena is wrong. It is much more than that. It is going to be the premier entertainment venue in New Jersey, if not the region.''</p>
        <p>Other projects have been portrayed as important to downtown revitalization, like the New Jersey Performing Arts Center, which opened in 1997, and the Bears and Eagles Riverfront Stadium, which opened in 1999.</p>
        <p>When asked to compare the Prudential Center with the stadium, the seldom-filled home of the minor-league Newark Bears baseball team, Mr. Vanderbeek said of the arena, ''It has a major-league team as a tenant that has won a world championship three times in the last 12 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Vanderbeek's stake in the project is civic as well as commercial. He grew up in New Jersey, first in Somerville, then Bridgewater, and lives in Warren. He, too, must drive construction-jumbled Interstate 78 to get to work.</p>
        <p>He was a Devils season-ticket holder for more than 10 years before buying a minority share in the team in 2000. He is a regular at Devils games at Continental Airlines Arena in East Rutherford, where the team has not sold out a game all season.</p>
        <p>The arena will represent not the completion of a project, but the beginning. It is planned as the hub of development that would include office and retail space, parking decks and a grassy park leading to the arena from Pennsylvania Station.</p>
        <p>''Jeff has been a constant factor and a cheerleader for making things go,'' said Bo Kemp, the city's business administrator.</p>
        <p>There are skeptics.</p>
        <p>George Zoffinger, the departing head of the New Jersey Sports and Exposition Authority, was quoted in the Feb. 19 New York Post as saying he doubted the arena would be done on time. The headline read: ''NJSEA: Newark Arena Long Way Off.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Vanderbeek and city officials held a ceremony late last month marking the placement of the highest piece of steel, he had gifts for the ironworkers: sweatshirts with that headline printed in bright red. ''On time'' plus ''and safe'' were printed on the sleeves.</p>
        <p>''There are skeptics in life, but that just makes the food taste all the sweeter when you do something that people say can't be done,'' Mr. Vanderbeek said later.</p>
        <p>The arena has helped entice businesses to think about moving into Newark or returning to it, city officials said.</p>
        <p>''It's a symbolic project as much as it is a real project, and this is a really, really, really big symbol,'' said William Crawley, head of the Newark Downtown Core Redevelopment Corporation, which is overseeing the arena construction. ''I've talked to people in the suburbs, and they're all excited about coming downtown.''</p>
        <p>Stefan Pryor, the deputy mayor for economic development, said the city, which is kicking in $210 million, had received inquiries from residential and commercial developers as well as hoteliers about building near the arena. Mr. Vanderbeek said activities at the arena could attract two to three million people a year, most after 5:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>''They will become patrons of Newark establishments more broadly,'' Mr. Pryor said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vanderbeek said he believes increased foot traffic downtown will override what has been perceived as the arena's biggest drawback -- that it is in an unsafe neighborhood in a city where murders are on the rise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kemp said of the arena, ''We think this is a principal component of repositioning Newark.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Booker compared the strip of redevelopment in Newark with that in Times Square. ''They'll all resonate with each other,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vanderbeek said he was focusing on trying to get the arena completed on time. His desk is piled with proposals from entertainment groups looking for a place for a gig. He has plenty to do besides selling the city. But he says there are a lot of cheerleaders.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of people who care about Newark,'' he said. ''There really are.''</p>
        <p>DEVELOPMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
