<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="15ctlistingsCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Torrington ''Colin Mochrie and Brad Sherwood,'' improvisational comedy with the stars of ''Whose Line Is It Anyway?'' April 20 at 8 p.m. $29.50 to $100. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Ballet Russes,'' directed by Daniel Geller and Dayna Goldfine. Friday at 8 p.m. Free. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Women on the Verge of a Nervous Breakdown,'' directed by Pedro Almodóvar; in Spanish with English subtitles. Friday and April 21 at 7:30 p.m.; Sunday at 2 p.m. $3 to $8. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Beauty and the Beast,'' comical version of the children's play. Through May 20. $13.50. Downtown Cabaret Theater, 263 Golden Hill Street. (203) 576-1636.</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Creativity Ignited!'' Interactive children's exhibition exploring the imagination. Through April 30. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Discovery Museum, 4450 Park Avenue. (203) 372-3521.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Calling Doctor Amelia Bedelia and Other Stories,'' a revue of the children's book, with a sing-along. Kindergarten through fourth grade. April 15 and Monday. $10 and $12. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.</p>
        <p>Norwalk ''Free Soccer Clinic,'' presented by the Norwalk Community Soccer Club. April 15, 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. Free. Stepping Stones Museum for Children, 303 West Avenue. (203) 899-0606.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Seussical,'' musical by Stephen Flaherty and Lynn Ahrens, based on stories by Dr. Seuss, presented by Theaterworks/USA. Ages 5 and up. April 22 at 1 p.m. and 3 p.m. $11 to $13. Jorgensen Center for the Performing Arts, 2132 Hillside Road, University of Connecticut. (860) 486-4226.</p>
        <p>Torrington ''Mary Pope Osborne and Will Osborne,'' selected readings by the authors of the Magic Tree House series. April 15 at 2 p.m. $7 to $20. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Color Play: The Art and Science of Color and Light,'' exploring light and holographic refraction. Ages 12 and under. Through June 17. The Children's Museum, 950 Trout Brook Drive. (860) 231-2824.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bridgeport Donnelly Benefit Concert: Jazz presented by Sill Life, Brian Torff and others. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $15; students, $10. Black Rock Art Center, 2838 Fairfield Avenue. (203) 367-7917.</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Tosca.'' Donna Balson, Soprano, and company will perform Puccini's opera. April 21 at 8 p.m. $20 to $52. Greater Bridgeport Symphony, 446 University Avenue. (203) 576-0263.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Baroque Bliss,'' featuring the Hartt Collegium, performing works by Handel, Marais, and others. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Free. ''A Year Ending in '7,' '' featuring organist Jason Charneski. April 22 at 4 p.m. Free. Center Church, 60 Gold St. (860) 249-5631.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Don Pasquale,'' opera by Gaetano Donizetti. Friday through April 28. $30 to $90. Connecticut Opera, 226 Farmington Avenue. (860) 527-0713.</p>
        <p>Middletown Wesleyan Spring Faculty Dance Concert. Friday through April 21. $6 to $8. Center for the Arts, (860) 685-3355.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Mixin' It Up: Adventures in Yiddish Swing,'' performed by Klezmer pioneer Hankus Netsky. April 15 at 4 p.m. Free. Opera/Oratorio, featuring Wesleyan music students, Monday at 8 p.m. $4 to $6. Silvana Saldaña and Javier Bravo, Brazilian guitar duo. April 22 at 7 p.m. Free. Crowell Concert Hall, Center for the Arts, Wesleyan University. (860) 685-3355.</p>
        <p>Milford New England Guitar Concert Series, Saldaña/Bravo Duo, guitar. April 21 at 8 p.m. $12. Milford Center for the Arts, 40 Railroad Avenue. (203) 878-6647.</p>
        <p>New Haven Taylor Ho Bynum Trio, jazz. Friday at 8:30 and 10 p.m. $10 and $15. Firehouse 12, 45 Crown Street. (203) 785-0468.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield Malcolm Holcombe, country and folk. April 22 at 7 p.m. $15 to $20. Temple Shearith Israel, 46 Peaceable Street. (203) 431-6501.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Russian Romance,'' Stamford Symphony conducted by Eckart Preu with pianist Andrew von Oeyen. April 21 through April 22. $17 to $65. Palace Theater, Stamford Center for the Arts, 61 Atlantic Street. (203) 325-4466.</p>
        <p>Torrington Gordon Lightfoot. The pop singer performs his classic hits. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. $32.50 to $50.50. ''An Evening of Doo Wop, Rock and Roll Vol. II,'' a concert featuring Sonny Turner, Buddy Holly's Crickets, and the Original Chantels. April 21 at 7:30 p.m. $35 and $40. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Greenwich Walter Isaacson, author of ''Einstein: His Life and Universe.'' April 15 at 2 p.m. Free. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.</p>
        <p>Hamden Bob and Lee Woodruff, authors of ''In An Instant.'' Monday at 7 p.m. Free. Alumni Hall, Quinnipiac University. (203) 582-8425.</p>
        <p>Hamden ''Mathematical Magic,'' lecture and magic tricks by Michael Nabel, professor of mathematics. Tuesday at 5 p.m. Free. Clarice L. Buckman Theater, Quinnipiac University. (203) 582-8937.</p>
        <p>Mystic ''Adventure Series,'' John Chatterton and Richie Kohler, shipwreck explorers, will talk about their discovery of the German submarine U-869 off the New Jersey coast. Thursday at 2 p.m. and 7:30 p.m. $9 to $15. Mystic Seaport, 75 Germanville Avenue. (860) 572-0711.</p>
        <p>New Canaan Santa Montefiore, author of ''Gypsy Madonna.'' Monday at 7:30 p.m. Free. New Canaan Library, 151 Main Street. (203) 594-5000.</p>
        <p>Old Greenwich Jane O'Conner, author of the children's book, ''Fancy Nancy and the Posh Puppy.'' April 21 at 1:30 p.m. Free. Arcadia Coffee Company, 20 Arcadia Road. (203) 637-8766.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale "Checkmate," mystery by Leslie Sands. Through April 15. $16 to $22. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Complete Hollywood (abridged).'' Reduced Shakespeare performs a Tinseltown parody. April 21 at 8 p.m. $30 and $35. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Murderers'' by Jeffrey Hatcher. Through May 27. $10 to $45. TheaterWorks Hartford, 233 Pearl Street. (860) 527-7838.</p>
        <p>Ivoryton ''Someone Who'll Watch Over Me'' by Frank McGuiness. Through April 22. $15 to $32. Ivoryton Playhouse, 103 Main Street. (860) 767-7318.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Blue Album'' by David Cale and Dael Orlandersmith, directed by Gordon Edelstein. Through April 29. $41.25 to $61.25. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Lulu'' by Frank Wedekind, directed by Mark Lamos. Through April 21. $22.50 to $55. Yale Repertory Theater, 1120 Chapel Street. (203) 432-1234.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Milton and the Minotaur,'' by Myles Gansfried, directed by Sherry Asch. Friday through April 28. $10. Ridgefield Theater Barn, 37 Halpin Lane. (203) 431-9850.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Shakespeare in Hollywood'' by Ken Ludwig, presented by the Connecticut Repertory Theater. Thursday through April 27. $15.50 to $26. Jorgensen Center for the Performing Arts, 2132 Hillside Road, University of Connecticut. (860) 486-4226.</p>
        <p>Torrington The Nancy Marine Studio Theater Season: ''Godspell.'' Through April 22. $10.50 to $17.50. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180. Waterbury "Viagara Falls," comedy by Joao Machado and Lou Cutell, directed by Don Crichton. Through April 15. $27 to $45. Seven Angels Theater, Plank Road in Hamilton Park Pavilion. (203) 757-4676.</p>
        <p>Westport ''All About Us,'' by Joseph Stein, directed by Gabriel Barre. Through April 28. $40 to $60. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-4177.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Brookfield ''Fiber Cartography: Mapping Imagination and Experience,'' works by ten fiber artists. Through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Brookfield Craft Center, 286 Whisconier Road. (203) 775-4526.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Zip, Bop and Whir: Toys of the 20th Century,'' exhibition exploring the evolution of toy technology. Through July 8. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. ''Painterly Controversy: William Merritt Chase and Robert Henri.'' Through April 29. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. ''Weaving a Collection: Native American Baskets From the Bruce Museum.'' Through June 10. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Natural Elements,'' works by Bryan Nash Gill, Catherine Kernan, and Eve Stockton. Through April 26. Hours: Mondays through Wednesdays and Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Flinn Gallery, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7947.</p>
        <p>Guilford ''Exhibition of Miniatures,'' works by Tom Edwards, Gail Friedland and others. Through April 22. Guilford Art Center, 411 Church Street. (203) 453-5947.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Soul Food: African American Cooking and Creativity,'' art and artifacts exploring Southern cooking and culture; presented by the Amistad Center for Art and Culture. Through April 22. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. ''Faith and Fortune: Five Centuries of European Masterworks,'' exhibition of European masterworks and sculpture from the museum's collection. Through Dec. 9. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. ''Connecticut Contemporary,'' a group of 24 local artists exhibit their work. Thursday through Aug. 12. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''Booming Out: Mohawk Ironworkers Build New York,'' photographs and sculpture documenting the Mohawk sky-walking construction tradition passed through six generations. Through May 27. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''A Newspaperman's Eye,'' American photographs from the collection of Russell G. D'Oench. Through May 27. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Davison Art Center, 301 High Street, Wesleyan University. (860) 685-2500.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Brushwork by Kazuaki Tanahashi.'' Tuesday through May 6. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Mansfield Freeman Center for East Asian Studies Gallery, Wesleyan University, 343 Washington Terrace. (860) 685-2330.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Random Access Memory,'' works dealing with memory by Liz Pagano and Colleen Tully. Through April 29. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Women's Studies: New Works by Mary Lesser.'' Thursday through April 29. Reception: April 15, 3 to 6 p.m. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. City Gallery, 994 State Street. (203) 782-2489.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Ceramic Abstraction: Exploration and Evidence,'' a juried group exhibition. Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Creative Arts Workshop, 80 Audubon Street. (203) 562-4927.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''New Haven's Garment Workers: An Elm City Story,'' photographs and artifacts documenting the 20th-century garment industry. Through May 4. Free. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to noon. Ethnic Heritage Center, 270 Fitch Street. (203) 392-6126.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Surface Explorations,'' works by Karen Green Recor. Through April 28. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m. White Space Gallery, 1020 Chapel Street. (203) 495-1200.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''UNStudio: Evolution of Space,'' exhibition of five projects by the Amsterdam-based firm. Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Yale School of Architecture Gallery, 180 York Street. (203) 432-2889.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Made for Love: Selections From the Jane Katcher Collection of Americana,'' 30 works of art that focus on the ways love and friendship are expressed through gift exchange. Through Aug. 26. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery, (203) 432-0600.</p>
        <p>New London ''Beyond Voodoo: Art From Haiti,'' works by various artists. Through April 28. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 4 p.m. ALVA Gallery, 54 State Street. (860) 437-8664.</p>
        <p>New London ''Gas in Glass: The Light Sculptures of Mundy Hepburn.'' Through June 24. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. ''Expresiones/Expressions: Caribbean and Latin American Art From the Benjamin Ortiz Collection.'' Through June 24. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>New Milford ''Rural Wealth,'' photographs by Ray Kwiatkowski. Through May 5. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''Shadows and Pulls: A Short History,'' photographs by Ellen Carey. Through May 5. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Diane Birdsall Gallery, 68 Lyme Street. (860) 434-3209.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. $4 to $8; under 6, free. ''A Circle of Friends: The Artists of the Florence Griswold Museum.'' Through July 1. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. (860) 434-5542.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''The Photograph as Canvas,'' works by artists who draw or paint on photographs. Through June 10. ''Tekrar,'' sound installation by David Abir. Through Aug. 12. ''W(E)AVE,'' sound and textile collaboration between Elana Herzog and Michael Schumacher. Through Aug. 12. ''Blow Ups: Spores, Pollen and Pollutants,'' works by Kysa Johnson. Through June 10. ''Castles, Dwarfs, and Happychaps,'' work by Arturo Herrera created using the Renaissance technique of pouncing. Through Sept. 2. ''Chrysanthemum Anthems,'' sculpture by Dario Robleto based on American soldiers' experience of wars. Through June 17. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Intemperate Times: Kathe Kollwitz, 1918-1934.'' Through May 6. ''Tradition and Innovation: Latin American Art From the Benton Collection.'' Through June 17. ''Old Master Drawings and Prints,'' exhibition of 15 Italian and Dutch works dating from 1539 to 1690. Through May 6. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>West Hartford Works by Paul Bowen and Pat de Groot. Through May 5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Brick Walk Fine Art, 322 Park Road. (860) 233-1730.</p>
        <p>Westport Oil paintings by Yetvart Kaprielian. Through April 27. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Galerie Je Reviens, 991 Post Road East. (203) 227-7716.</p>
        <p>Westport ''States of Connecticut,'' a juried exhibition with works by various artists. Through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Arts Center, 51 Riverside Avenue. (203) 222-7070.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Art and the Good Earth: As Seen Through the Painter's Eye,'' works by 14 artists. Through May 11. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
        <p>Willimantic ''Indigo: Traditional Chinese Blue Textiles.'' Through April 22. $5; students and seniors, $3.50. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Windham Textile and History Museum, 411 Main Street. (860) 456-2178.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Beyond the Lines,'' monoprints and paintings by Susan Newbold. Through Wednesday. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Rockwell Art Gallery in Wilton, 379 Danbury Road. (203) 762-8311.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Pattern Play,'' paintings by Anne Hebebrand and sculpture by Diana Chamberlain. Through May 13. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fenn Gallery, 345 Main Street South. (203) 263-3449.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on in and around Connecticut this week. Items for the guide should be sent at least three weeks in advance to ctcal@nytimes.com, or by mail to Connecticut Weekly, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036-3959.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Torrington ''Colin Mochrie and Brad Sherwood,'' improvisational comedy with the stars of ''Whose Line Is It Anyway?'' April 20 at 8 p.m. $29.50 to $100. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Ballet Russes,'' directed by Daniel Geller and Dayna Goldfine. Friday at 8 p.m. Free. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Women on the Verge of a Nervous Breakdown,'' directed by Pedro Almodóvar; in Spanish with English subtitles. Friday and April 21 at 7:30 p.m.; Sunday at 2 p.m. $3 to $8. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Beauty and the Beast,'' comical version of the children's play. Through May 20. $13.50. Downtown Cabaret Theater, 263 Golden Hill Street. (203) 576-1636.</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Creativity Ignited!'' Interactive children's exhibition exploring the imagination. Through April 30. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. The Discovery Museum, 4450 Park Avenue. (203) 372-3521.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Calling Doctor Amelia Bedelia and Other Stories,'' a revue of the children's book, with a sing-along. Kindergarten through fourth grade. April 15 and Monday. $10 and $12. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.</p>
        <p>Norwalk ''Free Soccer Clinic,'' presented by the Norwalk Community Soccer Club. April 15, 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. Free. Stepping Stones Museum for Children, 303 West Avenue. (203) 899-0606.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Seussical,'' musical by Stephen Flaherty and Lynn Ahrens, based on stories by Dr. Seuss, presented by Theaterworks/USA. Ages 5 and up. April 22 at 1 p.m. and 3 p.m. $11 to $13. Jorgensen Center for the Performing Arts, 2132 Hillside Road, University of Connecticut. (860) 486-4226.</p>
        <p>Torrington ''Mary Pope Osborne and Will Osborne,'' selected readings by the authors of the Magic Tree House series. April 15 at 2 p.m. $7 to $20. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>West Hartford ''Color Play: The Art and Science of Color and Light,'' exploring light and holographic refraction. Ages 12 and under. Through June 17. The Children's Museum, 950 Trout Brook Drive. (860) 231-2824.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Bridgeport Donnelly Benefit Concert: Jazz presented by Sill Life, Brian Torff and others. Friday at 7:30 p.m. $15; students, $10. Black Rock Art Center, 2838 Fairfield Avenue. (203) 367-7917.</p>
        <p>Bridgeport ''Tosca.'' Donna Balson, Soprano, and company will perform Puccini's opera. April 21 at 8 p.m. $20 to $52. Greater Bridgeport Symphony, 446 University Avenue. (203) 576-0263.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Baroque Bliss,'' featuring the Hartt Collegium, performing works by Handel, Marais, and others. Friday at 7:30 p.m. Free. ''A Year Ending in '7,' '' featuring organist Jason Charneski. April 22 at 4 p.m. Free. Center Church, 60 Gold St. (860) 249-5631.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Don Pasquale,'' opera by Gaetano Donizetti. Friday through April 28. $30 to $90. Connecticut Opera, 226 Farmington Avenue. (860) 527-0713.</p>
        <p>Middletown Wesleyan Spring Faculty Dance Concert. Friday through April 21. $6 to $8. Center for the Arts, (860) 685-3355.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Mixin' It Up: Adventures in Yiddish Swing,'' performed by Klezmer pioneer Hankus Netsky. April 15 at 4 p.m. Free. Opera/Oratorio, featuring Wesleyan music students, Monday at 8 p.m. $4 to $6. Silvana Saldaña and Javier Bravo, Brazilian guitar duo. April 22 at 7 p.m. Free. Crowell Concert Hall, Center for the Arts, Wesleyan University. (860) 685-3355.</p>
        <p>Milford New England Guitar Concert Series, Saldaña/Bravo Duo, guitar. April 21 at 8 p.m. $12. Milford Center for the Arts, 40 Railroad Avenue. (203) 878-6647.</p>
        <p>New Haven Taylor Ho Bynum Trio, jazz. Friday at 8:30 and 10 p.m. $10 and $15. Firehouse 12, 45 Crown Street. (203) 785-0468.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield Malcolm Holcombe, country and folk. April 22 at 7 p.m. $15 to $20. Temple Shearith Israel, 46 Peaceable Street. (203) 431-6501.</p>
        <p>Stamford ''Russian Romance,'' Stamford Symphony conducted by Eckart Preu with pianist Andrew von Oeyen. April 21 through April 22. $17 to $65. Palace Theater, Stamford Center for the Arts, 61 Atlantic Street. (203) 325-4466.</p>
        <p>Torrington Gordon Lightfoot. The pop singer performs his classic hits. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. $32.50 to $50.50. ''An Evening of Doo Wop, Rock and Roll Vol. II,'' a concert featuring Sonny Turner, Buddy Holly's Crickets, and the Original Chantels. April 21 at 7:30 p.m. $35 and $40. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Greenwich Walter Isaacson, author of ''Einstein: His Life and Universe.'' April 15 at 2 p.m. Free. Greenwich Library, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7900.</p>
        <p>Hamden Bob and Lee Woodruff, authors of ''In An Instant.'' Monday at 7 p.m. Free. Alumni Hall, Quinnipiac University. (203) 582-8425.</p>
        <p>Hamden ''Mathematical Magic,'' lecture and magic tricks by Michael Nabel, professor of mathematics. Tuesday at 5 p.m. Free. Clarice L. Buckman Theater, Quinnipiac University. (203) 582-8937.</p>
        <p>Mystic ''Adventure Series,'' John Chatterton and Richie Kohler, shipwreck explorers, will talk about their discovery of the German submarine U-869 off the New Jersey coast. Thursday at 2 p.m. and 7:30 p.m. $9 to $15. Mystic Seaport, 75 Germanville Avenue. (860) 572-0711.</p>
        <p>New Canaan Santa Montefiore, author of ''Gypsy Madonna.'' Monday at 7:30 p.m. Free. New Canaan Library, 151 Main Street. (203) 594-5000.</p>
        <p>Old Greenwich Jane O'Conner, author of the children's book, ''Fancy Nancy and the Posh Puppy.'' April 21 at 1:30 p.m. Free. Arcadia Coffee Company, 20 Arcadia Road. (203) 637-8766.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>East Farmingdale "Checkmate," mystery by Leslie Sands. Through April 15. $16 to $22. Arena Players Main Stage Theater, 296 Route 109. (516) 293-0674.</p>
        <p>Fairfield ''Complete Hollywood (abridged).'' Reduced Shakespeare performs a Tinseltown parody. April 21 at 8 p.m. $30 and $35. Quick Center for the Arts, 1073 North Benson Road. (203) 254-4010.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Murderers'' by Jeffrey Hatcher. Through May 27. $10 to $45. TheaterWorks Hartford, 233 Pearl Street. (860) 527-7838.</p>
        <p>Ivoryton ''Someone Who'll Watch Over Me'' by Frank McGuiness. Through April 22. $15 to $32. Ivoryton Playhouse, 103 Main Street. (860) 767-7318.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''The Blue Album'' by David Cale and Dael Orlandersmith, directed by Gordon Edelstein. Through April 29. $41.25 to $61.25. Long Wharf Theater, 222 Sargent Drive. (203) 787-4282.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Lulu'' by Frank Wedekind, directed by Mark Lamos. Through April 21. $22.50 to $55. Yale Repertory Theater, 1120 Chapel Street. (203) 432-1234.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''Milton and the Minotaur,'' by Myles Gansfried, directed by Sherry Asch. Friday through April 28. $10. Ridgefield Theater Barn, 37 Halpin Lane. (203) 431-9850.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Shakespeare in Hollywood'' by Ken Ludwig, presented by the Connecticut Repertory Theater. Thursday through April 27. $15.50 to $26. Jorgensen Center for the Performing Arts, 2132 Hillside Road, University of Connecticut. (860) 486-4226.</p>
        <p>Torrington The Nancy Marine Studio Theater Season: ''Godspell.'' Through April 22. $10.50 to $17.50. Warner Theater, 68 Main Street. (860) 489-7180. Waterbury "Viagara Falls," comedy by Joao Machado and Lou Cutell, directed by Don Crichton. Through April 15. $27 to $45. Seven Angels Theater, Plank Road in Hamilton Park Pavilion. (203) 757-4676.</p>
        <p>Westport ''All About Us,'' by Joseph Stein, directed by Gabriel Barre. Through April 28. $40 to $60. Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court. (203) 227-4177.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Brookfield ''Fiber Cartography: Mapping Imagination and Experience,'' works by ten fiber artists. Through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Brookfield Craft Center, 286 Whisconier Road. (203) 775-4526.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Zip, Bop and Whir: Toys of the 20th Century,'' exhibition exploring the evolution of toy technology. Through July 8. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. ''Painterly Controversy: William Merritt Chase and Robert Henri.'' Through April 29. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. ''Weaving a Collection: Native American Baskets From the Bruce Museum.'' Through June 10. $7; seniors and students, $6; children 5 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Bruce Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1 Museum Drive. (203) 869-0376.</p>
        <p>Greenwich ''Natural Elements,'' works by Bryan Nash Gill, Catherine Kernan, and Eve Stockton. Through April 26. Hours: Mondays through Wednesdays and Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Flinn Gallery, 101 West Putnam Avenue. (203) 622-7947.</p>
        <p>Guilford ''Exhibition of Miniatures,'' works by Tom Edwards, Gail Friedland and others. Through April 22. Guilford Art Center, 411 Church Street. (203) 453-5947.</p>
        <p>Hartford ''Soul Food: African American Cooking and Creativity,'' art and artifacts exploring Southern cooking and culture; presented by the Amistad Center for Art and Culture. Through April 22. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. ''Faith and Fortune: Five Centuries of European Masterworks,'' exhibition of European masterworks and sculpture from the museum's collection. Through Dec. 9. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. ''Picasso to Pop: Aspects of Modern Art,'' exhibition of the museum's holdings from many 20th-century genres. Through Nov. 18. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. ''Connecticut Contemporary,'' a group of 24 local artists exhibit their work. Thursday through Aug. 12. $3 to $10; members and children 12 and under, free. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; first Thursdays of the month, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street. (860) 838-4058.</p>
        <p>Mashantucket ''Booming Out: Mohawk Ironworkers Build New York,'' photographs and sculpture documenting the Mohawk sky-walking construction tradition passed through six generations. Through May 27. $10 to $15; children under 6, free. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; last admission, 3 p.m. Mashantucket Pequot Museum and Research Center, 110 Pequot Trail. (800) 411-9671.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''A Newspaperman's Eye,'' American photographs from the collection of Russell G. D'Oench. Through May 27. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Davison Art Center, 301 High Street, Wesleyan University. (860) 685-2500.</p>
        <p>Middletown ''Brushwork by Kazuaki Tanahashi.'' Tuesday through May 6. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Mansfield Freeman Center for East Asian Studies Gallery, Wesleyan University, 343 Washington Terrace. (860) 685-2330.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Random Access Memory,'' works dealing with memory by Liz Pagano and Colleen Tully. Through April 29. Free. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Arts + Literature Laboratory, 319 Peck Street. (203) 671-5175.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Women's Studies: New Works by Mary Lesser.'' Thursday through April 29. Reception: April 15, 3 to 6 p.m. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. City Gallery, 994 State Street. (203) 782-2489.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Ceramic Abstraction: Exploration and Evidence,'' a juried group exhibition. Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Creative Arts Workshop, 80 Audubon Street. (203) 562-4927.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''New Haven's Garment Workers: An Elm City Story,'' photographs and artifacts documenting the 20th-century garment industry. Through May 4. Free. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to noon. Ethnic Heritage Center, 270 Fitch Street. (203) 392-6126.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Surface Explorations,'' works by Karen Green Recor. Through April 28. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m. White Space Gallery, 1020 Chapel Street. (203) 495-1200.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''UNStudio: Evolution of Space,'' exhibition of five projects by the Amsterdam-based firm. Through May 4. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Yale School of Architecture Gallery, 180 York Street. (203) 432-2889.</p>
        <p>New Haven ''Made for Love: Selections From the Jane Katcher Collection of Americana,'' 30 works of art that focus on the ways love and friendship are expressed through gift exchange. Through Aug. 26. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 6 p.m. Yale University Art Gallery, (203) 432-0600.</p>
        <p>New London ''Beyond Voodoo: Art From Haiti,'' works by various artists. Through April 28. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 4 p.m. ALVA Gallery, 54 State Street. (860) 437-8664.</p>
        <p>New London ''Gas in Glass: The Light Sculptures of Mundy Hepburn.'' Through June 24. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. ''Expresiones/Expressions: Caribbean and Latin American Art From the Benjamin Ortiz Collection.'' Through June 24. $3 and $4; children 6 and under, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street. (860) 443-2545.</p>
        <p>New Milford ''Rural Wealth,'' photographs by Ray Kwiatkowski. Through May 5. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. New Milford Public Library, 24 Main Street. (860) 355-1191.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''Shadows and Pulls: A Short History,'' photographs by Ellen Carey. Through May 5. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Diane Birdsall Gallery, 68 Lyme Street. (860) 434-3209.</p>
        <p>Old Lyme ''The Freedom Business: Connecticut Landscapes Through the Eyes of Venture Smith,'' poems by Marilyn Nelson paired with paintings from the museum's collection. Through June 24. $4 to $8; under 6, free. ''A Circle of Friends: The Artists of the Florence Griswold Museum.'' Through July 1. $4 to $8; under 6, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street. (860) 434-5542.</p>
        <p>Ridgefield ''The Photograph as Canvas,'' works by artists who draw or paint on photographs. Through June 10. ''Tekrar,'' sound installation by David Abir. Through Aug. 12. ''W(E)AVE,'' sound and textile collaboration between Elana Herzog and Michael Schumacher. Through Aug. 12. ''Blow Ups: Spores, Pollen and Pollutants,'' works by Kysa Johnson. Through June 10. ''Castles, Dwarfs, and Happychaps,'' work by Arturo Herrera created using the Renaissance technique of pouncing. Through Sept. 2. ''Chrysanthemum Anthems,'' sculpture by Dario Robleto based on American soldiers' experience of wars. Through June 17. $7; seniors and students, $4; members, K-12 teachers and children under 18, free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Aldrich Contemporary Art Museum, 258 Main Street. (203) 438-4519.</p>
        <p>Storrs ''Intemperate Times: Kathe Kollwitz, 1918-1934.'' Through May 6. ''Tradition and Innovation: Latin American Art From the Benton Collection.'' Through June 17. ''Old Master Drawings and Prints,'' exhibition of 15 Italian and Dutch works dating from 1539 to 1690. Through May 6. Free. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4:30 p.m. William Benton Museum of Art, 245 Glenbrook Road. (860) 486-4520.</p>
        <p>West Hartford Works by Paul Bowen and Pat de Groot. Through May 5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Brick Walk Fine Art, 322 Park Road. (860) 233-1730.</p>
        <p>Westport Oil paintings by Yetvart Kaprielian. Through April 27. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Galerie Je Reviens, 991 Post Road East. (203) 227-7716.</p>
        <p>Westport ''States of Connecticut,'' a juried exhibition with works by various artists. Through April 29. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Arts Center, 51 Riverside Avenue. (203) 222-7070.</p>
        <p>Westport ''Art and the Good Earth: As Seen Through the Painter's Eye,'' works by 14 artists. Through May 11. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 4 p.m. Westport Historical Society, 25 Avery Place. (203) 224-1424.</p>
        <p>Willimantic ''Indigo: Traditional Chinese Blue Textiles.'' Through April 22. $5; students and seniors, $3.50. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Windham Textile and History Museum, 411 Main Street. (860) 456-2178.</p>
        <p>Wilton ''Beyond the Lines,'' monoprints and paintings by Susan Newbold. Through Wednesday. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Rockwell Art Gallery in Wilton, 379 Danbury Road. (203) 762-8311.</p>
        <p>Woodbury ''Pattern Play,'' paintings by Anne Hebebrand and sculpture by Diana Chamberlain. Through May 13. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Fenn Gallery, 345 Main Street South. (203) 263-3449.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
