<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fake 'n' Bake</title>
    <meta content="05get.samurai.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/style/tmagazine/15tsamurai.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SAMURAI SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suntan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suntan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suntan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fake 'n' Bake</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fake ’n’ Bake</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By S.S. FAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fair, S S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stupid, stupid, stupid. Not you -- the Samurai Shopper, slathered with baby oil and iodine at the beach, year after adolescent year, sunbathing on a bed of seagull guano, watching toddlers poke jellyfish with sticks, all the while roasting three shades darker than Danger Mouse. I looked good, at least by my account, and laughed at other beachniks slapping Kabuki-like zinc oxide on their noses. Dweebs, one and all, I said through a snicker. But sunbathing wrought terrible damage and put me where I am today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Samurai goes for the faux glow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stupid, stupid, stupid. Not you -- the Samurai Shopper, slathered with baby oil and iodine at the beach, year after adolescent year, sunbathing on a bed of seagull guano, watching toddlers poke jellyfish with sticks, all the while roasting three shades darker than Danger Mouse. I looked good, at least by my account, and laughed at other beachniks slapping Kabuki-like zinc oxide on their noses. Dweebs, one and all, I said through a snicker. But sunbathing wrought terrible damage and put me where I am today.</p>
        <p>And where am I today? In the office of Dr. Michael S. Cohen, a dermatologist in the 516 area code who specializes in Mohs surgery. And what is Mohs surgery? It's what you get when basal cell carcinomas creep over your face: skin-cancer damage control. It means Dr. Mike, wielding a laser, slices out the facial rot. Dr. Mike has done this three times, without once carving ''666'' on my forehead. But he's got time; skin-cancer treatments are an ongoing process that disfigures ears, chins and delusional narcissists who sunbathe till crispy.</p>
        <p>Still playing Russian roulette with your skin? Stupid, stupid, stupid -- and this time I do mean you. Especially with tons of self-tanners on tap and a real possibility that one of them won't turn you into one of Willy Wonka's Oompa-Loompas or, worse, George Hamilton. The Samurai Shopper began fiddling with self-tanners during an arctic chill, practicing for summer. At first I jumped into the fray without reading directions carefully, the same way I jump into swimming pools without testing the waters with my big toe. Though self-tanners are much improved from their Coppertone beginnings, you ignore directions at your own pumpkinesque peril. And every self-tanner says: Don't even think of doing this without exfoliating first. Slough off those dead cells or disappear into a Jackson Pollock canvas. Moisturize, too, especially your body's bonier bits: knees, knuckles, ankles, elbows.</p>
        <p>I dutifully assembled the exfoliators, which smelled heavenly but felt like the same wet sand burrowed in your bathing suit when you're bodysurfing. (Some sugar scrubs were so oily that they melted onto the bathtub floor and required molestation with Ajax before they disappeared.) Then I misapplied the brown gunk and turned my legs into streaky bacon strips. Finally I formulated a daring hypothesis, replete with cosmetic and cosmological implications: stick with tried-and-true brands. So straight to Kanebo's Sensei line: Cleansing Gel With Scrub and the delicate Silk Peeling Powder, which erased my checkered past and polished me up for the rest of Kanebo's new Sensei Silky Bronze Sun line.</p>
        <p>Yon-Ka is my other go-to beauty brand. Rhyming nicely with Willy Wonka, Yon-Ka is, in fact, serious aromatherapy skin care, available exclusively through spas. Check with a Yon-Ka facialist and pick the right mix for your skin. I applied Gommage 303, a soft facial peel, and then the Lait Auto Bronzant, filled with botanicals and fruit extracts. Yon-Ka's Phyto-Gel Exfoliant with jojoba pearls did the perfect prep job on my body; I was the new girl from Ipanema.</p>
        <p>Another sensational spa product is Guinot, sold at Clyde's on Madison Avenue. Type in your ZIP code at www.guinotusa.com and see if a Guinot-friendly spa pops up in your city. Guinot's Gommage Grain D'Eclat exfoliates gently, and Visage D'Ete is a tinted self-tanning moisturizer; it left me glowy, dark and very winter-in-St. Bart's.</p>
        <p>DHA, or dihydroxyacetone, a carbohydrate derived from plants, is what colors the skin. It doesn't penetrate the skin's surface but, when mixed with other ingredients, determines -- along with your skin type -- your tan's ultimate success. Clinique's Quick Bronze Tinted Self-Tanner Mousse and Sparkle Skin Body Exfoliating Cream have got the formula down pat; the exfoliant is minty and fine-grained, and the mousse is like buttah . . . and you'll be toast in a jiff (that's a good thing). Elemis's Total Glow turns out to be great for the fair-haired and freckled.</p>
        <p>But I soon tired of auto-tanning and surrendered to the pros at Ajune, 1294 Third Avenue, a medical day spa that airbrushes you brown. The excellent Zaza salt-scrubbed me to a shine ($100) and gave me the sun-kissed treatment ($70) as I posed like a sumo wrestler, like Schwarzenegger in his Mr. Universe days, like a ballet dancer in second position. The following morning I'd morphed into an Oompa-Loompa, but Zaza had warned me that excesses happen. The orange ultimately slithered down the drain, and I was brown and sugared. SkinCeuticals' Sans Soleil Sunless Tanner kept me that way for days.</p>
        <p>So the Samurai Shopper is no longer just a pretty, lasered face. Ajune sold me Colorscience's SPF 30 Sunforgettable protection brush, a magic wand dispensing non-dweeby zinc oxide to deliver me from any evil under the sun.</p>
        <p>SAMURAI SHOPPER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
