<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mets' Hernández Hits a Batter and a Nerve</title>
    <meta content="15mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/baseball/15mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Washington Nationals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Nationals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hernandez, Orlando</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mets' Hernández Hits a Batter and a Nerve</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">3 Homers and a Hit Batsman Chase Hernández</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Winters did not carry a gavel or demand order as he called balls and strikes at Shea Stadium yesterday. But during a dramatic moment in the Mets' game against the Washington Nationals, he sentenced Orlando Hernández with the authority of a judge. And for the record, he was wearing black.</p>
        <p>Winters ejected Hernández, the Mets' starter, in the sixth inning after Hernández hit the Nationals' starter, Shawn Hill, with a tight and chest-high fastball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlando Hernández was spectacular in his first two starts for the Mets, but he never had command of his pitches Saturday and was ejected in the sixth inning for hitting a batter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Winters did not carry a gavel or demand order as he called balls and strikes at Shea Stadium yesterday. But during a dramatic moment in the Mets' game against the Washington Nationals, he sentenced Orlando Hernández with the authority of a judge. And for the record, he was wearing black.</p>
        <p>Winters ejected Hernández, the Mets' starter, in the sixth inning after Hernández hit the Nationals' starter, Shawn Hill, with a tight and chest-high fastball.</p>
        <p>''I know it's intentional,'' Hernández said Winters told him.</p>
        <p>Hernández pleaded his case, insisting the verdict was unfair. But his appeal was disregarded.</p>
        <p>The Mets were already in a huge hole when Winters issued his ruling, and they did not recover, losing by 6-2.</p>
        <p>With the Mets (7-4) trailing by two runs, Ryan Church led off the sixth inning with a homer off Hernández, and Brian Schneider followed with a single. Chris Snelling then gave the Nationals a 6-1 lead with a two-run homer to right field.</p>
        <p>Hernández's next pitch glanced off Hill's pitching hand as he slightly leaned away from the plate. Hill, a right-hander, barely reacted before making his way to first base.</p>
        <p>But Winters immediately tossed Hernández from the game, sparking a heated exchange. Hernández gesticulated feverishly and had to be restrained by Manager Willie Randolph.</p>
        <p>Randolph said he thought Winters overreacted.</p>
        <p>''But I guess he felt like the guy hit a home run prior to nicking the pitcher and he thought that he was doing it intentionally,'' Randolph said.</p>
        <p>Winters told The Associated Press the ejection was appropriate.</p>
        <p>''The first pitch right after the home run was right at the hitter,'' Winters said. ''If it didn't hit him in the hand, it would have hit him in the chest.''</p>
        <p>Before leaving the field, Hernández took his case to the court of public opinion. He motioned to first base, where Hill was now standing, apologizing profusely -- three times by Hernández's count. He also turned to the Nationals' dugout to say he was sorry.</p>
        <p>Hernández said that he did not throw at Hill, he had no reason to and he did not know why the umpire thought he had.</p>
        <p>At the start of the game, all signs pointed to a solid outing from Hernández in his Shea Stadium debut this season. He was pitching on five days' rest and, for a change, the weather was not miserable. The game-time temperature was 50 degrees and the sun was shining.</p>
        <p>In Hernández's first two starts, a victory in St. Louis and a no-decision in Atlanta, he allowed a combined two runs in 13 innings. But by the second inning yesterday, the Nationals were leading, 2-0. In five-plus innings, Hernández allowed six earned runs on eight hits, including three home runs. He walked three and struck out four.</p>
        <p>Hernández (1-1) said he had a case of old-fashioned bad luck.</p>
        <p>''I throw fastball inside, home run,'' Hernández said. ''I throw curveball, home run. I throw changeup, a hit. No chance.''</p>
        <p>Ambiorix Burgos relieved Hernández and pitched two hitless innings. But the Mets' offense, while amassing 11 hits, never mounted a serious threat. The Mets sent more than five batters to the plate in only one inning, the second, when they used six batters and cut the Nationals' lead to 2-1 on José Valentín's run-scoring double.</p>
        <p>The Mets squandered an opportunity to tie the score in the third inning when Endy Chávez led off with a triple against Hill (1-2), a 25-year-old who was facing the Mets for the first time. Three quick outs followed, and so did boos from some of the 53,560 fans.</p>
        <p>''There's going to be times where we go out and score two runs,'' David Wright said afterward. ''It's part of the game; it's going to happen. This isn't maybe the first and it's definitely not going to be the last. There's times when good pitching's going to shut down good hitting, and that's what happened today.''</p>
        <p>Hill's sinker fooled the Mets throughout his seven innings. He surrendered eight hits and two runs while striking out five, including Carlos Beltrán, looking, to end the fifth inning. Beltrán responded by slamming his bat to the dirt in front of home plate and arguing with Winters. It took Randolph and Carlos Delgado, who was on deck, to quell the protestations.</p>
        <p>From the Mets' perspective, it was a day full of bad decisions, even some of their own.</p>
        <p>The Nationals (3-9) had runners at second and third with two outs in the fourth inning when Felipe López grounded to third base. Wright fielded the ball and would probably have ended the inning without any runs scoring had he simply thrown to first base. Instead, he chased Snelling back to second base, making the tag. But Schneider had already scored from third base to give the Nationals a 3-1 lead.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think we had a play at first base,'' Wright said.</p>
        <p>Randolph issued his verdict after the game, calling Wright's decision a mental mistake. Only this time, no one in the Mets' clubhouse objected.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>David Wright became the first player in franchise history to hit safely in the first 11 games of a season when he singled in the second inning. He had been tied with Darryl Strawberry (1987) and Robin Ventura (1999). Wright has now hit safely in 23 consecutive games, including the final 12 of last season.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
