<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With a Berth Secure, the Nets Plot a Playoff Renaissance</title>
    <meta content="15nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840678"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With a Berth Secure, the Nets Plot a Playoff Renaissance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About 30 minutes after his team knocked the Knicks out of playoff contention Friday night, and about 15 minutes before he would learn that his team had clinched a playoff spot, the Nets' Vince Carter, wide-eyed and speaking in his matter-of-fact tone, said, ''I'm just glad we're just one step closer to our goal.''</p>
        <p>For a team heading to the postseason for a franchise-record sixth consecutive year, making two N.B.A. finals appearances along the way, playoff qualification is typically anything but an achievement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About 30 minutes after his team knocked the Knicks out of playoff contention Friday night, and about 15 minutes before he would learn that his team had clinched a playoff spot, the Nets' Vince Carter, wide-eyed and speaking in his matter-of-fact tone, said, ''I'm just glad we're just one step closer to our goal.''</p>
        <p>For a team heading to the postseason for a franchise-record sixth consecutive year, making two N.B.A. finals appearances along the way, playoff qualification is typically anything but an achievement.</p>
        <p>The Nets' apparent satisfaction Friday night only highlighted the impact of a disappointing, injury-riddled and enigmatic season.</p>
        <p>The Nets (38-41) must now readjust their focus to the title aspirations with which they entered the season. That could prove a daunting task, considering their inability to beat quality teams and string together anything more than a four-game winning streak this season. They have insisted, however, that their focus is on the future.</p>
        <p>''We're on the 80th game right now,'' said point guard Jason Kidd, who will lead the Nets against the Pacers today in Indianapolis. ''If you ask me about who we played on the 14th game of the season or 50th game of the season, nobody could tell you, so who cares? That's the mind-set that you have to have, and you have to get better. That's the way we're approaching it.''</p>
        <p>The Nets, who have three games left until the postseason, may be able to suppress this season's failures. Yet the fact stands that their play has been worthy of a first-round exit.</p>
        <p>The Nets, who are two games behind the Washington Wizards for sixth place in the Eastern Conference, are 10-6 over their past 16 games. Their only victories against an opponent with a winning record over that span came against the injury-depleted Wizards. They were 0-4 against teams seeded higher than they are in the East playoffs -- the Detroit Pistons, the Miami Heat, the Chicago Bulls and the Cleveland Cavaliers.</p>
        <p>''We don't care if we win against the good teams or the bad teams,'' forward Bostjan Nachbar said after the Nets lost to the Cavaliers on Thursday night. ''The important thing is that we get those wins that are going to get us into the playoffs, and when the playoffs start, that's when we're going to start focusing on beating good teams.''</p>
        <p>When the Nets talk about what has gone wrong this season, they often refer to injuries.</p>
        <p>In late December, they lost their starting center, Nenad Krstic, to a torn knee ligament. Small forward Richard Jefferson missed 21 games because of ankle surgery. He now seems to be regaining his form. Over the past week he has had point totals of 27, 35 and 24.</p>
        <p>The Nets have also had an assortment of bumps and bruises: Kidd's ribs and back, guard Eddie House's hip, forward Cliff Robinson's knee and forward Josh Boone's shoulder.</p>
        <p>They began the season 11-18, and the last time they had a winning record was when they were 5-4 on Nov. 18. They fell below .500 four days later with a loss to the Portland Trail Blazers.</p>
        <p>''At one point, the playoffs was far-fetched,'' Carter said. ''I think as a unit we just stuck together and played one game at a time. That was our approach in the second half of the season. As bad as we played some nights, we still had a goal of making the playoffs and we still had a goal of sticking together until the end. And good things have happened when we've stuck together and played Nets basketball.''</p>
        <p>MAGIC 104, 76ERS 87 -- Dwight Howard scored a career-high 35 points yesterday to lead the visiting Magic, which can clinch a playoff spot today if it beats Boston and the Pacers lose to the Nets. (AP)</p>
        <p>CAVALIERS 110, HAWKS 76 -- LeBron James scored 23 points, Sasha Pavlovic added 15 and host Cleveland kept pace with idle Chicago (48-32) for the No. 2 seed in the Eastern Conference. (AP)</p>
        <p>SUNS 126, JAZZ 98 -- Steve Nash had 18 assists, Leandro Barbosa scored 28 points and visiting Phoenix moved closer to clinching the No. 2 seed in the Western Conference. (AP)</p>
        <p>IN OTHER GAMES -- Yao Ming scored 30 points and Tracy McGrady added 25 as Houston beat New Orleans, 123-112, and snapped a three-game home losing streak.  Chucky Atkins had 28 points and 12 assists and Tarence Kinsey matched a career high with 28 points to lead host Memphis to a 133-118 victory over Denver. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
