<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Under the Sea</title>
    <meta content="Ellmann.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/review/Ellmann.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mankell, Henning</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Depths (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Under the Sea</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Under the Sea</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LUCY ELLMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ellmann, Lucy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEPTHS</p>
        <p>By Henning Mankell.</p>
        <p>Translated by Laurie Thompson.</p>
        <p>403 pp. The New Press. $26.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Henning Mankell’s protagonist sounds the depths of waters around Sweden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEPTHS</p>
        <p>By Henning Mankell.</p>
        <p>Translated by Laurie Thompson.</p>
        <p>403 pp. The New Press. $26.95.</p>
        <p>This is where a land starts and ends,'' Henning Mankell says in the portentous style he favors in ''Depths.'' He could have added, ''This is how a mystery writer writes.'' Mankell, known in Sweden and beyond for his genre fiction, has dared to try something more nebulous here. But he's encumbered with all those irritating little habits mystery writers can develop: staccato sentences, paragraphs and chapters; characterless characters; implausible dialogue; heavy symbolism, with metaphors and similes battling for supremacy; clunky injections of back story and other info; reminders in case you forgot everything; and that old audience-grabber, plot for plot's sake, in the form of a murder every now and then (even the cat gets killed).</p>
        <p>The brevity of Mankell's sentences doesn't mean they're lean, mean and perfectly formed -- they can be as woolly as many a longer effort. His translator, Laurie Thompson, has presumably tried to replicate Mankell's style, or lack of it, and can't be held responsible for indecencies like ''Her tears seemed to tiptoe out of her eyes'' and ''The lead breathed. Its breath was white.'' How about this description of a pregnancy? ''Weeks passed. Kristina Tacker's stomach became bigger and bigger'' -- handy for readers who have no idea where babies come from. One-sentence paragraphs sometimes aren't sentences at all: ''Such as being responsible for checking the depth of secret naval channels.''</p>
        <p>This laziness might have been forgivable in a book a quarter of the length, making it a dreamy little allegory of a man torn between two women, a tale of ice and maps and the sea. But Mankell's fantasy is stretched beyond bearing and, despite the Northern waters and the Patricia Highsmith-style plot (in which the hero, caught in the lies he's told, turns violent), remains surprisingly stagnant. The details with which Mankell tries to perk it all up -- tidbits on turn-of-the-century technology, the Swedish Navy and World War I -- just aren't enough. ''Depths'' is not so much wistful as wasteful ... of paper.</p>
        <p>It's all too easy to be a hindsight wiseguy when writing historical fiction, embarrassing everybody with mentions of ''one of those new-fangled films, or whatever they were called,'' and presenting overwrought premonitions about the course of hostilities: ''The Baltic Sea and the North Sea, the Atlantic and perhaps other oceans as well will be filled with screams.'' If anything, hindsight requires you to be less vague about things. Unless Mankell's point is that men are ill equipped emotionally, culturally, even biologically, to know what damage they do when they go to war (and if it is, I missed it), it seems needlessly offensive to bring up a real war at all.</p>
        <p>Lars Tobiasson-Svartman is a naval officer trained as a hydrographic surveyor and entrusted to make soundings in the waters around Sweden in 1914 in order to chart new routes for bigger naval vessels. He has a sounding-lead he likes to sleep with, a fragrant but brittle wife he likes sleeping with less, and a fanatical and indefatigably metaphorical interest in measuring things. ''He had measured the depth around the Sandsankan lighthouse, but he had not succeeded in coordinating his discoveries with the navigable channels inside himself.'' Mark Twain would have choked on this.</p>
        <p>Tobiasson-Svartman realizes one day that he and his wife are both people who hit others -- he bashes an oarsman for having a runny nose, his wife boxes the servant girl's ear for giggling. ''That is one thing, at least, we have in common, my wife and I, we deliver powerful blows that resound against people's heads.'' Great -- what a pair. But his violent streak soon turns out to be in a class of its own, as he lies and murders his way out of the navy, his marriage and Stockholm, into the arms of a weird, smelly woman who lives all alone on a remote island. It's ''Dr. Zhivago'' with fishing nets and no revolution.</p>
        <p>What Mankell seems to know least about is something you can research without much effort: women. Though he gives his two female characters oddities that distinguish them somewhat, and awards them the moral high ground too, their lives are airless and dull, their only recourse for excitement being announcements that they're pregnant. For Tobiasson-Svartman, if not Mankell, women are big ballooning blanks, their motives and meaning more opaque than any fog at sea. But why? Women are right here to be seen and understood. It's infuriating when male writers make such a mystery of them, which is always ultimately a mockery.</p>
        <p>But Tobiasson-Svartman lacks substance too. ''He wondered why he so seldom laughed. What was he missing? Why did he so often think he must be fashioned out of faulty clay?'' Could the answer be that his creator failed to give him a personality? Tobiasson-Svartman is a much smaller entity than his mouthful of a name would imply: he is made of shifting sands. But there's no getting rid of him. ''It was not possible to erase the ship,'' Mankell writes, ''nor the ship's master, nor the navigable channels; it was not possible to erase himself.'' That is indeed a pity.</p>
        <p>Lucy Ellmann's most recent novel is ''Doctors &amp; Nurses.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lucy Ellmann's most recent novel is ''Doctors &amp; Nurses.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
