<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Rethinking the Javits Center</title>
    <meta content="LIjavits" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/opinion/nyregionopinions/LIjavits.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="The City | Long Island | Westchester"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Javits, Jacob K, Convention Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Javits, Jacob K, Convention Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Doctoroff, Daniel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EEDB123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Rethinking the Javits Center</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Rethinking the Javits Center</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The thousands of people who went to the New York International Auto Show in recent days saw first-hand the shabby state of the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center and its surroundings. For some time now politicians and developers have been trying to figure out how to improve both the center and the large, mostly untended patch of Manhattan around it. Now Gov. Eliot Spitzer and his new team are getting ready to put their own stamp on this painfully long-running story.</p>
        <p>It may be too much to hope for now, but the Spitzer people should try to make any new Javits Center better than just mediocre. Right now the planners seem determined to create a Javits Center that pleases almost no one. And that for only $2 billion, give or take a few $100 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It may be too much to hope for now, but Gov. Eliot Spitzer and his new team should try to make any new Javits Center better than just mediocre.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The thousands of people who went to the New York International Auto Show in recent days saw first-hand the shabby state of the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center and its surroundings. For some time now politicians and developers have been trying to figure out how to improve both the center and the large, mostly untended patch of Manhattan around it. Now Gov. Eliot Spitzer and his new team are getting ready to put their own stamp on this painfully long-running story.</p>
        <p>It may be too much to hope for now, but the Spitzer people should try to make any new Javits Center better than just mediocre. Right now the planners seem determined to create a Javits Center that pleases almost no one. And that for only $2 billion, give or take a few $100 million.</p>
        <p>Ideally, of course, we should just level the old monster -- which sits on Manhattan waterfront property that is probably worth a bundle -- and put a gleaming new convention center someplace else in the city. But there does not seem to be anyone in power brave enough to sponsor such a proposal. The possibility of delay alarms some business leaders, especially those in the hotel industry who have been collecting a tax for the Javits expansion.</p>
        <p>There are several proposals out there, although Daniel Doctoroff, the mayor's chief planner, has always insisted that only the present plan, designed by the famed architect Richard Rogers, really works. But rather than rush ahead with that or any other plan, Mr. Spitzer and the Empire State Development Corporation need to take a step back and assess the needs of the city and the exhibitors who use the center.</p>
        <p>First, the Spitzer people should make certain that, at a minimum, the center is secure and workable. A few months ago, after what seemed an endless planning process, the city and state finally showed the present proposal to some of those who now use the center. To say they were not happy greatly understates the case. Some Javits customers said they were shocked at how little exhibition space will be added by this costly expansion. Others are alarmed about how difficult it would be for the 200 to 400 trucks per show to operate in a new security system and marshaling area.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer and Patrick Foye, the head of the Empire State Development Corporation for downstate, have worked much harder than their predecessors to bring the major stakeholders into the planning process. That should help make any expansion more workable in the real world.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Spitzer and Mr. Foye should also make certain that the new center helps promote the inevitable development of one of Manhattan's least vibrant areas. The Bloomberg administration and Mr. Doctoroff have worked diligently to find ways to revive this section of the West Side. And even though their plans for an Olympic stadium were wrong for that part of town, the prospect of something other than the auto repair shops and storage bins that dominate the landscape is encouraging.</p>
        <p>Finally, for those who have been celebrating the revival of Manhattan's shoreline, the center needs to make some accommodation to the waterfront. There is nothing much appealing about the Hudson waterfront from 33rd Street to 42nd Street, but there are plans for an esplanade or a park attached to whatever replaces the city's tow pound.</p>
        <p>No one envies the Mr. Spitzer as he tries to untangle all the many interests at odds over New York City's convention center. And nobody expects a solution that pleases everyone. But the idea of spending around $2 billion without actually producing a workable, world-class convention center is not something the governor should entertain.</p>
        <p>The City | Long Island | Westchester</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
