<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Talk; Faith, Hope and Vanity</title>
    <meta content="05talk.trust.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E2DF153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Talk; Faith, Hope and Vanity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Christine Muhlke</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muhlke, Christine</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recently, as I lay naked below the waist while a stranger spread hot wax on my nether regions, I began to think about trust. Like most New Yorkers, I am wary of strangers -- even friends. If the woman telling me to flip over and spread my cheeks had tried to talk to me on the street, I wouldn't have made eye contact. And yet here we were, making tiny talk as she eyed my bikini line to make sure it was symmetrical. In 15 minutes, she'd be determining the sexual fate of yet another woman willing to pay to suspend suspicion in order to be pretty. How did we get here?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Recently, as I lay naked below the waist while a stranger spread hot wax on my nether regions, I began to think about trust. Like most New Yorkers, I am wary of strangers -- even friends. If the woman telling me to flip over and spread my cheeks had tried to talk to me on the street, I wouldn't have made eye contact. And yet here we were, making tiny talk as she eyed my bikini line to make sure it was symmetrical. In 15 minutes, she'd be determining the sexual fate of yet another woman willing to pay to suspend suspicion in order to be pretty. How did we get here?</p>
        <p>It's a question I've asked myself, as I've lain naked and facedown in a smoky hotel room with an American Indian healer who proceeded to rub my buttocks (is that legal?); allowed facialists with iffy skin to pop my pimples; fallen backward into the arms of a burly man in a secluded rooftop pool; let 20-year-olds cut my hair; assumed that the nail tools were sterilized, that the technician was licensed, that the eyelash dye wouldn't blind me, that the person with questionable taste should decide what my hair should say about me. I've always wanted to air my suspicions out loud, but never did. I didn't want to be rude.</p>
        <p>Dr. Debbie Then, a lifestyle psychologist in California, says we don't ask because we'd rather not know. ''We want to believe that the people we deal with are trustworthy,'' she says. But, she adds, ''How do we know, really, the training this person had? People just sit back, and they read the magazines and go into Zenland.''</p>
        <p>With hairstylists and colorists, trust is often a matter of taste -- and experience. After the publicist Marcy Engelman had her hair turned orange the day before her first trip to Europe, she took control. Before she went to Marie Robinson, now at Sally Hershberger, Engelman gave her the third degree: ''What percentage of bleach do you use? Tell me, what kind of color do you use with baliage? I don't want to use foils.'' Robinson listened intently and got the color right the first time. ''She took all my neuroses away,'' Engelman says. ''My biggest fear in life,'' she adds, ''is that Marie is going to retire.''</p>
        <p>By letting Robinson and her hairstylist, Serge Normant, do whatever they want, Engelman has avoided the trap of the distrustful, which is getting stuck in a style rut. You know the women. They're the ones who still look like Jennifer Aniston/Farrah Fawcett/Marlo Thomas.</p>
        <p>Kevin Mancuso, a New York hairstylist, believes that an important part of winning a client's trust is building a kind of lifestyle bridge. He says he looks for common ground to comfort that person, ''because when you're having a hands-on service where someone is touching you, it's an extremely vulnerable place to be.'' To Mancuso, common ground is the knowledge of what's in fashion, what's going on in the Hamptons. If you don't come across as one of them, he says, ''it's going to be perceived as, 'How's that person going to get my style?' ''</p>
        <p>Mancuso has seen many ways in which women cope. Some overextend trust; others are ''Venus flytraps'' who set him up to do what he wants but snap at him later. Others are simply art directors who walk him through every snip. (The latter are the most promiscuous and indiscreet salon-goers, since they're completely in control.) And then there are the clients who are just ''fishing'': ''They'll never be happy with you because they'll never be happy with themselves. 'Is it Paxil or Zoloft? Garren or Mancuso?' '' he says.</p>
        <p>Some of the most extreme makeovers occur when otherwise controlling women finally let go. ''The most high-powered executive will sit down and be as docile as a little lamb,'' Mancuso says with a chortle. ''Even the tone of voice changes. It's probably a voice that no one at the office has heard.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rita Freedman, a clinical psychologist in Harrison, N.Y., and the author of ''Bodylove,'' agrees: ''It gets really tiring to be so controlling.</p>
        <p>A woman needs a moment where she can let down her guard.'' Even distrustful women, Dr. Freedman says, are willing to cede their appearance to another because of the fundamental cultural belief that we all need to be fixed. ''We're not O.K. as we are,'' she says. ''We need to be made over.''</p>
        <p>How do we decide that the person we've spoken to for only a few minutes has the ability to see our best self and perform a miraculous transformation? Friends, celebrities and beauty editors serve as seals of approval. ''If they've read about it or a friend looks nice, people are less likely to question,'' Dr. Then says. ''Plus, most people do want to trust another person. And they do want to trust the setting because it's too anxiety-producing not to.''</p>
        <p>So sit back and relax. You're going to look beautiful. And if you don't remember what name to write on the tip envelope, just ask the girl behind the counter.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
