<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>STREETSCAPES/West 72nd Street; Where Town Met Country</title>
    <meta content="15scap" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/realestate/15scap.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Streetscapes | West 72nd Street"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DC133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>STREETSCAPES/West 72nd Street; Where Town Met Country</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Town Met Country</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gray, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Streetscapes column on history of residential buildings on West 72nd Street in Manhattan between Broadway and West End Avenue; buildings have received sharply varied degrees of attention from preservationists over years; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE block of West 72nd Street from Broadway to West End Avenue is, from the point of view of historic preservation, where the wild things are. Its buildings have been either left alone or mutilated, restored or destroyed, according to their owners' desires. At the Broadway end of the block, just beyond the boundary of the Central Park West Historic District, the delicate Colonial Club of 1892 has been flattened; at West End, the most striking house on the street has received surprisingly careful attention.</p>
        <p>There was little on the Upper West Side in the early 1880s. On this block of West 72nd Street the biggest building in 1883 was Theodore Havemeyer's large stable on the north side. In that year he sold 57 head of cattle, and buyers arrived from as far away as Ohio and Kentucky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The block of West 72nd Street from Broadway to West End Avenue is, from the point of view of historic preservation, where the wild things are.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE block of West 72nd Street from Broadway to West End Avenue is, from the point of view of historic preservation, where the wild things are. Its buildings have been either left alone or mutilated, restored or destroyed, according to their owners' desires. At the Broadway end of the block, just beyond the boundary of the Central Park West Historic District, the delicate Colonial Club of 1892 has been flattened; at West End, the most striking house on the street has received surprisingly careful attention.</p>
        <p>There was little on the Upper West Side in the early 1880s. On this block of West 72nd Street the biggest building in 1883 was Theodore Havemeyer's large stable on the north side. In that year he sold 57 head of cattle, and buyers arrived from as far away as Ohio and Kentucky.</p>
        <p>But town-house construction soon swept the street. Certainly the most unusual row of houses on the street is the dirty-white stone-fronted Gothic-style residences running from 250 through 254. These were designed in 1887 by George B. Pelham. The Gothic style is seldom seen in New York City houses, but that rarity counted for naught with a reviewer for The Real Estate Record &amp; Guide, who wrote in 1889 that Mr. Pelham's ''weak Gothicism may best be passed by in silence.''</p>
        <p>In 1890, William H. Boylan designed a somewhat awkward row for 208 through 214 West 72nd. Only 214 is left now, after recent demolition work at the corner of Broadway, but the row was notable for the strange top-story lookout at No. 208, meant for summer use. Early in its life, 208 also offered a mural of tropical scenery in a bathroom and a stained-glass skylight that ''sheds a ray of soft colors over the halls,'' according to The Record &amp; Guide in 1893.</p>
        <p>The round-cornered Colonial Club building went up at the Broadway corner in 1892 and served as the gateway to the block until its demolition just weeks ago.</p>
        <p>New buildings that came a little later were Nos. 226A, 230 and 288. These houses are 23 to 27 feet wide, big enough to edge into the mansion category, and although each has been irrevocably altered with a storefront, their upper sections still sound sophisticated notes. No. 230, designed in 1894 by C. P. H. Gilbert, is notable especially for its gargoyles and French Renaissance detailing.</p>
        <p>With its comfortably appointed dwellings, West 72nd Street was a major residential boulevard, connecting the carriage drives of Central Park with Riverside Drive. Householders appreciated the prestige of ''the riding and driving'' that passed by ''every fine afternoon,'' The Record &amp; Guide said in 1893. The entire street was under the supervision of the Department of Parks, which prohibited business traffic and paid for special plantings along the sidewalks.</p>
        <p>The 1890s bloom wilted quickly after the turn of the century, especially when the Broadway subway opened in 1904. Later, the automobile converted a genteel boulevard into an internal combustion highway.</p>
        <p>The occupancy track of Mr. Pelham's Gothic-style houses gives a flavor of the change that swept the street. In 1894 The New York Times noted that ''Frederick McKay of 250 West 72nd Street will spend the summer at Larchmont,'' and two years it later reported that Mr. and Mrs. Miles O'Brien, of 252 West 72nd, were giving a theater party and supper.</p>
        <p>But by 1910, 250 West 72nd had become the Hawthorne School. That year, The Times reported that Margaret Sumner, a student there, jumped off her father's yacht into Long Island Sound to save her classmate Elise Shearman, who was ''hampered by an automobile veil.''</p>
        <p>Things had declined sharply by 1931, when The Times reported that a resident of 252 West 72nd, a former showgirl whose stage name was Georgia Gray, was involved in a vice trial and accused the police of trumping up evidence against her. She died suddenly before she could testify, although the coroner stated that the cause was pneumonia, not foul play, The Times reported.</p>
        <p>The street's transition was hastened by the demolition of once-elegant houses to make way for apartment buildings. The earliest was the Wellwyn at 260 West 72nd, designed in 1912 by Rouse &amp; Goldstone.</p>
        <p>A later intruder was the New York Edison showroom at 236 West 72nd, built in 1927.</p>
        <p>The 1930s saw the last of the surviving private houses kneecapped by store alterations on the first and second floors, and some were completely blotted out by new fronts, like William Minogue's 1936 Moderne-style facade in orange brick chevrons at 224 West 72nd Street, which had black marble trim and black enamel signage.</p>
        <p>At the other end of the block, at No. 271, the striking turreted town house designed in 1895 by Gilbert Schellenger is receiving a different kind of attention. There, Joakim Aspegren, a principal in the Manhattan firm of Architecture Restoration Conservation, is supervising a program of cleaning, repointing, replacing copper trim, installing a new slate roof and completely reconstructing the turret. It is a wonderful sight, as tonic as it is unexpected.</p>
        <p>Streetscapes | West 72nd Street E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
