<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nascar At Crossroads After Years Of Growth</title>
    <meta content="15nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/othersports/15nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070419T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">France, Bill Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Montoya, Juan Pablo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Roush, Jack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nascar At Crossroads After Years Of Growth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Growth Hits a Wall, Nascar Faces a Less Certain Future</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIET MACUR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macur, Juliet</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the cusp of the 2007 season, Brian France, chairman and chief executive of Nascar, stood before reporters at Daytona International Speedway and declared that the sport was continuing its remarkable rise.</p>
        <p>France, the 44-year-old grandson of Bill France Sr., who founded Nascar 59 years ago, said on that February day that he expected television ratings to increase after a drop-off last year in more than 80 percent of the races featuring top drivers. He predicted that Nascar would rediscover the momentum that had transformed stock-car racing from a niche market in the Southeast to one of the most-watched sports in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six races into the current season, Nascar is at a crossroads, suffering from an identity crisis at the same time that television viewership has not recovered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the cusp of the 2007 season, Brian France, chairman and chief executive of Nascar, stood before reporters at Daytona International Speedway and declared that the sport was continuing its remarkable rise.</p>
        <p>France, the 44-year-old grandson of Bill France Sr., who founded Nascar 59 years ago, said on that February day that he expected television ratings to increase after a drop-off last year in more than 80 percent of the races featuring top drivers. He predicted that Nascar would rediscover the momentum that had transformed stock-car racing from a niche market in the Southeast to one of the most-watched sports in the United States.</p>
        <p>But six races into the current season, Nascar is at a crossroads, suffering from an identity crisis at the same time that television viewership has not recovered. Ratings are down about 14 percent compared with last season, said officials from International Speedway Corporation, which owns 12 of the 22 tracks where Nascar runs top races.</p>
        <p>The company announced last week that first-quarter revenue was down 19 percent because of lower attendance and concessions sales. In the past four months, International Speedway withdrew proposals for racetracks in Staten Island and in Washington State because of political opposition. John Saunders, the chief operating officer of International Speedway, in which the France family holds 63 percent of the voting stock, acknowledged that Nascar's growth had leveled off.</p>
        <p>''All sports have growth spurts and reach plateaus at various times,'' he said last Tuesday in a conference call. ''Nascar is not unique. What is unique is that this is Nascar's first time.''</p>
        <p>H. A. Wheeler, longtime race promoter and president of Lowe's Motor Speedway in North Carolina, said that Nascar is in transition as it struggles to straddle two worlds.</p>
        <p>''Are we moonshiners, country music, banjos and Route 66?'' said Wheeler, who is known as Humpy. ''Or are we merlot and Rodeo Drive? We just have to settle down and say: 'Is this what we want? Exactly who are we?' ''</p>
        <p>The task of defining the business falls to the France family, which has had a tight grip on Nascar for three generations.</p>
        <p>While hundreds of people work for them, the Frances -- who declined interview requests for this article -- are responsible for Nascar and its direction. They own Nascar, control most of the racetracks and collect the profits. They make the crucial decisions, choosing to relocate established races to nontraditional markets like Los Angeles and introducing a radical new Car of Tomorrow, designed to increase safety, decrease costs and improve competition.</p>
        <p>Bill France Sr., a tough, tall moose of a man, founded Nascar in 1948. His son Bill Jr. ran it like a dictatorship for 31 years before handing it to his son, Brian, in 2003. Bill Jr.'s daughter, Lesa France Kennedy, became president of International Speedway.</p>
        <p>Jim France, Bill Jr.'s brother, is vice chairman of Nascar and chief executive of International Speedway. The family has been tremendously successful. Forbes estimated that Jim and Bill France Jr. are each worth $1.5 billion, gained primarily from Nascar.</p>
        <p>The Frances remain one of the most powerful families in professional sports. Unlike in baseball, whose unions and owners often check the power of the commissioner, the family does what it wants because Nascar drivers are independent contractors. The Frances' word is rarely challenged, say drivers, teams and other prominent figures in auto racing. Both times drivers tried to form a union, in the 1960s and '70s, their efforts were quashed by the Frances.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes we overlook what could be considered a monopoly,'' said Kyle Petty, a third-generation Nascar driver. ''We overlook what could be considered price-fixing with the purses and stuff like that. We overlook it because, in the end, we make a good living and they make a good living.''</p>
        <p>Even Jack Roush, a feisty, often cantankerous owner of five top Nascar cars, knows he must bow to the Frances. ''If you want to be a part of their circus,'' Roush said, ''you have to play by their rules.''</p>
        <p>That means, though, that the Frances receive the credit when Nascar succeeds, as it has at a rapid pace in the past decade, and that they will be blamed if it sputters.</p>
        <p>Unforeseen Speed Bumps</p>
        <p>Although television ratings could have declined for many reasons, including an increase in channels and viewers' choices, the Frances hit speed bumps while trying to expand, with Kennedy, 45, leading the effort. A racetrack proposal for the Denver area is encountering early opposition, and plans for New York and Washington are dead, for now. ''Their missteps were early and often,'' said Councilman James S. Oddo, a Staten Island Republican. He added that International Speedway's first mistake might have been buying the land before gauging the probability of a racetrack's approval.</p>
        <p>At the first meeting with Staten Island officials, Oddo said, International Speedway's slide show presented only two alternatives for about 450 acres of unused industrial land. ''It was like they were saying, If we don't get a shiny brand-new stadium, then you get diesel fuel-belching tractor trailers that will clog your roads,'' Oddo said. ''If they intended to intimidate us, it backfired.''</p>
        <p>New investors are still attracted to Nascar. John Henry, principal owner of the Boston Red Sox, teamed with Roush this season.</p>
        <p>In an e-mail message, Henry said he had researched Nascar for three years before deciding to take a calculated risk to join the sport. He said too much emphasis was put on ''year over year'' television ratings, for Nascar and other sports.</p>
        <p>''The ratings generated by Nascar are terrific in relation to other sports,'' Henry wrote. ''It is a very, very strong sport that is very well run and well positioned for the future.''</p>
        <p>Nascar's television viewership is second best nationally to that of the National Football League. An army of about 100 Fortune 500 companies is involved in Nascar, but its corporate sponsorship revenue is growing at a slower rate than in the past, according to an April report by the brokerage firm A. G. Edwards.</p>
        <p>It is too early to gauge the success of Nascar's recent bold moves. The Frances began a playoff system in 2004, and have since fine-tuned it. They allowed the first foreign carmaker, Toyota of Japan, to compete in the top-tier Nextel Cup series this year.</p>
        <p>They are also trying to court a new base of fans with international personalities and races. Juan Pablo Montoya, a former Formula One driver from Colombia, made his Nextel Cup debut this season. The second-tier Busch series has scheduled races in Mexico City and Montreal.</p>
        <p>No recent move by the Frances has been more significant than the introduction of the standardized Car of Tomorrow, which is supposed to enliven races by making it easier to pass. It made its debut last month at Bristol Motor Speedway in Tennessee, receiving criticism from drivers. Wheeler, of Lowe's Motor Speedway, said the Car of Tomorrow would produce close racing, which would produce rivalries and drama that could bring the fans back. ''With this car, I can see that sparks will fly once again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Bill France Jr., 74, loves that kind of racing. He is obsessed with parity among Nascar's teams and keeping the competition close, said Lee White, senior vice president and general manager of Toyota Racing Development. France feared that Toyota would dominate Nascar, White said. But when France granted permission, saying Toyota could win its fair share but only by an inch, White said, ''It was like receiving the blessing from the pope.''</p>
        <p>Although he used to attend nearly all the races, France has faded from the forefront. He remains vice chairman of Nascar and chairman of International Speedway but is frail and ailing after a cancer diagnosis in 1999.</p>
        <p>''The Frances aren't at the racetrack like they used to be because they have other people handling the competition side,'' the longtime driver Ken Schrader said. ''Now Brian is looking for new sponsors for the series or finding bigger places to race. He has a bigger job.''</p>
        <p>The migration to bigger markets took Nascar east of Los Angeles, to California Speedway in Fontana, where its top division made its debut in 1997. That track gained a second race in 2003, at the expense of a Labor Day mainstay at Darlington Raceway in South Carolina, where the Southern 500 had been run since 1950.</p>
        <p>Empty Seats</p>
        <p>California Speedway does not sell out for either Nextel Cup race. Attendance figures are not released, but there have been patches of empty seats as Nascar struggles to win over Southern California, including the Latino market.</p>
        <p>Perhaps even more important to the state of Nascar, though, is that an examination of television ratings in specific markets suggests it may not be gaining as many fans in new and bigger areas as it has lost from its Southeast base. In fact, Nascar may be losing fans in both places.</p>
        <p>From 2004 through last season, ratings for races broadcast on Fox in the top five markets dropped in all but New York, where the ratings were stagnant. In Los Angeles, they fell by 22.2 percent, in Chicago by 12.5 percent and in Philadelphia by nearly 28 percent. At the same time, Fox ratings in some traditionally strong markets also fell. Atlanta was down by 18.2 percent; Greensboro, N.C., by 8 percent; and Greenville, S.C., 1.5 percent.</p>
        <p>The ratings for broadcasts of the Daytona 500 since 2004 have fallen as well, about 40 percent in Los Angeles, 28 percent in Chicago and about 11 percent in the New York, according to Nielsen Media Research.</p>
        <p>''I know that some core fans have had some displeasure with the rules and regulations, the Car of Tomorrow, and some new fans might not like those things either,'' said Robin Pemberton, Nascar's competition director. ''When you're in the middle of something so successful, and the expectations are up, it's hard to meet everybody's expectations.</p>
        <p>''You just take the criticisms, move on and hope the fans understand that things can't stay the same forever.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps nothing has changed more than the television contracts, and the money at stake. Nascar is in the first year of an eight-year contract with Fox, ABC/ESPN, TNT and Speed valued at about $4.5 billion, or $560 million a year. Its previous contract was worth $400 million a year.</p>
        <p>Kyle Petty cited NBC's decision not to renew its television contract with Nascar as a warning flag. ''That's a big, big story that someone walked away,'' he said. ''That's a huge blip on the radar.''</p>
        <p>NBC, which incurred losses on Nascar, had exclusive rights to renegotiate a new contract but decided to spend $600 million a year on the N.F.L. From 2001 to 2006, ratings for races broadcast on NBC fell by 38 percent in the Los Angeles area.</p>
        <p>For now, though, Petty said, the ratings and even the lower attendance have not caused a crisis because the race itself has become secondary to the marketing opportunities surrounding it.</p>
        <p>''It's not about the tickets or the TV ratings,'' Petty said. ''It's all about how many Cokes we could sell in that market.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 19, 2007, Thursday  A sports article on Sunday about the challenges facing Nascar after years of growth referred incorrectly to the finances of International Speedway Corporation, which owns many tracks where top races are run. The company's first-quarter revenue fell 4.5 percent compared with the same quarter a year ago -- not 19 percent, which was the decline in first-quarter earnings compared with the same period. The article also referred incompletely to the company's explanation for these declines. Aside from lower attendance and a drop in concessions sales, the company also cited higher expenses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 19, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A sports article on Sunday about the challenges facing Nascar after years of growth referred incorrectly to the finances of International Speedway Corporation, which owns many tracks where top races are run. The company's first-quarter revenue fell 4.5 percent compared with the same quarter a year ago -- not 19 percent, which was the decline in first-quarter earnings compared with the same period. The article also referred incompletely to the company's explanation for these declines. Aside from lower attendance and a drop in concessions sales, the company also cited higher expenses.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
