<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Amateur Ideal: Voters Know a Star When They See One</title>
    <meta content="15vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/othersports/15vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070418T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paralympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paralympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Amateur Athletic Union</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Joyner-Kersee, Jackie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Heiden, Eric</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitz, Mark</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Bonnie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E3D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Amateur Ideal: Voters Know a Star When They See One</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sullivan Voters Know a Star When They See One</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jackie Joyner-Kersee. Eric Heiden. Mark Spitz. Sarah Hughes. Bonnie Blair.</p>
        <p>These are some of the names on the Sullivan Award, given for the past 76 years to the best American athlete in the traditionally amateur sports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jessica Long is the first Paralympic athlete to win the Sullivan Award, given for the past 76 years to the best American athlete in the traditionally amateur sports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jackie Joyner-Kersee. Eric Heiden. Mark Spitz. Sarah Hughes. Bonnie Blair.</p>
        <p>These are some of the names on the Sullivan Award, given for the past 76 years to the best American athlete in the traditionally amateur sports.</p>
        <p>A new name is now going on that trophy, that of a young woman born in Russia, without bones in her lower legs, a double amputee at 18 months.</p>
        <p>Jessica Long of Dundalk, Md., is the first Paralympic athlete to win the Sullivan Award, given by the Amateur Athletic Union rather quietly last Wednesday night in New York.</p>
        <p>Hour by hour, the import of this election strikes home. The voters considered a 15-year-old athlete with no lower legs to have had the best year of any American, including Michael Phelps, the swimmer; and Brady Quinn, the Notre Dame quarterback.</p>
        <p>Comparing these national celebrities with a disabled swimmer might seem like an exercise in apples and bananas, but the Sullivan voters recognized a star jock when they encountered her.</p>
        <p>Long won three gold medals at the Paralympics in Athens in 2004, at age 12, and trains against able-bodied swimmers at home, beating most of them. Last year she won nine gold medals in world competition in South Africa. She also swam in a one-mile race across Chesapeake Bay. And for recreation, she climbs rocks.</p>
        <p>''She's basically fearless,'' said Julie O'Neill, the manager of the Paralympic swim team, based in Colorado Springs.</p>
        <p>Jessica's parents recognized the heart of a champion before she turned 2. Her journey to the Sullivan Award began with the dreams of a young couple, Steve and Beth Long, whose family seemed to have stopped growing after only two children. They went to a meeting to learn about adoption, and heard about a girl in Irkutsk, Russia, who was born without fibulas and was put up for adoption by her young mother.</p>
        <p>''We had to do a lot of soul-searching,'' Steve Long said the other day, adding that their Christian faith sent them to the orphanage on the other side of the world. They came home from Irkutsk with two children, Jessica, now 15; and Joshua, now 14. Joshua needed surgery for a cleft palate but Jessica needed much more. After a few months back in the United States, the parents realized her legs would have to be removed below the knees.</p>
        <p>''After her amputations, we were told she would need therapy to learn how to walk,'' Steve Long said, referring to the training to use prosthetic limbs.</p>
        <p>''But she just got up and starting walking,'' he added. ''We never made that call. She played basketball, she used the trampoline, she loved gymnastics, but they put a lot of stress on her legs. She started swimming around 10.''</p>
        <p>Jessica said she realized she loved to compete during a Paralympics-style competition in Minnesota five years ago. Coached by Stephanie Weisenborn at home in Baltimore, and by O'Neill in the national program, she is preparing for the Olympics in Beijing next year. But first she must adjust to having won an award over 14 other finalists, including two college basketball players, Joakim Noah of Florida and Candace Parker of Tennessee, who won championships on national television in the past two weeks.</p>
        <p>''They called my name and I was in shock,'' Long said in a telephone interview from Michigan, where she was to compete in a regional swim meet this weekend.</p>
        <p>''She is definitely one of the leaders in her age group,'' O'Neill said. ''We have athletes in their 20s and 30s, but she is very mature for her age. She has no problems with jet lag or food or local customs. It's all an education for her.''</p>
        <p>While Long is the first so-called disabled athlete to win the Sullivan Award, she does follow the 1987 winner, Jim Abbott, a left-handed pitcher who was born without a right hand. Abbott competed for Michigan, helped the United States win the 1988 Olympic gold medal in Seoul, South Korea, and later pitched a no-hitter for the Yankees. Abbott set the example one way; Long sets it another way.</p>
        <p>''This award proves that Paralympians are elite athletes,'' O'Neill said.</p>
        <p>O'Neill is somewhat bemused that she is working with a young woman born in Russia; as it happens, O'Neill majored in Russian history and has lived there and speaks the language. While Jessica is blonde and perhaps classically Russian-looking, O'Neill notes, ''She is the all-American girl.''</p>
        <p>Jessica says she plans to attend college and perhaps design clothing. Forthcoming prosthetic legs are expected to open up the world of high heels for her. She would also like to visit Russia some day.</p>
        <p>''I used to think about going back to find my natural mother,'' Jessica said, ''but now I don't think about it much.''</p>
        <p>Her parents have not been back since their fruitful visit 14 years ago. Russia, the third-largest source of adoptions to the United States, shut down the adoption channels last week, pending a revamping of the process.</p>
        <p>The Longs are not thinking of adopting anytime soon. They are busy. As so often happens, shortly after adopting Joshua and Jessica, the parents had two more daughters, giving them the large family they had wanted -- Amanda, Steve, Jessica, Joshua, Hannah and Grace.</p>
        <p>''We have children ranging from 24 to 8,'' Steve Long said.</p>
        <p>The children are all equal at home. But one of them has won the Sullivan Award.</p>
        <p>Rafer Johnson. Wilma Rudolph. Bill Bradley. Carl Lewis. Michelle Kwan.</p>
        <p>They are now in good company with Jessica Long.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 18, 2007, Wednesday  The Sports of The Times column on Sunday, about Jessica Long, a 15-year-old swimmer who became the first Paralympic athlete to win the Sullivan Award, given by the Amateur Athletic Union, misidentified her primary coach and misstated the age of her brother Joshua. Her coach is Andrew Barranco -- not Stephanie Weisenborn, who used to coach her. Joshua is 17, not 14.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 18, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>The Sports of The Times column on Sunday, about Jessica Long, a 15-year-old swimmer who became the first Paralympic athlete to win the Sullivan Award, given by the Amateur Athletic Union, misidentified her primary coach and misstated the age of her brother Joshua. Her coach is Andrew Barranco -- not Stephanie Weisenborn, who used to coach her. Joshua is 17, not 14.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
