<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spotlight: N.B.A.; Together In Toronto And Having A Few Laughs</title>
    <meta content="15hoops" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/basketball/15hoops.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bosh, Chris</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mitchell, Sam</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bargnani, Andrea</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1364" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spotlight: N.B.A.; Together In Toronto And Having A Few Laughs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Together in Toronto and Having a Few Laughs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sam Mitchell tossed perfect spirals toward his starting point guard, T. J. Ford, who dropped one to the hoots of teammates and coaches lingering in the Toronto Raptors' practice gym last week. Mitchell then punted the football to the ceiling.</p>
        <p>No matter that this is hockey-obsessed Canada, that Mitchell is the coach of the N.B.A.'s most improved team and that half of his players think of football as soccer. Such silly sporting juxtapositions seem perfectly natural to the Raptors; they were rebuilt to defy convention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Toronto, players from six nations surround the selfless star Chris Bosh and Coach Sam Mitchell and somehow, these diverse personalities and voices blend seamlessly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sam Mitchell tossed perfect spirals toward his starting point guard, T. J. Ford, who dropped one to the hoots of teammates and coaches lingering in the Toronto Raptors' practice gym last week. Mitchell then punted the football to the ceiling.</p>
        <p>No matter that this is hockey-obsessed Canada, that Mitchell is the coach of the N.B.A.'s most improved team and that half of his players think of football as soccer. Such silly sporting juxtapositions seem perfectly natural to the Raptors; they were rebuilt to defy convention.</p>
        <p>Players from six nations surround the selfless star Chris Bosh and the blustering but compassionate Mitchell, a third-year coach. (Mitchell, he will have you know, was a highly recruited high school tight end from Georgia before enjoying a productive 13-year career in the N.B.A.)</p>
        <p>Somehow, these diverse personalities and voices (representing Italy, Spain, Slovenia, Senegal, Israel via Illinois and Texas) blend seamlessly rather than form a basketball Babel.</p>
        <p>Returning to the playoffs after a five-year absence, the new-look Raptors -- who share the ball as freely as they do jokes -- may be the most refreshing team in the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>In the same way that Bosh saw no contradiction in being selfless and a star, he embraced his team's uncanny chemistry. ''It's not weird because it's fun,'' Bosh said in an interview Thursday. ''I think every team should try it.''</p>
        <p>But not every team has Bryan Colangelo as its architect. In the year since Colangelo arrived from Phoenix, where he had resurrected the Suns to win executive of the year honors, he has taken the right risks (under favorable conditions) to revive a moribund franchise in Toronto.</p>
        <p>The change is obvious in the standings: The Raptors have won 19 more games than they did last season, the biggest jump of any N.B.A. team, and captured their first Atlantic Division title. The change is more subtle in Colangelo's redesign of the locker room, his first step in conveying that this would be a first-class operation.</p>
        <p>''I hope that the culture changed immediately when I got here back in March,'' Colangelo said in an interview in his corner office at the Air Canada Center. ''I think the perception was a cloud had been lifted off the Raptors. Everything across the board needed to be revamped.''</p>
        <p>Not everything or everyone. Mitchell is still here. And now Colangelo wants him to stay.</p>
        <p>Rather than firing a struggling and emotional Mitchell last season, Colangelo waited. Rather than give Mitchell an extension before the season, he vowed to discuss it only after the season. Rather than fire Mitchell as the Raptors started 2-8, Colangelo worked with him.</p>
        <p>In trying to find comfort with the nine players Colangelo initially brought in, Mitchell was reluctant to give playing time to the No. 1 overall pick from Italy, the 7-footer Andrea Bargnani, or the free-agent forward Jorge Garbajosa of Spain.</p>
        <p>After prodding from management, Mitchell grew more confident in them, and Bargnani responded with accurate shooting and aggressiveness befitting a rookie of the year. Garbajosa provided versatility and energy until he broke his leg and ankle last month.</p>
        <p>The Raptors were able to stay afloat when Bosh missed 12 games in December with a knee injury. Now, despite losing Bargnani to an appendectomy last month (he may not return until next week because of minor illnesses), the Raptors have won eight of their last nine games.</p>
        <p>Colangelo had been modest in his praise of Mitchell, but last week he applauded him publicly for the first time as worthy of coach-of-the-year honors. When asked if Mitchell was worthy of an extension, Colangelo smiled and offered his strongest backing yet.</p>
        <p>''I have every intention to keep Sam Mitchell,'' Colangelo said.</p>
        <p>Mitchell waved off questions about the extension, saying it violated his team-first mantra. ''I've been asking all these guys to make sacrifices,'' Mitchell said after ''football'' practice. ''Now that we're winning, I'm going to jump up and down and say, 'I want mine now'? If I do my job, in return, I'll get taken care of.''</p>
        <p>Mitchell may have tripled his market value and will be in demand for coaching vacancies elsewhere. It is apparent that while Mitchell still rides players hard, they respect him and he feels comfortable with this group.</p>
        <p>''I love coming to practice, I love being on the bus with them,'' he said. ''This team is special because we're winning.''</p>
        <p>Or are the Raptors winning because they are special? Having players with international experience lends a more mature perspective, said guard Anthony Parker, who starred for five seasons with Maccabi Tel Aviv.</p>
        <p>Now better known as the brother of the Tennessee star Candace Parker, he said he was grateful to Colangelo for bringing him to the N.B.A. at age 31. (Colangelo created a buyout when his contract did not have one.)</p>
        <p>''You realize that this is a privilege to play here, not a right,'' said Parker, who wears 18 on his jersey, the number that symbolizes life in Hebrew.</p>
        <p>The mind-set of a European player, Colangelo said, tends to be different because basketball is taught with more of a team emphasis than in the United States. But that was not the sole reason for the Raptors' foreign influx.</p>
        <p>Maurizio Gherardini, the Raptors' assistant general manager, who was the top basketball executive in Italy, said, ''I think that the decision was based on what we needed, on the players' talent and what we perceived of their ability to melt into a group, not necessarily because of what was on their passport.'' Colangelo hired Gherardini, who was Bargnani's boss as Benetton Treviso's general manager, to be the N.B.A.'s first senior executive from Europe, giving the Raptors an advantage in the expanding international market.</p>
        <p>Colangelo credits the former Raptors general manager Rob Babcock for signing point guard José Calderón from Spain. It was Calderón who helped persuade Garbajosa, his national team teammate, to go to Toronto, selling him on the city's cosmopolitan nature and on the ease of playing with Bosh.</p>
        <p>''He's like one of us,'' Calderón said. ''We love him. That's the best thing about this team: We love everybody. Everybody knows their role.''</p>
        <p>Rasho Nesterovic, from Slovenia, acquired in a trade last summer with San Antonio, is the old soul in the locker room, while Ford is seemingly the origin of all team jokes.</p>
        <p>After Colangelo acquired Ford in an off-season trade with Milwaukee, he gave him a contract extension, perhaps one reason Ford has played so fast and loose this season.</p>
        <p>Ford's breakout season, combined with Bosh's emergence as a franchise player, has helped make the Raptors' offense one of the more dangerous ones. The backup guard Juan Dixon also gives the Raptors more firepower. He was acquired when Colangelo jettisoned the disappointing Fred Jones to Portland by getting Jones to waive the final year of his deal to go home to Oregon.</p>
        <p>Two advance scouts described Toronto's offensive sets as simple yet finely executed. Still, the Raptors are the N.B.A.'s fourth-worst rebounding team and their weak team defense could hurt them in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>A victory Friday over Detroit, which had clinched the top spot in the East, showed they are nearing the elite. Morris Peterson, the only remaining player from the Raptors' 2002 playoff season, credited Colangelo for the turnaround. ''Even though we weren't winning, he gave us a new sense of hope,'' Peterson said.</p>
        <p>Isiah Thomas, the Knicks' coach and general manager and Toronto's first general manager, also played a role. By taking Jalen Rose from the Raptors last February (Wayne Embry made the trade as interim general manager) for Antonio Davis, Thomas saved Toronto $17 million. The flexibility helped entice Colangelo to take the job because he had cap room to sign Bosh to a long-term contract and lure free agents.</p>
        <p>The Knicks and the Raptors meet tonight in Toronto, going in decidedly different directions. That hit home for Bosh when he attended the team's season-ending party for loyal fans Wednesday. ''It used to be called the RapUp party and we were wrapping up the season,'' Bosh said. ''We had three games left and it didn't go past there.''</p>
        <p>Now, Bosh realized with a grin, the real party has just begun.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
