<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Challenge to Survey Low-Wage Workers, Researchers Pursue 'Snowball Sample'</title>
    <meta content="15sage" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/15sage.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840635"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Statistics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Russell Sage Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sociology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sociology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Russell Sage Foundation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Challenge to Survey Low-Wage Workers, Researchers Pursue 'Snowball Sample'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Challenge to Survey Low-Wage Workers, Researchers Pursue ‘Snowball Sample’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russell Sage Foundation in New York City recruits experts to use snowball sampling technique and mathematical formula to identify hard-to-count population of low-wage and often exploited workers; researchers seek out workers who then recruit their friends in process they liken to chain letter or 'six degrees of separation' theory of connectedness; mathematical formula is then applied to sample; goal is to provide solid data on magnitude of problem of unregulated work and workers who are invisible (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Imagine a more challenging group to identify and quantify than jazz musicians. They tend to be itinerant. Also, poor. Go to the clubs, and those likely to be performing are the more successful ones. Ask the musicians' union, and chances are those enrolled will be disproportionately older and account for only a fraction of the total.</p>
        <p>Still, a Cornell University sociologist says he has figured out that there are 30,000 jazz musicians in metropolitan New York. And as it celebrates its centennial this week, the Russell Sage Foundation has recruited the sociologist and three other experts to use the same sampling technique and mathematical formula to identify another hard-to-count population: low-wage and often exploited workers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Russell Sage Foundation, which will celebrate its centennial this week, has managed to quantify populations that are difficult to count.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Imagine a more challenging group to identify and quantify than jazz musicians. They tend to be itinerant. Also, poor. Go to the clubs, and those likely to be performing are the more successful ones. Ask the musicians' union, and chances are those enrolled will be disproportionately older and account for only a fraction of the total.</p>
        <p>Still, a Cornell University sociologist says he has figured out that there are 30,000 jazz musicians in metropolitan New York. And as it celebrates its centennial this week, the Russell Sage Foundation has recruited the sociologist and three other experts to use the same sampling technique and mathematical formula to identify another hard-to-count population: low-wage and often exploited workers.</p>
        <p>''What the methodology allows us to do is get at a representative population that is often hidden from policy researchers,'' said Annette Bernhardt, deputy director of the poverty program at the Brennan Center for Justice at New York University. ''This has the potential to revolutionize how we identify, measure and respond to critical social and economic problems.''</p>
        <p>The Russell Sage Foundation, which is based in Manhattan, was created in 1907 by Margaret Olivia Sage, who named it for her late husband, a successful and notoriously parsimonious Wall Street financier. The mission of the foundation, which will mark its centennial on Thursday with a daylong social science symposium in Manhattan, is to use ''any means'' to effect ''the improvement of social and living conditions'' in the United States.</p>
        <p>''We have a very long history of looking at quality-of-work issues,'' said Eric Wanner, the foundation's president.</p>
        <p>Some of its latest research, he said, is focusing on the effects of income inequality and how economic forces are reshaping the labor market, including the impact of labor law violations on unregulated workers, especially immigrants, at the low end of the pay scale.</p>
        <p>''The workers are hard to find and often vulnerable,'' the foundation said in a statement announcing the $515,277 research grant to study workplace violations in New York City, ''the employers are reluctant to disclose sensitive information, and government compliance surveys shy away from the difficult task of measuring workplace practices beyond the standard wage, benefits and hours questions.''</p>
        <p>In a written explanation of their goals, the researchers said, ''In industries ranging from construction and food manufacturing to restaurants and janitorial services, workers are enduring minimum wage and overtime violations, hazardous working conditions, discrimination and retaliation for speaking up or trying to organize.''</p>
        <p>They contend that ''unregulated work'' is proliferating, but that ''advocates and policy makers have no solid data on the magnitude of the problem, on the industries that are the biggest culprits or on the workers who are most affected.''</p>
        <p>Their research, which is in its early stage, relies heavily on a technique developed by Douglas Heckathorn, the Cornell sociologist and a former Russell Sage visiting scholar. He said in an interview that its goal was to ''address the inherent difficulties in trying to reach a largely invisible and often vulnerable population'' -- whether jazz musicians (for the Research Center for Arts and Culture at Columbia University) or immigrant workers, ex-convicts, former welfare recipients and low-wage workers (whose invisibility potentially distorts statistics on issues ranging from unemployment to health insurance).</p>
        <p>Researchers pursue what is called a ''snowball sample,'' seeking out workers who then recruit their friends in a process they liken to a chain letter, or to the ''six degrees of separation'' theory of connectedness. A mathematical formula is applied to the sample like a ''corrective lens,'' Professor Heckathorn explained, to obtain a sample that is ''theoretically independent of its nonrandom starting points.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Bernhardt said of the method, ''If you keep doing more and more chains of referrals, after you're done it 10 times your sample has reached all parts of the population and is drawing on the trust that social networks have to bring people into the study.''</p>
        <p>Ruth Milkman, a sociologist at the University of California, Los Angeles, said, ''This method is ideal for hard-to-reach populations.'' Dr. Milkman, who is conducting the three-city study with Dr. Bernhardt and Nik Theodore, a urban planning scholar at the University of Illinois, added, ''What we can do is measure something that heretofore has been extremely difficult to measure.''</p>
        <p>The sampling technique has been adopted by various research projects, including one by the federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to identify intravenous drug users susceptible to AIDS. Professor Heckathorn is applying the method to a study of artists and sculptors who have reached retirement age. He said not every group can be sampled using this method.</p>
        <p>''There are certain requirements: The people have to have a connection,'' he said. ''It wouldn't work to find tax cheats.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
