<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State's New Education Commissioner Faces a Long To-Do List</title>
    <meta content="15ctpeopleCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15ctpeople.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SCHOOLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">McQuillan, Mark (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silverman, Fran</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rell, M Jodi (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E3D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State's New Education Commissioner Faces a Long To-Do List</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">State’s New Education Commissioner Faces a Long To-Do List</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRAN SILVERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Silverman, Fran</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Mark McQuillan, Connecticut's new commissioner of education, who comments on work he has ahead of him; he comments on Gov M Jodi Rell's new budget plan, suit filed against federal government seeking more funds to pay for services required under No Child Left Behind Act, suit on school financing brought by Connecticut Coalition for Justice in Education Funding and pressure to close achievement gap between higher- and lower-income students; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MARK. K. McQUILLAN says it was the sense of camaraderie and history of progressive education that brought him over the border from Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Mr. McQuillan, who is to begin his job on Monday as the state's commissioner of education, said Connecticut has been a leader in education reform and has a unique governing structure that fosters teamwork among local school boards, the State Department of Education, legislators and educational advocates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark K. McQuillan, who is to begin his job on Monday as the state’s commissioner of education, steps into the job at a busy time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MARK. K. McQUILLAN says it was the sense of camaraderie and history of progressive education that brought him over the border from Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Mr. McQuillan, who is to begin his job on Monday as the state's commissioner of education, said Connecticut has been a leader in education reform and has a unique governing structure that fosters teamwork among local school boards, the State Department of Education, legislators and educational advocates.</p>
        <p>''There is a culture in Connecticut that has always impressed me,'' Mr. McQuillan said. ''It differs from Massachusetts. There's a very strong sense of collaboration.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McQuillan, a former deputy education commissioner in Massachusetts, was named to the Connecticut post in the winter to succeed Betty J. Sternberg, who resigned last summer. He steps into the job at a busy time. State legislators are grappling with a new budget plan introduced by Gov. M. Jodi Rell that would funnel additional education money to towns that would have the option of using the funds for property tax relief.</p>
        <p>The Education Department is also suing the federal government for more money to pay for services required under the No Child Left Behind Act and is facing a lawsuit on school financing brought by the Connecticut Coalition for Justice in Education Funding. At the same time, there is pressure to close an achievement gap in which lower-income students in Connecticut are lagging on state test results.</p>
        <p>Mr. McQuillan, who has taught middle school and served as a superintendent in two Massachusetts districts, said that closing the achievement gap and working on ways to merge state accountability standards with federal standards were among the first issues he will tackle this week when he gets behind his desk. This includes outlining what actions he and the State Board of Education could take on a local level if a school were not making enough progress on student achievement levels, he said.</p>
        <p>''The conviction was that the accountability system we are working with needed more specificity and delineation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Another priority for Mr. McQuillan is preschool education. The state board has outlined an aggressive five-year preschool goal intended to help tackle the achievement gap by helping to provide quality education to young children during the crucial early years. ''We can move toward prevention of reading failure and dropouts instead of using schools as remediation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McQuillan said he would also like to extend the school day or year for struggling students. This could be achieved with pilot schools, similar to those that have been started in Boston, that offer extra and flexible hours, he said.</p>
        <p>The state may also consider a standard used in Massachusetts for special education instruction that puts the emphasis on providing services within the schools to students with special needs, he said.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is in agreement that if you can bring the services to students to the closest point where they live, it's really far better,'' said Mr. McQuillan, who served on a special education collaborative committee in Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>He said the state's lawsuit against the federal government on No Child Left Behind funding was pursued for legitimate reasons. He will defer to the state attorney general to settle the case, he said, but would like to see Connecticut ease tensions with the federal government.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to work more closely with the federal government,'' Mr. McQuillan said. ''There was a strain that arose over this.''</p>
        <p>Regarding the budget, he said that Governor Rell's proposal to give more education money to towns by lifting the cap on education cost-sharing funds would be beneficial. The proposal would overturn a law that requires that any additional money designated for education be spent on education and would allow towns with high per-pupil expenditures to use the additional funds for property tax relief.</p>
        <p>''This infusion of money is badly needed for local cities and towns across the state and will help immeasurably the overall commitment to education,'' Mr. McQuillan said. ''Standards will rise along with additional dollars.''</p>
        <p>Education advocates who have met Mr. McQuillan said they were impressed by his spirit of cooperation. ''He had a real sense of what was going on here and what we needed to do to bring our state to the next level,'' said Robert Rader, executive director of the Connecticut Association of Boards of Education. ''He wanted to hear everybody's opinions before he would move forward.''</p>
        <p>SCHOOLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
