<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giambi's Homer in 13th Cures All for Yanks</title>
    <meta content="15yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E1D8103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giambi's Homer in 13th Cures All for Yanks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees lead the majors in errors, with 13 in their first 10 games. Their starting rotation is depleted by injuries, and their bullpen is exhausted. But they are always a threat to change a close game with one swing.</p>
        <p>It happened Saturday at the Coliseum, when Jason Giambi belted a home run to right center off Lenny DiNardo in the 13th inning, leading the Yankees to a 4-3 victory over the Oakland Athletics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees lead the majors in errors, with 13 in their first 10 games. Their starting rotation is depleted by injuries, and their bullpen is exhausted. But they are always a threat to change a close game with one swing.</p>
        <p>It happened Saturday at the Coliseum, when Jason Giambi belted a home run to right center off Lenny DiNardo in the 13th inning, leading the Yankees to a 4-3 victory over the Oakland Athletics.</p>
        <p>The Yankees won despite making four errors, including two by Derek Jeter, a three-time Gold Glove winner. Jeter has five errors this season, more errors on his own than seven teams have made all season. His error in the first inning led to three unearned runs.</p>
        <p>But that was all the scoring the A's would do against Darrell Rasner and the entire Yankees bullpen. Manager Joe Torre had said he would not use Brian Bruney, who threw 36 pitches on Friday, or Kyle Farnsworth, who threw 23.</p>
        <p>But as the game wore on and the Yankees ran out of other options, both had to pitch. Farnsworth worked a scoreless 10th, and after Mariano Rivera pitched the 11th, Bruney survived the last two innings.</p>
        <p>Bruney struck out Travis Buck, who had tripled off him the night before, when Bruney lost in 11 innings to end the game. Buck was called out looking on a 94 mile-an-hour fastball, and Bruney pumped his fist after the umpire Rob Drake's call.</p>
        <p>In his first start, at home on April 7, Rasner struggled to command his off-speed pitches because of blisters on his right index finger. He was dropped from the rotation because of Thursday's scheduled off day, but a sudden injury to Carl Pavano put him back in. Pavano said he felt stiffness in a forearm muscle near his elbow during his start last Monday in Minnesota. He backed out of his start on Saturday, leaving Rasner to take over at a ballpark he visited while growing up. Rasner is from Carson City, Nev., a four-hour drive from Oakland.</p>
        <p>Yet with many friends and family members watching from the stands, Rasner seemed headed for an early exit. With one out in the first inning, Nick Swisher sliced a double to left and Mike Piazza came to the plate.</p>
        <p>Piazza is Oakland's designated hitter, taking his career a year at a time at age 38. He misses catching, he said, but stays focused on the game by not retreating to the clubhouse between at-bats. ''I'm a bench guy,'' he said by his locker on Saturday afternoon. ''I can't come up here, get a cup of coffee and make some calls, which I've heard guys do. I'm a game guy. If you come in the clubhouse, you get detached from the energy of the game.''</p>
        <p>Piazza hit a grounder to short, and with Swisher running, Jeter tried to gather the ball and throw Swisher out at third. But he bobbled it for his first error, putting runners at the corners for Eric Chavez, who drove in Swisher with a sacrifice fly.</p>
        <p>The two outs, plus the error, ensured that no runs in the inning would be earned. That was good news for Rasner's earned-run average, because the A's scored twice more and hit everything hard.</p>
        <p>Todd Walker singled up the middle, and Bobby Crosby doubled past Josh Phelps at first base, scoring Piazza. Buck hit a single to left that scored Walker and sent Crosby around third.</p>
        <p>With Hideki Matsui on the disabled list, the Yankees' left fielder is Melky Cabrera, whose arm is much stronger. Cabrera fired home to Wil Nieves, who held on and tagged Crosby for the third out.</p>
        <p>Oakland led, 3-0, and while the Yankees could not have known it then, Rasner would allow only one more hit and get 13 more outs. He overcame an error by Robinson Canó in the second, ending the inning with a ground-ball double play, and retired 12 of his last 13 hitters.</p>
        <p>Torre removed him with one out and the bases empty in the sixth, bringing in the left-hander Sean Henn to face the left-handed Chavez. Henn induced two grounders to second base. By then, the Yankees had cut the lead to 3-2. Alex Rodriguez led off the fifth with his seventh home run, the most in the majors, a line drive that cleared the scoreboard in left-center field. Cabrera singled in another run with one out, but Nieves popped out and Johnny Damon struck out, stranding two runners.</p>
        <p>The next time Nieves's spot came up, Torre would not let him hit. Nieves started only because Jorge Posada had caught 11 innings on Friday; he is 0 for 16 in the majors stretching to 2002. Posada came up as a pinch-hitter, a role in which he seems to thrive.</p>
        <p>Joe Blanton got ahead of Posada, 1-2, but his 110th and final pitch was a breaking ball Posada bashed into the right-field corner. Canó scored to make the score 3-3, but Damon grounded out against Jay Marshall, a rookie left-handed specialist, to end the inning.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang, who strained his right hamstring on March 23, threw 55 pitches in an extended spring training game in Tampa, Fla., allowing no hits and one walk. He then threw 15 more pitches in the bullpen. Joe Torre said Wang still needed to throw in a game for Class A Tampa on Thursday before he could be activated from the disabled list. ''This was all about physical stuff,'' Torre said. ''He still has to pitch a little bit.''  With first baseman Doug Mientkiewicz hitless in his last 21 at-bats, Torre started the right-handed Josh Phelps against the right-hander Joe Blanton.  Torre said the inexperience of Chase Wright would not preclude him from starting for the Yankees, if needed, on Tuesday. Wright, 24, has been dominant in two starts for Class AA Trenton. Carl Pavano is scheduled to start Tuesday if he feels good in the bullpen on Sunday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
