<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Julie Hyman, Howard Schnee</title>
    <meta content="15hyman" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/fashion/weddings/15hyman.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hyman, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schnee, Howard Craig</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D7133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Julie Hyman, Howard Schnee</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Julie Hyman, Howard Schnee</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Julie Hyman and Howard Craig Schnee were married last evening at the Engineers Club at the Garrett-Jacobs Mansion in Baltimore. Rabbi Micah Becker-Klein officiated.</p>
        <p>The bride, 30, will continue to use her name professionally. She is an on-air reporter with the television unit of Bloomberg L.P., the news and information service in New York. She graduated magna cum laude from Randolph-Macon College in Ashland, Va. She is a daughter of Sherry and Jon Hyman of Baltimore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Julie Hyman and Howard Craig Schnee were married last evening at the Engineers Club at the Garrett-Jacobs Mansion in Baltimore. Rabbi Micah Becker-Klein officiated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Julie Hyman and Howard Craig Schnee were married last evening at the Engineers Club at the Garrett-Jacobs Mansion in Baltimore. Rabbi Micah Becker-Klein officiated.</p>
        <p>The bride, 30, will continue to use her name professionally. She is an on-air reporter with the television unit of Bloomberg L.P., the news and information service in New York. She graduated magna cum laude from Randolph-Macon College in Ashland, Va. She is a daughter of Sherry and Jon Hyman of Baltimore.</p>
        <p>The bride's father is an owner of the Breakthrough Group, an advertising agency in Towson, Md. Her mother takes Internet orders at the Barnes &amp; Noble bookstore at Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 36, is an owner of Creative Entertainment Group, a music management, marketing and concert promotion firm in New York. He graduated from the University of Hartford. He is the son of Judy and Jack Schnee of Boynton Beach, Fla.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom's father retired as the owner of Hamilton Luggage, a chain of luggage stores that was based in Reading, Pa.</p>
        <p>The couple met in December 2004, during a holiday party at a mutual friend's apartment in New York. Mr. Schnee had arrived as the festivities were winding down. As he walked through the front door, he spotted Ms. Hyman, who was dancing. ''She was smiling and so full of life,'' he said. The soundtrack to that first meeting was ''Drop It Like It's Hot'' by the rapper Snoop Dogg.</p>
        <p>''I asked the host who she was,'' Mr. Schnee continued. ''He didn't know. She was a friend of a mutual friend. I figured I had a little bit of time, but when I noticed that she was putting on her coat to leave, I panicked.''</p>
        <p>He and two friends at the party had made plans to go out afterward. As Ms. Hyman walked toward the front door of the apartment, Mr. Schnee stood in front of her, grabbed her arms and said, ''You're coming with us!''</p>
        <p>''I was like, 'Who is this guy?' '' Ms. Hyman recalled. ''But then I thought, 'Why not?' ''</p>
        <p>Over drinks at a neighborhood bar, Ms. Hyman and Mr. Schnee ''hit it off,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Howie dropped me off in a cab at home,'' she said. ''He was a gentleman.''</p>
        <p>The couple dated for the first half of 2005, but Mr. Schnee was reluctant to commit. ''I had been in a relationship that lasted nearly four years, and I was determined to stay single for a while,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hyman, meanwhile, had been expressing a growing dissatisfaction with the course of their romance. ''I was kind of fed up,'' she recalled.</p>
        <p>In early August, they went to a Ben Folds concert in Prospect Park, and Mr. Schnee had ''an epiphany,'' he said. He felt he wanted a committed relationship with her.</p>
        <p>He did not say a word to her, however. ''I wanted to make sure I felt the same way the next day,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The following evening he called and asked to see her. When they met later that night, he said he confessed, ''I want to be with you and only you.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
