<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yes, Wall St. Still Gets Some Things Right</title>
    <meta content="15every" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/business/yourmoney/15every.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EVERYBODY'S BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Everybody's Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3D6133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yes, Wall St. Still Gets Some Things Right</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yes, Wall St. Still Gets Some Things Right</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN STEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stein, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FEW days ago, I was at a gathering of retirees at a friend's house. I fell into conversation with a group of prosperous-looking men from Texas. They were talking about new developments in oil exploration and recovery. In particular, they were talking about something called fracturing. This is done when oil is trapped in sedimentary rock and doesn't just gush out of the ground when you find it, the way it did for James Dean in ''Giant.''</p>
        <p>The drillers have to pump in immense amounts of a fluid like hydrochloric acid, which is dangerous, expensive and messy, to break up the rock and allow the oil to be sucked out. Sometimes they have to pour immense amounts of sand -- like a million pounds in a six-hour period -- into a well under superhigh pressure to break up the rock and release the oil to flow to the surface.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Let’s pause for a moment to be grateful for some of the marvelous developments in investing innovations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FEW days ago, I was at a gathering of retirees at a friend's house. I fell into conversation with a group of prosperous-looking men from Texas. They were talking about new developments in oil exploration and recovery. In particular, they were talking about something called fracturing. This is done when oil is trapped in sedimentary rock and doesn't just gush out of the ground when you find it, the way it did for James Dean in ''Giant.''</p>
        <p>The drillers have to pump in immense amounts of a fluid like hydrochloric acid, which is dangerous, expensive and messy, to break up the rock and allow the oil to be sucked out. Sometimes they have to pour immense amounts of sand -- like a million pounds in a six-hour period -- into a well under superhigh pressure to break up the rock and release the oil to flow to the surface.</p>
        <p>I marveled, as I always do, at how much trouble it is to get oil from the places where nature has stored it into pipelines and then into a refinery and then into my fire-breathing Cadillac STS-V (a freeway monster). The innovations in the energy field that allow us fools to zoom to the supermarket are incredible.</p>
        <p>A pleasant-looking man was standing next to the oil experts. I asked him if he were an oilman, too. ''No,'' he said, ''I made my living trading over-the-counter stocks. You can't believe what a great business it used to be. Commonly, the spreads on bid and asked were as big as a $1.50 bid, $2 asked, and when I made the sale, I got that 50 cents. On a $2 stock. Those were the days.''</p>
        <p>Suddenly, it hit me. I write constantly -- and with some reason -- about what's wrong in the securities business, and there's plenty. But there have also been some marvelous developments in the field that virtually beggar the imagination and would be hard for an investor working as late as the 1960s to imagine. In their way, they parallel the innovation and ingenuity in oil and gas recovery (and in high tech and manufacturing).</p>
        <p>Let's pause for a moment to be grateful for these investing innovations:</p>
        <p>THE DEREGULATION OF COMMISSIONS -- This spectacular breakthrough meant that investors who had been paying, say, a couple of dollars a share for a 100-share trade of a $60 stock could pay maybe $15 for the whole trade, and sometimes a lot less. Because a significant part of investors' market gains come from foregone fees and costs, this has been a heaven-sent gift for investors of all sizes. It has meant that Wall Street has had to diversify greatly in what it does in order to make ends meet. And the Street has done this well.</p>
        <p>THE RISE OF INDEX FUNDS -- Scholarly work by Burton G. Malkiel, Eugene F. Fama and others has proved that it is the rare investor indeed who can outperform the overall market. And not even most of the actively managed mutual funds have been able to outperform the market as a whole.</p>
        <p>But then came the greatest friend the ordinary investor ever had, John C. Bogle, founder of the Vanguard Funds, who created index funds for small investors. (His latest book, ''The Little Book of Common Sense Investing,'' is the best book in that field for the small investor.)</p>
        <p>These funds did not try to pick stocks; they relied on the power of price itself and of the markets. These funds typically came at very low cost to the investor, provided excellent returns, and were a major way for an intelligent smaller investor to achieve results as good as those of the big boys -- or better.</p>
        <p>At first, these index funds were largely based on major United States indexes like the Standard &amp; Poor's 500, but now such funds are based on most every way of slicing and dicing the market. To some extent, this goes against the grain of the original product, but it also allows for that great pal of the investor, diversification, to play a bigger role.</p>
        <p>It is not at all certain or even likely that buying 20 different segments of the market -- arrayed by market capitalization, industry (utilities, energy, etc.) or growth versus value investment styles -- will outperform just buying the whole market. But buying index funds in these categories far improves upon trying to pick stocks in these groups. The same goes for buying bonds, which used to be difficult and pricey but is now easy if you buy into giant funds run by companies like Vanguard, Fidelity and Pimco.</p>
        <p>AN EASIER PATH TO FOREIGN STOCKS -- It used to be that you had to buy foreign shares in very expensive and cumbersome ways on foreign markets, or else buy American depository receipts, usually with sparse available analysis. Now, the ordinary investor can buy index funds in distinct countries, and in distinct regions like Asia or Europe. In this way, an investor can buy at low cost and diversify just as the world economy is diversifying.</p>
        <p>Investors can also buy exchange-traded funds -- an even nimbler, leaner offshoot of index funds -- whether for emerging-market nations or for developed nations in Europe and Asia. Because these funds allow a play on growth abroad as well as a bet against our endlessly sliding dollar, they are a gift to the investor. Their returns in recent years have been staggering, which probably means that they will be less so in future years, but diversification is still a good thing.</p>
        <p>Other great innovations include online trading at a super-low cost (though it's not a benefit if it encourages reckless day-trading), free online access to research reports, and variable annuities with guaranteed inflation protection and protection of principal. The list goes on. I especially like online retirement calculators that help determine how much to invest during your working years.</p>
        <p>My point is simply this: Yes, Wall Street does plenty that I question. But in terms of making it much easier for the ordinary investor to get to safe retirement, the securities business is now</p>
        <p>incalculably superior to what it once was. It allows us little guys to blast profits out of the sedimentary rock of the stock markets. Let's be grateful.</p>
        <p>EVERYBODY'S BUSINESS Ben Stein is a lawyer, writer, actor and economist. E-mail: ebiz@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ben Stein is a lawyer, writer, actor and economist. E-mail: ebiz@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
