<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Safe Haven in New Haven</title>
    <meta content="15WEwucker" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Day Laborers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wucker, Michele</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFD7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Safe Haven in New Haven</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michele Wucker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wucker, Michele</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Michele Wucker, holding federal government has failed in its immigration policies, calls on municipalities to follow lead of New Haven, Conn, in embracing illegal immigrants (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS Washington tussles over the fate of the nation's estimated 12 million undocumented immigrants, municipal governments are taking sides. Places like Morristown, N.J., and Danbury, Conn., are cracking down. Others, like New Haven and New York City, are embracing their undocumented workers.</p>
        <p>City councils can't change the federal government's failed immigration policies, but they can choose whether to offset or intensify the damage. According to the Migration Policy Institute at New York University, United States municipalities passed 34 laws last year tightening the screws on undocumented immigrants; 56 more such measures are pending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS Washington tussles over the fate of the nation's estimated 12 million undocumented immigrants, municipal governments are taking sides. Places like Morristown, N.J., and Danbury, Conn., are cracking down. Others, like New Haven and New York City, are embracing their undocumented workers.</p>
        <p>City councils can't change the federal government's failed immigration policies, but they can choose whether to offset or intensify the damage. According to the Migration Policy Institute at New York University, United States municipalities passed 34 laws last year tightening the screws on undocumented immigrants; 56 more such measures are pending.</p>
        <p>But the costs of the crackdown cure -- high legal fees, damage to local businesses, scarce police resources wasted, the negative impact on public safety of keeping undocumented immigrants underground and the social division -- are far worse than the supposed illness.</p>
        <p>The officials pushing these crackdowns say they are doing so because of the burden imposed on government services by illegal immigrants. But if businesses close for lack of customers or workers, a town's tax base will fall and it will have to reduce the services that it provides.</p>
        <p>Last year, Riverside, N.J., voted to fine anyone who knowingly rents to or hires illegal immigrants, becoming one of the first municipalities to pass such an ordinance. Many of those towns now complain that immigrants -- with and without papers -- have packed up and left, causing worker shortages. And businesses have had to close because of a lack of customers.</p>
        <p>These policies have imposed other costs in the form of steep legal fees. In New Jersey, Freehold Borough ended up agreeing to pay as much as $278,000 to settle a lawsuit over an anti-loitering law aimed at preventing day laborers from soliciting employment in public places. In a similar case in New York, legal bills for the village of Mamaroneck are estimated in the hundreds of thousands of dollars.</p>
        <p>The direct and indirect costs of cracking down did not escape the notice of Long Island's Suffolk County legislators, who in late March voted down a similar anti-loitering bill. Almost immediately after the defeat, calm-headed proposals surfaced for setting up designated hiring sites while addressing residents' quality-of-life objections.</p>
        <p>Yet recent federal immigration raids in East Hampton, N.Y., including one on a household of American citizens of Ecuadorean descent, are evidence of unresolved tensions on Long Island. In Morristown and Danbury, where residents are deeply divided about whether local police officers should be enforcing federal immigration rules, protests have erupted.</p>
        <p>A much better approach would be for municipalities to follow New Haven's lead. This summer, the city expects to become the first place in the nation to allow undocumented immigrants to apply for municipal identification cards identifying them as city residents. The cards, equipped with a debit chip, will be useful for all residents by facilitating access to municipal services like the public beach, the library, the dump and parking.</p>
        <p>New Haven is also providing financial literacy and tax filing help to immigrants. It expects the ID's to reduce crime by widening access to bank accounts so that residents do not have to hide money in mattresses or carry it on them, making them easy targets for muggers.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, officials hope that their ''don't ask, don't tell'' policy, which prevents the police from inquiring about immigration status, will encourage undocumented residents to feel more comfortable reporting crimes and coming forward with information. What's more, it will allow law enforcement to focus scarce resources on fighting violent crime, a task that police officers widely prefer to chasing illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>New Haven and the dozens of other so-called sanctuary cities -- which include Newark, New York and Trenton -- base their approach on the theory that bringing undocumented residents out of the shadows benefits everyone.</p>
        <p>Morristown and Danbury could learn from New Haven's sensible approach. Identifying residents, encouraging them to trust the police and providing access to needed services makes sense.</p>
        <p>New Haven understands that citizens themselves benefit when all residents feel they have a stake and are not pariahs. A place is far better off when people want to come to it than if they are fleeing in fear, and when practical solutions take precedence over mean-spirited non-solutions.</p>
        <p>Michele Wucker is the author of ''Lockout: Why America Keeps Getting Immigration Wrong When Our Prosperity Depends on Getting It Right.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michele Wucker is the author of ''Lockout: Why America Keeps Getting Immigration Wrong When Our Prosperity Depends on Getting It Right.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
