<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In South Africa, Vintages That Match the Views</title>
    <meta content="15explore" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/travel/15explore.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EXPLORER: CAPE WINELANDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cape Winelands (South Africa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tsui, Bonnie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Africa</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DD153FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1226" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In South Africa, Vintages That Match the Views</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In South Africa, Vintages That Match the Views</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BONNIE TSUI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tsui, Bonnie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bonnie Tsui travel article on Cape Winelands, wine region north and east of Cape Town, South Africa; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you were asked to name locations of the top wineries in the world, several familiar regions would likely come to mind. Bordeaux. Barossa Valley. Napa.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it's time to add one more spot to that list: Cape Town.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you were asked to name locations of the top wineries in the world, Bordeaux and Napa would likely come to mind. It’s time to add Cape Town to that list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you were asked to name locations of the top wineries in the world, several familiar regions would likely come to mind. Bordeaux. Barossa Valley. Napa.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it's time to add one more spot to that list: Cape Town.</p>
        <p>The Cape Winelands of South Africa, stretching roughly 100 miles north and east from Cape Town, have been in production since the Dutch East India Company established the Cape Colony in 1652 and planted gardens at the foot of Table Mountain.</p>
        <p>In the three and a half centuries since, lush green vineyards have carpeted the valley floors around Cape Town, and grande dame estates like Vergelegen have regularly earned top accolades in international wine publications and competitions. And smaller, newer wineries are getting attention with exciting, experimental blends.</p>
        <p>There are more than 20 wine-growing areas and 17 wine routes surrounding Cape Town. All along the roads that crisscross the mountain valleys, signs proclaim ''Wynverkope'' -- Afrikaans for ''Wine Sales.'' A drive around the Winelands is an opportunity to sample stunning wines, many of which you cannot get in the United States -- and at affordable prices.</p>
        <p>In December, I spent a few summery Southern Hemisphere days driving through the Winelands with friends, visiting Franschhoek and Stellenbosch, two of the most important wine areas, both established around towns of the same names.</p>
        <p>Leaving Cape Town, the city quickly gave way to verdant farmlands and flowering lavender fields, all framed by jagged mountain peaks. Less than an hour's drive on meandering roads got us to Franschhoek, a striking valley originally settled by the French Huguenots 300 years ago.</p>
        <p>An arcing monument to the settlers stands in the town of Franschhoek, but Huguenot history is perhaps best preserved and honored in the area's lovely gabled houses -- many of them B &amp; Bs catering to oenophiles -- and its nearly 40 wineries and vineyards. (This is, after all, where the French first made wine in South Africa).</p>
        <p>Though a town of just 16,000, Franschhoek is a significant culinary hub, with an improbably high density of excellent restaurants on its main street. The cafes and sidewalks are often crowded, and are known to harbor celebrities (we spotted Jude Law casually strolling with his children).</p>
        <p>One of the most popular places for an alfresco lunch is Reuben's, with its sun-splashed jewel of a courtyard. Be sure to make a reservation, and make room for Reuben Riffel's incredible roast duck salad with mango, sprouts and mint.</p>
        <p>Another Reuben's owner, Marc Kent, doubles as the winemaker at Boekenhoutskloof, a celebrated winery that in a decade has grown to an annual production of 1.5 million bottles. It is known for its premium cabernet sauvignon and syrah.</p>
        <p>We tried both in the winery's brand-new tasting room, a bright, modern space that opens out to the vineyards and a covered patio. The tasting room attendants were helpful and friendly, and Mr. Kent can often be found chatting with customers. Boekenhoutskloof also produces excellent, good-value wines under the Chocolate Block and Porcupine Ridge labels.</p>
        <p>''We're still the top South African winery to Robert Parker, and we make the top red according to Wine Spectator, so we're doing very well considering that we started just 10 years ago,'' Mr. Kent said.</p>
        <p>Unlike many of his counterparts in the wine world, he does not adhere to the terroir-is-everything doctrine, the idea that elements of a vineyard can be tasted in a wine.</p>
        <p>''South Africa is a veritable fruit salad,'' he said. ''People have planted whatever they wanted, wherever, and so there is a lot of variation. Terroir doesn't really apply, and is certainly less important than getting the best barrels, the best grapes and making the best wine in the winery.''</p>
        <p>There are lots of other up-and-coming operations around Franschhoek, including the family-run Stony Brook Vineyards. We felt like we were at a friend's house when we sat on the veranda; the owners, Joy and Nigel McNaught, often serve guests themselves.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook's premium label is Ghost Gum, named for a 150-year-old tree on the farm, and its best wine is a 2003 cabernet sauvignon with touches of merlot and petit verdot. A visit there spotlights what this valley does best: pairing high-quality wine with an intimate, open-air tasting experience.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Boschendal was founded in 1685, and has its own museum and conservation area in the sprawling grounds. A prime example of Cape Dutch architecture is found there in the manor house; in the late 1890's, when a plague threatened to destroy the area's vineyards, the British-born financier and politician Cecil John Rhodes took over and helped revive the wine industry.</p>
        <p>Outside the tasting center, visitors sit at wrought-iron tables in the shade of a massive oak tree. The setting is majestic, but the service is far from personalized -- we were issued photocopied sheets by a harried server and asked to tick off the wines we wanted to taste. The estate produces an array of wine in six different ranges, including the easy-drinking Pavillion label and the small-batch Cecil John Reserve vintages.</p>
        <p>THE Winelands' most established estates are west of Franschhoek in Stellenbosch, considered the center of South Africa's wine industry. Unlike the tourist-focused village of Franschhoek, Stellenbosch is a large, thriving university center.</p>
        <p>The Stellenbosch wine route now includes over 130 wineries (spread across five sub-routes). We visited Thelema, a family-run cellar that makes deep, delicious cabernet sauvignons, and Ernie Els, the winery of the South African champion golfer that is winning accolades for its new, masterful reds.</p>
        <p>Then there was Vergelegen, a 7,400-acre estate with gorgeous hydrangea, camellia and rose gardens and 300-year-old camphor trees. Like Boschendal, Vergelegen is a large, time-honored estate, but its tasting room is smaller and its staff more attentive.</p>
        <p>In 2001 and 2003, Vergelegen won the Pichon Trophy for best blended red at the International Wine and Spirit Competition in London. It was voted best New World winery in 2005 by the Wine Enthusiast, and named the country's best winery in 2006 for the third year in a row by Wine magazine.</p>
        <p>After tasting the 2005 Vergelegen white, a highly prized, crisp, citrusy semillon-sauvignon blanc blend, we wandered through the sunny gardens and sat under a camphor tree. It had been around since 1700, when the estate was granted to a governor of the Dutch East India Company's Cape Colony supply station. Under that tree, 30 minutes from Cape Town, we discovered that wine was a pretty good way to get close to the city's roots.</p>
        <p>RED OR WHITE IN GREEN VALLEYS</p>
        <p>The annual John Platter South African Wine Guide (www.platteronline.com), a must-have primer, costs 133 rands (about $18.50 at 7.3 rands to the dollar) at bookstores and wine shops.</p>
        <p>Where to Taste</p>
        <p>In Franschhoek:</p>
        <p>Boekenhoutskloof (27-21-876-3320, www.boekenhoutskloof.co.za); tastings are free.</p>
        <p>Stony Brook Vineyards (27-21-876-2182, www.stonybrook.co.za); 20 rands, but refunded with wine purchase.</p>
        <p>Boschendal Wine Estate (27-21-870- 4272, www.boschendal.com); 15 rands.</p>
        <p>In Stellenbosch:</p>
        <p>Thelema Mountain Vineyards (27-21-885-1924, www.thelema.co.za); free.</p>
        <p>Vergelegen Wine Estate (27-21-847-1334, www.vergelegen.co.za); 2 to 10 rands a wine.</p>
        <p>Ernie Els Wines, (27-21-881-3588, www.ernieels.co.za); 30 rands for three wines.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay and Eat</p>
        <p>At Reuben's Restaurant and Bar (19 Huguenot Street, Franschhoek; 27-21-876-3772) lunch for two costs about 300 rands without wine.</p>
        <p>Le Quartier Français in Franschhoek (16 Huguenot Street; 27-21-876-2151, www.lequartier.co.za) is a 17-room Relaix &amp; Chateaux property with two restaurants. Doubles from 2,900 rands.</p>
        <p>EXPLORER: CAPE WINELANDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
