<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smoke (and Mirrors) on the Water</title>
    <meta content="WE--Yonkers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/opinion/nyregionopinions/WEYonkers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Westchester"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Forest City Ratner Companies</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Alsop, Will</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFD7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smoke (and Mirrors) on the Water</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Smoke (and Mirrors) on the Water</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds waterfront development proposal in Yonkers, NY, is huge, intrusive and strikingly out of whack with kind of reasonable, human-scale development that should be central elements of any master plan for city along Hudson River</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A first look at the drawing of the latest development proposal for the Yonkers waterfront is likely to elicit the kind of reaction a puzzled parent gives a bright-eyed toddler with paint-smeared fingers. ''This is interesting, sweetie. Am I holding it right-side up?''</p>
        <p>But then it hits you that this is serious -- that the little brown smudge near the bottom is the shell of a real building, the abandoned Glenwood Power Station; that the hulking mass of quilt triangles and gridwork looming above it is a condominium complex designed by a real British architect, Will Alsop; that a real New Jersey developer, REMI Companies, of Hoboken, N.J., wants to throw it up for $250 million, and that the people who run the City of Yonkers might just be inclined to let that happen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After looking at the latest development proposal for the Yonkers waterfront, you get the impression that the city’s eagerness to throw itself open to splashy development has trumped caution and patient good sense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A first look at the drawing of the latest development proposal for the Yonkers waterfront is likely to elicit the kind of reaction a puzzled parent gives a bright-eyed toddler with paint-smeared fingers. ''This is interesting, sweetie. Am I holding it right-side up?''</p>
        <p>But then it hits you that this is serious -- that the little brown smudge near the bottom is the shell of a real building, the abandoned Glenwood Power Station; that the hulking mass of quilt triangles and gridwork looming above it is a condominium complex designed by a real British architect, Will Alsop; that a real New Jersey developer, REMI Companies, of Hoboken, N.J., wants to throw it up for $250 million, and that the people who run the City of Yonkers might just be inclined to let that happen.</p>
        <p>But the main problem with this project, which is thankfully in the early stages of approval, is not its debatable aesthetics. It's the scale -- 25 stories for the main residential tower, far higher than the abandoned power plant's existing smokestacks, which the developers plan to snip off. The plan is huge and intrusive and strikingly out of whack with the kind of reasonable, human-scale development that should be the central elements of any master plan for a city blessed with such a precious quantity of land along such a cherished river.</p>
        <p>When you add this new project to the others bubbling along in Yonkers -- the $3.1 billion partnership of Stuever Fidelco Cappelli to build massive amounts of housing and offices and a ballpark downtown, and Forest City Ratner's Ridge Hill mini-city to the north -- you get the impression that the city's eagerness to throw itself open to splashy development has trumped caution and patient good sense.</p>
        <p>It's understandable that Yonkers officials want to get moving on redeveloping stagnant properties in their promising but underachieving city. It's impressive that the developers and architect have gone so far out of their way to imagine a complex that is so environmentally friendly, with rooftop windmills providing all its power and solar panels heating its water. And it's wonderful that they want to include a contemporary art museum in the mix, instead of the usual lame assortment of high-end retail shops and services.</p>
        <p>But all the eco-friendly attributes and all the chic extras amount to nothing if they blind the city to an oversized hulk that will squat by the river for generations, blocking light and diminishing public enjoyment by its massiveness. There are a lot of precious attributes of the Hudson waterfront that are easy to overlook in a developer's proposal -- light and air, public access, the matchless view. Yonkers needs to remember that a monster that's green is no less monstrous.</p>
        <p>Westchester</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
