<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maybe It Isn't Evident, but for Knicks, It's Progress</title>
    <meta content="15knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/basketball/15knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Crawford, Jamal</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lee, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maybe It Isn't Evident, but for Knicks, It's Progress</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Maybe It Isn’t Evident, but for Knicks, It’s Progress</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Failure smacked the Knicks across the face late Friday night, after a windup that lasted for four weeks. The whiplash was evident.</p>
        <p>The Knicks looked dazed and sounded worse. Forced to offer early post-mortems on the season, they could not decide whether to dwell on their flaws or grasp at the shards of progress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forced to offer early post-mortems on the season Friday night, Knicks players split the difference: the season was a failure, but it gave them reason for modest optimism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Failure smacked the Knicks across the face late Friday night, after a windup that lasted for four weeks. The whiplash was evident.</p>
        <p>The Knicks looked dazed and sounded worse. Forced to offer early post-mortems on the season, they could not decide whether to dwell on their flaws or grasp at the shards of progress.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, they split the difference: the season was a failure, but it gave them reason for modest optimism.</p>
        <p>''I think everything is judged based upon making the playoffs,'' Stephon Marbury said after the Nets eliminated the Knicks from postseason contention Friday. ''So did we grow this year as a team? Yeah, I would say we grew as a team. But not making the playoffs, that's not good.''</p>
        <p>Marbury did not use the word failure, although some teammates did. The Knicks (32-47) have won only nine more games than they did last season. Given their depleted state, they may not win any of their final three. They play tonight at Toronto.</p>
        <p>Injuries to Jamal Crawford, Quentin Richardson, David Lee and, finally, Marbury, sent the Knicks into a 3-13 free fall over the last four weeks. Only a month ago, they were firmly in contention for the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''We were going to the playoffs, no question about it,'' Crawford said.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Knicks will sit out the postseason for a third straight year and the fifth time in the last six seasons. Even before the injuries struck, the Knicks were on a pace for a sixth consecutive losing record. The closest they got to .500 after the All-Star Game break was 29-34, on March 10.</p>
        <p>By any objective definition, this is not ''evident and significant progress'' -- although that's what the Madison Square Garden chairman, James L. Dolan, declared he had seen when he gave Coach Isiah Thomas a multiyear contract extension on March 12.</p>
        <p>For long stretches of the season, the Knicks were inept on defense and prone to turnovers. They gave away games with poor free-throw shooting, and sometimes with inexperience.</p>
        <p>And sometimes, they seemed not to grasp the importance of each missed opportunity.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't a seasonlong thing,'' the veteran Malik Rose said, ''but there were times when certain people didn't take a loss as hard as other people did. I guess they have to learn or learn to care that much more.''</p>
        <p>While the Knicks took great pride in the development of Eddy Curry as a prolific scorer, they still lack a true franchise player -- someone who can carry the scoring load every night, play steady defense and both lead and elevate his teammates.</p>
        <p>What they do have is a deep stable of solid young players, some of whom could be packaged in a trade for a superstar. The names of Kevin Garnett, Jermaine O'Neal and Ray Allen are certain to be floated around the league this summer.</p>
        <p>A case could also be made for stability. From June 2005 to August 2006, the Knicks imported Curry, Richardson, Lee, Channing Frye, Nate Robinson, Jerome James, Steve Francis, Jared Jeffries, Mardy Collins, Renaldo Balkman and Coach Larry Brown. Last summer, they fired Brown, moved Thomas to the bench and, in many ways, started over again.</p>
        <p>This was Curry's first season as the Knicks' No. 1 scoring option and Lee's first as a major role player. It took half the season for the Knicks to establish an identity. Toward the end, the rookies Collins and Balkman became fixtures in the regular rotation.</p>
        <p>There are enough bright spots across the roster to make the Knicks believe they are capable of much more, if they merely stay together, and healthy, for a while.</p>
        <p>''I think next year will be a different year; we will all have been together,'' Marbury said. ''We have a system in place.''</p>
        <p>As premature as Dolan's decision to extend Thomas seemed, it removed any sense of instability from the coming off-season. There will be no coaching searches and, just as importantly, no lingering bitterness in the locker room. That could not have been said of the Knicks last April, after battles between Brown and his players, and Brown and his bosses.</p>
        <p>''Last year, when you went home you didn't feel good about yourself,'' Richardson said. ''No matter what you averaged or whatever, it was a dogfight, everybody's worst year of their career.''</p>
        <p>This year, the Knicks will head home having at least regained some pride and cohesion, even if the season was a collective failure. At their healthiest, they played at a .500 pace, alternating victories and losses for three months. It was enough to make them believe that, for the first time in years, they were on the right track.</p>
        <p>''We showed glimpses of really coming together and really being a solid unit out there,'' Curry said. ''And we had times when we fell apart. We got a young team. We got guys on this team who are still developing and who will play a major part in our success come next year.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
