<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>By a Nose, Dominican Claims Spot in the Derby</title>
    <meta content="15racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/sports/othersports/15racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840637"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>By a Nose, Dominican Claims Spot in the Derby</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">By a Nose, Dominican Secures Spot in the Derby</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>LEXINGTON, Ky., April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Street Sense was the 2-year-old champion, an imposing dark bay colt with an explosive finishing kick. He came here to the Blue Grass Stakes as the impeccably credentialed early favorite for the 133rd running of the Kentucky Derby on May 5.</p>
        <p>He will leave here with that reputation intact even though he lost this strangely run Grade I, $750,000 race by, at best, a nostril.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A gelding named Dominican ran down Street Sense and three other horses in a blanket finish that had the crowd of 18,056 here holding its breath for a photo finish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Street Sense was the 2-year-old champion, an imposing dark bay colt with an explosive finishing kick. He came here to the Blue Grass Stakes as the impeccably credentialed early favorite for the 133rd running of the Kentucky Derby on May 5.</p>
        <p>He will leave here with that reputation intact even though he lost this strangely run Grade I, $750,000 race by, at best, a nostril.</p>
        <p>A gelding named Dominican ran down Street Sense and three other horses in a blanket finish that had the crowd of 18,056 here holding its breath for a photo finish. Dominican, Street Sense, Zanjero and Teuflesberg were all within a half-length of one another.</p>
        <p>''We were worried,'' said Dominican's owner, Tommy Hamilton, who kept asking his trainer, Darrin Miller, if their horse was really the winner. Miller assured him that Dominican won.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't as sure as they all were that we had won,'' Hamilton said.</p>
        <p>They had plenty of reason to be: Dominican, the son of El Corredor, needed to come in first or second to compile enough graded stakes earnings to make the Derby field. But the camera did not lie.</p>
        <p>''We got there,'' Miller assured Hamilton. ''We wanted to go to the Derby, and we needed to see if we could hook them.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the $465,000 first-place check was plenty to punch their ticket, and the $18 payoff for a $2 bet pleased Dominican's backers.</p>
        <p>Street Sense, too, is going to the Derby, as the likely favorite. His trainer, Carl Nafzger, was looking only for a strong performance from his colt, not necessarily a victory, although he said that he had hoped to add his first Blue Grass triumph to his résumé. He got the former, but still must wait for the latter.</p>
        <p>Two factors conspired against Street Sense -- a pace that was beyond leisurely and an uncharacteristic immature performance by the colt in the lane.</p>
        <p>As the gates opened on this damp, misty afternoon, it was clear that this was going to be a Blue Grass like no other in the race's 83-year history. It was the first Blue Grass Stakes contested on a synthetic track, which made the rain that pounded the area all weekend a nonfactor.</p>
        <p>With Edgar Prado leading the way aboard Teuflesberg, it was also going to be a slow race. Prado waltzed the field of seven into a lullaby of a quarter mile in 26.12, and barely picked up the tempo through three quarters of a mile run in 1:16.65.</p>
        <p>''We were going so slow,'' said Street Sense's jockey, Calvin Borel, who was chugging along in fourth place when the field hit the stretch. ''There was no pace in the race.''</p>
        <p>Still, Borel was not worried. Neither was Rafael Bejarano, who was stalking Street Sense from the outside aboard Dominican. ''We knew Street Sense was going to be real tough,'' Bejarano said, ''so I tried to stay right behind him and wait.''</p>
        <p>Now, as they turned for home, it was time. But Borel had a problem. ''He started looking around at the crowd,'' Borel said. ''If someone would have gone with us, I could have got him running.''</p>
        <p>Instead, Borel had to ask Street Sense, the son of Street Cry, to find his explosive kick. Street Sense did not cooperate immediately. He ducked toward the rail once, twice, and finally a third time. Each time, Borel had to wrestle him back to a straight line.</p>
        <p>Still, a sixteenth of a mile from the finish line, Street Sense ducked his head in front of Zanjero and Teuflesberg. But Bejarano and Dominican were ready to pounce.</p>
        <p>''When I saw him moving at the quarter pole, I moved to the outside,'' Bejarano said.</p>
        <p>The two horses matched strides, trading noses in tandem. When they hit the wire, Dominican was a nose in front of Street Sense, who had a head on Zanjero, who was only a head in front of Teuflesberg.</p>
        <p>''We ran a winning race,'' said a crestfallen Borel, ''but I had to grab him three times and it cost him.''</p>
        <p>While Miller, Hamilton and Bejarano rejoiced over their sudden trip to Churchill Downs, Nafzger took the setback in stride. His colt had come home fast in a very slow race: 1:51.33 for the mile and an eighth route.</p>
        <p>''If he runs straight, you win the race,'' Nafzger told Borel. ''He finished good, and he finished strong. I think his learning process is over.''</p>
        <p>But neither Nafzger, nor anyone else, will know how well Street Sense took to his lessons until the Derby is run in another three weeks.</p>
        <p>NOTES</p>
        <p>Curlin stormed down the stretch to another lopsided victory Saturday, winning the Arkansas Derby at Oaklwan Park in Hot Springs, Ark., by a record 10 1/2 lengths for his third victory in three career starts. Now established as a strong contender for the Kentucky Derby, Curlin was considered a bit unproven coming into the Arkansas Derby because he was so lightly raced. (AP)</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
