<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Naughty, Yes, But Not Exactly Shocking</title>
    <meta content="15ctartsCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15ctarts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale Repertory Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hartford Stage Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Sylviane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lamos, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lichtenberg, Drew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wedekind, Frank (1864-1918)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Doug</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Jeremy B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lecesne, James</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lulu (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">I Am My Own Wife (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Wedekind, Frank</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Naughty, Yes, But Not Exactly Shocking</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Naughty, Yes, but Not Exactly Shocking</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIANE GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gold, Sylviane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sylviane Gold reviews Yale Repertory Theater production of Lulu, adapted by Mark Lamos and Drew Lichtenberg from Frank Wedekind's plays Earth Spirit and Pandora's Box and directed by Lamos; also reviews Hartford Stage production of Doug Wright play I Am My Own Wife, directed by Jeremy B Cohen and starring James Lecesne; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most anyone who took a modern theater course in college knows about Frank Wedekind. He's there at the front of the textbooks and the anthologies, having published his most famous -- and most scandalous -- plays around the turn of the 20th century. His writings were banned by the Kaiser for obscenity, and, in 1913, The New York Times called him ''the naughty boy of the new German drama.''</p>
        <p>Then, as now, being naughty in the theater was a good way to get ahead. Occasionally, you also get ahead of your time. Historians point to Wedekind as a crucial precursor of modernism, of Expressionist theater, of Brecht, of theater of the absurd. He wrote about sex and murder with a candor that shocked his contemporaries, and he structured his plays with a lofty disregard for the rules of naturalism, of genre, of conventional dramaturgy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A “Lulu” that lacks its sense of danger in the age of Britney Spears and Anna Nicole Smith.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most anyone who took a modern theater course in college knows about Frank Wedekind. He's there at the front of the textbooks and the anthologies, having published his most famous -- and most scandalous -- plays around the turn of the 20th century. His writings were banned by the Kaiser for obscenity, and, in 1913, The New York Times called him ''the naughty boy of the new German drama.''</p>
        <p>Then, as now, being naughty in the theater was a good way to get ahead. Occasionally, you also get ahead of your time. Historians point to Wedekind as a crucial precursor of modernism, of Expressionist theater, of Brecht, of theater of the absurd. He wrote about sex and murder with a candor that shocked his contemporaries, and he structured his plays with a lofty disregard for the rules of naturalism, of genre, of conventional dramaturgy.</p>
        <p>Sounds like just the ticket for the 21st century, right? His first drama, ''Spring Awakening,'' is indeed a hit musical on Broadway. And his pair of linked plays about an archetypal femme fatale, ''Earth Spirit'' and ''Pandora's Box,'' have been adapted anew by Mark Lamos and Drew Lichtenberg and mounted at the Yale Repertory Theater as ''Lulu.''</p>
        <p>Yes, she's the Lulu of G. W. Pabst's silent film with Louise Brooks and of the 1930s opera by Alban Berg -- the Lulu whose irresistible allure takes her from the streets to the apex of a corrupt society before dumping her back in the gutter, where Jack the Ripper finally puts an end to her career.</p>
        <p>Given the role's built-in pedigree, you'd imagine that plenty of Norma Desmondy actresses would have played her over the years. But in the theater, Lulu is cited more often than she is seen; the last time she appeared on Broadway was 1925, and the run was brief. The production at the Yale Rep, which runs through April 21, offers some clues about why the Lulu plays are so rarely done -- and so rarely done well.</p>
        <p>This ''Lulu'' starts off promisingly enough, with the ''turn off your cellphones and unwrap your candy'' directives. They are first rendered in elaborately convoluted German and then sparely translated into English with deadpan, Luluesque artlessness.</p>
        <p>If the director, Mr. Lamos, had managed to sustain a similarly dry and self-satirizing tone after the lights went down, the disparate elements of ''Lulu'' might have been held together. Wedekind's farcical flights and stylized, deliberately stilted dialogue (in the translation by Carl R. Mueller) invite just such an approach. Instead, Mr. Lamos went to extravagant lengths to re-create the sense of danger and transgression that made these plays so sensational when they were new.</p>
        <p>At some point in the last century, he might have succeeded. But the task is more difficult today, in an age that no longer distinguishes between notoriety and fame. Who needs Lulu when we have Britney Spears and Anna Nicole Smith? Hot and cold, voracious yet detached, brazen but strangely passive, Lulu is meant to be a revelation, a mantrap for all seasons. Today, she's a commonplace.</p>
        <p>It doesn't help that Mr. Lamos has placed the burden of this monster role on the slender shoulders of the winsome Brienin Bryant. Winsome won't quite suffice for a woman who draws men ineluctably to their doom. It's little wonder, then, that in this production, the play is dominated not by Lulu but by her men.</p>
        <p>This isn't necessarily a bad thing. While the outlines of Lulu's story sound like a cautionary tale, Wedekind was far more interested in savaging the male world that creates and rewards a Lulu than he was in exploring her character or warning women not to follow her lead.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lamos introduces the men of ''Lulu'' in a gross, sweaty lineup, straddling chairs in various states of undress. They leeringly pleasure themselves as the whip-wielding ringmaster -- Wedekind pointedly called him Animal Trainer -- presents Lulu in the guise of an untamed, exotic beast.</p>
        <p>Of course, it's her husbands and lovers who are the beasts, with their eyes ringed in black, their tongues hanging out and their genitals on display. The ''mature audiences'' sticker that comes with this production is not misplaced. In a grotesquely comic orgy of sex and whipped cream, Lulu's conquests -- including the only one with any dignity, a hopelessly smitten countess -- grope her and one another, demolishing a perfectly nice pastry buffet in the process.</p>
        <p>Wedekind's instinct for burlesque and caricature is well served by this scene, and by the production's design team. The cartoony sets, by Rumiko Ishii, have the bold outlines and jarring contrasts of the writing. And the lurid costumes of Christina Bullard often outshine the actors wearing them.</p>
        <p>But such good work can hardly make up for the deficits in the production overall. There may well be a way of staging a ''Lulu'' that feels both authentic and contemporary. But for now, Frank Wedekind is better venerated at the Yale University Library than at the Rep.</p>
        <p>CURTAIN UP!</p>
        <p>SOME plays benefit from surprise -- the less you know, the more rewarding they are. But for Doug Wright's ''I Am My Own Wife,'' which is in previews and opens at the Hartford Stage on Friday, it helps to be prepared.</p>
        <p>Not to worry -- a Ph.D. is not required. What you need to know is that there are dozens of characters in the play, and they're all played by one actor; it takes place mainly in Germany, over the lifetime of a remarkable person named Charlotte von Mahlsdorf; and Charlotte, who lived and died (in 2002) as a woman, was actually a man.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright intended to turn Charlotte, whose real name was Lothar Berfelde, into a hero: an openly gay transvestite who managed to survive both the Nazis and the Communists without hiding who he was. But some inconvenient facts got in the way. When the East German regime fell, newly public government records revealed that Charlotte had earned her free pass by acting as an informant for the secret police.</p>
        <p>The play Mr. Wright wanted to write might have been good. But the one he had to write, about truth and lies and history, is far better. It won the 2004 Tony Award and a Pulitzer Prize and gave Jefferson Mays, in a plain black dress and kerchief, the role of a lifetime. The Hartford Stage production is directed by Jeremy B. Cohen and stars James Lecesne, below, as Charlotte, whose tales about her adventures escaping from Nazis and smuggling antiques out of East Germany are theatrical and enthralling but ultimately suspect. For there's an unresolvable conundrum at the heart of this play: If you lie about who you are, can you tell the truth about anything else? And even more mysterious, between Charlotte and Lothar, which is the true lie?</p>
        <p>''Lulu,'' by Frank Wedekind (translated by Carl R. Mueller), is at the Yale Repertory Theater, 1120 Chapel Street, New Haven, through April 21. Information: (203) 432-1234 or www.yalerep.org.  ''I Am My Own Wife,'' by Doug Wright, is at the Hartford Stage, 50 Church Street, through May 13. Information: (860) 527-5151 or www.hartfordstage.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
