<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Me! Me! Me! All the Way Home</title>
    <meta content="15window" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/realestate/15window.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840465"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WINDOW SHOPPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tsao &amp; McKown</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slesin, Suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Balazs, Andre</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tsao, Calvin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E2DC133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Me! Me! Me! All the Way Home</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Me! Me! Me! All the Way Home</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE SLESIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slesin, Suzanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Window Shopping column on William Beaver House, 47-story, 319-unit condominium tower at 15 William Street in financial district of Manhattan; interiors of building were designed by Tsao &amp; McKown with luxury hotel-like amenities; occupancy is scheduled for spring of 2008; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERYBODY has been telling me something I'm not too excited about. Namely, that to get a good deal on a new condo one has to commit to a space before the building has even been topped off. That explains why developers spend oodles of money not only on mock-ups of rooms but also on elaborate marketing plans that highlight future amenities -- even if there's not a corner deli in sight in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Nowhere else does this seem to have been done with such élan as at the William Beaver House, André Balazs's 47-story, 319-unit tower at 15 William Street in the financial district.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Calvin Tsao tells Suzanne Slesin she is too old for theWilliam Beaver.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERYBODY has been telling me something I'm not too excited about. Namely, that to get a good deal on a new condo one has to commit to a space before the building has even been topped off. That explains why developers spend oodles of money not only on mock-ups of rooms but also on elaborate marketing plans that highlight future amenities -- even if there's not a corner deli in sight in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Nowhere else does this seem to have been done with such élan as at the William Beaver House, André Balazs's 47-story, 319-unit tower at 15 William Street in the financial district.</p>
        <p>The building is where William and Beaver Streets meet -- hence the name and the inspiration for the jaunty, cute, key-toting beaver that is the mascot of the project.</p>
        <p>''The fur trade is part of the original economy of the area, and there's some tongue-in-cheek going on here,'' explained Calvin Tsao, a partner in the Manhattan architectural firm of Tsao &amp; McKown, which designed the interiors of the building, to be ready for occupancy in the spring of 2008. The architectural firm of record is SLCE Architects.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsao was enthusiastic about showing off what he considers one of his most ambitious projects to date.</p>
        <p>I had gotten out of a cab at the triangular site, where a huge crane reached up to the sky, but the building was nowhere to be seen. Down the street -- and across a windswept plaza where a striking Dubuffet sculpture made me feel as if I were in Chicago -- I entered the sales office at 6 Hanover Street.</p>
        <p>Now that is one fabulous space. Cappuccinos are served during the day, drinks at night, in what was once a bank and now functions as the backdrop for a model of the building and full-size mock-ups of a kitchen, bedroom and bathroom.</p>
        <p>I was getting excited, but at the same time I was distracted by a video over the bar that mixed images of the building and its amenities with scenes of rushing woodland streams (remember the beaver?). I tried to concentrate on Mr. Tsao's rather refreshing soft-sell approach and sober explanation of the project.</p>
        <p>''This property was not on most of our radar, but with the exception of China, New York is the only place where entire neighborhoods will be reimagined,'' Mr. Tsao said. The William Beaver, he added, is going up on a site ''where a building had been torn down years ago and had more recently been an empty parking lot -- the new building is positioned so you can look all the way down William Street and to the water.''</p>
        <p>Now water views are something I would give up lots of other things for, so I was sort of surprised when Mr. Tsao said without hesitation: ''This building is absolutely not for you. Its target is a younger, more mobile community.''</p>
        <p>He was right, I guess. But somehow, as soon as someone says that something is not for me, it just makes me all the more interested.</p>
        <p>''Most of the units are small,'' Mr. Tsao continued. ''They are for people who travel, maybe not for families, as there's nothing like Central Park near here, and the Battery is quite far. They are for a new generation that love living in hotel rooms.''</p>
        <p>Now just hold on, Calvin, I wanted to shout. You may not know me all that well, but Calvin, that's me! Me! Me! I love everything about hotels -- especially room service, or any kind of service. And I'm particularly partial to Mr. Balazs's hotels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsao continued listing the building's future amenities -- and I was loving most of them: an upscale deli on the ground floor (that really caught my fancy); a spacious gym with an outdoor terrace; on-site parking and a garage; a screening room; an indoor pool; a covered dog run (with luck, our elderly cairn terrier will live long enough to enjoy it).</p>
        <p>I loved, loved, loved all those things -- and was not entirely immune to the handball court and half basketball court.</p>
        <p>''The building is a vertically integrated village, a very self-sufficient place to live,'' Mr. Tsao added, pointing out the comfy lounge area with its meandering sofas where I was enjoying my second espresso.</p>
        <p>''We're romancing the public areas -- where people can interact,'' he said, ''and trying to create a lobby that's a series of lounges you can use.'' I get that -- the large lobby where you can see the world come and go, as if you were a permanent guest in a grand hotel -- a hip, modern grand hotel.</p>
        <p>Maybe some of those mobile people who are on their way somewhere glamorous will be able to stop and interact with those of us who may be just over their age limit.</p>
        <p>Unaware of my geriatric thoughts, Mr. Tsao continued: ''Design is not only what you see -- it's planning with good DNA. The building is based on catching views and light. It's like a building in Hong Kong that is a sapling, a little tree, straining for light.''</p>
        <p>We walk over to the mock-up of a kitchen-dining area, past the seductive model with its apartments like ribbons encircling the tall structure. There are practically no apartments facing west; rather, most have been positioned to get the most light and views in a part of the city that is densely built.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to create a tall building that did not look like an office building,'' Mr. Tsao said, pointing out the way the exterior was conceived as two giant vertical folds, or pleats. ''We're reviving early Modernist ideas,'' he said. ''This is our Le Corbusier or Mies van der Rohe moment -- modernity that has a civic heart.''</p>
        <p>I was moving toward the mock-up of the kitchen and dining area where neat sliding panels hide a home office and a chopping block slips smoothly over the sink. ''Not innovation for innovation's sake,'' Mr. Tsao said, ''but keeping things simple so you can do your own thing.''</p>
        <p>I appreciated the smoothness of the Corian counters, and in the adjacent bedroom area, the recessed blinds in the tall windows and the louvered doors that separated the bedroom from the spacious bathrooms.</p>
        <p>''The bed and bath are en suite,'' Mr. Tsao said. ''That's for the spa moments. You can get out of the tub and be right in the bedroom.''</p>
        <p>There's also a large glassed-in shower and a separate toilet, as well as a nice pullout drawer under the single sink. Now that's a surprise. As far as I knew, two sinks were de rigueur in all luxury condominium bathrooms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsao was ready. ''People don't brush their teeth side by side,'' he asserted. ''He brushes in the shower. It's a boy thing.''</p>
        <p>Well, it certainly isn't a girl thing.</p>
        <p>I glanced at the price list. Sales began in January. So far, 92 units have been sold. Apartments still available include 698-square-foot studios (39D is $1.115 million, 31D is $1.02 million, and the estimated common charge is $640 for each). At the top of the line, both in price and position, is the $4.25 million Penthouse 3, with 1,623 square feet, two bedrooms, two and a half baths and a terrace. The estimated common charge is about $1,500.</p>
        <p>Tax abatements for the apartments are alluring. Without them, the estimated yearly taxes would be about $1,200 for most one-bedrooms, but with the abatements, they would be under $75. For the penthouse, the taxes would be about $2,400 without the abatement but only $113 with it.</p>
        <p>Sales seem to be brisk. Probably too brisk for me to take action quickly. All I can think now is, drat. I seem to be missing this particular real estate boat again, but this time in more ways than one.</p>
        <p>Oh well. Maybe I just have to play with people my own age.</p>
        <p>WINDOW SHOPPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
