<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Montauk Yacht Club Sold for $34 Million</title>
    <meta content="15liweekLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15liweek.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marinas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montauk (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Water Mill (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montauk Yacht Club Resort and Marina</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Island Global Yachting</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parrish Art Museum (Southampton, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suozzi, Thomas R (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Montauk Yacht Club</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E2D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Montauk Yacht Club Sold for $34 Million</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Montauk Yacht Club Sold for $34 Million</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Week column; Montauk Yacht Club Resort and Marina is sold to Island Global Yachting of Fort Lauderdale, Fla, for $34 million; County Executive Thomas Suozzi backs bill that would put red-light cameras at stoplights of 50 most dangerous intersections in Nassau County; Parrish Art Museum, citing unanticipated construction costs, scales back by more than 20 percent plans for new building in Water Mill with price tag of more than $100 million; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Montauk Yacht Club Resort and Marina has been a destination of choice for many guests -- with and without yachts -- since 1928. Now it is part of the changing face of the Montauk waterfront, having been sold this month for $34 million.</p>
        <p>The transaction followed the sale of another major waterfront property, the Panoramic View Hotel, which recently sold for $45 million. Other high-priced properties on the market include Gosman's Dock, a seafood complex, listed at $55 million; the Startop Ranch, a former horse farm, at $13.5 million; and a new 5,000-square-foot oceanfront home with a separate guest house on six acres in the moorlands, listed at $24.5 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new owner said it planned to improve the property, renovate the hotel and upgrade services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Montauk Yacht Club Resort and Marina has been a destination of choice for many guests -- with and without yachts -- since 1928. Now it is part of the changing face of the Montauk waterfront, having been sold this month for $34 million.</p>
        <p>The transaction followed the sale of another major waterfront property, the Panoramic View Hotel, which recently sold for $45 million. Other high-priced properties on the market include Gosman's Dock, a seafood complex, listed at $55 million; the Startop Ranch, a former horse farm, at $13.5 million; and a new 5,000-square-foot oceanfront home with a separate guest house on six acres in the moorlands, listed at $24.5 million.</p>
        <p>The buyer of the yacht club, Island Global Yachting, of Fort Lauderdale, Fla., operates more than a dozen marinas worldwide. Chuck Smith, a company spokesman, said it planned to improve the property, renovate the hotel and upgrade services.</p>
        <p>The 35-acre resort includes 232 boat slips, 107 guest rooms and villa suites, a spa, two restaurants and 12,000 square feet of meeting space.</p>
        <p>The original building was built by the developer Carl G. Fisher, who wanted to replicate his success in Miami Beach with Montauk. When he realized he needed a harbor to attract yachts, Mr. Fisher had a channel dug to create a private harbor. A 60-foot replica of the Montauk Lighthouse was added, and it remains a focal point of the resort.</p>
        <p>Joan Hegner, senior vice president of the Corcoran Group, which has the listing on the ranch and the oceanfront home, said that Montauk had begun to draw more big spenders looking to buy property where it is less congested than in the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>''Ten years ago, we never dreamed that we'd see these numbers,'' she said, citing the Andy Warhol estate that sold in January for $27 million. ''We are no longer the afterthought.''</p>
        <p>Traffic-Light Cameras Gain Suozzi's Backing</p>
        <p>If Thomas R. Suozzi, the Nassau County executive, gets his way, cameras at stoplights will soon be watching over drivers at 50 of the county's most dangerous intersections to make sure they don't get away with running a red light.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suozzi joined the sponsors of the measure in the State Legislature, Senator Charles J. Fuschillo Jr., Republican of Merrick, and Assemblyman Charles D. Lavine, Democrat of Glen Cove, at a news conference on Tuesday. If the state approves it, the cameras would take digital photographs of any vehicle running a red light, and a $50 summons would be mailed to the car's registered owner.</p>
        <p>Each camera costs $120,000, but once they are paid for, the county estimated, the measure will increase its annual revenues by $7 million.</p>
        <p>''The goal is not to bring in more money, but to change the behavior of drivers,'' Mr. Suozzi said. For example, he said, at the intersection of Carmans Road and Louden Avenue at the entrance to Sunrise Mall in Massapequa, there were 70 accidents between 2000 and 2005, resulting in 53 injuries. ''Of those, 41 could have been prevented if motorists had not ignored the traffic signal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>New York City is the only municipality in the state that has installed red-light cameras, beginning in 1994. New York City reported a 73 percent drop in red-light violations over the first 11 years, a 41 percent reduction in collisions at intersections with the cameras and a 35 percent drop in vehicular fatalities there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fuschillo said New York City's experience indicated that the cameras had deterred drivers from running red lights and had reduced accidents. ''If the technology is available, we should certainly take advantage of it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Among the Nassau intersections deemed most at risk for accidents are Post Avenue and Old Country Road in Westbury, the site of 382 accidents from 2000 to 2005; Glen Cove Road and Old Country Road in Carle Place (302 accidents); Nassau Expressway and Bay Boulevard (242) in Inwood/Lawrence; and Nassau Expressway and Burnside Avenue (239), also in Inwood/Lawrence.</p>
        <p>Museum's Building Plans Undergo Cutback</p>
        <p>The Parrish Art Museum's plans for a new building in Water Mill with a price tag of more than $100 million have been scaled back by more than 20 percent because of unanticipated construction costs.</p>
        <p>The museum, which has been in its original building in the Village of Southampton since 1898, has asked its architects to reduce the size of the new building on 14 acres in Water Mill to 63,000 square feet from 80,000 square feet. The new plan would also divide the construction into two phases, with the museum to open in the fall of 2009.</p>
        <p>The basic design concept of the building by the Swiss team of Jacques Herzog and Pierre de Meuron will be unchanged, said Erin Ferguson, a museum spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferguson said a capital campaign had raised $30 million, but ''when we started to begin to work with a construction management firm, the prices were higher than we had expected.''</p>
        <p>The revised plan calls for breaking ground in early 2008. Its first phase, estimated to cost $55 million to $60 million, will include about 42,000 square feet of gallery space, classrooms, a 260-seat auditorium, a central lobby, a cafe and museum shop, and offices. Phase 2, involving 20,000 square feet of administrative space and an expanded gift shop and cafe, will proceed once the necessary money is raised, Ms. Ferguson said.</p>
        <p>The museum has submitted its revised application to the Southampton Town Board for approval. Ms. Ferguson said it might take four to six months.</p>
        <p>The Parrish, Long Island's oldest art museum, is also looking for a new director, following the announcement in February that Trudy C. Kramer would retire after 26 years. Ms. Ferguson said that the board hoped to have a new director by this fall.</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
