<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Confederates Among Us</title>
    <meta content="15CIfromson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/opinion/nyregionopinions/15CIfromson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War (US) (1861-65)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fromson, Brett Duval</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Richard T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Civil War (US) (1861-65)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War (US) (1861-65)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED7133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Confederates Among Us</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Confederates Among Us</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Brett Duval Fromson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fromson, Brett Duval</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Brett Duval Fromson on Richard T Wilson, former Confederate financier and blockade runner from Georgia who moved to New York at end of Civil War and became multimillionaire (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>APRIL is a big month for Civil War buffs -- Robert E. Lee surrendered on April 9, 1865, and five days later Abraham Lincoln was fatally shot. As we remember those momentous dates in our nation's history, here's something for New Yorkers to think about.</p>
        <p>In the 1860s, thousands of white Southerners moved north to this state, particularly to the metropolitan area. These Confederate carpetbaggers were mainly young families who shared an intrepid character forged by years of chaos and deprivation in the South; they were refugees who had been displaced as early as 1862 by the invading Union Army. They did not delude themselves into thinking that the South would rise again. They saw New York as a place where second chances could be had.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The making of a New York Yankee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>APRIL is a big month for Civil War buffs -- Robert E. Lee surrendered on April 9, 1865, and five days later Abraham Lincoln was fatally shot. As we remember those momentous dates in our nation's history, here's something for New Yorkers to think about.</p>
        <p>In the 1860s, thousands of white Southerners moved north to this state, particularly to the metropolitan area. These Confederate carpetbaggers were mainly young families who shared an intrepid character forged by years of chaos and deprivation in the South; they were refugees who had been displaced as early as 1862 by the invading Union Army. They did not delude themselves into thinking that the South would rise again. They saw New York as a place where second chances could be had.</p>
        <p>The city absorbed these dislocated newcomers and channeled their ambitions and wounded pride to its advantage. Prior misdeeds were played down. Yes, a few New Yorkers snubbed the former rebels, but not many. And at a time when ugly nativism and racism were typical, these former Confederates had the advantage of being white, Protestant and American-born.</p>
        <p>They transformed themselves into financiers, merchants, railroad tycoons, lawyers, politicians and public intellectuals. Among the group was Virginia's Burton Harrison, who went from Jefferson Davis's personal secretary to a leading New York lawyer and political power broker. Thomas Fortune Ryan, another Virginian, rose to great wealth and influence through investments in railroads. A Tennessean, John Inman, climbed to the top via cotton trading and railroads. And perhaps the most remarkable of the group was Richard T. Wilson, a former Confederate financier and blockade runner from Georgia.</p>
        <p>Wilson was born to a poor farming family in northern Georgia. As a teenager, he made his way to Tennessee and became a commission merchant.</p>
        <p>At the Civil War's outbreak, he plunged into the high-profit, high-risk business of provisioning Confederate troops with salt pork and bacon. Amid shifting battle lines, he did well procuring meat for the rebels and was asked to join the Confederacy's commissary general. He was also an exceptional speculator in gold, currency, cotton and real estate, both for his own account and for some of the South's military and political leaders. He even financed the running of Southern cotton through the federal blockade, a risky but enormously profitable endeavor.</p>
        <p>Ever-retreating with the Confederate Army, Wilson and his family abandoned their home in Tennessee, fled to Atlanta on a flatbed railcar, then to Wilmington, N.C., from which they escaped via blockade runner in a harrowing night flight. They took a steamboat to Bermuda, north to Nova Scotia, across the icy North Atlantic to Liverpool and on to London.</p>
        <p>At war's end, they were living in London but eager to return to the United States. Wilson pledged allegiance to the Union, received a presidential pardon and moved his family to New York. With $500,000 amassed during the war, he established a cotton trading and investment banking firm and became a multimillionaire.</p>
        <p>He came to control one of the largest railroad systems in the South as well as mining and chemical companies, and rail car systems in several American cities -- including Detroit, Providence, R.I., and Yonkers. He was instrumental in the creation of New York's subway system and controlled several Manhattan- and Brooklyn-based gas utilities that later became part of Con Edison.</p>
        <p>As successful as Wilson was in business, his wife, Melissa, was even more socially adept. She charmed her way to the top of the ladder, leaping social barriers intended to bar the nouveaux riches.</p>
        <p>At the ripe old age of 80, Wilson died peacefully in his own bed surrounded by his family in his Fifth Avenue mansion. (It had been Boss Tweed's.) He was extolled in front-page obituaries in the New York papers. The robber baron J. P. Morgan attended his funeral. Wilson's body was buried in Woodlawn Cemetery in a mausoleum as big as the Georgia cabin he grew up in.</p>
        <p>Wilson has faded from the public memory. But, by the time of his death, his children had become celebrated citizens of New York -- one son owned Saratoga Race Course with his friend Harry Payne Whitney.</p>
        <p>As we think back about the war that tore apart this country, it's interesting to reflect on these little-known stories of Confederates who represent an archetypal New York experience. Losers can become winners and in the process reshape the city, the region, and the world.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Brett Duval Fromson is the author of ''Hitting the Jackpot: The Inside Story of the Richest Indian Tribe in History.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Brett Duval Fromson is the author of ''Hitting the Jackpot: The Inside Story of the Richest Indian Tribe in History.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
