<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CHILDREN'S BEST SELLERS: April 15, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Bestkids.paper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/bestseller/0415bestchildren.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1170" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CHILDREN'S BEST SELLERS: April 15, 2007</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Children’s Books</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 31, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books. All four children's lists appear each week on the Book Review's Web site. Publishers have provided the age designations for their best-selling children's titles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>1. FANCY NANCY AND THE POSH PUPPY, by Jane O’Connor2. FANCY NANCY, by Jane O’Connor 3. FLOTSAM, by David Wiesner 4. SOMEDAY, by Alison McGhee 5. MAHALIA MOUSE GOES TO COLLEGE, by John Lithgow</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 31, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books. All four children's lists appear each week on the Book Review's Web site. Publishers have provided the age designations for their best-selling children's titles.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>CHAPTER BOOKS</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>34</p>
        <p>NEW MOON, by Stephenie Meyer. (Megan Tingley/ Little, Brown, $17.99.) A human and a vampire continue their love affair; a sequel to ''Twilight.'' (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>THE INVENTION OF HUGO CABRET, written and illustrated by Brian Selznick. (Scholastic, $22.99.) A novel ''in words and pictures''; an orphaned thief must decipher his father's last message. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>IMPULSE, by Ellen Hopkins. (McElderry, $16.99.) Three suicidal teenagers meet at a psychiatric hospital. (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>51</p>
        <p>THE BOOK THIEF, by Markus Zusak. (Knopf, $16.95.) In Nazi Germany, a girl shares books with a Jewish man. (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>RULES, by Cynthia Lord. (Scholastic, $15.99.) Life with an autistic brother. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>THE HIGHER POWER OF LUCKY, by Susan Patron. Illustrated by Matt Phelan. (Richard Jackson/Atheneum, $16.95.) A 10-year-old plans to leave her small town. (Ages 9 to 11)</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>TWISTED, by Laurie Halse Anderson. (Viking, $16.99.) Caught spraying graffiti and sentenced to physical labor, a former nerd attracts his secret crush. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>ON THE WINGS OF HEROES, by Richard Peck. (Dial, $16.99.) In World War II, a Midwestern boy looks up to his brother (who's fighting) and his dad (who's not). (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>HATTIE BIG SKY, by Kirby Larson. (Delacorte, $15.95.) A young orphan inherits a Montana homestead in 1918. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE ASTONISHING LIFE OF OCTAVIAN NOTHING, by M. T. Anderson. (Candlewick, $17.99.) In 1700s Boston, a seemingly privileged black boy learns he's actually a slave. (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>PICTURE BOOKS</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>FANCY NANCY AND THE POSH PUPPY, by Jane O'Connor. Illustrated by Robin Preiss Glasser. (HarperCollins, $16.99.) What kind of dog is best for a fancy girl? (Ages 4 to 7)</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>64</p>
        <p>FANCY NANCY, by Jane O'Connor. Illustrated by Robin Preiss Glasser. (HarperCollins, $15.99.) A girl takes her family out. (Ages 4 to 7)</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>FLOTSAM, by David Wiesner. (Clarion, $17.) The things that wash up on the beach; a story in pictures. (Ages 4 to 7)</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>SOMEDAY, by Alison McGhee. Illustrated by Peter H. Reynolds. (Atheneum, $14.99.) A mother imagines her child's future. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>MAHALIA MOUSE GOES TO COLLEGE, by John Lithgow. Illustrated by Igor Oleynikov. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $17.99.) A rodent earns her Harvard degree. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>PIRATES DON'T CHANGE DIAPERS, by Melinda Long. Illustrated by David Shannon. (Harcourt, $16.) To recover treasure, a crew of pirates first has to baby-sit. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>DOG, by Matthew Van Fleet. Photography by Brian Stanton. (Paula Wiseman/Simon &amp; Schuster, $14.99.) An interactive look at 20 breeds. (Ages 3 to 5)</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>NOT A BOX, written and illustrated by Antoinette Portis. (HarperCollins, $12.99.) Imagination turns a young rabbit's cardboard box into anything but. (Ages 3 to 6)</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>TODAY I WILL FLY!, written and illustrated by Mo Willems. (Hyperion, $8.99.) Piggie is determined to fly, even though Gerald the elephant tells him it's impossible. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>19</p>
        <p>LIBRARY LION, by Michelle Knudsen. Illustrated by Kevin Hawkes. (Candlewick, $15.99.) A lion obeys the library rules until there's good reason not to. (Ages 5 to 8)</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>PAPERBACK BOOKS</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>ELDEST, by Christopher Paolini. (Knopf, $12.99.) Eragon in the land of elves; Book 2 in the Inheritance trilogy. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>IT's NOT EASY BEING MEAN, by Lisi Harrison. (Little, Brown, $9.99.) Actually, it's easier than you might think. A ''Clique'' novel. (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>101</p>
        <p>ERAGON, by Christopher Paolini. (Knopf, $9.95.) A boy and a dragon must navigate a world of dark powers. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>MAXIMUM RIDE: SCHOOL'S OUT -- FOREVER, by James Patterson. (Little, Brown, $6.99.) Who's trying to kill Max and her flying friends? (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>TWILIGHT, by Stephenie Meyer. (Megan Tingley/Little, Brown, $8.99.) The new girl falls in love with a vampire. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>MUGGLENET.COM'S WHAT WILL HAPPEN IN HARRY POTTER 7, by Ben Schoen et al. (Ulysses, $13.95.) Predictions from a leading fan Web site. (Ages 8 and up)</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>BRIDGE TO TERABITHIA, by Katherine Paterson. (HarperCollins, $6.99.) Unlikely friends rule an imaginary land. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>HEART OF GLASS, by Zoey Dean. (Little, Brown, $9.99.) Caught on a celebrity's estate, two girls have to organize a charity fashion show; an ''A-List'' novel. (Ages 15 and up)</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE STORY OF THE EASTER BUNNY, by Katherine Tegen. Illustrated by Sally Anne Lambert. (HarperCollins, $6.99.) How the Easter Bunny learned his trade. (Ages 3 to 8)</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>UGLIES, by Scott Westerfeld. (Simon Pulse, $7.99.) In a dystopian world, beauty is mandatory. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>SERIES</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>131</p>
        <p>MAGIC TREE HOUSE, by Mary Pope Osborne. Illustrated by Sal Murdocca. (Stepping Stone/Random House, hardcover and paperback.) Children travel in time. (Ages 6 to 9)</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>131</p>
        <p>JUNIE B., FIRST GRADER, by Barbara Park. Illustrated by Denise Brunkus. (Stepping Stone/Random House, hardcover and paperback.) Adventures in school. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>96</p>
        <p>THE SISTERHOOD OF THE TRAVELING PANTS, by Ann Brashares. (Delacorte, hardcover and paperback.) Four friends share magical pants. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>SEPTIMUS HEAP, by Angie Sage. (Tegen/HarperCollins, hardcover.) Lost at birth, a boy fulfills his destiny as a wizard. (Ages 9 and up)</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>131</p>
        <p>HARRY POTTER, by J. K. Rowling. (Levine/Scholastic, hardcover and paperback.) Trouble at Hogwarts. (Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>INTERNET GIRLs, by Lauren Myracle. (Amulet/Abrams, hardcover and paperback.) Social life, via instant messages. (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>130</p>
        <p>A SERIES OF UNFORTUNATE EVENTS, by Lemony Snicket. (HarperCollins, hardcover only.) The poor Baudelaires. (Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>WARRIORS: THE NEW PROPHECY, by Erin Hunter. (HarperCollins, hardcover only.) Cat warriors fight for survival. (Ages 10 to 14)</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>32</p>
        <p>THE ALEX RIDER ADVENTURES, by Anthony Horowitz. (Philomel/Speak, hardcover and paperback.) A boy spy follows in his father's footsteps. (Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>D'lacey's dRAGONs, by Chris d'Lacey. (Orchard/Scholastic, hardcover and paperback.) Clay figurines come to life. (Ages 9 to 12)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
