<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Talk: Scent Notes; Dirty Tricks</title>
    <meta content="05talk.chandler.t-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="T: Beauty" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4DB123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Talk: Scent Notes; Dirty Tricks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Chandler Burr</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dirty is vastly underrated as a perfume aesthetic. There are, of course, several kinds of dirty. Exhibit A is Agent Provocateur, a lingerie concern that, like Victoria's Secret, professes to sell sex. But while Victoria's Secret is that great Middle American Walt Disney of sex, Agent is slightly grittier, dirtier. Or it professes to be; sex packaged by marketers tends to promise the real thing but is in fact so sterile you couldn't even catch the other person's cold. It's dirt without germs, an idea of intimacy without actually experiencing it. The surprise is that this turns out to be an excellent concept for a perfume. The brilliance of Agent Provocateur, the company's rather astonishing first perfume, is that it doesn't actually smell like unwashed panties. It's better than that: it just reminds you of them. It smells like crushed raspberries and black plums on hot skin. Expertly constructed by the perfumer Christian Provenzano, the juice lasts beautifully, diffuses perfectly and could raise the fertility rate in Manhattan without raising laundry bills. It's like a photo of a thong and cheeky ouverts. All image, no dirt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dirty is vastly underrated as a perfume aesthetic. There are, of course, several kinds of dirty. Exhibit A is Agent Provocateur, a lingerie concern that, like Victoria's Secret, professes to sell sex. But while Victoria's Secret is that great Middle American Walt Disney of sex, Agent is slightly grittier, dirtier. Or it professes to be; sex packaged by marketers tends to promise the real thing but is in fact so sterile you couldn't even catch the other person's cold. It's dirt without germs, an idea of intimacy without actually experiencing it. The surprise is that this turns out to be an excellent concept for a perfume. The brilliance of Agent Provocateur, the company's rather astonishing first perfume, is that it doesn't actually smell like unwashed panties. It's better than that: it just reminds you of them. It smells like crushed raspberries and black plums on hot skin. Expertly constructed by the perfumer Christian Provenzano, the juice lasts beautifully, diffuses perfectly and could raise the fertility rate in Manhattan without raising laundry bills. It's like a photo of a thong and cheeky ouverts. All image, no dirt.</p>
        <p>Before I had ever smelled L'Autre by the niche French house Diptyque, I heard someone call it the dirtiest perfume they'd ever smelled. Most of the ''stories'' behind perfumes are pure, distilled lies (marketing being their dirtiest ingredient), but this one seems to check out: Diptyque claims that its creative director, Desmond Knox-Leet, was transfixed by the smell of a Damascus spice market, which he had his perfumer Serge Kalouguine recreate. The result is one of the world's most literal-minded perfumes. L'Autre is piles of spices simmering in the hot African sun. It is desert dust, the dirt on the street and a hint of body odor from the salesman's robes. If the spice is somewhat obvious, it is a picture worth 10,000 words. To wear it or not might require a considered decision, but there is a reason you see it as dirty; perfumers know well that one of the molecules in cumin is also found in sweat.</p>
        <p>Few people anymore use the term ''whore's bath'' (a brief splash of basin water under the arms), in part because the P.C. version (''sex worker's bath'') sounds moronic, in part because one doesn't get the chance: soap in every form is now so ubiquitous that most men have forgotten what a good hit of armpit from a hot young woman can do for a guy. One brilliant perfume will remind you. For Le Labo, the Nolita scent emporium belonging to Eddie Roschi and Fabrice Penot, the perfumer Daphné Bugey has injected rose with Cetalox Laevo, a synthetic ambergris, like an animal's breath, and the result is a completely contemporary perfume: elegant and yet something you smell between the sheets. A whiff of Rose 31 and you're not sure if you should offer its wearer a seat or watch your wallet.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
