<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>You Call That Seltzer? It's in a Plastic Bottle!</title>
    <meta content="15wecolWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/15wecol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Westchester"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seltzer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delivery Services</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berger, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Cott, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0D7123FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>You Call That Seltzer? It's in a Plastic Bottle!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">You Call That Seltzer? It’s in a Plastic Bottle!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH BERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berger, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph Berger column on Tom Van Cott, 62, one of only half-dozen seltzer men left in New York area, who delivers seltzer in thick glass siphon bottles; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU can call seltzer that comes in a home-delivered siphon bottle a refreshing beverage, but that's like calling Proust's madeleine a puffy pastry.</p>
        <p>People drink seltzer from a high-pressure bottle as much for the memories as for the bubbles. It reminds them of their childhood, when a visit from the seltzer man, hoisting a 60-pound crate of bottles on his shoulder and dangling another from his brawny arm, was an occasion for awe and wonder. At dinner, the thick bottle, its origins etched with acid into the sometimes-tinted glass, was as much a part of the table setting as a knife and fork. Pressing the trigger for a shpritz was a treacherous ritual eyed with trepidation. How many times did a beloved uncle splash seltzer over the tablecloth to the giggles of the children?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seltzer delivered to the door in glass siphon bottles allows nostalgic customers to relive their childhoods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU can call seltzer that comes in a home-delivered siphon bottle a refreshing beverage, but that's like calling Proust's madeleine a puffy pastry.</p>
        <p>People drink seltzer from a high-pressure bottle as much for the memories as for the bubbles. It reminds them of their childhood, when a visit from the seltzer man, hoisting a 60-pound crate of bottles on his shoulder and dangling another from his brawny arm, was an occasion for awe and wonder. At dinner, the thick bottle, its origins etched with acid into the sometimes-tinted glass, was as much a part of the table setting as a knife and fork. Pressing the trigger for a shpritz was a treacherous ritual eyed with trepidation. How many times did a beloved uncle splash seltzer over the tablecloth to the giggles of the children?</p>
        <p>Those children and grandchildren of the Bronx and Brooklyn walk-ups now own gracious homes in these parts and pine for a taste of grittier times. The siphon bottle that Norman D. Bloom, a 57-year-old cancer surgeon, keeps at the ready on a sideboard in his Mamaroneck stucco reminds him of the days when his immigrant grandparents lived below his family in the East Flatbush section of Brooklyn and survived on this European thirst-quenching elixir. Steven M. Cohen, a 57-year-old investor in Bedford Hills, remembers the cracked wooden crates that his grandparents, immigrants from Ukraine, stored on the fire escape of their Ocean Parkway apartment building until the seltzer man replaced the empties.</p>
        <p>''It was very kind of Old World,'' he said. ''Nowadays, everything is disposable.''</p>
        <p>The conjurer who delivers old-time flavor to these Westchesterites is Tom Van Cott, one of only a half-dozen seltzer men left in the New York area. So dispersed are his customers that Mr. Van Cott's route extends from northern Rockland as far south as Freehold, N.J. In the old days, a route was often a single city block.</p>
        <p>Mr. Van Cott's 200 or so customers are old enough to have grown up before the 1960s, when supermarkets began carrying seltzer in far cheaper plastic throwaways and working mothers could no longer take deliveries. They are persuaded that the supermarket stuff cannot match the zing in the throat from siphon seltzer, but such convictions are dwindling.</p>
        <p>''The only time I lose a customer is when they pass away,'' Mr. Van Cott said, concisely summing up both his customers' loyalty and their antiquity.</p>
        <p>There is so little work that Mr. Van Cott, a bearish six-footer of 62 with thinning brown hair, operates his business, Joy Beverages, out of his one-car garage across the Tappan Zee in Nanuet and delivers only three days a week, driving a maroon Ford van, not the amply racked beverage truck of yesteryear. His full-time job is as a security guard at New York Medical College in Valhalla on the 4-to-12 shift. Unlike lugging seltzer, it pays benefits.</p>
        <p>Like cleaning ladies who don't do windows, Mr. Van Cott no longer does walk-ups, a decision made ironclad by a hip replacement two years ago. (The surgeon was recommended by a seltzer customer, a gynecologist.)</p>
        <p>''I only deliver if there's an elevator,'' he said. ''A case of seltzer full weighs 60 pounds. In the old days, they were carrying 120 pounds. It was a brutal business.''</p>
        <p>It is no longer even much of a people business. With so many working couples, Mr. Van Cott picks up the empties and a check without the few minutes of schmooze that was once a highlight of the seltzer man's day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Van Cott refills his stash of 800 bottles with carbonated water under 60 pounds of pressure at Gomberg Seltzer Works in Canarsie, where Kenny Gomberg, a third-generation seltzer man, says his only refilling rival is a plant in Long Island. Mr. Van Cott charges $2 a bottle -- several times the cost of a liter of supermarket seltzer. But he points out that when you open a plastic bottle of seltzer, it starts to go flat. Siphon seltzer is sealed and controlled by an ingenious valve. That's why the surge of cold bubbles always leaves a more intense feeling in a parched throat.</p>
        <p>''Good seltzer,'' he said, ''has to hurt when you drink it.''</p>
        <p>Sales plummeted not just because of plastic bottles. Siphon seltzer is the ultimate recycling business, and quarter-inch-thick bottles that contain high pressure aren't made anymore. Almost all those remaining were manufactured decades ago in Czechoslovakia, and when they break, a small part of the business dies. The crates are even older -- most have two-letter telephone exchanges not seen since the 1950s. Luckily, the old metal heads can be replaced by plastic heads from Argentina.</p>
        <p>One flicker of hope comes from next-generation aficionados like Mr. Bloom's son Zach, 20. But nobody is eager to break into the seltzer trade. Mr. Van Cott, a grandfather of four, worries that when he retires, ''it's going to be hard to sell the business.''</p>
        <p>''Nobody wants to lug a case of seltzer anymore,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Westchester E-mail: joeberg@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: joeberg@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
