<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain Lags in Income But Excels In Spending, Report Shows</title>
    <meta content="15donate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/us/politics/15donate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirkpatrick, David D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pilhofer, Aron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D9103FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain Lags in Income But Excels In Spending, Report Shows</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">McCain Lags in Income, but Excels in Spending</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK and ARON PILHOFER ; John M. Broder contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D; Pilhofer, Aron</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican presidential candidate John McCain spent more than two-thirds of $12.5 million he raised in first quarter, ending up with about $5.2 million in cash and $1.8 million in debt; his rivals Mitt Romney and Rudolph W Giuliani raised about $21 million and about $14 million, respectively, and each ended with more than $10 million (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John McCain, long considered the presumptive front-runner in the Republican presidential primary, has raised less money and also burned through it faster than his two leading rivals, leaving him with about half as much cash as each of the others at the end of the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain spent more than two-thirds of the roughly $12.5 million he raised in the quarter, ending up with about $5.2 million in cash as well as $1.8 million in debt, according to a report filed Saturday with the Federal Election Commission. His rivals -- Mitt Romney, who raised about $21 million, and Rudolph W. Giuliani, who raised about $14 million -- each ended March with more than $10 million. The McCain campaign payroll was about 25 percent higher than the others, and it spent more on fund-raising to bring in less money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John McCain not only raised less money but also burned through it faster than his two leading rivals in the first quarter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator John McCain, long considered the presumptive front-runner in the Republican presidential primary, has raised less money and also burned through it faster than his two leading rivals, leaving him with about half as much cash as each of the others at the end of the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain spent more than two-thirds of the roughly $12.5 million he raised in the quarter, ending up with about $5.2 million in cash as well as $1.8 million in debt, according to a report filed Saturday with the Federal Election Commission. His rivals -- Mitt Romney, who raised about $21 million, and Rudolph W. Giuliani, who raised about $14 million -- each ended March with more than $10 million. The McCain campaign payroll was about 25 percent higher than the others, and it spent more on fund-raising to bring in less money.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain may also be struggling to keep up in the race to build a network of so-called bundlers, who can collect donations from wealthy friends and business associates. A preliminary analysis of the donors to the top three Republicans indicated that, so far, Mr. McCain has collected checks from roughly the same number of major fund-raisers for President Bush -- about 60 -- as Mr. Romney, a one-term governor of Massachusetts, who is far less well-known across the country. (Several gave to more than one candidate, and at least two -- the financiers Bradford Freeman and Elliot B. Broidy -- gave to all three.)</p>
        <p>Campaign finance laws cap individual contributions at $2,300 for the primary and another $2,300 for the general election, so campaigns depend on pyramids of bundlers to collect checks -- networks that are more important than ever in this race. All the leading candidates are planning to turn down public financing for both phases of the race because they can raise more from such private donations.</p>
        <p>The two major party nominees are each expected to raise and spend more than $500 million by Election Day.</p>
        <p>Acknowledging its problems at the close of the quarter, the McCain campaign shook up its fund-raising organization to catch up, adopting a system for recognizing big bundlers that is similar to the designation of ''pioneers'' and ''rangers'' that President Bush employed in his campaigns. Matt David, a spokesman for the campaign, said the new structure would ''provide more accountability and metrics to ensure success.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain spent about $8.4 million during the quarter, not including his $1.8 million in debts. Including the debts, his campaign spent almost as much as Mr. Romney and far more than Mr. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>The campaign spent about $1.6 million on its staff payroll, compared with about $1.1 million for Mr. Romney and about $900,000 for Mr. Giuliani, according to their first-quarter filings. And it spent about 14 percent of its expenses, or $1.2 million, including $644,574 on financial consultants, $306,891 on fund-raising phone calls, $146,562 to rent mailing lists and $104,359 on list management services. For the same items, Mr. Romney spent $860,000 and Mr. Giuliani about $458,000.</p>
        <p>McCain campaign officials said they thought slow fund-raising, not exorbitant spending, was their biggest problem.</p>
        <p>The campaign reported about 50,000 individual contributors who gave an average of about $250. Mr. Romney received contributions from about 32,000 people and Mr. Giuliani from about 28,000, although in each case their average donor gave more than twice as much as Mr. McCain's.</p>
        <p>The campaign filed its report late Saturday afternoon. All the presidential candidates are required to file their first quarter financial reports by midnight Sunday. Mr. Giuliani and Mr. Romney filed Friday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
