<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children's Books</title>
    <meta content="Shulman.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/books/review/Shulman.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Keturah and Lord Death (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2D8163FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children's Books</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Children’s Books</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By POLLY SHULMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shulman, Polly</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Keturah and Lord Death</p>
        <p>By Martine Leavitt.</p>
        <p>216 pp. Front Street/Boyds Mills Press. $16.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 12 and up)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Keturah and Lord Death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Keturah and Lord Death</p>
        <p>By Martine Leavitt.</p>
        <p>216 pp. Front Street/Boyds Mills Press. $16.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>The hardest part of writing fantasy may be getting the ending right. Often writers spin an intriguing premise into a whirling world of mystery, suspense and atmospheric adventure, only to let the whole thing collapse into a heap of disappointing nonsense. Not so Martine Leavitt in ''Keturah and Lord Death,'' which was a finalist last fall for a National Book Award. The conclusion is the best part of this novel-length fairy tale: at once unexpected and inevitable, sad and triumphant, satisfying yet abidingly mysterious.</p>
        <p>The story begins with the narrative equivalent of Once Upon a Time, as Keturah, the 16-year-old heroine, follows a great hart into the forest. Keturah is an orphan with humble ambitions: ''to have my own little cottage to clean, my own wee baby to hold and most of all, one true love to be my husband.'' She's also, as we learn right away in the prologue, a spinner of tales. So when she loses her way in the woods and Death comes for her, she makes like Scheherazade. She starts to tell him a story about a girl who finds her one true love, then stops in the middle and refuses to finish until the next day.</p>
        <p>''You think too highly of love,'' Death says. ''Love is no more than a story spun out of dust and dreams, having no substance.'' Still, he wants to hear the end of the story, so he agrees to give her another day. And if she finds her own true love in that day, he promises, he'll let her live.</p>
        <p>The agreement sets the scene for a who-will-marry-whom story, which unfolds with the expected symmetries. Possible candidates for Keturah's hand include the town choirmaster, the tailor and a wealthy farmer. But Keturah's two best friends have their eyes on Choirmaster and Tailor, and Ben the farmer really needs to marry a good cook. Then there's the son of the Lord of the Manor, John. He's warm, brave, handsome. But isn't he too highborn for Keturah?</p>
        <p>Readers who think they know exactly where the story is headed will find themselves pleasantly surprised. Not that Leavitt frustrates all expectations -- much of what clearly has to happen does happen. But she takes what looks on the surface like a rather shallow story and plunges it, from time to time, into the depths that come only with pain.</p>
        <p>The best scenes, and by far the most romantic ones, are those that include Death. ''We all know Lord Death,'' the town wise woman tells Keturah. ''It is closeness to him that imbues my stuffs with power. What is a love potion without the breath of him upon it? How can I make a healing draught without sensing from which direction he comes? One day you will understand, Keturah, that he infuses the very air we breathe with magic.''</p>
        <p>Death is ''tall and fine and strong,'' ''royal and commanding,'' ''a goodly man, severe but beautiful, not old but in the time of his greatest powers.'' He's not without compassion for those he takes, but he's as overpowering as any Gothic hero: ''In the light of day he seemed appalling. How dare he ride in the sunlight without apology, without shame?'' No wonder Keturah keeps spinning out her time with him, to the very end.</p>
        <p>Compared with the richness of the ending, though, the way there sometimes feels dusty and flat. There's a tradition of fleshing out bare-bones fairy tales into novels, spinning schematic Snow Whites and Cinderellas into living girls with freckles and foibles. ''Keturah and Lord Death'' evokes that tradition, but it might have been better shorter -- fairy tale length, rather than novel length. At least in this book, Leavitt's mythmaking is more gripping than the specifics of her story. None of her other characters come alive half as well as Death.</p>
        <p>Polly Shulman is the author of ''Enthusiasm,'' a young adult novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Polly Shulman is the author of ''Enthusiasm,'' a young adult novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
