<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Wagon, Now in Half Pints</title>
    <meta content="15BLOCK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/15/automobiles/autoreviews/15BLOCK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1840449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AROUND THE BLOCK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Suzuki Motor Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5DD133FF936A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Wagon, Now in Half Pints</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">High Wagon, Now in Half Pints</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK KURCZEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kurczewski, Nick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TESTED: 2007 Suzuki SX4.</p>
        <p>WHAT IS IT? Small crossover-style wagon.</p>
        <p>HOW MUCH? $15,624 base; $16,724 as tested with automatic transmission.</p>
        <p>WHAT DRIVES IT? A 2-liter in-line 4; four-speed automatic; all-wheel drive.</p>
        <p>IS IT SAFE? All SX4's have six air bags, including head-protection curtains. Antilock brakes and a tire pressure monitor are standard. Traction control and electronic stability control are available only on the SX4 Sport. The government has not crash-tested the SX4.</p>
        <p>HOW THIRSTY? With the automatic gearbox, the E.P.A. rating is 24 miles a gallon in town, 30 on the highway.</p>
        <p>ALTERNATIVES: Honda Fit $14,650; Nissan Versa SL $15,550; Chrysler PT Cruiser $17,620. (All similarly equipped.)</p>
        <p>AS the new wave of economical hatchbacks ripples through the American auto market, the era of lumbering sport utility vehicles already seems as kitschy as towering tailfins or butterfly-collar disco shirts. The Suzuki SX4 wagon is taking advantage of this shift by straddling a razor-thin line between the baby sport utility and the all-wheel-drive economy car.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Suzuki SX4 wagon straddles a razor-thin line between the baby sport utility and the all-wheel-drive economy car.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TESTED: 2007 Suzuki SX4.</p>
        <p>WHAT IS IT? Small crossover-style wagon.</p>
        <p>HOW MUCH? $15,624 base; $16,724 as tested with automatic transmission.</p>
        <p>WHAT DRIVES IT? A 2-liter in-line 4; four-speed automatic; all-wheel drive.</p>
        <p>IS IT SAFE? All SX4's have six air bags, including head-protection curtains. Antilock brakes and a tire pressure monitor are standard. Traction control and electronic stability control are available only on the SX4 Sport. The government has not crash-tested the SX4.</p>
        <p>HOW THIRSTY? With the automatic gearbox, the E.P.A. rating is 24 miles a gallon in town, 30 on the highway.</p>
        <p>ALTERNATIVES: Honda Fit $14,650; Nissan Versa SL $15,550; Chrysler PT Cruiser $17,620. (All similarly equipped.)</p>
        <p>AS the new wave of economical hatchbacks ripples through the American auto market, the era of lumbering sport utility vehicles already seems as kitschy as towering tailfins or butterfly-collar disco shirts. The Suzuki SX4 wagon is taking advantage of this shift by straddling a razor-thin line between the baby sport utility and the all-wheel-drive economy car.</p>
        <p>The SX4 is only 162.8 inches long, half a foot shorter than the four-door Versa and only about five inches longer than the Fit. From the outside, the SX4's squat dimensions, tall windows and large side mirrors, which bear some resemblance to Mickey Mouse's ears, deliver a welcome dose of cuteness, a trait not usually found in the macho realm of S.U.V.'s.</p>
        <p>But the SX4's best party trick is its standard all-wheel-drive system. A switch on the center console has three settings: front drive, four-wheel drive (which transfers power between the front and rear axles), or a four-wheel mode that locks the center differential for very slippery situations.</p>
        <p>So has Suzuki managed to obtain the station wagon equivalent of geek-chic?</p>
        <p>When you step inside, you realize that the huggable exterior is somewhat muted by a sober cabin. Expanses of gray plastic are brightened (but only a bit) by slivers of metallic-looking plastic on the center console and gearshift knob. The dashboard layout is clear, with easy-to-read gauges and large rotary knobs for the air-conditioner. The base four-speaker AM/FM/CD/MP3 and XM-ready stereo is a cinch to master, if a little tinny-sounding when the volume is cranked up. A nine-speaker stereo, with subwoofer and six-disc, in-dash CD player, is standard on the SX4 Sport.</p>
        <p>My basic test vehicle came with a four-speed automatic in lieu of the five-speed manual, but it lacked the $300 convenience package that includes cruise control and a leather-wrapped steering wheel with integrated audio controls. (I was stuck with a thin, slippery steering wheel instead.) On a more positive note, the smooth-shifting automatic did a fine job in mixed city and highway driving.</p>
        <p>The SX4's steering is solid and agile. But with a curb weight of nearly 3,000 pounds, acceleration is merely adequate with the 143-horsepower 4-cylinder engine.</p>
        <p>Fuel economy is also just on the right side of O.K., and an 11-gallon tank limits the range to as little as 260 miles between fill-ups. Oddly, the SX4 carries a higher mileage rating with the automatic than with the manual.</p>
        <p>A ride through Manhattan, Brooklyn and Long Island proved the comfort of the suspension and cloth seats. With the 60/40 split-folding rear seat lowered, there is a useful 54.3 cubic feet for cargo. The cabin is roomy enough for four average-size adults.</p>
        <p>Air-conditioning, power windows and power locks are standard, and the six air bags include side curtains. It is too bad, though, that traction and stability controls are available only on the pricier SX4 Sport.</p>
        <p>The SX4 wagon will be joined this fall by a sedan version, introduced recently at the New York auto show.</p>
        <p>The SX4 lacks the lofty mileage figures and nimble demeanor of some competitors. Yet as a pint-size wagon with standard all-wheel drive, a roomy interior and a price around $15,000, it has little direct competition at all.</p>
        <p>NICK KURCZEWSKI</p>
        <p>AROUND THE BLOCK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
