<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.J. Transit Approves Fare Increases For Its Riders</title>
    <meta content="19transit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/nyregion/19transit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Transit</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0D91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.J. Transit Approves Fare Increases For Its Riders</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">N.J. Transit Approves Fare Increases for Its Riders</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN BELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belson, Ken</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey Transit approved a 9.6 percent average fare increase on its buses, trains and light rail yesterday to help close a $60 million budget gap for next fiscal year.</p>
        <p>The increase, which will take effect on June 1, is the third since 2002 and brings rates on New Jersey Transit trains closer to the higher fares charged by Metro-North and the Long Island Rail Road on a per mile basis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 9.6-percent average fare increase is intended to help close a $60 million budget gap for the next fiscal year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Jersey Transit approved a 9.6 percent average fare increase on its buses, trains and light rail yesterday to help close a $60 million budget gap for next fiscal year.</p>
        <p>The increase, which will take effect on June 1, is the third since 2002 and brings rates on New Jersey Transit trains closer to the higher fares charged by Metro-North and the Long Island Rail Road on a per mile basis.</p>
        <p>Train and interstate bus ticket prices will increase by 9.9 percent, while the price of tickets for a single one-zone bus and for the more local light-rail service will rise by 8 percent, to $1.35 from $1.25.</p>
        <p>New Jersey Transit contends that it needs the additional revenue to help keep up with its rising operational costs, and to expand service and build and refurbish rail stations at Mount Arlington, Trenton and Broad Street in Newark. New Jersey Transit will also add about 100 new multilevel train cars on some of its busiest lines.</p>
        <p>In January, New Jersey Transit made its first proposal to increase fares. Officials held 13 public hearings and accepted comments on the Internet and by mail. Riders and other citizens submitted more than 2,000 statements about the need for affordable and more frequent service. While New Jersey Transit did not change its overall fare increase proposals, it decided to begin charging peak rates for train tickets at 7 a.m. instead of 6:30 a.m., which could save riders several dollars per round trip.</p>
        <p>This change will affect the price of off-peak round-trip tickets on 16 morning trains. Riders who buy monthly passes will not be affected by this change. Three of the 16 trains are on the Northeast Corridor line.</p>
        <p>About 5,000 riders a day take the 16 affected trains. In a worst-case situation for New Jersey Transit, it might lose $300,000 in revenue if many riders switch to earlier trains.</p>
        <p>New Jersey Transit also said that it would appoint a customer advocate to better address rider concerns. The agency is also working with the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey and the city of Newark to consider how to improve service to and from Newark Liberty International Airport, as well as pricing to the airport from New York City.</p>
        <p>''We do everything we can to avoid a fare increase; it's our last resort,'' said Richard R. Sarles, the executive director of New Jersey Transit who this month succeeded George D. Warrington, who retired.</p>
        <p>''But in terms of dealing with specific suggestions from customers,'' Mr. Sarles added, ''these were the ones we could do immediately.''</p>
        <p>New Jersey Transit expects to receive about $300 million in state aid the coming fiscal year, which Mr. Sarles said he appreciated given New Jersey's budget woes. The money, however, goes only part of the way toward paying for the record number of riders on New Jersey Transit, he said.</p>
        <p>Each weekday, New Jersey Transit currently handles 857,000 riders, its most ever, on its buses, trains and light-rail lines. Total ridership in the second quarter of this fiscal year, October-December 2006, jumped by 5.9 percent compared with the same quarter a year earlier. Ridership in the 2005 and 2006 fiscal years also hit record highs.</p>
        <p>Still, rider advocates say that public transit commuters are being unfairly treated at the expense of drivers in the state. New Jersey Transit has raised fares five times since the state last raised the gas tax in 1988. They also question how seriously officials at New Jersey Transit considered suggestions from riders, given that the proposed fare increases were almost unchanged from the original proposal.</p>
        <p>''There is really nowhere else where senior management is as accessible as they are here,'' said David Peter Alan, chairman of the Lackawanna Coalition, a rider advocacy group. ''But when it comes down to it, we're irrelevant.''</p>
        <p>The fare increase, he said, ''was a done deal.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
