<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witness Says Tip He Gave Went Unused In Skakel Trial</title>
    <meta content="19skakel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/nyregion/19skakel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Skakel, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Moxley, Martha</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2D91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witness Says Tip He Gave Went Unused In Skakel Trial</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Witness Says Tip He Gave Went Unused in Skakel Trial</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON LEIGH COWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowan, Alison Leigh</byline>
      <dateline>STAMFORD, Conn., April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Crawford Mills, a former classmate of Michael C. Skakel's, testified on Wednesday that he tried to give lawyers information he thinks might have prevented Mr. Skakel's 2002 conviction for the 1975 murder of Martha Moxley in Greenwich.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mills was appearing in the second day of a civil proceeding in State Superior Court, initiated by Mr. Skakel's appellate lawyers, who are seeking a new trial for Mr. Skakel based on newly discovered evidence. To grant a new trial, the court would need to agree that any new information was not available at the time of the 2002 trial and that it had the potential to sway the verdict.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>STAMFORD, Conn., April 18  Crawford Mills, a former classmate of Michael C. Skakel’s, testified on Wednesday that he tried to give lawyers information he thinks might have prevented Mr. Skakel’s 2002 conviction for the 1975 murder of Martha Moxley in Greenwich.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Crawford Mills, a former classmate of Michael C. Skakel's, testified on Wednesday that he tried to give lawyers information he thinks might have prevented Mr. Skakel's 2002 conviction for the 1975 murder of Martha Moxley in Greenwich.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mills was appearing in the second day of a civil proceeding in State Superior Court, initiated by Mr. Skakel's appellate lawyers, who are seeking a new trial for Mr. Skakel based on newly discovered evidence. To grant a new trial, the court would need to agree that any new information was not available at the time of the 2002 trial and that it had the potential to sway the verdict.</p>
        <p>Appearing as a witness for Mr. Skakel, Mr. Mills, often known as Tres, may also be called to testify for the other side, the prosecutors who tried the case.</p>
        <p>He said he had always been fascinated by the notorious case and had even written a screenplay about it, called ''Little Martha,'' but had never sold it.</p>
        <p>He testified that between Christmas 2001 and New Year's 2002, another former classmate, Gitano Bryant, told him that he and two friends from New York went to Greenwich on the night of the 1975 killing and that Mr. Bryant thought they might have killed Miss Moxley.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Mills, Mr. Bryant told him that the friends had fantasized aloud about getting a girl ''caveman-style'' and later gloated that they had done so.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Skakel was awaiting trial in 2002, Mr. Mills said, he had the impression that Mr. Bryant, known as Tony, would not mind if he gave his information to the authorities and to others, but that Mr. Bryant wanted to remain anonymous.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mills said he remembered calling Mr. Skakel's trial lawyer, Mickey Sherman, as well as the prosecutor's office, and told them ''everything Tony told me, except Tony's name.''</p>
        <p>Later, after the June 2002 guilty verdict, Mr. Mills said, he implored Mr. Bryant to come forward to make it easier for others to investigate his claims, but Mr. Bryant resisted. At that point, Mr. Mills said, he again contacted prosecutors and possibly Mr. Sherman and for the first time named Mr. Bryant as his source.</p>
        <p>He said he also gave Mr. Bryant's name to Robert F. Kennedy Jr., Mr. Skakel's cousin, who later tracked Mr. Bryant down and eventually helped Mr. Skakel's appellate lawyers obtain audio and videotaped recordings of his statements.</p>
        <p>In an interview on Wednesday, Mr. Sherman declined to disclose what he is expected to say in testifying on Thursday, though he did say: ''I have no misgivings about any aspect of my conduct in this case. All I regret is losing. We should have won.''</p>
        <p>During prehearing depositions, Mr. Bryant has refused to testify, invoking his Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination, as have his two friends, Adolph Hausbrouck and Burton Tinsley.</p>
        <p>In challenging the claim for a new trial, the trial prosecutors suggested in cross-examination of Mr. Mills that the alternative explanation of the homicide lacks credibility because few people recall seeing Mr. Bryant and his friends in Greenwich that night or heard the boasts that Mr. Bryant recounted.</p>
        <p>Leaving the courtroom for a midafternoon break, Ms. Moxley's mother, Dorthy, said she found the proceedings interesting.</p>
        <p>''It's just strange,'' she said. ''We hadn't heard of any of these people before. They're all new.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
