<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. Searches Home Of California Lawmaker</title>
    <meta content="19lobby" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/us/19lobby.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070421T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Doolittle, John T</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Abramoff, Jack</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1D81E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. Searches Home Of California Lawmaker</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">F.B.I. Searches Home of California Lawmaker</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS and DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D; Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>F.B.I. agents last week searched the suburban Washington home of Representative John T. Doolittle, Republican of California, and his wife whose activities are being investigated in connection with her ties to the convicted lobbyist Jack Abramoff, Mr. Doolittle's lawyer acknowledged Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The lawyer, David G. Barger, said the warrant for the search of the home in Oakton, Va., was directed at the activities of Sierra Dominion Financial Solutions Inc., a fund-raising company run by Mr. Doolittle's wife, Julie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The wife of Representative John T. Doolittle is being investigated in connection with her ties to the convicted lobbyist Jack Abramoff, her lawyer said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>F.B.I. agents last week searched the suburban Washington home of Representative John T. Doolittle, Republican of California, and his wife whose activities are being investigated in connection with her ties to the convicted lobbyist Jack Abramoff, Mr. Doolittle's lawyer acknowledged Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The lawyer, David G. Barger, said the warrant for the search of the home in Oakton, Va., was directed at the activities of Sierra Dominion Financial Solutions Inc., a fund-raising company run by Mr. Doolittle's wife, Julie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doolittle was elected to a ninth term last fall in a race that was unusually close for a heavily Republican district, largely because of questions over an unusual business arrangement with his wife's company as well as his ties to Mr. Abramoff.</p>
        <p>Under the arrangement, Mrs. Doolittle, through her company, served as her husband's chief fund-raising consultant and took a 15 percent commission on most of his donations. An October 2006 fund-raiser for Mr. Doolittle that featured President Bush's visit to the district netted about $90,000 for Mrs. Doolittle. Mr. Doolittle has defended his wife, saying her commission is in line with what other consultants charge.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Doolittle was subpoenaed in the Abramoff investigation in June 2004 when federal investigators sought information about her marketing and events-planning work for Mr. Abramoff's lobbying firm and for his Washington restaurant, Signatures, which he later sold. Her lawyer, William L. Stauffer, said Mrs. Doolittle was contacted the following year by the Justice Department and asked for additional records.</p>
        <p>In a statement released by his office in California, Mr. Doolittle said, ''My wife has been cooperating with the F.B.I. and the Justice Department for almost three years, and that cooperation is going to continue in the future. I support my wife 100 percent and fully expect that the truth will prevail.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Doolittle has links to Mr. Abramoff aside from his wife's work. He received about $14,000 in campaign donations from him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doolittle's name has also surfaced in investigations involving former Representative Randy Cunningham, a fellow California Republican, and Brent Wilkes, a San Diego military contractor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cunningham is in prison after pleading guilty to accepting bribes from Mr. Wilkes in exchange for directing military contracts to his companies. Mr. Wilkes was recently indicted for bribery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doolittle, a member of the House Appropriations Committee, directed about $37 million in federal spending to Mr. Wilkes's companies in 2004 and 2005 in the form of earmarks, the financing of special projects that individual lawmakers insert into spending bills.</p>
        <p>Over the same period, Mr. Doolittle's campaigns and political action committee received tens of thousands of dollars from Mr. Wilkes and his associates. The timing of many of the contributions coincided with the progress of the spending legislation including the earmarks as it passed from committee to the floor to the president's signature, said Keith Ashdown, a researcher at Taxpayers for Common Sense, which tracks earmarks.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 21, 2007, Saturday  A picture of Representative John T. Doolittle on Thursday with an article about a search of his home by the F.B.I. carried an erroneous credit. The photographer was Pablo Martinez Monsivais/Associated Press, not Max Whittaker for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 21, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A picture of Representative John T. Doolittle on Thursday with an article about a search of his home by the F.B.I. carried an erroneous credit. The photographer was Pablo Martinez Monsivais/Associated Press, not Max Whittaker for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
