<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Latin-African Textures, And Ballet Dismantled</title>
    <meta content="19ball" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/arts/dance/19ball.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Joyce Theater</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Grupo Corpo</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1DA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Latin-African Textures, And Ballet Dismantled</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Latin-African Textures, and Ballet Dismantled</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSLYN SULCAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sulcas, Roslyn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Les Ballets Jazz de Montréal was founded in 1972, modern dance didn't have much of a presence in Canada, but jazz dance, with its showy fusion of Broadway, modern and ballet, was all the rage. Times are different now, and the company, directed by Louis Robitaille, has a broader dance aesthetic and bills itself as [bjm--danse]. It's uncontestably more modern, if not particularly comprehensible.</p>
        <p>Its mission, however, still seems to be to entertain and charm, and on its first visit to New York since 2003 it seems set to do just that. Tuesday night's program at the Joyce Theater opened with Rodrigo Pederneiras's ''Mapa,'' a pleasant if slightly monotonous dance that makes a more muted use of African and Brazilian dance forms than is customary for Mr. Pederneiras, the resident choreographer of the Brazilian Grupo Corpo since 1978. The work has a '70s feel, with an Op Art backdrop (by Fernando Velloso), a woodwind-and-drums percussive score by Marco Antonio Pena Araújo (whose initials make up the title) and the kind of flared jazz pants costumes (by Anne-Marie Veevaete) that were the height of dance chic during that era.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On its first visit to New York since 2003, the company seemed set to entertain and charm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Les Ballets Jazz de Montréal was founded in 1972, modern dance didn't have much of a presence in Canada, but jazz dance, with its showy fusion of Broadway, modern and ballet, was all the rage. Times are different now, and the company, directed by Louis Robitaille, has a broader dance aesthetic and bills itself as [bjm--danse]. It's uncontestably more modern, if not particularly comprehensible.</p>
        <p>Its mission, however, still seems to be to entertain and charm, and on its first visit to New York since 2003 it seems set to do just that. Tuesday night's program at the Joyce Theater opened with Rodrigo Pederneiras's ''Mapa,'' a pleasant if slightly monotonous dance that makes a more muted use of African and Brazilian dance forms than is customary for Mr. Pederneiras, the resident choreographer of the Brazilian Grupo Corpo since 1978. The work has a '70s feel, with an Op Art backdrop (by Fernando Velloso), a woodwind-and-drums percussive score by Marco Antonio Pena Araújo (whose initials make up the title) and the kind of flared jazz pants costumes (by Anne-Marie Veevaete) that were the height of dance chic during that era.</p>
        <p>The movement is smooth and sleek, with slinky hip rolls and low wheeling jumps and crouches, all punctuated by loose-legged little kicks and bouncy walks. The effect is clean and smart, and the 12 dancers perform with boundless enthusiasm. But it all begins to blur as the ever-rhythmic music continues and the dancers stream endlessly on and off the stage with little change in mood or affect.</p>
        <p>A trio stands out for its clever variations on a gymnastic motif as a woman ''dismounts'' from her two partners in a high, propelled arc. And the red-haired Tara Dyberg makes something striking of her solo, infusing its quick jumps and turns with sharp, clear accents and vivid personality.</p>
        <p>Aszure Barton's ''Chambres des Jacques'' is something else entirely: a rare instance of a dance that feels as if it were plucked straight from the choreographer's extremely specific imagination and set, full-grown, onstage. ''Les Chambres'' offers an entire world, full of surprise and humor, emotion and pain, expressed through a dance vocabulary that takes ballet technique and dismantles it to near-invisibility.</p>
        <p>The piece begins with a brilliant, rubber-limbed solo from a man (James Gregg) to a rambunctious Québecois folk song and goes on to another equally wonderful solo, long-limbed and thrashing, danced by Youri de Wilde to a gorgeous Vivaldi aria. That the work's musical mix (which also includes the Cracow Klezmer Band, Les Yeux Noirs and Roberto Iglesias) feels so seamless is testament to the unifying power of Ms. Barton's dance imagination. Through solos, duos, small groupings and an occasional assembling of all 13 dancers, she creates a buckling-bodied, flailing, loose-limbed language that has no finished edges but is as rigorous and precise as a ballet class.</p>
        <p>''Les Chambres des Jacques'' seems to be about sexual politics, and it evokes all the pathos, ineptitude, drama and humor of being in love or lust. The work's wonderful theatricality owes much to the sunlight-through-storm-clouds artistry of Daniel Ranger's lighting design, and to the fully committed performances by the dancers, who make us feel Ms. Barton's weird and wonderful world as their own.</p>
        <p>Performances continue through Sunday at the Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 242-0800 or www.joyce.org.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
