<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nothing to Cheer, Now Everything To Root For</title>
    <meta content="19anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6D61E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nothing to Cheer, Now Everything To Root For</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a decade, those April voices had lost their decibels. Wild roars for the Rangers from the slopes of Madison Square Garden simply didn't exist.</p>
        <p>In seven of those years, the Rangers, who preceded the Knicks as dollar for dollar the worst franchise in sports history, had not even qualified for the playoffs. Two years ago, because of the season-long lockout, there were no playoffs at all. When the Rangers finally squeezed into the playoffs a year ago, they were dispatched by the Devils in four straight games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a decade, those April voices had lost their decibels. Wild roars for the Rangers from the slopes of Madison Square Garden simply didn't exist.</p>
        <p>In seven of those years, the Rangers, who preceded the Knicks as dollar for dollar the worst franchise in sports history, had not even qualified for the playoffs. Two years ago, because of the season-long lockout, there were no playoffs at all. When the Rangers finally squeezed into the playoffs a year ago, they were dispatched by the Devils in four straight games.</p>
        <p>Ranger fans have endured a decade of nothing to cheer about since a five-game playoff loss to the Philadelphia Flyers in 1997, which followed a five-game elimination of the Devils. But now those April voices, with a hockey team finally worth cheering for, are as loud as ever, maybe even louder.</p>
        <p>And after the Rangers whirled onto the ice last night for Game 4 of their Eastern Conference quarterfinal series with the Atlanta Thrashers, all those April voices serenaded a 4-2 victory that lifted the Rangers into the conference semifinals with only their third 4-0 playoff sweep in the franchise's 81 years.</p>
        <p>In 1994, when Mark Messier finally hoisted the Cup after a 54-year drought, the Rangers swept the Islanders in the opening round before eliminating the Washington Capitals in five games. They then beat the Devils in seven in the conference finals and the Vancouver Canucks in seven in the Cup finals.</p>
        <p>In 1972, the Rangers swept the Chicago Blackhawks in the semifinals before losing in six games to Bobby Orr and the Boston Bruins in the Cup finals. That season, Vic Hadfield scored 50 goals, Jean Ratelle 46 (before he broke his ankle late in the season) and Rod Gilbert 43.</p>
        <p>But these are not the Rangers of the last decade or last season.</p>
        <p>They were trailing in the second period last night, 2-1, but their three players who had earned Cup titles provided the goals -- Brendan Shanahan (three with Detroit) for the 2-2 tie, Matt Cullen (last year's with Carolina) for the 3-2 lead and Jaromir Jagr (two with Pittsburgh) on the clinching empty-netter.</p>
        <p>''We felt going into the third period, we had to do two things: shortening our shift and rolling our three lines,'' Shanahan said. ''When we did, that got us back into the rhythm of our first three games. As for my goal, that's part of the reason I came here -- to play at tough moments and contribute clutch goals.''</p>
        <p>Cullen's go-ahead goal pinged off the crossbar and landed inches inside the goal line before the puck bounced out.</p>
        <p>''I didn't even think it was in; I thought I hit the crossbar,'' Cullen said. ''But when the replay took so long, I thought it was good.''</p>
        <p>Jagr, the weary 35-year-old captain and right wing, broke away to score his empty-net goal with 93 seconds remaining.</p>
        <p>''I was so tired, you wonder if you can go,'' Jagr said, ''but when you're on the ice, you just go. I'm just enjoying every moment I have a chance to play here.''</p>
        <p>''In Pittsburgh, Mario gave me the Cup,'' he added, referring to Mario Lemieux, ''and I've always wanted to help guys who never won the Cup.''</p>
        <p>The three guys who had won a Cup helped all the other Rangers who had not last night. But during the traditional handshake at center ice, the only name chanted was that of Sean Avery, who didn't play for the Red Wings in 2002 but was in uniform for their on-ice celebration.</p>
        <p>''A-very!'' the fans chanted. ''A-very!''</p>
        <p>In a recent Hockey News player poll, Avery was voted the league's most hated player, but Rangers fans cherish him. Avery, along with the prospect John Seymour, arrived Feb. 5 in a trade with the Los Angeles Kings for right wing Jason Ward and the unsigned forwards Marc-André Cliché and Jan Marek.</p>
        <p>In accumulating 58 penalty minutes (he had 261 to lead the league and 257 in his two full seasons with the Kings) while producing 8 goals and 12 assists in 29 games as a Ranger, he seemed to wake up his teammates and was quickly adopted as a Garden favorite.</p>
        <p>After a Feb. 24 loss, the Rangers didn't appear to be a playoff team. They were 12th in the conference, four spots out of the final playoff berth. That was not much different from the Rangers teams of those seven empty seasons without a playoff berth, teams with the N.H.L.'s highest payroll and worst work ethic.</p>
        <p>But of their last 20 games in the regular season, the Rangers won 13 -- 8 in the regulation 60 minutes, 4 in a shootout, 1 in overtime. Of their seven losses, three were in regulation, two in overtime, two in a shootout.</p>
        <p>''We've been playing good hockey for a long time; don't change anything,'' center Michael Nylander said Tuesday night after scoring three goals in a 7-0 rout of the Thrashers. ''We just have to continue working the way we have, the way we should. And whatever happens, happens.''</p>
        <p>Whatever happens, the Rangers have already allowed all those April voices to cheer again, and to dare to dream of the Stanley Cup.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
