<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Little Botox Shop Around the Corner</title>
    <meta content="19skin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/fashion/19skin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SKIN DEEP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Botox (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Botox (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Botox (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E3DA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Little Botox Shop Around the Corner</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Little Botox Shop Around the Corner</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATASHA SINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Singer, Natasha</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a busy section of East 59th Street in Manhattan, a half block from Bloomingdale's, two plastic surgeons are preparing to open a new kind of cosmetic medical entity: a Botox-only storefront office. No appointment necessary.</p>
        <p>Smoothmed, scheduled to open next month, will offer only one procedure: Botox injections to smooth wrinkles around the forehead, eyes, lips or neck. Its owners said the idea is convenience, competitive pricing and standardized care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A convenience center in a fashionable neighborhood offers storefront wrinkle removal (and it’s not a dry cleaner).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a busy section of East 59th Street in Manhattan, a half block from Bloomingdale's, two plastic surgeons are preparing to open a new kind of cosmetic medical entity: a Botox-only storefront office. No appointment necessary.</p>
        <p>Smoothmed, scheduled to open next month, will offer only one procedure: Botox injections to smooth wrinkles around the forehead, eyes, lips or neck. Its owners said the idea is convenience, competitive pricing and standardized care.</p>
        <p>''Botox-on-the-go is the way we like to think of it,'' said Dr. Andrew I. Elkwood, an owner of Smoothmed. He and his business partner, Dr. Michael I. Rose, are plastic and reconstructive surgeons who practice in Manhattan and in Shrewsbury, N.J.</p>
        <p>Botox Cosmetic, a diluted form of botulinum toxin, is used to temporarily paralyze the muscles underlying wrinkles. Dr. Rose said that making injections easily available would expand the market.</p>
        <p>''It will appeal to people who took a few hours to shop at Bloomingdale's, to secretaries on their lunch hours, to people who live and work in the neighborhood, and we will be getting visitors who think on a whim, 'I wouldn't normally do this at home, but we're in New York, so let's try it,' '' Dr. Rose said.</p>
        <p>A patient's first visit to Smoothmed should take about 30 minutes or less, and follow-up appointments will take 15 minutes or less, he said. ''People just need to be educated that it's fast, it's cheap and it's not intimidating.''</p>
        <p>In an age-conscious society that has already accustomed itself to Botox parties, Botox house calls, Botox in spas and Botox at malls, the idea of a Botox specialty retailer akin to Starbucks seems inevitable. With more than 4.5 million treatments performed in the United States last year, Botox is the most popular nonsurgical cosmetic medical procedure in the country, according to plastic surgery associations. But that number amounts only to about one million patients who regularly seek wrinkle injections.</p>
        <p>To expand the demographic, pharmaceutical companies like Allergan Inc., which makes Botox, are stepping up their marketing and advertising. And, independently, physicians are devising strategies for expanding their client bases. Dr. Rose predicted that the Smoothmed model would be successful because Botox lasts about four months, engendering repeat business.</p>
        <p>''Botox is the female yuppie heroin,'' Dr. Rose said. ''It's like electricity: If you want to keep it on, you have to keep paying.''</p>
        <p>But the idea of a drop-in injection center raises the question of whether, in the course of mainstreaming, Botox is destined to become the new manicure, an impulse purchase readily available at local storefronts.</p>
        <p>Some doctors who specialize in administering such injections contended that convenience and pricing are inappropriate criteria for choosing a cosmetic medical provider.</p>
        <p>''This may be trivializing the procedure the way the teeth-whitening center on the corner trivializes dentistry, taking it out of the context of overall teeth health and maintenance,'' said Dr. Fredric S. Brandt, a dermatologist who practices in Manhattan and Coral Gables, Fla.</p>
        <p>Dr. Elkwood disagreed, saying that medical care will not be compromised just because Smoothmed brands itself as a Botox convenience center.</p>
        <p>''We are approaching it as a serious medical procedure, but that doesn't mean we have to flaunt the serious nature of it,'' Dr. Elkwood said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Elkwood and Dr. Rose specialize in microsurgery, including the reattachment of limbs and breast reconstruction after cancer. Half their practice is devoted to cosmetic surgery, with Botox injections an adjunct treatment, Dr. Rose said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Elkwood said they wanted to create a new, simpler model of Botox delivery that would set itself apart from some ''medi spas,'' where nurses may administer injections. At Smoothmed, physicians who are general practitioners will give Botox.</p>
        <p>''Botox should not be done in a spa where you don't always know exactly who is injecting you and where it is presented in the same context as a hot stone massage or a facial scrub,'' Dr. Elkwood said. ''Nor should it be done in someone's house where the doctor can't control the cleanliness or the lighting.''</p>
        <p>Smoothmed is a 1,100-square-foot medical office with golden walls, large plate-glass windows and three treatment rooms. Dr. Elkwood said first-time patients will have a consultation with a doctor who takes their medical history, examines their faces and explains the benefits and risks of Botox. Patients will also have their faces photographed and, if appropriate, receive a pregnancy test, he said.</p>
        <p>Doctors will use a syringe gun to control the amount of each injection, Dr. Elkwood said. He added that he and Dr. Rose have developed their own computerized system; it will impose a grid over a patient's photograph and record the exact locations and amounts of the Botox injections so that it is easy for a doctor at Smoothmed to replicate the treatment on a patient's subsequent visits.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rose said Smoothmed plans to charge $12 to $13 per unit of Botox, which will add up to about $250 to $300 for the forehead or eye area and roughly $150 for the lip area. Nationally, patients pay an average of about $12 per unit of Botox treatment; the average price in New York is about $15. Typically, medical insurance does not cover cosmetic treatments.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mary A. Cigliano, a physician in family practice in New York, has been hired to be the full-time injector at Smoothmed. Dr. Cigliano said she studied how to inject Botox in 2004 by taking a certification course run by Allergan as well as an additional course in cosmetic injections run by Dr. Michael Kane, a plastic surgeon in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''Once you learn the facial anatomy, it is kind of like being an artist with the face,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Is a Botox convenience store an appropriate model for mainstreaming cosmetic injections? Some doctors interviewed for this article said that Botox should not be presented as an impulse buy that induces consumers with speed and pricing.</p>
        <p>''There are places where you can get your car painted for $29 and, if you want to take your BMW to the $29 place, you are welcome to do it,'' said Dr. Richard G. Glogau, a clinical professor of dermatology at the University of California, San Francisco. ''But, even in Brazil, which has the highest consumption of cosmetic services, the car-wash approach to cosmetic therapy has never really taken off.''</p>
        <p>Both Dr. Glogau and Dr. Brandt have been paid consultants and researchers for Allergan.</p>
        <p>Dr. Glogau said that patients would be better off going to dermatologists and surgeons who have extensive training in facial anatomy and aesthetics and long experience injecting Botox. To that end, the American Society for Aesthetic Plastic Surgery, the American Academy of Facial Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, and the American Society for Dermatologic Surgery will start a campaign Friday, called the Physicians Coalition for Injectable Safety, to promote the idea that only board certified surgeons and dermatologists can guarantee cosmetic expertise.</p>
        <p>''I consider myself an experienced injector, and even I have enough trouble getting Botox to work the way I want each time,'' Dr. Glogau said.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Rose disagreed, saying that general practitioners like Dr. Cigliano who have basic training and experience using Botox could be good injectors, especially using Smoothmed's method of standardizing treatments and making them reproducible.</p>
        <p>''Botox is not very user dependent,'' Dr. Rose said. ''As long as you inject it in roughly the right spot, it works. It's like a flu shot. You can have it in your deltoid or your buttocks and it spreads out. It doesn't have to be to the millimeter.''</p>
        <p>But that idea infuriated injectors like Dr. Glogau and Dr. Brandt, who eschew syringe guns and grid systems because they believe each treatment should be more individualized.</p>
        <p>''It's not just about eliminating lines and wrinkles,'' Dr. Brandt said. ''It's about reshaping the brow and the forehead, which requires you to understand not only which area you are immediately affecting, but also how that affects all the contours of the face.''</p>
        <p>He also questioned whether a Botox-only center could offer comprehensive cosmetic care.</p>
        <p>''If Botox is the only thing you are doing, are you going to use Botox on patients for whom Botox is not the ideal solution?'' Dr. Brandt asked.</p>
        <p>Dr. Elkwood, though, said that Smoothmed would set a standard for providing cosmetic medical care by qualified doctors in an era in which some physicians are handing off their cosmetic injections to nurses or are delegating treatments like laser hair removal to aestheticians.</p>
        <p>''There is a right way to do it, which is using physicians who are trained to make diagnoses and handle all kinds of adverse events and creating a system to provide the safest care and the most reproducible results,'' Dr. Elkwood said. If Smoothmed is successful, he said, the doctors plan to open similar locations.</p>
        <p>Deborah A. Sullivan, author of a critique of the augmentation industry called ''Cosmetic Surgery: The Cutting Edge of Commercial Medicine in America,'' said that locating an injection center near Bloomingdale's would capitalize on the insecurities of shoppers who come to terms with their appearances in department store dressing rooms.</p>
        <p>''You go in, you try something on, you think, 'Who is that old woman in the mirror?' You come out of the store rattled, and you walk by a Botox store,'' said Dr. Sullivan, a sociology professor at the School of Social and Family Dynamics at Arizona State University. ''What a clever idea! They will probably be very successful.''</p>
        <p>SKIN DEEP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
