<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Eastern Bloc of Outsourcing; Europe Finds Its Own Answer to Bangalore, And It's Growing Fast</title>
    <meta content="19prague" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/business/worldbusiness/19prague.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic/Prague</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Prague (Czech Republic)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Eastern Bloc of Outsourcing; Europe Finds Its Own Answer to Bangalore, And It's Growing Fast</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Eastern Europe Becomes a Center for Outsourcing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <dateline>PRAGUE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fillip Pejfar works in a sparkling new office tower here on the western edge of the Czech capital, using high-resolution scanners to enter accounting material into the computing systems of Accenture, the global business consulting group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pejfar's bookkeeping is not helping Czech clients. His expertise is meant for companies like the French chemical giant Rhodia and the big German software group SAP.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few urban areas of the former Communist bloc are transforming into outsourcing centers for corporations in the U.S. and Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fillip Pejfar works in a sparkling new office tower here on the western edge of the Czech capital, using high-resolution scanners to enter accounting material into the computing systems of Accenture, the global business consulting group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pejfar's bookkeeping is not helping Czech clients. His expertise is meant for companies like the French chemical giant Rhodia and the big German software group SAP.</p>
        <p>Prague is turning into a center for outsourcing white-collar jobs like bookkeeping, data crunching and even research and development. The Czech Republic and other Central European countries like Poland, Hungary and Slovakia are clamoring to serve the needs of multinational corporations -- and themselves.</p>
        <p>The United States may turn to India to fill many of its call-center jobs and the like. But Western Europe is turning more frequently these days to its own backyard, transforming a few urban centers of the former Communist bloc into the Bangalores of Europe.</p>
        <p>American companies are cashing in as well. In recent years, I.B.M., Dell and Morgan Stanley, among others, have outsourced services to Eastern Europe, or helped other American companies do so.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Eastern Europe, with an outsourcing business estimated at about $2 billion this year, represents just a fraction of the global outsourcing market, estimated this year at nearly $386 billion. But Robert H. Brown, an outsourcing analyst at Gartner Dataquest, expects growth in Eastern Europe to outstrip the rest of the market in the next four years, expanding close to 30 percent by 2010, compared with 25 percent for the global market.</p>
        <p>What is unusual about Eastern and Central Europe is that their most advanced cities offer a potent mix of attributes that even Bangalore cannot rival: a highly educated, multilingual pool of talent in an increasingly affluent consumer market -- all barely a stone's throw from its prime clients.</p>
        <p>Outsourcing is booming as this region moves more quickly to integrate itself economically with its more affluent neighbors to the west, reflecting progress that is reducing the high unemployment that plagued these countries for years after the fall of the Berlin Wall and the collapse of the Soviet empire.</p>
        <p>It is also feeding a real estate boom in high-rise office space. Despite high unemployment in much of Europe, Western European companies are pressed by labor shortages in several important occupations, encouraging them to turn to their eastern neighbors to ease the strain.</p>
        <p>''Yes, there is a trend, and it started a few years ago,'' said Miroslaw Proppé, the director for the Warsaw office of KPMG, the accounting firm. He added that it was ''not necessarily based on low labor costs, but on the potential of young Polish graduates.'' Commerzbank of Germany does its data processing in Prague, and Siemens, the electrical giant, does bookkeeping, research and development here. Philips, the Dutch electrical conglomerate, operates a shared services center outside Warsaw.</p>
        <p>Last summer, Morgan Stanley announced that it was opening a business services and technology center in Budapest that would supplement a mathematical research center the company established there in 2005.</p>
        <p>The company employs about 200 people there, said Hugh Fraser, a spokesman, and will employ about 450 when fully up and running. He said the choice of Budapest in both cases was made because of the ''availability of high-quality talent.''</p>
        <p>The reasons for Central Europe's new attractiveness for outsourcing are not limited to promising talent at cheap prices. Central and Eastern European countries also remain some of the world's great untapped markets for services and consumer goods.</p>
        <p>But there is no doubt that low wages in the region appeal to Western companies. Employees in Hungary and the Czech Republic earn a quarter of what employees in Western Europe make; Slovakia's pay runs only a fifth as much, the statistical agency Eurostat says.</p>
        <p>If that does not make the region attractive enough, governments also offer incentives like simplified tax structures and subsidies for office construction.</p>
        <p>Unlike other regions that compete for outsourcing work, like India or the Philippines, where English is the sole operating language, employees in Accenture's Central European business speak a variety of languages, giving clients access to people who speak English, French, German, Russian and local languages.</p>
        <p>''The key thing is language,'' said Andrew Grech, an Australian native who directs Accenture's operations here. ''The other factor is a stable political and economic environment. The Czechs are in the European Union and NATO.''</p>
        <p>The growth of these jobs is helping stanch a hemorrhaging of workers from Central and Eastern Europe to the West in search of jobs. And it is exerting some influence on decreasing the unemployment rate across Eastern Europe, Mr. Proppé said.</p>
        <p>In the Czech Republic, unemployment fell by the start of this year to 7.1 percent from 7.8 percent in 2002; in Poland, joblessness dropped to 13.4 percent from 20.2 percent five years ago; and in Slovakia, to 11.6 percent from 19.7 percent, according to Eurostat.</p>
        <p>In Hungary, however, the unemployment rate rose, despite an increase in outsourcing jobs, to 8.2 percent from 5.8 percent, mostly because of government austerity measures to cut jobs in the public sector.</p>
        <p>Growth has been strong. Accenture will not disclose its total employment in this country, but the Rhodia account alone employs more than 110 people, and the firm occupies 13 stories in an 18-story skyscraper, plus two stories in an adjacent building. A fourth building is scheduled to go up in the new corporate park, and Accenture plans to take some of that space, too.</p>
        <p>Since entering the Czech Republic in 2001, Accenture has expanded to the city of Brno, the Slovak capital of Bratislava and Budapest. Last year, it opened offices in Warsaw and Bucharest, the capital of Romania.</p>
        <p>''We're mostly serving Western European clients,'' Mr. Grech said. He said those clients were increasingly interested in expanding the types of service they received, including bookkeeping and accounting, and computer and personnel services. The growth has come so fast that shortages are arising for specialists in finance and computer services, giving rise to recruiting services in Prague and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, Ilona Jankovich started a recruiting firm in Budapest to find employees for Western companies moving services to Central Europe.</p>
        <p>''I had Hungarian roots,'' said Ms. Jankovich, a lawyer by training whose father fled Hungary for the Netherlands after the unsuccessful 1956 uprising. ''I wanted to come home, and I saw a need for professional recruitment services. Many new companies are coming in, and they all need people.''</p>
        <p>The firm, called ProfiPower, has 35 employees and continues to expand. Ms. Jankovich's brother, Bela Jankovich, 39, recently joined and is working to spread the business into Romania.</p>
        <p>As the reservoir of capable labor in Central Europe dries up, companies are looking as far east as Ukraine. ''We have a regional vision,'' Mr. Jankovich said. With many of the countries of Central Europe now in the European Union, barriers to migration have been reduced. But most Western European countries still maintain hurdles to migrants.</p>
        <p>So instead of the people moving to jobs in Western Europe, the jobs are moving here. In 2004, when SAP chose to move accounting and personnel services to Prague, the company could hire five employees for the price of one in Germany. By now, the difference is down to 3.5 to 1, but SAP is still expanding, expecting to increase its work force to 450 by the end of this year from about 350 now. The wave of outsourcing is raising sticky questions among Western European white-collar workers and their union representatives. In 2005, when Unilever announced that it was seeking to outsource its Western European accounting, personnel and computer activities to Eastern Europe, company employees responded to calls from German labor leaders for a one-day walkout, fearing that as many as 4,000 jobs would be lost.</p>
        <p>Last year, Unilever awarded lucrative contracts for the outsourcing to I.B.M. and Accenture, but assured the unions that jobs in the West would be eliminated only through attrition or voluntary job changes.</p>
        <p>Union leaders remain skeptical. ''Until now it has not been a major problem,'' said Jörg Reinbrecht, who is responsible for financial service employees at Verdi, a German union that represents many white-collar workers. ''But I think it will grow larger as Europewide banks and financial service companies form.''</p>
        <p>But for all the concerns of union leaders, business executives say that such outsourcing often offers benefits to both sides of the equation.</p>
        <p>''You cannot view it negatively,'' said Bernard Bauer, the director of the Czech-German Chamber of Commerce. ''It means a market for many companies -- after all, there are 12 million people in the Czech Republic alone.''</p>
        <p>The location here also serves Western companies as a springboard to markets further east, he said, pointing to more slowly developing Romania, with its 22 million people; Bulgaria, with a population of 7.5 million; and one day, perhaps, even Ukraine, with 47 million people.</p>
        <p>The movement, though, may be limited by the future availability of skilled workers in the countries that are now home to outsourcing.</p>
        <p>''We may face an enormous shortage of qualified personnel,'' Mr. Bauer said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
