<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Banker Says He'll Smooth His Style, but Waters Are Choppy</title>
    <meta content="19wolfowitz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/washington/19wolfowitz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841348"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Bank</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Riza, Shaha Ali</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4D91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Banker Says He'll Smooth His Style, but Waters Are Choppy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Banker Says He’ll Smooth His Style, but Waters Are Choppy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz sought Wednesday to quell discontent over his leadership of the World Bank by promising top aides that he would change his management style, but he suffered a blow when one of those aides urged him to resign, bank officials said.</p>
        <p>The officials said that at a meeting with about 30 vice presidents of the bank, Mr. Wolfowitz asked for suggestions on how he could restore faith in his management after a furor over charges of favoritism toward his companion in 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz’s efforts to quell discontent over his leadership suffered a blow when one of his aides urged him to resign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul D. Wolfowitz sought Wednesday to quell discontent over his leadership of the World Bank by promising top aides that he would change his management style, but he suffered a blow when one of those aides urged him to resign, bank officials said.</p>
        <p>The officials said that at a meeting with about 30 vice presidents of the bank, Mr. Wolfowitz asked for suggestions on how he could restore faith in his management after a furor over charges of favoritism toward his companion in 2005.</p>
        <p>He has also been criticized by bank employees for being insular and overly reliant on a handful of aides.</p>
        <p>According to several bank officials who talked to people who were at the meeting, one of Mr. Wolfowitz's two senior deputies in charge of running the bank, Graeme Wheeler, a former senior Finance Ministry official from New Zealand, said Mr. Wolfowitz needed to step down as president for the good of the bank.</p>
        <p>''The fact that Graeme would ask him to resign has been all over the bank today,'' one official said. ''He is an unassuming guy who is very well respected here.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wheeler, appointed managing director last year by Mr. Wolfowitz, did not return telephone calls or respond to an e-mail message seeking comment.</p>
        <p>The session with Mr. Wolfowitz and his vice presidents was the first such meeting since the world's finance ministers were in town last weekend. It was seen within the bank as reflecting his determination to remain in his job, as he vowed to do on Sunday, despite a rebuke from the bank's most powerful oversight committee, which issued a statement of ''great concern'' about his leadership.</p>
        <p>Bank officials said that while Mr. Wolfowitz was not specific about what the management changes would be, he did say that resigning would not be good for the bank. In the meeting with the vice presidents on Wednesday and in separate talks with groups of them on Tuesday, Mr. Wolfowitz solicited ideas on ''the way forward,'' they said.</p>
        <p>Officials said the vice presidents left the second meeting with a mandate to discuss Mr. Wolfowitz's appeal for suggestions and Mr. Wheeler's call for his resignation with their staffs.</p>
        <p>The bank's 24-member executive board also scheduled a meeting for Thursday to discuss the situation. Officials close to the board said they did not expect any specific actions to be taken.</p>
        <p>They said the board was still trying to decide whether to reprimand Mr. Wolfowitz or to make some other assessment of his role in the transfer and promotion of his companion, Shaha Ali Riza, in 2005, when he came to the bank, and the large raises she got.</p>
        <p>Bank officials said the board would also discuss disclosures about the conduct of Ms. Riza in taking a monthlong leave in 2003 to go to Iraq under the auspices of a private Defense Department contractor.</p>
        <p>Bank officials said Ms. Riza did not clear the trip with top bank officers, and some said it was contrary to bank regulations for her to travel to Iraq at a time when it was inappropriate for the bank to have dealings with the American-led military occupation.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, The New York Times reported that a private contractor, the Science Applications International Corporation, said it had been directed by the Defense Department to hire Ms. Riza as a consultant on governance issues in Iraq.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon has decided to look into details of the contract, The Associated Press reported Wednesday, quoting a spokesman there. Bank officials said that many at the bank thought it was inappropriate for her to travel to Iraq, and that this issue, although not directly connected to Mr. Wolfowitz's conduct, might be taken up by the board on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Reports of Mr. Wolfowitz's plans to change his management style did not appear to placate the staff association, which has called on him to resign.</p>
        <p>''The staff association has been raising these issues consistently since he came in,'' said Alison Cave, the association's chairwoman. ''He has never said how he's going to work with us. He has never said anything to the staff.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz got a vote of confidence from the White House on Wednesday, when a spokesman, Tony Fratto, said, ''We'd like to see him remain.'' Asked if the bank's reputation had been hurt by the controversy, Mr. Fratto said, ''It's not what we believe.''</p>
        <p>While generally praising Mr. Wolfowitz, the Treasury Department has said that it would not comment on an internal process by the bank's board.</p>
        <p>The United States has one representative on the board, Eli Whitney Debevoise II, a New York lawyer, but he took office less than two weeks ago. The United States representative has 16 percent of the votes on the board, but most actions are taken by consensus.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
