<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Remaking Home, One Stick of Furniture at a Time</title>
    <meta content="19martinez" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/garden/19martinez.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Easton (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martinez, Carl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Louie, Elaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1DA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Remaking Home, One Stick of Furniture at a Time</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Remaking Home, One Stick of Furniture at a Time</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE LOUIE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Louie, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>EASTON, Pa.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carl Martinez, designer of architectural hardware, invites his parents, both retired librarians, to share his 1890 Victorian weekend house in Easton, Pa; most of home conforms to his minimalist preferences, but parents have created warm, richly layered bedroom for themselves; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOT long after he bought and renovated an 1890 brick Victorian as a weekend house in Easton, Pa., Carl Martinez, then 41, did what many people his age would consider unthinkable: He invited his parents, Pat and Mehry Martinez, both retired librarians, to move in.</p>
        <p>''Every friend that I have was shocked,'' said Mr. Martinez, a designer of architectural hardware. ''Most people see their parents as thorns in their sides,'' he added. ''But I can't get enough of them.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a diverse family, a place to regroup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOT long after he bought and renovated an 1890 brick Victorian as a weekend house in Easton, Pa., Carl Martinez, then 41, did what many people his age would consider unthinkable: He invited his parents, Pat and Mehry Martinez, both retired librarians, to move in.</p>
        <p>''Every friend that I have was shocked,'' said Mr. Martinez, a designer of architectural hardware. ''Most people see their parents as thorns in their sides,'' he added. ''But I can't get enough of them.''</p>
        <p>The elder Martinezes sold their town house in Montgomery Village, Md., along with their two cars and most of their furniture three years ago and moved to the four-story house in Easton.</p>
        <p>Five days a week, Carl, now 45, lives in Manhattan, where he makes hardware for architects and designers like Tsao &amp; McKown, Pierce Allen and Robert Couturier. On Fridays, he rents a car and drives 65 miles west, arriving by dinnertime; his brother, Michael, a 47-year-old designer and draftsman of homes and restaurants at GKA Design Group in Long Island City, Queens, and who also lives in Manhattan, usually arrives around the same time, and the two men stay until Sunday.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to see Michael and Carl more than once every three months,'' said Mrs. Martinez, who is now, like her husband, 74. ''We wanted to see them every weekend -- and we're saving a lot of money by living together.''</p>
        <p>In Maryland, the couple had a mortgage, utility bills, auto insurance and other expenses; in Easton, they contribute $1,000 a month to the mortgage and Carl takes care of nearly everything else, bringing supplies like Chinese vegetables, wines and cheeses from New York and driving his parents around during the weekend. (On weekdays, they walk or take the local bus.)</p>
        <p>The money they save frees them to travel at will; they spend two to four months each year in Rome, where their daughter Lisa lives with her partner and infant son, and another month in Tucson with their younger daughter, Nina, her husband and their two children.</p>
        <p>''I don't know how I'd feel if Carl and Michael were living here full time,'' Mrs. Martinez said on a recent weekend at the house. ''But we all have our freedom for five days.'' The senior Mr. Martinez, who retired in 1992 as the librarian at the Export-Import Bank of the United States in Washington, visits the local library every day to read. Mrs. Martinez retired from her job as a library technician at the National Library of Medicine in Bethesda, Md., in 2000, and now spends her time knitting clothes for her grandchildren, reading and preparing Persian feasts for her sons' weekend visits.</p>
        <p>Carl and his brother and sisters, who read, write and speak Farsi, spent their childhood in Iran, where his mother grew up and his parents met. In 1958, his father was stationed in Tehran with the United States Air Force when he walked into the United States Information Service library there.</p>
        <p>''I went to the reference desk and asked for The New Yorker, and the clerk happened to be Mehry,'' he said. He asked her to lunch. She said no. He returned the next day, and the next, and by the third day, she relented.</p>
        <p>As much as the sons and their parents enjoy their independence, the family is clearly close-knit, in part because of its history. They lived in Iran from 1968 until the revolution in 1979, after which they lived a slightly nomadic life for many years, spending time in Albuquerque before settling in Maryland. ''We didn't leave Iran willingly,'' Carl said, ''and we all use the word displacement a lot. I think we just have that in us, the desire to reconnect.''</p>
        <p>Their only disagreements, it seems, are over décor. After renovating the house in 2003 and 2004 for about $150,000 (he bought it in 2003 for $102,000), Carl furnished it in a super-minimalist style that plays up its intricate wood floors, multiple original fireplaces and general airy feeling.</p>
        <p>The lone sofa is in the television room; the living room contains just a table and two rigid 19th-century iron chairs that are rarely used. The equally austere dining room has little more than a six-foot-high antique mirror topped with a swirl of metal garlands and vines, and a cherry-wood gateleg table with no chairs. (Just as no one sits in the living room, no one eats in the dining room; the family dines in an enclosed porch off the kitchen, facing the garden.)</p>
        <p>''I inherited my minimalism from my father,'' said Carl, adding that he likes lots of air, rather than objects, circulating around him. ''He doesn't mind there being one sofa in my house. But my mother wants more comfort.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Martinez said wistfully of her old house in Maryland, ''We had a regular stuffed sofa and comfortable chairs.'' Here, she said, ''Carl gave me the freedom of one room.''</p>
        <p>Actually, he gave his parents a whole floor to decorate as they like. Carl lives on the third floor, below the attic, and his parents are on the second floor, where they have furnished their bedroom in a warm, richly layered way. Family photographs are grouped on the dresser. Persian rugs cover a low bench. His father has a separate study nearby, the floor covered in another Persian carpet. ''We use rugs as tablecloths, on walls, on beds,'' said Mrs. Martinez, who draped more rugs in the guest room.</p>
        <p>Carl has placed natural objects, including pieces of slate, a hornet's nest and twisted pieces of driftwood, throughout the house, and enlivened the white paint scheme with bold shots of color: teal walls in a room off his third-floor studio, green-stained floors in two bathrooms.</p>
        <p>He declined his mother's Scandinavian dining set, however, because its reddish-orange color clashed with the stripped, pale wood floors. Instead, he installed his own dining table, a wooden one from the 1970s that he bought for $10 at an antiques market and painted white on top and slate gray on the legs and base.</p>
        <p>Carl is aware of his mother's yearning for more comfort, and is looking for an armoire to display her collection of antique and voluptuously shaped copper pots. He also plans to place a clean-lined sofa with deep cushions upholstered in velvet in the living room, near the fireplace. Opposite the sofa, he envisions two comfortable chairs. ''There is furniture,'' he said of the current décor, which he bought largely before his parents moved in. Still, he allowed, ''perhaps it's not the right furniture.''</p>
        <p>On a recent Sunday, as Ms. Martinez made chicken khoresh, a Persian stew, Carl reflected on the sense of permanence that the home in Easton, and his live-in houseguests, have created for him.</p>
        <p>''I think when you leave a country so suddenly, like we did during the revolution, there's something uprooted in your core,'' he said, ''and there's something that's restored, pre-revolution, when I get to Easton. That's the best part of having my parents here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
