<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Should Wolfowitz Stay, or Should He Go?</title>
    <meta content="l19wolfowitz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0D81E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="390" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Should Wolfowitz Stay, or Should He Go?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Public Rebuke for Wolfowitz, but He Digs In'' (front page, April 16):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Public Rebuke for Wolfowitz, but He Digs In'' (front page, April 16):</p>
        <p>For someone who prides himself on holding nations accountable on ethical standards, Paul D. Wolfowitz, the president of the World Bank, has shown that he is not above the corruption he supposedly decries.</p>
        <p>His appointment to the World Bank was already clouded with cries of cronyism from the beginning, and Mr. Wolfowitz has only reinforced the belief that Bush administration officials -- both former and current -- do not respect the bounds of decency.</p>
        <p>Although his resignation is appropriate, it would do nothing to repair the damage already inflicted on America's world image.</p>
        <p>Kevin Yeh  Ithaca, N.Y., April 16, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Time for Mr. Wolfowitz to Go'' (editorial, April 16):</p>
        <p>I do not agree that Paul D. Wolfowitz should resign as president of the World Bank. Although your ostensible reasons for his doing so have nothing to do with Iraq, or his last job in Donald H. Rumsfeld's Pentagon, I would be willing to bet that the calls for his staying put or resigning coincide very neatly between those who supported the Iraq war (and the Bush administration) and those who did not.</p>
        <p>From all that I have read, it appears that Mr. Wolfowitz was above board about his relationship with his companion, and his attempts to recuse himself from decisions about her placement were rebuffed.</p>
        <p>Because of the Bush administration's incompetence in Iraq, the president and those associated with him are weakened. The knives are out, and a Wolfowitz resignation will be a victory for those at the World Bank (and elsewhere) who resented his appointment from Day 1.</p>
        <p>Alexander Goldstein  Brooklyn, April 16, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Over the last 30 years, Paul D. Wolfowitz has been accused of, among other things, being an apologist for dictators, developing and carrying out the strategies for the illegal invasion of Iraq, and most recently, his uncompromising and damaging executive stint at the World Bank.</p>
        <p>And after all of this, we are just now publicly scrutinizing Mr. Wolfowitz's character because he is accused of using influence to get his girlfriend a job and a pay raise. Thank heaven for the indiscretions of the heart. They may just save the world.</p>
        <p>Jim Hill  Patchogue, N.Y., April 16, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
