<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Portrait of a Gunman, and of a Society</title>
    <meta content="l19virginia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E0D81E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Portrait of a Gunman, and of a Society</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''In Words and Silence, Hints of Anger and Isolation'' (front page, April 18):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''In Words and Silence, Hints of Anger and Isolation'' (front page, April 18):</p>
        <p>The tragedy at Virginia Tech and discussions of Cho Seung-Hui's behavior as a student make it clear that, as a society, we cannot accurately identify and predict who will commit murder, nor are we able to effectively intervene in advance.</p>
        <p>The obvious solution is strict controls on handguns so that individuals do not have the means to commit such atrocities.</p>
        <p>This requires legislators to have the courage to stand up to the powerful pro-gun organizations, which -- through a combination of propaganda, financial and political influence -- made it possible for a man to simply walk into a gun store and buy a 9-millimeter handgun on the spot.</p>
        <p>Wendy M. Geringer  Croton-on-Hudson, N.Y.  April 18, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Cho Seung-Hui did not emerge in our world full grown with guns blazing. He has been with us a long time. He was a child in our school systems. He was a person in our community, in our mental health system. He was part of a family.</p>
        <p>Instead of rushing to fight a gun lobby that will not move one inch, what about finding ways to help the young, desperate, angry, isolated and miserable among us?</p>
        <p>That means money for early childhood education, parent education, mental health and school counselors. Ways that we can intervene in the lives of the disassociated young before it is so tragically too late.</p>
        <p>Susan K. Finkel  Seattle, April 18, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Once again, a mentally disturbed individual has wreaked havoc on a community, and we are left wondering how we might reduce the chances of this sort of tragedy occurring again.</p>
        <p>A psychologist friend of mine made what I think is the most creative and also the most practical suggestion I have yet heard. Why not require yearly mental health checkups of all students in high school and college? By making them routine, we would remove any stigma.</p>
        <p>Those identified with problems could be scheduled for more frequent checkups. And the practice would encourage a sensible long-term habit.</p>
        <p>Preventive mental health care makes as much sense as any other kind of preventive medicine. Millions go to the dentist for regular checkups. But which is more important: our state of mind or the state of our teeth?</p>
        <p>Emrys Westacott  Alfred, N.Y., April 18, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In light of the tragic events at Virginia Tech, and in the spirit of legal clarity, perhaps we should change the language of the Second Amendment to what it has effectively become.</p>
        <p>The amendment currently states, ''A well regulated militia, being necessary to the security of a free state, the right of the people to keep and bear arms shall not be infringed.''</p>
        <p>To align with what the National Rifle Association and its political handmaidens assert, let's change it to: ''As a protected part of American culture, the right of psychopaths, criminals and violent family members to keep and bear arms shall not be infringed.''</p>
        <p>At least that would be more honest.</p>
        <p>Tim Zagat  New York, April 18, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Horror at Virginia Tech, Then the Hard Questions'' (letters, April 18):</p>
        <p>Are there really people who believe that if there were more guns on campuses there would be fewer shootings and less violence? The logic is so perverted that if it were not so tragic it would be funny.</p>
        <p>I wonder how many students at Virginia Tech today would like the campus rules relaxed so that more students could carry a weapon? I am guessing that the vast majority would prefer the rules to be better enforced so that no one can enter a campus building with any kind of weapon.</p>
        <p>Alison Nicholls  Port Chester, N.Y., April 18, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>My sincere condolences go to the families who are in deep mourning over losing their loved ones.</p>
        <p>When the news broke that the gunman was a 23-year-old Korean immigrant, I was in total shock. As a Korean-American, I never thought or imagined that this type of crime could be done by a Korean.</p>
        <p>My heart is trembling with grief, and my head is still filled with pictures of devastation. I just want to reach out to the mourning families and tell them how sorry I am and that I am grieving, too.</p>
        <p>Christine Lee  Northvale, N.J., April 18, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>We now know who was responsible for the mass shootings at Virginia Tech and are relieved that he was not a terrorist. But suppose it had been a terrorist attack?</p>
        <p>This incident has no obvious homeland security dimensions: homeland security measures did not fail because they did not apply.</p>
        <p>But the homeland security implications of the attack should be troubling to those who protect us from terrorists because it isn't obvious why those who do wish our destruction have not attacked us in the manner of the Virginia Tech massacre.</p>
        <p>The disturbingly simple method of the devastating Virginia Tech attack makes it a national security matter. How else can the easily replicated, methodical killing of 32 innocents be thought of as anything else?</p>
        <p>John C. Abell  Reston, Va., April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Black Day in the Blue Ridge,'' by Lucinda Roy (Op-Ed, April 17):</p>
        <p>Struck by unimaginable grief, an otherwise unsentimental man says, ''We'll need to act like a family.'' Too bad no one thought of that before.</p>
        <p>Cho Seung-Hui was the invisible student. It was clear that he was deeply troubled. But instead of reaching out, those closest to him labeled him strange. Instead of intervening, they dismissed and ignored him.</p>
        <p>The shooting spree may have been unthinkable, but the suicide was foreseeable. If it had been solitary and silent, would anyone have cared, or even noticed?</p>
        <p>To prevent future massacres, we don't need metal detectors, armed guards or reflexive campus lockdowns. We need more compassion and more humanity. We need to act more like a family.</p>
        <p>Jeff Hersh  Austin, Tex., April 17, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Thank you to Lucinda Roy for finding the words to describe Blacksburg, Va., which many of us simply could not articulate during this time of shock and sorrow.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, three childhood friends were introduced at a wedding as ''the Blacksburg girls''; my husband and I are the epitome of a ''Blacksburg couple,'' having met there in the first grade. Those terms will never mean the same thing again.</p>
        <p>Sadly, we cannot continue to say of our hometown, ''You've never heard of it unless you follow college football.'' Blacksburg is a beautiful place filled with beautiful people. Someday, it will return to being ''boring,'' but it will always be our ''home in southwest Virginia.''</p>
        <p>Colleen Shea-Brown  New York, April 17, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
