<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Butkus Seeks Control of Linebacker Award</title>
    <meta content="19butkus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/sports/football/19butkus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Chicago Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bears</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Butkus, Dick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="530" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Butkus Seeks Control of Linebacker Award</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Butkus Seeks Control of Linebacker Award</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Butkus, a member of the College and Pro Football Halls of Fame, is suing the Downtown Athletic Club of Orlando to gain control of an award given in his name to a college football linebacker.</p>
        <p>Since 1985, the Butkus Award has been presented to college football's top linebacker by the athletic club in Orlando, Fla., after a vote by a panel of journalists. Patrick Willis of the University of Mississippi was the 2006 winner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Chicago Bears legend Dick Butkus is suing the Downtown Athletic Club of Orlando to gain control of an award given in his name to college football’s top linebacker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Butkus, a member of the College and Pro Football Halls of Fame, is suing the Downtown Athletic Club of Orlando to gain control of an award given in his name to a college football linebacker.</p>
        <p>Since 1985, the Butkus Award has been presented to college football's top linebacker by the athletic club in Orlando, Fla., after a vote by a panel of journalists. Patrick Willis of the University of Mississippi was the 2006 winner.</p>
        <p>Butkus and athletic club officials disagree about which charitable organizations should benefit most from Butkus's association with the award, according to his lawyer, Robert Helfing. By taking control, he said, Butkus hopes to raise more money for charities with which he is affiliated.</p>
        <p>''The Downtown Athletic Club of Orlando has been using Dick's name for the award and supporting their causes, with permission that was granted some time ago, but that permission has been terminated,'' Helfing said in a telephone interview yesterday. ''It was very a much a handshake agreement between Dick and the club. There was no timetable ever established as to how long their association would continue.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''They have not been paying Dick. Dick is not in any financial straits, and he is not doing this for mercenary purposes.''</p>
        <p>The lawsuit was filed Monday in Federal District Court in Los Angeles. Helfing said a letter about the action was sent yesterday to the Downtown Athletic Club of Orlando.</p>
        <p>Shelley Ferguson, the club's executive director, said she had not heard about the lawsuit. ''Until we know more,'' she said by telephone yesterday, ''we will not be commenting.''</p>
        <p>Butkus, 64, played in the N.F.L. for nine seasons, from 1965 through 1973, with the Chicago Bears. He was known as a ferocious hitter who was dominant at middle linebacker. Since retiring as a player, he has been an actor, an announcer and a celebrity pitchman.</p>
        <p>He also started an educational campaign, called Lean Mean and Clean, to eradicate steroids among high school athletes. Butkus works closely with the Taylor Hooton Foundation, named after a former high school baseball pitcher from Plano, Tex., and a cousin of the former major league pitcher Burt Hooton. Taylor Hooton committed suicide in 2003 at age 17, before his senior year. The family started the foundation because they say his use of anabolic steroids played a significant role in causing severe depression, leading to his suicide.</p>
        <p>In seeking licensing control of his name for an award to a college linebacker, Butkus contends, he would be able to use his status to bring more attention and money to organizations, like the Taylor Hooton Foundation. Helfing said Butkus had discussed his concerns with the athletic club, but that the sides had been unable to reach an agreement.</p>
        <p>''It's possible that we could still work this out and that Dick could reach an new agreement with the club,'' Helfing said. ''If not, maybe we'll present it in Chicago, or somewhere where Dick has closer ties. But we just wanted to confirm with the court that Dick has the right to use his name with a college football award and that Dick was terminating his licensing agreement with the club.''</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
