<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Strong Finish, the Nets Secure the Sixth Seed</title>
    <meta content="19nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFD71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Strong Finish, the Nets Secure the Sixth Seed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets' chance to make amends for a disappointing regular season will begin in earnest this weekend, but they got an early start on their postseason push Wednesday night against the Chicago Bulls.</p>
        <p>With the playoff stakes high for both teams, the Nets came away with a 106-97 victory to vault into the sixth seed in the Eastern Conference and a first-round matchup against the Toronto Raptors. The victory allowed the Nets (41-41) to avoid a losing record and capped a late-season push.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nets' chance to make amends for a disappointing regular season will begin in earnest this weekend, but they got an early start on their postseason push Wednesday night against the Chicago Bulls.</p>
        <p>With the playoff stakes high for both teams, the Nets came away with a 106-97 victory to vault into the sixth seed in the Eastern Conference and a first-round matchup against the Toronto Raptors. The victory allowed the Nets (41-41) to avoid a losing record and capped a late-season push.</p>
        <p>The Bulls (49-33) tumbled from the second seed all the way to fifth and will play the defending N.B.A. champions, the Miami Heat, in the first round. If the Bulls survive the Heat, the most devastating part of slipping so far would be that they would probably play the Detroit Pistons, the No. 1 team in the East, in the second round.</p>
        <p>''We have an opportunity to put ourselves in a good position,'' Bulls guard Ben Gordon said before the game. ''It's very important. This is a playoff game for us.''</p>
        <p>But the Bulls lost, and because the Cavaliers defeated the Milwaukee Bucks on Wednesday night, they took over the No. 2 seed and will face the seventh-seeded Washington Wizards in the first round.</p>
        <p>Before this season, the three division winners were awarded the top three playoff seeds in each conference, regardless of final records. That led to unfair matchups in the first and second rounds, and it also made it tempting for some teams to try for a lower seed in order to face a team with a worse record.</p>
        <p>To avoid those situations, the N.B.A. changed the seeding system this season. The three division winners are each guaranteed one of the top four seeds. So if there were two good teams in a single division, the second-place team would have an opportunity to have one of the top seeds.</p>
        <p>The Central Division, however, has the three teams with the best records in the East -- the Pistons, the Bulls and the Cavaliers. For the Bulls, that meant that losing one game equated to a three-seed drop.</p>
        <p>Bulls Coach Scott Skiles said that he thought the N.B.A. did the best it could to make the seeding system fair and that he could envision a day when the league would seed teams by record alone, and perhaps make division records the first tie breaker.</p>
        <p>''I'm fairly certain it is a work in progress,'' Skiles said before Wednesday's game. ''You can't possibly dream up every scenario before you set down the rules. Whatever the league does, I'm sure they're open about it.''</p>
        <p>On March 23, the Nets were seven games behind the Wizards and the sixth seed appeared to be an unrealistic goal. But the Wizards lost their two All-Stars, Gilbert Arenas and Caron Butler, and started to tumble. They entered Wednesday night having lost 8 of their previous 10 games, while the Nets had won 7 of 10.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday night, the Wizards faced the prospect of falling from the sixth seed to the eighth seed in a matter of two days. But they defeated the Indiana Pacers, 98-95, to maintain the No. 7 position. The Orlando Magic stayed at No. 8 and will face the Pistons in the first round.</p>
        <p>The Nets have set up a juicy first-round matchup against Vince Carter's former team, the Raptors. His time in Toronto ended on bad terms and he is certain to face a lot of heckling. But that was not on his mind after Wednesday night's game. He was clearly in a good mood, slapping the walls and taking off his jersey as he skipped toward the locker room.</p>
        <p>''I was excited about the turnaround that we've made, how hard this team has worked,'' he said. ''I don't care if we lose, it's just the effort and the way we played in the last month. It's just been exciting.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
