<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Red Cross, A New Head Is Appointed From I.R.S.</title>
    <meta content="19cross" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/us/19cross.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Red Cross</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Internal Revenue Service</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6D81E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Red Cross, A New Head Is Appointed From I.R.S.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Red Cross, a New Head Is Appointed From I.R.S.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM; David Cay Johnston contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American Red Cross yesterday named Mark W. Everson, the commissioner of the Internal Revenue Service, as its president and chief executive.</p>
        <p>When he takes over in May, Mr. Everson will join an organization hit by criticism of its response to Hurricane Katrina and other disasters. An I.R.S. spokesman said Mr. Everson was not available for comment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark W. Everson will join an organization hit by criticism of its response to Hurricane Katrina and other disasters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American Red Cross yesterday named Mark W. Everson, the commissioner of the Internal Revenue Service, as its president and chief executive.</p>
        <p>When he takes over in May, Mr. Everson will join an organization hit by criticism of its response to Hurricane Katrina and other disasters. An I.R.S. spokesman said Mr. Everson was not available for comment.</p>
        <p>The Red Cross spent more than a year courting candidates but had difficulty securing a commitment until Congress, which oversees it under a federal charter, passed legislation mandating an overhaul of its board and the appointment of an ombudsman to report to Congress.</p>
        <p>That legislation will pare the board from 50 members to no more than 20 by 2012 and change the way they are nominated to increase their independence and curb the influence of local Red Cross chapters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Everson thus may have a different relationship with the board than his predecessors had. But he will still have to grapple with a deeply entrenched culture that embraces change reluctantly, experts said -- though he has dealt with a somewhat similar culture at the I.R.S.</p>
        <p>''Governance is a red herring,'' said Peter Dobkin Hall, an expert on nonprofit organizations and public policy at Harvard University. ''Its real problems have to do with an inwardly turned organization that has not aligned its architecture and processes to address its purpose as it and the world have evolved.''</p>
        <p>For instance, victims of Hurricane Katrina had to fill out forms in triplicate to receive Red Cross services when other organizations and federal agencies used computers to process requests. The Red Cross says its slow adoption of technology is a reflection of its reliance on volunteers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Everson will inherit problems that have afflicted the Red Cross's blood distribution business, which in September was fined $4.2 million for failing to comply with Food and Drug Administration regulations.</p>
        <p>Sean O'Keefe, the chancellor of Louisiana State University, knew Mr. Everson when they worked at the Office of Management and Budget in the first two years of President Bush's administration. Mr. O'Keefe said Mr. Everson had experience in dealing with bureaucracies and weathering criticism that would serve him well at the Red Cross.</p>
        <p>''I told him when he went to the I.R.S., boy, you really know how to put yourself right in the middle of the Cuisinart, don't you,'' he said. ''On your best day, people will ignore you; on your worst day, they'll be coming after you with ice picks. I don't think the Red Cross will be that different.''</p>
        <p>The new job will quite likely mean a raise. At the I.R.S., Mr. Everson is paid $154,600 a year. In the fiscal year that ended June 30, 2005, the last president of the Red Cross, Marsha J. Evans, was paid $505,795 in salary and to cover expenses. Ms. Evans resigned in December.</p>
        <p>Mr. Everson, who has led the I.R.S. since 2003, will succeed Jack McGuire, the Red Cross's interim president and chief executive, who will continue as executive vice president for the blood services operations.</p>
        <p>As commissioner, Mr. Everson doubled the number of I.R.S. audits. But some complained that the pressure to complete audits quickly, particularly those of large corporations, meant that the agency did not collect all the money it could have.</p>
        <p>He improved I.R.S. oversight of nonprofits, increasing audits, overhauling the nonprofit credit counseling business, fighting the use of charities as tax shelters and taking on issues like excessive compensation.</p>
        <p>''His sense of accountability, his energy and his respect for institutions while being reform-minded are all attributes the Red Cross needs,'' Senator Charles E. Grassley, an Iowa Republican who has long pressed for Red Cross reform.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dobkin Hall said, however, that he did not expect major changes at the Red Cross unless donors were to begin withholding contributions.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't the whining of journalists and professors that made the United Way change,'' he said, referring to an overhaul at another nonprofit. ''It was the fact that it started losing donors.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
