<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Man With the Most Caps, Somehow Seeing All the Cards</title>
    <meta content="19card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/crosswords/bridge/19card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0DA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Man With the Most Caps, Somehow Seeing All the Cards</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Man With the Most Caps, Somehow Seeing All the Cards</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alder, Phillip</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The diagramed deal, which was originally reported in The Guardian, the British newspaper, arose during the Camrose match between England and the Republic of Ireland in January. The Camrose is contested annually by England, Northern Ireland, the Republic of Ireland, Scotland and Wales.</p>
        <p>At the other table Michael O'Briain for the Republic (South) opened one diamond. Justin Hackett (West) doubled, and Padraig O'Briain (North) redoubled to show 10-plus points. Jason Hackett (East), Justin's twin brother, jumped to two spades, which was pre-emptive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The diagramed deal, which was originally reported in The Guardian, the British newspaper, arose during the Camrose match between England and the Republic of Ireland in January.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The diagramed deal, which was originally reported in The Guardian, the British newspaper, arose during the Camrose match between England and the Republic of Ireland in January. The Camrose is contested annually by England, Northern Ireland, the Republic of Ireland, Scotland and Wales.</p>
        <p>At the other table Michael O'Briain for the Republic (South) opened one diamond. Justin Hackett (West) doubled, and Padraig O'Briain (North) redoubled to show 10-plus points. Jason Hackett (East), Justin's twin brother, jumped to two spades, which was pre-emptive.</p>
        <p>After an opening bid a takeout double and a value-showing redouble, fourth hand is known to be weak. But if he has a definite preference between the three unbid suits, he expresses it, even with zero high-card points. And if he has extra length in one of these suits, he may jump, as happened here.</p>
        <p>South rebid three diamonds to say that he had a long suit. North converted to three no-trump, a contract that would have hinged on the diamond guess after the defense began with three rounds of spades. And South retreated to five diamonds.</p>
        <p>After this was passed out, West led his spade king.</p>
        <p>Most tournament players lead the ace from an ace-king holding, but when the contract is five clubs or higher, it is a good idea to start with the king, asking partner to give count. (An ace lead requests an attitude -- encouraging or discouraging -- signal.) So East played his spade eight to show an even number of cards in the suit, which had to be six given his two-spade bid.</p>
        <p>West, knowing that South's spade jack was a singleton, shifted to a low heart. Declarer took East's jack with his ace and led his club. West did not rise with his ace, so the trick was won with the king on the board. South, after ruffing a spade in his hand, played a diamond to dummy's ten, losing to East's singleton king. East returned a club, which declarer ruffed. South led a diamond to dummy's ace and played a heart to his ten, but West produced the queen for down one.</p>
        <p>In the other room South was John Armstrong, who recently became England's most ''capped'' Camrose player. You receive a cap every time you represent your country internationally. I believe the expression comes from cricket, a sport that is intelligible to residents of Commonwealth countries but mystifying to the rest of the world.</p>
        <p>Armstrong, who has always been an aggressive bidder, decided to make life as tough as possible for his opponents by opening five diamonds.</p>
        <p>This was passed out, and the play began as at the other table. West led the spade king and shifted to a heart, South taking East's jack with his ace and playing his club. Here, though, West went in with his ace. Now you might expect West to try to cash the spade ace, but he strangely continued with a second heart. West should have known from East's heart jack at Trick 2 that South had started with the ace-king-ten. If East had held the heart ten or king, he would have played that card, not the jack.</p>
        <p>After Armstrong won with his heart ten, the spectators assumed he would play a diamond to dummy's ten, losing to East's singleton king and going down one. But declarer, capping a fine performance, surprised the kibitzers, leading a diamond to dummy's ace and making his contract.</p>
        <p>Why did Armstrong do that? West was known to have started with the spade ace-king, club ace and heart queen -- 13 high-card points. Armstrong felt that if West also had the diamond king, he would not have passed over five diamonds.</p>
        <p>When a bridge expert is ''in the zone,'' he sees the hidden: he correctly visualizes in his mind's eye where the important missing honor cards are. There is something very satisfying in playing as if the opponents' cards are made of glass.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
