<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Biggest Sell Is the Audition</title>
    <meta content="19hosts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/fashion/19hosts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">QVC Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E3DA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Biggest Sell Is the Audition</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Biggest Sell Is the Audition</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN SALKIN; Shivani Vora contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salkin, Allen</byline>
      <dateline>WEST CHESTER, PA.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT took most of her life for Roma Seegers to arrive at this moment. Clutching a wreath of pastel-color eggs as she entered a long hallway that is hallowed space to her, Ms. Seegers, a 26-year-old sales specialist at a bank outside Pittsburgh, thought back to when she was a little girl, playing with her friend Sarah in her bedroom.</p>
        <p>At an age when some girls played house and others pretended to be movie stars, little Roma held a ring her mother had bought from a home-shopping network and, facing an imaginary camera, extolled its shininess, versatility and extremely fair price.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At QVC, 392 hopefuls gather in West Chester, Pa., to vie for the role of shopper’s friend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT took most of her life for Roma Seegers to arrive at this moment. Clutching a wreath of pastel-color eggs as she entered a long hallway that is hallowed space to her, Ms. Seegers, a 26-year-old sales specialist at a bank outside Pittsburgh, thought back to when she was a little girl, playing with her friend Sarah in her bedroom.</p>
        <p>At an age when some girls played house and others pretended to be movie stars, little Roma held a ring her mother had bought from a home-shopping network and, facing an imaginary camera, extolled its shininess, versatility and extremely fair price.</p>
        <p>''We pretended to be QVC hosts,'' Ms. Seegers said last week, a few minutes before she entered a tiny room off the hallway at QVC headquarters here, to audition in front of a real camera. ''I would say the price, the item number and the specifics of the product: a blue-topaz, 14-karat-gold marquise-shaped ring.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Seegers was one of 392 aspiring program hosts who showed up at a once-a-year open audition at QVC, the largest home shopping network.</p>
        <p>What the 392 were competing for was a career soaked in fame of a strange kind. If any one of them eventually manages to land a job, he, or more likely she, will appear before millions of viewers not because she can croon a spine-tingling ''Mandy,'' dance up a storm with Jerry Rice or out-congenial Miss Mississippi, but because she can effuse extemporaneously to a camera about everything from zinnia-petal earrings to ''country style'' crab cakes.</p>
        <p>''Most people show up thinking it's easy,'' said Jack Comstock, the vice president for television sales at QVC. In his 14 years at the network, he has hired 18 of its 23 hosts. ''But it's difficult to find someone that can really talk to the camera as if it was their friend.''</p>
        <p>Rare is the Hollywood movie, network television program or Broadway show that casts its stars from an open call. But QVC, a $7 billion annual business, where hosts can have television careers that span decades, does. The nominal stars of QVC are the budget clothing and jewelry designers who offer their creations, inventors touting new housewares and faded celebrities with exercise programs. But on a network that can move tens of thousands of dollars of merchandise a minute, the host plays a crucial role: part cheerleader for a celebrity guest, part M.C. executing the orders of producers to end a slow-selling item's airtime gracefully, part fantasy friend to viewers, coaxing them to call.</p>
        <p>It's a rare skill set, and industry sources say the network is willing to compensate hosts for it extremely well, up to $500,000 a year.</p>
        <p>Among the hopefuls who lined up outside QVC's corporate headquarters before 6:15 a.m. last Friday was Mark Werden, a former singer and dancer with the self-empowerment performance group Up With People. The candidates had been told to bring an object they would pretend to sell during their two-minute auditions. Mr. Werden, wearing a bright pink sweater, carried an aluminum frying pan his mother gave him when he left for college.</p>
        <p>''This frying pan comes with love,'' he said, beginning his audition in a cramped room with three QVC employees looking on from behind a videocamera. Tapes from promising candidates would be shown to higher-ups, and around 35 would be called back for the next round. The company intends to hire two to four hosts this year, said Michael George, its president and chief executive.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Mr. Werden, 42, said he was hoping for a career change from being a private guidance counselor. Why the old frying pan?</p>
        <p>''It's pretty easy to sell something if you believe in it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Professional hosts must move merchandise even if they don't believe in it. As the hopefuls auditioned, Leah Williams, a host who joined QVC in 1996, performed live in the spacious studio at the back of the building, playing a gracious sidekick to an accessories designer, Kathy Van Zeeland, who was offering an imitation leather handbag. After Ms. Van Zeeland flipped the bag open and said the exterior fabric had a ''leather hand'' (meaning it feels like leather), Ms. Williams said that what appealed to her was the tiny makeup mirror on the inside of the top flap.</p>
        <p>''Love it,'' the host said, sweeping her gaze from bag to camera. ''Love,'' she repeated. She paused long enough for the word that can mean so much, and so little, to inhabit its own full measure of airtime. Finally, she completed her thought with another word spoken as if it deserved its own sentence: ''It.''</p>
        <p>A lot of drama for a $37.12 handbag and only a few seconds in a three-hour shift on camera.</p>
        <p>''For me,'' said Sandra Bennett, a host who was hired after last year's open call, ''the hardest challenge is staying perky for three hours.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bennett, 36, a former television news anchor in Harrisburg, impressed her auditioners so much that they ushered her into Mr. Comstock's office that very day. She soon signed a contract and began the rigorous six-month training program and trial period for new hosts. Now she typically arrives at QVC at 11 p.m. to prepare and appears on the air at 3 a.m.</p>
        <p>QVC officials would not say how much hosts are paid, but Kerry McNally, a former host on rival HSN who is now on the ShopNBC network, said they can make half a million dollars or more annually.</p>
        <p>And a kind of celebrity comes with the job. Mary Beth Roe, a former Minnesota beauty queen, who has been a QVC host for 17 years, said that fans often want to hug her. ''Viewers are very sweet,'' she said.</p>
        <p>While QVC, which employs 16,900 people worldwide (there are channels in England, Germany and Japan), is a major economic engine for West Chester, some residents say a few of the hosts have developed swollen egos.</p>
        <p>''There's some of them who host shows who think they're movie stars,'' said Allan Hofmann, the general manager of Transplant Transmissions, a repair shop in this college town, the home of West Chester University, founded in 1871. ''They talk down to people. When they're in the stores, they act like they shouldn't have to pay for stuff. 'Do you know who I am?' they ask.''</p>
        <p>Online discussion boards like those at tvtalkshows.com chronicle every hairstyle change and facial wrinkle of some hosts. One thread on a discussion board about Ms. Bennett is titled ''Sandra is superhot, but lacks pizazz.'' Another remarks on her ''sexy feet.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bennett said she has stopped reading about herself. ''I'd rather my feedback come from my producers than whether someone online likes my hair or not,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Being the subject of celebrity gossip is a problem plenty of people might like, judging by the eagerness of would-be hosts. Sporting a furry beard and metal-rim glasses, and with a soft midsection, Eddie Deutch, a salesman at an Apple computer store in King of Prussia, showed up with a laptop to ''sell'' at his audition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deutch, 53, spoke easily to the camera during his two minutes. Was he telegenic enough for QVC? He did not have the baby blue eyes of Rick Domeier, who appeared in his pre-host days on the soap opera ''The Young and the Restless'' and in the movie ''Evil Dead II.''</p>
        <p>Appearance did not seem to concern Mr. Deutch, who maintained: ''Viewers don't care if it's coming from a model or someone who can just talk clearly to them. Talking about tech is something I'm good at.'' He went away hopeful.</p>
        <p>Although QVC is more than twice the size of HSN, its nearest competitor, Mr. George, the QVC president, keeps watch on his rivals. He has seven televisions on in hisoffice, some tuned to ShopNBC, Jewelry Television and HSN.</p>
        <p>How does he compare his network with the others? ''What makes us unique in the world of televised retailing,'' he said, ''is we were founded on the basic notion that this is a new nascent industry of TV shopping that is filled with hype and schlock, and we're going to be the opposite of that, the quality, value, convenience network.''</p>
        <p>Executives at HSN, formerly the Home Shopping Network, did not seem to dispute that assessment. Andy Sheldon, who was named the senior vice president for television at HSN five months ago, said by phone he hopes to class up its image, in part by toning down the on-the-air talent's heavy eye makeup and ''big hair.'' He is flying his hosts to New York to have them styled by Oscar Blandi at his salon.</p>
        <p>''If a host starts putting on weight, then I will absolutely say something to them,'' Mr. Sheldon said from his company's headquarters in St. Petersburg, Fla.</p>
        <p>As Ms. Seegers, the bank employee, auditioned, her blond hair was perfectly in place and her voice was calm as she made her points, including remembering the correct item number, H98618, for the sugared Easter wreath she was selling. (It had already appeared on QVC.) The fabric on the wrists of her black blazer vibrated slightly, apparently betraying her nerves.</p>
        <p>Even television pros can falter under audition pressure. Shelley Crenshaw, a former television news reporter at stations in the Seattle area, who has been out of work for about a year, was also hoping to be hired. Wearing a low-cut purple shirt, she spoke clearly, but her performance did not wow Mr. Comstock, who said later he would probably invite her back for a second audition, based only on her résumé. ''My advice to Shelley would be calm down, be yourself,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crenshaw said she would not be ashamed at moving from the world of television journalism to home shopping, but while waiting to hear from QVC, she's spending her time watching CNN.</p>
        <p>''For example, that stuff with the shootings in Virginia and Imus,'' she said, ''I've been glued to the TV. I still like to know what's going on in the world.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
