<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Austria's Chancellor Has Clout At the Opera</title>
    <meta content="19aust" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/arts/music/19aust.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria/Vienna</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Vienna (Austria)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Austria</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Vienna State Opera</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Shicoff, Neil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0DA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Austria's Chancellor Has Clout At the Opera</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Austria’s Chancellor Has Clout at the Opera</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>VIENNA, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alfred Gusenbauer vividly recalls his first nights at the opera. As a son of working-class parents, who came to Vienna from the provinces to study, he spent precious schillings to stand at the rear of the horseshoe-shaped auditorium in the Vienna opera house.</p>
        <p>Two decades later Mr. Gusenbauer, 47, is the new chancellor of Austria and still a dedicated opera fan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Vienna State Opera’s search for a director has become a politically fraught process since Alfred Gusenbauer, the new chancellor of Austria, muddied the waters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alfred Gusenbauer vividly recalls his first nights at the opera. As a son of working-class parents, who came to Vienna from the provinces to study, he spent precious schillings to stand at the rear of the horseshoe-shaped auditorium in the Vienna opera house.</p>
        <p>Two decades later Mr. Gusenbauer, 47, is the new chancellor of Austria and still a dedicated opera fan.</p>
        <p>''The major difference between then and now is that I'm sitting instead of standing,'' he said in an interview in his office, across an elegant park from the Hofburg, the imperial palace of the Hapsburgs.</p>
        <p>Actually, people here point out, this is not the biggest difference. Mr. Gusenbauer's coalition government oversees the Vienna State Opera, the most famous opera house in the German-speaking world and perhaps the most hallowed cultural institution in Austria.</p>
        <p>The opera is choosing a new director, a politically fraught process that has become even more fraught since Mr. Gusenbauer muddied the waters. In recent weeks, according to several people in the Viennese cultural establishment, he has indicated privately he would like the job to go to Neil Shicoff, an American opera singer who lives and works mostly in Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shicoff, the chancellor acknowledged this week, is a close friend and political supporter. But he insisted that the choice of a successor to Ioan Holender, the longest-serving director in the postwar history of the state opera, is entirely up to his culture and education minister.</p>
        <p>''I follow the opera quite closely,'' said Mr. Gusenbauer, whose other hobbies include fine wine and languages. (He speaks five, including English.) ''I like it,'' he added. ''But it's not my decision.''</p>
        <p>Few people here seem persuaded. The chancellor's not-so-subtle behind-the-scenes involvement has kicked up an operatic tiff here, with opposition parties and the Viennese papers criticizing him for meddling in high culture.</p>
        <p>The leftist Green Party labeled him ''an operetta chancellor who considers art important only if he can put himself on center stage.'' Thomas Trenkler, an editor of the Vienna newspaper Der Standard, wrote that Mr. Gusenbauer was misusing ''art as a political stage.''</p>
        <p>Their cavils are not directed against Mr. Shicoff, 57, a tenor and a Brooklyn-born cantor's son who has won a loyal following here with performances in Halévy's opera ''La Juive'' and Mozart's ''Idomeneo.'' Some agree that he is qualified and would be an intriguing choice, though others point to his lack of managerial experience -- he has never run an orchestra or an opera house -- and his lack of German as handicaps.</p>
        <p>The biggest problem, the critics say, is the whiff of cronyism, which could damage Mr. Shicoff's credibility with Vienna's notoriously finicky operagoers even if he won the job on legitimate grounds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shicoff declined a request for an interview.</p>
        <p>The chancellor and the tenor met seven years ago through a mutual friend. Mr. Shicoff, a staunch supporter of Mr. Gusenbauer's Social Democratic Party, was photographed giving Mr. Gusenbauer a hug before his last televised debate with his predecessor, Wolfgang Schüssel, whom he unseated after a razor-thin victory in October.</p>
        <p>By law the director is selected by the culture minister, in this case Claudia Schmied, a Social Democrat, who has said she is soliciting applications until April 21 and plans to make a decision before the summer.</p>
        <p>''This is one of the four or five most important cultural positions in the world,'' said Peter Marboe, director of Vienna Mozart Year 2006, a festival celebrating the 250th year of Mozart's birth. ''The process should be handled in a very transparent way, in which the best person is chosen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marboe -- whose father, Ernst Marboe, was the director when the opera house reopened after World War II -- said the job was demanding enough without creating suspicions about how one got it.</p>
        <p>In addition to handling divas and conductors, the director must negotiate with the Vienna Philharmonic, whose members are drawn from the orchestra of the opera. Proud and prickly, the Philharmonic is regularly at odds with the director over how much its musicians are paid.</p>
        <p>Then there are the news media, which remorselessly dissect the judgment of the director, whether it is the choice of repertory and casting or how often the conductor appears in the house. (Seiji Ozawa, the current music director, has been absent because of a lengthy illness and will be returning late this month.)</p>
        <p>Among those who have braved the brickbats are Karl Böhm, once booed for spending too much time abroad; Herbert von Karajan, who won grudging respect; and Lorin Maazel, the American conductor, who lasted only from 1982 to 1984.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holender, a Romanian-born baritone with a deep tan and a dazzling smile, has shown a remarkable knack for navigating Vienna's treacherous cultural waters. But after 19 years he announced that he would not extend his contract beyond 2010, which set off the horse race.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holender has not hesitated to offer suggestions about who should succeed him. Speaking to the Austrian paper Kurier, he proposed Klaus Bachler, the director of the Burgtheater, who is not available, since he signed a contract to take over the Bavarian State Opera next year.</p>
        <p>In an interview Mr. Holender spoke glowingly about another candidate, Franz Welser-Möst, the Austrian conductor now at the helm of the Cleveland Orchestra. The German conductor Christian Thielemann, who once directed the Deutsche Oper in Berlin, is also in the running.</p>
        <p>Asked about Mr. Shicoff, with whom he has worked on several productions, Mr. Holender turned uncharacteristically silent. ''I'm not involved in it,'' he said, ''and I don't want to be involved in it.''</p>
        <p>Still, he added, he had no objection to Chancellor Gusenbauer's involvement. ''It would be sad if he didn't have an opinion, because if it goes badly, it is his problem,'' Mr. Holender said.</p>
        <p>''There are only three things everyone knows about Austria: the state opera, the Vienna Philharmonic and the snow in the winter,'' Mr. Holender said, reclining in an office lined with photos of famous maestros. ''Now the snow is disappearing, so Austria is known for only two things.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
