<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Chaos, One Notably Restrained Voice</title>
    <meta content="19watc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/arts/television/19watc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE TV WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">ABC Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">MSNBC</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gibson, Charles</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Couric, Katie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Brian</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rose, Charlie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Chaos, One Notably Restrained Voice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amid Chaos, One Notably Restrained Voice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brian Williams of ''NBC Nightly News'' told PBS's Charlie Rose on Tuesday that the shootings at Virginia Tech proved that viewers still wanted traditional network anchors.</p>
        <p>Most don't need more than one, however.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The positive response to Charles Gibson’s calm handling of the Virginia shootings on ABC shows viewers still want traditional network anchors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brian Williams of ''NBC Nightly News'' told PBS's Charlie Rose on Tuesday that the shootings at Virginia Tech proved that viewers still wanted traditional network anchors.</p>
        <p>Most don't need more than one, however.</p>
        <p>The excruciatingly close-up and continuous coverage of the massacre helps explain why viewers are increasingly turning to Charles Gibson of ABC. When it comes to an anchor's presence at a major breaking story, less can be more.</p>
        <p>And particularly in the middle of so wrenching a tragedy, tone matters as much as content. Hurricane Katrina, even more than 9/11, emboldened television newscasters to fold themselves and their feelings into the story, and that has led to the Anderson Cooperization of the evening news.</p>
        <p>Network anchors often behave as if they are the nation's grief counselors. One reason that Mr. Gibson has been gaining in the ratings could be that he acts like the nation's newsman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams and CBS's Katie Couric were in Blacksburg, Va., on Monday, the day of the shootings -- CBS that night extended the evening newscast to a full hour. Mr. Gibson, who didn't arrive on the scene until Tuesday and delegated many interviews to ABC colleagues, was better than either of his rivals at keeping an even keel. His interview with a group of survivors on Tuesday night was more bearable to watch, mostly because his questions, posed in a kindly but neutral manner, solicited information, not emotion.</p>
        <p>''And how would you describe his facial manner and demeanor?'' Mr. Gibson asked, referring to the gunman. ''Could you feel him pushing against the door?'' Perhaps relieved to be asked for facts and not just their feelings, the students delivered both.</p>
        <p>Until recently, NBC could always count on easily outdoing its rivals on a major breaking story. On Monday NBC had slightly more viewers, 10.3 million, than ABC, which was about 270,000 behind, according to preliminary ratings figures. (CBS was a distant third, with two million fewer.) But Mr. Gibson, who took over the ABC anchor desk permanently almost a year ago, has in recent months been steadily gaining on NBC. For the week of April 2, ABC ranked first in total viewers, with its greatest margin over NBC since August 2005.</p>
        <p>Bad news always draws large audiences, but in a major tragedy, be it 9/11, Hurricane Katrina or a campus shooting like Columbine and now Virginia Tech, the viewer also looks more closely at the messenger -- sometimes punitively. When nerves are raw, even an anchor's tiniest misstep or phony moment can grate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams is polished and authoritative when delivering the news, but he turns longwinded and cloyingly personal in one-on-one interviews, perhaps trying to compensate for a stuffy Savile Row style or to relive his more emotive reporting during Katrina.</p>
        <p>Ms. Couric, who anchored Monday's broadcast in white slacks and very little makeup to signal to viewers that she was hard at work in the field (actually, it was a university alumni room), is less wordy, but in interviews she tends to lower her voice to signal compassion and to gaze at the interviewee with gauzy, sorrowful looks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gibson, who comes across on-screen as rumpled, pleasant and serious, doesn't try as hard to look softhearted.</p>
        <p>The networks went all-out on the story, all three extending their evening newscasts to an hour on Tuesday and crashing special editions of their magazine shows onto the air on Monday and Tuesday. Right after delivering Tuesday's evening news, Ms. Couric was host of a special edition of ''48 Hours.''</p>
        <p>Anchors are most useful during a prolonged crisis -- they marshal the fast-flowing, sometimes contradictory facts and bring an authoritative narrative to an unfinished story. But unlike Katrina or 9/11, this catastrophe was not a continuing disaster: sadly, the worst was over before midday. All the news programs were working with the same distressing material -- and even videotape -- packaging the story as much as reporting it.</p>
        <p>CNN, which dispatched 100 or so people to Blacksburg, often surpassed the networks. CNN was the news organization that first got hold of the disturbing cellphone recording of shots being fired in Norris Hall, which was sent to the CNN Web site, cnn.com, by a student bystander. On Tuesday evening CNN had found two suitemates who recounted some of the most chilling details about the gunman, Cho Seung-Hui, including that he had an imaginary girlfriend named Jelly.</p>
        <p>Yesterday MSNBC had the strangest news bulletin of all: that cable news outlet said that NBC had received a package of material from Mr. Cho that was apparently sent between the two shootings.</p>
        <p>Coverage on the whole was thorough, dignified and respectful, but the effort to stake a special claim to the story appeared at times strained. All three anchors had brief one-on-one interviews on Tuesday with President Bush and the first lady, who had come to attend the university convocation; CBS and ABC had theirs in the same corner of a room lined with maroon and gold insignias. Introducing her interview, Ms. Couric told viewers, '' I sat down with President and Mrs. Bush.'' (Actually, they stood for the entire conversation.)</p>
        <p>NBC's newsmagazine show, ''Dateline,'' couldn't quite shake its innate cheesiness. Every news program had the same outdoor interview with John Markell, the owner of the Roanoke gun shop where Mr. Cho bought one of his weapons. Chris Hansen, who is the host of the ''To Catch a Predator'' features on ''Dateline,'' sat in a room posing questions via satellite to Mr. Markell, who was outdoors surrounded by leafy trees. It had the look of one of those hokey interview parodies on ''The Daily Show With Jon Stewart.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gibson didn't look as if he were simulating emotion or fact-finding; he looked professional and self-effacing. And in a calamity, that is actually a comfort.</p>
        <p>THE TV WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
