<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BACK ON BROADWAY</title>
    <meta content="19rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/sports/hockey/19rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Thrashers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cullen, Matt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Shanahan, Brendan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lundqvist, Henrik</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6D61E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BACK ON BROADWAY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers’ Sweep Sends Atlanta South</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the delay dragged on in the third period last night and the Madison Square Garden crowd chanted nervously, ''Goal, goal, goal,'' Rangers center Matt Cullen tried not to let his mind sneak ahead. The longer the replay officials looked at his shot that hit the crossbar and dropped to the goal line, the better Cullen felt. He knew the game and the Rangers' first playoff series victory in 10 years were hanging on it.</p>
        <p>When referee Mike Hassenfratz pointed to center ice to signal a goal, the Garden crowd erupted. The old arena shook. The Rangers pushed through to a 4-2 victory, finishing off a 4-0 sweep against a Thrashers team that never quite knew what hit it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Atlanta played much tougher in Game 4, twice taking a lead before the Rangers stormed back to win and advance to the second round of the playoffs for the first time in a decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the delay dragged on in the third period last night and the Madison Square Garden crowd chanted nervously, ''Goal, goal, goal,'' Rangers center Matt Cullen tried not to let his mind sneak ahead. The longer the replay officials looked at his shot that hit the crossbar and dropped to the goal line, the better Cullen felt. He knew the game and the Rangers' first playoff series victory in 10 years were hanging on it.</p>
        <p>When referee Mike Hassenfratz pointed to center ice to signal a goal, the Garden crowd erupted. The old arena shook. The Rangers pushed through to a 4-2 victory, finishing off a 4-0 sweep against a Thrashers team that never quite knew what hit it.</p>
        <p>''It felt like a lot more than two or three minutes,'' Cullen said of the delay. ''It felt like a long time. But it was great. It was a great feeling.''</p>
        <p>Cullen's goal, scored two minutes into the third period, was the game- and series-winner.</p>
        <p>A Rangers team that had clawed its way into a playoff spot late in the regular season was now the first team to advance to the second round, sweeping third-seeded Atlanta out of its first playoff appearance.</p>
        <p>The Rangers will not find out their next opponent until the other Eastern Conference series are concluded. The N.H.L. reseeds after each round, and the Rangers could end up playing Buffalo, the Devils, Ottawa or Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>But for now, the Rangers will enjoy their accomplishment. It was their first series victory since beating Devils in the second round in 1997. It was their first playoff series sweep since they routed the Islanders in the first round in 1994. This sweep came a year after the Rangers were dispatched by the Devils in four straight games after ending a nine-year playoff drought.</p>
        <p>The Rangers left little doubt about this series. They won two one-goal games in Atlanta, then overwhelmed the Thrashers in a 7-0 rout Tuesday night at the Garden to set up the clincher.</p>
        <p>It did not come easily. The Thrashers found the kind of fight they had been sorely lacking in Game 3 and took the lead twice. They came in hoping to catch the Rangers in a moment of complacency.</p>
        <p>The Thrashers scored the game's first goal, by the otherwise ineffective Keith Tkachuk, who was acquired at the trading deadline. They took a 2-1 lead late into the second period on a goal by defenseman Greg DeVries.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers could hardly feel rattled with a three-game cushion. Two months ago, they were the Eastern Conference's 11th-place team, all but needing a telescope to see a playoff spot. With that perspective, a first-round sweep of Atlanta almost seemed like too much to ask.</p>
        <p>''I don't know that anybody ever goes into any series expecting to sweep,'' Rangers forward Brendan Shanahan said. ''They're pretty rare, regardless if you're a first seed playing an eighth seed. I don't think anybody ever says, 'We're going to sweep this series.' ''</p>
        <p>Shanahan played a big role in ensuring this sweep. With the Rangers trailing by 2-1 late in the second, he led a 2-on-1 rush with Martin Straka when Atlanta defenseman Alexei Zhitnik was caught deep in the Rangers' zone. With the remaining defenseman, Niclas Havelid, playing the pass to Straka, Shanahan took a shot that hit goalie Johan Hedberg and trickled over the goal line with 1 minute 42 seconds left in the second.</p>
        <p>That gave the Rangers a huge lift and they showed renewed energy in the third. Cullen's goal came 2:06 in, but after he scored, the Rangers peppered the Thrashers with scoring chances. Hedberg kept turning them away until he was no longer in the net. With 1:33 left, Jaromir Jagr finally ended the drama with an empty-net goal.</p>
        <p>''It's one step,'' Jagr said. ''It's exciting to win four straight and get a long rest, but it wasn't our goal to just make the first round. The last 20 or 30 games of the regular season, if we played the way we played, we could beat anybody.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers never let the Thrashers get a foothold in this series. They held the high-scoring combination of Ilya Kovalchuk, Marian Hossa and Slava Kozlov to one goal and one assist, both by Kovalchuk. The three combined for 256 points in the regular season.</p>
        <p>''I learned a lot,'' said Kovalchuk, who was making his first playoff appearance. ''I don't think I played my best, but I tried hard. It feels really empty when you lose four in a row.''</p>
        <p>Atlanta Coach Bob Hartley did not help his team by flip-flopping goalies, benching the regular-season starter Kari Lehtonen for Hedberg twice. But he pointed to the dominance of the Rangers' top line of Jagr, Michael Nylander and Marcel Hossa as the reason. They combined for 7 goals and 10 assists in the series.</p>
        <p>''That line caused a lot of damage,'' Hartley said. ''They were basically unstoppable.''</p>
        <p>In the end, though, the Rangers found themselves waiting on a replay of a shot by Cullen. It was his first goal of the series. It was the biggest one of all.</p>
        <p>''If we play like we played here,'' Cullen said, ''anything can happen.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Rangers forward Brendan Shanahan's second-period goal was his third of the playoffs and the 56th of his playoff career. He is fourth among active players in playoff goals. One of those Shanahan trails is his teammate, Jaromir Jagr, who has 69. Rangers center Michael Nylander had an assist on Michal Rozsival's power-play goal in the second period, giving him 8 points in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
