<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Old School Soufflé Of Charm And Power</title>
    <meta content="19hold" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/arts/19hold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AN APPRAISAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">An Appraisal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hart, Kitty Carlisle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Old School Soufflé Of Charm And Power</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Old School Soufflé of Charm and Power</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anyone fortunate enough to have observed Kitty Carlisle Hart in her mid-90s singing the great American songbook at Feinstein's at the Regency or dropping pearls of show business lore at this or that tribute or benefit, was a witness to one of the most amazing final acts in New York City cultural history.</p>
        <p>A quintessential Manhattan grande dame of the old school, Miss Carlisle, as she was known professionally, combined a meticulously cultivated charm with a shrewd awareness of where the lines of power flowed, along with a hearty enjoyment of life that made you wonder what was her secret.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kitty Carlisle Hart combined a meticulously cultivated charm with a shrewd awareness of where the lines of power flowed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anyone fortunate enough to have observed Kitty Carlisle Hart in her mid-90s singing the great American songbook at Feinstein's at the Regency or dropping pearls of show business lore at this or that tribute or benefit, was a witness to one of the most amazing final acts in New York City cultural history.</p>
        <p>A quintessential Manhattan grande dame of the old school, Miss Carlisle, as she was known professionally, combined a meticulously cultivated charm with a shrewd awareness of where the lines of power flowed, along with a hearty enjoyment of life that made you wonder what was her secret.</p>
        <p>Good genes of course. But what else? Was it the self-discipline she described in her 1988 memoir, ''Kitty: An Autobiography,'' and which has been noted in numerous magazine profiles? There was her daily exercise routine of arching her legs over her head to touch the floor. There was her morning ritual of pausing to study her reflection in the mirror and saying, ''I forgive you.''</p>
        <p>Her insatiable curiosity about the world was certainly a major factor.</p>
        <p>On a Sunday afternoon in the mid-1980s I was summoned to tea at Miss Carlisle's Upper East Side apartment. There was of course an agenda. She wanted to know the best way to get more newspaper coverage of the New York State Council on the Arts. She talked of the joy she took in her job as chairwoman of the council. What she loved most, she said, was, ''peeking through doors to see what's behind them.''</p>
        <p>When she met someone for the first time, she opened with pointed questions: ''Where did you go to school?'' And, ''What does your father do?'' Intimidating to be sure but phrased in a tone that signaled any answers would be acceptable. It was one of her shortcuts to getting acquainted.</p>
        <p>Even into her mid-90s Miss Carlisle was indefatigable. Never one to sit back, sigh and let life pass her by, she was a dyed-in-greasepaint show business trouper who enthusiastically took her act on the road until her health began to fail.</p>
        <p>As she reminisced onstage, telling anecdotes that were just salty enough to suggest the foibles of the numerous legends she knew without toppling them, Broadway was ''the American musical thea-tah,'' a term she trilled with the zest of a schoolgirl. She made you believe that the dazzling world of famous composers, directors, politicians and show folk in which moved constituted an exclusive place of ultimate glamour and civility that has now vanished. Among the standards she sang in a remarkably sturdy voice, tinged with an operatic vibrato, she brought a special conviction to Rodgers and Hammerstein's ''Something Wonderful.''</p>
        <p>Who knows if the golden world she conjured was as enchanted as she described it? Now and then she hinted it was much closer in spirit to the one we live in now, in which driven, neurotic artists and social climbers with substance-abuse problems, insecurities and personal secrets play at being grown-ups while jockeying for position.</p>
        <p>Here are a few of her recollections from her show. George Gershwin, who courted her but never got to second base, ''needed continual approval.'' In his pursuit of women he invented a ditty he sang and played in which he left a word blank to be filled in with the name of the lady of the moment. An invitation to audition for him by singing ''Summertime'' was his equivalent of inviting a woman up to see his etchings.</p>
        <p>Remembering the playwright and director Moss Hart, with whom she had a storybook marriage, she lifted the veil just enough to describe him as ''a poor boy from the Bronx who went to a college he made up called Hebrew Tech.''</p>
        <p>Jerome Kern was a stern taskmaster who once berated her for a changing a chord he had written. Twenty-five years before ''My Fair Lady,'' its composer, Frederick Loewe, vowed to her that he would one day write ''the greatest musical on Broadway,'' and on the show's triumphant opening night, he reminded her of his vow.</p>
        <p>But my favorite bon mot in her show was her recollection of words spoken by her mother about the way time flies: ''When you pass 50, every 15 minutes it's breakfast.''</p>
        <p>AN APPRAISAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
