<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Four Women Are Convicted In Attack on Man in Village</title>
    <meta content="19attack" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/nyregion/19attack.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EED91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Four Women Are Convicted In Attack on Man in Village</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Four Women Are Convicted in Attack on Man in Village</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four young women from Newark were convicted of gang assault yesterday in the beating and stabbing of an independent filmmaker in Greenwich Village last summer, the jury rejecting their contention that they were defending themselves against an anti-lesbian attack.</p>
        <p>But one of the women, Patreese Johnson, 19, was acquitted of attempted murder, the most serious charge in the case. Prosecutors said she had stabbed the filmmaker, Dwayne Buckle, in the abdomen with a steak knife that she carried in her purse. Ms. Johnson contended that she had only tried to cut Mr. Buckle's arm to keep him from choking two of her friends.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four young women from Newark were convicted of gang assault yesterday in the beating and stabbing of an independent filmmaker in Greenwich Village last summer, the jury rejecting their contention that they were defending themselves against an anti-lesbian attack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four young women from Newark were convicted of gang assault yesterday in the beating and stabbing of an independent filmmaker in Greenwich Village last summer, the jury rejecting their contention that they were defending themselves against an anti-lesbian attack.</p>
        <p>But one of the women, Patreese Johnson, 19, was acquitted of attempted murder, the most serious charge in the case. Prosecutors said she had stabbed the filmmaker, Dwayne Buckle, in the abdomen with a steak knife that she carried in her purse. Ms. Johnson contended that she had only tried to cut Mr. Buckle's arm to keep him from choking two of her friends.</p>
        <p>Along with gang assault, the jury found Ms. Johnson, who is 4-foot-11 and weighs less than 100 pounds, guilty of first-degree assault, which carries the same penalty of 5 to 25 years in prison as the attempted murder charge.</p>
        <p>The young women sobbed and wailed ''No-oo!'' ''Mommy!'' and ''I didn't do it!'' as Justice Edward J. McLaughlin of State Supreme Court in Manhattan ordered them jailed until their sentencing next month, but it was almost impossible to tell who was saying what as they were led away in handcuffs by court officers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnson, who worked as a night cashier at Wal-Mart, turned and mouthed ''I love you'' to a sister, brother and cousin in the spectator seats.</p>
        <p>The trial attracted attention because both sides, though in opposite ways, framed the case as a bias attack involving lesbians and a straight man. The other three defendants, Renata Hill, 25; Terrain Dandridge, 20; and Venice Brown, 19, were convicted of second-degree gang assault and face 3 1/2 to 15 years in prison.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buckle, 29, of Queens said he was sitting on a fire hydrant and handing out DVDs of one of his films outside the Independent Film Center at Avenue of the Americas and West Third Street just before 2 a.m. on Aug. 18 when the women walked by him and he made a flirtatious remark.</p>
        <p>He testified that they then attacked him without any physical provocation on his part. While recovering at St. Vincent's Hospital Manhattan, he told The New York Post that he had been ''the victim of a hate crime against a straight man.''</p>
        <p>The defense scoffed at the idea that Mr. Buckle was just sitting on the street trying to promote his films.</p>
        <p>The women contended that Mr. Buckle made crude sexual advances, and when they told him they were not interested because they were lesbians, he spat at them, threw a cigarette and tried to choke two of them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnson's lawyer, Alan Lippel, said the jury appeared to believe at least some of her testimony. ''I think they were not convinced beyond a reasonable doubt that she intended to kill the guy,'' Mr. Lippel said.</p>
        <p>Susan V. Tipograph, who, along with Laurie Cohen, represented Ms. Hill, said after the verdict, ''We're disappointed.'' She said that although ''nobody takes any satisfaction in what happened,'' the four women had come to New York to have a good time and never anticipated anything like what happened.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tipograph's presence on the defense team was, perhaps, one indication of the passions stirred by the case. Although she often defends obscure indigent defendants, her clients have also included former Black Panthers and Lynne F. Stewart, the leftist lawyer convicted in 2005 of aiding terrorism by smuggling messages out of prison for a client, Sheik Omar Abdel Rahman.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tipograph said she had volunteered to defend Ms. Hill pro bono after learning through the National Lawyers Guild that the young woman was seeking a lawyer. ''It was pitched as it is,'' Ms. Tipograph said. ''She was one of a number of women who had gotten harassed on the street.''</p>
        <p>But she added: ''I certainly didn't get involved in this as part of a cause. She was a decent young woman in a jam, calling out for some help.''</p>
        <p>Many of the defendants' female supporters in the courtroom wore long robes and head scarves, and Mr. Lippel said that his client's sister was a practicing Muslim.</p>
        <p>''It's not over,'' said Kevin G. Roe, a lawyer for Ms. Dandridge, saying the defense would appeal.</p>
        <p>The jury of 10 women -- many of them not too much older than the defendants -- and two men, reached its verdict after only about five hours of deliberations.</p>
        <p>The defense contended that a mysterious man in a pink shirt, shown in a surveillance videotape joining the brawl, had actually stabbed Mr. Buckle.</p>
        <p>The police searched for the man in the pink shirt but never found him, a police officer testified.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
