<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Queens Man Kills Mother and 2 Others, Then Himself</title>
    <meta content="19dead" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/nyregion/19dead.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6D71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Queens Man Kills Mother and 2 Others, Then Himself</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Queens Man Kills Mother and 2 Others, Then Himself</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARA BUCKLEY and THOMAS J. LUECK; Maureen Seaberg contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J; Buckley, Cara; Seaberg, Maureen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 20-year-old man with a history of mental disturbance shot and killed his mother, her companion and her companion's health care aide before killing himself in a quiet Queens neighborhood yesterday, the police said.</p>
        <p>Moments before the shootings, the mother, Sonia Taylor, 44, called the police frantically, saying she feared for her life. A fifth person, the companion's nephew, escaped by leaping out of a back window. He had played dead after the gunman grazed him in the leg, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The killings appear to have been the culmination of an increasingly fractious relationship between the gunman and his mother.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 20-year-old man with a history of mental disturbance shot and killed his mother, her companion and her companion's health care aide before killing himself in a quiet Queens neighborhood yesterday, the police said.</p>
        <p>Moments before the shootings, the mother, Sonia Taylor, 44, called the police frantically, saying she feared for her life. A fifth person, the companion's nephew, escaped by leaping out of a back window. He had played dead after the gunman grazed him in the leg, the police said.</p>
        <p>The killings appear to have been the grim culmination of an increasingly fractious relationship between the gunman, Wade Jimmy Lee Dawkins, and Ms. Taylor, who called the police twice on Monday, saying she was frightened by arguments with her son. The police said they had responded, but concluded that the arguments -- one of which was about the use of a computer and a telephone -- did not amount to a crime.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dawkins was taken to Long Island Jewish Hospital for emotional disturbance in October, after his mother, who worked at NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital in Manhattan, called the police, saying he was throwing things around the house. In that instance, too, the police said there was insufficient evidence to arrest Mr. Dawkins. It is unclear whether he was admitted to the hospital. But Ms. Taylor filed a complaint with the Police Department's Internal Affairs Bureau because she thought that he should have been arrested, the police said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor's sister, Ann Taylor, lashed out at the authorities yesterday, saying her sister had called the police seven times in recent days -- the police confirm only the three -- because she was desperate for protection against her son.</p>
        <p>''Nobody would get him out of the house,'' Ann Taylor said tearfully. ''This is ridiculous. Oh, my God.''</p>
        <p>The shootings took place shortly after 11:40 a.m. yesterday, in a small home on a tree-lined stretch of 225th Street in Cambria Heights. Ms. Taylor lived there with her companion, Arnold Lawson, 47, who used a wheelchair after a recent stroke. His home health aide, identified by the police as Syndi Boye, 28, of Brooklyn, was there, along with Mr. Lawson's nephew, Maurice Johnson, 21, who was visiting from Jamaica to help care for his uncle, who had also worked at NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor and Mr. Lawson's son, Jamal, who is 8, also lived at the home, friends said, but was most likely at school when the shootings occurred.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor called 911 shortly after 11:30 am., the police said. She was distraught, saying her son was wrecking the house, and that they had been arguing for five hours. If the police did not come, Ms. Taylor said, ''something terrible would happen.'' The dispatcher asked if he had a weapon. ''Yes,'' Ms. Taylor replied. Officers were dispatched.</p>
        <p>Moments later, Mr. Dawkins began firing, the police said. Ms. Taylor and Ms. Boye were shot in the face, and their bodies fell in the living room and kitchen, three feet apart. Mr. Dawkins then went to the bedroom at the back of the first floor and shot Mr. Lawson, who was standing up at the time, in the chest and the face, the police said. He then shot Mr. Johnson, who fell back into a closet on a heap of clothes, his leg grazed, and pretended he was dead.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dawkins then went upstairs to a front bedroom, the police said, pressed a gun to the right side of his head and pulled the trigger. After hearing the shot, Mr. Johnson jumped out of the back window and raced to the 3 J's Restaurant nearby on Linden Boulevard, where the owner, Joyce Reynolds Walcot, called for help.</p>
        <p>''I saw this man barge through the door screaming for help,'' said Ms. Walcot, 50. ''He told me the house he was in was all shot up.''</p>
        <p>By then, the police had arrived at Ms. Taylor's house, responding to her call. They found the bodies of Ms. Taylor and Ms. Boye, both in white nurses' uniforms, on the first floor. Mr. Lawson's body was found in the back room, face down on the floor, and Mr. Dawkins's was found upstairs, a .40-caliber Smith &amp; Wesson semiautomatic gun nearby.</p>
        <p>It was not yet known yesterday evening how many shots he had fired, and the police said the gun was not stolen.</p>
        <p>Neighbors and family friends said Mr. Dawkins had seemed troubled of late, since his recent return from Jamaica, where he had visited relatives. Some people hinted that he had been using drugs.</p>
        <p>''Since then, he is not the person I used to know,'' said one acquaintance, who worked at the nearby Boston Jerk Palace and Restaurant, but would not give her name. Another family friend, Ronald Capers, 30, said Mr. Dawkins ''was a troubled person.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dawkins did not have a job, friends said.</p>
        <p>Ann Taylor said she learned of the deaths yesterday afternoon when she happened to be passing by in her minivan and saw the ribbons of police tape. Through tears, she insisted that the authorities ignored her sister's calls for help. But a police spokesman said yesterday that Ms. Taylor had never sought an order of protection against her son, or gone to court to have him evicted from her home.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor and her family rented the home, and two hours after the shootings, their landlord, Neville Shaw, was solemnly escorted by the police through the cluster of reporters and into the house. Four hours later, around 5:45 p.m., the victims' bodies, each wrapped in black cloth, were wheeled out on gurneys and into the medical examiner's vans.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
