<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disallowed Goal Deflates the Islanders</title>
    <meta content="19islanders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/sports/hockey/19islanders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Drury, Chris</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dipietro, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EED71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disallowed Goal Deflates the Islanders</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Disallowed Goal Deflates the Islanders</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The puck squirted between the legs of Buffalo Sabres goaltender Ryan Miller and slid into the net. Miller then crashed backward, taking the brunt of the most ferocious and decisive collision of the game Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>The Islanders would later contend that they should have been credited with a goal, that the score should have been tied with 1 minute 42 seconds left in regulation. That they should have had a chance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chris Drury scored two goals, including the winner 39 seconds into the third period, to help the Sabres take a 3-1 lead over the Islanders in the best-of-seven series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The puck squirted between the legs of Buffalo Sabres goaltender Ryan Miller and slid into the net. Miller then crashed backward, taking the brunt of the most ferocious and decisive collision of the game Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>The Islanders would later contend that they should have been credited with a goal, that the score should have been tied with 1 minute 42 seconds left in regulation. That they should have had a chance.</p>
        <p>Instead, they left Nassau Coliseum fuming after a 4-2 loss to fall behind by 3-1 in their Eastern Conference first-round series.</p>
        <p>''I don't care what anybody says,'' Islanders Coach Ted Nolan said. ''That was a goal.''</p>
        <p>The Sabres can now eliminate the Islanders from their best-of-seven series on Friday, when Game 5 will be in Buffalo. The sting of Wednesday's loss could last until then.</p>
        <p>Garth Snow, the Islanders' former backup goalie who is now the team's first-year general manager, said the Islanders were victimized by lopsided officiating. Officials, he said, have treated the Islanders poorly since he joined the team in 2001.</p>
        <p>''A call like this happens on a regular basis,'' Snow said.</p>
        <p>Reporters were shown a replay of the collision after the game. The puck, pushed toward Miller by Islanders defenseman Brendan Witt, can be seen sliding between his legs. Witt and Islanders right wing Miroslav Satan then barged into Miller.</p>
        <p>Islanders center Mike Sillinger said he was told by the referee Mike Leggo that the goal did not count because Miller had been shoved into the net. Witt said the officials had not blown their whistles to stop play.</p>
        <p>''Why it was no goal, I have no idea,'' Sillinger said.</p>
        <p>Play was stopped, the capacity crowd of 16,234 was told over the public-address system, so the play could be reviewed. The delay lasted a few minutes, long enough for the fans to see a replay and begin a chant of ''Goal!''</p>
        <p>The play was finally ruled no goal. Buffalo right wing Jason Pominville scored 30 seconds later to give the Sabres a two-goal lead. Islanders goaltender Rick DiPietro, who made 27 saves, snapped his stick in two by slamming it against a goal post.</p>
        <p>''After a goaltender makes a save, they can't be pushed into the net after making the save,'' Leggo said after the game. ''I deemed the puck was under him and he made the save, and then he was pushed into the net. After he was in the net, I saw the puck came loose. I didn't see the puck until he got up, actually.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders contended that Miller had not stopped the puck before he was hit.</p>
        <p>''Our guys have worked too hard for the outcome of a game to be dependent on this,'' Snow said. ''Most important, our fans deserve better than to be treated like this.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders made it to the playoffs, in part because they played the role of the relentlessly passionate, hard-working underdogs to the hilt. They opened Wednesday's game by playing aggressively and getting the crowd into the game.</p>
        <p>Jason Blake gave the Islanders a 1-0 lead 6:24 into the game, scoring his first goal of the playoffs just as an Islanders power play expired. But Buffalo's Thomas Vanek and Chris Drury scored 1:48 apart midway through the first period.</p>
        <p>The Islanders tied the score with 16 seconds left in the period on a goal by Sillinger. The goal was set up by Islanders left wing Ryan Smyth, who beat Buffalo defenseman Henrik Tallinder to a loose puck before icing could be called.</p>
        <p>The goal was only the second of the series with the Islanders on the power play. The Islanders, 2 for 15 with a man advantage in the series, gained the power play when Buffalo defenseman Teppo Numminen shoved Blake headfirst into the boards and was called for boarding. Blake did not return to the game until late in the second period.</p>
        <p>''In minor hockey, a kid probably gets suspended for a month for hitting from behind,'' Nolan said.</p>
        <p>Drury scored his second goal of the game on a power play 39 seconds into the second period. It proved to be the winner.</p>
        <p>''You've just go to play hard and battle and fight to the end, that's what you've got to do,'' DiPietro said. ''We can't sit here and feel sorry for ourselves.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
