<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gomez Turns It On, And Turns The Tide</title>
    <meta content="19devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/sports/hockey/19devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gomez, Scott</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brodeur, Martin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lecavalier, Vincent</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EED71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gomez Turns It On, And Turns The Tide</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gomez Shares Spotlight in Win</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scott Gomez had been eclipsed in these playoffs by a younger, hungrier teammate, Zach Parise, but with one shot Wednesday night, Gomez reversed his and the Devils' course.</p>
        <p>Gomez, who will be a sought-after free agent at the season's end, scored his first goal of the postseason in the eighth minute of overtime to lead the Devils past the Tampa Bay Lightning, 4-3, to tie their Eastern Conference quarterfinal series at two games each.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scott Gomez scored his first goal of the N.H.L. postseason in the eighth minute of the first overtime to lead the Devils past the Lightning on Wednesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scott Gomez had been eclipsed in these playoffs by a younger, hungrier teammate, Zach Parise, but with one shot Wednesday night, Gomez reversed his and the Devils' course.</p>
        <p>Gomez, who will be a sought-after free agent at the season's end, scored his first goal of the postseason in the eighth minute of overtime to lead the Devils past the Tampa Bay Lightning, 4-3, to tie their Eastern Conference quarterfinal series at two games each.</p>
        <p>After pouncing on a blocked shot in his end, Gomez carried the puck up ice and flicked a shot past goaltender Johan Holmqvist, who made 7 of his 33 saves in the overtime.</p>
        <p>''It just went to the perfect spot,'' Gomez said of the shot, which he did not see go in. He knew it was good when he heard the groan of the St. Pete Times Forum crowd of 20,940.</p>
        <p>It was a dramatic end to a game that had seemed to slip from the Devils' grasp during a four-minute stretch in the second period when the Lightning erased a 3-1 deficit with goals by Martin St. Louis and Vincent Lecavalier.</p>
        <p>Over the past 13 postseasons, the Devils lost 43 of 51 games when allowing at least three goals. They prevailed on this night because goaltender Martin Brodeur made 5 saves in the overtime period on his way to 30.</p>
        <p>Two of the final three games will be played at the Meadowlands, starting Friday with Game 5.</p>
        <p>''It's a big momentum shift for us,'' Brodeur said. ''You lost that, you're down, 3-1. Now it's 2-2 and a different ballgame, so we're definitely happy about the situation that we're in.''</p>
        <p>Gomez's first career overtime playoff goal overshadowed another sterling performance by the second line of Parise, Jamie Langenbrunner and center Travis Zajac. Parise, who entered the game tied for the N.H.L. lead in postseason goals with four, scored twice to equal the team record for goals in a playoff series, set by Claude Lemieux in 1995 in the conference semifinals against the Pittsburgh Penguins.</p>
        <p>Led by Parise, the second line created its opportunities in the usual way, with good old-fashioned hard work. Their scrappiness was not matched in Games 2 or 3 by Gomez and his linemates Patrik Elias and Brian Gionta. That line had not scored in either of those games, both losses, but Lou Lamoriello, the team's general manager and coach, professed not to be worried.</p>
        <p>He was pleased with the line's effort and so he stuck with the trio even as some outsiders were suggesting that perhaps he should break the players up. Gomez and Company responded as Lamoriello was telling people they would, with Elias putting the game's first shot on net and Gomez the last. In between, Gionta put the Devils ahead, 1-0, at 6 minutes 4 seconds in the first period when he banged home a rebound of a shot by John Oduya.</p>
        <p>The Lightning, which did not record a shot in the opening 10 minutes, tied the game in the 13th minute of the first by capitalizing on a Devils mistake. Elias gave up the puck at his blue line to Éric Perrin, who spun around and released a shot from beyond the left circle that beat Brodeur on his glove side at 12:08.</p>
        <p>It was only the third save Brodeur had been summoned to make, and the fact that he flubbed another save he normally would make could have caused a less self-possessed goaltender to panic.</p>
        <p>Brodeur's save percentage after the first three games was .871, and the general consensus was that he was guilty of thinking too much about where the Lightning's leading goal scorer, Lecavalier, might put the puck instead of simply playing the puck.</p>
        <p>Would the goal by Perrin, who had never scored in 15 previous playoff games, be another loose thread in the unraveling of Brodeur, the Devils' security blanket? Before any such thought could creep into the Devils' minds, Parise redirected the spotlight with his fifth goal of the postseason.</p>
        <p>It came 2:12 after Perrin's score, on a tick-tack-toe play from Zajac to Paul Martin to Parise, who tipped it past Holmqvist. Parise, whose line accounted for 12 of the Devils' 22 shots in the first two periods, scored a power-play goal in the 10th minute of the second to extend the Devils' lead.</p>
        <p>In the overtime period, ''We were all over them, getting great chances,'' Parise said, adding, ''We worked hard to create our own chances. I think that was the difference.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
