<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Evolutions and Mutations of a Knob-Tweaking Guitarist</title>
    <meta content="19torn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/arts/music/19torn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Berne, Tim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2DA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Evolutions and Mutations of a Knob-Tweaking Guitarist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Evolutions and Mutations of a Knob-Tweaking Guitarist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE CHINEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chinen, Nate</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Torn is a guitarist, composer and producer, though the word order may depend on whom you consult. His career, stretching back more than 30 years, could easily be the work of several different people. He has carved a niche at the extreme end of guitar culture, while working extensively (and successfully) in film and commercial music. To call him a hero of the electric avant-garde would be accurate but incomplete.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday night Mr. Torn made a relatively rare appearance at Joe's Pub in celebration of ''Prezens,'' his new album on ECM. The show was sold out, and the house was suitably well stocked with guitarists. The stage was well stocked too, with an intimidating assemblage of amplifiers, electronics and what looked like a dozen effects pedals. At first glance it seemed clear which of Mr. Torn's identities would take center stage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Disruption served as a compositional device throughout Mr. Torn’s set at Joe’s Pub.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Torn is a guitarist, composer and producer, though the word order may depend on whom you consult. His career, stretching back more than 30 years, could easily be the work of several different people. He has carved a niche at the extreme end of guitar culture, while working extensively (and successfully) in film and commercial music. To call him a hero of the electric avant-garde would be accurate but incomplete.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday night Mr. Torn made a relatively rare appearance at Joe's Pub in celebration of ''Prezens,'' his new album on ECM. The show was sold out, and the house was suitably well stocked with guitarists. The stage was well stocked too, with an intimidating assemblage of amplifiers, electronics and what looked like a dozen effects pedals. At first glance it seemed clear which of Mr. Torn's identities would take center stage.</p>
        <p>Performing with Mr. Torn were the alto saxophonist Tim Berne, the keyboardist Craig Taborn and the drummer Tom Rainey; in another context they have a collective identity as Hard Cell, working mainly with the corkscrew compositions of Mr. Berne. But at Joe's Pub, as on ''Prezens,'' they submitted to Mr. Torn's sonic designs, which evolved, or perhaps just mutated, over the course of an hourlong group improvisation.</p>
        <p>Disruption served as a compositional device throughout the set, which began with a rhythmic repetition by Mr. Taborn and some clucking sounds by Mr. Berne. Out of nowhere a broken beat exploded into being: Mr. Rainey's entrance. Then the beat halted, just as abruptly. Into the expectant quiet Mr. Berne played a six-note saxophone pattern, which Mr. Torn electronically sampled, setting up a jagged funk groove.</p>
        <p>Mr. Torn generated a precise scrum of feedback and oceanic noise, making expressive use of the tremolo arm on his guitar. When Mr. Taborn insinuated a new underlying pulse with his Fender Rhodes piano -- a slow-burn vamp in 14/8 meter -- Mr. Torn shifted more toward static. With one hand tweaking knobs on a console and one foot glued to a pedal, he seemed like a hybrid: the guitarist-as-producer, with the instrument serving as an interface.</p>
        <p>''Prezens,'' Mr. Torn's first ECM album since ''Cloud About Mercury'' about 20 years ago, proposes a more radical mediation. Though it began as a series of free improvisations, Mr. Torn filtered and fractured the results, producing an ambitious compositional collage.</p>
        <p>''It's incredible,'' Mr. Berne said of the album, in his role as onstage spokesman on Tuesday night. ''It's probably better than this,'' he added with a chuckle, before the band plunged into action. He wasn't serious or right, exactly, but on some level he had a point.</p>
        <p>David Torn performs on May 18 at Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762 or tealoungeny.com.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
