<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Prosecutor's Ouster Central to Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="19attorneys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841371"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EED91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Prosecutor's Ouster Central to Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON; David Johnston contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales takes the witness chair on Thursday before the Senate Judiciary Committee, the dismissal of the United States attorney from New Mexico will be a topic of particular scrutiny, committee members and their staff said.</p>
        <p>That case, perhaps more than any of the other ousters, demonstrates the interaction of the Republican Party, the White House, a prominent Republican senator and Mr. Gonzales that led up to the firings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales takes the witness chair on Thursday before the Senate Judiciary Committee, the dismissal of the United States attorney from New Mexico will be a topic of particular scrutiny, committee members and their staff said.</p>
        <p>That case, perhaps more than any of the other ousters, demonstrates the interaction of the Republican Party, the White House, a prominent Republican senator and Mr. Gonzales that led up to the firings.</p>
        <p>Investigators have already determined that Mr. Gonzales spoke directly three times with Senator Pete V. Domenici, Republican of New Mexico, about his complaints regarding David C. Iglesias, the state's former top federal prosecutor.</p>
        <p>Administration officials have confirmed that Mr. Gonzales also spoke with President Bush and Karl Rove, the president's chief political adviser, about the perceived lack of enthusiasm in Mr. Iglesias's office, among others, for prosecuting voting fraud cases, a top Republican Party priority. And investigators know that Mr. Iglesias's name was among the last to be added to the ouster list.</p>
        <p>''On what precise date, why and by whom was Mr. Iglesias placed on the list of U.S. attorneys to be fired?'' asked Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, in a list of questions he has presented to Mr. Gonzales.</p>
        <p>Judiciary Committee staff members said Wednesday that given the repeated instances in which Mr. Gonzales was directly involved in discussions related to Mr. Iglesias, it might be hard for the attorney general to refuse to testify about these discussions or any follow-up conversations or to deny any recollection of them.</p>
        <p>The attorney general's appearance is regarded by lawmakers in both parties, by White House officials and by his own aides as the most important of his public life, with his job as the country's chief legal officer hanging in the balance.</p>
        <p>''His credibility is going to be an issue which is very much front and center,'' Senator Arlen Specter, Republican of Pennsylvania, said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>There will also be no shortage of questions about the seven other prosecutors who lost their jobs, particularly Carol C. Lam, the former United States attorney in San Diego, who was involved in the corruption investigation of former Representative Randy Cunningham, a Republican who was sentenced to prison.</p>
        <p>Senator Richard J. Durbin, Democrat of Illinois, said Wednesday that he would also push to understand why at least one Justice Department official considered, even if only briefly, dismissing Patrick J. Fitzgerald, the United States attorney in Chicago, who led the prosecution of I. Lewis Libby Jr., Vice President Dick Cheney's former chief of staff.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Mr. Gonzales has carefully shifted his public remarks from at first denying that he was involved in any discussions related to the ousters to acknowledging that he had misspoke and that he might have participated in several conversations or meetings.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Gonzales frequently says he cannot recall details of these discussions.</p>
        <p>That includes an October 2006 conversation that, according to the White House, Mr. Gonzales had with President Bush about voting fraud matters in New Mexico and two other states, and a request for the dismissal of Mr. Iglesias that Mr. Domenici reportedly made.</p>
        <p>Some Senate Judiciary Committee members have already protested the attorney general's claims of faulty recollection, particularly because his former chief of staff, D. Kyle Sampson, has told Senate investigators that he spoke with the attorney general late last year about the concerns President Bush had raised with him regarding Mr. Iglesias.</p>
        <p>''If he has nothing to hide, why is the attorney general parsing words and using lawyerly language to evade questions?'' Mr. Schumer said at a news conference Wednesday. ''Tomorrow, we need clear answers, not clever dodges.''</p>
        <p>The Senate hearing occurs as House investigators are continuing to push the Justice Department to provide access to a long list of department officials for interviews, including Mr. Iglesias's former deputy, Larry Gomez, now the acting United States attorney in New Mexico.</p>
        <p>The House committee on Wednesday also released a letter it said it had received anonymously from Justice Department employees in which they complain about a partisan bias they said exists in hiring law school students or young lawyers for summer internships or new jobs.</p>
        <p>The letter says senior aides to Mr. Gonzales removed from consideration any candidates who ''had interned for a Hill Democrat, clerked for a Democratic judge, worked for a 'liberal' cause or otherwise appeared to have 'liberal' leanings.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Specter repeated Wednesday that the testimony will be a ''make or break'' moment for the attorney general, a point that several Democrats echoed.</p>
        <p>''Attorney General Gonzales comes to this hearing with a burden of proof,'' Mr. Durbin said. ''He has been caught in repeated inconsistencies, he has misled the Judiciary Committee and the public about this role and I am not sure that he can salvage his reputation. But he has the burden to go forward. And ignorance is no excuse.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
