<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Low-Crime Japan Seeks Answers to Killing of Mayor of Nagasaki</title>
    <meta content="19japan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/world/asia/19japan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5D91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Low-Crime Japan Seeks Answers to Killing of Mayor of Nagasaki</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Low-Crime Japan Seeks Answers to Killing of Mayor of Nagasaki</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN FACKLER</byline>
      <dateline>NAGASAKI, Japan, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japan, a nation that prides itself on low crime rates, was searching for answers on Wednesday in the death of this southern Japanese city's mayor in a murky gang-related killing.</p>
        <p>The mayor, Kazunaga Ito, 61, who used the name Itcho Ito in public life, was shot twice in the back on Tuesday night on a sidewalk here after a campaign speech, said Hirozumi Chiyoda, a spokesman for the Nagasaki prefecture police. He died hours later in a local hospital from blood loss, Mr. Chiyoda said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Residents were left wondering whether the killing of the mayor was a simple crime, or politically motivated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japan, a nation that prides itself on low crime rates, was searching for answers on Wednesday in the death of this southern Japanese city's mayor in a murky gang-related killing.</p>
        <p>The mayor, Kazunaga Ito, 61, who used the name Itcho Ito in public life, was shot twice in the back on Tuesday night on a sidewalk here after a campaign speech, said Hirozumi Chiyoda, a spokesman for the Nagasaki prefecture police. He died hours later in a local hospital from blood loss, Mr. Chiyoda said.</p>
        <p>The police have identified the killer as Tetsuya Shiroo, 59, a member of Japan's largest organized crime group, the Yamaguchi-gumi. Mr. Shiroo was detained at the scene by members of Mr. Ito's campaign staff, and is in police custody, Mr. Chiyoda said.</p>
        <p>Such brazen acts of violence are rare in Japan, where the killing dominated local news coverage. Nagasaki residents were left wondering whether the killing of the mayor was a simple crime, or politically motivated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chiyoda would not comment on a possible motive, but local news media reports have quoted unnamed police officials as saying Mr. Shiroo had confessed to the shooting, saying he was angry with the city over its handling of a traffic accident four years ago. However, the amount involved was reportedly small -- only about $1,000, according to some reports -- leaving many who knew Mr. Ito wondering if the killer had a stronger motive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ito, who was born in Nagasaki two weeks after the United States dropped an atomic bomb there in 1945, was an outspoken critic of nuclear weapons. He also said that convicted war criminals should not be honored at Yasukuni Shrine, a Tokyo war memorial to Japanese war dead, including war criminals of World War II.</p>
        <p>The shrine is popular with the far right in Japan. Rightists, many with links to organized crime, have a history of attacking left-leaning politicians, particularly those who speak against Yasukuni and the Imperial family.</p>
        <p>In 1990, Hitoshi Motoshima, then the mayor of Nagasaki, was wounded by gunfire after saying Emperor Hirohito, Japan's emperor during World War II, bore some responsibility for the war.</p>
        <p>''My honest belief is that crime happened because Mayor Ito probably went too far in his peace activism,'' said Hirotami Yamada, secretary general of the Nagasaki Council of A-bomb Sufferers, which opposes nuclear weapons. ''Why would someone who is near 60 do something like this because of a mere 100,000 yen?'' Some in Japan fear that political violence, aimed at silencing opponents of the right, may be increasing here.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, a former member of a right-wing group was arrested in Tokyo on suspicion of throwing a homemade firebomb at the offices of Nihon Keizai Shimbun, the largest financial daily in Japan. The attack occurred last July after the newspaper reported on documents that showed Emperor Hirohito had disapproved of the enshrinement of war criminals at Yasukuni.</p>
        <p>In Nagasaki on Wednesday, television images showed citizens lining up at a city office to honor the mayor. In Tokyo, Prime Minister Shinzo Abe denounced the killing as ''a challenge to democracy,'' and said he wanted a thorough investigation.</p>
        <p>The crime is of particular note because homicides, particularly those involving guns, are still rare in Japan. While crime rates have crept up since the 1990s, Japan remains one of the safest countries. Crime experts have attributed this to its stringent gun controls, and its relatively close-knit social fabric.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
