<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chrysler Plans to Build Engine and Axle Plants in Southern Michigan</title>
    <meta content="19chrysler" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/automobiles/19chrysler.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Michigan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Chrysler Group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6D71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chrysler Plans to Build Engine and Axle Plants in Southern Michigan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chrysler Plans to Build Engine and Axle Plants in Southern Michigan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK BUNKLEY</byline>
      <dateline>AUBURN HILLS, Mich., April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chrysler Group said on Wednesday that it would spend $1.43 billion to build two plants in southern Michigan that would make parts for Chrysler and Mercedes vehicles, even as the American and German companies prepare for a possible divorce.</p>
        <p>Although Chrysler, the State of Michigan and the United Automobile Workers union all praised the investment, the new factories -- an engine plant southwest of Detroit and an axle plant northeast of the city -- are expected to employ about 1,815 fewer workers than the ones they will replace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The automaker said it would spend $1.43 billion to build two plants, even as the U.S. and German companies prepare for a possible divorce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chrysler Group said on Wednesday that it would spend $1.43 billion to build two plants in southern Michigan that would make parts for Chrysler and Mercedes vehicles, even as the American and German companies prepare for a possible divorce.</p>
        <p>Although Chrysler, the State of Michigan and the United Automobile Workers union all praised the investment, the new factories -- an engine plant southwest of Detroit and an axle plant northeast of the city -- are expected to employ about 1,815 fewer workers than the ones they will replace.</p>
        <p>Many of the losses are on top of 13,000 job cuts announced in February as part of Chrysler's overhaul program, its second such plan in seven years.</p>
        <p>The development comes as Chrysler's parent, DaimlerChrysler, said it was keeping all options open for Chrysler, including a sale. Discussions with potential bidders are said to be moving slowly. And the U.A.W.'s president, Ron Gettelfinger, repeated Wednesday that the union would prefer the company remain part of DaimlerChrysler.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that Chrysler's new owner could scrap plans for the plants, depending on whether Chrysler is able to bounce back from $1.5 billion in losses last year.</p>
        <p>Still, Chrysler's chief executive, Thomas W. LaSorda, insisted Wednesday that construction would begin soon, saying the automaker would be wrong to wait until its fate was determined. The plants being replaced are aging -- one was built in 1917 -- and inefficient, he said.</p>
        <p>''We can't just look forward expecting something to happen,'' Mr. LaSorda said. ''We must continue to run this ship and make decisions.''</p>
        <p>The axle and engine plants are the largest pieces of a $1.78 billion investment in southeast Michigan that Chrysler detailed Wednesday. The company also plans to modernize two assembly plants in suburban Detroit.</p>
        <p>In February, Mr. LaSorda pledged to spend $3 billion to develop new engines and transmissions within three years. Chrysler plans to introduce 20 vehicles in that same period, but does not expect to be profitable before 2009.</p>
        <p>Despite that, Mr. Gettelfinger said that the 1998 merger had ''worked well'' and created synergies that would be lost if the companies split up.</p>
        <p>He added, ''We just don't need the aggravation of going through whatever happens.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gettelfinger said he particularly opposed the sale of Chrysler to a private equity firm because he feared the company would be broken apart or radically changed. Two private equity firms, Cerberus Capital Management and the Blackstone Group, which is working with another equity firm, Centerbridge Capital, are in the running.</p>
        <p>The bidders also include a Canadian auto supplier, Magna International, and the billionaire investor Kirk Kerkorian. Mr. Kerkorian has proposed giving an equity stake in Chrysler to workers.</p>
        <p>A Chrysler sale could complicate this summer's scheduled talks between Detroit's automakers and the U.A.W. on a labor contract. Mr. LaSorda said that the uncertainty surrounding his company had not hindered preliminary discussions with the union.</p>
        <p>Despite the net loss of jobs, Michigan's governor, Jennifer M. Granholm, described Chrysler's plans as the largest investment in the state by a single company since she was elected five years ago.</p>
        <p>Ford Sells Glass Maker</p>
        <p>DETROIT, April 18 (Reuters) -- The Ford Motor Company said on Wednesday that it had reached a tentative deal to sell the glass-making operations it took back from its former subsidiary, Visteon.</p>
        <p>Ford said that it agreed to sell the glass-making unit, which employs about 1,600 workers, to Glass Products of Tulsa, Okla.</p>
        <p>Ford, which took back the unit in 2005, did not disclose the value of the sale, which comes as part of its own overhaul effort.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
