<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Given Breathing Room, Igawa Gets First Victory</title>
    <meta content="19yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/sports/baseball/19yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Igawa, Kei</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EED71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Given Breathing Room, Igawa Gets First Victory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Yankees’ Bats Give Igawa Breathing Room</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Technically, Kei Igawa is a major league rookie because his eight years of professional experience before this season were in Japan.</p>
        <p>So by pitching six innings last night in a 9-2 victory against the Cleveland Indians at Yankee Stadium, Igawa became the second Yankees rookie starter in two nights to gain his first major league victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>By pitching six innings Wednesday night, Kei Igawa became the second Yankees rookie starter in two nights to gain his first major league victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Technically, Kei Igawa is a major league rookie because his eight years of professional experience before this season were in Japan.</p>
        <p>So by pitching six innings last night in a 9-2 victory against the Cleveland Indians at Yankee Stadium, Igawa became the second Yankees rookie starter in two nights to gain his first major league victory.</p>
        <p>Chase Wright did it Tuesday night. Another rookie, Darrell Rasner, will close the series with the Indians this afternoon.</p>
        <p>''I'm a rookie, but I don't feel like a rookie,'' Igawa said through an interpreter. ''There are a lot of expectations.''</p>
        <p>Such are the tribulations of a wealthy, talented, veteran team with injury problems plaguing the starting pitchers. Igawa, 27, was obtained in the off-season for a $26 million posting fee and a four-year, $20 million contract. He gave up two runs on five hits to go with five strikeouts and one walk. He threw 62 strikes in 92 pitches.</p>
        <p>Igawa (1-0) now has as many victories as Boston's Daisuke Matsuzaka, a more-heralded acquisition from Japan who will face Wright on Sunday night at Fenway Park. Igawa had command of his changeup last night and used it effectively after getting ahead of hitters with first-pitch strikes.</p>
        <p>''My changeup was not as good in the first two outings,'' Igawa said. In those, he gave up 11 hits, 5 walks and 9 earned runs in 101/3 innings.</p>
        <p>Igawa's victory was fueled by a five-run, seven-hit third inning that erased a 2-1 deficit and put Indians starter Jeremy Sowers (0-1) out of the game. But the hits that most excited the crowd of 41,379 were back-to-back home runs in the sixth inning by Alex Rodriguez and Jason Giambi.</p>
        <p>''This team consists of the best lineup in the world,'' Igawa said of a lineup that had 14 hits, three by Derek Jeter. ''I'm happy to have that support.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez hit a two-run homer to left field, his ninth in 13 games, against Tom Mastny. Aaron Fultz replaced Mastny and gave up Giambi's home run to right, his third of the season. Giambi also doubled home the go-ahead run in the third.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez said of Igawa: ''He had a nice pace all night. His velocity was up. He's pitching with more control. He looked very comfortable.''</p>
        <p>The rest of the rotation is coming into focus for the three-game weekend series at Boston. The veteran left-hander Andy Pettitte will open tomorrow, followed by the rookies Jeff Karstens and Wright.</p>
        <p>Karstens, a 24-year-old right-hander who went 2-1 late last season, is recovering from right elbow tendinitis. He will join the team today for the flight to Boston and will be activated Saturday, Manager Joe Torre said.</p>
        <p>Wright, a 24-year-old left-hander, earned the second start of his major league career by working five innings in a 10-3 victory against the Indians. He came to the Stadium on Wednesday unaware of his immediate future and apparently did not learn that he would start Sunday until informed by reporters.</p>
        <p>''First I've heard of it,'' Wright said. When asked his reaction, he smiled and said: ''Excited. Good deal.''</p>
        <p>Catcher Jorge Posada said that he had to talk to Wright early in Tuesday's game to calm him down.</p>
        <p>''It seemed like he wasn't even breathing at times,'' Posada said.</p>
        <p>Three other starters -- Chien-Ming Wang, Mike Mussina and Carl Pavano -- are on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>Torre said that he hoped that Wang, who has a pulled right hamstring, would make his first start for the Yankees on Tuesday night against Tampa Bay. Mussina, who has a pulled left hamstring pull, can come off the disabled list April 27. Pavano can come back two days before that, but Torre said that Pavano's return from soreness in his arm was harder to predict than Mussina's and that Pavano had not thrown since being hurt.</p>
        <p>Should the veterans continue to ache or should the young pitchers falter, the Yankees could look to Phil Hughes, a 20-year-old right-hander who is considered their best pitching prospect. He threw six scoreless innings, allowing 2 hits with 10 strikeouts for Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre in a 4-0 victory against Syracuse last night.</p>
        <p>But Torre said Tuesday that Hughes might join the Yankees late in the season. If Igawa and the other rookies keep doing well, what's the rush?</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
