<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid the Chaos of Deaths, a Minister Attends to Those Who Are Grieving</title>
    <meta content="19grief" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/us/19grief.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0D81E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid the Chaos of Deaths, a Minister Attends to Those Who Are Grieving</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amid the Chaos of Deaths, a Minister Attends to Those Who Are Grieving</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last three days, the Rev. Alexander W. Evans has spent his time in a cluster of small meeting rooms on the second floor of the hotel and conference center at Virginia Tech, listening over and over to a shared lexicon of grief, spoken in so many different voices.</p>
        <p>''The reaction was the same: devastation, overwhelming pain,'' said Mr. Evans, who accompanied the Blacksburg and Virginia Tech police chiefs as they took families into private rooms to give them the news. ''That means crumbling to the floor, crying out, 'No, no! My baby! It can't be!' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rev. Alexander W. Evans has listened and spoken to those closest to the killings of the 32 Virginia Tech students and faculty members.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the last three days, the Rev. Alexander W. Evans has spent his time in a cluster of small meeting rooms on the second floor of the hotel and conference center at Virginia Tech, listening over and over to a shared lexicon of grief, spoken in so many different voices.</p>
        <p>''The reaction was the same: devastation, overwhelming pain,'' said Mr. Evans, who accompanied the Blacksburg and Virginia Tech police chiefs as they took families into private rooms to give them the news. ''That means crumbling to the floor, crying out, 'No, no! My baby! It can't be!' ''</p>
        <p>''You could hear it from outside the rooms, all around you,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The pastor of Blacksburg Presbyterian Church, Mr. Evans, 49, also serves as a Blacksburg Police Department chaplain. From the time he got a phone call from the police Monday morning, he has listened and spoken to those closest to the killings of the 32 Virginia Tech students and faculty members: the police officers who rushed into Norris Hall and found all but the two victims who had been shot dead about two hours earlier in a dormitory, and the families who now wait to take them home.</p>
        <p>''There is no way to prepare for this, to train for this,'' Mr. Evans said. ''It demands all of our compassion as human beings. It demands that we help each other through it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans's first assignment began Monday afternoon at the police command center next to Norris Hall, where only a few hours earlier a gunman, Cho Seung-Hui, had chained the doors shut before going from classroom to classroom, calmly shooting at everyone inside before putting the gun to his own head and pulling the trigger one last time.</p>
        <p>At the command center, Mr. Evans met the officers who had rushed to Norris and shot the locks from the chained doors to get inside. ''It means running into your most impossible fear,'' he said. ''It is facing evil and its result.''</p>
        <p>The police here, he said, are well-trained, but the chaos and agony they saw had exhausted them.</p>
        <p>''Several said they had never seen anything like this,'' Mr. Evans said. ''A number of them were dealing with the wounded, dragging them out of the building and racing them to the hospital in their own cars. They were repeating the cries of the students, they were telling me that the students were saying, 'I'm going to die, I'm going to die.' That's the kind of thing that keeps you up at night.''</p>
        <p>The youth of the victims has been ''at the core of the pain'' of many officers, Mr. Evans said. ''They could see their own kids, a roomful of kids.''</p>
        <p>On Monday night, after an impromptu prayer vigil at his church, Mr. Evans was called again, this time to work with other chaplains, counselors and administrators on the death notifications.</p>
        <p>Once the police notified one family member of a death, it fell to Mr. Evans to tell other relatives as they arrived at the center, the Inn at Virginia Tech. The first person he was with was the older sister of a young woman who was killed. The rest of her family arrived around midnight. One relative walked up to him and said, ''Do we know anything?''</p>
        <p>''And all I said was, 'Yes,' '' Mr. Evans said. ''And then they knew.''</p>
        <p>The dead were taken to the medical examiner's office in Roanoke, which is not set up to handle personal identifications of so many people, Mr. Evans said. Instead, the coroner's office used forensic evidence to confirm an identity. Only in a few instances were photos sent to the Inn so relatives could identify a victim. Sometimes one family member would view the photos, sometimes a group.</p>
        <p>''That was probably the most difficult,'' Mr. Evans said. ''The visual identification makes the reality that much more painful.''</p>
        <p>Now that all notifications have been made, he said, anger is growing among some families because they cannot claim their relatives from the coroner's office until autopsies are complete. Mr. Evans understands that anger, he said, just as he understands the need for a thorough investigation.</p>
        <p>Once the autopsies are complete, the victims will be released to funeral homes chosen by their families, and only then will relatives be able to see their loved ones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans said he hoped he had been able to show both the police officers and victims' relatives who are suffering that they were not alone and that they were not without God. ''I think God is crying with all those who are crying and giving encouragement to all those giving encouragement,'' he said, ''and urging us to find ways to make a safer, more peaceful society.''</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
