<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atomic Agency Confirms Advances by Iran's Nuclear Program</title>
    <meta content="19nukes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/world/middleeast/19nukes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iran</location>
        <org class="online_producer">International Atomic Energy Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ahmadinejad, Mahmoud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E3D91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atomic Agency Confirms Advances by Iran's Nuclear Program</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Atomic Agency Confirms Advances by Iran’s Nuclear Program</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iran has now begun enriching small amounts of uranium in more than 1,300 centrifuges at a newly opened underground site at its main nuclear complex, the International Atomic Energy Agency's top inspector said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The information, contained in a letter from the inspector to Iran, provided the first official confirmation of Iran's boast that the country had made significant technical progress in recent weeks, in defiance of United Nations' resolutions aimed at curbing the Iranian nuclear program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iran has begun enriching small amounts of uranium at a newly opened underground site at its main nuclear complex.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Iran has now begun enriching small amounts of uranium in more than 1,300 centrifuges at a newly opened underground site at its main nuclear complex, the International Atomic Energy Agency's top inspector said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The information, contained in a letter from the inspector to Iran, provided the first official confirmation of Iran's boast that the country had made significant technical progress in recent weeks, in defiance of United Nations' resolutions aimed at curbing the Iranian nuclear program.</p>
        <p>The details of Iran's progress that were spelled out in the letter, obtained through a European diplomat, lend some credence to Iran's contention that it will soon have installed 3,000 of the centrifuges, which can be used to provide nuclear fuel to power reactors, or can produce fuel for a weapon.</p>
        <p>If Iran can get that many centrifuges running, experts say, it could possibly produce enough fuel for a weapon within about a year. But so far there is no evidence that Iran is enriching the nuclear material at the level needed to produce a weapon, and American officials said the amount of fuel now being fed into the system was so small that it might simply indicate that the Iranians were trying a test run with the delicate machinery.</p>
        <p>In the past, Iran has had tremendous difficulty keeping all the machines spinning together in what is known as a cascade, a process that results in enriched uranium.</p>
        <p>The confirmation came in a confidential letter sent by the agency's deputy director general and its chief inspector, Olli Heinonen, to a top Iranian official complaining that inspectors had not been given sufficient access to some Iranian facilities.</p>
        <p>By moving forward with the assembly of the centrifuges, the Iranian government is in a contest of wills with the United Nations Security Council, which has demanded full suspension of the enrichment program. This month, President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad warned that if the West did not end pressure on Iran to halt uranium production, Iran would consider halting cooperation with the agency. He said that the West ''should know that the Iranian nation will defend its right and that this path is irreversible.''</p>
        <p>In private, some American officials say Iran's hand may be strengthened by its calculation that, with the United States distracted across the border in Iraq, Mr. Bush has no stomach for a confrontation. White House officials say that is a misreading of Mr. Bush's mind, and that the United States plans to increase gradually the severity of sanctions against Iran, in the hope that it will prompt pressure on Mr. Ahmadinejad and other hard-liners in the government.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday evening, Gordon Johndroe, the spokesman for the National Security Council, said that ''the I.A.E.A.'s letter to Iran shows the Iranian government continues to defy the international community.''</p>
        <p>''The letter also indicates that Iran is obstructing the I.A.E.A.'s inspection requests,'' Mr. Johndroe added. ''While the government of Iran sees this as an advance, this is unfortunately a step backward for the Iranian people.''</p>
        <p>He added that ''Iran looks like it may be headed for additional resolutions'' at the United Nations.</p>
        <p>The Security Council announced a new set of sanctions in March, and gave Iran 60 days to comply. But at the speed at which Iran's workers are installing centrifuges, diplomats and outside experts say, it is possible that Iran will have many more cascades operating by the time the agency is supposed to issue its next report on the status of the Iranian effort, in late May.</p>
        <p>Iran's decision to deploy the centrifuges appears to be a victory, at least for now, for hard-liners in the government who have warned that to suspend uranium enrichment would be a surrender to the United States and Europe. But American officials have been hoping to use each Iranian announcement to prompt Russia and China, which have been most resistant to severe sanctions, to agree to a series of tougher resolutions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
