<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Governors, A Temptation To Go Faster</title>
    <meta content="19corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/nyregion/19corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5D71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Governors, A Temptation To Go Faster</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Governors, a Temptation to Go Faster</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI and RONALD SMOTHERS; Reporting was contributed by Ken Belson and Diane Cardwell from New York, Danny Hakim from Albany, and Nate Schweber from Camden, N.J.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cardwell, Diane; Smothers, Ronald; Hakim, Danny; Kocieniewski, David; Schweber, Nate; Belson, Ken</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is always another hand to shake, delaying departures. Constituents or colleagues waiting at the next stop to have their photos taken or questions answered. Too many meetings squeezed into too few hours.</p>
        <p>So despite guidelines reserving flashing lights and high speed for emergencies, former governors and others who frequently rode in their motorcades said it was hardly unusual in this state of 2,835 highway miles for them to race as fast as 91 miles per hour, as Gov. Jon S. Corzine's sport utility vehicle was doing en route to a meeting Thursday night when it had a devastating crash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former New Jersey governors said it was hardly unusual for them to race as fast as 91 miles per hour, as Gov. Jon S. Corzine’s vehicle was doing when it crashed on the way to a meeting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is always another hand to shake, delaying departures. Constituents or colleagues waiting at the next stop to have their photos taken or questions answered. Too many meetings squeezed into too few hours.</p>
        <p>So despite guidelines reserving flashing lights and high speed for emergencies, former governors and others who frequently rode in their motorcades said it was hardly unusual in this state of 2,835 highway miles for them to race as fast as 91 miles per hour, as Gov. Jon S. Corzine's sport utility vehicle was doing en route to a meeting Thursday night when it had a devastating crash.</p>
        <p>''It happened all the time,'' recalled Pete McDonough, who traveled frequently with Gov. Christie Whitman as her press secretary for six years. ''How fast? I don't know, but it was always faster than the pace of traffic.'' With enormous pressure to stay on schedule competing with ''that guy at the Elks Club who wants you to stop for 30 minutes that turns into 45 minutes,'' Mr. McDonough said, speeding with the governor's entourage was ''just part of the culture.''</p>
        <p>Former Gov. Thomas H. Kean said that the troopers who drove him were so eager to please that he had to be careful not to inadvertently spur them on. ''Never make the mistake of telling them 'I'm late, hurry up,' '' he warned. ''I did that once, and I remember seeing it hover around 80 miles per hour and then telling them to slow down.''</p>
        <p>Though the state police superintendent, Col. Joseph R. Fuentes, originally said speed was not a factor in the accident that broke more than a dozen bones in Mr. Corzine's body, it now seems clear that the S.U.V.'s speed and its use of emergency lights startled other drivers and were significant factors in causing the crash and in its severity. Mr. Fuentes has asked an independent panel to review the accident to determine whether the trooper who was driving, Robert J. Rasinski, should face disciplinary action or a traffic citation, and whether the state police's executive protection unit should adjust its training.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rasinski, who has been the driver in four previous accidents -- two while on duty -- has told colleagues that as the governor's vehicle spun off the road, where it slammed into a guardrail, he tried to steer it to shield Mr. Corzine from the impact.</p>
        <p>''He told me that he thought he was going to die,'' David Jones, head of the state troopers' union, said of Mr. Rasinski.</p>
        <p>Because drivers in the executive protection unit are responsible for both transporting and safeguarding the governor, they receive training from the United States Secret Service; but unlike Secret Service agents, who routinely close roads along the route of a presidential motorcade, the governor's drivers often find themselves navigating through traffic on New Jersey's notoriously clogged highways.</p>
        <p>Colonel Fuentes said troopers are required to travel the speed limit and obey all traffic laws, except in an emergency, but are also instructed not to leave the governor ''bogged down'' in traffic, where he could be vulnerable to an attack, and are given the discretion to speed or use flashing lights to escape jams.</p>
        <p>Capt. Al Della Fave, a spokesman for the state police, said security concerns prevented him from disclosing how many troopers are assigned to the protection unit and discussing its training and procedures, saying the manual is so confidential that even he has not seen it.</p>
        <p>But traffic safety advocates said it is incomprehensible that New Jersey, a state with 10 pages of regulations outlining when police may use their cars to chase fleeing criminals, would allow troopers to routinely flout the law to keep the governor from falling behind schedule. Current and former elected officials with their own motorcades also said they were surprised both by the leeway given to Mr. Corzine's chauffeurs and by the governor's decision not to wear a seat belt.</p>
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg of New York said that on Wednesday morning he put up a sign in the back of his city car that reads ''Please fasten your seat belt.'' Mr. Bloomberg said that he had forbidden the police detectives who drive him to use lights and sirens without asking him, and that he rarely allowed it.</p>
        <p>''I don't think an elected official that wants to get to someplace for a photo op is appropriate,'' he said. ''When I go to visit a fire or watch a fire I've certainly not had lights and sirens. I'm not a firefighter. I can't put out the fire.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Jones, president of the New Jersey State Troopers Fraternal Association, brushed aside criticism of the state's policy, saying that it until last week it had functioned effectively since 1921.</p>
        <p>He said it was essential for the governor's drivers to speed and use emergency lights to create a buffer zone between Mr. Corzine's vehicle and other cars.</p>
        <p>''You can't allow yourself to be boxed in, paralleled or overtaken,'' Mr. Jones said. ''That's Executive Protection 101.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rasinski, 34, who has been among Mr. Corzine's drivers for the past year, has told state police investigators that the governor never instructed him to speed, according to a report released on Wednesday. Heavy rain forced Mr. Corzine to scrub plans to use a helicopter on Thursday as he raced from a 10 a.m. funeral in Pottstown, Pa., for a slain F.B.I. agent, to a noon appearance 120 miles northeast in Hackensack, N.J., then 130 miles south to Atlantic City for events at 2 and 2:45, before returning 90 miles northwest to Drumthwacket, the governor's mansion in Princeton.</p>
        <p>The accident happened on the Garden State Parkway, five miles north of the Atlantic City Expressway, about 6:15 p.m., as Mr. Corzine's two-car caravan was running late for the Drumthwacket meeting between the Rutgers women's basketball team and Don Imus, the talk-radio host who had made a racist and sexist comment about the players on the air.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine remained in critical but stable condition at Cooper University Hospital in Camden on Wednesday, relying on a ventilator for the sixth full day. He broke his thigh bone, collar bone, sternum, a vertebra and 11 ribs in the crash and is heavily sedated. Dr. Steven E. Ross, Cooper's head of trauma, said that on Wednesday doctors inserted two catheters into Mr. Corzine's back to deliver pain medication more directly to his ribs in the hopes of removing the breathing tube within a few days.</p>
        <p>''But it could be longer,'' Dr. Ross warned.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael E. Goldberg, chief of the anesthesiology department at Cooper, said the catheters would deliver Bupivacaine, a local anesthetic, and that they were inserted far enough from his spine to avoid risking nerve damage from internal bleeding, a serious concern because Mr. Corzine is on blood thinners. He said the anesthetic would not affect Mr. Corzine's brain, adding, ''It won't impair his breathing, only the pain.'' The catheters are likely to remain for at least five days.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ross said that while Mr. Corzine still could not speak because of the breathing tube in his mouth, he ''understands several things about his care'' and can move his hands and feet when asked.</p>
        <p>''He's doing far better than any of us would have expected,'' Dr. Ross said. ''He's just in a lot of pain.''</p>
        <p>State police records show that Trooper Rasinski has never been ticketed, despite his four previous car accidents. In 2004, he was parked and operating a radar gun in Newark when a tractor-trailer hit his vehicle. The year before, he was behind the wheel of a state police car that slid on icy pavement and hit a guardrail; the accident caused no injuries, but a state police review found that it could have been prevented.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's attorney general, Stuart Rabner, is now reviewing the crash involving Mr. Corzine and the executive protection unit's procedures. In interviews Wednesday, several former governors suggested that the state avoid putting troopers in a difficult position by allowing more use of helicopters.</p>
        <p>Former Gov. Jim Florio, who ran the state from 1990 to 1994, said that he occasionally relied on the state helicopter when his schedule was hectic, but was criticized for that practice by Mrs. Whitman in her successful campaign to unseat him.</p>
        <p>''The governor is the C.E.O. of a $33-billion-a-year enterprise, and it is silly to utilize his time traveling by car,'' Mr. Florio said. ''I know it sounds undemocratic, but the use of the governor's time cries out for more efficiency. The roads are getting more clogged.''</p>
        <p>Brendan T. Byrne, who was governor from 1974 to 1982, said the flights also had the benefit of being ''a crowd pleaser,'' recalling that ''people remember my landing in the town square, and there was a kind of pageantry about it.''</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Whitman said there was value in a governor experiencing the same traffic headaches as constituents.</p>
        <p>''It's what people of the state face every day,'' she said, ''and the governor should face that also.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
