<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Korean-Americans Brace for Problems in Wake of Killings</title>
    <meta content="19korea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/us/19korea.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Korean-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0D81E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Korean-Americans Brace for Problems in Wake of Killings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Korean-Americans Brace for Problems in Wake of Killings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An unidentified man called into a show on Radio Korea here to say that his young son had been spat on by two students at school, said Charles Kim, executive director of the local Korean-American Coalition, who was a guest on the show.</p>
        <p>Soojin Lyuh, 25, a graduate student at the University of Southern California, was advised by relatives in Korea to ''stay home as much as possible and to not tell anyone that I was Korean.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Koreans around the country have watched the events in Virginia unfold with particular unease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An unidentified man called into a show on Radio Korea here to say that his young son had been spat on by two students at school, said Charles Kim, executive director of the local Korean-American Coalition, who was a guest on the show.</p>
        <p>Soojin Lyuh, 25, a graduate student at the University of Southern California, was advised by relatives in Korea to ''stay home as much as possible and to not tell anyone that I was Korean.''</p>
        <p>For Junette Kim, 27, the images of Koreans standing with shotguns in front of their shops during riots in Los Angeles over a decade ago here are indelible, like the memories of her parents frantically closing their restaurant and collecting her early from school. ''We're worried a lot about Koreans being harassed now,'' she said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Across the nation, Koreans have braced for harassment in the wake of the Monday shooting rampage on the Virginia Tech campus that left 33 dead, including Cho Seung-Hui, the South Korean-born gunman.</p>
        <p>Fearful of the backlash that Arab-Americans and others encountered after the Sept. 11 attacks and disquieted by what many Koreans interviewed perceive to be ominous portrayals of their culture -- the stereotypical Asian loner becomes a killer -- Koreans around the country have watched the events in Virginia unfold with particular unease.</p>
        <p>In South Korea, political and religious leaders issued messages of condolence for the victims. President Roh Moo-hyun called his shock ''beyond description.''</p>
        <p>Policy makers worried about the potential impact of the killings on relations with the United States and, more immediately, on Seoul's efforts to win Congressional support for waiving visas for thousands of South Koreans traveling to the United States each year.</p>
        <p>Fears are particularly acute here in Los Angeles, home to roughly half a million people of Korean descent, many with deep and painful memories of the 1992 riots that brought down more than 2,000 Korean businesses and exposed deep fissures between Koreans and other minority groups.</p>
        <p>''The Korean-American community is really concerned,'' said Kyeyoung Park, an associate professor of anthropology and faculty member of the Center for Korean Studies at the University of California, Los Angeles. ''Particularly here, where the Korean-American was scapegoated in 1992 civil unrest,'' she said, referring to the violence here that followed a deadly confrontation between a Korean store owner and a black teenager.</p>
        <p>In cities with large Korean populations, a refrain with recurring themes could be heard this week. ''The first thing I thought was please, please don't let him be Korean,'' said Chong Duk Chung, 47, who works in a beauty salon in New York. ''As a member of the Korean-American community, I'm a little embarrassed and a little ashamed,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Joseph Park, 65, a resident of Alexandria, Va., echoed that view.</p>
        <p>''As a Korean, I apologize,'' said Mr. Park, who was visiting Flushing, Queens, on a business trip. ''I feel I need to apologize because innocent people were killed by someone from my same nation.</p>
        <p>''Everyone feels so sorry for what happened, so sorry about it. They're scared. They're shocked, shocked to death. When the news media said it was an Asian, we prayed, we prayed, 'Not Korean, not Korean.' ''</p>
        <p>In Chantilly, Va., Sung Han Kim, 36, said his friends have agreed that they should probably avoid bars dominated by whites ''because people are more likely to point out you are Korean.''</p>
        <p>Peter Chin, the pastor of Open Door Presbyterian Church in Herndon, Va. -- roughly five miles from the home of Mr. Cho's family -- said he had received reports of hateful comments aimed at Koreans being posted on Facebook and various blog sites.</p>
        <p>Professor Park in Los Angeles said she was troubled that Mr. Cho's ethnicity had quickly become central to the narrative of his crime. ''Calling him a South Korean native, as if he arrived yesterday, doesn't make sense to me,'' she said of Mr. Cho, who arrived in the United States with his parents at age 8.</p>
        <p>''If the person arrived yesterday or last year, he is not familiar with this kind of guns,'' Professor Park said. ''A person who majored in English -- a newly arrived student is not majoring in English. Whatever characterization about the young man as a loner and antisocial fits the stereotype about Asian-American men, when in fact this person seems like a psycho.''</p>
        <p>Yul Kwon, 32, of San Mateo, Calif., winner of last year's television contest ''Survivor'' and a lawyer, raised a similar concern.</p>
        <p>''One of the reasons I went on a reality show is that I wanted to change stereotypes about Asians, and particularly Asian-American men,'' Mr. Kwon said. ''The fear is this will perpetuate that Asian-American men are socially maladjusted.''</p>
        <p>The shooting at Virginia Tech, which the police now say was a heinous coda to a pattern of disturbing behavior on the part of the gunman, has also highlighted what some mental health and Asian studies experts say is the cultural reluctance of Koreans and other Asians to seek mental health care here.</p>
        <p>A recent national study financed by the National Institute of Mental Health found that Asian-Americans are less likely to seek care for mental health problems than other groups. The study, which sampled 2,095 Asian-Americans of various backgrounds, concluded that Asians born in the United States and those who immigrated as children had higher rates of mental disorders, especially depression, than Asians who immigrated to the United States as adults.</p>
        <p>''Korean culture does not recognize mental illness,'' said Professor Park, the anthropologist. ''People do not recognize it or get help. There is a huge stigma.''</p>
        <p>Roughly two million ethnic Koreans live in the United States, where Korean emigration gained momentum with the adoption of thousands of war orphans after the Korean War.</p>
        <p>Today, thousands of South Koreans send their children to the United States each year, or move as families, to help them learn English and benefit from an education away from what they see as their home country's overly competitive, overpriced school system. The nation takes exceptional pride in Koreans who have become successful in the United States.</p>
        <p>An estimated 93,000 South Koreans are enrolled in colleges and universities in the United States, forming one of the largest foreign student communities, with about 460 South Korean students reportedly enrolled at Virginia Tech alone.</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
