<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Lunching, The Ladies Go Shopping</title>
    <meta content="19CRITIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/fashion/19CRITIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CRITICAL SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Upper East Side (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4DA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Lunching, The Ladies Go Shopping</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Lunching, the Ladies Go Shopping</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Zarah Crawford</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crawford, Zarah</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''WE had Passover with all the grandchildren, which was fabulous,'' the woman in pearls said. She had just finished her shift in the designer room at the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center Thrift Shop and was filling in the next volunteer, a slight, silver-coiffed woman wearing Ferragamo pumps. ''You're not allowed to eat bread at Passover, are you?'' her friend asked in tones that recalled Katharine Hepburn. ''No,'' the first woman said. The silver-haired woman thought for a moment. ''What about muffins?''</p>
        <p>Located at the back of this most genteel Upper East Side charity shop, past the alligator bags, upholstered sofas and preloved tuxedos, the designer room is a shoe-box-size repository for the choicest women's wear, culled from the thousands of items donated every week, and sold at prices slightly higher than the average thrift outlet but still lower than most vintage stores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many of the pieces displayed at the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center Thrift Shop are not just secondhand clothes but the storied and strangely intimate artifacts of generations of the ladies who lunch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''WE had Passover with all the grandchildren, which was fabulous,'' the woman in pearls said. She had just finished her shift in the designer room at the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center Thrift Shop and was filling in the next volunteer, a slight, silver-coiffed woman wearing Ferragamo pumps. ''You're not allowed to eat bread at Passover, are you?'' her friend asked in tones that recalled Katharine Hepburn. ''No,'' the first woman said. The silver-haired woman thought for a moment. ''What about muffins?''</p>
        <p>Located at the back of this most genteel Upper East Side charity shop, past the alligator bags, upholstered sofas and preloved tuxedos, the designer room is a shoe-box-size repository for the choicest women's wear, culled from the thousands of items donated every week, and sold at prices slightly higher than the average thrift outlet but still lower than most vintage stores.</p>
        <p>Because the cancer center has over the years included among its supporters some of the city's wealthiest and most socially prominent women, many of the pieces displayed here are not just secondhand clothes but the storied and strangely intimate artifacts of generations of the ladies who lunch.</p>
        <p>In fact, before her death in 2005, one of those women, Nan Kempner, whose extensive wardrobe was the recent subject of an exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum, bequeathed Memorial Sloan-Kettering the entire contents of her closets. Although a date is yet to be decided, this collection, filling some 25 storage crates, will eventually be sold through the store.</p>
        <p>Because the clothing in it has been ''presorted,'' the designer room offers a perfect initiation for the novice thrifter lacking the confidence, and perhaps the stomach, to comb through the crammed standard-issue. Yet the editing process remains idiosyncratic enough to ensure that old hands will not feel deprived of sport. For instance, I saw a drab and crumpled Louis Féraud linen coat ($95) hanging happily alongside a museum quality '60s Arnold Scaasi cocktail dress ($150) in the most sublime emerald shantung.</p>
        <p>And possibly because of the store's location, some labels appear to be more at a premium than others, Chanel being the most prized of all. ''We can't keep Chanel in the store,'' the silver-haired saleslady informed me as I examined a cropped Chanel jacket in stretchy white rayon ($450). ''Our ladies just love those buttons, you know?''</p>
        <p>Indeed, I witnessed firsthand the seductive power of the little interlocking C's. Despite the fact that this jacket was overpriced, of distinctly démodé cut and in a fabric that was oddly greasy to the touch, every second woman who came into the Designer Room tried it on.</p>
        <p>IN comparison, an '80s black Karl Lagerfeld suit with a hobble skirt and peplum hacking jacket ($150) was a great buy, and I might have taken it home if its snug fit had not rendered all movement impossible. More heartbreaking still was the curvaceous and collectible Thierry Mugler white piqué suit with polka-dot trim, priced way below its true value at $150; it obstinately refused to button. My luck finally changed with a classic Yves Saint Laurent satin-lapel smoking jacket, again a steal at $150, and now it's mine.</p>
        <p>For anyone who, like my grandmother, is squeamish about wearing secondhand clothes -- she could never be disabused of the macabre suspicion that they were harvested for sale from dead bodies -- there is usually a selection of new stock, donated by some of the city's designers. On a day I visited, there was an entire rack of Carolina Herrera dresses and separates, which included cashmere knit tops with contrasting cuffs and tie collars ($175, marked down from $1,690), matching pleated print silk skirts ($150 from $1,599) and strapless beaded sheaths ($375, from $3,590).</p>
        <p>An ethereal full-length evening gown in diaphanous layers of claret and coffee silk chiffon ($250) by the couturier John Anthony, who made dresses for Jacqueline Kennedy, still bore its original tag -- a jaw-dropping $12,500. A very tall, slim woman took this exquisite creation into the changing room but reneged on her promise to come out and show me the dress on, having discovered that it was entirely see-through.</p>
        <p>The room's proportions, and the fact that there is just one changing room, makes shopping here an unusually convivial experience. As women wait their turn to try things on, their attention naturally turns to their fellow customers and their finds. On this day the atmosphere was greatly enhanced by the hostess skills of our saleslady, who read aloud from a donated copy of ''Elizabeth Taylor: My Love Affair With Jewelry.''</p>
        <p>La Taylor had just posed the question, ''How many young women get a set of rubies just for doing something wholesome?'' when a handsome middle-aged woman emerged from the changing room in a skintight red satin cheongsam embroidered with dragons ($90), to the general acclaim of the room. The silver-haired saleslady looked up from her book. ''Oh, I can just see you on a summer night with a glass of Champagne in your hand!''</p>
        <p>The woman in the cheongsam had originally selected the beautiful shantung Scaasi cocktail dress. ''Isn't this divine?'' she had asked me. I agreed, adding that Scaasi was one of Nancy Reagan's favorite designers. ''Honey, that's no incentive,'' she said, quickly replacing the dress on the rack. ''Nancy Pelosi, maybe.''</p>
        <p>As I was leaving, our indomitable saleslady was recounting stories of the famous people who have shopped in this tiny room. Apparently Geoffrey Beene was a regular visitor, spending afternoons scouring the racks for his own old pieces. On his death three years ago, he left his archive to Memorial Sloan-Kettering, and sometime soon those clothes will be hung back on those same racks, a strange and poignant tribute to a master of no-fuss, minimalist chic.</p>
        <p>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center Thrift Shop  1440 Third Avenue (between 81st and 82nd Streets); (212) 535-1250</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- A small and clean but unremarkable space, the intimate dimensions of which encourage customers actually to talk to one another.  SERVICE -- The volunteer cast of Upper East Side grandes dames is friendly, helpful and endlessly entertaining.  ALSO NOTEWORTHY -- A pair of immaculately tailored late '60s Gucci clam diggers ($150) in khaki canvas with a matching head scarf that for the young or daring (or both) could double as a bandeau top.</p>
        <p>CRITICAL SHOPPER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
