<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. All Ears as Ex-Senator Weighs Bid</title>
    <meta content="19thompson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/us/politics/19thompson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thompson, Fred Dalton</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6D71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. All Ears as Ex-Senator Weighs Bid</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">G.O.P. All Ears as Ex-Senator Weighs Bid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Senator Fred D. Thompson of Tennessee is not a declared presidential candidate, but he demonstrated his political star power Wednesday by drawing an audience of dozens of House Republicans searching for an alternative to their party's current presidential field.</p>
        <p>An estimated 40 to 50 lawmakers, about a quarter of House Republicans, trooped from the Capitol to a nearby Republican club to meet with Mr. Thompson, 64, an actor who is engaged in public and private deliberations about whether he should try for the actual White House job he has held on the screen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Senator Fred D. Thompson of Tennessee demonstrated his political star power by drawing an audience of dozens of House Republicans searching for another candidate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Former Senator Fred D. Thompson of Tennessee is not a declared presidential candidate, but he demonstrated his political star power Wednesday by drawing an audience of dozens of House Republicans searching for an alternative to their party's current presidential field.</p>
        <p>An estimated 40 to 50 lawmakers, about a quarter of House Republicans, trooped from the Capitol to a nearby Republican club to meet with Mr. Thompson, 64, an actor who is engaged in public and private deliberations about whether he should try for the actual White House job he has held on the screen.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to come over and see some of my old friends and make some new friends and tell them what was on my mind and listen and see what was on their minds,'' Mr. Thompson said after spending about an hour closeted with the House members. ''We will be seeing some more of each other, I am sure.''</p>
        <p>Those who met with Mr. Thompson, a regular in the television series ''Law &amp; Order'' and a radio commentator, said he did not tip his hand about whether he would enter the presidential race. But he assured fellow Republicans that he knew he could not deliberate too long and promised an unconventional candidacy should he become a contender.</p>
        <p>Many of those on hand were eager to see him start campaigning as a more conservative, palatable alternative to the current crop of Republican candidates, and one who could have wide appeal in Southern states.</p>
        <p>''He was called presidential and he was,'' said Representative Zach Wamp, Republican of Tennessee and a leader of an effort to draft Mr. Thompson. ''He was told he was electable, and he is.''</p>
        <p>As they left the session, lawmaker after lawmaker voiced frustration with the current presidential contenders and said the strong interest in Mr. Thompson illustrated a hunger for an alternative to the leading candidates, former Gov. Mitt Romney of Massachusetts; former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani of New York and Senator John McCain of Arizona. Each is seen by some party members to have some liabilities that limit his electability.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wamp said five of the seven members of the party's House leadership attended the meeting.</p>
        <p>''I think we are still looking, and probably looking for someone who is not out there yet,'' said Representative Jo Bonner, Republican of Alabama. ''We want Ronald Reagan, and we know Ronald Reagan is not going to be our nominee.''</p>
        <p>The House members do see a bit of Reagan in Mr. Thompson, both for his conservative record and an acting career in which he has often played the commanding authority figure, a fact they said should not be overlooked in assessing his appeal.</p>
        <p>''Certainly, you hear that voice and you know you have heard it before,'' said Representative Shelley Moore Capito, Republican of West Virginia.</p>
        <p>But party operatives and lawmakers noted that Mr. Thompson's popularity -- he has performed strongly in polls although he is not a candidate -- could be enhanced by the fact that he has not been subject to the scrutiny of rivals. And if he were to enter the race, they also noted, he would be far behind opponents in organization and fund-raising.</p>
        <p>As for his record, the two biggest criticisms are that Mr. Thompson supported the campaign finance law abhorred by conservative groups, and the perception that he was not one to overwork himself in Congress. Some say he has not shown the burning desire it takes to mount a presidential bid.</p>
        <p>His supporters say that if he decided to run, he would devote himself fully to the race. And Mr. Wamp, acknowledging some unrest over the campaign finance issue, said he did not think that would disqualify Mr. Thompson.</p>
        <p>Republicans who met with Mr. Thompson came from the crucial primary states of Iowa and South Carolina and from Southern strongholds like Florida, Texas, Georgia, North Carolina and Tennessee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson is being advised and encouraged by an inner circle of influential Tennessee political figures including former Senators Howard H. Baker Jr. and Bill Frist and former aides scattered around the lobbying firms on K Street and in Congressional offices. Associates believe he is moving steadily toward a candidacy. His disclosure last week that he is in remission from lymphoma was seen as an indicator of seriousness.</p>
        <p>"Seven weeks ago, I would have put it very low,'' Senator Bob Corker, Republican of Tennessee, said of the odds of a Thompson bid. "Four weeks ago, when I talked on the phone to both he and his wife, I would have put it at 50-50.</p>
        <p>''Last Wednesday, I talked to them both again on the phone, and I have to tell you I think he is very interested. I think he is at the 75- to 80-percent level at this point. I really do."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
