<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mental Health and Guns: Do Background Checks Do Enough?</title>
    <meta content="19weapons" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/us/19weapons.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070421T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Americans for Gun Safety</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Government Accountability Office</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFD81E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mental Health and Guns: Do Background Checks Do Enough?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mental Health and Guns: Do Background Checks Do Enough?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL LUO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Luo, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Revelations about Cho Seung-Hui's 2005 stay in a psychiatric center under a magistrate's order have raised questions about whether background checks adequately scrutinize the mental health history of potential gun buyers.</p>
        <p>Federal law prohibits those who have been ''adjudicated as a mental defective'' by a court, as well as those who have been involuntarily committed to a mental health facility, from buying a firearm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Revelations about Seung-Hui Cho’s stay in a psychiatric center have raised questions about whether background checks adequately scrutinize the mental health history of potential gun buyers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Revelations about Cho Seung-Hui's 2005 stay in a psychiatric center under a magistrate's order have raised questions about whether background checks adequately scrutinize the mental health history of potential gun buyers.</p>
        <p>Federal law prohibits those who have been ''adjudicated as a mental defective'' by a court, as well as those who have been involuntarily committed to a mental health facility, from buying a firearm.</p>
        <p>Only 17 states, however, submit such mental health information to the background check systems they use on gun purchases, said Dennis Henigan, legal director of the Brady Center to Prevent Gun Violence.</p>
        <p>Although Virginia has some of the most permissive gun laws in the country, the state does, in fact, include such mental health records in the background checks it conducts when someone tries to buy a handgun, said Donna Tate, program manager in the firearms transaction center for the Virginia State Police.</p>
        <p>''We determined Mr. Cho to be lawfully eligible to purchase a gun on two occasions,'' Ms. Tate said, referring to the Glock 9-millimeter handgun and .22-caliber pistol recovered after the shootings.</p>
        <p>A magistrate ordered that Mr. Cho be evaluated at Carilion Saint Albans Behavioral Health Center on Dec. 13, 2005, after two women who were students complained about his behavior. The next day, a special justice approved outpatient treatment for Mr. Cho and he was free to go, which may explain why no red flags were raised by the state's background check system when he bought the weapons this year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tate said that she was not familiar with the specifics of Mr. Cho's case but said it was up to the courts to decide whether an involuntary commitment to a psychiatric facility qualifies for notification to the state police system.</p>
        <p>Gun control advocates seized upon the revelations about Mr. Cho's psychiatric history to call for more complete background checks on gun buyers, particularly expanding the number of situations in which someone may be disqualified from buying a gun because of mental health issues.</p>
        <p>''The problem with the federal system and the problem with the Virginia system is the premium is on speed,'' Mr. Henigan said.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts, which has some of the toughest gun laws in the country, prohibits anyone who has ever been confined to a mental institution from buying a gun, although the person can provide a written affidavit from a physician to obtain an exception.</p>
        <p>Opponents of stricter gun control measures say such restrictions might not have helped prevent the massacre in Virginia.</p>
        <p>''A guy like that probably shouldn't have been able to buy a gun,'' said Mike McHugh, president of the Virginia Gun Owners Coalition. ''But my point is, that's not going to stop a guy like this.''</p>
        <p>Gun control advocates conceded that an array of issues would complicate efforts to tighten such laws, including privacy concerns and difficulties in determining whether someone is mentally unstable.</p>
        <p>''If you cataloged every American who has been depressed, you'd probably have a majority of the population,'' said Ladd Everitt, a spokesman for the Coalition to Stop Gun Violence.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Everitt added: ''I think it's something that should be looked at. That's as far as I would go. I think it's a debate we should have.''</p>
        <p>A 2002 report by the Americans for Gun Safety Foundation cited a Government Accountability Office study that said that for every 75,000 people who had tried to buy a gun, only one was denied by the background check system because of mental health criteria. The report cited another G.A.O. study that estimated that background check information was missing for as many as 2.6 million people who have been involuntarily institutionalized.</p>
        <p>Virginia is what those in the gun world call a shall issue state, meaning anyone who is not excluded under certain restrictions can obtain a gun. But in more restrictive states like California, New Jersey, New York, Hawaii, Massachusetts and others, people are first referred to local police departments for an extensive vetting process. In some cases, references must be provided; there is usually a waiting period.</p>
        <p>''This kid never would have gotten a gun in New York, New Jersey or any state that does that in a million years,'' Mr. Everitt said. ''There's just no way.''</p>
        <p>Representative Carolyn McCarthy, Democrat of New York, whose husband was killed in 1993 by a gunman on a Long Island Rail Road train, has been pushing House leaders this week to move quickly on a bill that would require states to automate their criminal history records so that computer databases used to conduct background checks on gun buyers are more complete. The bill would also require states to submit their mental health records to their background check systems and give them money to allow them to do so, said George Burke, a spokesman for Ms. McCarthy.</p>
        <p>But even some leading Democrats in Congress have been reluctant to push gun control legislation, particularly in light of their efforts to keep their recent electoral gains in more conservative districts they captured during the 2006 elections.</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 21, 2007, Saturday  An article on Thursday about questions surrounding the adequacy of background checks for gun buyers in the wake of the massacre at Virginia Polytechnic Institute incorrectly described the meaning of Virginia's being a ''shall issue'' state. The term refers to the qualifications for obtaining a permit to carry a concealed weapon, not for obtaining a weapon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 21, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about questions surrounding the adequacy of background checks for gun buyers in the wake of the massacre at Virginia Polytechnic Institute incorrectly described the meaning of Virginia's being a ''shall issue'' state. The term refers to the qualifications for obtaining a permit to carry a concealed weapon, not for obtaining a weapon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
