<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Redwoods Grow, The Oddballs Also Flourish</title>
    <meta content="19masl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/books/19masl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Preston, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Wild Trees, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E1DA1E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Redwoods Grow, The Oddballs Also Flourish</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where the Redwoods Grow, the Oddballs Also Flourish</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Wild Trees  A Story of Passion and Daring  By Richard Preston  Illustrated. 294 pages. Random House. $25.95.</p>
        <p>The bride wore lichen. She and the groom hung from a rope suspended between two tree spires. The wedding rings were cast from redwood sprigs, and the minister was also a geologist willing to stand on a branch in midair. The day before the ceremony, as the betrothed pair climbed the trees and prepared the rigging, the bride made a mistake while attaching her descender device. Had she not caught this error, she would have given new meaning to the idea of marriage as a giant leap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once again Richard Preston combines the thrill of exploration with the quirkiness of those who choose it as their lives’ work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Wild Trees  A Story of Passion and Daring  By Richard Preston  Illustrated. 294 pages. Random House. $25.95.</p>
        <p>The bride wore lichen. She and the groom hung from a rope suspended between two tree spires. The wedding rings were cast from redwood sprigs, and the minister was also a geologist willing to stand on a branch in midair. The day before the ceremony, as the betrothed pair climbed the trees and prepared the rigging, the bride made a mistake while attaching her descender device. Had she not caught this error, she would have given new meaning to the idea of marriage as a giant leap.</p>
        <p>Richard Preston, who describes these nuptials in ''The Wild Trees,'' has taken his own leap with this book's choice of subject matter. After creating a best-selling horrible-disease franchise with books including ''The Hot Zone'' in 1994 (ebola) and ''The Demon in the Freezer'' in 2002 (smallpox), Mr. Preston could have remained on the biohazard beat indefinitely. Instead he has written an exciting book about botany (sic) that recalls his 1987 astronomy book ''First Light,'' about the Hale telescope. Once again he combines the thrill of exploration with the quirkiness of those who choose it as their lives' work.</p>
        <p>''My goal is to reveal people and realms that nobody had ever imagined,'' Mr. Preston writes. Certainly he does so. The giant, ancient California redwoods from which ''The Wild Trees'' takes its title have hidden in plain sight, some of them not far from a well-traveled road. And yet Mr. Preston makes them seem as wildly exotic to his readers as they are to the assorted oddballs who choose to climb them. Mr. Preston transforms himself into one of those oddballs before this story is over.</p>
        <p>As illustrated by Andrew Joslin, whose plain line drawings of redwood structure are astonishing, ''The Wild Trees'' presents its subjects as ''the blue whales of the plant kingdom.'' Mr. Preston writes that ''in order to see a giant tree you need a magnifying glass,'' and this book is fascinating in its keen, inquisitive account of the redwoods' biosphere.</p>
        <p>These organisms are the size of 30-odd-story buildings, yet they are anchored by roots that are disproportionately small. Their upper reaches are home to bonsai trees, berry bushes, tiny aquatic creatures and nitrogen-based fertilizer. They grow so slowly that their development is hard to measure during the course of a scientist's lifetime. But they are not the world's largest living organisms. That honor, according to Mr. Preston, belongs to an edible fungus in Oregon that lives underground and measures three square miles.</p>
        <p>Still, the redwoods are colossal and daunting. And ''The Wild Trees'' wonders what kind of people would become obsessed with them. Mr. Preston, who entered this strange realm by writing an article for The New Yorker, went to Arcata, in Northern California, in 2003 to meet Steve Sillett, the tree explorer whose adventures are central to the human side of this book's story.</p>
        <p>''Recreational climbers regarded Sillett as a near-legendary figure, and he regarded them with alarm,'' Mr. Preston writes. Mr. Sillett was married to Marie Antoine, the aerial bride who had sewn lichen into her veil. And their home had become a magnet for redwood devotees. ''The clothing was Gore-Tex,'' Mr. Preston writes, ''and the conversation was trees, trees, trees.''</p>
        <p>''The Wild Trees'' reaches into the past to explain how Mr. Sillett and Ms. Antoine got to that point. It begins in 1987, when Mr. Sillett, then an acrophobic college student majoring in biology, saw his first redwood forest and decided to start climbing. ''I'm lusting for this tree,'' he told his brother and a friend, and thus a career of exploration began. It is the book's impressive but not entirely provable claim that Mr. Sillett has been the first person to visit many of the midair wonders he has seen.</p>
        <p>The reader learns of Ms. Antoine's nature-loving Ontario childhood, and the more roundabout route to tree study followed by Michael Taylor, a onetime knife salesman and grocery clerk. Like all of the stories here these are told in slightly excessive detail (Mr. Taylor's mother married a potter; Mr. Sillett's grandmother gave him honey-roasted peanuts for Christmas) and reflective of a lonely, obsessive inner state. The very names these climbers give to the trees they discover -- Bamboozle, Bushy Toe, Pig Snout, Trifecta, Screaming Titans and a whole lot of Tolkien -- reveal an off-the-grid new branch of science and express the strangeness of the tree-pioneering culture they help create.</p>
        <p>The book treats redwoodphilia as a true addiction. ''Why would a child get so whacked-out on redwoods,'' Mr. Preston asks about Mr. Taylor. ''He couldn't say. And it was getting worse and worse, this redwood thing. He felt that he needed to go into some kind of redwood detox.'' But whatever it is, Mr. Preston makes it contagious by filling his book with amazing details based on the trees' gigantism and mystery.</p>
        <p>In a particularly dramatic sequence a big and slightly tilted tree called Telperion (from Tolkien's ''Silmarillion'') is climbed and then hit by a squall after the climbers have ensconced themselves in treetop hammocks. They reassure themselves that the tree has survived for eons and gone untouched by countless storms. But this is the one that, after the climbers escaped, brings Telperion down and creates a 60-foot-high mud splash in the process.</p>
        <p>''The Wild Trees'' sags slightly when Mr. Preston begins describing his own climbing career, since it is no match for the book's other exploits. And it reaches too strenuously for a final note of wisdom. Maybe we learn from trees. ''Maybe these trees can teach us something about ourselves,'' Mr. Sillett says. Or maybe a labyrinthine sky-high structure holding huckleberries, copepods, lettuce lungwort and centuries' worth of silent history is devoid of lessons but speaks mesmerizingly for itself.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
