<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Warm In Florida, To Delight Of the Mets</title>
    <meta content="19mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/sports/baseball/19mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Florida Marlins</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Maine, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EED71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Warm In Florida, To Delight Of the Mets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s Warm in Florida, to Delight of the Mets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets traded their long underwear for short sleeves, stashed the woolen caps and ditched the parkas. No need for winter clothing here, where, for the first time in two weeks, they could embrace playing baseball alfresco.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to feel the heat,'' Manager Willie Randolph said before Wednesday's game against the Florida Marlins. ''Want to run around naked.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mets’ starting pitcher John Maine carried a no-hitter into the seventh inning while David Wright set a franchise record by notching a hit in his 25th consecutive game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets traded their long underwear for short sleeves, stashed the woolen caps and ditched the parkas. No need for winter clothing here, where, for the first time in two weeks, they could embrace playing baseball alfresco.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to feel the heat,'' Manager Willie Randolph said before Wednesday's game against the Florida Marlins. ''Want to run around naked.''</p>
        <p>Don't worry: The Mets did not take up their manager on his offer, but they proved amenable to another sort of streaking while coasting to a 9-2 victory at Dolphin Stadium.</p>
        <p>The starting pitcher, John Maine, took a no-hitter into the seventh inning. On their way to building a 4-0 lead, the first six hitters reached base against the team's longtime nemesis, Dontrelle Willis. For good measure, David Wright, with his second-inning single, set a franchise record by notching a hit in his 25th consecutive game.</p>
        <p>That all of this happened in 80-degree weather should hardly be undervalued, and no one was as pleased to see the palm trees as Maine. His scheduled starts Sunday and Monday were pushed back because of the downpours that soaked the Northeast. Pitching on eight days' rest, he flirted with a no-hitter for the second time in two weeks -- on April 4 in St. Louis, he allowed only a fifth-inning single in seven shutout innings -- before Miguel Cabrera lead off the seventh with a sharp single to left-center field.</p>
        <p>''He was outstanding,'' the pitching coach Rick Peterson said of Maine. ''Anything less would be an understatement.''</p>
        <p>In striking out seven, including the side in the second, Maine mowed down a team that entered Wednesday with the highest batting average (.288) in baseball. Until Cabrera's single, Maine allowed only one ball out of the infield, Hanley Ramirez's third-inning flyout, while mixing in his slider and changeup with his low-90s fastball. When Maine left after 107 pitches, he was still reaching 92 and 93 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>''I've been doing a better job preparing,'' Maine said. ''I felt good from the first through the seventh.''</p>
        <p>Through five innings, the only thing that could stop him, it seemed, would be a pitch count that ballooned to 77 because of three walks and five strikeouts. Maine was scheduled to lead off the sixth, and Randolph was prepared to send David Newhan up as a pinch hitter until he looked up at the scoreboard and saw that Maine had yet to allow a hit.</p>
        <p>Randolph was aware of how efficient Maine needed to pitch if he wanted any chance at lasting deeper into the game. Almost as ordered, the sixth went by in a bizarre eight-pitch blur -- four-pitch walk, three-pitch strikeout and a first-pitch double play -- and Maine was nine outs away from throwing the first no-hitter in franchise history.</p>
        <p>''I really thought we had a shot,'' Paul Lo Duca said.</p>
        <p>At least until Cabrera, who turned 24 Wednesday, came up in the seventh. He fell behind, 1-2, and was then tempted by a high fastball. Cabrera started to swing, then thought better of it. He held up, according to the first-base umpire, Laz Diaz.</p>
        <p>''Borderline,'' Lo Duca said.</p>
        <p>''No swing,'' Carlos Delgado said.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was close,'' Maine said with a smile.</p>
        <p>Given new life, Cabrera poked the next pitch, Maine's 90th, into the outfield for a single. As the ball hit the outfield grass, Maine slapped his glove out of frustration.</p>
        <p>Maine lost his shutout a few batters later, when Joe Borchard smashed a two-run homer over the 434-foot sign in straightaway center field. After retiring the next hitter, Alfredo Amézaga, Maine was bathed in a standing ovation from the largely pro-Mets crowd of 17,219.</p>
        <p>Maine is gradually cementing his role as one of the team's more reliable starters, a job that Willis has relished with the Marlins for the last five seasons. He entered the game tied for the league lead in victories, boasting a 3-0 record and a 3.32 earned run average. Nice numbers, sure, but check out Willis's lifetime success against the Mets: In 16 starts before Wednesday, Willis was 11-2 with a 2.02 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>None of that mattered much when Reyes led off the game with a line single, the first of his four hits. Lo Duca, in the lineup a day after a foul tip bruised his right index finger and forced him to leave the game, reached on an error. Carlos Beltrán ripped a first-pitch single, scoring Reyes, and Delgado followed with a double down the right-field line. By the time Willis had thrown nine pitches, the Mets led, 2-0. They tacked on two more when Beltrán scored on an error and Alou's single scored Delgado.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The club record for longest hitting streak was previously shared by Hubie Brooks (1984) and Mike Piazza (1999).  The Braves are sending their three best pitchers to face the Mets this weekend at Shea Stadium: Tim Hudson will face Mike Pelfrey on Friday, Chuck James will oppose Oliver PÉrez on Saturday and John Smoltz will start against Tom Glavine in Sunday's series finale.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
