<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Complete Another Lost Season</title>
    <meta content="19knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/sports/basketball/19knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Charlotte Bobcats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Charlotte Bobcats</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFD71E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Complete Another Lost Season</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Knicks Complete Another Lost Season</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLOTTE, N.C., April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Isiah Thomas began his Knicks coaching tour with an ultimatum and a belief. He had to win to save his job. He was sure he had the players to do so.</p>
        <p>By the time he reached the finish line of his 82-game gantlet Wednesday, Thomas had already won his job security -- a contract extension given to him last month. He had already won the faith of enough fans to fill Madison Square Garden for the past few months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Wednesday night’s victory, the Knicks completed their sixth straight losing season and their fourth since Isiah Thomas became team president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Isiah Thomas began his Knicks coaching tour with an ultimatum and a belief. He had to win to save his job. He was sure he had the players to do so.</p>
        <p>By the time he reached the finish line of his 82-game gantlet Wednesday, Thomas had already won his job security -- a contract extension given to him last month. He had already won the faith of enough fans to fill Madison Square Garden for the past few months.</p>
        <p>Yet there was no mistaking the anguish in Thomas's face in the final weeks, right through Wednesday night's 94-93 victory over the Charlotte Bobcats. As the injury-depleted Knicks lost 15 of their last 19 games, Thomas lost what he perhaps wanted most: definitive proof that he was right all along.</p>
        <p>Thomas believes in his roster. James L. Dolan, the Garden chairman, believes in Thomas -- and awarded him the extension. But without a playoff appearance, or even a .500 record, Thomas has no case to sway the skeptical masses.</p>
        <p>Thomas never confesses to seeking vindication. But his grim expression, low tones and clenched jaw betray a frustration that goes beyond mere losses. His sense of regret seeped out on the season's final day, as Thomas, in his strongest terms yet, blamed injuries for his team's demise.</p>
        <p>''I think it's pretty safe to say, had we not been so decimated, this would be a little different tonight,'' he said before the game. ''Had we not been hit by the injuries the way we were hit, I think it's safe to say we could have squeezed out at least six to seven more wins and be sitting in a totally different position than we're in.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, it was not long ago that Thomas pointed to this finale against the Bobcats as a game that could determine the Knicks' playoff position.</p>
        <p>The Knicks were 29-34, and occupying eighth place in the Eastern Conference, on March 12. Serious injuries to Jamal Crawford, David Lee and Quentin Richardson destroyed any chance the Knicks had to build on that moment.</p>
        <p>They had played at a .500 pace for about three months. Had they maintained that pace over the final 19 games, the Knicks would have finished with 38 or 39 victories. The Orlando Magic earned the eighth and final playoff spot with a 40-42 record.</p>
        <p>The Knicks (33-49) closed their sixth straight losing season, and their fourth since Thomas became president. They went out on a high note, as Eddy Curry scored on a tip-in with 0.6 seconds left to deliver a final victory.</p>
        <p>''I wish we were still playing, and I wish we were still continuing,'' a still-grim Thomas said after the game. ''I don't think I was elated at all walking off the court. As a matter of fact, I think I was a little angry.''</p>
        <p>Curry said the players were, too.</p>
        <p>''We definitely wanted to be in the postseason,'' he said. ''Nobody had plans on us going home this early.''</p>
        <p>Thomas is unwavering in his belief that Curry will be a franchise center, that Stephon Marbury remains an elite point guard, and that a surrounding cast of Crawford, Lee, Richardson and a crop of young prospects can lead the Knicks to better days.</p>
        <p>But Thomas will need a fresh 82-game slate to prove it to anyone not drawing a Garden paycheck.</p>
        <p>''I have a great understanding of where we are, regarding injuries and everything else,'' he said. ''I like what we have. And I like the direction that we're headed in. At the end of the season, there will only be one winner and there will be 29 losers. And we'll be one of the 29.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks have solid talent throughout the roster, but they lack a transcendent player who can transform a perennial loser into a legitimate power. With no salary-cap room for at least three more years, Thomas will have to find one via trade, or keep tinkering around the edges with draft picks and free agents.</p>
        <p>The Knicks are unlikely to find that elite player through the draft. For the second straight year, the Chicago Bulls own the Knicks' lottery pick, as part of the Curry trade. That makes the Knicks' free fall all the more painful for Thomas. Every Knicks loss in the past month has increased the Bulls' chances of winning the No. 1 pick, and the right to draft Greg Oden (if he declares) or Kevin Durant.</p>
        <p>Wednesday's victory helped, pushing the Knicks from sixth in the lottery standings to a tie for seventh. The N.B.A. will break all ties in the draft order, including the lottery, with a blind draw on Friday.</p>
        <p>The team with the seventh-worst record has a 4.3 percent chance of winning the No. 1 pick in the draft. However, the odds will change slightly once the league breaks the ties.</p>
        <p>Thomas was not yet ready to address his summer priorities. The Knicks could certainly use an ace shooter and, given Curry's defensive deficiencies, a shot-blocker and interior defender.</p>
        <p>Thomas said he was thinking more about the Knicks' ''culture and the style of play,'' themes he has harped on all season, while praising his team's resiliency. He said the Knicks had gained respect around the league.</p>
        <p>''You may look at the record,'' he said, ''but I don't think there's a team out there that walks in saying, 'This is an easy night for us.' You can't say that wasn't the case all the time. I don't think that will be again.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
