<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Knicks Standout Sees Team Turning Page</title>
    <meta content="brescia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4D91130F93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Knicks Standout Sees Team Turning Page</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE BRESCIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his new book, ''The New American Story,'' Bill Bradley presents his detailed solutions for improving the United States. Regarding his former team, the Knicks, he already sees progress toward a better future.</p>
        <p>''I think they're better than last year,'' Bradley said in Manhattan recently at the Volvo for Life Awards, which honor people who perform heroic acts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his new book, ''The New American Story,'' Bill Bradley presents his detailed solutions for improving the United States. Regarding his former team, the Knicks, he already sees progress toward a better future.</p>
        <p>''I think they're better than last year,'' Bradley said in Manhattan recently at the Volvo for Life Awards, which honor people who perform heroic acts.</p>
        <p>Bradley said that the Knicks had two building blocks in Jamal Crawford and Eddy Curry, and that he had seen some of the qualities in Crawford that helped the Knicks win two N.B.A. titles when he played for the team in the 1960s and '70s.</p>
        <p>''I like the way he moves on the court,'' Bradley said of Crawford. ''I like his shot off the dribble. He seems really good.''</p>
        <p>Bradley said of Curry: ''He's a big guy. He's got work to do to develop. But I think the decision to run the offense through him will put him on the fast track.''</p>
        <p>Bradley, a former United States senator from New Jersey, was a Democratic presidential candidate in 2000. In his new book, he offers his view of how each American can shape the future. Bradley said that he had not sent a copy to inspire Knicks Coach Isiah Thomas and his players. He said that he respected the job Thomas was doing as the team's president and coach.</p>
        <p>''I give him a lot of credit for putting himself on the line,'' Bradley said. ''I've always liked someone who puts themselves on the line and takes responsibility.''</p>
        <p>Bradley retired from politics in 2000 and is a managing director at Allen &amp; Company, an investment bank in New York. He said that he would not want to do any of Thomas's jobs for the Knicks, or for any other team.</p>
        <p>''I have no interest in getting back in the game,'' Bradley said. ''I have too much on my agenda right now.''</p>
        <p>Bradley said his book, No. 9 on the New York Times best-seller nonfiction list, kept him busy. But he said that he still made time to watch a few games, although he did not like some aspects of today's N.B.A., like the 3-point shot and what he considers a lack of foul calls.</p>
        <p>''I had a wonderful 10 years in the N.B.A,'' Bradley said. ''I still love basketball. I'd love the Knicks to win. And I like to see my friends like Phil Jackson do well.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
