<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bangladesh Says It Won't Let an Ex-Leader Re-enter the Country</title>
    <meta content="19bangladesh" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/19/world/asia/19bangladesh.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bangladesh</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E4D91E3FF93AA25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bangladesh Says It Won't Let an Ex-Leader Re-enter the Country</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bangladesh Says It Won’t Let an Ex-Leader Re-enter the Country</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA; Julfikar Ali Manik contributed reporting from Dhaka, Bangladesh.</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The army-backed government of Bangladesh on Wednesday barred a former prime minister, whom it has accused of involvement in deaths during a political demonstration, from returning to the country.</p>
        <p>The action was taken amid a sweeping crackdown on political parties over accusations of corruption and malfeasance as a caretaker government prepares for new elections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The action was taken amid a crackdown on political parties as the government prepares for new elections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The army-backed government of Bangladesh on Wednesday barred a former prime minister, whom it has accused of involvement in deaths during a political demonstration, from returning to the country.</p>
        <p>The action was taken amid a sweeping crackdown on political parties over accusations of corruption and malfeasance as a caretaker government prepares for new elections.</p>
        <p>The former prime minister, Sheik Hasina Wajed, reached by telephone in Washington, where she was visiting her son, vowed to defy the government order and stick to her plans to go back home next week.</p>
        <p>The country's caretaker government seemed to be at work on an exile-for-clemency deal with Sheik Hasina's rival, Khaleda Zia. One of Mrs. Zia's sons, detained on a corruption charge, was released from custody earlier this week in what appeared to be an effort to persuade her to go into exile.</p>
        <p>Her other son remains in jail on graft charges. Mrs. Zia was prime minister until her five-year term ended last October.</p>
        <p>She had been accused by Sheik Hasina's party, the Awami League, of trying to rig elections that had been scheduled for Jan. 22. Violent protests prompted the suspension of the elections and the declaration of a state of emergency.</p>
        <p>Last week, the caretaker government charged Sheik Hasina with murder in connection with the deaths of 10 people during one of the demonstrations. On Wednesday, the Home Ministry said in a statement that ''special security measures regarding Sheik Hasina's return to the country'' had been taken.</p>
        <p>Sheik Hasina said she was innocent and prepared to answer the charges in court. ''Why do they want to prevent me from going to my country?'' she said. ''It's my constitutional right. I'm the daughter of the father of our nation.''</p>
        <p>Sheik Hasina's father, Sheik Mujibur Rahman, was the leader of the country's war of independence from Pakistan. Sheik Hasina said she would leave Washington late Wednesday for London, and would leave for Dhaka, Bangladesh's capital, next Monday.</p>
        <p>She said she had offered to return home last week to face the charges against her but was told by government officials not to rush.</p>
        <p>The current government, which took over in January, has promised to hold elections by the end of 2008. It has said nothing yet about whether the two main political party leaders will be allowed to participate.</p>
        <p>The government has pledged to cleanse politics of crime and corruption. Its latest moves could radically alter the political landscape, by weakening the two major parties, and their respective dynasties.</p>
        <p>The Bangladesh Nationalist Party, led by Mrs. Zia, and the Awami League, run by Sheik Hasina, have taken turns governing since democracy was restored in 1991.</p>
        <p>To simply boot them out of the country may not rid Bangladesh of their influence, nor would it necessarily yield long-lasting political reform, said Christine Fair, a senior research associate with the United States Institute for Peace, a nonpartisan group financed by Congress to help prevent or resolve conflicts. How long the government can hold on, without alienating public opinion, she said, is the bigger question.</p>
        <p>''Like military governments elsewhere, this army has no exit strategy and they will likely lose the support they enjoy now over some not-so-distant time horizon,'' she said by e-mail.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
