<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giveaway in Honolulu Raises Eyebrows as It Lifts Spirits</title>
    <meta content="07hawaii" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/us/07hawaii.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Honolulu (Hawaii)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hawaii</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oahu (Hawaii)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nieves, Evelyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kawamoto, Genshiro</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahale, Dorie-Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii/Honolulu and Oahu</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hawaii</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E5D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giveaway in Honolulu Raises Eyebrows as It Lifts Spirits</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giveaway in Honolulu Raises Eyebrows as It Lifts Spirits</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nieves, Evelyn</byline>
      <dateline>HONOLULU, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Genshiro Kawamoto, one of Japan's richest real estate developers, is making good on plan to open eight houses he owns in Oahu's most exclusive area to poor families of Native Hawaiian descent; Dorie-Ann Kahale's family and two others were chosen from among 3,000 letters sent to Kawamoto after he announced his plan in Oct 2006; they are living rent free in houses worth up to $6 million; he has promised to let them live in houses for 10 years; Kawamoto's past business practices have made many suspicious; he is known for buying houses on whim, failing to maintain them and serving eviction notices to entire communities on short notice; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One morning a few weeks ago, as Dorie-Ann Kahale was straightening the room she lived in with her five daughters, a visitor arrived sporting coiffed gray hair and keys to a mansion.</p>
        <p>The visitor, Genshiro Kawamoto, a Japanese equivalent of Donald Trump, had come by to tell Ms. Kahale that he was about to change her life. She and her girls would be leaving a homeless shelter for one of his multimillion-dollar houses in Honolulu's Kahala neighborhood, the Beverly Hills of Oahu.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of Japan’s richest real estate developers is making good on a plan to open eight houses he owns in Oahu’s most exclusive area to poor families of Native Hawaiian descent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One morning a few weeks ago, as Dorie-Ann Kahale was straightening the room she lived in with her five daughters, a visitor arrived sporting coiffed gray hair and keys to a mansion.</p>
        <p>The visitor, Genshiro Kawamoto, a Japanese equivalent of Donald Trump, had come by to tell Ms. Kahale that he was about to change her life. She and her girls would be leaving a homeless shelter for one of his multimillion-dollar houses in Honolulu's Kahala neighborhood, the Beverly Hills of Oahu.</p>
        <p>''It's God's miracle,'' Ms. Kahale said, standing barefoot on the marble tile floor of the four-bedroom, four-and-a-half-bath, modified Colonial-style house. ''Look! I have crystal chandeliers in every room.''</p>
        <p>At the shelter, she had been sleeping on the floor of a room smaller than her new kitchen, and her daughters, ages 6 through 20, had been sharing one double bed.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kahale, a customer service representative for a small Hawaiian phone and Internet company, is not the only person of modest means moving up to Kahala living. In a gesture worthy of Oprah Winfrey and reality TV, Mr. Kawamoto, one of Japan's richest real estate developers, is making good on a plan to open eight houses he owns in Oahu's most exclusive area to poor families of Native Hawaiian descent.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kahale's family and two others were chosen from among 3,000 letters sent to Mr. Kawamoto after he announced his plan last October; they are living rent free (utilities not included) in houses worth up to $6 million. He has promised to let them live in his houses for 10 years.</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Kawamoto's act of charity has made headlines around the world, it has also raised plenty of questions.</p>
        <p>The trouble is that his past business practices have made many suspicious. As Lee Cataluna, a columnist for The Honolulu Advertiser, put it: ''He doesn't have a track record of generosity or compassion. Just what is he up to?''</p>
        <p>What Mr. Kawamoto does have is a reputation for capricious adventures in real estate in Hawaii and California. He is known for buying houses on a whim, failing to maintain them and serving eviction notices to entire communities on short notice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kawamoto and other real-estate investors are partly responsible for driving up housing prices in Oahu during the mid-1980s. He snapped up nearly 200 houses and apartments by cruising communities in a limousine, pointing to properties he wanted and making cash offers that homeowners could not refuse.</p>
        <p>In 2002, he decided to sell nearly all the properties to take advantage of rising housing prices and gave some tenants only 30 days' notice before evicting them. His actions coincided with the beginning of a rental shortage that has made Hawaii's median rents (about $1,900 for a two-bedroom apartment) among the highest in the United States, said Ricky Cassiday, a residential real estate analyst.</p>
        <p>In 2002, Mr. Kawamoto also served 30-day eviction notices to hundreds of families in Santa Rosa, Calif., and the suburbs of Sacramento. That fueled an outcry so strong it led to new tenant-protection laws in California, and Mr. Kawamoto granted tenants an additional 60 days.</p>
        <p>Since 2002, he has spent more than $115 million buying 22 houses in Kahala. But since then, some of those mini- and mighty mansions have stood empty and neglected, their lawns strewn with dead palm fronds, their fences rusting and pools green with algae. Residents of this sprawling enclave have complained and threatened legal action. Some also have publicly worried that Mr. Kawamoto was trying to drive down property values so he could snatch up more houses at lower prices. But Mr. Kawamoto, battle hardened at 75 years old, shrugs off the critics. ''I don't hear anything,'' he told reporters at a news conference held in late March in the circular driveway of Ms. Kahale's new home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kawamoto, who spoke through an interpreter, also announced there that he was waiving the $150-a-month rent he had planned to charge. Ms. Kahale burst into tears. Mr. Kawamoto teared up, too.</p>
        <p>He said it gave him great joy to provide places to live to hard-working people who had fallen on tough times, which is why he chose Native Hawaiians. Ms. Kahale, 39, and a single mother (she also has a son, 21, who is on his own), fit Mr. Kawamoto's bill perfectly. She makes $13 an hour but she lost her apartment two years ago when her rent rose to $1,200 from $800. She and her girls stayed with relatives, then spent five months on a beach before they moved in September to a shelter that opened an hour's drive from her job and church.</p>
        <p>Before his tenants moved to his houses, Mr. Kawamoto had the swimming pools filled in with rocks for insurance reasons. He also had the front gates and walls removed so the houses, he said, looked more like ''old Hawaii.'' He furnished the houses with a few sofas and beds, and gave each family $1,000 in $100 bills for moving expenses.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kahale has visited Mr. Kawamoto's other tenants and hopes to organize monthly get-togethers. One is a single mother of five who works at an elementary school; the other is a couple with six children (the wife is a bank teller, the husband is unemployed).</p>
        <p>When they moved in, a four-foot-tall Buddha statue out front was buried under overgrown palms. The backyard was a jungle. She and her daughters, with friends from church, raked and weeded for five days.</p>
        <p>''I want us to fit in,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Recently, Ms. Kahale stood outside her white-columned house, daydreaming of her daughters taking prom pictures under the portico. (She has 14-year-old twins and a 15-year-old.)</p>
        <p>Then she peeked into her mailbox. ''My first letter!'' she exclaimed. It was an invitation to join the Kahala Community Association.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Kahale's smile disappeared as she read. The letter noted the problems the association had with Mr. Kawamoto's properties. But what got Ms. Kahale was the $40 needed to join the group. To that, she said, she would have to give some serious thought.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
