<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opening Up a Jewelry Box; From Handbags to Hotels, Bulgari Is Remodeling Itself</title>
    <meta content="07bulgari" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia/Bali</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1331" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opening Up a Jewelry Box; From Handbags to Hotels, Bulgari Is Remodeling Itself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nicola Bulgari entered his Manhattan office as if he owned it, which, of course, as the grandson of Sotirio Bulgari, the great Roman jeweler, he did. In the big room, with windows overlooking Tiffany and Vuitton, almost everything looked fairly old, at least since the last generation, including the portrait of his father leaning against the wall, still unhung. Only a new white sofa stuck out. It did not match his sensibility.</p>
        <p>''I'm getting a dark-green leather one,'' he said, taking his place behind the desk and calling out for colored jewels, for new collections, to show off. Bring more and then more again, he commanded a young woman who had already brought several trays. One diamond ring, with a stone as sparkling as an Arctic morning, was admired. ''Two and a half million dollars,'' he said proudly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nicola Bulgari entered his Manhattan office as if he owned it, which, of course, as the grandson of Sotirio Bulgari, the great Roman jeweler, he did. In the big room, with windows overlooking Tiffany and Vuitton, almost everything looked fairly old, at least since the last generation, including the portrait of his father leaning against the wall, still unhung. Only a new white sofa stuck out. It did not match his sensibility.</p>
        <p>''I'm getting a dark-green leather one,'' he said, taking his place behind the desk and calling out for colored jewels, for new collections, to show off. Bring more and then more again, he commanded a young woman who had already brought several trays. One diamond ring, with a stone as sparkling as an Arctic morning, was admired. ''Two and a half million dollars,'' he said proudly.</p>
        <p>The house of Bulgari is getting a face lift, not just Mr. Bulgari's office, but the entire Fifth Avenue store at the corner of 57th Street, a multimillion-dollar rethinking of the old space that had been ''dark and secretive,'' whispered another aide. Much of the forbidding front wall -- the wall of a palazzo -- has been ripped away and huge windows, stretching almost from sidewalk to roof, have been installed. Not a vault anymore, but an atrium where the customer is made welcome, allowed to buy not only the one-of-a-kind jewelry, but also the $19,000 python handbags soon to be introduced (with Roman and Greek coins imbedded in the skins), not to mention the new $500 sunglasses.</p>
        <p>Bulgari is breaking out, opening hotels in Italy and Bali and underwriting the opening festivities for the galleries of Hellenistic, Etruscan and Roman art at the Metropolitan Museum of Art the week of April 16. Bulgari is also making an increasing amount of money: its 2006 earnings report trumpeted a 15 percent rise in net income. At the same time, the company, public but still family-run, is trying to counter an impression in some circles that it has lost its sophisticated edge, the chic that propelled it through the swinging '60s and '70s.</p>
        <p>To illustrate Bulgari's new campaign, James Hurley, a managing director at the Telsey Advisory Group and the senior analyst covering luxury goods, cited the huge billboard that covered the scaffolding during the Manhattan store's revamping. The billboard featured a quote from Andy Warhol from the '60s, saying that a visit to Bulgari was like a trip to a contemporary art museum. ''That certainly harks back to the heyday, doesn't it?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hurley compared Bulgari to Chanel and Gucci and Vuitton -- but with even more growth potential. Louis Vuitton sells 5 billion euros, or about $6.69 billion, of its largely V-imprinted merchandise a year; Chanel sells $2.5 billion, he said. ''Bulgari just hit $1 billion with this latest statement for 2006. There's still a lot of organic growth to come.''</p>
        <p>As with many luxury goods analysts, he said he saw no waning of the hunger for those glamorous names. While the National Retail Federation is forecasting a ''subdued'' picture for most retailing in the first half of 2007, many of the luxury brands are forecasting double-digit growth.</p>
        <p>''Gucci is doing well, even after Tom Ford left,'' he said. ''Chanel -- one brand that had a little bit of a pause at the end of '05 and the beginning of '06 -- has really come on strong lately. Its classic quilted bag has now become the 'it' bag.''</p>
        <p>That fits in with Bulgari's rosy predictions. And if Mr. Bulgari, 66, the company's vice chairman, is more concerned with coins and jewels, his nephew, Francesco Trapani, 50, is more involved with finance. Mr. Trapani, the chief executive of the company, said its most audacious new venture -- the Bulgari Hotel Spa in Milan, opened two years ago, and its newer sister resort in Bali -- ''will remain a small part, will have little impact,'' on the company's finances. ''The real impact of the hotel,'' he said, in an interview via closed-circuit video from Rome, ''is to promote the brand.''</p>
        <p>The Bulgari hotel operation, Mr. Trapani said, is different from those of other luxury brands, notably Armani and Versace. ''We did not license out the name to other companies,'' he said. ''We are going very slow. It's a virgin industry for us. We did not want to be just an investor. We own 65 percent, and the Ritz-Carlton owns 35 percent. In this role, we not only control the image and design, we decide what kind of services to offer.''</p>
        <p>Within the next several years, he said, Bulgari hopes to open three or four more hotels, and is looking at properties in Paris, London, New York, Tokyo and Shanghai, among others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trapani once waxed ecstatic about the growth potential of China. While still proclaiming the significance of that market -- Bulgari ended 2006 with four stores and plans to end 2007 with eight -- he now called doing business there ''very challenging.''</p>
        <p>''The bureaucracy is very heavy; you need thousands of authorizations,'' he said. ''It's a mess.''</p>
        <p>Because of that, he said, ''the assortment of products in our stores there is not as complete because the imports of merchandise -- the replenishment -- is still very slow.''</p>
        <p>Still, he said, he is optimistic, not only about mainland China, but Hong Kong, Taipei and especially Macao, which he said was developing ''very quickly.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, he said he felt that the American market, which represents 16 percent of the business, was not doing as well as it could, hence, the new store remodeling in Midtown. He added that the plan is to invest even more in the United States in the next three to five years: Bulgari will open ''a lot of additional stores in second-tier cities; this year, we've opened in Costa Mesa and we'll open in Boca Raton.''</p>
        <p>Besides opening stores, Bulgari plans to bolster its wholesale watch business -- that is, its sales to department stores and other non-Bulgari boutiques. ''Not increasing the number of stores,'' he said, ''but becoming more important, more of a presence, in those we supply.''</p>
        <p>Right now, jewelry -- baubles like a pink tourmaline and diamond ''jellyfish'' Mr. Bulgari exhibited ($38,800) -- make up 40 percent of the company's sales. Watches make up 29 percent, perfume 20 percent and accessories like the python handbags make up 10 percent.</p>
        <p>Those percentages could shift around in the next couple of years. ''We expect accessories to grow faster than the others, if only for a few years,'' the chief executive said, adding that he is even considering opening some ''dedicated'' accessory shops, that is, boutiques that sell only accessories like leather goods and sunglasses.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Trapani said he would like to introduce even more expensive ladies' watches, which start at $1,400, Mr. Hurley, the analyst, said he believed that Bulgari should be expanding its women's watches downward in price -- their jeweled watches sell for more than $20,000 -- and become more ''sporty.''</p>
        <p>While other luxury watch brands remain white-hot, ''Bulgari's watch business has been weaker than expected,'' Mr. Hurley said. ''Watches, as a total percentage of total revenues, have declined.''</p>
        <p>Although the percentage loss may have something to do with the introduction of new products like handbags and sunglasses, Mr. Hurley said that Bulgari, unlike some other luxury watch companies, does not manufacture its own watches. ''The company buys its movements from third parties,'' he said. (Bulgari actually produced its first watch movement in 2006, a tourbillon that sells for $137,000, Mr. Trapani said.)</p>
        <p>In the past, the company has also had problems with ''gray goods,'' authentic merchandise that was shipped from distributors to retailers, perhaps in other countries, who then sold it at unauthorized discounts, undercutting the market, Mr. Hurley said.</p>
        <p>Company officials said that situation was corrected as soon as they found about it.</p>
        <p>Whatever the problems may have been, the company's most recent numbers were strong.</p>
        <p>''They've been trying to get the great vibes back,'' Mr. Hurley said, ''and I think they've done it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
