<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Aiming to Retain Their Hold on Sixth Place</title>
    <meta content="07rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/sports/hockey/07rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Aiming to Retain Their Hold on Sixth Place</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers Aiming to Retain Their Hold on Sixth Place</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With one game to go before the playoffs, the Rangers this season have something in common with the Rangers of last season: If they lose their final game, they could end up facing the Devils in the first round of the postseason.</p>
        <p>The comparisons, however, pretty much end there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the Rangers lose their final game, they could end up facing the Devils in the first round of the postseason, something they would like to avoid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With one game to go before the playoffs, the Rangers this season have something in common with the Rangers of last season: If they lose their final game, they could end up facing the Devils in the first round of the postseason.</p>
        <p>The comparisons, however, pretty much end there.</p>
        <p>The Rangers head into their final game, tonight at Pittsburgh, on their hottest streak of the season. They are 12-2-3 since March 2, resuscitating a season once left for dead. A year ago, they lost their last five games and were playing with a rookie goalie who was trying to shake an injury. After losing the Atlantic Division title to the Devils on the last day, they had to play the Devils, who had won 11 consecutive games, in the first round of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The Rangers can avoid playing the Devils, once again the division champs, in the first round by finishing ahead of the Tampa Bay Lightning and staying in sixth place. They would then face the Atlanta Thrashers, who clinched the Southeast Division last night.</p>
        <p>Finishing seventh means another matchup with the Devils.</p>
        <p>Rangers Coach Tom Renney said he would prefer to finish sixth. He will not be resting anyone, including goalie Henrik Lundqvist, against Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>''Last year we faced a team that was very hot, had a great goaltender and won a lot of games,'' Rangers forward Jaromir Jagr said. ''This time, it's the other way around. Let's see if we can take advantage of that.''</p>
        <p>Forward Martin Straka said: ''The last four or five weeks we've been playing playoff hockey. We know how it feels to be in the position that if you lose you are going to be out of it.''</p>
        <p>Lundqvist is 8-0-1 in his past nine decisions, a far cry from last year. Late last season, he struggled to recover from a hip flexor injury, had migraines and battled fatigue during a season that included winning the Olympic gold medal with Sweden.</p>
        <p>The Rangers have been fortified with extra players during this stretch drive. They traded for forward Sean Avery in February. Forward Ryan Callahan and defenseman Dan Girardi, who have become valuable contributors, arrived from the Hartford Wolf Pack.</p>
        <p>Avery and Callahan added offense, enabling the Rangers to spread their scoring among three lines. They no longer need to rely as much on their top line of Jagr, Straka and Michael Nylander, as they did at the start of the season.</p>
        <p>''I think mentally it helps me a lot,'' Jagr said of the addition of other scoring lines. ''I know for sure that we can win even if I don't feel good. That's big. That way you don't have to press to score.''</p>
        <p>Goals have been difficult for him this season. He has 30, down from a team-record 54 last season, a typical total during his 621-goal career.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers have seven forwards with at least 16 goals, and the playing time is spread out. Jagr is averaging 21 minutes 45 seconds of ice time, about 3 fewer than he is used to.</p>
        <p>''It's what you need for the playoffs,'' he said. ''If you can have more energy in a Game 7, it can be a huge difference.''</p>
        <p>So far, it has gotten them to game No. 82 with the playoffs ahead.</p>
        <p>TAMPA BAY GAINS NO GROUND -- Olli Jokinen had a goal and an assist and Ville Peltonen set up three goals for the Florida Panthers in a 7-2 victory last night against the host Tampa Bay Lightning.</p>
        <p>The loss, combined with Atlanta's 4-1 victory at Carolina, ended Tampa Bay's chance for a third Southeast Division championship in four seasons. The Lightning remained seventh in the Eastern Conference, 2 points behind the Rangers.</p>
        <p>The Panthers chased Lightning goalie Johan Holmqvist with four goals on their first 12 shots. The backup Marc Denis took over with 1 minute 48 seconds left in the first period.</p>
        <p>Florida led by 7-0 early in the third period. Jason Ward spoiled the shutout bid by Panthers goalie Ed Belfour with 8:41 to play. (AP)</p>
        <p>HOBEY BAKER WINNER ANNOUNCED -- North Dakota forward Ryan Duncan won the Hobey Baker Memorial Award last night as the nation's top college hockey player. Duncan, a 5-foot-8 sophomore from Calgary, Alberta, had 31 goals and 26 assists to lead the Fighting Sioux to their third consecutive Frozen Four. They lost to Boston College in the semifinals. (AP)</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
