<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deputies to a U.S. Attorney Step Down</title>
    <meta content="07attorneys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/washington/07attorneys.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Minneapolis (Minn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paulose, Rachel K (US Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marti, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mozangue, Erika R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lackner, James E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota/Minneapolis and St. Paul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Minneapolis (Minn)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deputies to a U.S. Attorney Step Down</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Deputies to a U.S. Attorney Step Down</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON; Eric Lipton contributed reporting from Washington, and Libby Sander from Chicago.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rachel K Paulose has drawn criticism since her swearing-in ceremony in March as US attorney in Minneapolis; her top deputies, John Marti, Erika R Mozangue and James E Lackner, have stepped down from their leadership positions and returned to their prosecutorial jobs; several of their associates describe action as protest over Paulose's ideologically driven and dictatorial managerial style; she is first person of South Asian descent to be confirmed as US attorney; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rachel K. Paulose's swearing in on March 9 as the United States attorney in Minneapolis stirred debate in local legal circles because of the ceremonial trappings, including a performance by a municipal choir and a Marine Corps color guard, at the event attended by more than 300 people at the city's University of St. Thomas law school.</p>
        <p>But the complaints about Ms. Paulose's investiture seem mild in comparison with the uproar ignited on Thursday, when three of her top deputies stepped down from their leadership positions. Several of their associates described the action as a protest over what the three deputies regarded as Ms. Paulose's ideologically driven and dictatorial managerial style.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three of Rachel K. Paulose’s top deputies stepped down as a protest over her ideologically driven managerial style.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rachel K. Paulose's swearing in on March 9 as the United States attorney in Minneapolis stirred debate in local legal circles because of the ceremonial trappings, including a performance by a municipal choir and a Marine Corps color guard, at the event attended by more than 300 people at the city's University of St. Thomas law school.</p>
        <p>But the complaints about Ms. Paulose's investiture seem mild in comparison with the uproar ignited on Thursday, when three of her top deputies stepped down from their leadership positions. Several of their associates described the action as a protest over what the three deputies regarded as Ms. Paulose's ideologically driven and dictatorial managerial style.</p>
        <p>None of the three are quitting. Each is returning to a nonsupervisory role within the office, but their decisions to give up their managerial roles signaled a rebellion of sorts to Ms. Paulose. At 34, she is the first woman in the state's history to hold the job as United States attorney, and she is also the first person of South Asian descent in the country to be confirmed in that position.</p>
        <p>Ms. Paulose was a senior aide to Paul J. McNulty, the deputy attorney general, before she was named as an interim United States attorney in Minneapolis in early 2006. The appointment followed the resignation of Thomas B. Heffelfinger, who had been selected for the job in President Bush's first term.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heffelfinger said he left voluntarily and had been under no pressure to resign. He was, however, not among the Justice Department's most highly regarded prosecutors, according to department officials. They have not said whether, before his resignation, he had been on a list of possible candidates for removal.</p>
        <p>E-mail released by the department suggests that Mr. Heffelfinger may have been on a preliminary list. One e-mail message in January 2006 from D. Kyle Sampson, who was then chief of staff for Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales, to Harriet E. Miers, the White House counsel, listed seven prosecutors who might be removed.</p>
        <p>The names of three additional United States attorneys were edited from the copy of the e-mail message turned over to Congress, apparently because they had resigned and were replaced with other prosecutors slated for dismissal. Since Mr. Heffelfinger was among the three who resigned shortly after the e-mail was sent, there has been speculation he may have been on a list. He said he did not know whether he was ever on any such list.</p>
        <p>One Democratic senator said the problems in the Minneapolis office could reflect broader problems caused by last year's dismissals.</p>
        <p>''This is another example of the proud corps of U.S. attorneys being deprofessionalized,'' said the senator, Charles E. Schumer of New York, who has led the Congressional inquiry into the removals. ''We wonder in how many other offices the same lack of confidence is taking its toll. Attorney General Gonzales has a responsibility to see that the finest people are put in these positions, not simply cronies.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Paulose had experience as a federal prosecutor in Minnesota from 1999 to 2002. She is also one of several conservative lawyers who worked at Justice Department headquarters or the White House who have been named to top jobs in United States attorneys offices on an interim basis. Others are J. Timothy Griffin in Arkansas, Bradley J. Schlozman in Missouri, R. Alexander Acosta in Miami and Matthew M. Dummermuth in Iowa.</p>
        <p>Jeanne F. Cooney, a spokeswoman for the Minneapolis office, said on Friday that John Marti, the top assistant prosecutor; Erika R. Mozangue, chief of the office's civil division; and James E. Lackner, head of the office's criminal division, had returned to their prosecutorial jobs. Ms. Cooney said Ms. Paulose would have no comment.</p>
        <p>The decisions by the three prosecutors to step down came after a career prosecutor assigned to the Justice Department's United States attorney liaison office flew to Minneapolis on Thursday to meet with the prosecutors and Ms. Paulose in an unsuccessful effort to mediate the conflict.</p>
        <p>Brian Roehrkasse, a spokesman for the Justice Department, said in a statement that Ms. Paulose had been selected for the appointment only with the approval of Senator Norm Coleman, Republican of Minnesota, and had been unanimously confirmed by the Senate.</p>
        <p>''She is dedicated to leading an effective U.S. attorney's office in Minnesota and enforcing the laws to ensure public safety,'' Mr. Roehrkasse said. ''Three managers have determined to go back to the line to be full-time prosecutors protecting the community they serve, and the department respects their decisions.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Paulose's defenders at Justice Department headquarters said the criticism of her was unwarranted. They said older lawyers had difficultly dealing with a young, aggressive woman who had tried to put into place policies important to Mr. Gonzales like programs to combat child exploitation.</p>
        <p>Their associates said conflict had been steadily building since Ms. Paulose arrived as an interim prosecutor in early 2006. They said she had embraced the department's policies with a single-minded zeal that cost her the confidence and trust of lawyers in her office.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
