<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strong Suits and Voids, And Two Attempts at a Slam</title>
    <meta content="07card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/crosswords/bridge/07card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EED9173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strong Suits and Voids, And Two Attempts at a Slam</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Strong Suits and Voids, and Two Attempts at a Slam</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alder, Phillip</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over 10 days of play at a North American Bridge Championships, there are bound to be several interesting deals. The one in the diagram particularly caught my eye, for reasons that will become apparent.</p>
        <p>First, look only at the East hand. You are playing in the Vanderbilt Knockout Teams -- 64 head-to-head boards to decide which team moves into the next round. Your side is vulnerable and the opponents are nonvulnerable. Your left-hand opponent opens one club, your partner overcalls one diamond, and an aggressive bidder on your right passes. What would you do?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over 10 days of play at a North American Bridge Championships, there are bound to be several interesting deals. The one in the diagram particularly caught my eye, for reasons that will become apparent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over 10 days of play at a North American Bridge Championships, there are bound to be several interesting deals. The one in the diagram particularly caught my eye, for reasons that will become apparent.</p>
        <p>First, look only at the East hand. You are playing in the Vanderbilt Knockout Teams -- 64 head-to-head boards to decide which team moves into the next round. Your side is vulnerable and the opponents are nonvulnerable. Your left-hand opponent opens one club, your partner overcalls one diamond, and an aggressive bidder on your right passes. What would you do?</p>
        <p>This deal occurred when my teammates, Jeff Aker of Briarcliff, N.Y., and Glenn Milgrim and Barry Rigal of New York, and I lost to the eventual winners, Christal Henner-Welland, Bjorn Fallenius and Roy Welland of New York, Antonio Sementa from Italy and Cezary Balicki and Adam Zmudzinski from Poland. The pivotal deal, which cost 20 of the 22 international match points by which we were defeated, was when I failed to find the opening lead to defeat five clubs doubled in the final quarter. But that deal was too complicated for a newspaper column. (It is described on Page 9 of Daily Bulletin 9, which can be found at web2.acbl.org/nabcbulletins/2007spring/db9.pdf.) This deal was in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>The given bidding sequence occurred at the other table. Milgrim (South) opened one spade, getting his excellent five-card major into the auction immediately. Sementa (West) overcalled two diamonds, Aker (North) passed, and Henner-Welland made a three-spade splinter bid, promising at least four-card diamond support and game-going values with a singleton or void in spades. South, trading on the favorable vulnerability, jumped to five clubs in an effort to describe the nature of his hand.</p>
        <p>West cue-bid five hearts to show his first-round heart control and interest in a grand slam. This prompted North to sacrifice in six spades, but East passed, promising a first-round spade control. (With only a singleton, she would have doubled.) West happily converted to seven diamonds, knowing that a heart finesse, if needed, was likely to work because it would be through the opening bidder. Trusting his opponents and not willing to risk a large adverse swing, North bid seven spades. East doubled, saying that her first-round spade control was a void, not the singleton ace. (With the spade ace, East could have passed, inviting her partner to bid seven no-trump.)</p>
        <p>Declarer played carefully, despite the 3-0 trump break, to get out for down five.</p>
        <p>At the other table, Fallenius (South) opened one club, hoping conveniently to show both of his suits. But after Rigal (West) overcalled one diamond and Welland (North) passed, I wondered what had happened to the spades. Guessing correctly that South had length there and trying to keep him out of the auction, I leapt to six diamonds.</p>
        <p>South considered bidding six spades but eventually decided that was too big a position to take.</p>
        <p>After South passed, I mentally breathed a sigh of relief. But then my partner started thinking. And a few seconds later, he raised to seven diamonds. Aagghh!</p>
        <p>All was for the best, though. North led the heart seven. Declarer took South's king with his ace, played a diamond to dummy's (East's) jack to learn about the 3-0 split, returned a heart to his queen, cashed his diamond ace, led a diamond to dummy's queen and took the three top clubs, discarding two hearts and a spade. Declarer ruffed a heart in his hand, trumped a spade on the board, discarded his last spade on the heart ten and claimed.</p>
        <p>Minus 1,100 and plus 2,140 gave our team 14 imps in a losing cause.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
