<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Loved His Family, His Chili, His F.B.I.</title>
    <meta content="07agent" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/nyregion/07agent.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bank Robberies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Readington Township (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pnc Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Barry Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Loved His Family, His Chili, His F.B.I.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">He Loved His Family, His Chili, His F.B.I.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Barry Lee Bush, FBI agent killed on April 5 by apparent accidental discharge of another agent's weapon outside bank in Readington Township, NJ, where team of agents had tracked group of armed men; he was 51st agent killed on duty (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On stakeouts, Barry Lee Bush's favorite lunch was chili from Wendy's. He would talk lovingly of his wife, Karen, and two children, now 20 and 23, or his dream of retiring to a waterfront community to spend days staring at the ocean.</p>
        <p>Since his earliest days as a local law enforcement officer, Mr. Bush, 52, had dreamed of being an agent with the Federal Bureau of Investigation. All he disliked about the F.B.I. was the paperwork.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Thursday, after almost 20 years with the bureau, Barry Lee Bush became the 51st agent killed on duty in the F.B.I.’s history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On stakeouts, Barry Lee Bush's favorite lunch was chili from Wendy's. He would talk lovingly of his wife, Karen, and two children, now 20 and 23, or his dream of retiring to a waterfront community to spend days staring at the ocean.</p>
        <p>Since his earliest days as a local law enforcement officer, Mr. Bush, 52, had dreamed of being an agent with the Federal Bureau of Investigation. All he disliked about the F.B.I. was the paperwork.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, after almost 20 years with the bureau, he became the 51st agent killed on duty in its history, felled by the apparently accidental discharge of another agent's weapon outside a bank when they confronted a group of armed men they had been stalking for weeks.</p>
        <p>''He treated everybody with respect, whether you were having lunch together or he was arresting you,'' Mr. Bush's longtime friend and fellow agent, Jack Jupin, said in an interview Friday evening. ''He could have been a guy who worked in a department store.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush did not work in a department store, and on Friday there was a sadness at the F.B.I.'s building in Newark that seemed to seep into everything. Calls had come in from other F.B.I. offices around the country, and some even from people that Mr. Bush had helped arrest and send to prison. They all wanted to know how they could help and whether they could send money.</p>
        <p>''We're not dealing with this very well at the F.B.I.,'' Mr. Jupin said, lowering his head to hide a slight quiver around his lips. ''I think we can all relate to this kind of tragic death.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jupin, who has been with the bureau for 12 years, recalled his close work with Mr. Bush gathering and piecing together physical evidence from the 1998 bombings of United States Embassies in Kenya and Tanzania, and how one of his friend's favorite subjects, other than work, was his family.</p>
        <p>The life of an F.B.I. agent, he said, was what Mr. Bush had wanted since he entered law enforcement as a police officer in Pottstown, Pa.</p>
        <p>After serving on evidence response teams as a supervisor during the embassy bombing investigation and then a stint on the F.B.I.'s SWAT team, in recent years Mr. Bush had sought assignments in which he did not have to travel very far from home. Still, he worked long hours, Mr. Jupin said, recruiting informants and tracking down violent criminals but always resenting the paperwork involved.</p>
        <p>''Barry was old-time F.B.I. and loved to work the streets, and he was an excellent agent and even better person,'' Mr. Jupin said. ''He died the way he lived.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
