<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Argument Near Airport Turns Fatal</title>
    <meta content="07murder" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/nyregion/07murder.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kennedy International Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richards, Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buckley, Cara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Argument Near Airport Turns Fatal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Argument Near Airport Turns Fatal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARA BUCKLEY; Daryl Khan contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Buckley, Cara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott Richards is pronounced dead outside his home in Queens, where his companion drove him after she says he was shot twice in head by another man as the three of them were driving to Kennedy International Airport from Bronx; companion says gunman got out of car at airport and took a livery cab; police searching for suspect say killing might have involved drugs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Katherine Campbell awoke with a start before dawn yesterday. Someone was banging on her front door, and when she answered it, she found her nephew's companion standing there, sobbing and struggling to catch her breath.</p>
        <p>Ms. Campbell's nephew, Scott Richards, had been shot, the woman said. Ms. Campbell looked past the woman to the street, where a gold-colored Hyundai was double-parked and idling. She saw a shadowy form slumped in the passenger seat. It was Mr. Richards, and the woman said she had driven him to Ms. Campbell's Queens home from Kennedy International Airport because she did not know where else to go.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investigators were searching for a suspect and a motive in the murder of a man being driven to the airport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Katherine Campbell awoke with a start before dawn yesterday. Someone was banging on her front door, and when she answered it, she found her nephew's companion standing there, sobbing and struggling to catch her breath.</p>
        <p>Ms. Campbell's nephew, Scott Richards, had been shot, the woman said. Ms. Campbell looked past the woman to the street, where a gold-colored Hyundai was double-parked and idling. She saw a shadowy form slumped in the passenger seat. It was Mr. Richards, and the woman said she had driven him to Ms. Campbell's Queens home from Kennedy International Airport because she did not know where else to go.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richards, who was 34, was pronounced dead at the scene, and investigators were searching for a suspect and a motive yesterday, though law enforcement officials said it might have involved drugs.</p>
        <p>It took place as Mr. Richards, his companion and the suspect were driving on the Van Wyck Expressway toward Terminal 7 at J.F.K. around 5:30 a.m. The names of the suspect and Mr. Richards's companion were not released.</p>
        <p>The three got into the car earlier that morning in the Bronx, where Mr. Richards's companion lives. Either Mr. Richards or the suspect -- the police did not know which one -- was planning to take an early flight to Los Angeles, the woman later told the police. They had just arrived on airport property in the Hyundai, with the woman at the wheel, when the men started arguing.</p>
        <p>The suspect, who was sitting in the back seat, pulled out a gun and shot Mr. Richards twice in the head, the police said. Then the suspect ordered the woman to drop him off in front of the terminal, where he took a black livery cab.</p>
        <p>Panicked, the woman drove to Mr. Richards's home a short distance away on 123rd Avenue just off the Van Wyck near Rockaway Boulevard, where he lived with Ms. Campbell and other relatives.</p>
        <p>Ms. Campbell's husband dialed 911, and after the police arrived, Mr. Richards was pronounced dead at 5:51. Meanwhile, airport officials stopped a United Airlines flight, which was on the runway and set to depart for Los Angeles at 7, but they did not find the suspect, who was in his 20s and wearing a dress shirt, a tie, dark pants and a windbreaker, the police said.</p>
        <p>The woman's decision to drive to Mr. Richards's home instead of calling 911 baffled Mr. Richards's uncle, Samuel Walker.</p>
        <p>''Why did you drive a dead man from the airport to here?'' he said to the throng of reporters and news cameramen gathered yesterday outside the family's home. ''Why don't you stop and call the police?''</p>
        <p>The woman was being questioned by investigators. Ms. Campbell and Mr. Walker said they did not know her name.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richards, whose family is from Trinidad, had recently opened a rubbish disposal business, Mr. Walker said. He had four children, two living in Trinidad and two in New York, Mr. Walker said, though his current companion was not the mother.</p>
        <p>He served more than seven years in prison for manslaughter and possessing a weapon and was released in March 2004, according to a spokeswoman for the state Department of Correctional Services.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
