<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woods Is Three Over Par, But He's Still in the Game</title>
    <meta content="07anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/sports/golf/07anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Augusta National Golf Club</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woods Is Three Over Par, But He's Still in the Game</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Woods Is Three Over Par, but He’s Still in the Game</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, GA.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Augusta National's ninth hole, a dogleg par 4 of 460 yards that turns downhill then uphill, Tiger Woods hooked his tee shot so far into the pine trees on the left that you couldn't see him from behind the elevated green. And he couldn't see the green. All he could do was chip his ball laterally onto the fairway.</p>
        <p>As if that were not bad enough, his approach shot with an iron, after thudding onto the front of the green, spun back halfway down the slope. He used his wedge to skid the ball to about 8 feet above the hole and he made the putt to salvage a bogey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tiger Woods is five strokes off the lead and behind only 14 golfers at Augusta, but he can’t afford another 73-74.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Augusta National's ninth hole, a dogleg par 4 of 460 yards that turns downhill then uphill, Tiger Woods hooked his tee shot so far into the pine trees on the left that you couldn't see him from behind the elevated green. And he couldn't see the green. All he could do was chip his ball laterally onto the fairway.</p>
        <p>As if that were not bad enough, his approach shot with an iron, after thudding onto the front of the green, spun back halfway down the slope. He used his wedge to skid the ball to about 8 feet above the hole and he made the putt to salvage a bogey.</p>
        <p>With a three-over-par 39 on the front nine, Woods was four over par for the Masters in yesterday's second round. As he marched toward the 10th tee, he stared straight ahead, as if hoping that would translate into hitting his tee shots on the back nine straight instead of having to watch them soar left or right.</p>
        <p>Behind the roped walkway, several voices in the gallery yelled, ''Let's go, Tiger,'' then another voice chirped, ''30 on the back, baby.''</p>
        <p>Yes, 30 on the back, baby. In the opening round of his first Masters as a pro in 1997, the 21-year-old Woods, after struggling to a 40 on the front nine, shot a 30 on the back nine for a 70 en route to his record 12-stroke 18-under-par victory. At the time, nobody realized how special that round of 70 was.</p>
        <p>In the 71 Masters since 1934, hundreds of golfers have shot a 70, but according to the Augusta National archives, Woods is the only one to do it with nines of 40-30, a remarkable 10-stroke rally.</p>
        <p>The best Woods could do on the back nine yesterday was a one-under-par 35 for a 74 and a 36-hole total of 147, three over par, hardly the usual location for the winner of 4 Masters and 12 major championships. In most tournaments, he would already be too far behind too many golfers to challenge the leaders over the weekend, but not at this year's Masters, where the wind is swirling and the greens are so hard and fast that it's like putting on nearby Interstate 20.</p>
        <p>''Yesterday, I threw away a good round,'' he said of his 73 on Thursday. ''Today, I salvaged a bad one. I turned a 90 into a 74, kept myself right there in the ballgame.''</p>
        <p>Despite his six bogies and four birdies yesterday, Woods is only five strokes behind the co-leaders, Tim Clark, a South African who finished second to Phil Mickelson here last year, and Brett Wetterich, an American Ryder Cup rookie last year. Even more important, Woods is behind only 14 golfers with 36 holes remaining. With two rounds under 70, he might leapfrog all of them.</p>
        <p>But in the only two previous Masters in which he was over par after two rounds, Woods never contended. In 2003, he started 76-73 and tied for 15th despite a 66-75 finish as Mike Weir won. In 2000, he opened with 75-72 and finished fifth, despite a 68-69 rally, as Vijay Singh won.</p>
        <p>''This is probably as dry as it was in '99,'' Woods said, referring to when he tied for 18th after opening with 72-72. ''Only difference is, you've added 500 yards, about a billion trees and they've got rough out there. It's a totally different golf course than when we played in '99. It's just as dry. The greens are starting to get that little sheen to them. Putts are starting to roll out. Wind affects putts quite a bit. I hit a couple good putts, but a couple gusts knocked them way off line.''</p>
        <p>A gust also knocked his tee shot on the short No. 12 into Rae's Creek, leading to a bogey that dropped him to six over par for the tournament. On the 13th tee, a similar gust escorted a flock of birds that stopped Woods in midswing.</p>
        <p>''The birds flew right over me, and I stopped it somehow,'' he said. ''Felt like I broke my back, my wrist, my neck, my legs. I don't know how those baseball players do it, with those check swings. Felt like the shaft was going to snap.''</p>
        <p>Even when he was five over par for the tournament until he birdied Nos. 15 and 17, Woods insisted that he had not sneaked a peek at the leader board to see how far behind he was. He knew none of the leaders were about to run away, not in the unusual chill that is expected to continue over the weekend.</p>
        <p>''They're not going to go low here,'' Woods said. ''I played with Paul Casey today and he played just one of the great rounds of golf you'll ever see, and shot 68. With the conditions on the weekend, we're all going to have to grind. Whether you're a rookie or a vet, you're going to have your hands full this weekend.''</p>
        <p>Or whether you're the world's No. 1-ranked golfer. Woods is five strokes off the lead and behind only 14 golfers, but he can't afford another 73-74.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
