<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Place for Minimalism Amid Long, Loud Notes</title>
    <meta content="07dice" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/arts/music/07dice.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070410T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Pop</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Guitars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D8173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Place for Minimalism Amid Long, Loud Notes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Place for Minimalism Amid Long, Loud Notes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was Mick Barr's night. On stage Wednesday at Studio B in Greenpoint, Brooklyn, he stood with his electric guitar, eaves of long hair falling on either side of his face, nodding at his work. His piece -- it was only one piece -- started with one repeated loud staccato note, played with a pick ad infinitum as a seemingly endless dexterity drill.</p>
        <p>This was Ocrilim, Mr. Barr's latest project for solo electric guitar. What he was doing here relates to what he does in his guitar-drums duos Orthrelm and Hella. After 20 seconds came the first hurdle for the brain: this note isn't going to change, is it? Of course it did, but not until it started to sound different, until you weren't hearing just the pitch of the note but also the shape and snap of it, and the whupa-whupa-whupa made by hand, pick, string and the pickup of his Gibson SG. It sounded like something. Like what? Oh, yeah, helicopter blades rotating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was Mick Barr’s night. On stage Wednesday at Studio B in Greenpoint, Brooklyn, he stood with his electric guitar, eaves of long hair falling on either side of his face, nodding at his work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was Mick Barr's night. On stage Wednesday at Studio B in Greenpoint, Brooklyn, he stood with his electric guitar, eaves of long hair falling on either side of his face, nodding at his work. His piece -- it was only one piece -- started with one repeated loud staccato note, played with a pick ad infinitum as a seemingly endless dexterity drill.</p>
        <p>This was Ocrilim, Mr. Barr's latest project for solo electric guitar. What he was doing here relates to what he does in his guitar-drums duos Orthrelm and Hella. After 20 seconds came the first hurdle for the brain: this note isn't going to change, is it? Of course it did, but not until it started to sound different, until you weren't hearing just the pitch of the note but also the shape and snap of it, and the whupa-whupa-whupa made by hand, pick, string and the pickup of his Gibson SG. It sounded like something. Like what? Oh, yeah, helicopter blades rotating.</p>
        <p>Then, intermittently, a short, snaky chromatic figure worked itself into the long strings of single notes. And again, this time reordered, almost sounding as if the notes were played in reverse order. And finally the one-note wall gave way to wider, developing figures, but still at that same tempo of the whupa-whupa-whupa. What Mr. Barr is up to could be the solitary-artist extension of death metal; it also could be the rock extension of Coltrane's ''Interstellar Space.'' What Mr. Barr doesn't stop at, thankfully, is minimalism. He used mesmerizing repetition, definitely, for stretches. The piece lasted about 45 minutes, routing through gently bent bar chords and long, finger-busting episodes where his fretting hand stayed in one position but the fingers jumped like popcorn. But as the song grew it developed along clean lines of Western harmony, in ways that finally complimented the brain for what it knew, rather than stumping it by what it didn't understand. The music didn't retreat into itself; it was exciting.</p>
        <p>Black Dice, the 10-year-old Brooklyn trio that headlined the show, wasn't on its best game. Concept-slingers as much as musicians, they've gone from broken, thrashing aggression to amiable droning, and now into something much more earnestly rhythmic, or polyrhythmic. But at any given time, the band's music hasn't stayed in one place, and it never reduces easily. All non-notated music benefits from little discrepancies of phrasing and groove between players: this creates tension and promotes the human touch. But Black Dice's rhythmic discrepancies, as its members layered the rhythms with squelching keyboard noises and guitar notes, were so big that sometimes you couldn't tell what they were intending -- whether they wanted their rhythms so off-centered or not.</p>
        <p>It definitely wasn't the night for No Age, which opened the show, even though there's a clever pop band inside the sawed-off racket of these two guys from Los Angeles, Randy Randall and Dean Spunt. Mr. Spunt is an awkward drummer; Mr. Randall is a less awkward guitarist. Their songs begin artlessly, as if heading nowhere fast, only to become bigger than you might have expected, with the activation of a digital pedal or a new riff. But on Wednesday they just weren't making friends with their materials. They used minidiscs to create extra sound layers, and the discs weren't working. The kick drum got pushed out from Mr. Spunt's heavy thumping, and he kicked it over, continuing without it for a while. The crash cymbal kept falling over. ''I feel like this is way too uncalled-for-ly sloppy,'' Mr. Randall said. And he was right. After about 15 minutes, they just gave up.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 10, 2007, Tuesday  A music review on Saturday about a solo guitar performance by Mick Barr, at Studio B in Brooklyn, referred incorrectly to the band Hella and to Mr. Barr's association with the band. While Mr. Barr has released duo recordings with Zach Hill, Hella's drummer, Hella is not a duo and Mr. Barr is not a member.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 10, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A music review on Saturday about a solo guitar performance by Mick Barr, at Studio B in Brooklyn, referred incorrectly to the band Hella and to Mr. Barr's association with the band. While Mr. Barr has released duo recordings with Zach Hill, Hella's drummer, Hella is not a duo and Mr. Barr is not a member.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
