<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gordon and Bulls Deal a Blow to the Nets' Confidence</title>
    <meta content="07nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gordon and Bulls Deal a Blow to the Nets' Confidence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets have been inching toward solidifying a playoff spot, and they have become secure enough with themselves to withstand setbacks.</p>
        <p>By that standard, Friday night's brutal 105-74 loss to the Chicago Bulls at the United Center did not leave them floored. It was the Nets' most lopsided loss since they fell to the Orlando Magic by 33 points on Feb. 2, their worst loss of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nets have been inching toward solidifying a playoff spot, and they have become secure enough with themselves to withstand setbacks.</p>
        <p>By that standard, Friday night's brutal 105-74 loss to the Chicago Bulls at the United Center did not leave them floored. It was the Nets' most lopsided loss since they fell to the Orlando Magic by 33 points on Feb. 2, their worst loss of the season.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more bruising to the Nets' ego, however, is the fact that they are out of the race for the Atlantic Division, which they had won in four of the previous five seasons. By virtue of the Nets' defeat and the Toronto Raptors' victory over the Philadelphia 76ers on Friday night, Toronto (43-33) secured its first division title in franchise history.</p>
        <p>With their playoff fate still in limbo, the Nets (35-40) seemed to accept their dethronement with apathy.</p>
        <p>''That doesn't mean anything,'' said point guard Jason Kidd, who sparked the Nets' run of division titles when he came to the team five seasons ago.</p>
        <p>Nets guard Vince Carter spent his first six and a half seasons with the Raptors. ''Congratulations to them,'' he said with a slight twist of the mouth and a shrug.</p>
        <p>As it stands, the Bulls (46-31) and the Nets would face each other in the first round of the playoffs. That prospect led Bulls Coach Scott Skiles to treat Friday night's game with diligence, in light of what the Nets had done to his team earlier in the season.</p>
        <p>The Nets overcame 18-point deficits to win in each of their previous two games against the Bulls.</p>
        <p>''We'd like to play well,'' Skiles said before Friday night's game. ''We don't want them feeling, if they are our opponent, that somehow in every game they can just turn it on and blow right by us, which they've done in both games.''</p>
        <p>On Friday night, Skiles's team again quickly jumped ahead of the Nets.</p>
        <p>Midway through the first quarter, the Bulls had an 11-point lead.</p>
        <p>The Nets' were pitiful on offense, missing their first nine shots. Only two of those attempts were from inside 14 feet. The Nets settled for outside jumpers on a night when they should have been looking to attack in the paint. The Bulls played without their starting center, Ben Wallace, and their emerging power forward, Tyrus Thomas. Both missed the game with illnesses. Together they account for an average of more than three blocks a game.</p>
        <p>The Nets also did not do much to slow Chicago's attack. The Bulls shot 59.1 percent from the field in the first quarter and 48.9 percent in the first half. During a 10-0 run late in the second quarter, the Bulls scored on five of seven possessions, capped by a 20-footer from guard Kirk Hinrich that made the score 51-33 with 2 minutes 27 seconds remaining in the half.</p>
        <p>Ben Gordon led the Bulls with 27 points.</p>
        <p>The Nets, who shot 34.2 percent in the game, were led by Carter's 21 points.</p>
        <p>''You get out of it what you put into it,'' Nets Coach Lawrence Frank said. ''We didn't put a whole lot into the game. You got to give Chicago credit. They beat us in every single facet of the game.''</p>
        <p>The Nets remained within reach of the sixth spot, held by Washington. The Wizards will finish the season without two injured stars, Gilbert Arenas and Caron Butler. Starting Saturday night, the Nets have two games remaining against the Wizards (39-36), who lost to the Cleveland Cavaliers on Friday night for their third consecutive defeat.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Nets' Serbian center Nenad Krstic, whose season ended with a torn anterior cruciate ligament in December, traveled with the team for the first time since his injury. Krstic, who hopes to start running by next month, said he wanted to get out of the house and that Chicago had ''a big Serbian population here, so there's a lot of Serbian restaurants here.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
