<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Now, Donovan Has a Haven</title>
    <meta content="07rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/sports/ncaabasketball/07rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Donovan, Billy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rhoden, William C</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Now, Donovan Has a Haven</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Now, Donovan Has a Haven</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after his Florida team won its third consecutive Southeastern Conference tournament championship last month, Billy Donovan and I stood outside Donovan's office, speaking more as human beings who had known each other for 20 years than as coach and reporter.</p>
        <p>We first met when Donovan was a high school star at St. Agnes on Long Island. I followed his career through Providence and an assortment of college coaching jobs, culminating with his being hired at Florida.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sports arena is a difficult place in which to find sustained peace of mind and for the moment, the University of Florida loves Billy Donovan and Donovan loves Florida.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A day after his Florida team won its third consecutive Southeastern Conference tournament championship last month, Billy Donovan and I stood outside Donovan's office, speaking more as human beings who had known each other for 20 years than as coach and reporter.</p>
        <p>We first met when Donovan was a high school star at St. Agnes on Long Island. I followed his career through Providence and an assortment of college coaching jobs, culminating with his being hired at Florida.</p>
        <p>Somehow our conversation last month focused on quality of life, and Donovan brought up the concept of inner peace. ''What's the one thing that everyone wants, the only thing that really matters in life?'' Donovan asked. ''Peace of mind, inner peace.''</p>
        <p>We exchanged personal anecdotes about events -- some happy, some sad -- that changed our priorities and perspectives. March was the anniversary of my older sister's death; Donovan shared that a close friend had learned of a devastating medical diagnosis that morning. We talked about how one phone call could turn your life upside down, make things that seemed so pressing one moment become irrelevant the next.</p>
        <p>In light of Donovan's decision on Thursday to remain at the University of Florida, I realized that he was telling me that he had found a home -- and a measure of peace -- in Gainesville.</p>
        <p>Eleven days after Donovan and I had our conversation, Tubby Smith announced quite suddenly that he was leaving Kentucky after 10 seasons and becoming head coach at the University of Minnesota.</p>
        <p>Everyone's first reaction was that Donovan would succeed Smith. In Kentucky's inflated view of itself, Donovan was the perfect candidate. He had been an assistant under Rick Pitino at Kentucky, had the high profile and had the prestige and the cachet of having led Florida to consecutive national championships.</p>
        <p>Donovan would have made oodles of money at Kentucky, would have had even more prestige, but he would never, ever have had peace of mind. Florida allowed Donovan to grow, allowed him to make mistakes and to learn from the mistakes and come back stronger. So I wasn't terribly surprised on Thursday when Donovan officially turned down the Kentucky job. At his news conference, Donovan told reporters: ''I love Florida. I felt that at this time in my life, the best place for me was the University of Florida.''</p>
        <p>At the same time -- and for all the talk about peace of mind -- Donovan has to know that peace is tough to find in his business and even tougher to maintain. Peace of mind in the fluid and often mercenary sports industry is fleeting, at best.</p>
        <p>''And it's elusive,'' Smith said yesterday from his apartment in Minnesota. Ten years ago, Smith appeared to have discovered peace in Lexington. He became Kentucky's head coach, the university's first African-American head coach, in May 1997. In his first season, Smith led the Wildcats to their seventh N.C.A.A. men's Division I basketball title, its second in three seasons.</p>
        <p>In retrospect, Smith said the feeling he had after winning the championship was not peace but inner confidence -- confidence in his acumen as a top-flight head coach. There is no sustained peace at Kentucky or in any program where winning is important.</p>
        <p>After being in a program or at a place for a long time, you can tell when the peace is beginning to fade -- when what was right is suddenly wrong. Smith recalled: ''You start hearing comments from your superiors like, 'You don't seem to be happy, Tubby' or 'You don't seem to have that same energy, Tubby.' That's sending a message to you.''</p>
        <p>Smith's sudden resignation on March 22 fell two months short of what would have been his 10th anniversary at Kentucky. He left with an impressive résumé: a national championship, a 16-0 regular-season conference record in 2003, five SEC regular-season championships, five SEC tournament titles, two Round of 16 finishes and three finishes in the Round of 8. In 10 seasons.</p>
        <p>Smith wasn't fleeing Kentucky. ''It wasn't a matter of running from anything; it was a matter of running to a situation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Minnesota is the polar opposite of Kentucky. Where Kentucky devours coaches -- and feels it has a Rupp-ian right to devour them -- Minnesota is desperate for success after several disappointing seasons. The program has been demoralized since 1999, when it was scandalized by academic fraud during Clem Haskins's regime. Last season, Minnesota had its first-ever 20-loss season.</p>
        <p>The sports arena is a difficult place in which to find sustained peace of mind. For the moment, the University of Florida loves Donovan and Donovan loves the University of Florida. But things change rapidly. On Thursday, Donovan's four best players, the foundation of his back-to-back championship teams, announced that they were turning pro. If the Gators falter next season, Donovan will receive a pass; maybe he'll receive one in the season after that. But Donovan has created a thirst for winning that in many ways is antithetical to the peace of mind we talked about outside his office.</p>
        <p>The solution lies in the message he drilled into his team's psyche the past two seasons: live for the moment, live for the dream.</p>
        <p>Grab peace where you can find it.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
