<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Karzai Says He Has Met With Some Taliban Members in an Effort at Reconciliation</title>
    <meta content="07afghan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/world/asia/07afghan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sangin (Afghanistan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karzai, Hamid (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Omar, Mullah Mohammad</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Taliban</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Karzai, Hamid</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Karzai Says He Has Met With Some Taliban Members in an Effort at Reconciliation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Karzai Says He Has Met With Some Taliban Members in an Effort at Reconciliation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>KABUL, Afghanistan, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Hamid Karzai has held meetings with members of Taliban as part of reconciliation effort, but he rules out talks with Taliban leader, Mullah Muhammad Omar, or foreign militants fighting with Taliban; makes comments as Taliban claims responsibility for suicide bombing in Kabul that killed six people, and as NATO battles Taliban for control of Sangin, important town in southern Afghanistan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Hamid Karzai said Friday, for the first time, that he had held meetings with members of the Taliban as part of a reconciliation effort, but he ruled out talks with the Taliban leader, Mullah Muhammad Omar, or foreign militants fighting with the Taliban.</p>
        <p>He made the comments as the Taliban claimed responsibility for a suicide bombing in the capital that killed six people, and as NATO battled Taliban forces for control of an important town in southern Afghanistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Hamid Karzai held meetings with members of the Taliban but ruled out talks with the Taliban leader, Mullah Muhammad Omar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Hamid Karzai said Friday, for the first time, that he had held meetings with members of the Taliban as part of a reconciliation effort, but he ruled out talks with the Taliban leader, Mullah Muhammad Omar, or foreign militants fighting with the Taliban.</p>
        <p>He made the comments as the Taliban claimed responsibility for a suicide bombing in the capital that killed six people, and as NATO battled Taliban forces for control of an important town in southern Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>''We've had representatives from the Taliban meeting with the different bodies of the Afghan government for a long time,'' Mr. Karzai said at a news conference at the presidential palace. ''I've had some Taliban coming to speak to me as well, so this process has been there for a long time.'' Mr. Karzai set up a reconciliation commission in 2005 to woo Taliban members over to the government, but it has had limited success.</p>
        <p>''Afghan Taliban are the sons of this soil,'' he said. ''As they repent, as they regret, as they want to come back to their own country, they are welcome.''</p>
        <p>''About Mr. Mullah Omar, that's a different issue,'' he said. ''The foreign Taliban are not welcome. They should be kicked out, should be destroyed; they are destroying our lives, killing our people. They are not welcome, and there will be no talks with them.''</p>
        <p>A senior government official confirmed recently that the president was in touch with some high-level members of the Taliban but stressed that contacts were with individuals and not with the movement as a whole.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karzai also ruled out making any further concessions to Taliban kidnappers. He said he had freed five members of the Taliban in exchange for the freedom of an Italian journalist recently because the Italian government, which has 1,800 troops in Afghanistan, might have collapsed over the issue.</p>
        <p>''The Italian prime minister called me several times and asked for cooperation from our side,'' Mr. Karzai said. ''The Italian government was facing collapse.''</p>
        <p>He has been criticized over the deal, and there has been a rash of kidnappings since it took place. Five Afghan health officials were kidnapped last week, and a Taliban spokesman said the movement was holding two French aid workers who were reported missing along with three Afghans on Wednesday in southwestern Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karzai said he would not repeat such a prisoner exchange. ''No more deals, with no one and with no other country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The North Atlantic Treaty Organization said Friday that it had taken control of the strategic town of Sangin, in southern Helmand Province, from Taliban forces. The town has been in Taliban hands for months, despite the nearby presence of NATO and Afghan bases. A center of poppy cultivation and drug smuggling, Sangin lies on the road to the Kajaki dam, the main source of electricity to southern Afghanistan. The American government is planning $10 million in renovations to the dam, but the strong presence of Taliban forces in the region has prevented work for over a year.</p>
        <p>NATO forces began an airborne assault on the town on Wednesday night, mobilizing 1,000 NATO and Afghan forces. It secured the town on Friday morning, the military said in a statement. Residents said the town center was badly damaged from two weeks of bombardment by NATO forces, and tribal elders eventually persuaded the Taliban to pull out.</p>
        <p>''The elders begged the Taliban to evacuate the territory,'' said Izatullah, a shopkeeper in Sangin who was contacted by telephone. He said the elders were mediating between the Taliban and British forces, which are part of NATO's International Security Assistance Force, to negotiate a long-term truce.</p>
        <p>The suicide car bombing in southwestern Kabul on Friday morning killed six people, including a police officer who was trying to stop the bomber. The police at the scene said two people in a taxicab were seen driving slowly along a main street and the police commander of a nearby police station, Wazir Agha, ordered them to halt. As he opened the car door, the car exploded, throwing his body across the street.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
