<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Six Flags Is Planning Your Next Vacation</title>
    <meta content="07interview" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/business/07interview.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SATURDAY INTERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Six Flags Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shapiro, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Juston</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Six Flags Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Shapiro, Mark</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2D7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Six Flags Is Planning Your Next Vacation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Six Flags Is Planning Your Next Vacation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUSTON JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Juston</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from interview with Six Fl</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six Flags has long been a popular place for teenagers to hang out during the summer. But the image of rambunctious teenagers isn't what Mark Shapiro, the 37-year-old chief executive, wants to come to mind at the mention of the company. He is on a mission to make Six Flags a family destination.</p>
        <p>He spoke recently about how the company is focusing on the preteenage market, compared the cost of a trip to an amusement park with a night at a ballpark and discussed borrowing from the Disney playbook. Following are excerpts:</p>
        <p>Q. How many parks are open now?</p>
        <p>A. We have eight that are open every day right now. Six Flags Great Adventure in Jackson, N.J., is open every day through April 15 because it's spring break. And beginning April 15, all parks will be open every weekend until Memorial Day, when they will open full time for the summer.</p>
        <p>Q. How many parks do you own?</p>
        <p>A. There are 20 operating parks, as well as one in New Orleans. But that one might not come back because of damage sustained during Hurricane Katrina.</p>
        <p>Q. What new features are planned for the parks this year?</p>
        <p>A. It varies. From Memorial Day till Labor Day, there will be a different concert every Thursday night at all the parks. For example, the New England park in Springfield, Mass., in June will have Chris Daughtry of ''American Idol'' fame, and they will also have Bow Wow. Corbin Bleu from Disney's ''High School Musical'' is going to be at one of the parks, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark Shapiro, the 37-year-old chief executive, is on a mission to make Six Flags a family destination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Six Flags has long been a popular place for teenagers to hang out during the summer. But the image of rambunctious teenagers isn't what Mark Shapiro, the 37-year-old chief executive, wants to come to mind at the mention of the company. He is on a mission to make Six Flags a family destination.</p>
        <p>He spoke recently about how the company is focusing on the preteenage market, compared the cost of a trip to an amusement park with a night at a ballpark and discussed borrowing from the Disney playbook. Following are excerpts:</p>
        <p>Q. How many parks are open now?</p>
        <p>A. We have eight that are open every day right now. Six Flags Great Adventure in Jackson, N.J., is open every day through April 15 because it's spring break. And beginning April 15, all parks will be open every weekend until Memorial Day, when they will open full time for the summer.</p>
        <p>Q. How many parks do you own?</p>
        <p>A. There are 20 operating parks, as well as one in New Orleans. But that one might not come back because of damage sustained during Hurricane Katrina.</p>
        <p>Q. What new features are planned for the parks this year?</p>
        <p>A. It varies. From Memorial Day till Labor Day, there will be a different concert every Thursday night at all the parks. For example, the New England park in Springfield, Mass., in June will have Chris Daughtry of ''American Idol'' fame, and they will also have Bow Wow. Corbin Bleu from Disney's ''High School Musical'' is going to be at one of the parks, too.</p>
        <p>We also have a host of new licensed intellectual property this year. We will have a Wiggles World at several of our parks. We will have Thomas the Tank Engine Towns. We also struck a deal with Tony Hawk, the extreme sports star, and are opening Tony Hawk roller coasters in San Antonio and St. Louis. We are also launching a massive stunt show called Operation SpyGirl. It was co-developed by the creator of the TV show ''24.'' It is the story of a girl who has 24 minutes to save the world. If it does well in Chicago, we will open it up in several of the parks next year.</p>
        <p>Q. When you became chief executive, you said that Six Flags had to become less reliant on big rides and had to diversify into concerts and themed attractions. Is this the execution of that strategy?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. All of this is illustrative of our mission to broaden our entertainment offerings for the entire family. We are now targeting the tweens, or preteens. That is a new course for Six Flags. Before I came on board in 2005, the main target of the company was teenagers. While we want to retain those teenagers, we are aiming for the family crowd. And the members of the family who usually dictate where the family goes are usually the tweens.</p>
        <p>Q. Did you know that there is a Wikipedia entry devoted to ''incidents,'' or accidents, at Six Flags parks?</p>
        <p>A. No, but I'm not surprised.</p>
        <p>Q. How do you address the safety concerns of customers?</p>
        <p>A. Safety is our No. 1 priority. We spend a tremendous amount of money on maintenance, ride inspections and on technicians at every park, not only to make sure that we are complying with state standards, which vary from state to state, but also to be certain that we have full confidence in our rides. Every ride is tested every day at every park.</p>
        <p>Q. You went to Six Flags after more than a decade of working at ESPN, which is owned by Walt Disney. Your parks compete directly with Disney's parks. Have you taken any ideas from Disney or tried to duplicate anything that you think works for them?</p>
        <p>A. I think Disney does things especially well in two areas. The first is unparalleled guest service. When you work for Disney, whether you are working at a theme park or at ESPN, you're taught what it means to be a cast member, what it means to keep the customer happy and smiling. They wrote the book on it, and we have tried to take a page out of their book as we have rebuilt Six Flags. By doing it, we focus on training, recruitment and retention.</p>
        <p>The other area where they are terrific is in storytelling. When you go to a theme park, it is an escape from everyday life.</p>
        <p>Q. In your last earnings statement, you reported a wider loss in 2006 than in 2005. How are you going to keep that from happening this year?</p>
        <p>A. We have reduced capital expenditures by $40 million, and we expect to get closer to being cash-flow positive through improving our operational performance. To do that we are spending more than the company has ever spent on advertising to increase attendance and the amount that each guest spends. We are very close to an average of $40 a guest per visit.</p>
        <p>Q. But at $40 a guest, has family fun become unaffordable for the average household?</p>
        <p>A. Absolutely not. Baseball's opening day was earlier this week, and I was watching the news and heard that the average ticket price for a baseball game is in the mid-$20's. And that's just to get into the game. Forget about parking, food, souvenirs. And the game only lasts two hours. At Six Flags, the average ticket price is $21, and there are discounts all over the community, from Coke to McDonald's, that cut into that even further. And the parks are open about 12 hours a day.</p>
        <p>And the season pass is even a better value. You can get into a park every day all season long for $50 to $60. Try buying a season ticket to the Yankees or Red Sox or Cubs. You'd likely be paying several hundred dollars.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY INTERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
