<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chlorine Gas Attack by Truck Bomber Kills Up to 30 in Iraq</title>
    <meta content="07iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/world/middleeast/07iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chlorine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ramadi (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Alissa J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6D7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chlorine Gas Attack by Truck Bomber Kills Up to 30 in Iraq</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chlorine Gas Attack by Truck Bomber Kills Up to 30 in Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISSA J. RUBIN; Qais Mizher contributed reporting from Baghdad, and Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Baghdad, Diwaniya and Ramadi.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubin, Alissa J</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Suicide truck bomb loaded with chlorine gas explodes in Ramadi, Iraq, killing as many as 30 people, many of them children (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A suicide truck bomb loaded with chlorine gas exploded in Ramadi on Friday, killing as many as 30 people, many of them children, a security official said.</p>
        <p>The explosion burned victims' lungs, eyes and skin. Dr. Ali Abdullah Saleh, of the main Ramadi hospital, said 30 people had been admitted with shrapnel wounds and 15 had been sent to a second hospital in the city. He said 50 people had been admitted for breathing problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A suicide truck bomb loaded with chlorine gas exploded in Ramadi on Friday, killing as many as 30 people, many of them children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A suicide truck bomb loaded with chlorine gas exploded in Ramadi on Friday, killing as many as 30 people, many of them children, a security official said.</p>
        <p>The explosion burned victims' lungs, eyes and skin. Dr. Ali Abdullah Saleh, of the main Ramadi hospital, said 30 people had been admitted with shrapnel wounds and 15 had been sent to a second hospital in the city. He said 50 people had been admitted for breathing problems.</p>
        <p>It was at least the sixth chlorine bomb detonated in Anbar Province since late January and the most lethal, though it appears that most victims were killed by the explosion rather than the chlorine. Insurgents have also used chlorine bombs in the northern part of Baghdad, the capital, and near Taji, a town about 20 miles to the north.</p>
        <p>The attacker in Ramadi struck in the late morning of the Muslim day of prayer, when children off from school usually play in the street and adults run errands and visit before going to the mosque at midday.</p>
        <p>The truck, a fuel tanker loaded with the toxic gas, sped toward an Iraqi police checkpoint, according to witnesses and Col. Tareq al-Dulaimi, the head of security for Anbar Province. The police officers opened fire and the truck swerved toward a residential area, where the bomb exploded, he said.</p>
        <p>The United States military said in a statement that some victims had been evacuated to hospitals at American facilities in Iraq. The military said that the use of chlorine gas had been suspected but not confirmed, and that it was unclear whether the explosion had been set off by the police gunfire or by the suicide bomber.</p>
        <p>Anbar Province is a stronghold of the Sunni insurgency, and a haven for the insurgent group Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia. There has been fierce fighting in the area between tribes who support Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia and those who oppose it and now work more closely with the government. In the past two months, there have been assassinations and bomb attacks on the tribes opposing Al Qaeda, including three truck bombs filled with chlorine gas in mid-March.</p>
        <p>In military action, there was a daylong fight between American soldiers and Shiite militia members in the city of Diwaniya, south of Baghdad, a statement from the Fourth Brigade Combat Team of the 25th Infantry Division in Baghdad said. The operation's goal seemed to be to reduce the influence of Shiite militias in the area.</p>
        <p>Residents of Diwaniya said the operation began before dawn when Iraqi and American soldiers closed off neighborhoods known to be havens for Shiite militias, including the Mahdi Army, aligned with the radical Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr. Residents said the soldiers distributed pamphlets asking people to cooperate with the American and Iraqi troops and then began house-to-house searches.</p>
        <p>The statement said three militia members were killed and six wounded. The police put the death toll at 10 but said several were civilians killed during the shooting.</p>
        <p>American and Iraqi forces uncovered an assembly area for the powerful roadside bombs known as explosively formed projectiles, the statement said. Four bombs were already assembled, it added, and others were in various stages of being put together.</p>
        <p>Residents said there had been open fighting in central Diwaniya between American soldiers and members of the Mahdi Army. There seemed to be little effort on the part of local residents to defend the militia, they said. Several said they held militia members responsible for killings and kidnappings in the area.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadr's office in Diwaniya sharply criticized the operation. ''This operation is unjustified,'' said Haydar al-Natiq, who runs the office. ''It will stir up the situation in the time where a peace conference was supposed to be held between the Sadrists and the security forces.''</p>
        <p>In Baghdad, 11 bodies were found Friday, the Interior Ministry announced. Mortars and gunfire killed at least four others in the capital, it said. Residents in the predominantly Sunni Arab district of Adamiya said American soldiers had killed a civilian in the neighborhood. The American military said it had no information on the episode.</p>
        <p>The United States military said Friday in a statement that a soldier had been shot to death in Kirkuk Province on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The bomb blast in Anbar Province left residents shaken.</p>
        <p>Sabir Muhammad al-Rishawi, a shopkeeper who sells mobile phones, was close to the explosion.</p>
        <p>''There were many people outside their homes because usually on Friday, you see a lot of activity in our area,'' he said. ''Then we saw a fuel tanker come close to the police checkpoint. The policemen shot at the driver and he exploded his truck to destroy the building close to the area he was trying to bomb. I felt my temperature start to rise and then we knew that there was chlorine in the bombs.''</p>
        <p>Chlorine is widely available because it is used in water purification plants. Insurgents linked to Al Qaeda have become increasingly adept at stealing the chlorine, raiding water plants in the areas of Anbar that they control, said Colonel Dulaimi, the Anbar security chief.</p>
        <p>The chlorine is trucked from Jordan and Syria. Insurgents recently held up four chlorine trucks on the route to Water Ministry warehouses in Baghdad. As a result, Anbar officials stopped 12 other chlorine trucks that were in Trebil, near the Jordanian border.</p>
        <p>''We've stopped these trucks from moving further into Anbar until we can prepare good protective convoy for them,'' Colonel Dulaimi said.</p>
        <p>Chlorine gas, first used in World War I, is a choking agent. There is no antidote for it. The only remedy is to try to remove it from clothes, skin and eyes with soap and water, according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta. If the exposure is limited, people generally survive without suffering lasting damage.</p>
        <p>The symptoms can be as slight as a burning in the lungs, coughing, tearing eyes and a burning sensation on the skin. Or they can be far more dire, destroying the delicate lung tissue and making people feel as if they are suffocating.</p>
        <p>Colonel Dulaimi said that even though the bomb destroyed a building with six apartments, the city was fortunate.</p>
        <p>''God was helping families in Ramadi today, because the wind was blowing away from the residential area and toward an empty area,'' he said ''If the wind direction had not been like this, there would have been a huge tragedy in Ramadi today.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
