<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Top Aide to Gonzales Resigns, Becoming Latest Fallout Casualty</title>
    <meta content="07goodling" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/washington/07goodling.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Relations and Publicity</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stout, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzales, Alberto R (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodling, Monica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Relations and Publicity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Goodling, Monica</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gonzales, Alberto R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Top Aide to Gonzales Resigns, Becoming Latest Fallout Casualty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Top Aide to Gonzales Resigns, Becoming Latest Fallout Casualty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STOUT and DAVID JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David; Stout, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Monica Goodling, top aide to Atty Gen Alberto R Gonzales, resigns, becoming another casualty of political storm that has rocked Justice Dept in aftermath of last year's dismissals of eight US attorneys; Goodling helped to coordinate those dismissals with White House, episode that has provoked demands for Gonzales's dismissal; even Gonzales's allies, including Pres Bush, say dismissals were bungled from public relations and political standpoint; Goodling has notified Senate Judiciary Committee that she would invoke her constitutional right not to testify in panel's inquiry about dismissals (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A top aide to Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales resigned on Friday, becoming another casualty of the political storm that has rocked the Justice Department in the aftermath of last year's dismissals of eight United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>The aide, Monica Goodling, had helped to coordinate those dismissals with the White House, an episode that has provoked demands for Mr. Gonzales's dismissal. Even Mr. Gonzales's allies, including President Bush, say the dismissals were bungled from a public relations and political standpoint.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Monica Goodling had helped to coordinate the dismissals of eight U.S. attorneys with the White House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A top aide to Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales resigned on Friday, becoming another casualty of the political storm that has rocked the Justice Department in the aftermath of last year's dismissals of eight United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>The aide, Monica Goodling, had helped to coordinate those dismissals with the White House, an episode that has provoked demands for Mr. Gonzales's dismissal. Even Mr. Gonzales's allies, including President Bush, say the dismissals were bungled from a public relations and political standpoint.</p>
        <p>Ms. Goodling, who has been on leave as the Justice Department's liaison to the White House, notified the Senate Judiciary Committee through her lawyer on March 26 that she would invoke her constitutional right not to testify in the panel's inquiry about the dismissals -- not because she had anything to hide, the lawyer said, but because she did not expect fair treatment in the current climate of political hostility.</p>
        <p>In a three-sentence resignation letter, Ms. Goodling wrote to Mr. Gonzales, ''May God bless you richly as you continue your service to America.''</p>
        <p>Her resignation is effective immediately, Richard A. Hertling, an acting assistant attorney general, told the Judiciary Committee in a letter on Friday. Whether her resignation was encouraged or accepted with regret, or both, was not clear.</p>
        <p>How long Mr. Gonzales's service will continue has been a topic of constant speculation of late, given the turmoil over the dismissals and skepticism over his accounts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzales's job is expected to hinge on his testimony scheduled for April 17 before the Senate Judiciary Committee, when, lawmakers in both parties say, they expect him to clarify his role in the dismissals. He has said he had only limited involvement in the deliberations leading to the dismissals, but e-mail messages and other documents released by the Justice Department show that he was briefed at least twice on the subject.</p>
        <p>Democrats had hoped that Ms. Goodling, in her role as a link between the Justice Department and the White House, would provide details about the role of Karl Rove, the chief political adviser to President Bush, in the dismissals. After refusing to testify, she also declined a Democratic invitation to answer questions in a private interview.</p>
        <p>But there has been a collective embarrassment in the agency over Ms. Goodling's stance, a sense that it is especially unseemly for a Justice Department official to decline on Fifth Amendment grounds to testify about her official duties.</p>
        <p>Ms. Goodling, 33, was not widely known before her refusal to testify. She is a 1995 graduate of Messiah College in Grantham, Pa., and received her law degree at Regent University in Virginia Beach, according to many Web site postings. Messiah describes itself as ''committed to an embracing evangelical spirit,'' while Regent was founded by the Christian broadcaster Pat Robertson.</p>
        <p>Although United States attorneys serve at the pleasure of the president, there has been an uproar over the recent dismissals, in part because Democrats and even a few Republicans have raised questions about whether they were meant to achieve partisan goals by hampering or spurring investigations. At the very least, Mr. Gonzales's critics say, the dismissals were not explained adequately.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer, a New York Democrat who sits on the Judiciary Committee and has been a persistent critic of Mr. Gonzales, said Friday afternoon that Ms. Goodling had had no choice but to resign. ''This is the third Justice Department official involved in the U.S. attorney firings who has stepped down,'' Mr. Schumer said.</p>
        <p>D. Kyle Sampson resigned as Mr. Gonzales's chief of staff after accepting responsibility for how the dismissals were handled. And Michael A. Battle, the former director of the Executive Office for United States Attorneys who notified the prosecutors of their dismissals, announced several weeks ago that he was leaving to enter private practice.</p>
        <p>Unlike Ms. Goodling, Mr. Sampson was eager to testify, and he appeared voluntarily before the Senate Judiciary Committee. He testified that Mr. Gonzales had been involved in discussions that led to the dismissals, and that Mr. Gonzales's statements to the contrary were ''incorrect.''</p>
        <p>Lawmakers want the Justice Department to turn over additional documents to the House and Senate committees investigating the removals. At issue are several hundred pages of documents, most of them unedited versions of documents that were provided to Congress only in edited form. One document is a lengthy and highly negative evaluation of Kevin V. Ryan, who was dismissed as the United States attorney in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Among these documents are lists of United States attorneys who were considered for dismissal, but who were later taken off the list. Other documents include communications that show Justice Department officials deliberating over possible replacements for the ousted prosecutors, though department officials have said they did not have a list of successors prepared at the time of the dismissals.</p>
        <p>Congressional investigators have been allowed to review the unedited documents at the Justice Department, but they have not been permitted to make copies or take lengthy notes. Department officials have granted access to the papers only on the condition that lawmakers refrain from using the unedited documents to question Mr. Gonzales or other officials who testify, on grounds that the documents contain sensitive personnel information.</p>
        <p>The attorney general is to testify before the Senate committee on April 17 in what is increasingly seen as a make-or-break appearance for him. He will have his well-wishers on the panel, mostly on the Republican side. He may still have the support of President Bush, who has so far been loyal to his old friend from Texas.</p>
        <p>But he will surely encounter hostility from Democrats, refreshed after their spring recess and provided with new grist by Ms. Goodling's departure.</p>
        <p>''Attorney General Gonzales's hold on the department gets more tenuous each day,'' Mr. Schumer said Friday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
