<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Need to Lower The Bills? Just Ask</title>
    <meta content="07instincts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/business/07instincts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASIC INSTINCTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunleavey, M P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wireless Communications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E0D7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Need to Lower The Bills? Just Ask</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Need to Lower the Bills? Just Ask</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. P. DUNLEAVEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunleavey, M P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M P Dunleavey Basic Instinct column on negotiating with companies about lowering bills when consumer thinks they are too high (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF someone said that you could reduce your bills by a significant amount by taking one simple step -- and this step would be neither time-consuming nor embarrassing -- wouldn't you want to know what it was?</p>
        <p>This may sound like the sort of empty instant-money promise you would see in a New York subway ad, but I have a bona fide bill-reduction strategy. It's as simple as this: Just call and ask.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Negotiating with your creditors is a too-often neglected staple of the personal finance canon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF someone said that you could reduce your bills by a significant amount by taking one simple step -- and this step would be neither time-consuming nor embarrassing -- wouldn't you want to know what it was?</p>
        <p>This may sound like the sort of empty instant-money promise you would see in a New York subway ad, but I have a bona fide bill-reduction strategy. It's as simple as this: Just call and ask.</p>
        <p>That may not sound like much. But negotiating with your creditors is a too-often neglected staple of the personal finance canon. And I have to credit a family member with reminding me that it is also an efficient way to restore a chunk of money to your budget.</p>
        <p>My sister-in-law, Deirdre Scanlon Dunleavey, rediscovered this technique after she volunteered to take over the household bill-paying operations from her husband.</p>
        <p>When she noticed that their cellphone bill was more than $100 a month -- for relatively scant use -- a red flag went up.</p>
        <p>''When I looked at the bills there was all this stuff on there we didn't need,'' she said.</p>
        <p>One phone call later, their basic cellphone package was $35 lighter.</p>
        <p>That inspired her to do some old-fashioned comparison shopping with their car insurance, which, upon seeing their premiums, infuriated her. ''Why were we paying $176 a month when we're both over 35 and driving safe cars?''</p>
        <p>She put in a call to a rival insurer and got a rate that was $75 cheaper per month.</p>
        <p>Total savings: about $110, and there was an added bonus. ''I was surprised by how nice people were when I asked,'' she said.</p>
        <p>If shrinking the bills is really this easy, why doesn't everyone do it? Is it the dread of being mired in an endless, automated phone tree? The fear of being seen -- even by an unseen customer service representative -- as a cheapskate? I wondered whether most people even considered this sort of negotiating as a financial option.</p>
        <p>Katherine Meyers, an administrative assistant at a small company in Burlington, Vt., said that she thinks many people don't realize that even the biggest corporations might be responsive to a customer's request for a lower price -- and sometimes the better deal is already there for the asking.</p>
        <p>Ms. Meyers was looking for ways to lower shipping costs at her office and called FedEx to see what was possible. ''I didn't even have to ask if there was a better deal they could give us,'' she said. ''The rep immediately mentioned that we could probably get a 25 to 30 percent discount if we switched to another plan.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Meyers said that she was amazed, and not just by the on-the-spot bargain: ''Why didn't they ever mention this before?'' She estimates that her company now spends about $375 less a month on shipping -- a large enough gain that she is considering a similar approach with her personal bills. ''It makes you realize that it's worth asking.''</p>
        <p>THAT was Toni McLellan's attitude a couple of years ago when she learned that her health insurance would cover only part of a surgical procedure, leaving her with a $1,000 medical bill. ''I called the hospital and asked if they offered any discounts if you paid in full.''</p>
        <p>They did, and Ms. McLellan, a freelance writer in Woodstock, Ill., ended up paying only $750. ''Who knew?'' she said.</p>
        <p>Now she said she deploys the ''ask and it's likely ye shall receive'' strategy all the time. She isn't always successful, but Ms. McLellan said that she believed in challenging the financial status quo.</p>
        <p>''We're socialized to be good citizens, and we tend to take our bills at face value,'' she said. ''We're not a culture that haggles. In other parts of the world haggling is an art. If you do it here, it's seen as somewhat shady.''</p>
        <p>It's a shame that more people don't view basic financial negotiations as a citizen's right and privilege, because they are. I suspect many people not only fear being seen as underhanded, but as poor. The point isn't what you can afford to pay, but whether it is sometimes reasonable to ask to pay less.</p>
        <p>Inspired by my own research, last month I decided to call my cellphone company to protest more than $100 in charges that were assessed because I had exceeded my allotted minutes. I knew that the company allowed people to purchase extra minutes, although usually before the end of the billing cycle.</p>
        <p>It took some effort -- and two phone calls -- but they finally agreed to reduce my bill by $47.</p>
        <p>Now if only I could do that at the gas station.</p>
        <p>BASIC INSTINCTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
