<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fourth Man Is Caught After F.B.I. Agent's Death at Bank</title>
    <meta content="07bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/nyregion/07bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AN AGENT FALLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bank Robberies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Readington Township (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pnc Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Barry Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herrera-Genao, Francisco J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berrios, Wilfredo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruz, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lynn, Efrain</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kovaleski, Serge F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rashbaum, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fourth Man Is Caught After F.B.I. Agent's Death at Bank</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fourth Man Is Caught After F.B.I. Agent’s Death at Bank</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE F. KOVALESKI and WILLIAM K. RASHBAUM; Nate Schweber and Ronald Smothers contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kovaleski, Serge F; Rashbaum, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>All-night manhunt results in arrest of Francisco Herrera-Genao several miles from bank in Readington Township, NJ, where FBI agent Barry Lee Bush was killed on April 5; Bush was part of team of more than two dozen FBI agents who were tracking several men whom ythey believed to be violent, heavily armed robbers about to undertake their fifth holdup at PNC Bank; operation went awry when one FBI agent's weapon accidentally discharged and led to confrontation with suspects outside bank; charges filed against Herrera-Genao, Wilfredo Berrios and Michael Cruz may be amended to include murder and assault on federal officer; fourth man arrested, Efrain Lynn, was not present at bank during confrontation; at least two other men are being sought; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By about 9:15 a.m. Thursday, it seemed the surveillance operation was going smoothly and according to plan. A team of more than two dozen agents from the Federal Bureau of Investigation was one step ahead of its quarry, shadowing several men whom they believed to be violent, heavily armed bank robbers about to undertake their fifth holdup in New Jersey in two months, this one at a PNC Bank in Readington Township.</p>
        <p>The agents, carrying significant firepower of their own and backed up by a SWAT team, were tracking one of the suspects, who was driving a white Acura. They watched as he picked up two or three other men in New Brunswick, N.J. They followed the Acura to a department store parking lot nearby, where the would-be robbers rendezvoused with a man in a stolen black Honda before the two vehicles traveled in tandem to the bank, about 15 miles east.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A surveillance operation ended with the fatal shooting of a veteran F.B.I. agent and an all-night manhunt for a suspect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By about 9:15 a.m. Thursday, it seemed the surveillance operation was going smoothly and according to plan. A team of more than two dozen agents from the Federal Bureau of Investigation was one step ahead of its quarry, shadowing several men whom they believed to be violent, heavily armed bank robbers about to undertake their fifth holdup in New Jersey in two months, this one at a PNC Bank in Readington Township.</p>
        <p>The agents, carrying significant firepower of their own and backed up by a SWAT team, were tracking one of the suspects, who was driving a white Acura. They watched as he picked up two or three other men in New Brunswick, N.J. They followed the Acura to a department store parking lot nearby, where the would-be robbers rendezvoused with a man in a stolen black Honda before the two vehicles traveled in tandem to the bank, about 15 miles east.</p>
        <p>But just before noon, when the moment came to move in and intercept the suspects, things went terribly awry: A veteran F.B.I. agent was fatally shot, apparently when another agent's weapon accidentally discharged as they confronted the suspects outside the bank. One of the suspects fled to a densely wooded area, triggering an all-night manhunt involving up to 300 law enforcement officers. The hunt ended with his arrest in a wooded area about 8 a.m. yesterday.</p>
        <p>The man, Francisco J. Herrera-Genao, 22, of New Brunswick, was captured without incident four and a half miles east of the bank, after a state trooper spotted him lying in brush behind the Red Mill Inn motel on busy Route 22 in Branchburg Township. He was shirtless and barefoot, shivering after spending the night outside in freezing temperatures.</p>
        <p>''He rose, put his hands in his pockets and walked toward me,'' said the arresting officer, State Trooper Robert Pasquino, 35, who approached the man with his gun drawn, accompanied by two Readington police officers, a canine handler and a search dog. ''He repeated, 'Just shoot me, just shoot me.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Herrera-Genao was the fourth man arrested over 20 hours in connection with the string of recent bank robberies; the authorities said yesterday that they were still looking for at least two other members associated with the group. The F.B.I. agent in charge of the investigation, Carrie Brzenzinski, described the suspects as ''tough guys -- wanting the thrill.''</p>
        <p>''A statement was overheard that they were prepared to go down in a blaze of glory,'' said Ms. Brzenzinski, who has been tracking bank robbers in New Jersey for 16 years. ''This was a rush for them. This was their thing, and they were getting away with it.''</p>
        <p>The charges filed against the three suspects in Thursday's attempted robbery -- Mr. Herrera-Genao, Wilfredo Berrios, 28, and Michael Cruz, 21 -- may be amended to include murder and assault on a federal officer in connection with the death of the F.B.I. agent, Barry Lee Bush, 52.</p>
        <p>A fourth man, Efrain Lynn, 21, was not present at the confrontation at the bank on Thursday but was arrested at another location later in the day in connection with a March 16 holdup of a Bank of America branch in South Brunswick. The four lived within blocks of one another in a New Brunswick neighborhood near Rutgers University.</p>
        <p>Pedro Ruiz, the acting special agent in charge of the Newark F.B.I. office, refused to provide any details yesterday on how Mr. Bush was shot or which other agents were involved; the matter is being investigated by the F.B.I.'s Washington-based inspection division, in a process that the authorities said could take months.</p>
        <p>Col. Joseph R. Fuentes, superintendent of the New Jersey State Police, said that after hunting all night for Mr. Herrera-Genao, whom they believed to be armed and dangerous, officers began searching the area around the motel about 7:30 a.m. because a woman living nearby alerted the police that a ''muddy man'' had tried to carjack her.</p>
        <p>Colonel Fuentes said that investigators were trying to piece together where Mr. Herrera-Genao had been during the night, what had become of much of his clothing and whether he was linked to several break-ins reported in the rural area even as scores of law enforcement officers were searching for him.</p>
        <p>''I just look at the environment he was in -- temperatures in the low 30s, high 20s -- and he was missing much of his clothing,'' Colonel Fuentes said. ''He was covered with leaves and twigs and very muddy and showed evidence of being in the weeds or water.''</p>
        <p>Among the items found on Thursday in the two cars used by the suspects, according to a criminal complaint filed by federal prosecutors, were an AK-47 assault rifle, an SKS rifle and a .380-caliber handgun, all of them loaded, as well as two ski masks.</p>
        <p>While it is common for bank robbers to carry guns, Ms. Brzenzinski said, the crew was unusual because it routinely fired weapons, if only to establish control. In three of the four robberies attributed to the group, according to the criminal complaint, recovered bullets and shell casings were found to have come from a .380-caliber handgun.</p>
        <p>''Also, in three of the robberies, assault rifles were brandished,'' the complaint says. ''Two individuals were injured by ricocheting bullets and several individuals were held at close gunpoint.''</p>
        <p>In the first robbery attributed to the crew, at a Piscataway bank on Feb. 8, Ms. Brzenzinski said that Mr. Herrera-Genao fired a shot and jumped up on the wall separating the tellers from the gunmen before pulling down his ski mask and gathering $9,000 from the tellers' drawers in a matter of minutes.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 16, the robbers struck again, in East Brunswick, and this time a suspect had his ski mask on as he walked through the door and fired a shot, Ms. Brzenzinski said. After vaulting the tellers' partition, the man and a masked accomplice stationed at the door escaped with $28,000.</p>
        <p>In the third robbery, on March 2 in Ocean Township, a gunman believed to be Mr. Herrera-Genao fired while leaping over the tellers' partition. It was also that robbery, in which the gunmen took $16,000, that gave the F.B.I. a crucial break in the case.</p>
        <p>Investigators already knew that the crew favored Hondas as getaway cars, typically stealing them the day of the robbery or the day before, then dumping them in favor of a second vehicle of a different model and color, known as a ''switch car.'' After the March 2 robbery, Ms. Brzenzinski said, the authorities recovered a Honda in a shopping center parking lot that matched the description of the getaway car, and while canvassing the area turned up a description and license plate number of what seemed to be the switch car.</p>
        <p>Tracing that tag led investigators to a rental agency. According to the criminal complaint, ''Video surveillance tapes from the rental agency revealed that defendant Francisco Herrera accompanied defendant Wilfredo Berrios when the latter rented the vehicle.'' Surveillance then began in earnest.</p>
        <p>For the March 16 robbery in South Brunswick, the crew added a fourth person to wait in the getaway car, Ms. Brzenzinski said. Otherwise, she said, the methods, and even the words spoken, were always the same: ''Everyone down. Give me your money. Big bills.''</p>
        <p>In reference to the March 16 robbery in South Brunswick, another complaint says, ''One gunman wearing a dark hooded sweatshirt, jeans and a ski mask jumped onto the teller ledge and fired one round from a .380 handgun into the wall.'' The bullet broke the teller window and injured a teller, who was taken to the hospital, the document says.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, according to investigators, Mr. Cruz bought .380-caliber ammunition at a store in New Jersey. Early the next morning, the authorities put Mr. Berrios under surveillance.</p>
        <p>A law enforcement official who had been briefed on the events leading up to the shooting on Thursday and spoke on the condition of anonymity because the investigation was continuing, said the bank robbers were ''a shifting crew.''</p>
        <p>''Not every robbery is done by everyone in the crew,'' the official said. ''Sometimes it's three or four guys and sometimes some of these guys, but not others. And they were also hitting at a fairly regular pace.''</p>
        <p>The official added, ''They had these guys under surveillance, and they observed them steal a car or saw them come back with a stolen car, and as of Wednesday night, it looked like they had taken the steps they take for a robbery on Thursday or Friday.'' The previous four robberies all took place on Thursdays or Fridays.</p>
        <p>Because the robbers had been operating with heavy weapons and an escalating level of violence, members of the task force investigating the holdups had decided they would not wait for the men to enter the bank, the official said.</p>
        <p>''So the conscious decision was made that if we have them going up to a bank, we're going to make every effort to get them before'' they go inside, the official said, adding, ''The determination is if they take us to a bank, we're going to take them down outside.''</p>
        <p>According to the criminal complaint, F.B.I. agents approached the white Acura on Thursday morning outside the PNC Bank to arrest those inside.</p>
        <p>''Shots were fired at this time, and a special agent of the F.B.I. was shot and subsequently died,'' the document said. ''The individual inside the Acura was defendant Michael Cruz,'' it continued, saying that Mr. Cruz ''subsequently made statements admitting to his participation in the attempted robbery of the PNC Bank.''</p>
        <p>A separate criminal complaint against Mr. Lynn said that Mr. Cruz, since his arrest, had also admitted to participating in the March 16 robbery and was responsible for driving the switch car that day.</p>
        <p>The document also quotes Mr. Cruz as implicating Mr. Herrera-Genao, Mr. Berrios and Mr. Lynn in the March 16 robbery.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Herrera-Genao, Matthew McCurry, a detective with the state police, said that he had tried to break into a woman's Hyundai Elantra yesterday morning as she drove in a neighborhood adjacent to the Fox Hollow Golf Club, near Route 22. The woman, whose doors were locked, drove to a business on Route 22, where she called the police.</p>
        <p>Soon after, officers from numerous agencies responded, using dogs to catch Mr. Herrera-Genao in the woods behind the inn.</p>
        <p>The searchers -- hundreds of them from the state police, the F.B.I., the United States Marshals Service and several town police forces -- set up a loose perimeter and moved inward, focusing on the neighborhood next to the golf club, where they conducted a house-to-house search.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCurry said state police helicopters used infrared to search for heat sources, hoping for a human, but instead detecting only wildlife.</p>
        <p>''We ended up finding a turkey roosting in a pine tree,'' he said.</p>
        <p>AN AGENT FALLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
