<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Guggenheim Passed Over for New Venice Museum</title>
    <meta content="07veni" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/arts/design/07veni.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venice Biennale</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Guggenheim Foundation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D8173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Guggenheim Passed Over for New Venice Museum</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Guggenheim Passed Over for New Venice Museum</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING; Elisabetta Povoledo contributed reporting from Milan.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a battle involving money, art and politics, the French billionaire François Pinault has been chosen over the Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation to turn a much-coveted unused customs house at the entrance to Venice's Grand Canal into a new museum of contemporary art.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pinault, France's wealthiest art collector, whose business empire includes Christie's, Gucci, Yves Saint Laurent and three chains of department and media stores, has promised to install the bulk of his collection in the 17th-century building, at a site known as the Punta della Dogana.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The French billionaire François Pinault has been chosen to turn a much-coveted unused customs house at the entrance to Venice’s Grand Canal into a new museum of contemporary art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a battle involving money, art and politics, the French billionaire François Pinault has been chosen over the Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation to turn a much-coveted unused customs house at the entrance to Venice's Grand Canal into a new museum of contemporary art.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pinault, France's wealthiest art collector, whose business empire includes Christie's, Gucci, Yves Saint Laurent and three chains of department and media stores, has promised to install the bulk of his collection in the 17th-century building, at a site known as the Punta della Dogana.</p>
        <p>The triangular customs house, which looks out toward the Doge's Palace beside the Piazza San Marco, will be renovated and transformed into a museum by the Japanese architect Tadao Ando at an estimated cost of $26 million. The plan is for the museum to be ready by June 2009, in time for that year's Venice Biennale.</p>
        <p>The decision to grant Mr. Pinault a 30-year concession to the space was announced Thursday by Luigi Bassetto, the head of Venice's heritage organization, following a recommendation by a committee of experts.</p>
        <p>''The proposal by the Guggenheim Foundation did not specify which works would be permanently exhibited in the museum,'' Mr. Bassetto was quoted as telling Agence France-Presse. ''This was a requisite in the invitation to tender. The committee considered that the foundation excluded itself.''</p>
        <p>Philip Rylands, director of the Peggy Guggenheim Collection in Venice, said that the terms of the competition had been altered during the process, ''so the vision for the Punta della Dogana changed from a dynamic center of contemporary art to a static museum of modern art.'' He added, ''We trusted that the city would share our vision of a dynamic museum, but we were mistaken.''</p>
        <p>The Guggenheim Foundation, which has operated the Peggy Guggenheim Collection since 1980, first set its eyes on the Punta della Dogana building in the late 1990s but was reportedly unable to raise the funds necessary to transform it. A fierce competition for the space began after Mr. Pinault, 70, bought the 18th-century Palazzo Grassi, also on the Grand Canal, in 2005.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pinault's move to Venice followed his own failure to reach agreement with municipal authorities in Boulogne-Billancourt, outside Paris, on construction of a $195 million contemporary-art museum on an island in the Seine. But while he began holding temporary shows of works from his collection and others in the Palazzo Grassi a year ago, he soon expressed interest in expanding his presence in the city.</p>
        <p>Politics quickly intervened, with the left-of-center mayor of Venice, Massimo Cacciari, backing Mr. Pinault's bid for the former customs house and the conservative president of the Veneto region, Giancarlo Galan, supporting the New York-based Guggenheim Foundation and its high-profile director, Thomas Krens.</p>
        <p>The foundation, which already operates museums in Berlin, Las Vegas and Bilbao, Spain, pointed to its experience in museum management, its post-1960s collection and its long presence in Venice. Mr. Pinault in turn built his bid around the strength of the 2,000 or so works in his contemporary art collection and his ability to cover the costs of adapting and running the new museum out of his own pocket.</p>
        <p>The competing proposals were initially considered of equal value, and there was even talk of a joint Pinault-Guggenheim project. But any such plan imploded after one of the Guggenheim's backers, Alberto Rigotto of the ABM merchant bank, attacked Mr. Pinault as a ''wandering merchant'' in an interview with Le Monde.</p>
        <p>After the Palazzo Grassi won what a headline in the French newspaper Le Figaro Friday called ''the battle of Venice,'' Mr. Pinault said in a statement that he hoped to work closely with other contemporary art institutions. Jean-Jacques Aillagon, a former French culture minister who heads the Palazzo Grassi, said he expected that this would include collaboration with the Guggenheim Foundation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rylands welcomed this possibility. ''Congratulations to Palazzo Grassi,'' he said. ''They're friends in town and we have worked together in the past and will do so in the future.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
