<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gillispie Now Shoulders Kentucky's Expectations</title>
    <meta content="07kentucky" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/sports/ncaabasketball/07kentucky.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838527"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Kentucky</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Donovan, Billy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Smith, Tubby</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E2D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gillispie Now Shoulders Kentucky's Expectations</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gillispie Says He Is Ready for Kentucky’s Expectations</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY GLIER and THAYER EVANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glier, Ray; Evans, Thayer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Kentucky men's basketball program, known in recent years as much for the unyielding pressure on its coach as for its winning tradition, pulled Billy Gillispie away from Texas A&amp;M yesterday to fill its coaching vacancy.</p>
        <p>Kentucky introduced Gillispie as its new coach a day after Billy Donovan, the Wildcats' first choice, announced that he would stay at Florida, and six days after Texas A&amp;M offered Gillispie a multiyear deal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Billy Gillispie, who took Texas A&amp;M to the Round of 16, was introduced as the Wildcats&amp;#8217; new coach on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Kentucky men's basketball program, known in recent years as much for the unyielding pressure on its coach as for its winning tradition, pulled Billy Gillispie away from Texas A&amp;M yesterday to fill its coaching vacancy.</p>
        <p>Kentucky introduced Gillispie as its new coach a day after Billy Donovan, the Wildcats' first choice, announced that he would stay at Florida, and six days after Texas A&amp;M offered Gillispie a multiyear deal.</p>
        <p>The prestige of Kentucky -- and the money it offered -- apparently were enough to persuade Gillispie to cut short his tenure with A&amp;M, a program he took from obscurity to the top of the Big 12 Conference in just three seasons. His seven-year contract with Kentucky will pay him $2.3 million a year, with another $850,000 available in bonuses linked to his team's on-court and academic performances.</p>
        <p>The Wildcats' vacancy, created when Tubby Smith left for Minnesota on March 22, hovered over the N.C.A.A. tournament, with rampant speculation about who would accept the challenge of trying to appease the demanding Kentucky fan base.</p>
        <p>Smith guided Kentucky to its seventh national title in 1998, his first season as coach, and he had an overall record of 263-83 with the Wildcats. But he had not been to the Final Four since 1998, and Kentucky lost to Kansas in the second round of the N.C.A.A. tournament this year.</p>
        <p>''I like expectations,'' Gillispie, 47, told reporters at a news conference yesterday in Lexington, Ky. ''My most favorite year was this, when we had pressure. And that expectation, it either drives you or it diminishes your ability -- and my ability isn't diminished by expectations.''</p>
        <p>Gillispie is known among his peers as a workaholic, and he forged a reputation as a formidable recruiter in stints as an assistant under Bill Self at Tulsa and Illinois. Texas A&amp;M was 7-21 the season before Gillispie arrived, but the Aggies went 27-7 this season, a team record for victories, and won two games in the N.C.A.A. tournament.</p>
        <p>The hiring of Gillispie was the most high profile of a flurry of college coaching moves this week, and it allowed some anxious athletic directors and fans to exhale after wondering whether their coach would be lured to Kentucky.</p>
        <p>Mike Hamilton, the Tennessee athletic director, said he would be able to relax and see Jerry Seinfeld perform in Knoxville knowing that the last big domino of the coaching-search frenzy had fallen.</p>
        <p>''When there are openings popping like this, you never know what to expect,'' said Hamilton, whose men's basketball coach, Bruce Pearl, was a candidate for the opening at Iowa, which hired Butler Coach Todd Lickliter on Tuesday. ''We seem to have weathered that storm.''</p>
        <p>After Smith's move to Minnesota, Michigan fired Tommy Amaker and lured John Beilein from West Virginia. Bob Huggins, a West Virginia graduate, then left Kansas State -- after one season -- to take over the Mountaineers' program.</p>
        <p>Arkansas had a coach for a day in Dana Altman, who left Creighton to replace the fired Stan Heath and then changed his mind and went back to Creighton.</p>
        <p>Jeremy Foley, the Florida athletic director, endured several days of rumors linking Donovan to Kentucky. Two years ago, Foley outmaneuvered Notre Dame for Urban Meyer, who led the Gators' football team to a national championship last season.</p>
        <p>''The biggest mistake you can make is rush and pay attention to what other people are saying, what's in the media, and all the rumors,'' Foley said. ''You just have to put your head down and go to work. Nobody likes to be without a head coach for very long.''</p>
        <p>Texas A&amp;M had to begin its coaching search yesterday. ''We are committed to building champions in all areas,'' A&amp;M Athletic Director Bill Byrne said in a statement.</p>
        <p>An increasingly common phrase in negotiations is ''buyout clause,'' but even that has not deterred some teams from getting the coach they want.</p>
        <p>At his news conference yesterday, Gillispie tried to play down the high-stakes nature of coaching. When asked about the backroom politics of coaching searches and whether there were contacts between Kentucky and his representatives, Gillispie, a native of a small town in Texas, said, ''I don't have representatives.''</p>
        <p>''I'm an old country boy,'' he added. ''I'm a handshake man.''</p>
        <p>But Kentucky got more than a handshake from Gillispie. Mitch Barnhart, Kentucky's athletic director, said at the news conference that there was a buyout clause in Gillispie's contract.</p>
        <p>If another program wants to hire Gillispie, it will have to pay Kentucky for that privilege.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
