<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Money Shift Could Clear Way To Shut North Korea Reactor</title>
    <meta content="07korea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/world/asia/07korea.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assets, Frozen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Macao</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Macao</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Macao</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">North Korea</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Money Shift Could Clear Way To Shut North Korea Reactor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Money Shift Could Clear Way to Shut North Korea Reactor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US says that it has found way to return frozen money to North Korea, leaving North only a week to meet deadline for disabling its main nuclear facility; Bush administration says solution applies to legal and technical problems that prevented return of $25 million frozen during investigation of Macao bank (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States said Friday that it had found a way to return frozen money to North Korea, leaving the North only a week to meet the deadline for disabling its main nuclear facility.</p>
        <p>The announcement seemed to remove the major impediment to North Korea's cooperation under an agreement that calls for the North to shut down its main nuclear facility. The Bush administration said the solution applied to legal and technical problems that prevented the return of $25 million frozen during the investigation of a Macao bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States said that it had found a way to return frozen money to North Korea, leaving the North only a week to meet the deadline for disabling its main nuclear facility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States said Friday that it had found a way to return frozen money to North Korea, leaving the North only a week to meet the deadline for disabling its main nuclear facility.</p>
        <p>The announcement seemed to remove the major impediment to North Korea's cooperation under an agreement that calls for the North to shut down its main nuclear facility. The Bush administration said the solution applied to legal and technical problems that prevented the return of $25 million frozen during the investigation of a Macao bank.</p>
        <p>A delegation of senior Treasury Department officials left Beijing on Friday after 13 days of talks over how to return money -- including what the United States said were proceeds from the sale of illicit weapons and other illegal activities -- held in accounts at a tiny Macao bank known as Banco Delta Asia. Among the accounts, American and intelligence officials said, were some that President Kim Jong-il and other leaders used to buy the loyalty of the North Korean elite.</p>
        <p>When United States officials announced a deal in mid-February under which North Korea agreed to freeze, and ultimately dismantle, its main nuclear complex, they said they expected that the illicitly gained money would still be withheld by the authorities in Macao.</p>
        <p>But on Friday, the State Department said the United States expected that all the money would be released, a move that a senior State Department official said was ''always considered an option.''</p>
        <p>North Korea had demanded the return of that money as a prerequisite for moving forward with the freeze-and-dismantlement deal. President Bush has frequently described the seizure of the money as a tactic that succeeded in getting the attention of North Korea's leaders. But his decision to return that money has been harshly criticized by hawks inside and outside the administration.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Bush's top nuclear proliferation aides, Robert Joseph, left the administration after strenuously arguing that the deal would perpetuate the rule of a government that holds political prisoners in gulags and trades in drugs and counterfeits American currency, using the profits to build its nuclear arsenal.</p>
        <p>The State Department spokesman, Sean McCormack, said Friday that a ''technical pathway'' had been found to return the funds, transferring them to a new account that North Korea has agreed to use for ''humanitarian'' purposes. ''We support the release of all the funds,'' he said. ''It is now a matter of technical implementation,'' which he said was up to the authorities in Macao and China.</p>
        <p>If the banking issues are truly resolved, attention will be refocused on the core question raised by the deal: whether North Korea is willing to meet its first deadline, next Saturday, to shut and disable its five-megawatt nuclear reactor at Yongbyon and its reprocessing facility that turns its nuclear fuel into weapons-grade plutonium.</p>
        <p>It was plutonium produced at Yongbyon, intelligence experts say, that fueled the crude nuclear weapon that the North tested Oct. 9, making it the world's ninth nation known to possess nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>Nothing in the deal that was signed in February set a schedule for North Korea to give up its nuclear weapons stockpile, which American intelligence analysts and outside experts estimate at a half-dozen to a dozen weapons, or the fuel to make them. That is one reason that conservatives once closely allied with Mr. Bush have gone public with searing criticisms of the agreement.</p>
        <p>Administration officials have insisted publicly that the 60-day deadline for freezing nuclear operations remain in place. But they have hinted that they may view the deadline as flexible, because the process of unfreezing the money in Macao took so much longer than expected.</p>
        <p>Stopping activity at Yongbyon would not be difficult; the reactor there has been shut down before, sometimes for maintenance. But no one has yet defined what it means to ''disable'' it, and no schedule has been set for actually dismantling it.</p>
        <p>The next steps after a shutdown would be harder. The chief American negotiator, Christopher R. Hill, who is returning to Asia next Saturday, would have to negotiate to get North Korea to give up its existing stockpiles and to explain what happened to equipment it bought to enrich uranium, another pathway to a bomb.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
