<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Borrowing Provides the Currency to Cash In Quickly on Deals</title>
    <meta content="07charts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/business/07charts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFF THE CHARTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Standard &amp; Poor's Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Borrowing Provides the Currency to Cash In Quickly on Deals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Borrowing Provides the Currency to Cash in Quickly on Deals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Floyd Norris Off the Charts column on growing number of private companies that are paying back invested money, not from profits, but from additional borrowing; says Standard &amp; Poor's reports that companies borrowed $26.9 billion to pay dividends to their owners during first quarter of 2007, increase of 67 percent over 2006 period; notes at this rate, annual record of $56 billion, set in 2006, will fall by end of July; says most of money came from what are now called leveraged loans, and only little from more conventional junk bond market; holds much of leveraged loans come from institutional investors, including hedge funds, which often buy parts of loans after they are sliced to produce some relatively safe securities and some very risky ones; graphs (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN a company goes private, you might think that the buyers would make money only if the company generated a lot of profits. Otherwise, they would have to wait until they sold the company.</p>
        <p>But in the current private equity boom, with leveraged buyouts growing, that is no longer the case. More and more private companies are able to pay back the invested money, not from profits, but from additional borrowing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the current private equity boom more and more private companies are able to pay back invested money, not from profits, but from additional borrowing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN a company goes private, you might think that the buyers would make money only if the company generated a lot of profits. Otherwise, they would have to wait until they sold the company.</p>
        <p>But in the current private equity boom, with leveraged buyouts growing, that is no longer the case. More and more private companies are able to pay back the invested money, not from profits, but from additional borrowing.</p>
        <p>During the first quarter of 2007, Standard &amp; Poor's reports, companies borrowed $26.9 billion to pay dividends to their owners, 67 percent more than in the 2006 period. At this rate, the annual record of $56 billion, set in 2006, will fall before the end of July.</p>
        <p>Most of that money came from what are now called leveraged loans, and only a little from the more conventional junk bond market. Leveraged loans are normally negotiated by banks, but they put up only a little of the cash. Much of it comes from institutional investors, including hedge funds, which often buy parts of the loans after they are sliced and diced to produce some relatively safe securities and some very risky ones.</p>
        <p>With lending markets so friendly, some public companies are even tapping the market to fund large dividends, in some cases perhaps hoping to discourage others from trying to take them private.</p>
        <p>To those not versed in the wonderful world of private equity, the word ''dividend'' may conjure up a couple of inaccurate images. The first is that the sum is small, like the quarterly dividend normally paid by many public companies. I.B.M., to pick an example, pays 30 cents a quarter on a stock that sells for nearly $100. The second is that dividends come from profits.</p>
        <p>In this market, dividends are often large. For companies that have gone private, the first dividend is often larger than the price the investors paid when they bought the stock. After that is paid, the investors who took the company private have assured themselves of making money, even if the company eventually fails.</p>
        <p>The companies still may not be earning money, but they can nonetheless borrow more. A few years ago, debt of 4 or 4.5 times earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization, or Ebitda, seemed as high as the market would go. Now that multiple is up to 6. Add in the fact that a healthy economy has increased Ebitda for many companies, and they can borrow a lot more.</p>
        <p>Steven Miller, a managing director in S.&amp; P.'s leveraged commentary and data division, says that when companies borrowed the money to pay the first big dividend back in 2003, the payment usually came more than four years after the company went private. But the dividends being paid now come only two years after the deals were done.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the loan market, people say it is priced to perfection,'' Mr. Miller said, meaning that it assumes nothing will go wrong, and that all loans will be repaid. Still, he added, ''it has been nearly perfect.'' Over the last year the default rate is a tiny 0.45 percent, the lowest ever.</p>
        <p>As long as that continues, the wave of companies going private is not likely to ebb.</p>
        <p>OFF THE CHARTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
