<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Intelligence Chief Finds That Challenges Abound</title>
    <meta content="07intel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/washington/07intel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Intelligence Services</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mazzetti, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcconnell, Michael (Dir)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Robert M (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hayden, Michael V (Dir)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Intelligence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Defense Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McConnell, John Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0D7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Intelligence Chief Finds That Challenges Abound</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Intelligence Chief Finds That Challenges Abound</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK MAZZETTI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mazzetti, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike McConnell, new director of national intelligence, has taken stock of position and found it lacking; intelligence experts are optimistic that McConnell, Defense Sec Robert M Gates and CIA Dir Michael Hayden are right people to fix problems of intelligence structure that nearly everyone agrees is less than perfect (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Being the director of national intelligence is not without its privileges, including being among the first people to brief the president in the morning and leading nearly 100,000 people from 16 intelligence agencies.</p>
        <p>But two months after he left a lucrative consulting career to accept the intelligence post, Mike McConnell has taken stock of the position and found it lacking. And he seems eager to begin an overhaul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike McConnell has taken stock of the position of director of national intelligence and found it lacking. And he seems eager to begin an overhaul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Being the director of national intelligence is not without its privileges, including being among the first people to brief the president in the morning and leading nearly 100,000 people from 16 intelligence agencies.</p>
        <p>But two months after he left a lucrative consulting career to accept the intelligence post, Mike McConnell has taken stock of the position and found it lacking. And he seems eager to begin an overhaul.</p>
        <p>Some of the problems remain outside Mr. McConnell's control. The White House has not selected a deputy to fill the vacancy created 10 months ago when Gen. Michael V. Hayden was tapped to lead the Central Intelligence Agency.</p>
        <p>Officials said the empty post was creating significant problems at the top of an intelligence apparatus installed just two years ago to protect the United States from another terrorist attack.</p>
        <p>Some intelligence officials and analysts say the vacancy shows that the White House, which initially opposed creating the intelligence job but relented under Congressional pressure, has never given the job the authority or attention it deserves.</p>
        <p>In public comments this week, Mr. McConnell described the job in terms that made it sound like one part green eyeshade accountant and another part hall monitor: dictating the budgets of the 16 intelligence agencies and ''ensuring that no one breaks the law.''</p>
        <p>He complained that he lacked the authority to hire and fire members of the staff he nominally leads, as most intelligence employees actually report to cabinet officials other than him.</p>
        <p>Mr. McConnell, 63, who brought a decade of experience as a management consultant to his current job, euphemistically called this situation a ''challenging management condition.''</p>
        <p>He even grumbled a bit about his long hours, describing a workday that sometimes begins at 4 a.m. to prepare for the president's intelligence briefing and often does not end until 11 p.m.</p>
        <p>''My biggest challenge early is just stamina,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Officials said that having a deputy in place could lighten the work burden, but that the White House had rejected a handful of possible candidates submitted by Mr. McConnell this year.</p>
        <p>Gordon D. Johndroe, a White House spokesman, declined to comment, saying the White House did not discuss personnel matters before candidates were nominated by the president.</p>
        <p>Mr. McConnell hinted this week that he was working on a list of proposed changes he could take to the president that could improve some of the structural problems he was encountering, saying that in his opinion ''we need to adjust.''</p>
        <p>Chad Kolton, a spokesman for the director of national intelligence, said that Mr. McConnell was ''taking a very careful look at the authorities that the D.N.I. has,'' but that he was not ready to take any recommendations to the president.</p>
        <p>Amy Zegart, an intelligence expert and an associate professor at the University of California, Los Angeles, said the office of the director of national intelligence, originally intended to be a lean organization that could ride herd over an often dysfunctional intelligence community, had ballooned into an apparatus of more than 1,500 people that had merely added another layer to an unwieldy bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Zegart praised Mr. McConnell as trying to overhaul the organization he inherited.</p>
        <p>''The good news is that McConnell is aware and very candid about the problems he's finding on the job,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Officials said that some of the problems had been created by the often tense working relationship between John D. Negroponte, Mr. McConnell's predecessor, and former Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld, who long resisted ceding the Pentagon's control over a large part of the intelligence budget to the new spy czar.</p>
        <p>''The relationship between Negroponte and Rumsfeld was formal at best, and it's no secret that Rumsfeld was never a proponent of this approach to intelligence reform,'' a senior intelligence official said, speaking on condition of anonymity. ''This slowed down the process of moving on some very fundamental reforms.''</p>
        <p>One change Mr. Rumsfeld resisted was lending military intelligence personnel to civilian agencies and making stints at a number of difference agencies a requirement for promotion.</p>
        <p>But Mr. McConnell and Robert M. Gates, Mr. Rumsfeld's successor at the Pentagon, have a friendship going back several years, and officials said Mr. Gates was far less territorial about allowing military personnel to be farmed out to other agencies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates himself is a former director of central intelligence, and intelligence experts said they were optimistic that he and Mr. McConnell, along with General Hayden at the C.I.A., were the right people to fix the problems of an intelligence structure that nearly everyone agrees is less than perfect.</p>
        <p>''These guys are the A-team,'' said Mark M. Lowenthal, an assistant director of the C.I.A. from 2002 to 2005. ''If they can't make this thing work, then it's hopeless.''</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
