<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Successful At 96, Writer Has More to Say</title>
    <meta content="07bern" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/books/07bern.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5D8173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1110" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Successful At 96, Writer Has More to Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Successful at 96, Writer Has More to Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOTOKO RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Motoko</byline>
      <dateline>BRICK, N.J., April 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the time Harry Bernstein was 24, he had published a short story in a magazine beside works by William Carlos Williams and Gertrude Stein. That was 1934.</p>
        <p>It took another seven decades before he achieved literary success again, this time at 96 with a memoir, ''The Invisible Wall,'' about his early childhood on a poverty-stricken street in an English mill town, where Jews and Christians were strictly divided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seven decades after his first literary success, Harry Bernstein has returned to writing with the memoir, “The Invisible Wall.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the time Harry Bernstein was 24, he had published a short story in a magazine beside works by William Carlos Williams and Gertrude Stein. That was 1934.</p>
        <p>It took another seven decades before he achieved literary success again, this time at 96 with a memoir, ''The Invisible Wall,'' about his early childhood on a poverty-stricken street in an English mill town, where Jews and Christians were strictly divided.</p>
        <p>In a forthright voice and with heartbreaking details, the book, published last month by Ballantine Books, is a chronicle of the bigotry the family suffered, their struggles to make ends meet, and a Romeo and Juliet romance involving Mr. Bernstein's oldest sister. Reviewing it in The New York Times on Wednesday, William Grimes wrote, ''In Mr. Bernstein's hands, the small events of family life and the daily dramas on the street take on a shimmering, timeless quality.''</p>
        <p>In a publishing world where first books by 20-something wunderkinds are often dissected as much for their authors' photographs as for their prose, Mr. Bernstein is a refreshing antidote. Not that he is immune to the exhilaration of being a nonagenarian discovery.</p>
        <p>''I don't know about the word 'celebrity,' '' he said, speaking in his modest two-bedroom bungalow in a retirement community near the Jersey Shore. Referring to the arrival of several newspaper reporters and the cavalcade of letters he has received from readers, he said, ''It has been a lot of exciting, interesting days.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein was born in 1910 in Stockport, England, the fifth of seven children whose parents had immigrated from Poland. His mother, he said, told him he was born on April 17, but his birth certificate says May 30. ''I've not been celebrating either one of them lately,'' he said in a raspy voice that had all but lost any traces of an accent.</p>
        <p>''The Invisible Wall'' covers young Harry's life from about 4 to just before the family moved to the United States, when he was 12. Mr. Bernstein is now working on another memoir, ''The Dream,'' which covers the family's early years in America.</p>
        <p>He had mined some of that material -- as well as the period covered by ''The Invisible Wall''-- for his early writing, which was published in literary magazines like Story and Literary America.</p>
        <p>He recalled that some of those short stories caught the attention of Clifton Fadiman, then editor of Simon &amp; Schuster, who invited him to submit a novel. ''I proceeded at once to write a novel that would never get published,'' Mr. Bernstein said, adding that Mr. Fadiman nevertheless helped him get a job reading books and scripts for a movie studio.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein later took a job editing a trade magazine for builders, but he continued to write, and publish. In 1950 he sold a three-part article entitled ''Twelve Years in an English Ghetto'' to a Jewish monthly for $100. He even wrote a novel, ''The Smile,'' about a model, which was published in 1981 by West End Press, though it did not call much attention to itself. ''I did get one reader's letter,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The catalyst for ''The Invisible Wall'' was the death, nearly five years ago, of Ruby, Mr. Bernstein's beloved wife of 67 years, who had leukemia. ''It was a terrible thing for me because it never occurred to either one of us that it would not last forever,'' he said, his large frame folded into a worn burgundy leather chair. ''There was so much emptiness, especially at nighttime, and you had to find something to fill in that gap. I was looking for a home.''</p>
        <p>He found it, he said, in his childhood memories, and then in writing about them. ''I realized then why I had failed in writing novels,'' he said. ''Because I turned away from personal experience and depended on imagination.''</p>
        <p>The book is filled with rich dialogue, intense political debates and long quotations from letters that no longer exist. Mr. Bernstein acknowledges that he took some creative license. ''The memoir is not necessarily an accurate day-to-day detailing of your life,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But, he continued, ''certain scenes are projected in your mind as if they are on a screen and you are looking at it.''</p>
        <p>In the book, his devotion to his mother comes through. His father comes across as an ogre, who once dragged Mr. Bernstein's sister, Lily, through the streets by the hair and prevented her from taking a scholarship, instead sending her to work in a tailor's shop. Mr. Bernstein clearly felt no love for the man, and he admits to sometimes feeling guilty for writing ill of him.</p>
        <p>''I sometimes felt that was not the way anyone should speak of his father,'' he said. ''I certainly would not want my children to dwell on my faults.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein sent the manuscript for ''The Invisible Wall'' to several New York publishers, all of whom turned it down, though some praised the writing. Then he sent it to an editor at Random House UK, where it sat in the so-called slush pile of unsolicited manuscripts for a year before she read it and passed it on to Kate Elton, publishing director at Arrow, a Random House imprint.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Bernstein's book arrived without a cover letter from an agent, Ms. Elton said, ''it had none of the overhyped pitch that you sometimes get with these things, and I read it without knowing what I was getting at all.'' Her reaction, she said, was instant, and she knew she wanted it published by Hutchinson, another Random House imprint. In February 2006, Mr. Bernstein said, she called him and offered a £5,000 advance (about $8,900), which he accepted.</p>
        <p>Despite his age, Mr. Bernstein does not appear to write as if he is under any pressure. ''I indulged in the luxury of writing when I felt like it, just as when you are hungry you sit down and eat a meal,'' he said. On Thursday, half of Page 386 of ''The Dream'' was still on the platen of the IBM electric typewriter given to him a few years ago by his daughter, Adraenne. (He also has a son, Charles.) He figures he will finish the manuscript by the end of the month.</p>
        <p>''If I had not lived until I was 90, I would not have been able to write this book,'' Mr. Bernstein said. ''It just could not have been done even when I was 10 years younger. I wasn't ready.'' And he suggested that he might not be an anomaly: ''God knows what other potentials lurk in other people, if we could only keep them alive well into their 90s.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
