<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Piracy Move On China Seen as Near</title>
    <meta content="07trade" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health; Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/business/worldbusiness/07trade.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Counterfeit Merchandise</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">China Copyright Alliance</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Counterfeit Merchandise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Counterfeit Merchandise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E0D7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Piracy Move On China Seen as Near</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Piracy Move on China Seen as Near</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS; David Barboza contributed reporting from Shanghai.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration officials have strongly hinted that they are close to filing formal trade complaint against China at World Trade Organization related to pirated copies of American movies, music, books, pharmaceuticals and software; China Copyright Alliance, industry coalition that includes Hollywood studios, independent movie and television producers and recording industry, has been pushing administration for months to file formal legal complaint (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After months of prodding China to crack down on pirated copies of American movies, music and software, the Bush administration appears ready to escalate the dispute into a legal confrontation.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, administration officials have strongly hinted that they are close to filing a formal trade complaint against China at the World Trade Organization, saying that China has failed to prosecute all but a small fraction of the ubiquitous and visible street trade in bootlegged American entertainment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration appears close to filing a formal trade complaint against China over pirated copies of films, music and software.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After months of prodding China to crack down on pirated copies of American movies, music and software, the Bush administration appears ready to escalate the dispute into a legal confrontation.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, administration officials have strongly hinted that they are close to filing a formal trade complaint against China at the World Trade Organization, saying that China has failed to prosecute all but a small fraction of the ubiquitous and visible street trade in bootlegged American entertainment.</p>
        <p>''The United States has made it clear that formal W.T.O. consultations will be necessary without concrete actions by China in this area,'' the office of the United States trade representative warned this week in its annual trade report to Congress.</p>
        <p>The administration went on to complain about ''inadequate'' enforcement of intellectual property rights -- copyrights, patents and trademarks -- in movies, music, books, pharmaceuticals, software and many other areas.</p>
        <p>The China Copyright Alliance, an industry coalition that includes Hollywood studios, independent movie and television producers and the recording industry, has been pushing the administration for months to file a formal legal complaint. Administration officials have made it clear they are preparing to do so.</p>
        <p>''We're all going to run out of patience at some point, and that's going to be sooner rather than later,'' said Susan C. Schwab, the United States trade representative, in a speech on Feb. 22.</p>
        <p>Bloomberg News, citing industry executives who said they had been briefed by the administration, said Ms. Schwab was likely to file two complaints against China as early as next week.</p>
        <p>Sean Spicer, a spokesman for the trade representative, refused to comment on administration plans. But industry executives have been expecting a formal complaint.</p>
        <p>''It's a sign of growing impatience, including within the business community,'' said William A. Reinsch, president of the National Council on Foreign Trade, an association that represents companies on international trade issues.</p>
        <p>Industry executives said they had been waiting for the Bush administration to file two separate complaints. One addresses what American companies say is China's reluctance to use criminal laws for people caught selling DVDs with pirated material on them.</p>
        <p>A second complaint would be about expanding ''market access'' for American products in China.</p>
        <p>If the United States files the twin actions, it would be the third time this year that the Bush administration has sought to pressure China for its trade practices, signaling a tougher policy after taking a largely conciliatory approach for six years.</p>
        <p>On March 30, the United States announced it would reverse more than 20 years of practice and impose potentially steep tariffs on Chinese manufactured goods on the ground that China is illegally subsidizing some of its exports.</p>
        <p>In February, the administration leveled a complaint with the world trade group that China subsidizes a number of industries in violation of trade rules.</p>
        <p>The growing American trade deficit with China, which reached a record $232.5 billion last year, has been denounced by Democrats as the cause of hundreds of thousands of lost jobs. Many Democrats elected last fall campaigned for a tougher policy on trade with China, and Democrats have threatened to pass legislation to retaliate. Any new legal actions against China over intellectual property could be an effort to preempt those.</p>
        <p>Chinese authorities have made moves in recent days to head off a legal confrontation. On March 26, China's National Anti-Piracy and Pornography Office announced that it had raided a storage facility in Guangzhou, after receiving information from the Motion Picture Association, and seized what it said were about 1.6 million pirated copies of movies and television shows.</p>
        <p>This week, the Chinese Embassy in Washington announced that China's Supreme Court had issued a ''new judicial interpretation'' that would lower the threshold under which prosecutors are allowed to charge people under criminal laws against piracy.</p>
        <p>Until this week, prosecutors could impose administrative penalties only on people caught with fewer than 1,000 illegal DVDs. Now the threshold will be just 500 DVDs</p>
        <p>But those moves are not enough to satisfy the movie industry or the recording industry. Nor are they likely in themselves to make a serious dent in the open sales of bootlegged music and software. In big cities like Shanghai, vendors sell pirated goods along major thoroughfares like the Nanjing Road as well as along bridges, small roads and alleyways.</p>
        <p>Dan Glickman, president of the Motion Picture Association of America, told a Congressional hearing in February that movie producers were worried that pirated copies of American movies would not only lead to lost sales in China but be exported around the world and even back to the United States.</p>
        <p>''We have walked a long way down the China road, looking and hoping for improvement,'' Mr. Glickman testified. ''We may be nearing the end of that course and deciding on whether to take another.''</p>
        <p>The broader issue is how China reacts to any legal complaint that the United States might bring. It is unclear whether the W.T.O. would agree with the United States, and it is even less clear what kind of punishments it would allow even if it did rule against China.</p>
        <p>If the new complaints are filed, under the trade organization's rules, the United States would formally ask for ''consultations'' with China. After 60 days, it would be allowed to ask for an independent panel of the World Trade Organization to consider the dispute. That process often takes years to complete.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
