<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Wall Collapse at Chumley's Brings Forth a Cascade of Memories</title>
    <meta content="07chumleys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/nyregion/07chumleys.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chumley's (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0D8173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Wall Collapse at Chumley's Brings Forth a Cascade of Memories</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Wall Collapse at Chumley’s Brings Forth a Cascade of Memories</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>People reminisce about Chumley's, storied Greenwich Village bar, after wall collapse forces it to close temporarily; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ken Baron, a marketing consultant, remembers leading his sister-in-law and a co-worker -- two Texans in New York for a conference -- through Greenwich Village last fall. He showed them a landmark here and a famous address there.</p>
        <p>The last stop was on Bedford Street, at a place with no sign. A onetime speakeasy, he said. A dark, cozy, beery place that was a footnote to literary history, he said. A hangout for luminaries like F. Scott Fitzgerald, John Steinbeck and Norman Mailer, he said. It is called Chumley's, he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chumley’s, a bar that is a relic of the Roaring Twenties, will be closed for a month or two after a wall collapsed, according to a real estate broker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ken Baron, a marketing consultant, remembers leading his sister-in-law and a co-worker -- two Texans in New York for a conference -- through Greenwich Village last fall. He showed them a landmark here and a famous address there.</p>
        <p>The last stop was on Bedford Street, at a place with no sign. A onetime speakeasy, he said. A dark, cozy, beery place that was a footnote to literary history, he said. A hangout for luminaries like F. Scott Fitzgerald, John Steinbeck and Norman Mailer, he said. It is called Chumley's, he said.</p>
        <p>''A dinner at Bouley or fifth-row-center seats would not have impressed them more,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But on Thursday, the bar with no sign became the bar with no chimney when part of a wall collapsed. And yesterday, people who had discovered Chumley's reminisced about a storied bar that will reopen in a month or two, according to a real estate broker who said he represents the owners.</p>
        <p>Chumley's is a relic of the Roaring Twenties, but the memories are being shared the 21st-century way, over the Internet. Yesterday, after reports of the wall collapse, more than 30 people posted anecdotes about Chumley's on nytimes.com, some wondering about its future.</p>
        <p>The broker representing the owners, Bill Butler, said the taps would be flowing and the burgers sizzling in 30 to 60 days. He said that renovation work had been going on outside the restaurant when the accident happened.</p>
        <p>And for-sale signs with a $3.75 million price tag for the property that houses Chumley's and three rental apartments went up a couple of months ago. A listing on the Web site masseyknakal.com, for the Manhattan real estate company Massey Knakal, said that the bar's lease runs through 2086.</p>
        <p>''The property does have potential structural issues,'' the listing warned, ''as the facade is in disrepair.''</p>
        <p>It was not always that way. Chumley's began as the domain of Lee Chumley, who favored loud ties and a hard-to-miss floppy hat. Speakeasy owner during Prohibition was the last of his many occupations. When he died in April 1935, 16 months after Prohibition ended, The New York Times said he had been a laborer, stage-coach driver, artist, waiter, newspaper cartoonist and editorial writer.</p>
        <p>His widow, Henrietta, reigned over Chumley's for the next quarter-century, as the Village changed around Chumley's. In 1954, in an article in The New York Times Magazine with the headline, ''The Village: Bohemia Gone Bourgeois,'' William Barrett of The Partisan Review complained that a ''collegiate tone has taken over whole bars in the Village that used once to be the haunts of honest-to-God derelicts.''</p>
        <p>Chumley's, he said, had been ''submerged by the collegiate tide years ago.''</p>
        <p>In the 1960s it was, said Robert Gately, who ran a bar at the 1964 World's Fair, ''a great memorable hangout never to be forgotten by those who loved lonely seedy bars where solitary men with notebooks seemed always huddled in a corner writing.''</p>
        <p>A few years later, when his wife signed on as a cocktail waitress at the Village Gate and he worked at Maxwell's Plum, Chumley's was the place they went for a nightcap.</p>
        <p>''I remember we took Nina Simone there one night while she was playing the Gate, and she loved the place,'' Mr. Gately wrote in an e-mail message. ''Being buddies with the bartender always got you an overpour and him a good tip.''</p>
        <p>Andrew Deutsch did not go in much, but knew what was going on there. He leased an apartment above Chumley's when he moved to New York in 1977, just out of law school. The rent, he said yesterday, was ''at least $500, but it was eye-popping at the time.''</p>
        <p>''What was memorable was the scene that played out several times a week in the courtyard of the apartment,'' where there were several doors but only one that led to Chumley's, he said. ''The dialogue was always the same, although the inebriation of the actors varied.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Deutsch said the routine went like this:</p>
        <p>''They told me there's a bar here,'' the first voice said.</p>
        <p>''Are you kidding, there's no bar here,'' the second voice said.</p>
        <p>That was followed by the sound of a locked door being pulled vigorously and a voice saying, ''I guess it must be someplace else.'' Then, the sound of departing footsteps.</p>
        <p>But plenty of people figured out which door was the right door, Jeff Lewonczyk among them. Last year he wrote ''The Folly Ball,'' a play that takes place at Chumley's in 1933. As it happens, his play is to be performed at another bar, Mo Pitkin's House of Satisfaction in the East Village.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lewonczyk had never been to Chumley's until he decided to write ''The Folly Ball.''</p>
        <p>He had never been to London, either.</p>
        <p>He went there soon after he started writing the play and struck up a conversation with one of the Yeoman Warders at the Tower of London who are known as Beefeaters.</p>
        <p>''The first words out of his mouth upon finding out that I lived in New York were, 'Oh, have you been to Chumley's?' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
