<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Difficult Journey of Devotion to One Faith and to a Spouse of Another Faith</title>
    <meta content="07religion" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/us/07religion.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON RELIGION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boova, Carrie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boova, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freedman, Samuel G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFD8173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Difficult Journey of Devotion to One Faith and to a Spouse of Another Faith</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Difficult Journey of Devotion to One Faith and to a Spouse of Another Faith</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL G. FREEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freedman, Samuel G</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Samuel G Freedman column on Carrie and Chris Boova, Manhattan couple who are both serious about their different faiths, Judaism in her case and Roman Catholicism in his; discusses their efforts to accommodate differences and reconcile the irreconcilable; says Easter and Passover remain deeply philosophical in ways that underscore both the nearness and distance between Judaism and Christianity; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Toward the end of the worship service on Good Friday in 2001, Carrie Pass looked down the pew at the man she was thinking she just might marry. His name was Chris Boova, and in their nearly two years as a couple she had never seen his face so stricken.</p>
        <p>Chris was normally the analytic sort, first as a submarine officer in the Navy, more recently as an executive assessing technology stocks. Yet as a priest intoned Christ's final words, ''Father, into your hands I commend my spirit,'' and as a dancer beside the altar enacted Mary's maternal grief, Chris appeared close to tears.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For 1.25 million Americans in Jewish-Christian marriages, the spring confluence of Easter and Passover presents a significant challenge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Toward the end of the worship service on Good Friday in 2001, Carrie Pass looked down the pew at the man she was thinking she just might marry. His name was Chris Boova, and in their nearly two years as a couple she had never seen his face so stricken.</p>
        <p>Chris was normally the analytic sort, first as a submarine officer in the Navy, more recently as an executive assessing technology stocks. Yet as a priest intoned Christ's final words, ''Father, into your hands I commend my spirit,'' and as a dancer beside the altar enacted Mary's maternal grief, Chris appeared close to tears.</p>
        <p>A Jewish woman in love with a Roman Catholic man, Carrie reached into her own faith for some parallel, perhaps the prayers for atonement she offered on Yom Kippur. Even so, essential parts of Chris's experience eluded her. There was something ultimately foreign to her in the very beliefs that tormented Chris -- Jesus being the Son of God, Jesus dying for humanity's sins.</p>
        <p>In that moment six years ago at the Church of St. Ignatius Loyola on the Upper East Side of Manhattan, Carrie and Chris experienced what has become a central element of their life since May 10, 2003, as Mr. and Mrs. Boova. They have chosen, like a relatively small proportion of couples in interfaith marriages, to intensively pursue both their Jewish and Christian identities.</p>
        <p>For 1.25 million Americans in Jewish-Christian marriages, the so-called December dilemma when Hanukkah and Christmas converge tends to command the greatest attention and anxiety. The spring confluence of Easter and Passover, however, presents a more significant challenge to the observant faction of such couples, who constitute roughly 15 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>The religious aspects of Christmas and Hanukkah were long ago buried under commercialism and seasonal festivity. Passover and Easter remain deeply theological in ways that underscore both the nearness and distance between Judaism and Christianity.</p>
        <p>On the one hand, Jesus came into Jerusalem for Passover, and the Last Supper with the disciples was a seder; the wafer in communion harks back to the Jewish holiday's matzo. On the other hand, beyond celebrating Jesus' divinity, Easter has historically been the occasion for anti-Semitic passion plays and pogroms, motivated by the belief that the Jews killed Jesus.</p>
        <p>For the Boovas, the season means a seder with Carrie's parents in Florida and Good Friday and Easter services with Chris's parents in Pennsylvania. It means examining liturgy and ritual for the elements that can be awkward, or even offensive, to the other. It means memberships in the B'nai Jeshurun synagogue and the St. Ignatius Loyola church, as well as active participation in the Interfaith Community, an organization with a goal of providing a ''safe and neutral space for Jewish-Christian families'' in the New York metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>''You need to respect what's sacred in the other and what's central in the other,'' said Mr. Boova, 41, a senior vice president at J. &amp; W. Seligman &amp; Company. Mrs. Boova, 42, a senior meeting planner for Merrill Lynch, said, ''He doesn't force his beliefs on me, and he's never judged me for not making the leap of faith.''</p>
        <p>Such efforts at accommodating difference, at trying to reconcile the irreconcilable, are rarely easy for observant interfaith couples.</p>
        <p>''It makes it harder in the sense that it takes a lot of energy,'' said Sylvia Barack Fishman, a professor at Brandeis University and the author of ''Double or Nothing? Jewish Families and Mixed Marriage.'' ''These are people who spend a lot of time on religion in their homes. It's much more common for couples to retreat from both religions.''</p>
        <p>The theological discomfort, however, does not play out equally. While 72 percent of Christians in interfaith relationships say they ''look forward'' to Passover, only 19 percent of Jews express similar anticipation about Easter, according to a survey by InterfaithFamily.com, a group serving intermarried families that are raising children solely in Judaism.</p>
        <p>Chris and Carrie Boova may have spared themselves some of the greatest tensions by recognizing early the limits of compromise. Chris went to Catholic elementary school, was an altar boy in his parish and remained actively Catholic during college and young adulthood. Growing up, Carrie belonged to a Conservative synagogue, where she had her bat mitzvah, and after some drift away, spent a year in a Torah-study program at the Hineni Heritage Center, which is led by the Orthodox theologian Esther Jungreis.</p>
        <p>Recognizing that neither one would convert, Chris and Carrie joined an interfaith group and got counseling from a rabbi even before becoming engaged. They waited four years until marrying, and their ceremony was jointly led by a rabbi and a priest and included readings from First Corinthians and the Book of Ruth. The Boovas do not have children.</p>
        <p>''When we started out, we were looking for 'The Answer,' '' Chris said about the challenge of maintaining two substantial religious lives. ''The paradigm changed for us when we realized there is no checklist. There is no answer. There is only a journey.''</p>
        <p>On that journey, Carrie has accompanied Chris to Mass scores of times, speaking the Catholic prayers that address God, remaining silent for those that beseech Jesus. She can conceive of him, she said, as a rabbi, a teacher, a tremendous influence on the world, but only as a human.</p>
        <p>For Chris, Passover can feel almost familiar because of its place in the Jesus narrative. After years of attending the Pass family seder, this year, for the first time, he led a second-night seder in his and Carrie's Manhattan apartment.</p>
        <p>The more wrenching part of his odyssey involved separating himself from millennia of Catholic teaching about deicide (Jewish responsibility for Jesus' death) and replacement theology (Christianity supplanting Judaism as the one true faith and the only way to salvation). Though he had grown up in the wake of the Vatican II reforms, which formally disavowed those tenets, he studied them only when he had to answer for himself how to remain a true Catholic while being the husband of a true Jew.</p>
        <p>In this doubly holy week, he pulled off his bookshelf a slender volume with a reassuring message in the form of a photograph. It showed Pope John Paul II at the Western Wall in Jerusalem. He had watched Carrie, on a trip to Israel last summer, praying and crying at the same sacred place.</p>
        <p>ON RELIGION E-mail: sgfreedman@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: sgfreedman@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
