<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Honor Robinson, Everyone Can Wear No. 42 for a Day</title>
    <meta content="07pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uniforms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE7DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Honor Robinson, Everyone Can Wear No. 42 for a Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On April 15, when the Yankees play in Oakland, Mariano Rivera may not be the only Yankee wearing No. 42.</p>
        <p>Rivera is currently the only major leaguer wearing No. 42, which was retired throughout the majors in 1997 to honor Jackie Robinson, who wore it while breaking baseball's color line for the Brooklyn Dodgers in 1947. All players who were wearing 42 at the time it was retired were allowed to continue wearing it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On April 15, when the Yankees play in Oakland, Mariano Rivera may not be the only Yankee wearing No. 42.</p>
        <p>Rivera is currently the only major leaguer wearing No. 42, which was retired throughout the majors in 1997 to honor Jackie Robinson, who wore it while breaking baseball's color line for the Brooklyn Dodgers in 1947. All players who were wearing 42 at the time it was retired were allowed to continue wearing it.</p>
        <p>This year, to mark the 60th anniversary of Robinson's debut, Major League Baseball is allowing all players to switch to 42 for the day, if they wish. The idea came from the Cincinnati Reds' Ken Griffey Jr., and many major leaguers have said they would join Griffey in switching, including Barry Bonds of the San Francisco Giants, Gary Sheffield of the Detroit Tigers and Dontrelle Willis of the Florida Marlins.</p>
        <p>Rob Cucuzza, the Yankees' equipment manager, said any Yankee could wear 42 on April 15, even though Rivera already has it. Cucuzza added that he had not yet asked the players about it, but in interviews, Derek Jeter and Robinson Can贸 said they would like to wear 42 if they were allowed.</p>
        <p>Can贸 is named for Jackie Robinson, and he wears No. 24 because the digits are the reverse of 42. When told that the entire Los Angeles Dodgers team would wear No. 42 on April 15, Can贸 seemed excited by the idea that he could, too.</p>
        <p>''Oh, there can be two people on the same team?'' Can贸 said. ''Good.''</p>
        <p>The last Yankees to wear No. 42 before Rivera were pitchers Domingo Jean and John Habyan in 1993.</p>
        <p>DAMON FEELING BETTER -- General Manager Brian Cashman said the Yankees would not place Johnny Damon on the disabled list. Damon, who has been out of the lineup since Monday because of a strained right calf, took batting practice before last night's game and said he was feeling better.</p>
        <p>''There was massive improvement last night,'' Damon said. ''I'm close to being ready. Considering how I felt on Wednesday, I thought it was real bad. I only feel it a little bit right now.''</p>
        <p>Damon told Manager Joe Torre that he would be available off the bench last night, but Torre decided to be careful.</p>
        <p>''His legs mean more to him than maybe someone who doesn't run quite as fast or hard,'' Torre said. ''You want to make sure you don't take something away from him.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees' next series is on artificial turf, in Minnesota, but Damon said he was more concerned with this weekend's series at home. He said the cold weather probably caused the injury in the first place.</p>
        <p>''The weather out there is just awful on us,'' Damon said.</p>
        <p>When Damon is unavailable, the Yankees play with a three-man bench. If they choose, they could add depth to their bench Monday by promoting an outfielder like Kevin Thompson and sending down the fifth starter, Darrell Rasner.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
