<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Gandhi Fights for His Family's Political Base</title>
    <meta content="07india" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/world/asia/07india.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Uttar Pradesh (India)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gandhi, Rahul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gandhi, Rahul</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Gandhi Fights for His Family's Political Base</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Another Gandhi Fights for His Family’s Political Base</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <dateline>KANPUR, India, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rahul Gandhi, heir apparent to India's ruling political dynasty, is trying to save Congress Party from becoming irrelevant in Uttar Pradesh, India's most populous state and Nehru-Gandhi family's home base; map; photo shows Gandhi campaigning for candidates in state elections (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rahul Gandhi, the fashionably bestubbled, 36-year-old heir apparent to India's ruling political dynasty, is facing his first real test of political mettle: Can he save his Congress Party from becoming utterly irrelevant here in Uttar Pradesh, India's most populous state and the Nehru-Gandhi family's home base?</p>
        <p>With state elections to start Saturday, his part rock star, part royalty road show raced through the heart of Uttar Pradesh this week in an effort to raise party morale. Women stood on rooftops to watch his helicopter touch down in suffocating swirls of dust. Near stampedes broke out at some stops. As his motorcade meandered noisily through this crowded, garbage-piled city for five hours on Tuesday, so many hands pressed his that by late evening, his right hand was swathed in bandages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rahul Gandhi, the 36-year-old heir apparent to India’s ruling political dynasty, is being groomed as a potential future prime minister.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rahul Gandhi, the fashionably bestubbled, 36-year-old heir apparent to India's ruling political dynasty, is facing his first real test of political mettle: Can he save his Congress Party from becoming utterly irrelevant here in Uttar Pradesh, India's most populous state and the Nehru-Gandhi family's home base?</p>
        <p>With state elections to start Saturday, his part rock star, part royalty road show raced through the heart of Uttar Pradesh this week in an effort to raise party morale. Women stood on rooftops to watch his helicopter touch down in suffocating swirls of dust. Near stampedes broke out at some stops. As his motorcade meandered noisily through this crowded, garbage-piled city for five hours on Tuesday, so many hands pressed his that by late evening, his right hand was swathed in bandages.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gandhi waved, smiled, addressed adoring crowds who had wilted for hours in the heat, and at every stop, left a carpet of rose petals flung by his fans. He delivered hazy nationalist appeals for voters of all stripes to unite behind Congress. He promised nothing specific, except the very grandest of ambitions.</p>
        <p>''What doors were closed for Congress, I will open them,'' he declared Tuesday in Bharthana, a small town not far from here and a stronghold of the state's governing Samajwadi Party.</p>
        <p>The Congress Party, which has led this country for most of its 60 years of independence, has steadily hemorrhaged voters here to a new crop of local caste-based parties. In recent weeks, the party has lost two state elections, and will face several others in the coming months.</p>
        <p>Although Congress leads a national coalition government, its fate perhaps matters more in Uttar Pradesh than in any other place in India. If the party's standing cannot be revived here, its strength in national elections in 2009 is likely to be compromised, forcing deals with smaller parties to retain power.</p>
        <p>It will also bear on the political standing of Mr. Gandhi, who Congress makes clear is being groomed as a potential future prime minister.</p>
        <p>''Rahul Gandhi has staked his personal political capital,'' said Pratap Bhanu Mehta, a political commentator who is president of the New Delhi-based Center for Policy Research. ''If the Congress does well, it'll be a huge, huge boost to his credibility. If it doesn't make major gains, he will appear to be a very diminished crown prince.''</p>
        <p>Uttar Pradesh is a weather vane of national trends in other respects. The most pressing challenges of India prevail here: tenacious poverty, political rot and elections driven almost entirely by caste and religious loyalties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gandhi's party has always been hitched to his family. He is following in the footsteps of his father, Rajiv, his grandmother, Indira, and his great-grandfather, Jawaharlal Nehru, the country's founding leader. His mother, Sonia, who now heads the party, turned down the prime minister's chair nearly three years ago, when a Congress-led coalition swept to power.</p>
        <p>It was during those same elections, in 2004, that Rahul Gandhi entered politics. He handily won a parliamentary seat from Amethi, an Uttar Pradesh town once represented by his mother and before that, by his father, who was assassinated by a suicide bomber associated with Sri Lankan ethnic Tamil guerrillas in 1991.</p>
        <p>Indeed, pedigree was the one thing that his supporters repeatedly cited. ''When we see him, we see Rajiv Gandhi,'' Manish Sahu gushed as he waited for his road show to pass.</p>
        <p>Ram Kishore, doling fried snacks from a pushcart, shrugged when asked about Mr. Gandhi's potential impact. A lifelong Congress supporter, Mr. Kishore said he was fed up with rising prices of food and fuel, which critics here blame on the economic policies of the Congress-led central government.</p>
        <p>How much Mr. Gandhi's crowd-pulling skills will translate into boosting votes for his party remains to be seen as the elections here among the state's 114 million people unfold over the next four weeks.</p>
        <p>A poll conducted in late March, by the Delhi-based Center for the Study of Developing Societies, showed that Congress would fare worst among the four main parties, commanding barely 9 percent of the total vote.</p>
        <p>The front-runners, according to the poll, which had a margin of error of two percentage points, were two local parties that have capitalized on caste and religion. One is Samajwadi, which enjoys overwhelming support among Muslims and Yadavs, members of a mid-level Hindu caste. The other is the Bahujan Samaj Party, whose main constituents are low-caste Dalits.</p>
        <p>According to the Association for Democratic Reforms, a nonprofit watchdog group, 130 of the 785 candidates contesting this weekend in the first phase of voting face criminal charges. The chief minister himself, Mulayam Singh Yadav, of Samajwadi, is under investigation, suspected of holding assets that far exceed his earnings.</p>
        <p>These elections are also seen to be his toughest fight. On Wednesday, at a rally held in front of a gun shop, Mr. Yadav issued a string of barely concealed appeals to the various blocs he is trying to woo. He promised everything from free medicine to paved roads to around-the-clock electricity -- the very things that his opponents harp on as his failures.</p>
        <p>The same day, the Bharatiya Janata Party rallied its own largely Hindu upper caste base. One member of that party, Satish Mahana, seeking a fifth consecutive term in the state Legislature, went door to door to pay respects to his most important loyalists here in Kanpur.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahana said his party had opted to focus on issues like rising prices, lawlessness and what it calls the ''appeasement'' of Muslims by the Congress and Samajwadi parties. No longer, he said, did it serve to campaign on what was once the party's core issue: the building of a Hindu temple in Ayodhya, where a Hindu mob led by his party destroyed an ancient mosque in 1992.</p>
        <p>Predictably, he dismissed Mr. Gandhi's foray through the state. ''He doesn't know how to speak,'' he said, with a swipe of his hand. ''He's just moving around.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gandhi's approach, meanwhile, was to cast Congress as rising above petty community loyalties, protecting the interests of all Indians.</p>
        <p>''He's trying to shift the terrain of Uttar Pradesh politics from caste and religion,'' the historian, Ramachandra Guha, said of his strategy. ''It's a calculated move.''</p>
        <p>This has always been the Congress Party's rhetorical line, he added, though the Congress-led national government has itself actively appealed to caste and religion, proposing, for instance, quotas in jobs and university admissions.</p>
        <p>At a press conference here on Wednesday, Mr. Gandhi sidestepped a local journalist's question about his own stance on quotas for Muslims, saying only that he saw people as neither Hindu nor Muslim, but as Indians.</p>
        <p>The one question he answered, somewhat definitively, was to assure everyone that he intends to stick around in politics. ''For me this is the beginning of a process,'' he said. ''Successful road show, unsuccessful road show.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
