<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Life Lessons From the Army</title>
    <meta content="l07army" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindland, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sauvageot, Andre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Galloway, Nancy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frank, Nathaniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Higginbotham, Edwin M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, Adrian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7D7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Life Lessons From the Army</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letters from Roger Lindland, Andre Sauvageot, Nancy Galloway, Nathaniel Frank, Edwin M Higginbotham, Mark Johnson and Adrian O'Connor respond to Robert Wright's April 3 Op-Ed about his experiences growing up on military base; drawing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''My Life in the Army,'' by Robert Wright (column, April 3):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''My Life in the Army,'' by Robert Wright (column, April 3):</p>
        <p>After college graduation in 1955, I moved up my draft date because I found my new job as a General Motors management trainee to be a slow experience. The Army provided excellent work in my chosen field and more responsibility.</p>
        <p>In later years, whether working as a bank president or as an international consultant, I was aware of the benefit that Army ''brats'' had within the level playing field of schooling, personal standards and responsibility. I marveled at the articulate, highly motivated people I met in life and found so often that they were the children of Army professionals -- officers and enlisted alike.</p>
        <p>Yes, the Army is a family affair. Now my son has completed his training as an Army medic and is working to become an Army nurse. A truly noble endeavor and one for which I am very proud of him.</p>
        <p>Roger Lindland  Rancho Santa Fe, Calif.  April 3, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>When Robert Wright said, ''If all of America were more like the Army, it would be a better country,'' it was hardly hyperbole.</p>
        <p>If that were the case, intelligence would be rigorously scrutinized, not misrepresented to justify war.</p>
        <p>Atrocities like Abu Ghraib would be much less likely to occur. The conditions for abuse were created by civilians in this administration, including the attorney general, who was the president's legal counselor.</p>
        <p>The Army effectively applied President Harry Truman's policy of integrating blacks. President Dwight D. Eisenhower used the loyal United States Army to force compliance with the Supreme Court's decision requiring school integration.</p>
        <p>If the new Democratic Congress can muster the courage to pass legislation repealing the bigoted, human-resource-wasting ''don't ask, don't tell'' policy, the Army meritocracy would, yet again, lead the way in social equality.</p>
        <p>Andre Sauvageot  Reston, Va., April 3, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a retired United States Army colonel.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I was delighted to read about Robert Wright's experiences growing up on a military base, as my experience was similar. I, however, joined the Air Force after college, and was commissioned as a second lieutenant by my father, a retired lieutenant colonel.</p>
        <p>After nine years in the Air Force, I joined the Foreign Service, where I was repeatedly insulted and derided for my military background.</p>
        <p>Upon leaving the Foreign Service, I compared the two this way: In the military, you dress the same but you can think differently. In the Foreign Service, you can dress differently but you have to think the same way.</p>
        <p>Nancy Galloway  Crawford Bay, British Columbia April 3, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Robert Wright calls the military a ''bastion of egalitarianism'' and hopes that America will learn from the Army's commitment to equality in schools, health care and professional mobility.</p>
        <p>But he remains silent on a key policy that undermines respect for the military: its exclusion of known gays and lesbians.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Wright argues, much of today's military is indeed conscientious, professional and respectful of diversity. This increasingly includes tolerance of gays and lesbians. It is the political and military leaders who claim that soldiers are too bigoted to serve with their gay comrades who are responsible for staining the honor and dignity of a military that deserves better.</p>
        <p>Nathaniel Frank  Philadelphia, April 3, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a senior research fellow at the Michael D. Palm Center, University of California at Santa Barbara.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I wonder if the egalitarianism of Robert Wright's childhood extended to housing and playgrounds as well as schools. My experience on both sides of the bar was that officers' children were separated from enlisted dependents by the hierarchy of rank as well as by the geography of the housing.</p>
        <p>I am not surprised that Shaquille O'Neal, the son of a sergeant, was less than impressed when Mr. Wright, the son of a colonel, told him that they had played basketball at the same high school at Fort Sam Houston.</p>
        <p>Edwin M. Higginbotham  Shreveport, La., April 3, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a former staff sergeant and retired Air Force major.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Even though the Army provides benefits to soldiers that liberals might wish our country provided for all of its citizens, we shouldn't forget the questionable ends for which our Army is often deployed.</p>
        <p>Nor should we forget the underfinanced social programs that the trillions in military spending represent.</p>
        <p>Mark Johnson  Kirkland, Wash., April 3, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Robert Wright seems to dismiss the Abu Ghraib abuses as merely a product of the decisions made by upper-echelon civilians.</p>
        <p>Certainly, an incredible amount of blame goes to political figures like former Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld, Vice President Dick Cheney, President Bush and John C. Yoo, a former Justice Department lawyer. They helped create an environment in which the horrors of Abu Ghraib would not only take place but also go largely unpunished.</p>
        <p>But there still exists within the military a culture that saw those abuses as not only permissible but also so amusing as to warrant photographs and thumbs-up signs.</p>
        <p>The problems that led to the abuses of Abu Ghraib, and to those of Guantánamo Bay, run far deeper than Mr. Wright might have us believe.</p>
        <p>Adrian O'Connor  Paris, April 3, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
