<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pérez Continues The Mets' Streak Of Sparkling Starts</title>
    <meta content="07mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/sports/baseball/07mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pérez, Oliver</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reyes, Jose</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pérez Continues The Mets' Streak Of Sparkling Starts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pérez Continues the Mets’ Streak of Sparkling Starts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the giant American flag was presented, the military jets flew overhead and the Braves were introduced, something unprecedented happened for an opening game at Turner Field: The rafters in left field, where the pennants commemorating the Braves' division championships hang, remained quiet.</p>
        <p>It was not a mistake. The Mets spoiled the Braves' 14-year streak of division titles last season, and on Friday night they thrashed previously unbeaten Atlanta, 11-1, in an early-season battle for divisional supremacy before a disgusted sellout crowd of 51,014. It was the fourth consecutive victory for the Mets and each one has been more dominant than the previous one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coming off their three-game sweep against the Cardinals, the Mets continued to receive excellent starting pitching, this time by Oliver Pérez, and contributions up and down their lineup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the giant American flag was presented, the military jets flew overhead and the Braves were introduced, something unprecedented happened for an opening game at Turner Field: The rafters in left field, where the pennants commemorating the Braves' division championships hang, remained quiet.</p>
        <p>It was not a mistake. The Mets spoiled the Braves' 14-year streak of division titles last season, and on Friday night they thrashed previously unbeaten Atlanta, 11-1, in an early-season battle for divisional supremacy before a disgusted sellout crowd of 51,014. It was the fourth consecutive victory for the Mets and each one has been more dominant than the previous one.</p>
        <p>Matching their best start since 1985, the Mets have yet to trail, outscoring their opponents, 31-3, while receiving stellar starting pitching. The latest masterpiece came from Oliver Pérez, who, making his first start since Game 7 of last season's National League Championship Series, allowed one run in seven innings while scattering five hits, striking out six and, perhaps most important, walking none.</p>
        <p>''The first four guys have all outdone each other,'' catcher Paul Lo Duca said.</p>
        <p>Coming off their three-game sweep against the World Series champion Cardinals, every Mets starter had at least one hit, with José Reyes leading the way with three, including two triples, and four runs batted in. Leading by 2-1 through five innings, the Mets knocked out starter Mark Redman in the sixth, scoring three times, and then tacked on six more in the eighth to turn the game into a rout.</p>
        <p>The Braves managed only five hits, including a solo homer from Jeff Francoeur, who also provided the Braves' defensive highlight, a routine catch of a Carlos Delgado fly ball that earned him play-of-the-game honors. There was not really much else to choose from.</p>
        <p>Not since 1894 had two unbeaten N.L. teams with at least three victories faced each other -- it was Baltimore and Boston, for those scoring at home -- and the retooled Braves entered this series having swept the Phillies in Philadelphia. The same Phillies, it should be noted, whose starting shortstop, Jimmy Rollins, talked all spring about Philadelphia being the team to beat in the East.</p>
        <p>''It's just another example of why you keep quiet about something, because too often it comes back to bite you,'' Tom Glavine said before the game.</p>
        <p>Like the Phillies and Braves, the Mets retouched their roster during the off-season, but their biggest acquisition may wind up being Pérez. When he joined the team in a deal with Pittsburgh at last season's trading deadline, the Mets thought they had a potential steal -- that is, if they could overhaul his confidence while harnessing his superior ability. He went 1-3 for the Mets, but, after the impressive performance in Game 7, spent the off-season thinking about how that would be a springboard for his career.</p>
        <p>''Any time he pitches, I always feel like he's going to pitch well, because he has the stuff to do it,'' Manager Willie Randolph said.</p>
        <p>During his heyday with the Pirates, when he struck out 239 in 2004, Pérez threw one of the game's more lethal sliders. The pitch started returning this spring when he struck out nine Red Sox batters on March 15-- including Manny Ramírez and David Ortiz twice each. It was just as good, if not better, Friday night.</p>
        <p>Pérez plowed through the Braves in the first inning on nine pitches, including a strikeout of the leadoff hitter and former Met Chris Woodward on a slider. In the sixth, he caught Edgar Renteria staring at a 79-mile-an-hour backdoor slider. The next inning, Andruw Jones and Brian McCann never came close with their swings.</p>
        <p>''Everything was down in the zone,'' Pérez said.</p>
        <p>Randolph started the same lineup for the fourth consecutive game, and it was not only because he did not want to mess with success. With two days off in the first week, he said he needed to keep his regulars sharp. And they were.</p>
        <p>Reyes led off the game with a booming triple off Redman and scored on Lo Duca's sacrifice fly. In the second inning, José Valentín, who hit .219 against left-handed pitching last season, ripped a run-scoring double, making the score 2-0.</p>
        <p>No one could have faulted Randolph if he had started 22-year-old Lastings Milledge in right field against a left-hander, but he stuck with Shawn Green, who entered the game 4 for 4 in his career against Redman. Green popped up in his first two at-bats but singled home David Wright in the sixth with the Mets' third run. Three batters later, Reyes ripped a two-run triple to right-center that extended the Mets' lead to 5-1. As he always does after a triple, Reyes clapped his hands five times and beamed his wide smile.</p>
        <p>''I'm always trying to have fun,'' Reyes said. ''I have even more fun when we're winning.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Duaner Sánchez has chosen to have surgery on Tuesday to repair the hairline fracture of his coracoid, a small bone in the front of his right shoulder. Doctors will insert a small screw into the shoulder, and Sánchez is expected to be out until at least mid-August.  Reliever Juan Padilla suffered a setback in his return from reconstructive elbow surgery and will meet with the team medical director, Dr. David Altchek, on Monday. Padilla started feeling soreness shortly after making his only spring appearance, on March 11, and it has not subsided, said the assistant general manager John Ricco.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
