<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marbury Hurts Toe as the Knicks Lose Again</title>
    <meta content="07knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/sports/basketball/07knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Minnesota Timberwolves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Minnesota Timberwolves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marbury Hurts Toe as the Knicks Lose Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Marbury Hurts Toe as the Knicks Lose Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stephon Marbury has stood out on the court for the Knicks these past few weeks, and not just because of the quality of his play or his scoring. He has been the rarest of Knicks, someone who has been relatively healthy. With the way things have been going for the Knicks, maybe that was too good to last.</p>
        <p>Add Marbury to the long list of battered Knickerbockers. As David Lee returned from a right-leg stress injury and a bone bruise, Marbury missed most of last night's game, a 99-94 loss to the Minnesota Timberwolves, with turf toe on his right foot. He was not sure if he would be able to play tonight against Milwaukee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Without Stephon Marbury for much of the game, the Knicks saw their already faint hope of making the playoffs grow even dimmer Friday night against Minnesota.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stephon Marbury has stood out on the court for the Knicks these past few weeks, and not just because of the quality of his play or his scoring. He has been the rarest of Knicks, someone who has been relatively healthy. With the way things have been going for the Knicks, maybe that was too good to last.</p>
        <p>Add Marbury to the long list of battered Knickerbockers. As David Lee returned from a right-leg stress injury and a bone bruise, Marbury missed most of last night's game, a 99-94 loss to the Minnesota Timberwolves, with turf toe on his right foot. He was not sure if he would be able to play tonight against Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>The injury to Marbury, who came out of the game with 10 minutes 40 seconds remaining in the second quarter and did not return until there were 35 seconds left in the game, was just one piece of bad news for the Knicks.</p>
        <p>Without their leading scorer for much of the game, they saw their already faint hope of making the playoffs grow even dimmer.</p>
        <p>The loss was the fourth in a row for the Knicks (31-44) and their 10th in their past 12 games. They are now three games behind the Orlando Magic (34-41), which was idle last night, for the eighth and final playoff spot in the Eastern Conference. With only seven games left in the regular season and with so many top players injured, there is little reason to believe the Knicks are headed anywhere but home for the postseason.</p>
        <p>Marbury injured his toe a few minutes before he came out of the game, after he got tangled up with the Timberwolves' Michael James and landed awkwardly on his right foot. Marbury said he was nothing more than a ''decoy'' when he re-entered the game in the final seconds.</p>
        <p>''I was coming off a pick and roll and my foot got jammed up on the back of Mike James's foot, and then my foot hit the floor and I banged it,'' Marbury said. ''It was the same toe I jammed when we were playing against L.A. It's something I've been fighting for a while. At halftime, I got a shot in my foot. It numbed it up, but my toe got stiff, and I know when this shot wears off it's going to hurt.''</p>
        <p>Marbury said the injury would probably remain a problem the rest of the season.</p>
        <p>Not long before Marbury left the game, Lee entered. He came off the Knicks bench with 4:54 to go in the first quarter, seeing action for the first time since he played only 10 minutes on March 22. He played 20 minutes last night, scoring 6 points and grabbing 8 rebounds.</p>
        <p>''I'm playing the rest of the year,'' Lee said. ''As long as I can walk, I'll be out there trying to play.</p>
        <p>''I'm not anticipating feeling great tomorrow. Especially depending on how Steph feels tomorrow, we need guys. It's about more than me.''</p>
        <p>Before Marbury went out of the game, the Knicks were already in trouble. The first quarter ended with the Timberwolves leading, 28-17. The Knicks could not generate consistent offense and trailed, 59-41, at the half.</p>
        <p>But with Nate Robinson scoring 15 points in the third quarter, the Knicks cut Minnesota's lead to 4 points entering the fourth quarter and tied the score, 74-74, early in the period on a layup by Mardy Collins. But Randy Foye hit two 3-pointers in quick succession to give Minnesota some breathing room. Robinson hit a 3-pointer with 6:50 left in the game to pull the Knicks within 86-83, but Minnesota (32-43) regained some momentum and took an 8-point lead with 5:57 left.</p>
        <p>The Knicks closed within 2 points on a putback by Renaldo Balkman in the final minute. But Craig Smith pulled down an offensive rebound on the other end to seal Minnesota's victory after Foye missed the second of two free throws.</p>
        <p>''All season long, we have battled, but we don't do the little things,'' Coach Isiah Thomas said. ''Every time you're in a close game, it's the little things that hurt you. It's not the monumental things. I can remember saying the same things after the Cleveland game here, where we missed a lot of loose balls and didn't get rebounds.</p>
        <p>''All season long, we do the big things and do them quite well. When it comes down to the simple things you need to do to complete a game and complete a play, we're not quite there yet.''</p>
        <p>Robinson led the Knicks with 21 points and Eddy Curry had 20. Foye led Minnesota with 19 points.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Quentin Richardson, who underwent surgery March 29 to repair a herniated disk in his back, said that the operation appeared to be a complete success. ''I feel a lot better,'' he said. ''I walk better than I did before the surgery. I'm more straight up. I don't have any pain anymore. The only pain is from the wound and that's pretty minimal. I'm cool.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
