<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reporter at Dow Jones Online Site Resigns Over Web Venture</title>
    <meta content="07watch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/business/media/07watch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Marketwatch.com Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vator.tv</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Francisco, Bambi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Darlin, Damon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EED7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reporter at Dow Jones Online Site Resigns Over Web Venture</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reporter at Dow Jones Online Site Resigns Over Web Venture</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON DARLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Darlin, Damon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporter at Dow Jones Online</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A reporter for MarketWatch, an online business news site owned by Dow Jones, resigned yesterday after published reports suggested that a Web site she started on her own might have created a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>Dow Jones, which also owns The Wall Street Journal, issued a brief statement that said the reporter, Bambi Francisco, a columnist and video host, had decided to leave the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A reporter for MarketWatch resigned Friday after published reports suggested a Web site she started on her own might have created a conflict of interest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A reporter for MarketWatch, an online business news site owned by Dow Jones, resigned yesterday after published reports suggested that a Web site she started on her own might have created a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>Dow Jones, which also owns The Wall Street Journal, issued a brief statement that said the reporter, Bambi Francisco, a columnist and video host, had decided to leave the company.</p>
        <p>Ms. Francisco confirmed in her final MarketWatch column that she was leaving and said she was turning her attention to her online venture, Vator.tv, a video service that presents executives of start-up companies making pitches for financing from venture capitalists. (Vator refers to an ''elevator pitch,'' an entrepreneur's hurried description of a company's business plan.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Francisco received approval to start the company last year from MarketWatch's editor in chief, David Callaway.</p>
        <p>She said in an e-mail message that she was told she could not promote the site in her work at MarketWatch, which is based in San Francisco, or write about companies that appeared on Vator.tv.</p>
        <p>But she did write about some of the companies. ''I deemed some companies worth reporting on,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Francisco also wrote on MarketWatch about her partner in Vator.tv, Peter Thiel, a co-founder of PayPal and now a prominent Silicon Valley venture capitalist and hedge fund manager.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thiel revealed the relationship with Ms. Francisco last month in a talk he gave to a group of Silicon Valley business journalists. He did not respond to requests for comment.</p>
        <p>CNet, a technology news Web site, reported the story Thursday. It quoted Mr. Callaway as saying, ''the rigid rules of the past may not always apply to the new media.''</p>
        <p>But on Thursday, Mr. Callaway sent a message to MarketWatch staff saying that the company's ethical standards were identical to those of Dow Jones, which prohibits its employees from investing in companies they write about.</p>
        <p>Ms. Francisco said in an e-mail message that, ''My investment essentially was the sweat-equity I poured into creating it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Francisco said she expected Dow Jones to issue a news release saying that she did not violate the company's code of conduct rules and that she used sound judgment.</p>
        <p>But in a statement released yesterday evening, L. Gordon Crovitz, executive vice president of the parent company, said nothing that would either clear or incriminate Ms. Francisco.</p>
        <p>''Dow Jones demands the highest journalism standards at our own publications and services, as reflected by our strict code of conduct. Our MarketWatch reporter Bambi Francisco started Vator.tv on her own time with our approval, under certain guidelines on permitted areas of coverage. Bambi has decided to pursue her enterprise full time,'' the statement said.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Dow Jones said that Mr. Callaway would remain as editor of MarketWatch.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
