<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Griffin Spins Wheel and Gets Horse With Derby Potential</title>
    <meta content="07racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/sports/othersports/07racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Griffin, Merv</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Griffin Spins Wheel and Gets Horse With Derby Potential</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Griffin Spins Wheel and Gets Horse With Derby Potential</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his primary pursuits, success has always come easily for Merv Griffin, who, with his hit records, hit game shows, popular talk shows and savvy real estate investments, is good at just about whatever he does. Horse racing, though, is different. Last year Griffin, who operates a modest-sized racing stable, could not conquer the Kentucky Derby, where winning is as much about luck as it is about talent or smarts.</p>
        <p>In Stevie Wonderboy, the champion 2-year-old of 2005, he had the horse. But the colt sustained a hairline fracture to his right front ankle about two months before the Derby and has not raced since. Now, Griffin has another chance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Merv Griffin’s Cobalt Blue has won three of four lifetime starts, including the San Felipe Stakes at Santa Anita, and will be favored in Saturday’s Illinois Derby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his primary pursuits, success has always come easily for Merv Griffin, who, with his hit records, hit game shows, popular talk shows and savvy real estate investments, is good at just about whatever he does. Horse racing, though, is different. Last year Griffin, who operates a modest-sized racing stable, could not conquer the Kentucky Derby, where winning is as much about luck as it is about talent or smarts.</p>
        <p>In Stevie Wonderboy, the champion 2-year-old of 2005, he had the horse. But the colt sustained a hairline fracture to his right front ankle about two months before the Derby and has not raced since. Now, Griffin has another chance.</p>
        <p>Just 22 days after Stevie Wonderboy was injured, Griffin paid $325,000 at a 2-year-old sale for an unraced colt named Cobalt Blue. That is not a lot of money in an era where well-bred yearlings and 2-year-olds often sell for millions, but Griffin wound up with a very good horse.</p>
        <p>Cobalt Blue has won three of four lifetime starts, including the San Felipe Stakes at Santa Anita, and will be favored in today's Illinois Derby at Hawthorne. With a victory, and barring an injury, he will head to Churchill Downs as one of the favorites for the Kentucky Derby on May 5.</p>
        <p>''I really feel fortunate,'' Griffin said. ''I had no idea this was going to happen again. We knew that we had bought a really exciting little colt with great breeding, but we never expected him to do the things he's done.''</p>
        <p>The Illinois Derby is just one of three major Kentucky Derby prep races that will be run Saturday. At Aqueduct, Any Given Saturday and Nobiz Like Shobiz are the big names among a field of seven entered in the Wood Memorial. Ten are set to go in the Santa Anita Derby, which drew one of its weakest fields in years.</p>
        <p>Cobalt Blue won his first career start, a five-furlong race last June at Hollywood Park. But he failed in his stakes debut, running seventh in the Best Pal Stakes. It turned out that he had a muscle problem during the race and was given the rest of the year off.</p>
        <p>He returned with an allowance victory at Santa Anita on Feb. 14 and then won the mile-and-a-sixteenth San Felipe in his attempt beyond 6 1/2 furlongs.</p>
        <p>''Is he better than Stevie? I couldn't say that,'' Griffin said. ''They're different horses. They're almost the same size and they're both very powerful horses, but Stevie was something amazing. We have yet to find out if this horse is truly amazing. We think he is, but the race is the thing. It's like on Broadway, where the play is the thing.''</p>
        <p>The Louisiana Derby winner Circular Quay was expected to run in the Wood Memorial, but the trainer Todd Pletcher changed his plans. Willing to buck the conventional wisdom that says a horse can not win the Derby off any kind of extended layoff, Pletcher decided to skip today's round of prep races. Circular Quay will now come into the Derby off an eight-week layoff. His stablemate Any Given Saturday, who was second behind the Eclipse Award winner Street Sense in the Tampa Bay Derby, will take his place in the Wood Memorial lineup.</p>
        <p>Nobiz Like Shobiz is trained by Barclay Tagg, who won the 2003 Kentucky Derby with Funny Cide. He is coming off a modest effort in the Fountain of Youth at Gulfstream, where he finished third. Hoping to have his horse more focused this time, Tagg will race Nobiz Like Shobiz in blinkers for the first time.</p>
        <p>''He's got plenty of talent, but he's still a little immature,'' Tagg said. ''Hopefully, the blinkers will help.''</p>
        <p>The Santa Anita Derby usually brings together the most talented 3-year-olds based in Southern California, but several are taking part in other prep races around the country. Among those who have stayed, Liquidity may be the most talented. He is trained by Doug O'Neill, also the trainer of Cobalt Blue. Pletcher is also represented in the Santa Anita Derby with King of the Roxy. Sam P. Pletcher, who could start as many as seven horses in the Derby, will run Cowtown Cat in the Illinois Derby.</p>
        <p>NOTES</p>
        <p>Barbaro's little brother has a name: Nicanor. Like the name Barbaro, Nicanor comes from a painting owned by the horses' owners, Roy and Gretchen Jackson. The painting features several dogs, one of whom is named Barbaro. In the painting, the dog closest to Barbaro is named Nicanor. Nicanor the horse is a 1-year-old who could make his racing debut as early as next summer. Barbaro's dam, La Ville Rouge, is set to deliver another foal, who will also be a full brother to Barbaro, ''any day now,'' according to Roy Jackson. Jackson added that no decision has been made concerning where Barbaro's ashes will be spread.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
