<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jazz Meets Ballet and a Tango Breaks Out</title>
    <meta content="07odys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/arts/dance/07odys.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EED9173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jazz Meets Ballet and a Tango Breaks Out</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jazz Meets Ballet and a Tango Breaks Out</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Odyssey Dance Theater called its New York debut program ''Shut Up and Dance!'' but failed to heed that advice. A jazz-ballet company based in Salt Lake City, Odyssey performs in a fusion style that is now familiar, blending traditional jazz with classical ballet and modern dance and in the process losing much of the distinctively sharp, thrusting edge of traditional jazz dance.</p>
        <p>What the dancers performed on Thursday night at the Ailey Citigroup Theater, in choreography by Mia Michaels, Mandy Moore and the company's founder and artistic director, Derryl Yeager, was dull-edged and freighted with solemn themes and messages, though none was self-apparent. Suddenly I missed the slam-bang jazz dance of old, for all its heartless, soul-less pizazz.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Odyssey Dance Theater called its New York debut program “Shut Up and Dance!” but failed to heed that advice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Odyssey Dance Theater called its New York debut program ''Shut Up and Dance!'' but failed to heed that advice. A jazz-ballet company based in Salt Lake City, Odyssey performs in a fusion style that is now familiar, blending traditional jazz with classical ballet and modern dance and in the process losing much of the distinctively sharp, thrusting edge of traditional jazz dance.</p>
        <p>What the dancers performed on Thursday night at the Ailey Citigroup Theater, in choreography by Mia Michaels, Mandy Moore and the company's founder and artistic director, Derryl Yeager, was dull-edged and freighted with solemn themes and messages, though none was self-apparent. Suddenly I missed the slam-bang jazz dance of old, for all its heartless, soul-less pizazz.</p>
        <p>The Odyssey dancers can certainly perform that way. Just when it seemed that traveling fast across the stage -- or traveling at all -- must be against the company rules, the dancers were allowed to let loose toward the end of Ms. Michaels's ''Transitional Illuminations.'' The themes of air flight and loneliness were addressed, and then finally, blessedly, ''Illuminations'' did shut up and allow its performers just to move, which they did excitingly in churning, odd-shaped cross-stage runs, crawls and encounters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeager's background in musical theater and industrial shows was evident in ''Moulin Rouge!'' Loosely based on the film musical, it was choreographed with Andrea Hale and three company members. Here, too, the dancers were allowed to move, which they did exuberantly and skillfully, in cancans, a tango, a ballet-jazz duet and a solo for the Toulouse-Lautrec character, poignantly portrayed by Thayne Jasperson. In the solo, Mr. Yeager created an ingenious dance for a man whose physical deformities were never quite lost, even as he wafted and spun in a love-inspired dream. His dream lover was danced by Christina Bluth, in a lead cast completed by Eldon Johnson, Karl Hendrickson and Junior Case. Mr. Case was a rotund delight as the dance's master of ceremonies and pimp. He would be well advised to keep his shirt on. But ''Moulin Rouge!'' was a lot of fun.</p>
        <p>''Shut Up and Dance!'' continues through tomorrow at the Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Manhattan; (212) 686-4444.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
