<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sometimes Keeping The Beat Is Easy</title>
    <meta content="07perc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/arts/music/07perc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Manhattan School of Music</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Juilliard School</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wuorinen, Charles</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D8173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sometimes Keeping The Beat Is Easy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sometimes Keeping the Beat Is Easy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL J. WAKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wakin, Daniel J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A brigade of young percussionists flicked their mallets up and down amid a thick underbrush of drums, chimes, vibes and the metal equipment that held them. An encyclopedia of plinks and plunks, thwoks and whacks flew out from the stage.</p>
        <p>It was a performance at the Manhattan School of Music of the Percussion Symphony by Charles Wuorinen, the thorny modernist composer who at 68 is experiencing a new springtime late in his career.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Manhattan School of Music and the Juilliard School’s joint performance of Charles Wuorinen’s Percussion Symphony is heaven for those who wield the mallet for a living, or aspire to.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A brigade of young percussionists flicked their mallets up and down amid a thick underbrush of drums, chimes, vibes and the metal equipment that held them. An encyclopedia of plinks and plunks, thwoks and whacks flew out from the stage.</p>
        <p>It was a performance at the Manhattan School of Music of the Percussion Symphony by Charles Wuorinen, the thorny modernist composer who at 68 is experiencing a new springtime late in his career.</p>
        <p>The scene Thursday night was rare on several levels. The piece, which calls for 20 percussionists and three keyboard players, is not often performed. Who can bring so many drummers together at once? And the players came from the Manhattan School of Music and the Juilliard School in an unusual collaboration between two sometime rivals.</p>
        <p>''It is a party on stage,'' Jeffrey Milarsky, the conductor, said last week. ''It's an unbelievable controlled cacophony.'' Yet the 45-minute work also has the scope, the sound world, of a symphony ''in the truest sense,'' said Mr. Milarsky, the director of the Manhattan School's percussion ensemble, a Columbia University lecturer and a self-described Wuorinen fanatic.</p>
        <p>A second performance is scheduled for April 16 at Alice Tully Hall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milarsky cooked up the idea for the concerts in 2005 with an old friend and colleague, Daniel Druckman, chairman of Juilliard's percussion department and a member of the New York Philharmonic. It is the kind of composition that can rarely be done outside conservatories and universities, which have the troops.</p>
        <p>The two schools coordinate audition times for students and share teachers and new-music concert programs. But they do not often join up in such a high-profile way.</p>
        <p>The concerts are percussion heaven for those who wield the mallet for a living, or aspire to. The long list of instruments includes cymbals, glockenspiels, chimes, timpani (two sets), triangles, metal plates, brake drums, gongs, tam-tams, 12 roto-toms (differently pitched small drums), glass chimes, wood blocks, tambourines, bass drums, two vibraphones and a xylophone. The vibraphone and marimba players occasionally use contrabass bows against the edge of their bars to create eerie glass harmonica sounds, like a finger around a wet glass rim. There are a celesta and two pianos, with one assigned a player to tap on the strings inside. The score has a diagram of how to place the instruments.</p>
        <p>''It's the entire gamut of drums, skins, metals, keyboards and mallets,'' Mr. Milarsky said. ''It's every sort of timbre we have.''</p>
        <p>For centuries percussion had a peripheral role in orchestras, used for exclamation points or color. Only in the last hundred years has the percussion family come into its own, thanks to the discovery of instruments of other cultures, improved technique and a modern search for different sounds.</p>
        <p>''We're not just the timekeepers anymore, but fully fledged musicians,'' Mr. Milarsky said. Hence modern composers like Mr. Wuorinen are considered their masters.</p>
        <p>''He's one of the two or three most important people for us in terms of central works and stretching the limits of what the instruments can do,'' Mr. Druckman said of Mr. Wuorinen.</p>
        <p>Percussionists are attractive to write for, Mr. Wuorinen said in an interview. ''They have a sense of their classic literature being made now. There's a different attitude.''</p>
        <p>But the nature of the instruments also appeals to him, he said. ''They can make a lot of noise, which is always fun.''</p>
        <p>More seriously, Mr. Wuorinen said he was drawn by instruments that make sounds that decay, or ring, rather than sustain. ''It's a marvelous sound world,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wuorinen took an active role in the preparation, answering Mr. Milarsky's questions and sitting in on rehearsals. During one rehearsal last week at Juilliard, he sat in a chair next to the conductor and closely followed the score, often suggesting changes in balance, timbre or tempo, and even pointing out a single wrong note in a complex marimba passage. At one point, one of the pianists had trouble muting the inside strings with one hand. ''Just play it on the keyboard,'' Mr. Wuorinen said. ''Life's too short.''</p>
        <p>At the first concert, two grand pianos were wedged together, like a yin and a yang, in front of Mr. Milarsky on the stage of the Manhattan School's Borden Hall. The vibes, marimba and xylophone stood in a semicircle around them. The other instruments were arrayed beyond in widening ranks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wuorinen sat in the front of the audience, which appeared to be mostly students. After the frequently tranquil second movement, Mr. Milarsky turned to stare down a snorer in the front row. When it was over, after enthusiastic applause, Mr. Wuorinen took a bow, and Mr. Milarsky pointed his finger at him, as if to say ''You da man.'' Afterward, Mr. Wuorinen said, ''That was really good.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wuorinen wrote the Percussion Symphony in 1976, well before most of the performers were born, and it has been well liked by critics. It has received performances every several years, and it was recorded for the Nonesuch label. The performances this month are the latest in a spate of recent concerts and recordings of Mr. Wuorinen's music after his highly modernist idiom fell out of fashion in the Minimalist and neo-Romantic surge of recent decades.</p>
        <p>The piece is in three meaty, atonal movements of ever shifting meters, moods and sound palettes. The music evokes the gamelan, or incandescent undersea creatures suddenly shadowed by a big fish. Sounds combine in fascinating combinations: high piano notes and the xylophone, a wood block and a marimba, a vibraphone and a glockenspiel.</p>
        <p>Two ''entr'actes'' surround the slow middle movement, otherworldly and beautiful reworkings of a 15th-century vocal setting of Petrarch's ''Vergine Bella'' by Guillaume Dufay that are like sherbet courses in the main meal and serve as a ''little break'' between the movements, Mr. Wuorinen said.</p>
        <p>''Some people don't approve of this pillaging of old music,'' he added, revealing his longstanding polemical streak. ''But I don't care. If there's something I like in old music, I steal it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
