<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Setback Then a Reprieve for Vonage in Courts</title>
    <meta content="07vonage" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/technology/07vonage.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royalties</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vonage Holdings Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hilton, Claude M (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Laurie J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Vonage</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Verizon Communications</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Setback Then a Reprieve for Vonage in Courts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Setback Then a Reprieve for Vonage in Courts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Judge Claude M Hilton issues partial injunction that says Vonage can service existing customers but not new ones; federal appeals court gives Vonage temporary stay of that injunction, allowing company to continue to enroll customers while it seeks to overturn lower court ruling; Vonage has been entangled for years in patent dispute with Verizon Communications, which has accused it of violating three patents covering technology that allows low-cost voice calls to be made over Internet; court action comes one month after jury ruled that Vonage was guilty of patent infringement and ordered it to pay Verizon $58 million and royalties on future sales (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vonage Holdings, the Internet phone company, had a wild ride in the courtroom yesterday.</p>
        <p>First, a federal judge in Alexandria, Va., barred Vonage from signing up new customers for its Internet phone service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal court gave Vonage a reprieve shortly after a lower court barred it from enrolling new subscribers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vonage Holdings, the Internet phone company, had a wild ride in the courtroom yesterday.</p>
        <p>First, a federal judge in Alexandria, Va., barred Vonage from signing up new customers for its Internet phone service.</p>
        <p>Then hours later, a federal appeals court gave Vonage a temporary stay of that injunction, allowing the company to continue to enroll customers while it sought to overturn the lower court ruling.</p>
        <p>Vonage, based in Holmdel, N.J., has been entangled for years in a patent dispute with Verizon Communications, which had accused it of violating three patents covering technology that allows low-cost voice calls to be made over the Internet.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the United States Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit in Washington issued its temporary stay in response to a request from Vonage. The move came after Judge Claude M. Hilton of the Federal District Court in Alexandria, Va., issued a partial injunction that said Vonage could service existing customers but not new ones.</p>
        <p>The court action came a month after a jury in the Eastern District of Virginia ruled that Vonage was guilty of patent infringement and ordered it to pay Verizon $58 million and royalties on future sales.</p>
        <p>For Vonage, being able to continue enrolling new subscribers was essential -- particularly in an industry where customers tend to jump from one provider to another.</p>
        <p>The lawyer for Vonage told the court yesterday that the company loses more than 50,000 subscribers a month, so being prevented from acquiring new customers could have a serious impact on the company's survival.</p>
        <p>''It's the difference of cutting off oxygen as opposed to the bullet in the head,'' the lawyer for Vonage, Roger Warin, told the court, according to The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>Several years ago, Vonage was among the very first to market with technology that transmits voice calls over the Internet, an approach known as VoIP. It currently has 2.2 million customers.</p>
        <p>But the company has faltered badly in the face of competition from a host of well-heeled cable and phone companies, and its stock has lost 80 percent of its value since its initial public offering.</p>
        <p>During the last year, traditional phone companies as well as the cable industry have moved into the market, offering low-cost bundles of services, including phone, cable and Internet access. As a result, Vonage stock has steadily lost value.</p>
        <p>Last May, Vonage went public in a highly publicized offering priced at $17. It sold 31.3 million shares and raised $531.3 million. The shares fell nearly 13 percent on the first day, closing at $14.85. It closed at $3.37 Thursday. The stock market was closed yesterday.</p>
        <p>Vonage shares dropped more than 25 percent to reach a record low of $3 a share after Judge Hilton ordered the company on March 23 to stop using technologies patented by Verizon.</p>
        <p>Shares of Verizon rose 39 cents, to close at $38 on Thursday.</p>
        <p>John Thorne, Verizon senior vice president and deputy general counsel, said in an interview yesterday that Vonage did not adequately make its case for a full stay of the ruling, which would have allowed the company to continue acquiring new business while the appeal was pending.</p>
        <p>The partial injunction, he said, was a fair compromise.</p>
        <p>''Judge Hilton exercised the court's equitable discretion to craft a middle path that allows Vonage to continue serving its existing customers while protecting Verizon's patents from increased infringement during the appeal process,'' Mr. Thorne said in a statement. Mr. Thorne said he expected the ruling to be upheld on appeal.</p>
        <p>Verizon filed its original complaint against Vonage last June, accusing the company of violating seven patents related to voice calls on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Later, the company scaled back the complaint to include only five patents, and in March the court ruled Vonage had not infringed two of them. The patents that the court ruled that Vonage had infringed related to connecting Internet calls to traditional phone networks, Wi-Fi and services like call-waiting and voice mail.</p>
        <p>Vonage has denied the claims, saying that its service uses standard ''off the shelf'' technology. Nevertheless, the company said, it is developing a workaround that does not include the technology in dispute.</p>
        <p>Gigi Sohn, a lawyer with Public Knowledge, a public interest research organization in Washington, criticized the ruling for its potential impact on competition so early in an emerging industry. ''Any time a company is told they can't add new customers it's pretty serious,'' Ms. Sohn said. ''I'm not sure the judge fully understands what this could do to a relatively small company like Vonage.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sohn said Verizon was unfairly using its patents as a competitive weapon. ''I think Verizon is pulling out all the stops to put Vonage out of business,'' she said.</p>
        <p>At a hearing scheduled for next Thursday the judge will set the amount of bond Vonage must post during the appeal process.</p>
        <p>Verizon has asked the court for a bond of $189 million to cover damages for infringement of the patents by Vonage's existing customers, in addition to the $66 million bond it was already ordered to post.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
