<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Neighborhood in Shock and Four Young Men Facing Possibility of Life in Prison</title>
    <meta content="07robbers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/nyregion/07robbers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838552"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AN AGENT FALLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bank Robberies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Brunswick (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pnc Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berrios, Wilfredo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lynn, Efrain</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruz, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herrera-Genao, Francisco J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Barry Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Capuzzo, Jill P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Richard G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EED6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Neighborhood in Shock and Four Young Men Facing Possibility of Life in Prison</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Neighborhood in Shock and Four Young Men Facing Possibility of Life in Prison</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JILL P. CAPUZZO and RICHARD G. JONES; Jill P. Capuzzo reported from New Brunswick and Richard G. Jones from Yardley, Pa. William K. Rashbaum and Ronald Smothers contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Capuzzo, Jill P; Jones, Richard G</byline>
      <dateline>NEW BRUNSWICK, N.J., April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Four men accused of being part of gang of bank robbers whose confrontation with authorities on April 5 ended in death of veteran FBI agent all lived within blocks of one another in New Brunswick, NJ; their relatives and neighbors are reeling from news; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The four men lived within blocks of one another in the shadow of Rutgers University, in a neighborhood of aging single-family and row homes sprinkled with bodegas and small drugstores.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the four young men were in federal custody, accused of being part of a gang of bank robbers whose confrontation with the authorities in New Jersey on Thursday ended in the shooting death of a veteran F.B.I. agent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four young men who lived near Rutgers University are now in federal custody, accused of being part of a gang of bank robbers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The four men lived within blocks of one another in the shadow of Rutgers University, in a neighborhood of aging single-family and row homes sprinkled with bodegas and small drugstores.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the four young men were in federal custody, accused of being part of a gang of bank robbers whose confrontation with the authorities in New Jersey on Thursday ended in the shooting death of a veteran F.B.I. agent.</p>
        <p>Back in their working-class neighborhood, Jose Nieves was replacing the wooden doorjamb at 68 Comstock Avenue that the authorities had smashed while seeking clues they hoped would lead to one of the suspects.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nieves had always sworn to Alejandrina Herrera, his companion, that he would care for her son if she no longer could. After Ms. Herrera died in a car accident in her native Mexico last year, Mr. Nieves, 61, kept his promise.</p>
        <p>But what he said he could not do was keep her son, Efrain Lynn, from running with the wrong crowd.</p>
        <p>''He was always in trouble, skipping school, driving crazy, getting in fights,'' Mr. Nieves said. ''I never knew what he was really up to.''</p>
        <p>Now he does.</p>
        <p>Officials say that Barry Lee Bush, a veteran F.B.I. agent in the Newark bureau, was killed during a confrontation with Mr. Lynn's three friends, who along with him are suspected of carrying out a string of armed bank robberies in northern and central New Jersey.</p>
        <p>One law enforcement official who spoke on the condition of anonymity described the gang as ''a crew of guys'' who elaborately planned the robberies and then went about them armed with assault rifles and other large-caliber weapons.</p>
        <p>Carrie Brzenzinski, the F.B.I agent in charge of the investigation into the bank robberies, said the modus operandi of the crew was unusual, in that they typically fired a shot upon entering banks to show that they were in control. She said it was the first time in 16 years of investigating bank robberies that she had encountered actual shots being fired.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brzenzinski said of the four: ''Based on my observations, they were not living large. But they were aggressive, cocky and had this 'in your face nature.' There was this growing boldness and sense of confidence.''</p>
        <p>Shortly after the shooting on Thursday, the authorities arrested Mr. Lynn and two of the other men from New Brunswick: Wilfredo Berrios, 28, and Michael Cruz, 21. The fourth man, Francisco Herrera-Genao, 22, was arrested shirtless, shoeless, muddy and cold Friday morning after spending the night in a wooded area in the central New Jersey town of Readington.</p>
        <p>The men are expected to be arraigned on robbery and weapons charges Monday before United States Magistrate Judge Madeleine Cox Arleo in Newark. Additional charges -- including murder -- will probably be forthcoming in connection with Mr. Bush's death, though Charles McKenna, a federal prosecutor, said the federal felony murder charge, which carries the death penalty, would not apply because the crime had not occurred on federal property.</p>
        <p>Mr. McKenna said that nonetheless, each suspect would most likely face up to 140 years in prison if convicted on all the charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynn and Mr. Cruz lived on Comstock Street, while Mr. Herrera-Genao lived on Lee Avenue and Mr. Berrios on Welton Street, all within blocks of one another.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nieves said he was not surprised by the news that the man he described as his son-in-law -- and with whom he had an increasingly strained relationship over the past seven years -- had been arrested.</p>
        <p>''He don't talk to me, I don't talk to him,'' Mr. Nieves said.</p>
        <p>But he said he had been fairly stunned by the knot of F.B.I. agents and police officers who showed up at his house on Thursday night -- and who handcuffed him and led him outside while they searched the house.</p>
        <p>''They grabbed me and dragged me outside with no shoes,'' he said. ''I'm not a criminal. But they wouldn't tell me anything. I guess they were looking for a gun.''</p>
        <p>In the end, there were no guns among the 41 items seized, according to an F.B.I. inventory. But there were bank records, phone records, documents from the Middlesex County juvenile court and probation office pertaining to Mr. Lynn, a passport, a firefighter's application, shoes, clothing and ''a plastic container of brown and green substance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nieves said that after Mr. Nieves's mother, an aunt and a cousin were killed in the car crash last year, he had let Mr. Lynn, the father of two young daughters from different mothers, live on the second floor of his home.</p>
        <p>Down the street, at the Cruz home, family members were still reeling from the news of Michael Cruz's arrest. His brother, Ronald, answered the door of their gray frame house, but declined to comment at the urging of his mother.</p>
        <p>''We really don't want to talk about it,'' Mr. Cruz said. ''It's been hard enough.''</p>
        <p>There was no answer at the single-family house of Mr. Herrera-Genao, whom Mr. Nieves described as Mr. Lynn's best friend.</p>
        <p>At the apartment building where Mr. Berrios lived with his wife and child, a neighbor across the hall, Maria Hernandez, said the F.B.I. had also surrounded her building on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>''We were nervous,'' Ms. Hernandez said. ''There was a lot of noise and a lot of police. We thought someone was fighting.''</p>
        <p>She described the Berrioses, who were not at home when the police arrived, as quiet.</p>
        <p>The same could not be said about Mr. Lynn.</p>
        <p>''He was changing cars every two or three weeks, so we guessed there was something wrong there,'' said the neighbor, a mother of three who did not want to give her name.</p>
        <p>Steve Gartzman, a 22-year-old engineering student at Rutgers, who rents a two-bedroom house across the street from Mr. Lynn, called the burst of law enforcement agents Thursday night thrilling.</p>
        <p>''There were these F.B.I. agents all over the place, wearing camouflage and carrying big machine guns,'' Mr. Gartzman said. ''I thought it was really exciting. Finally we get some action around here.''</p>
        <p>AN AGENT FALLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
