<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Wins Singles Matches To Take Control Against Spain</title>
    <meta content="07tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/sports/tennis/07tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Blake, James</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Roddick, Andy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Robredo, Tommy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Verdasco, Fernando</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EED6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Wins Singles Matches To Take Control Against Spain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Wins Singles Matches to Take Control Against Spain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
      <dateline>WINSTON-SALEM, N.C., April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last time the United States faced Spain in the Davis Cup, James Blake was at home in Tampa, Fla., recovering from injury, illness and the death of his father. And the Americans were in deep trouble.</p>
        <p>Blake could do little more than watch as the United States lost in that 2004 final in Seville, Spain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>James Blake made short work of Spain’s No. 1 singles player, defeating Tommy Robredo while Andy Roddick capped a sweep for the United States against Fernando Verdasco.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last time the United States faced Spain in the Davis Cup, James Blake was at home in Tampa, Fla., recovering from injury, illness and the death of his father. And the Americans were in deep trouble.</p>
        <p>Blake could do little more than watch as the United States lost in that 2004 final in Seville, Spain.</p>
        <p>This time, Blake made his presence felt. He gave the United States a 1-0 lead against Spain Friday in its quarterfinal match at Lawrence Joel Veterans Memorial Coliseum. Blake made short work of Spain's No. 1 singles player, defeating Tommy Robredo by 6-4, 6-3, 6-4 in front of a capacity crowd of 14,453.</p>
        <p>Andy Roddick, showing no signs of the strained hamstring he sustained a week ago in Miami, capped a sweep of the day for the United States with a 7-6 (5), 6-1, 6-4 victory against Fernando Verdasco.</p>
        <p>With its 2-0 lead, the United States can clinch the quarterfinal with a victory in the doubles match Saturday, when Bob and Mike Bryan will face Verdasco and Feliciano López.</p>
        <p>The Bryans are 10-1 in Davis Cup competition.</p>
        <p>A victory would advance the United States to the semifinals in September against the winner of the quarterfinal between Sweden and Argentina. Sweden led, 2-0, after Friday's matches.</p>
        <p>For Blake, there was a familiar feel to his match against Robredo. He was back on the court where he made his Davis Cup debut as a 21-year-old in 2001, defeating Leander Paes of India in front of a crowd that included his parents.</p>
        <p>''I'll never get that smile he had out of my memory when he was watching me play,'' Blake said of his father, Thomas, who died of cancer in July 2004. ''He knew I was going to win. I was nervous. I was so uptight and scared, and he had that big smile on his face and was just happy that I was playing and proud of me and knew I would do my best.</p>
        <p>''And coming off the court he had a huge smile on his face. And so did my mom. They were so happy for me and I was so happy for them. And that's something I'll remember forever.''</p>
        <p>Blake said he drew on that memory Friday. This time, along with his mother, Betty, he had his brother, Thomas, offering support from the stands, as well as a partisan, flag-waving crowd.</p>
        <p>It was the first time Blake won an opening match for the United States; he lifted his Davis Cup record to 10-7. The victory had to serve as a boost for Blake, who has been struggling with his confidence. He was 3-6 in his previous nine matches, including consecutive losses in tournaments at Indian Wells, Calif., and Miami.</p>
        <p>''To beat a top-10 player in three straight sets, that's going to give me a little confidence,'' Blake said.</p>
        <p>Blake and the United States team became the clear favorites when Spain's top player, Rafael Nadal, decided not to play because of a foot injury. Nadal, ranked No. 2 in the world, chose to prepare for the clay-court season.</p>
        <p>The hardcourt surface here also favors the Americans. Spain won its 2004 final on clay.</p>
        <p>Robredo came in ranked sixth in the world and was a strong stand-in for Nadal. But not strong enough.</p>
        <p>''To me, it was a big moment for him, with Andy coming in, having come off of his leg injury,'' the United States captain, Patrick McEnroe, said of Blake.</p>
        <p>Roddick improved his Davis Cup record to 23-9, although he had a few nervous moments at the end. Roddick let five match points slip away before finishing off Verdasco.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
