<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Rite of Spring, Couples Makes Cut at Augusta for 23rd Straight Time</title>
    <meta content="07masters" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Rite of Spring, Couples Makes Cut at Augusta for 23rd Straight Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a season of limited golf swings and loads of back pain, Fred Couples arrived this week at Augusta National Golf Club seeking a few good golf shots and the continuation of a Masters streak.</p>
        <p>By sundown Friday, he had achieved both. Couples, the 1992 champion, shot a four-over-par 76 to make his 23rd consecutive cut at the Masters, tying the record held by Gary Player.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a season of limited golf swings and loads of back pain, Fred Couples arrived this week at Augusta National Golf Club seeking a few good golf shots and the continuation of a Masters streak.</p>
        <p>By sundown Friday, he had achieved both. Couples, the 1992 champion, shot a four-over-par 76 to make his 23rd consecutive cut at the Masters, tying the record held by Gary Player.</p>
        <p>His round completed, Couples signed his scorecard and walked up a hill behind the 18th green. With a 10-shot deficit behind the leaders, Brett Wetterich and Tim Clark, his chances of winning a second green jacket seemed nonexistent. Still, he found comfort in the familiar: golf at Augusta National on the weekend.</p>
        <p>''To make the cut is great,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Couples, 47, has been so worn down by pain this year that he entered the Masters having played only two competitive rounds this season. A year ago at the Masters, he played in the final group with Phil Mickelson before finishing tied for third. That would be a long shot this year.</p>
        <p>''The way I played, I was a little sloppy,'' Couples said. ''I could have been better. It's a hard course. It's not a back issue.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Couples has had his back seize up at unexpected times in his life. He said he was not sure when he would play again after the Masters. The on-again, off-again nature of his pain has bogged him down.</p>
        <p>''This is probably the only tournament I'll play in,'' he said. ''It's driving me crazy.''</p>
        <p>AN UNKIND CUT -- The dash to make the cut, which fell at eight-over-par 152, was an eventful exercise Friday. The 57-year-old Tom Watson seemed a cinch to make it to the weekend until he made a triple bogey on the 18th hole. He missed the cut by a stroke.</p>
        <p>''Not a good way to end the Masters,'' he said. ''It was very disappointing. These greens are the toughest I've seen them.''</p>
        <p>The 71-year-old Gary Player, in his 50th Masters tournament, finished at 16-over-par 160.</p>
        <p>A HOME FOR TIGER'S EVENT -- Not all the news Tiger Woods has received at the Masters has been bad. Late Thursday evening, his inaugural tournament, the AT&amp;T National, secured Congressional Country Club in Bethesda, Md., as its home through 2008.</p>
        <p>This year's event will be played from July 2-8. It is a limited-field tournament of 120 players that will benefit the Tiger Woods Foundation.</p>
        <p>COOL TIMES IN GEORGIA -- Unseasonably cool temperatures were expected to continue through the weekend at Augusta National. The forecast for Saturday is for sunny skies and a high of 57 degrees. Sunday's forecast calls for sunny skies and a high of 62 degrees. On each day, a frost warning is possible, which could delay the start of play.</p>
        <p>DO NOT CALL -- Brett Wetterich has the kind of friends who call at 1:30 in the morning even when their buddy has an important tee time in just a few hours.</p>
        <p>Wetterich, tied for the lead at the Masters, has plenty to worry about without those kind of distractions.</p>
        <p>Wetterich got his share of the lead by shooting a one-over-par 73 Friday, and he did it even though he may have been a bit tired for his 8:55 a.m. start. You see, his phone rang a little late the night before.</p>
        <p>''I'm the type of person that gets phone calls like that every now and then,'' he said. ''My buddies forget that I'm playing the Masters and I have to get up at 5:30.'' (AP)</p>
        <p>TOO LATE FOR CLARKE -- Darren Clarke pulled his game together a little too late.</p>
        <p>Even with bogeys on the last two holes, Clarke shot a one-under-par 71 yesterday -- a 12-stroke turnaround from the first round. But his 83 on Thursday put him 10 over for the tournament, two strokes above the cut line.</p>
        <p>It's only the third time he has missed the cut in 10 trips to Augusta.</p>
        <p>''Strangely enough, I didn't play that badly yesterday,'' he said. ''Today I played just a little bit better. I had a lot of chances. Almost gave me a chance to make the cut there.''</p>
        <p>Clarke made only one birdie and seven pars on Thursday to go with eight bogeys and two double bogeys. He made three birdies yesterday but was bogey-free until his last two holes.</p>
        <p>At least Clarke had a nice fallback plan.</p>
        <p>''I'm back to the beach in the Bahamas,'' Clarke said with a grin. ''Bye-bye.'' (AP)</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
