<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Creator of Inspector Chen, China Is a Tough Case to Crack</title>
    <meta content="07qiu" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/world/asia/07qiu.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE SATURDAY PROFILE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Books And Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cultural Revolution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shanghai (China)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Qiu Xiaolong</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington University (St Louis)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Qiu Xiaolong</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Shanghai</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cultural Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Communism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Shanghai (China)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E6D7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1330" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Creator of Inspector Chen, China Is a Tough Case to Crack</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Creator of Inspector Chen, China Is a Tough Case to Crack</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Qiu Xiaolong, professor at Washington University in St Louis, is perhaps most successful author of detective stories set in China; he grew up in Shanghai during Cultural Revolution; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Qiu Xiaolong reflects on his life, the path has an air almost of inevitability.</p>
        <p>The arc includes an inquisitive childhood in Shanghai during the Cultural Revolution; studying poetry in Beijing, where he translated the complete works of T. S. Eliot; traveling in the early days of détente to the United States, where he eventually became a professor; and finally his status today as perhaps the most successful author of detective stories set in China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few authors have written about Shanghai as intimately, or as presciently, as Qiu Xiaolong, the man behind the Inspector Chen detective novels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Qiu Xiaolong reflects on his life, the path has an air almost of inevitability.</p>
        <p>The arc includes an inquisitive childhood in Shanghai during the Cultural Revolution; studying poetry in Beijing, where he translated the complete works of T. S. Eliot; traveling in the early days of détente to the United States, where he eventually became a professor; and finally his status today as perhaps the most successful author of detective stories set in China.</p>
        <p>Nothing, of course, seemed clear or preordained at the time. Not even, he says, for a single moment.</p>
        <p>Life for Mr. Qiu (pronounced Cho) has been a series of accidents, though for him often very fortunate ones. At 54, like most Chinese people of his generation, he has been through an awful lot. But in telling his own story, there is a particular grace about this optimistic man, who pauses at the mention of great coincidences and laughs deeply at the mystery of it all.</p>
        <p>Mr. Qiu, who teaches at Washington University in St. Louis, was ostensibly visiting the city of his youth to attend an international literary festival here, and to promote his latest book, ''A Case of Two Cities.'' This too, however, would be a gross oversimplification.</p>
        <p>Shanghai is much more than his hometown. It is his muse, and it has been the one consistent subject of his fiction, the four Inspector Chen detective novels he has written so far, which have sold over 700,000 copies and have been translated into 16 languages, including Chinese.</p>
        <p>Chinese? Yes, since leaving the country at the age of 35 in 1988 on a Ford Foundation fellowship, Mr. Qiu has written in English instead of his native language. The choice, which today sometimes displeases Chinese authorities, he said, has been forced upon him by circumstances in his own country -- from the bloody antidemocracy crackdown at Beijing's Tiananmen Square in 1989, to the many restrictions on speech, especially anything construed as political speech, that have followed.</p>
        <p>He was reminded of these restrictions during his current visit home, when he wrote an article in homage of Yang Xianyi, an aging and infirm translator of Chinese classics into English. Mr. Yang became a hero to his generation of intellectuals for his decision to resign from the Communist Party over its handling of the pro-democracy demonstrations at Tiananmen Square.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Qiu approached Chinese magazines to get it published, they were unfailingly polite but unyielding. ''We're sorry,'' he said editors would announce with a smile. ''It's very interesting, but for certain reasons, we're afraid we can't publish it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Qiu's first inklings that he might be able to write date from an experience that still looms large in his life: the hounding and humiliation of his father, a businessman who was labeled a class enemy, or tagged ''black'' in the language of the Cultural Revolution.</p>
        <p>While his father was hospitalized for cataract surgery and temporarily unable to see, he was ordered to write a self-criticism. Mr. Qiu, who was in his early teens at the time, stood in for him, writing the document.</p>
        <p>Later, while working as an Eliot scholar in St. Louis, the poet's native city, Mr. Qiu tried his hand at detective fiction. ''I had trouble putting all of my thoughts together in poems,'' he said. ''Mystery gave me a framework, because you start with a body and end with a conclusion.''</p>
        <p>His editor liked his first effort so much that she said he would have to write more. ''So you see, I had no choice,'' Mr. Qiu said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>Mr. Qiu received a visitor in the rickety two-story walkup where he grew up, in central Shanghai. It lies in an area of narrow streets buzzing with activity, where neighbors live in a closeness bordering on promiscuity, of the sort that is fast disappearing in a city racing toward a homogenized vision of modernity.</p>
        <p>Back then the Red Guards, the enforcers of a cult of Mao Zedong worship who held sway during the Cultural Revolution, were present even in hospital wards, he said. Schools were all but closed during that decade, from 1966 to 1976, and young people were sent by the tens of millions to the countryside to learn from peasants.</p>
        <p>''People would use drums and gongs and chant slogans to call out the names of those who did not go,'' he said of his neighbors. ''Every day I was scared I'd be called out by name. But I was lucky and they never called me.''</p>
        <p>YEARS later, while visiting his father's grave, Mr. Qiu received the inspiration for what many readers consider to be his finest work, ''When Red Is Black,'' which like all his novels is a story about the exploits of Chief Inspector Chen of the Shanghai Police Bureau. In this novel, the detective is looking into the murder of a novelist and former member of the Red Guards.</p>
        <p>This background enables Mr. Qiu to process his deepest feelings about the fortunes of his family and of his country during the topsy-turvy years of ideological zealotry, as well as what the author considers the abandonment of virtually all values -- save for the pursuit of money -- that has followed.</p>
        <p>''Nowadays, the most popular people in the city are rich, and the party is even changing the Constitution so that business people can be members,'' Mr. Qiu said during a book event at the Shanghai International Literary Festival. ''As I stood at my father's grave I wondered what he would think if he were alive today, all that suffering for nothing. Today, it is the businesspeople who are red, and the people without pensions, without homes, they are black.''</p>
        <p>The novel is concerned just as deeply with Shanghai, a city that few authors have written about so intimately, or so presciently. One of the plot lines of ''When Red Is Black'' involves the collusion of senior party officials, local developers and organized crime groups in redeveloping large parts of the city. One passage reads like fly-on-the-wall dialogue in a still unfolding real estate corruption scandal that recently toppled Shanghai's Communist Party secretary, Chen Liangyu, and has ensnared many other officials and real estate developers here.</p>
        <p>Having gutted most of the city's distinctive neighborhoods to build nondescript high rises and shopping complexes, one member of this cabal has an inspiration he describes as being ''struck by a Zen master's stick dealing the blow that enlightens.''</p>
        <p>The project involves recreating some of the city's most famous architecture, the fast-disappearing shikumen, or stone gatehouses that are built around internal lanes, like those on Mr. Qiu's own street.</p>
        <p>''I'll let you in on a secret,'' a developer tells a policeman after describing a luxury real estate project. ''I applied for the use of the land for cultural preservation. After all, shikumen-style architecture is an integral part of Shanghai history.</p>
        <p>''One or two small museums may be included in the concept. A museum for ancient coins is one idea.'' A moment later, he adds: ''But most of the new shikumen houses will be for commercial use. Really high-end, luxury premises.''</p>
        <p>CENSORS here could be called prescient too, however. They refused to allow the title ''When Red Is Black'' to be used in the Chinese version of the book, because of its clear ideological connotations. They also would not allow the city in question to be named Shanghai, designating it ''City H'' instead.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Qiu's crime stories all have conclusions, their central character, Inspector Chen, a lover of classical poetry like the author himself, does not. Corruption is a recurrent theme, because ''it is everywhere,'' Mr. Qiu says. ''What is the reason? Is it one-party rule? Is it something deeper in Chinese culture, because a legal culture does not have deep roots? Is it absolute power corrupting absolutely?''</p>
        <p>''The chief inspector does not have all the answers,'' Mr. Qiu says. ''Like all Chinese, he is just coming to terms with all that is changing around him.''</p>
        <p>THE SATURDAY PROFILE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
