<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Second Fiddle to an Old Master</title>
    <meta content="07marchese" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/opinion/07marchese.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violins</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marchese, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stradivari, Antonio (C1644-1737)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Christie's</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stradivari, Antonio</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EED8173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Second Fiddle to an Old Master</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Second Fiddle to an Old Master</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Marchese</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marchese, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Author John Marchese Op-Ed article notes that Christie's recently auctioned off 268-year-old Stradivari violin for more than $2.7 million; says that with each big-ticket sale like one at Christie's, musical world gets one step closer to day when all great Stradivari instruments belong to non-musicians; maintains that maybe then musicians will stop coveting some illusive perfection and embrace work of mere mortals who walk among them; says they will get good fiddles and more disposable income; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST Monday night, Christie's auctioned off a 268-year-old carved wooden box with funny-looking holes in it for more than $2.7 million.</p>
        <p>There were strings attached.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In what other field would someone pay more for a 300-year-old tool than for a new one?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST Monday night, Christie's auctioned off a 268-year-old carved wooden box with funny-looking holes in it for more than $2.7 million.</p>
        <p>There were strings attached.</p>
        <p>It was a violin, of course, made in Cremona, Italy, by an old man named Antonio Stradivari, who is thought by many to be the greatest craftsman who ever lived. His fiddles (in the violin world, ''fiddle'' is a term of endearment) are considered supreme works of art, and the marketplace values them commensurately.</p>
        <p>But the violin is also a tool. As prices rise into the stratosphere for the instruments from the workshop of the Cremonese master -- and also from those of a number of his contemporaries -- one thing is certain: fewer and fewer of these violins are in the hands of people who can actually play them. This week's buyer is remaining anonymous, but it's a safe bet that he or she isn't a full-time musician. Musicians, even successful ones, can't afford those prices.</p>
        <p>And maybe that's a good thing. The strength of tradition is incredibly strong in classical music, and maybe even more powerful in the craft of violinmaking. Stradivari never left behind a shop manual, but nearly every one of his instruments has been analyzed and measured down to the millimeter. For many years, luthiers, as makers of string instruments are known, perhaps the first reverse engineers, have been producing copies with slavish fidelity. A top violinmaker named Joseph Curtin once told his colleagues that he was beginning to feel like a Civil War re-enactor.</p>
        <p>It has long been thought that Stradivari possessed some ''secret.'' Speculation focused on two aspects. Was it special wood, or wood specially treated? Or had he devised a secret recipe for the varnish?</p>
        <p>The real secret of Stradivari, according to the legendary violin expert Simone Sacconi, who devoted his life to studying, restoring and copying Stradivari violins, is that there was no secret. Stradivari was simply the best there ever was at his trade, the apotheosis of a craft tradition that began about a hundred years before he was born.</p>
        <p>That explanation seems reasonable and provides a rationale for the transformation of Stradivari's fiddles from tools to collectible art objects. But it doesn't support the cult of age in the wider world of violins.</p>
        <p>Strad, as he is known by musicians and luthiers, built instruments in the days of carriages and candlelight; he could never have envisioned the demands placed on the modern musician by international air travel and bigger concert halls. Few people know that most of Stradivari's instruments have been significantly altered over the years to better meet the demands of modern performance. Despite that, they are still old, and sometimes they don't work well.</p>
        <p>It is another quietly concealed fact in the music world that a number of top violinists keep antiqued modern copies in their collection and play them when their fine old fiddles are out of kilter. Do listeners really notice the difference? A few years ago I attended a concert where a world-renowned violin soloist performed a concerto with an internationally acclaimed orchestra. He was supposed to be playing a very expensive Stradivari, but instead he used a violin made that very year in Brooklyn, by a top luthier named Sam Zygmuntowicz.</p>
        <p>Did the audience rise up as one and heckle him for the ruse? No, they gave him three standing ovations.</p>
        <p>Violinists swear they can feel and hear the difference a Strad makes in that intimate spot under the ear where a violin is cradled. But there's plenty of evidence that their listeners in the audience can't. In listening test after listening test, the common result is that even great violinists and top dealers can't discern the sound of a Stradivari from that of violins from other luthiers, even -- imagine! -- some who are alive and working now.</p>
        <p>Though these are the facts of life for modern luthiers, the situation still makes them a little crazy. They can do nothing but stand by and watch as the limited number of Stradivari fiddles get more and more expensive and disappear into the hands of foundations and rich collectors. At the same time, musicians ignore the violins, violas and cellos of modern luthiers and instead pay high prices for lesser instruments simply because they're old. In what other field would someone pay more for a 300-year-old tool than for a new one?</p>
        <p>With each big-ticket sale like the one at Christie's on Monday, the musical world gets one step closer to the day when all of the great Stradivari instruments belong to non-musicians. That will be a sad day in one sense, but hopeful in another. Maybe musicians will stop coveting some illusive perfection and embrace the work of mere mortals who walk among them. They'll get good fiddles and more disposable income.</p>
        <p>Sam Zygmuntowicz, carving away each day in Brooklyn, likes to remind his customers of a fact so obvious it is often overlooked. He's even made it into a pin and stuck it over his workbench. It reads, ''Strad Made New Fiddles.''</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor John Marchese is the author of ''The Violin Maker: Finding a Centuries-Old Tradition in a Brooklyn Workshop.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Marchese is the author of ''The Violin Maker: Finding a Centuries-Old Tradition in a Brooklyn Workshop.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
