<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So Far, the Course Is Winning</title>
    <meta content="07augusta" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/sports/golf/07augusta.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070413T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Augusta National Golf Club</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hack, Damon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Singh, Vijay</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E3DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So Far, the Course Is Winning</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Elite Field Is in the Wrong Place Too Many Times</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A golf course can be an eerie place when the best players in the world are flailing about, when Tiger Woods splashes balls into creeks and Phil Mickelson hits tee shots into forests.</p>
        <p>Through two days of the 71st Masters, Augusta National has been mean and relentless. The dry, difficult course has pelted golfers with big numbers and left a gallery with its hands in its pockets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Through two days of the 71st Masters, Augusta National has been mean and relentless, pelting golfers with big numbers and leaving a gallery with its hands in its pockets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A golf course can be an eerie place when the best players in the world are flailing about, when Tiger Woods splashes balls into creeks and Phil Mickelson hits tee shots into forests.</p>
        <p>Through two days of the 71st Masters, Augusta National has been mean and relentless. The dry, difficult course has pelted golfers with big numbers and left a gallery with its hands in its pockets.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot more quiet out here,'' Tim Herron said after Friday's round of 75. ''You don't hear the roars like you used to.''</p>
        <p>The usual applause for birdies has given way to a beaten-down leader board filled with a jumble of players with various skills -- long hitters, short hitters, and players in between.</p>
        <p>Brett Wetterich and Tim Clark share a one-stroke lead over the hometown favorite Vaughn Taylor, who shot a 72. Wetterich, who shot a 73, and Clark, who shot a 71, stood at two-under-par 142. Their scores are the highest through 36 holes at the Masters since 1982, when 144 led.</p>
        <p>Vijay Singh and Jerry Kelly headlined a group two shots back, Woods was among a cluster of players five back and Mickelson stood seven shots behind on this slippery-quick track.</p>
        <p>Many players failed to stay patient on a breezy day with temperatures stuck around 60. The cut, which was at eight-over-par 152, removed several big names from the premises. Ernie Els and Sergio García each shot 154, Robert Allenby a 159.</p>
        <p>On a course famous for shouts around every bend, little noise was heard over its 7,445 yards. Woods drowned two balls into Rae's Creek, hit another over the back of the 15th green, and flirted with playing himself out of the tournament before he rallied for a 74.</p>
        <p>On the par-3 12th hole, he knocked a ball into the creek but still saved a bogey after pitching onto the green and making a 20-footer.</p>
        <p>On the par-5 13th, he belted his ball into a tributary of the creek, but hit a deft chip to 5 feet and saved his par.</p>
        <p>For most of the round, Woods fought a swing that deposited shots on various trajectories. ''The whole idea is never make a double around this place,'' said Woods, who hasn't during the tournament.</p>
        <p>Mickelson, the defending champion, was stuck in the trees to the left of No. 11, trying to find his ball after a tee shot that sailed far off the mark. When he found it, he took a one-stroke penalty drop, hit a punch shot onto the fairway, laced an iron to the green and made a 10-footer for a bogey.</p>
        <p>''I've got to hit more fairways,'' he said. ''First day, I drove it horrible, putted horrible. Second day, drove it horrible and putted better. So I should be O.K.''</p>
        <p>With Mickelson and Woods flubbing their lines, others have stepped into the Masters glare. Clark, who is from South Africa, finished second to Mickelson last year after holing a bunker shot with his final stroke.</p>
        <p>''I've dreamt of coming here and playing this tournament as a child, and I'm here now,'' he said. ''I'm going to the make the most of it.''</p>
        <p>Wetterich, a bulky golfer with a big swing, continues to display a quiet confidence in his first Masters. He was not even exempt on the PGA Tour until he earned his card at qualifying school in December 2005.</p>
        <p>Last year, Wetterich won his only PGA Tour event, the Byron Nelson Championship. Two weeks ago, he finished second to Woods at the CA Championship.</p>
        <p>''You always hear the great players say that pars are great in majors,'' Wetterich said. ''I was just going out there to try to make as many as I could.''</p>
        <p>Some players who made the cut moaned about a course that played more like a punishing United States Open. Lee Westwood, who is at 152, said he did not really like the Masters.</p>
        <p>''Not anymore,'' he said. ''When the course was shorter, more of us had an answer. Now, only six or seven people in the field can win. I wouldn't say it's unfair, but it's not fair for everybody.''</p>
        <p>Singh added, ''It's not playing easy by any means.''</p>
        <p>Mickelson had four bogeys and three birdies.</p>
        <p>Woods carded six bogeys and four birdies, including a pair of birdies on the 15th and 17th holes that saved him from a worse fate. On No. 15, a 530-yard par 5, Woods got up and down after blasting his second shot 30 yards past the hole. On No. 17, a 440-yard par 4, he rolled in a 15-footer.</p>
        <p>No golfer is dominating. Augusta National is.</p>
        <p>''You just try to put the ball in the right spot, if you can,'' Woods said. ''And if you can't, somehow don't have any wrecks out there.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 13, 2007, Friday  A sports article on Saturday about the second round of the Masters referred imprecisely to the scoring for Phil Mickelson on hole No. 11, where he hit a ball into the trees. Mickelson took a free drop -- not a penalty drop requiring an extra stroke -- because there were cables and pipes in the way. (As the article noted, he did make a bogey on the hole.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 13, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A sports article on Saturday about the second round of the Masters referred imprecisely to the scoring for Phil Mickelson on hole No. 11, where he hit a ball into the trees. Mickelson took a free drop -- not a penalty drop requiring an extra stroke -- because there were cables and pipes in the way. (As the article noted, he did make a bogey on the hole.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
