<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rotation in Need of a Lift Doesn't Get It From Mussina</title>
    <meta content="07yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E3DF143FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rotation in Need of a Lift Doesn't Get It From Mussina</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every team in the majors has had a starter pitch five innings at least once this season. Every team, that is, except the Yankees.</p>
        <p>The season, of course, is only three games old. And the man who is arguably the most important pitcher in the organization, Phil Hughes, had a strong debut at Class AAA Scranton last night -- five innings, two hits, two runs and six strikeouts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every team in the majors has had a starter pitch five innings at least once this season. Every team, that is, except the Yankees.</p>
        <p>The season, of course, is only three games old. And the man who is arguably the most important pitcher in the organization, Phil Hughes, had a strong debut at Class AAA Scranton last night -- five innings, two hits, two runs and six strikeouts.</p>
        <p>But the big leaguers have struggled so far, with Mike Mussina enduring one of his worst starts last night in a 6-4 loss to the Baltimore Orioles at Yankee Stadium. The Yankees have lost two of their three games, and the starters have an 8.76 earned run average, allowing 20 hits and 8 walks over 121/3 innings.</p>
        <p>''Every team in the league counts on its rotation, but we count on our rotation a lot,'' said Mussina, who gave up six runs in four innings. ''It's going to make or break our season, and we didn't do very well the first handful of starts here. It's disappointing. We've got to improve.''</p>
        <p>The night could have been worse for the Yankees. Derek Jeter fouled a ball off his right foot in the first inning and left the game after eight. The X-rays on his second toe showed only a bruise, and Jeter said he expected to play today.</p>
        <p>''I don't see any reason why not,'' Jeter said. ''I played today. They just took me out because I wasn't moving too good.''</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre said that Jeter told him in the eighth inning that he would need a pinch-runner if he reached base. It was a rare admission of physical pain, and Torre used Miguel Cairo for defense in the ninth.</p>
        <p>Jeter went 2 for 5, and his third-inning double was his 2,154th career hit, breaking a tie with Don Mattingly and moving him to sixth on the Yankees' career list. Otherwise, it was a forgettable game, notable mostly for what Mussina could not do.</p>
        <p>Mussina allowed eight hits and three walks in his four innings. Andy Pettitte lasted four innings on Thursday, and Carl Pavano was lifted with one out in the fifth on Monday.</p>
        <p>For Mussina, it was the first time in exactly three years -- since April 6, 2004 -- that he had worked four innings or fewer while allowing at least six earned runs. That start also followed six days off, coming after Mussina's season-opening start in Japan.</p>
        <p>Mussina was not pleased to make that trip, which badly disrupted his routine. When Wednesday's rainout ensured that he would make this start on extra rest, Mussina was dubious about his chances. But he made no excuses after the game.</p>
        <p>''I could say it was cold; I could say it had been a long time since I pitched; I could say a lot of things,'' Mussina said. ''But it was just bad. I was about six inches from where I wanted to be on every pitch.''</p>
        <p>Brian Roberts led off with a long double to the gap in left-center field, and Melvin Mora dropped a perfect bunt for a single. Both runners scored on a double by Nick Markakis, who doubled again in the third to start a three-run rally.</p>
        <p>It was 6-2 Orioles by the time Mussina left, and the Yankees squandered most of their chances to score against Adam Loewen, who beat them twice last season. They stranded five runners in scoring position in Loewen's five innings, scoring only in the second, when Alex Rodriguez and Robinson Canó doubled.</p>
        <p>The Yankees expected their lineup and bullpen to be strong. Their obvious question was the rotation, even before losing Chien-Ming Wang to a mild hamstring strain. Wang has thrown off a mound in Tampa but has not been scheduled for a game.</p>
        <p>Mussina and Pettitte are tested veterans, but both are past their primes and have dealt with elbow injuries in recent seasons. Neither Pavano nor Kei Igawa pitched in the majors in 2006.</p>
        <p>Pavano was injured and returned to pitch decently on opening day, allowing one unearned run through four innings before coming apart in the fifth. Igawa, a former star for the Hanshin Tigers in Japan, takes the mound today.</p>
        <p>The Yankees hoped to sign Daisuke Matsuzaka, bidding $33 million for his negotiating rights. When the Boston Red Sox dwarfed that figure, the Yankees turned to Igawa, winning his rights for $26 million and then signing him to a five-year, $20 million contract.</p>
        <p>Igawa said he was watching on Thursday when Matsuzaka humbled the Kansas City Royals over seven innings, striking out 10 and allowing one run to earn a victory in his debut.</p>
        <p>''Yes, I saw him pitch yesterday on TV,'' Igawa said through an interpreter yesterday, ''and for his skills, that's normal for him.''</p>
        <p>Asked what would be a normal performance for his own skills, Igawa asked to have the question repeated. Then he laughed and said, ''I don't know until I play.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees do not need Igawa to repeat Matsuzaka's performance. These days, a tidy five innings would be progress.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
