<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Official Put on Leave In Student Loan Investigation</title>
    <meta content="07loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/washington/07loans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Lending Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Student Loan Xpress</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fontana, Matteo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Fontana, Matteo</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0D7173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Official Put on Leave In Student Loan Investigation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Federal Official Put on Leave in Student Loan Investigation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON and JONATHAN D. GLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W; Glater, Jonathan D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matteo Fontana, senior Education Dept official who owned stock in student loan company while helping oversee federal lending program, is placed on leave; 2003 prospectus for stock offering filed by Education Lending Group, parent company of Student Loan Xpress at time, showed that Fontana planned to sell 10,500 shares in company valued at about $100,000; New York Atty Gen Andrew M Cuomo widens his investigation into student lending business to see if other federal, state or local public officials had received stock or benefits from Student Loan Xpress or its parent companies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A senior Education Department official who owned stock in a student loan company while helping oversee the federal lending program was placed on leave yesterday, the department said.</p>
        <p>The New York attorney general also widened his investigation into the industry, subpoenaing one of the nation's largest student lenders for a list of all former employees who had worked for the federal department in the past six years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The moves came a day after the Education Department said it would investigate the shareholdings of the senior official, Matteo Fontana.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A senior Education Department official who owned stock in a student loan company while helping oversee the federal lending program was placed on leave yesterday, the department said.</p>
        <p>The New York attorney general also widened his investigation into the industry, subpoenaing one of the nation's largest student lenders for a list of all former employees who had worked for the federal department in the past six years.</p>
        <p>The moves came a day after the Education Department said it would investigate the shareholdings of the senior official, Matteo Fontana, general manager in a unit of the Office of Federal Student Aid and a department employee since 2002.</p>
        <p>A 2003 prospectus for a stock offering filed by the Education Lending Group, the parent company of Student Loan Xpress at the time, showed that Mr. Fontana planned to sell 10,500 shares in the company valued at about $100,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fontana's stake in the student loan company has raised questions about a potential conflict of interest, and the department has referred the matter to its inspector general. Senior financial aid officers at Columbia University, the University of Texas at Austin and the University of Southern California also held stock in the company, according to the prospectus. They were also placed on leave this week by their universities.</p>
        <p>Margaret Spellings, the education secretary, also asked one of those officials, Lawrence W. Burt, director of student financial aid at Texas, to resign from a federal advisory committee on student aid, said her spokeswoman, Katherine McLane.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burt held and sold shares in the parent company of Student Loan Xpress, one of the lenders the university recommends to its students.</p>
        <p>With the disclosure that Mr. Fontana had been put on leave, Andrew M. Cuomo, the New York attorney general, said he was widening his investigation into the student lending business to see if other federal, state or local public officials had received stock or benefits from Student Loan Xpress or its parent companies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo issued subpoenas yesterday to Student Loan Xpress and CIT Group, its parent company since 2005, according to John Milgrim, a spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milgrim said Mr. Cuomo also issued a subpoena to SLM Corporation, the giant student lending company known as Sallie Mae, asking for a list of all of its former employees who had worked for the Education Department in the last six years, and for e-mail messages and other communications between those former employees and the company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fontana had worked for Sallie Mae from 1994 to 2001.</p>
        <p>Tom Joyce, a Sallie Mae spokesman, said he did not know how many other former employees moved to the Education Department. He said the company planned to cooperate with Mr. Cuomo.</p>
        <p>Representative George Miller, Democrat of California and chairman of the House Education and Labor Committee, released yesterday a letter he sent to the education secretary seeking information about relationships between lenders and the federal officials who oversee them.</p>
        <p>The University of Southern California said yesterday that it had struck Student Loan Xpress from a list of lenders that had provided good rates and service to its students.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
