<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HUD Institutes Changes To Speed Storm Repairs</title>
    <meta content="07rebuild" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/07/us/07rebuild.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Katrina (Storm)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rita (Storm)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Louisiana</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Housing and Urban Development Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eaton, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Louisiana</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Housing and Urban Development Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5D6173FF934A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HUD Institutes Changes To Speed Storm Repairs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">HUD Institutes Changes to Speed Storm Repairs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eaton, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Louisiana homeowners may get faster access to rebuilding grants after decision by Housing and Urban Development Dept that is forcing state to change its slow-moving $7.5-billion Road Home program to repair houses damaged by Hurricanes Katrina and Rita in 2005; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Louisiana homeowners may get faster access to rebuilding grants after a federal decision late last month that is forcing the state to change its slow-moving $7.5-billion ''Road Home'' program to repair houses damaged or destroyed by hurricanes in 2005.</p>
        <p>But the changes, which should be detailed next week, have raised concerns that some homeowners will not use their grants of up to $150,000 for repairs or could lose them to fraud or debt, potentially leading to increased blight in hard-hit areas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The changes, which will affect Louisiana homeowners, have raised concerns that some homeowners will not use their grants of up to $150,000 for repairs or could lose them to fraud or debt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Louisiana homeowners may get faster access to rebuilding grants after a federal decision late last month that is forcing the state to change its slow-moving $7.5-billion ''Road Home'' program to repair houses damaged or destroyed by hurricanes in 2005.</p>
        <p>But the changes, which should be detailed next week, have raised concerns that some homeowners will not use their grants of up to $150,000 for repairs or could lose them to fraud or debt, potentially leading to increased blight in hard-hit areas.</p>
        <p>The program has been criticized around the state for its slow pace in handing out the money, which was provided by the federal government. As of April 3, more than 121,000 families had applied to Road Home, but roughly half had still not had been told how much money they could receive.</p>
        <p>Just 6,100 families -- 5 percent of applicants -- had actually reached the ''closing'' stage and been given access to the cash by early April. And the money has been doled out through banks only as homeowners proved that rebuilding was in progress.</p>
        <p>But according to changes that have been broadly outlined by the state under the new federal requirements, people who reach the closing stage will get all of their money in a lump sum.</p>
        <p>''The money will be wired to their accounts,'' said Andy Kopplin, executive director of the Louisiana Recovery Authority, which devised the program. ''Homeowners will be in the driver's seat and will have access to the money immediately.''</p>
        <p>The change worries bankers who hold the mortgages on the damaged properties. In return for oversight of the rebuilding money, they had agreed not to seize it to cover overdue mortgage payments.</p>
        <p>Some bankers say they are concerned that people who have left New Orleans may choose to use the money for purposes other than rebuilding. Others argue that the slow pace of the system helped protect homeowners from unscrupulous contractors who might have demanded huge payments upfront and then fail to make repairs.</p>
        <p>The new rules ''will lead to less rebuilding, more foreclosures and more fraud,'' said Francis P. Creighton, a senior director of government affairs for the Mortgage Bankers Association, which has been involved in program negotiations.</p>
        <p>Local officials are playing down the possibility that giving homeowners the money directly will lead to abandoned properties in New Orleans and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''I am concerned but not worried,'' Edward J. Blakely, director of recovery for the city, wrote in an e-mail message. ''In a sense a homeowner should have the option to do whatever they want with their own money and we should be making a city they want to live in.''</p>
        <p>Others in New Orleans were blunter. ''I think all that's foolishness,'' said Wade R. Ragas, a real estate expert and former professor at the University of New Orleans.</p>
        <p>A more serious barrier to rebuilding, Mr. Ragas said, is the slow pace of the Road Home program. ''The long delay,'' he said, ''has made it much harder for people'' who have by now put down roots in other communities, 19 months after the storms.</p>
        <p>Critics of Road Home hailed the changes as an improvement, but said many more would be necessary to make the program function properly -- and quickly. For one thing, the byzantine process of qualifying for the program -- which includes proof of clear title, when many homeowners have lost their paperwork to the floodwaters -- has not been eased by the latest changes. One group, the Citizens' Road Home Action Team, is calling for an independent oversight board to represent homeowners.</p>
        <p>''The program is not designed primarily with the applicants in mind,'' said Melanie Ehrlich, a founder of the group, adding that dealing with the new requirements has thrown Road Home into even more disarray than before.</p>
        <p>When the program was first developed, state officials said, they insisted on giving banks a role in doling out the grants in part to make sure people did not walk away from their damaged houses. But they also said they did not expect many people to take the money and run, noting that in order to get grants homeowners have to agree to legal covenants, including agreeing to live in their repaired homes for three years.</p>
        <p>''To say people will walk away, that there are a lot of irresponsible people, I don't accept that,'' said Walter J. Leger Jr., a lawyer in New Orleans who is head of the state recovery authority's housing task force.</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Leger said, ''if there are going to be people walking away from their houses, HUD can be thanked for that.''</p>
        <p>He was referring to the federal Department of Housing and Urban Development, which financed Road Home through Community Development Block Grants after Congress agreed to the $7.5 billion price tag. Louisiana officials say the agency had approved the original plan, last year, to hand out the money through banks, in what are called disbursement accounts.</p>
        <p>But it was only in late January, when HUD officials reviewed some documents during a visit to Louisiana, that the federal officials suspected that the state had created a housing rehabilitation program, which comes with more regulations than a direct compensation program would have, said D. J. Nordquist, a spokeswoman for the agency.</p>
        <p>In March, after further exchanges of information, agency officials informed the state that forcing repairs led to extensive environmental reviews. To avoid the reviews, the state is moving to a lump-sum program.</p>
        <p>The agency does not foresee widespread problems with foreclosures, Ms. Nordquist said, noting that these problems do not seem to have arisen so far with a similar but smaller program in Mississippi that gave homeowners lump sums.</p>
        <p>''We also don't see any evidence that people are using the money for other things or that they are walking away from their homes,'' Ms. Nordquist wrote in an e-mail message. ''Homeowners tend to be very responsible people who have roots in their neighborhoods and have a deep emotional and financial investment in their communities.''</p>
        <p>HUD's decision will affect the second phase of Mississippi's program, which is supposed to help low-income homeowners rebuild even if they were not sufficiently insured. This phase of the program had originally required bank involvement in disbursing money, in part because of concerns about ''predatory lenders and predatory contractors,'' said Donna Sanford, who manages disaster recovery efforts for the state's development authority.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mississippi will emphasize providing financial counseling and information to those who qualify for the grants. About 7,300 families have applied, Ms. Sanford said. The state has already handed out $845 million to more than 12,000 families who applied for the first round of grants, which went to those outside the flood zone whose houses were damaged.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
