<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Soulful, Still Swinging, Still Ready to Bust Loose</title>
    <meta content="21brow" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/arts/music/21brow.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DC163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Soulful, Still Swinging, Still Ready to Bust Loose</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Still Soulful, Still Swinging, Still Ready to Bust Loose</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a sharp suit, black fedora and sunglasses, with a gold tooth glinting and a well-traveled guitar in his hands, Chuck Brown, 72, was the image of a classic bluesman leading his band at Joe's Pub on Thursday night. But he wasn't playing the blues: he was playing go-go, the dance-club music from Washington that has survived long enough to be a tradition of its own.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown was a pioneer of go-go in the 1970s. In marathon live sets, he used a midtempo, Latin-tinged beat to string together old and new songs, merging the variety of a disc-jockey set with the sweaty teamwork of a funk band. Not too fast but deeply funky, the go-go beat was made for dancing all night long.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a sharp suit, black fedora and sunglasses, Chuck Brown, 72, was the image of a classic bluesman leading his band at Joe’s Pub on Thursday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a sharp suit, black fedora and sunglasses, with a gold tooth glinting and a well-traveled guitar in his hands, Chuck Brown, 72, was the image of a classic bluesman leading his band at Joe's Pub on Thursday night. But he wasn't playing the blues: he was playing go-go, the dance-club music from Washington that has survived long enough to be a tradition of its own.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown was a pioneer of go-go in the 1970s. In marathon live sets, he used a midtempo, Latin-tinged beat to string together old and new songs, merging the variety of a disc-jockey set with the sweaty teamwork of a funk band. Not too fast but deeply funky, the go-go beat was made for dancing all night long.</p>
        <p>Go-go was going to be the next big thing in the '80s, aiming for a national follow-through to Mr. Brown's 1979 hit, ''Bustin' Loose.'' But despite a movie about the music (''Good to Go'' in 1986) and countless happy clubgoers in and around Washington, go-go couldn't translate its live pleasures into radio hits. It's still a regional phenomenon, and with Mr. Brown's band, it's still a delight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown played his late show at Joe's Pub -- a 100-minute nonstop set, brief by D.C. standards -- to an audience including Washingtonians who eagerly followed call-and-response cues. When he said, ''Tell me what you feel like doin', y'all,'' they shouted, ''Feel like movin' that body!'' They picked up Parliament's chant ''Do That Stuff'' and sang ''doo-wah, doo-wah'' to Duke Ellington's ''It Don't Mean a Thing (if It Ain't Got That Swing).''</p>
        <p>As that span suggests, a go-go set is African-American music that, in Kurt Vonnegut's phrase, has come ''unstuck in time.'' Mr. Brown reached back to swing tunes and ''Moody's Mood for Love,'' stopped off in '60s and '70s funk and did a hip-hop medley, including songs from Doug E. Fresh and the Notorious B.I.G., all to the go-go pulse. A horn section played soul riffs and took jazzy solos. The band's drummer and its percussionist -- whose setup included congas, bongos and the plastic buckets of Washington's so-called junkyard bands -- worked continuously.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown played skillful lead guitar: wah-wah blues lines or smooth-jazz phrases with parallel scat singing. He started the set by crooning the love theme from ''The Godfather,'' not only showing he could sing but also claiming his title as the godfather of go-go.</p>
        <p>For someone who first heard go-go in the 1980s, there was plenty of déjà vu, from a brief stretch of the ''Woody Woodpecker'' theme to ''Bustin' Loose.'' But the old shtick still works, and now hip-hop adapts easily to the go-go treatment -- it's just one more generation of music for go-go to absorb.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown brought on his daughter KK to rap on ''Chucky Baby,'' a song from his new album, ''We're About the Business'' (Raw Venture). The best musical hooks, as they have been throughout go-go's history, were borrowed from other people's hits. But on the dance floor, that hardly matters.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
