<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Bollywood Ideas To Portray Today's India</title>
    <meta content="21indi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/movies/21indi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070428T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Museum of Modern Art</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DC163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Bollywood Ideas To Portray Today's India</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Using Bollywood Ideas to Portray Today’s India</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL SALTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saltz, Rachel</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Americans think of Indian cinema they most likely think of classic Bollywood: movie stars dripping with old-fashioned glamour, long films with improbable plots improbably interrupted by song-and-dance sequences (and never by kissing).</p>
        <p>And if Americans think at all about the other Indian cinema -- often called the parallel cinema -- they probably think of the lyrical naturalism of Satyajit Ray, whose greatest films were made decades ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“India Now,” a series of nine features and two shorts at the Museum of Modern Art, shows that the boundaries between Bollywood and not-Bollywood are blurring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Americans think of Indian cinema they most likely think of classic Bollywood: movie stars dripping with old-fashioned glamour, long films with improbable plots improbably interrupted by song-and-dance sequences (and never by kissing).</p>
        <p>And if Americans think at all about the other Indian cinema -- often called the parallel cinema -- they probably think of the lyrical naturalism of Satyajit Ray, whose greatest films were made decades ago.</p>
        <p>But a funny thing happened on the way to the 21st century. As ''India Now,'' a series of nine features and two shorts beginning tomorrow at the Museum of Modern Art, shows, the boundaries between Bollywood and not-Bollywood began to blur. All but two of these films are independent productions, financed outside the commercial studio system, but in terms of production values, seriousness of artistic purpose and, for lack of a better term, entertainment value, not much separates the best of these indies from the adventurous Bollywood selections.</p>
        <p>Joshua Siegel, assistant curator in the museum's department of film, who organized the series with Uma Da Cunha, a guest curator based in India, said he wanted to show the diversity of the largest film industry in the world, ''not to be encyclopedic, but to give a sense of the range and of the genres.''</p>
        <p>The films at MoMA, none more than two years old, include a documentary, an animated short, a Shakespeare adaptation, a movie inspired by T. S. Eliot's ''Murder in the Cathedral,'' a drama about the 2002 Gujarat riots, comedies, tragedies and, of course, some glorious melodramas.</p>
        <p>Amid all that variety certain themes pop up again and again: the precariousness of the middle class; corruption and the betrayal of secular ideals; the difficult necessity of working and living abroad; and, the most surprising common thread, the centrality of women in the stories being told. (''Kaalpurush,'' directed by Buddhadeb Dasgupta, one of the leading lights of Bengali cinema, was not available for early viewing.)</p>
        <p>''India Now,'' anchored by four strong films, two independent and two Bollywood, begins with a jolt of communal violence. ''Parzania,'' based on a true story of a Parsi boy who disappeared during the riots in the western state of Gujarat, is an accomplished, evenhanded drama about a still-raw national wound. (More than 1,000 people were killed when Hindu mobs attacked Muslims and other non-Hindus.)</p>
        <p>A nostalgia for Gandhian ideals hovers over ''Parzania,'' which begins with a schoolroom lesson about the ''great secular democracy of India'' and ends with the anguished testimony of the lost boy's mother (a wonderful, understated Sarika) calling the government to account: We were middle-class people waiting for the police to protect us, she says; isn't it the government's duty to provide safety and security for its citizens?</p>
        <p>Rahul Dholakia, a Gujarati now living in Los Angeles, directed ''Parzania,'' an independent production mainly in English. Perhaps only a nonresident Indian could have made this movie, which has been cleared for release in Gujarat but not yet been shown because of threatened violence by Hindu extremists.</p>
        <p>Sisterhood is transforming and, well, powerful in Nagesh Kukunoor's ''Dor,'' a feminist buddy film about the unlikely bond between a self-assured Muslim woman and a shy, oppressed Hindu widow. The plot sounds like pure Bollywood hokum, but this is another technically accomplished indie, well acted and well told. (The Muslim woman needs the Hindu to sign papers pardoning her husband, who is accused of murdering the Hindu woman's husband in Saudi Arabia, where the two men were working.)</p>
        <p>With two nuanced lead performances (by Gul Panag and Ayesha Takia) and two visually potent locations (the green mountains of Himachal Pradesh and the Rajasthan desert, a screen natural), ''Dor'' is a social drama that wears its heavy themes lightly. In one lovely sequence the women and their sidekick dance among the sand dunes, in part a burlesque of Bollywood, in part a recognition of the reliable pleasure it brings to these characters' lives.</p>
        <p>''Khosla Ka Ghosla,'' an urban and urbane Bollywood comedy about the middle class fighting to enjoy its privileges, is a change of scene and pace. Here is the modern Indian family in flux: the daughter with her short hair and Western clothes; the good engineer son, Cherry (''Hi, Bill Gates,'' he's often greeted), with his spectacles and a job waiting in America; the girlfriend who, gasp, lives alone in the big city; the father, who doesn't consider decency a sliding scale.</p>
        <p>Along with ''Khosla Ka Ghosla,'' ''Omkara,'' the other Bollywood selection in ''India Now,'' bears witness both to the variety and vitality of the commercial cinema. In the hands of the director Vishal Bhardwaj, this adaptation of ''Othello'' makes Bollywood seem like a natural home for Shakespearean tragedy.</p>
        <p>The Othello character, Omkara, is a half-caste gangster general (Ajay Devgan in a physically commanding performance) and his Desdemona, Dolly, is admired for her light skin. (Their union, one character says, will be ''like milk in a coal pot.'') Set in Uttar Pradesh, the dusty Indian heartland, this movie lovers' movie, with its striking widescreen compositions, folk-inflected score (that detours briefly into ''I Just Called to Say I Love You'') and languorous pacing, can count among its influences everything from Sergio Leone and Sam Peckinpah to ''Sholay'' (1975), the great Bollywood western.</p>
        <p>Each selection in ''India Now'' has its interests and pleasures, whether a performance (Kay Kay Menon in ''Shoonya''), outstanding cinematography (''Maati Maay''), a loose comic energy (''The Bong Connection'') or a commitment to social justice (the Manipuri documentary ''A Cry in the Dark''). Mr. Siegel of MoMA said the museum was considering mounting Indian film series with some regularity, perhaps yearly. Here's hoping it does.</p>
        <p>''India Now'' runs tomorrow through April 30 at the Museum of Modern Art, 11 West 53rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 708-9400; schedule at moma.org.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 28, 2007, Saturday  A picture caption in The Arts last Saturday with an article about ''India Now,'' a film series at the Museum of Modern Art, included erroneous information from the museum about the actress shown in a scene from ''Dor,'' a film in the series. She was Gul Panag -- not Ayesha Takia, one of the movie's stars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 28, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in The Arts last Saturday with an article about ''India Now,'' a film series at the Museum of Modern Art, included erroneous information from the museum about the actress shown in a scene from ''Dor,'' a film in the series. She was Gul Panag -- not Ayesha Takia, one of the movie's stars.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
