<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeing Victories Where Others See History</title>
    <meta content="21anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeing Victories Where Others See History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the first four games, Martin Brodeur had not been what he is: hockey's best goaltender. His goals against average was 2.87, in contrast to 1.89 in his previous 153 Stanley Cup playoff games. And his save average against the Tampa Bay Lightning had been a shaky .897.</p>
        <p>But in last night's 3-0 victory that lifted the Devils into a 3-2 lead in their Eastern Conference quarterfinal series going into tomorrow's rematch in Tampa Bay, Brodeur again was what he is: hockey's best goaltender.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the first four games, Martin Brodeur had not been what he is: hockey's best goaltender. His goals against average was 2.87, in contrast to 1.89 in his previous 153 Stanley Cup playoff games. And his save average against the Tampa Bay Lightning had been a shaky .897.</p>
        <p>But in last night's 3-0 victory that lifted the Devils into a 3-2 lead in their Eastern Conference quarterfinal series going into tomorrow's rematch in Tampa Bay, Brodeur again was what he is: hockey's best goaltender.</p>
        <p>Over the first four games, Vincent Lecavalier had five goals for the Lightning and Martin St. Louis had three with five assists. But between them last night, they had only four shots as Brodeur made 31 saves in his 22nd playoff shutout, one short of the retired Patrick Roy's record total.</p>
        <p>''Our survival mode was great,'' Brodeur said. ''Our guys in front of the net were blocking shots, doing everything. We were happy to win when we were outshot by double, almost.''</p>
        <p>More than double. The Devils had only 14 shots, including Scott Gomez's empty-net goal that assured the Devils, even if they were to lose tomorrow, of returning home for a decisive Game 7 on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>''Thirty-six hours ago, things were very different,'' Brodeur said, referring to when the Devils were struggling in Game 4 before Gomez's overtime goal. ''Now we just have to take this into Sunday's game.''</p>
        <p>When Brodeur was growing up in Montreal, his idol was Roy, who earned two Cup rings with the Canadiens before getting two more with the Colorado Avalanche. But when he was told that he needs only one more shutout to equal Roy's playoff record, he shrugged.</p>
        <p>''It's wins,'' he said. ''It's all about wins in the playoffs. For me, it's 22 wins, not 22 shutouts.''</p>
        <p>And so the Devils finally took charge of this series after Lecavalier, the big center, and St. Louis, the swift wing, had tormented Brodeur. But last night, St. Louis, on the ice for more than 26 minutes, had only one shot. In more than 25 minutes, Lecavalier got off only three.</p>
        <p>Andy Greene, a rookie defenseman, and Brian Gionta provided the Devils' 2-0 lead that Brodeur protected before Gomez's goal.</p>
        <p>For a change, the Devils didn't need any goals from Zach Parise, who missed about half of the first period when his right skate needed to be repaired. But he continued to lead all playoff scorers with six goals.</p>
        <p>''It's been a lot of fun,'' Parise said after Thursday's team meeting.</p>
        <p>Other players all over the N.H.L. often mention the pressure of the playoffs, but Parise used the word ''fun'' several times, as in, ''It's fun when the game gets more physical'' and ''How much more exciting the playoffs are, how much more fun.'' On the ice all that fun has created all those goals.</p>
        <p>''Even in practice, he wants to score every time he gets the puck,'' Brodeur said. ''He's learning how good he can be.''</p>
        <p>Good enough to have been the Devils' leading goal-scorer during the season with 31, in addition to 31 assists. His burst of six playoff goals equaled the franchise record for a playoff series. Claude Lemieux, the fiery right wing, did it in five games against the Penguins in the 1995 Eastern Conference semifinals en route to the Devils' first Stanley Cup championship.</p>
        <p>''His love of the game, his commitment, tenacity and determination,'' said Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' coach-impresario, listing some of Parise's strengths. ''He loves to score and he's not afraid to work to do it. He loves what he's doing. You can see it in his face.''</p>
        <p>When Parise was reminded that he was still 20 playoff goals short of catching his father, J. P. Parise, a legendary Islander, he laughed.</p>
        <p>''He had a series winner,'' he said with a smile. ''That's big.''</p>
        <p>In the decisive third game of the 1975 Islanders-Rangers opening-round playoff series, Jean-Paul Parise's overtime goal after only 11 seconds stunned and silenced the crowd at Madison Square Garden -- his most memorable moment of a 14-season career with Boston, Toronto, Minnesota, the Islanders and Cleveland. He scored 238 goals in the regular season, and 27 in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>In only his second season, Zach Parise seems to be blessed with an even greater gift than his father for scoring goals.</p>
        <p>''It's experience, being more comfortable in the league, more confident,'' he said. ''I like to think I'm faster. I've had a lot of scoring chances. I've been in a good spot at the right time. I've got good bounces.''</p>
        <p>Told about those good bounces, Brodeur, who sees Parise every day at practice as well as from the other end of the rink during games, smiled.</p>
        <p>''You don't get bounces, you create your bounces,'' Brodeur said. ''Every time there's a loose puck, he's there. He really enjoys the moment. And when you're young, you're quicker. And you listen more. You've got to work at it, but you need to have it.''</p>
        <p>Whatever ''it'' is, Zach Parise has it. So does Martin Brodeur.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
