<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 State Panels to Review Factors That Led to Governor's Crash</title>
    <meta content="21crash" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/nyregion/21crash.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 State Panels to Review Factors That Led to Governor's Crash</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2 State Panels to Review Factors That Led to Governor’s Crash</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As New Jersey's attorney general and state police conduct twin investigations into the auto accident that left Gov. Jon S. Corzine in critical condition, one of the most complex and delicate tasks will be to determine Mr. Corzine's role in his two-car caravan's violation of traffic laws.</p>
        <p>The state trooper who was driving Mr. Corzine's sport utility vehicle 91 miles an hour, emergency lights flashing, before the April 12 crash has told investigators and union representatives that the governor never explicitly pushed him to break the law or veer from police regulations limiting the use of the lights and high speeds to emergencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the most delicate tasks in the inquiry will be to determine New Jersey Gov. Jon S. Corzine's role in his caravan’s violation of traffic laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As New Jersey's attorney general and state police conduct twin investigations into the auto accident that left Gov. Jon S. Corzine in critical condition, one of the most complex and delicate tasks will be to determine Mr. Corzine's role in his two-car caravan's violation of traffic laws.</p>
        <p>The state trooper who was driving Mr. Corzine's sport utility vehicle 91 miles an hour, emergency lights flashing, before the April 12 crash has told investigators and union representatives that the governor never explicitly pushed him to break the law or veer from police regulations limiting the use of the lights and high speeds to emergencies.</p>
        <p>But it is widely acknowledged -- by former governors, police officials and even some of Mr. Corzine's aides -- that for decades, troopers driving New Jersey's chief executive have frequently been pushed to adhere to schedules so packed with events that speeding is assumed.</p>
        <p>So as a state police panel studies whether the crash was preventable and whether the driver, Trooper Robert J. Rasinski, should face disciplinary charges or a traffic citation, it must weigh whether his actions were in keeping with the unwritten protocol of his unit: to accommodate the governor, who is, after all, their direct supervisor, their boss's boss's boss, and the state's chief constitutional officer. And as Attorney General Stuart Rabner convenes a separate, independent group to review the guidelines for the executive protection unit that drives the governor, it must address the interaction between troopers and the premier passenger they serve.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to be limited to just looking at speed or seat belts,'' Mr. Rabner said in an interview on Friday. ''We're going to cover some basic concerns on the mission of the executive protection unit as a whole, things like training, equipment and guidelines for emergency.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rabner is assembling a team of half a dozen officials with experience in law enforcement, dignitary protection and the Secret Service. The panel is expected to begin work next week and complete its report in about a month.</p>
        <p>Until Mr. Corzine's Chevrolet Suburban slammed into a guardrail on the Garden State Parkway, few people in New Jersey government questioned the latitude given the governor's drivers, who serve as both chauffeur and security guard. Col. Joseph R. Fuentes, the state police superintendent, said this week that troopers were trained to avoid leaving the governor sitting in traffic where he might be exposed to a threat. But Mr. Corzine was injured while racing toward the governor's mansion for a meeting at which the radio host Don Imus apologized to members of the Rutgers University women's basketball team for making racist and sexist remarks.</p>
        <p>The severity of the governor's injuries has brought criticism over his failure to wear a seat belt and to instruct his driver to slow down, and pressure for Mr. Rabner's commission to recommend the tighter restrictions used elsewhere.</p>
        <p>In New York City, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg said this week that he forbade his drivers to speed unless he expressly permitted it.</p>
        <p>Denny King, former president of the National Governors Security Association, said he worked for years in the Tennessee executive protection unit and was never asked to speed except in the case of dire emergency.</p>
        <p>''It's always safety first,'' said Mr. King, a federal marshal. ''And from what I heard around the country, that's how it worked in most places.''</p>
        <p>But Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico has been publicly chastised for speeding several times in recent years. And after The Philadelphia Daily News clocked him exceeding 100 miles an hour, Gov. Edward G. Rendell of Pennsylvania acknowledged that he had frequently told his drivers, ''Let's fly.''</p>
        <p>Security experts said that simple power dynamics make it difficult for a driver to refuse a request from the governor, even if it is relayed implicitly, and suggested that Mr. Rabner's panel devise a mechanism that would allow troopers to decline even a direct order to drive unsafely.</p>
        <p>''The way it is now, if a driver in an executive protection unit tells a governor, 'I'm not going to speed,' or, 'I'm not going to get you there on time,' I guarantee you that the very next day he'd be protecting a mall or a crosswalk somewhere,'' said Tony Scotti, who has trained police officers around the country to drive elected officials and dignitaries.</p>
        <p>While the attorney general's panel reviews the department's policies, a six-member state police panel will investigate the specific actions Trooper Rasinski took. Since 2004, similar panels have reviewed all of the 1,261 accidents involving state troopers, deeming about a third of them preventable, said Capt. Al Della Fave, a state police spokesman.</p>
        <p>Trooper Rasinski has been involved in two other on-duty accidents, one of which occurred when his cruiser was parked on a roadside. The other was ruled preventable because he lost control of his vehicle on an icy road and slid into a guardrail.</p>
        <p>If the review finds that Trooper Rasinski was negligent, it would be up to Colonel Fuentes to determine his punishment.</p>
        <p>''It could range from a slap on the wrist to dismissal,'' Captain Della Fave said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
