<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parting Thoughts From a Master of the Ephemeral</title>
    <meta content="21lew" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/arts/design/21lew.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">LeWitt, Sol</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DC163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1294" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parting Thoughts From a Master of the Ephemeral</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Parting Thoughts From a Master of the Ephemeral</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <dateline>BEACON, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the greatness of Sol LeWitt, the Minimal-Conceptual artist who died this month at 78, has so far escaped you, make haste to this quiet Hudson River town and its main cultural attraction, the massive art space called Dia:Beacon. Here, among the often hulking displays of Minimal Art, you'll find an exhilarating show of 14 of LeWitt's mind-teasing, eye-filling wall drawings. All were made by people other than the artist, following his written instructions -- a habit that has always given LeWitt's detractors fits. If this show doesn't persuade you of his accomplishment, it is your loss.</p>
        <p>Although LeWitt has plenty of white, geometric Minimalist sculpture to his name, the wall drawings he began making in 1968 pose the most interesting questions about art and have had the greatest influence. He rediscovered the wall, an artistic working surface since the time of cave paintings, the way the Earth artists of his generation rediscovered the desert, home of the pyramids. In other words, something that was there all along, but greatly underutilized by contemporary artists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the greatness of artist Sol LeWitt has so far escaped you, make haste to Beacon, N.Y., a quiet Hudson River town, to see hulking displays of his minimal art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the greatness of Sol LeWitt, the Minimal-Conceptual artist who died this month at 78, has so far escaped you, make haste to this quiet Hudson River town and its main cultural attraction, the massive art space called Dia:Beacon. Here, among the often hulking displays of Minimal Art, you'll find an exhilarating show of 14 of LeWitt's mind-teasing, eye-filling wall drawings. All were made by people other than the artist, following his written instructions -- a habit that has always given LeWitt's detractors fits. If this show doesn't persuade you of his accomplishment, it is your loss.</p>
        <p>Although LeWitt has plenty of white, geometric Minimalist sculpture to his name, the wall drawings he began making in 1968 pose the most interesting questions about art and have had the greatest influence. He rediscovered the wall, an artistic working surface since the time of cave paintings, the way the Earth artists of his generation rediscovered the desert, home of the pyramids. In other words, something that was there all along, but greatly underutilized by contemporary artists.</p>
        <p>LeWitt gave modern drawing the scale of painting and the immateriality of pure thought, and made it a partner of architecture and real space. Legions of younger artists followed suit, starting with Mel Bochner and Dorothea Rockburne around 1970 and continuing into the present with Jessica Diamond, Lily van der Stokker, Katharina Grosse and Robin Rhode.</p>
        <p>The works at Dia, conceived from 1968 to 1975, were selected and arranged by LeWitt during his final illness. The show's carefully sequenced contrasts and echoes outline the scope and lucidity of his early vision in a memorably idiosyncratic way. Think of someone drawing up a seating chart for a dinner of old friends whose connections he knows better than anyone. It was a rare opportunity for someone whose work is by definition ephemeral; this exhibition, like his others, will eventually be painted over. And it is a tribute to the profound respect for artists at the heart of the Dia enterprise.</p>
        <p>LeWitt's drawings brim with the fineness and foibles of the human condition. With their generating instructions written into their titles, they compress the inspiration, physical labor and implicit gamble of art-making into a single yet dissectible experience -- reducing the path from idea to artwork into a short, fully exposed line. Yet their crisp geometries, accumulating marks and radiating patterns force us to mind the gap between artistic thought and artistic action, to accept the inability of language to predict visual outcome.</p>
        <p>The repeating freehand lines in some of the drawings here can add up to expanses that resemble wood grain or falling rain, shoulder-high grass or marbleized endpapers (but weirdly linear and desiccated ones). Add rulers, and the results can evoke a game of pick-up sticks gone wild, or a Pollock drip painting parsed by a mad geometry teacher.</p>
        <p>What do ''50 randomly placed points all connected by straight lines'' look like? One answer is ''Wall Drawing No. 118,'' a great transparent, crystalline structure of radiating lines and sharp peaks floating on the wall. It resembles an extrarational mountainscape or a constellation of stars strung together with piano wire. The lines project simultaneously inward and outward, forming the illusion of a two-sided drawing seen from both sides at once.</p>
        <p>LeWitt was a kind of lapsed Duchampian, as were his fellow Minimalists Donald Judd and Dan Flavin. All three artists were inspired by Duchamp's vexing readymades, which disdained artistic touch, favored chance and put ideas first. Yet all three strove to unite Duchamp's radicalism with a visual opulence descended from Matisse.</p>
        <p>LeWitt's wall drawings achieved this unity with unusual efficiency. His readymades were not industrial objects or materials (like Flavin's fluorescent light tubes or Judd's metal boxes). They were the intellectual staples of plane geometry -- grids, arcs, straight lines, squares, circles -- whose many applications could be adjusted in a twinkling and rendered with the sweep of a hand holding a bit of graphite, colored pencil, chalk or crayons (and possibly a straight edge).</p>
        <p>You couldn't get more basic. The delegation of responsibility eliminated the preciousness of the artist's hand, yet glorified human touch.</p>
        <p>The earliest works in this show are two immense, fuguelike drawings from Dia's collection that line the four walls of the four galleries designed for them and are being shown in their complete form here for the first time. They are theme-and-variation meditations on grids whose squares are veiled by fine, gauzy parallel lines, whether horizontal, vertical or diagonal. Moving through all the possibilities of layering and sequence, first in graphite and then in colored pencil, the works swing back and forth between symmetry and randomness, alternately confounding and reassuring the senses. (Small diagrams that are miniature wall drawings unto themselves help keep track.) Foundational works, they remind you of LeWitt's admiration for Bach.</p>
        <p>Moving from strict to goofy to obsessive to elegant, the Dia exhibition delineates the range of LeWitt's ideas and their even rangier visual outcomes. Opposite the random, spacey peaks of ''Wall Drawing No. 118,'' for example, is ''Wall Drawing No. 273,'' where more lines radiate from points, but in an entirely different manner.</p>
        <p>These lines are made by bright red, yellow and blue crayon, and the points are givens, including the corners and the center of the wall. Plotted over a faint pencil grid, they add up to schematized fireworks translated into a big banner.</p>
        <p>The next drawing cleans the slate. The grid is gone, and so is color: all that remains is the shocking starkness of two long, heavy lines of black crayon that meet at the wall's center point. One extends downward from the wall's upper right corner; the other passes through the center, aiming for its upper left corner, but never gets there. They form a failed chevron.</p>
        <p>In the next two drawings, also in black crayon, LeWitt lets the draftsmen making the works determine the placement of a few points, shapes or lines. But they are carefully plotted and foreshadowed by pale, Cubistic scaffoldings of intersecting pencil lines. LeWitt required that the determining procedure be detailed in words, and these ghostly blocks of text are also part of the drawing.</p>
        <p>In the next drawing, simple offstage instructions return, dictating three layers of action. The result is a delicately scaled, edge-to-edge grid in red pencil, covered by black concentric circles radiating from the center, and then by yellow arcs radiating from the center points of the wall's edges. It resembles a fine weaving or an immense, pulsing radar screen.</p>
        <p>In an expansive three-wall work, the lines again turn thick and black, and the geometry grows big and spare, but is regulated by the grid. Titled ''Wall Drawing No. 136: Arcs and Lines,'' it presents all the possible two-part combinations of horizontal, vertical and diagonal arcs and straight, broken and wavy lines -- a total of 190 in all.</p>
        <p>The work begins with a Matissean buoyancy as the arcs bound down and across the wall, suggesting clouds, hills and dance steps. But the straight lines soon take over, and then the broken and wavy ones. The piece dissipates in a distended yet shimmering stillness. It is like watching a day, a season or a life proceed with understated majesty from start to finish.</p>
        <p>LeWitt is rightly seen as a progenitor of Conceptual Art and might even have coined the phrase -- in his late-1960s essays ''100 Paragraphs on Conceptual Art'' and ''100 Sentences on Conceptual Art.'' For him the idea was the most important aspect of an artwork. But even more crucial was the intimate, timeless drawing processes that turned one into the other, and the generous ways he let us in on them.</p>
        <p>''Sol LeWitt: Drawing Series'' is on view through Sept. 10 at Dia:Beacon, 3 Beekman Street, Beacon, N.Y.; (845) 440-0100.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
