<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Following Father's Footsteps, but on Own Terms</title>
    <meta content="21jordan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/sports/ncaabasketball/21jordan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Jordan, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lucas, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Following Father's Footsteps, but on Own Terms</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Following Jordan’s Footsteps, but Strictly on His Own Terms</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WEINREB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinreb, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before he chose to play in the game that bears his surname, Jeffrey Jordan spoke to his father, Michael. He wanted to be sure, he said, that this was not mere nepotism, and that he truly belonged on the court tonight at the Jordan Brand All-American Classic, a high school all-star game at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>In the midst of their discussion, according to Jeffrey, his father told him, ''You've earned it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the son of one of the most famous athletes on the planet, Jeffrey Jordan has grown accustomed to being singled out while playing his father’s game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before he chose to play in the game that bears his surname, Jeffrey Jordan spoke to his father, Michael. He wanted to be sure, he said, that this was not mere nepotism, and that he truly belonged on the court tonight at the Jordan Brand All-American Classic, a high school all-star game at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>In the midst of their discussion, according to Jeffrey, his father told him, ''You've earned it.''</p>
        <p>As the son of one of the most famous athletes on the planet, Jeffrey Jordan has grown accustomed to being singled out while playing his father's game. On Thursday, he donned a jersey that bears his father's silhouette for a team practice at a Manhattan gym. Then he took the floor with some of the top high school seniors in the country, most of whom have committed to major programs like Duke, Georgetown, Arizona and Michigan State.</p>
        <p>But for Jordan, a 6-foot guard from Loyola Academy in Wilmette, Ill., the choices are less prestigious: Valparaiso and Davidson, he said, were on his short list. He said that he was also considering several Big Ten programs, including Northwestern, Illinois and Penn State, but would probably be a walk-on for those teams.</p>
        <p>Most recruiting analysts say that Jordan could be a solid guard for a midmajor college team like Valparaiso, which he visited this week. It has made for an awkward situation for Jordan, an 18-year-old who is not only dwelling in the impossibly large shadow of his father, but whose younger brother Marcus, a 6-3 sophomore at Loyola Academy, is already regarded as a better college prospect.</p>
        <p>''None of us will ever know what it's like,'' said Pat Mahoney, the athletic director at Loyola Academy. ''What is real to him and what isn't?''</p>
        <p>All of that has made for what one analyst, Dave Telep of scout.com, described as ''the most unique recruiting scenario we've seen in a while.''</p>
        <p>It has scared away coaches who simply cannot imagine they could ever land an audience with Michael Jordan, and attracted coaches who would like to bring in Jeffrey Jordan simply because of his name.</p>
        <p>''I think it's gone both ways,'' said Rob Harrington, a recruiting analyst for prepstars.com. ''Some people have been a little wary, trying to recruit a kid whose father is larger than life. And anything that wrests control of a program from a coach might make them back off. But there are also collateral benefits to bringing a Jordan into your program.''</p>
        <p>Jordan is, of course, not the first young prospect whose father preceded him in the game. Jai Lucas, the son of the former N.B.A. All-Star John Lucas, is also playing in the Classic tonight.</p>
        <p>But Jai Lucas is being recruited by several major programs, including Florida, Kentucky and Oklahoma State.</p>
        <p>And Jai Lucas's father was able to attend the practice session without an entourage of security guards trailing him wherever he went, which is usually the case when Jordan watches his sons (he was not in attendance Thursday).</p>
        <p>''The attention he gets is crazy,'' Jai Lucas said of Jeffrey Jordan. ''I wouldn't want to have security guards following me around all the time. But that just comes with his last name being Jordan.''</p>
        <p>John Lucas said, ''That's a different level.''</p>
        <p>It's a reality that officials at Loyola Academy have become accustomed to over the years. Crowds at the school's games increased significantly, with fans curious about the sons and hoping to catch a glimpse of the father. But Mahoney said that Jeffrey and Marcus had blended in with the student body and had shrugged off the taunts from fans at opposing schools.</p>
        <p>And Jeffrey Jordan insists that his father has been uncharacteristically hands-off when it comes to his sons' coaching and recruitment. Jeffrey acknowledges, though, that he has enjoyed certain favors.</p>
        <p>For instance, he won a spot at the Nike summer camp between his sophomore and junior seasons, an honor, Harrington said, that is usually reserved for the top players in the class.</p>
        <p>During his freshman and sophomore seasons at Loyola, Jeffrey Jordan said, his father had visions of Jeffrey walking on at his alma mater, North Carolina, and proving his worth to Coach Roy Williams.</p>
        <p>''Coach Williams talked to my dad -- he's a family friend,'' Jeffrey Jordan said after practice Thursday. ''He wants me to go somewhere I can play my freshman and sophomore year.''</p>
        <p>Which means that North Carolina is no longer on this Jordan's list.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
