<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Memorial Services Held In U.S. and Around World</title>
    <meta content="21virginia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/us/21virginia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Virginia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Urbina, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fernandez, Manny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Sun-Kyung</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Memorial Services Held In U.S. and Around World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Memorial Services Held in U.S. and Around World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN URBINA and MANNY FERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fernandez, Manny; Urbina, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many of 32 victims of shooting rampage at Virginia Tech are remembered at memorial services around state, nation and world, at same time as family of killer, Seung-Hui Cho, issues apology; statement, released by his sister, Sun-Kyung Cho, says that family members never envisioned that he was capable of such violence; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many of the 32 victims of the shooting rampage at Virginia Tech were remembered Friday at memorial services around the state, the nation and the world, at the same time as the family of their killer issued an apology.</p>
        <p>''He has made the world weep,'' said the statement, released by Sun-Kyung Cho, the sister of Seung-Hui Cho, the 23-year-old Virginia Tech senior who methodically killed dozens of students and faculty members on Monday. ''We are living in a nightmare.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The victims of the shooting rampage at Virginia Tech were remembered at memorial services and the family of their killer issued an apology.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Many of the 32 victims of the shooting rampage at Virginia Tech were remembered Friday at memorial services around the state, the nation and the world, at the same time as the family of their killer issued an apology.</p>
        <p>''He has made the world weep,'' said the statement, released by Sun-Kyung Cho, the sister of Seung-Hui Cho, the 23-year-old Virginia Tech senior who methodically killed dozens of students and faculty members on Monday. ''We are living in a nightmare.''</p>
        <p>The statement, given to The Associated Press by Wade Smith, a lawyer in Raleigh, N.C., on behalf of Ms. Cho, said that family members never envisioned that Mr. Cho was capable of such violence, noting that he struggled to fit in.</p>
        <p>''We feel hopeless, helpless and lost,'' Ms. Cho said. ''This is someone that I grew up with and loved. Now I feel like I didn't know this person.'' She added, ''Our family is so very sorry for my brother's unspeakable actions.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cho's parents, who live in Centreville, Va., a Washington suburb, and work in the dry cleaning business, have not made any statements or been seen publicly since their son was identified as the gunman on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The statement was the first indication the family preferred to refer to their son as Seung-Hui Cho, rather than Cho Seung-Hui, the more traditional Korean formation the university used when identifying him on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The statement came as six memorial services for victims were held around the world on Friday -- three in Virginia, one in New Jersey, one in Israel and another in Nova Scotia. Arrangements have been made for at least 16 other services in six states through Tuesday.</p>
        <p>That Friday also happened to be the eighth anniversary of another mass killing, at Columbine High School near Littleton, Colo., added another grim element to a day already heavy with grief.</p>
        <p>''It's a hard day,'' said the Rev. Alexander W. Evans, the pastor of Blacksburg Presbyterian Church, at a memorial service for Kevin P. Granata, 45, an engineering professor who was killed by Mr. Cho. ''But we're here to give thanks for his life.''</p>
        <p>Tears flowed among those in the sanctuary as a former department chairman described Mr. Granata's bravery in ushering students into his office and out of harm's way before going to investigate the gunfire.</p>
        <p>Less than 40 miles away in Narrows, Va., a line of about 300 mourners shuffled quietly through a gymnasium at Narrows High School, casting their gaze down at the body of Jarrett Lee Lane.</p>
        <p>''Everybody in town knew Jarrett,'' said Darrel Tawney, a family friend of Mr. Lane, who was the high school's 2003 valedictorian and a star baseball player. ''You didn't go to the ballgame except to watch him.''</p>
        <p>Governors in 39 states and Guam declared Friday as an official day of mourning, while businesses closed briefly at noon in Blacksburg to observe a statewide moment of silence.</p>
        <p>Also on Friday, President Bush announced in his weekly radio address that senior officials at the Departments of Education, Justice and Health and Human Services would participate in a review of the broader questions of dealing with people whose mental health makes them a danger to society.</p>
        <p>The officials, he said, would travel to communities around the nation, meeting with educators, mental health experts and local officials. He said Michael O. Leavitt, the health and human services secretary, would report back to him with recommendations about how to avoid such tragedies in the future.</p>
        <p>Having retrieved the bodies of their relatives from the medical examiner's office in Roanoke, Va., grieving families returned home to mourn in ways that were as diverse as the faiths and backgrounds of those people killed, including cremations, Roman Catholic wakes, secular remembrances and sitting shiva. Some ceremonies were public, while others were not.</p>
        <p>At a Hindu ceremony on campus Thursday, 33 candles were lighted, including one for Mr. Cho, who shot himself after his deadly killing spree.</p>
        <p>''He also was a lost soul,'' said Kusum Singh, who helped organize the Hindu ceremony to memorialize G. V. Loganathan, 52, a professor of civil and environmental engineering, and Minal Panchal, 26, an architecture student from Mumbai, India.</p>
        <p>Several hundred people gathered on the Virginia Tech campus's Drill Field to watch the release of 32 maroon and orange balloons, each bearing a victim's name.</p>
        <p>''Mike, we love you,'' said Katie Willson, of Williamsburg, Va., as she let go a balloon for Michael S. Pohle Jr., a fifth-year senior biology major who was killed in his German class.</p>
        <p>In the background, four state troopers stood in front of Norris Hall, the site of 30 of the shootings still cordoned off with yellow crime-scene tape.</p>
        <p>The widespread distribution of the week's funerals made clear the global nature of the tragedy.</p>
        <p>In Sumatra, Indonesia, services were held for Partahi Mamora Lumbantoruan, an engineering doctoral student.</p>
        <p>In Nova Scotia, a memorial service was held Friday for Jocelyne Couture-Nowak, a French professor killed while teaching a class.</p>
        <p>Also on Friday, in Ra'anana, Israel, family members attended the burial of Liviu Librescu, a 76-year-old engineering lecturer and Holocaust survivor, who was shot while trying to protect students in a classroom.</p>
        <p>''They ask me today about your past and I don't know what to say, but that I am proud of you,'' said the victim's son, Joe Librescu. ''You taught me right from wrong, and sometimes I didn't listen. But now my ears are open.''</p>
        <p>In mourning, families struggled with the senselessness of the violence. Souheil Samaha, the cousin of one of the victims, Reema Samaha, marveled at the irony of her death in America. He said that the last time Ms. Samaha was in Lebanon visiting extended family, she got trapped in northern Beirut by the war that broke out last summer and was among the American-Lebanese civilians who had to be evacuated by an American warship.</p>
        <p>''I haven't really processed everything that has happened,'' Mr. Samaha, a Virginia Tech student, said in a telephone interview, adding that a burial will be held for Ms. Samaha on Monday.</p>
        <p>Tuesday's service for Austin Michelle Cloyd in her hometown, Champaign, Ill., will be held on what would have been her 20th birthday. The family of Emily Jane Hilscher, a member of the campus equestrian club who dreamed of becoming a veterinarian, asked that donations be made to the Rappahannock Animal Welfare League in Amissville, Va.</p>
        <p>Other campuses found their own ways to show support.</p>
        <p>At Pennsylvania State University, about 800 students have signed up to wear maroon and orange shirts and will sit in the stands in the formation of the VT symbol during the university's football game this weekend.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Cho, the sister of the gunman, mourning came with a promise that the family would do whatever necessary to explain Mr. Cho's actions.</p>
        <p>''There is much justified anger and disbelief at what my brother did, and a lot of questions are left unanswered,'' she wrote in the statement. ''Our family will continue to cooperate fully and do whatever we can to help authorities understand why these senseless acts happened. We have many unanswered questions as well.''</p>
        <p>MASSACRE IN VIRGINIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
