<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justice Dept. Is Asked To Investigate Reading Plan</title>
    <meta content="21reading" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/us/21reading.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Department (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schemo, Diana Jean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Higgins, John P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E7DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justice Dept. Is Asked To Investigate Reading Plan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Justice Dept. Is Asked to Investigate Reading Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schemo, Diana Jean</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Education Dept Inspector Gen John P Higgins asks Justice Dept to investigate Reading First, Bush administration's $6 billion program to teach poor children to read by third grade; testifies at Congress's opening hearing on Reading First, which awards grants to states to buy teaching materials and for training; Higgins has issued half dozen reports finding conflicts of interest, cronyism and bias in how federal officials and private consultants operated program and awarded grants (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Education Department's inspector general has asked the Justice Department to investigate Reading First, the Bush administration's $6 billion program to teach poor children to read by third grade.</p>
        <p>The inspector general, John P. Higgins, testified about his request at Congress's opening hearing on Reading First, which awards grants to states to buy teaching materials and for training. Mr. Higgins has issued a half-dozen reports finding conflicts of interest, cronyism and bias in how federal officials and private consultants operated the program and awarded the grants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Education Department’s inspector general has issued a half-dozen reports finding conflicts of interest, cronyism and bias in the operation of Reading First.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Education Department's inspector general has asked the Justice Department to investigate Reading First, the Bush administration's $6 billion program to teach poor children to read by third grade.</p>
        <p>The inspector general, John P. Higgins, testified about his request at Congress's opening hearing on Reading First, which awards grants to states to buy teaching materials and for training. Mr. Higgins has issued a half-dozen reports finding conflicts of interest, cronyism and bias in how federal officials and private consultants operated the program and awarded the grants.</p>
        <p>The civil division of the Justice Department is looking into his findings, but has not decided whether to begin an investigation, a spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Also at the hearing, three current and former professors at the University of Oregon, who played important roles in advising states on how to apply for Reading First grants, testified that they had collected hundreds of thousands of dollars in royalties from curriculums and tests they had authored, whose use grew exponentially through the program. But they denied any conflicts of interest.</p>
        <p>Christopher Doherty, the former director of Reading First, defended his operation of the program. But Representative George Miller, Democrat of California and chairman of the education committee, said Reading First ''officials and contractors created an uneven playing field that favored certain products,'' particularly those that emphasized phonics.</p>
        <p>Turning to the inspector general, Mr. Miller said, ''I think when we put the evidence together we may end up joining you in those criminal referrals.''</p>
        <p>The hearing unfolded a day after Education Secretary Margaret Spellings released test results from schools in the Reading First program showing students making progress. The data echoed an earlier report by the Government Accountability Office. But Wednesday's data also showed that most of these states used a once obscure assessment developed by the panelists from Oregon, which the inspector general's report suggested had been unfairly promoted through Reading First.</p>
        <p>Starr Lewis, Kentucky's associate commissioner of education, said her state applied four times for Reading First money. The only significant change between the first and fourth application, she said, was that her state surrendered to pressure from federal officials to drop the testing instrument it was using in favor of the Oregon assessment.</p>
        <p>The three Oregon panelists who appeared at the hearing were Roland H. Good III, Edward J. Kame'enui and Deborah Simmons. Dr. Good, who created the assessment, testified that a company he formed in 2003 to market it had collected nearly $1.3 million in royalties from 2003 to 2006, through states that used it.</p>
        <p>Though the assessment is available as a free download, many schools pay the University of Oregon $1 per child to score the test results. Still others buy a hand-held device to score students' reading skills. Dr. Good said his company collects 40 cents per child per year from a partner company that markets the device to schools.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewis, of Kentucky, said her state alone had paid Wireless Generation, the partner company that markets the handheld devices, nearly $750,000 since 2004 for the devices and for scoring the assessments.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kame'enui, who is temporarily the federal Commissioner of Special Education Research, said royalties from curriculums he had authored had grown steadily each year under Reading First, to $150,000 last year. Dr. Kame'enui was director of a regional center at Oregon that advised states applying for Reading First grants.</p>
        <p>Dr. Simmons, a former professor who had also advised states on Reading First, said materials she co-authored with Dr. Kame'enui had brought her similar revenues.</p>
        <p>All three Oregon panelists said they had not ranked their own materials' fitness for use under Reading First, and so had avoided any conflict of interest. And they said it was the quality of their programs, not direct or indirect pressure from Education Department officials, that explained their popularity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doherty, who resigned when the first Inspector General's report appeared last September, talked about a tension in the law authorizing Reading First, because it calls on states to use reading approaches grounded in scientific research, but bars the federal government from dictating, or even endorsing, specific reading programs or assessments. And he accused the committee of a bias of its own.</p>
        <p>''Reading First was and probably will remain the highlight of my professional career,'' Mr. Doherty said. ''I know that some state directors wanted to testify today, and were told by the staff that the committee was not interested in positive things about the program.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
