<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2008 Democratic Hopefuls Propose a Ceiling on the President's Tax Cuts</title>
    <meta content="21tax" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/us/politics/21tax.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Gains Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obama, Barack (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Gains Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Obama, Barack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Edwards, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dodd, Christopher J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Biden, Joseph R Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Richardson, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E2D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2008 Democratic Hopefuls Propose a Ceiling on the President's Tax Cuts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2008 Democrats Propose a Ceiling on Bush Tax Cuts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leading Democratic presidential candidates, grappling with one of biggest domestic policy choices that will confront next administration, say they will raise variety of taxes on affluent people but extend Pres Bush's tax cuts for middle- and lower-income families; Hillary Rodham Clinton, Barack Obama and John Edwards are backing variants of same approach, which would result in higher taxes on income, capital gains and stock dividends for upper-income people; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grappling with one of the biggest domestic policy choices that will confront the next administration, the leading Democratic presidential candidates say they would raise a variety of taxes on affluent people but extend President Bush's tax cuts for middle- and lower-income families.</p>
        <p>Virtually all of Mr. Bush's tax cuts are set to expire at the end of 2010, and the issue of whether to extend some or all of them sharply divides the parties and is a complex one for the Democratic candidates on both political and fiscal policy grounds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leading candidates say they would raise taxes on the affluent but extend President Bush’s tax cuts for others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Grappling with one of the biggest domestic policy choices that will confront the next administration, the leading Democratic presidential candidates say they would raise a variety of taxes on affluent people but extend President Bush's tax cuts for middle- and lower-income families.</p>
        <p>Virtually all of Mr. Bush's tax cuts are set to expire at the end of 2010, and the issue of whether to extend some or all of them sharply divides the parties and is a complex one for the Democratic candidates on both political and fiscal policy grounds.</p>
        <p>Already, Republicans are signaling that they will attack the Democrats for what they say would be a mammoth tax increase that would threaten the economy and fuel growth in government spending. Democrats say the shift they are advocating would bring more fairness to the tax system and help pay for needed expansions of social programs while helping to keep the budget deficit under control.</p>
        <p>Although they have yet to release detailed proposals or to talk about the issue in any depth on the campaign trail, Senators Hillary Rodham Clinton and Barack Obama, and former Senator John Edwards, said through aides that they were backing variants of the same approach, which would result in higher taxes on income, capital gains and stock dividends for upper-income people. All of them, as well Senators Christopher J. Dodd and Joseph R. Biden Jr. and Gov. Bill Richardson, have made clear that they would support keeping in place the tax cuts that have benefited the vast majority of people, roughly speaking households with income less than $200,000 or so. In that way, the Democratic stance would ensure that a substantial portion of one of Mr. Bush's signature policies would outlast his presidency, even if his party loses the White House.</p>
        <p>But Democrats have also signaled that they intend to undo a central principle of the Bush tax cuts -- that they should extend to all income levels -- by rolling back reductions that have benefited the wealthiest Americans in recent years.</p>
        <p>''Yes, we'll have to raise taxes,'' Mr. Edwards declared in February in one of the first statements by a Democratic candidate on the issue.</p>
        <p>Democratic strategists said the candidates were all keenly aware that Republicans are eager to attack them over tax increases. Vice President Dick Cheney accused Congressional Democrats last week of already planning ''the biggest tax increase in American history.''</p>
        <p>''The result would be a staggering tax increase on the middle class, on families and small businesses, and a return of the federal death tax from zero back up to a confiscatory 55 percent,'' Mr. Cheney said.</p>
        <p>But Democratic campaign officials have not shied away from the conflict, asserting that the Bush tax cuts were tilted in favor the rich and need to be rebalanced.</p>
        <p>''Americans know there is a difference between keeping taxes as low as possible on the middle class, and giving away the bank to the wealthiest Americans,'' said Bill Burton, a spokesman for Mr. Obama. ''If President Bush's tax cuts are extended, the wealthiest 1 percent will save more than the bottom 80 percent combined, at a cost of $1 trillion over 10 years.''</p>
        <p>The Democratic candidates would be trying to recapture a big chunk of the revenues that were allocated to tax cuts in the Bush years. And they would be challenging one of the main arguments offered by conservatives in favor of tax cuts, that reducing rates on upper-income people spurs more investment and job creation.</p>
        <p>To keep in place the entire package of Bush tax cuts would cost the government about $1.8 trillion over the next decade, according to Congressional budget analysts, a period when the nation will also begin confronting the costs of an aging population to the Medicare and Social Security systems.</p>
        <p>Simply extending Mr. Bush's tax cuts for families that earn less than $200,000, and most of the reduction in estate taxes on inherited wealth, could cost about $900 billion over the next decade, according to new estimates by the Tax Policy Center, a nonprofit research group whose tax estimates are considered reliable by most analysts.</p>
        <p>For people with incomes of more than $200,000 a year, roughly the top 3 percent of earners, the Democratic candidates would essentially revert to the tax regime under President Bill Clinton in the 1990s. The top marginal tax rate would return to 39.6 percent, up from 35 percent currently, for people with taxable incomes of more than $336,550. People with incomes between $200,000 and $336,550 would see their top rate climb to 36 percent from 33 percent today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's signature tax cuts for capital gains and stock dividends would all but disappear, because people earning more than $200,000 receive the vast bulk of such earnings.</p>
        <p>None of the Democratic candidates would eliminate the estate tax on inherited wealth, long one of the Republicans' goals. Under law, the estate tax becomes smaller each year until it disappears in 2010, only to bounce back in full when the tax cut expires at the end of that year.</p>
        <p>Several Democratic candidates said they would let the estate tax dwindle to levels set for 2009. At that point, estates worth less than $3.5 million -- and less than $7 million if owned by a couple -- would be excluded from any tax.</p>
        <p>But the candidates have not said how they would reconcile their goal of leaving a portion of the tax cuts in place with the Democratic Party's professed objective of doing nothing to aggravate the budget deficit. Indeed, the presidential candidates are on a collision course with Congressional Democratic leaders who have adopted rules that require paying for new tax cuts with savings or tax increases elsewhere, a stance that would presumably apply to an extension of the existing tax cuts.</p>
        <p>At the same time, leaving even a portion of the Bush tax cuts in place means that the next president and the next Congress would have less money to allocate to spending programs than they would if they allowed all the tax cuts to expire, leaving them with a choice between further increasing the budget deficit or limiting their plans for addressing health care, education, energy and other needs.</p>
        <p>Robert Greenstein, director of the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, a liberal research group, said Mr. Bush had left Democrats in a very difficult position.</p>
        <p>''What strikes me now is the degree to which the fairly fiscally irresponsible policies of the last six years have put Democrats in a box,'' Mr. Greenstein said. ''They've got these large tax cuts in place, they have even larger fiscal problems in the coming decades and they have large unmet needs right now, such as 45 million uninsured people. Addressing all three of those things will be very difficult.''</p>
        <p>Even preserving just the so-called ''middle class'' tax cuts could reduce revenues almost $150 billion a year, a bigger cost to the Treasury than the war in Iraq or marquee Democratic initiatives like expanding health care for low-income children.</p>
        <p>None of the Democratic candidates has laid out a detailed agenda for Mr. Bush's tax cuts, but Mr. Edwards, of North Carolina, has been the most explicit. He has said he would not even wait for the tax cuts to expire and would immediately seek to repeal them for everybody earning more than $200,000. He would use the money for his plan to deliver health care to all Americans.</p>
        <p>Measured as a share of the gross domestic product, which many economists say is the best gauge for measuring the size of tax cuts and increases, a repeal of all Mr. Bush's tax cuts would be smaller than tax increases imposed during World War II, the Korean War and the tax increases signed by Mr. Clinton.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
