<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Health Inspector Calls and Chef's Pride Cracks</title>
    <meta content="21chef" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/nyregion/21chef.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sanitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brasserie La Cote Basque (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Health and Mental Hygiene Department (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Konigsberg, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rachou, Jean-Jacques</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Health and Mental Hygiene Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Health Inspector Calls and Chef's Pride Cracks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Health Inspector Calls and Chef’s Pride Cracks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC KONIGSBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Konigsberg, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brasserie La Cote Basque, venerable New York restaurant, was shut down by city's Health Dept after it failed inspection on March 8; it is one of 297 restaurants that city has closed since week ending Feb 24; Jean-Jacques Rachou, chef and owner of Brasserie La Cote Basque, believes that he was made example of; city denies that; restaurant passed new inspection on March 30, but it has yet to reopen; Rachou says he is too depressed; his attitude has complicated future of restaurant with rich pedigree; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was 11:59 a.m., according to the report from the city's Department of Health and Mental Hygiene. The first lunch reservations at Brasserie La Côte Basque, just off Fifth Avenue in Manhattan, were about to arrive. The inspector introduced himself to the hostess and headed straight for the kitchen, where he found Jean-Jacques Rachou, the restaurant's owner and chef, at the stove.</p>
        <p>Six and a half hours later, the inspector finished his evaluation -- and shut the place down. ''The next morning, we had a yellow sign in the window,'' Mr. Rachou says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A restaurant owner cannot bring himself to reopen Brasserie LCB, which city officials had temporarily closed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was 11:59 a.m., according to the report from the city's Department of Health and Mental Hygiene. The first lunch reservations at Brasserie La Côte Basque, just off Fifth Avenue in Manhattan, were about to arrive. The inspector introduced himself to the hostess and headed straight for the kitchen, where he found Jean-Jacques Rachou, the restaurant's owner and chef, at the stove.</p>
        <p>Six and a half hours later, the inspector finished his evaluation -- and shut the place down. ''The next morning, we had a yellow sign in the window,'' Mr. Rachou says.</p>
        <p>The city Health Department has closed 297 restaurants since the week ending Feb. 24. That was when a scene of rats teeming around a Taco Bell/KFC in Greenwich Village was captured on a widely disseminated videotape, a sight that triggered a tough new round of health department inspections. A vast majority of the restaurants have been reinspected and reopened.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rachou cannot bring himself to reopen the brasserie just yet. Of all the shuttered restaurants, this may be the one with the greatest reputation for the seriousness of its food and the profile of its chef.</p>
        <p>While chefs at other restaurants said the brasserie's code violations were fairly routine, the details of its closing reveal a very human clash of agendas and sensibilities, as well as a frustration and heartbreak that cannot be captured in a statistic. Mr. Rachou believes he was made an example of; the city denies that. While the chef's attitude may have played a role, it has certainly complicated the future of a restaurant with a rich pedigree.</p>
        <p>The closing was on March 8. On March 30, the restaurant passed a new inspection with flying colors. But Mr. Rachou has yet to reopen; he says he is too depressed: ''The kitchen is ready, but the mind is not yet. Look, first I have to get over it. I need another two weeks to pull myself together. Maybe then.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, his 40 or so employees have been out of work -- or working elsewhere -- and the restaurant has forfeited what industry observers speculate may be around $100,000 per week in revenues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rachou has salt-and-pepper hair (skewing salt) and a mustache, and at 71 he represents the ancien régime of the New York restaurant world as both a mentor over the years to many great chefs and as a stubborn personality type.</p>
        <p>Across the regulatory divide from him was the inspector, Lalbachan Sukhu, a civil servant not much more than half Mr. Rachou's age, under orders to leave no bain-marie unturned as he and his colleagues set about to systematically scrutinize every commercial kitchen in town.</p>
        <p>Brasserie La Côte Basque, at 60 West 55th Street, is the renamed and more relaxed iteration of La Côte Basque, which Mr. Rachou, a classically trained chef from France, took over in 1979. He said his restaurant's closing last month was a great shock.</p>
        <p>''When this happened, I was really destroyed,'' Mr. Rachou said, standing outside the restaurant, which was dark, its bentwood chairs stacked on tables.</p>
        <p>''I would say in the city, my kitchen is one of the 10 best,'' Mr. Rachou said. ''If not, it would go against my rules. They made an example of me.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I don't deserve it. Maybe I deserve it. I don't know.''</p>
        <p>Restaurateurs and health department officials alike acknowledge that when an inspector calls, tensions run high. ''It can be a deadly experience, and what you don't want to do is let your emotions get away with you,'' said Steve Millington, the general manager of Michael's, the media-crowd hangout a few doors from Brasserie LCB.</p>
        <p>''It's like a cop giving you a speeding ticket,'' he said. ''You'll be there until the cows come home. There's almost a petulance to the inspectors. You really need to shut up and be servile to them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sukhu would not consent to an interview. But Elliott Marcus, associate commissioner of the food safety bureau, said that his inspectors have found the crackdown period demoralizing as well. ''They're not exactly welcomed at these restaurants with open arms,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still, walking into Mr. Rachou's kitchen during lunch service is a little bit like trying to measure the pope's head for a new miter in the middle of high Mass: It struck him as intrusive.</p>
        <p>''Apparently, Jean-Jacques did not receive the man the way it should be done,'' said Andre Ihuellou, the brasserie's manager. ''The inspector went around and around the kitchen. He went to the walk-in icebox. Then he made him throw a few ducks in the garbage.''</p>
        <p>Ten whole, cooked ducks, in fact, along with six cooked chickens and eight pounds of sausage and lentils, were registered at 48 to 50 degrees Fahrenheit and tossed out. The regulation maximum temperature is 41 degrees. Mr. Rachou estimates that he disposed of $50,000 worth of food.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rachou recalled: ''I was not very fresh with the inspector. I just make him understand that from 10 o'clock in the morning until 8 o'clock at night I am busy cooking.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sukhu continued his evaluation. Mr. Rachou ignored him. ''They say you are always supposed to accompany the inspector, because maybe you can explain things to him, but I was too busy,'' Mr. Rachou said. ''Next time.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Rachou finished cooking lunch, the inspector was still in the restaurant, sitting in the dining room as he punched information into a hand-held computer.</p>
        <p>''I left at 3 o'clock to take my nap, and when I came back three hours later, he was still here,'' Mr. Rachou said. ''I kept coming out of the kitchen: 'You finished?' 'You finished?' He said, 'No, there are some détails.' ''</p>
        <p>It was during the restaurant's dinner service that Mr. Sukhu phoned a supervisor -- who, according to the health department's rules, must have spoken to his own supervisor -- and then informed Mr. Rachou's maître d'hôtel that he was going to close the restaurant.</p>
        <p>The restaurant's hostess began to cry.</p>
        <p>After pleading, Mr. Rachou was allowed to finish serving the customers who were already seated inside the 40-table restaurant. ''But then he made us lock the door,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sukhu had cited Mr. Rachou's restaurant for 13 health code violations. Many of them were minor -- ''Choking first aid poster not conspicuously displayed in dining area,'' for example, and some cutting boards were noted to be ''badly worn'' -- but they added up to 80 points. A tally of 28 points or more is a failing score.</p>
        <p>Brasserie La Côte Basque received 28 points on one violation alone, multiple instances of ''mouse activity'': four dead mice and ''fresh and stale mice excreta observed'' in several storage areas. There were also a few roaches. ''If you lift every can, you find a cockroach,'' Mr. Rachou said. ''It's not a bank, it's a restaurant.''</p>
        <p>Although restaurants that receive failing scores are often allowed to remain open while problems are remedied, Mr. Marcus, of the health department, said this one was shut down ''both for the seriousness of some of its violations and because it had a history of violations.'' A department spokesman, Andrew Tucker, said it had failed two other inspections in the past three years.</p>
        <p>La Côte Basque's history as a temple of both the haute (cuisine) and the high (society) is grand. Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, Frank Sinatra and Babe Paley all made the scene, and a chapter of Truman Capote's unfinished novel ''Answered Prayers'' was set there, a barely fictionalized -- and most unkind -- piece of social satire.</p>
        <p>As a restaurateur, Mr. Rachou has survived any number of potentially devastating currents, from nouvelle cuisine to the restaurant's move to the West Side in 1995 (its original location was one block east).</p>
        <p>Like many institutions burdened with the warhorse label, Mr. Rachou and his restaurant struggled to grow old gracefully. While retaining its share of regulars, the restaurant also feeds a lot of tourists and business travelers. Mr. Rachou's friends and colleagues say he had already been considering retirement, but he describes himself as reluctant.</p>
        <p>''That's all I know to do: work, work, work,'' he said. ''Cooking is my life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
