<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2nd House Republican Yields Committee Post</title>
    <meta content="21lobby" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/washington/21lobby.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arizona</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Renzi, Rick (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charlton, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2nd House Republican Yields Committee Post</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2nd House Republican Yields Committee Post</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS; Eric Lipton contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Rick Renzi of Arizona steps down from House Intelligence Committee, saying he is doing so because he is under federal investigation dealing with series of financial transactions; Arizona Democrats point out that federal prosecutor who began investigation, Paul Charlton, was one of eight US attorneys fired by Bush administration last year; Renzi photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Rick Renzi of Arizona stepped down suddenly Friday from the House Intelligence Committee, saying he was doing so because he was under federal investigation dealing with a series of financial transactions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Renzi is the second Republican congressman in the last two days to relinquish an important committee post because of a federal inquiry, a development suggesting a quickening pace of some federal corruption investigations of members of Congress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Rick Renzi of Arizona stepped down from the House Intelligence Committee, saying he was doing so because he was under federal investigation dealing with a series of financial transactions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Rick Renzi of Arizona stepped down suddenly Friday from the House Intelligence Committee, saying he was doing so because he was under federal investigation dealing with a series of financial transactions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Renzi is the second Republican congressman in the last two days to relinquish an important committee post because of a federal inquiry, a development suggesting a quickening pace of some federal corruption investigations of members of Congress.</p>
        <p>Representative John T. Doolittle of California gave up his seat Thursday on the powerful House Appropriations Committee. Mr. Doolittle has been linked in three inquiries to accusations that committee members accepted bribes or campaign contributions in exchange for earmarking federal money to certain projects.</p>
        <p>The investigation of Mr. Renzi, a wealthy developer from the Flagstaff area, began before the November elections and involves accusations that he improperly used his influence as a congressman to engineer a land swap benefiting a business associate.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued by his office Friday, Mr. Renzi said: ''Yesterday, the F.B.I. came to my family's business to obtain documents related to their investigation. I view these actions as the first step in bringing out the truth. Until this matter is resolved, I will take a leave of absence from the House Intelligence Committee.''</p>
        <p>Federal agents raided the office of the Patriot Insurance Agency Inc. in Sonoita, Ariz., on Thursday. The Phoenix Business Journal said state records listed Roberta Renzi, the congressman's wife, as the company's president.</p>
        <p>Arizona Democrats were quick to point out that the federal prosecutor who began the investigation, Paul Charlton, was one of the eight United States attorneys fired by the Bush administration last year. Their dismissal has produced a political firestorm for the White House and was the subject of a Senate Judiciary Committee hearing Thursday at which Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales defended the firings.</p>
        <p>David Waid, the chairman of the Arizona Democratic Party, said in a statement, ''After half a year of sitting on this probe, the Department of Justice pursues it on the very day that Attorney General Gonzales is called before Congress for firing the very prosecutor who opened the Renzi investigation in the first place.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Waid said that ''the dots are connected, and they lead right back to the attorney general's doorstep.''</p>
        <p>Brian Roehrkasse, spokesman for the Justice Department, said in response that the department ''under Attorney General Gonzales has never retaliated against a United States attorney for conducting or failing to pursue a public corruption investigation.''</p>
        <p>Documents previously released by the Justice Department in response to requests from Congressional Democrats detail a handful of reasons for department officials' unhappiness with Mr. Charlton. None of those documents refer to the Renzi investigation.</p>
        <p>In a second case involving Mr. Renzi, federal authorities opened a preliminary investigation last fall into whether legislation he introduced had benefited the ManTech International Corporation, a military contractor that employed his father, a retired major general, as senior executive vice president.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
