<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Bank to Broaden Its Inquiry Into Wolfowitz</title>
    <meta content="21wolfowitz" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/washington/21wolfowitz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riza, Shaha Ali</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Bank</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E7DB163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Bank to Broaden Its Inquiry Into Wolfowitz</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">World Bank to Broaden Its Inquiry Into Wolfowitz</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World Bank's board of directors expresses 'great concern' about furor over Paul D Wolfowitz's leadership as president, and they say their inquiry into his conduct will extend beyond allegations of favoritism shown to his companion at bank, Shaha Ali Riza (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The World Bank's board of directors expressed ''great concern'' on Friday about the furor over Paul D. Wolfowitz's leadership as president, and they said their inquiry into his conduct would extend beyond the allegations of favoritism shown to his female companion at the bank.</p>
        <p>The board's action, announced after a meeting that started at midafternoon on Thursday and ended at 1:30 a.m. on Friday, increased the uproar consuming Mr. Wolfowitz, who has rejected demands from the bank's staff and from one of his own top deputies that he resign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The board of directors said their inquiry into Paul D. Wolfowitz’s leadership would extend beyond allegations of favoritism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The World Bank's board of directors expressed ''great concern'' on Friday about the furor over Paul D. Wolfowitz's leadership as president, and they said their inquiry into his conduct would extend beyond the allegations of favoritism shown to his female companion at the bank.</p>
        <p>The board's action, announced after a meeting that started at midafternoon on Thursday and ended at 1:30 a.m. on Friday, increased the uproar consuming Mr. Wolfowitz, who has rejected demands from the bank's staff and from one of his own top deputies that he resign.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Wolfowitz's future clouded, but little appetite on the board to force his ouster, officials at the bank said the board had decided to broaden and lengthen its investigation into Mr. Wolfowitz, possibly into next month, in the hope that he would quit or that the Bush administration would recognize that his situation had become untenable.</p>
        <p>The board did not specify any issues to be examined, but it set up an ad hoc committee to look into ''possible violations of staff rules'' and ''a number of issues requiring further consideration.'' The implication seemed unmistakable.</p>
        <p>''It was designed to be a very clear message that they're going to turn over everything and look under every rock,'' said a bank official who had been briefed on the board's meeting.</p>
        <p>Among the issues that bank officials said the board would look into are accusations that a top aide of Mr. Wolfowitz recently tried to curb the bank's support of contraception in Africa, allegations of selectivity in prosecuting ethics violations by the bank's integrity unit and supposed favoritism in granting large salaries to top Wolfowitz aides.</p>
        <p>In addition, the board said it would look into ''various public communications made by the bank'' on the controversy over Mr. Wolfowitz's role in arranging for a pay and promotion package for his companion, Shaha Ali Riza, when she was detailed to the State Department shortly after Mr. Wolfowitz became the bank's president in 2005.</p>
        <p>At issue, bank officials said, were statements to news organizations earlier this year that Mr. Wolfowitz had let top ethics officials handle Ms. Riza's transfer. These were contradicted by some of the ethics officials, who said they had not been involved in the pay increase that raised her salary to $193,590 from $132,660.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz's reaction to the board's announcement was muted but defiant. A statement from his office said he ''welcomes the decision of the board to move forward and resolve this very important issue.'' Bank officials said the board had discussed the possibility of rendering some kind of verdict on Mr. Wolfowitz's conduct on the matter of Ms. Riza as early as next week, accompanied perhaps by a larger assessment of his tenure at the bank.</p>
        <p>But the board members were reportedly divided about whether a gesture of no confidence was the right strategy.</p>
        <p>Officials familiar with the board's deliberations, speaking anonymously because the issues were supposed to be confidential, said that some directors from Europe and Asia favored a tough rebuke, but that representatives from the United States, Canada and Japan were resisting that approach.</p>
        <p>Board members from Latin America were described as favoring Mr. Wolfowitz's departure, whereas African leaders are known to have mixed views. African leaders have been grateful that Mr. Wolfowitz has increased aid to their region. But they also fear that European antagonism toward him could jeopardize their future support from the bank.</p>
        <p>European officials said that British, French, German, Dutch and Nordic leaders feared a confrontation with the United States over Mr. Wolfowitz, who has received almost daily words of support from the White House this past week.</p>
        <p>The Europeans' hope, according to various officials, is that a delay by the executive board, coupled with its widening investigation, could force the Bush administration to drop its support, perhaps persuading him to leave voluntarily.</p>
        <p>''The steady view of the Europeans, led by the Germans, is that Wolfowitz's position is untenable,'' said a senior European official. ''They know that people at the Treasury Department agree, but that it will take time to convince George Bush. If the Europeans force the issue now, it becomes a clash.''</p>
        <p>Several bank officials said the situation was extremely delicate because Mr. Bush would not want an ouster of a onetime pillar of the administration at a time when Attorney General Alberto Gonzales is also under fire.</p>
        <p>As a result, this official said, it could take some weeks for Mr. Wolfowitz's fate to be decided. ''What all sides are doing is playing for time,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Another factor, bank officials said, was the importance of discussing with the White House the question of whether Mr. Bush would be able to name a successor to Mr. Wolfowitz if he leaves before the end of his five-year term. While it is customary for the American president to name the leader of the bank, European leaders have been seeking a reconsideration of that practice.</p>
        <p>Officials also noted the bank's need to raise $30 billion from wealthy countries over the next three years for low-cost loans and grants to the world's poorest countries.</p>
        <p>So far, the wealthy countries have pledged the money, but all have fallen behind in fulfilling their commitments, and there are fears that Mr. Wolfowitz's difficulties may make raising the money harder, especially in Europe.</p>
        <p>A large amount of the discontent over Mr. Wolfowitz has focused on his top aides, Robin Cleveland and Kevin Kellems, both of whom worked with him on defense issues in the Bush administration. Bank officials have claimed that they have been given too much power and that their salaries, in excess of $200,000, are too high.</p>
        <p>But other complaints focus on other aides, including Juan J. Daboub, a former finance minister of El Salvador who is one of two top deputies to Mr. Wolfowitz; and Ana Palacio, a former foreign minister of Spain, who is general counsel and vice president.</p>
        <p>Documents have surfaced indicating that Mr. Daboub recently omitted language supporting contraceptives on family planning programs in Madagascar, and bank officials charge that he has been trying to undercut such programs for poor countries in general.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daboub, in an e-mail message to The New York Times, denied that he was seeking to change the policies. Mr. Wolfowitz gave similar assurances in a meeting of his own vice presidents earlier this week, bank officials said. But they said this matter would now be investigated by the bank's board.</p>
        <p>In addition, the bank's staff association asked the bank's integrity unit earlier this year to investigate the matter of Ms. Riza's salary. But the head of the unit sent an e-mail message back to the staff that investigating Mr. Wolfowitz's office was beyond its jurisdiction. This issue, too, is to be investigated by the bank's board, officials said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
