<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting Out of Hedge Funds</title>
    <meta content="21offline" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/business/21offline.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841750"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S OFFLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organic Foods and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bloomberg Markets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Spectrem Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Smart Money (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fast Company (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">US Green Building Council</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Black Enterprise Magazine</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Glamour (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strasburg, Jenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paskin, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Konrad, Walecia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Paul B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3DB163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting Out of Hedge Funds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Getting Out of Hedge Funds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL B. BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Paul B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Offline column; Jenny Strasburg writes in Bloomberg Markets that Americans with net worth of at least $25 million, excluding value of their primary homes, reduced their exposure to hedge funds in 2006; Spectrem Group figures show some 38 percent of wealthy investors surveyed had money in hedge funds in 2005 last year, and amount of money that wealthy investors had in hedge funds fell by even greater percentage; average balance, which was $2.8 million in 2005, was $1.6 million last year, 43 percent decline; Janet Paskin writes in Smart Money that mutual funds with highest turnover, managers who trade more than 150 percent of their portfolio a year, do better than those who hold funds by about 2 percentage points per year; Walecia Konrad writes in Fast Company that commercial real estate sector is hot, but 'sustainable construction' that is environmentally conscious is even hotter; estimated 5 percent of all new construction received certification from US Green Building Council last year, and within three years 10 percent of all new commercial construction is expected to be sustainable; Black Enterprise reports African-Americans are more likely to be dedicated buyers of organic foods than their white counterparts; Glamour magazine, in anticipation of Earth Day, breaks issue into bite-size pieces on environmental degradation and protection; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to hedge funds, do the extremely rich know more than the rest of us?</p>
        <p>While institutions are increasing their holdings in hedge funds -- and some of the largest hedge funds are planning to sell shares to an eagerly awaiting public -- the wealthiest Americans have been bailing out, Bloomberg Markets reports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to hedge funds, do the extremely rich know more than the rest of us?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to hedge funds, do the extremely rich know more than the rest of us?</p>
        <p>While institutions are increasing their holdings in hedge funds -- and some of the largest hedge funds are planning to sell shares to an eagerly awaiting public -- the wealthiest Americans have been bailing out, Bloomberg Markets reports.</p>
        <p>''Americans with a net worth of at least $25 million, excluding the value of their primary homes, reduced their exposure to hedge funds in 2006,'' Jenny Strasburg writes, citing research by the Spectrem Group, a consulting firm that specializes in retirement savings and investing by the affluent.</p>
        <p>Some 38 percent of the wealthy investors surveyed had money in hedge funds in 2005. That number fell to 27 percent last year, and the amount of money that wealthy investors had in hedge funds fell by an even greater percentage. The average balance, which was $2.8 million in 2005, was just $1.6 million last year, a 43 percent decline.</p>
        <p>''What some individuals say is that hedge funds have become too risky, and it's unclear to them where the returns are being generated,'' said George H. Walper Jr., president of Spectrem.</p>
        <p>MANIC MONEY -- The traditional wisdom is that you do not want to invest in a mutual fund that trades frequently, because each trade adds a commission, which is deducted from potential returns. That is one main reason that most financial experts recommend a buy-and-hold investment approach.</p>
        <p>''But some overlooked research from the University of Maryland notes a surprising exception,'' Janet Paskin writes in Smart Money. ''Funds with the highest turnover, that is, managers who trade more than 150 percent of their portfolio a year, do better than their slowpoke peers by about two percentage points a year.''</p>
        <p>These funds overcome the higher costs they incur by following specific strategies -- like momentum investing -- and make large sector bets.</p>
        <p>But in addition to higher trading costs, high-turnover funds have another drawback -- potentially higher tax bills for investors. One potential way around the problem is to keep these funds in an individual retirement account or another tax-advantaged account.</p>
        <p>GOING GREEN -- The commercial real estate sector is hot, but ''sustainable construction'' that is environmentally conscious is even hotter, Walecia Konrad writes in Fast Company.</p>
        <p>An estimated 5 percent of all new construction received certification from the U.S. Green Building Council last year, and within three years 10 percent of all new commercial construction is expected to be sustainable.</p>
        <p>The easiest way to invest in this phenomenon is, of course, through real estate investment trusts that are committed to buying new or renovated green buildings.</p>
        <p>But as Ms. Konrad notes, two of the greenest REITs have been acquired: Arden Realty by GE Real Estate and Equity Office Properties by the Blackstone Group.</p>
        <p>One REIT she singled out for investment is Liberty Property Trust, which is expected to increase the number of green properties it owns.</p>
        <p>GOING ORGANIC -- ''African-Americans are more likely to be dedicated buyers of organic foods than their white counterparts,'' Black Enterprise reports.</p>
        <p>Citing research by the Hartman Group, a health-and-wellness research and consulting firm, Brenda Porter writes that ''African-Americans are 24 percent more likely to be core organic consumers than members of the general population.'' She adds that ''the findings debunk the myth that only educated whites with high incomes are purchasing these pricier items.''</p>
        <p>FINAL TAKE -- It is difficult to grasp a concept as complex as environmental degradation/protection. In anticipation of Earth Day, which is tomorrow, Glamour breaks the issue into bite-size pieces.</p>
        <p>The examples include: ''10 times as much energy is wasted when you use a computer screen saver instead of using sleep mode''; three-quarters of the electricity used to power a television is used when it is plugged in but not turned on; and ''14 plastic grocery bags contain enough petroleum to fuel a car for a mile.''</p>
        <p>PAUL B. BROWN</p>
        <p>WHAT'S OFFLINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
