<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Voyage to the Bottom of the League</title>
    <meta content="21leitch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/opinion/21leitch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841777"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Celtics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leitch, Will</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oden, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durant, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Boston Celtics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Franchises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Franchises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Oden, Greg</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bird, Larry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Voyage to the Bottom of the League</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Voyage to the Bottom of the League</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Will Leitch</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leitch, Will</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Author Will Leitch Op-Ed article holds that it appears that Boston Celtics and several other teams tried to finish season with worst record so they would have best opportunity to draft college superstars Greg Oden and Kevin Durant; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Boston Celtics are one of the most storied franchises in all of sport and, more to the point, a multimillion-dollar operation. They sell tickets, they license merchandise, they serve as a cultural touchstone in one of our country's most historic and thriving cities. This season, the Celtics paid 12 tall men a total of nearly $63 million to run up and down a court for 48 minutes two or three nights a week for six months and, theoretically, entertain us.</p>
        <p>And for the last two months of the regular season, which ended Wednesday, it appeared that they tried to lose. The crazy thing is that their fans, the people shelling out the cash to make all this happen, seemed perfectly O.K. with this.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If a fan doesn’t root for his team to win, who is he, exactly?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Boston Celtics are one of the most storied franchises in all of sport and, more to the point, a multimillion-dollar operation. They sell tickets, they license merchandise, they serve as a cultural touchstone in one of our country's most historic and thriving cities. This season, the Celtics paid 12 tall men a total of nearly $63 million to run up and down a court for 48 minutes two or three nights a week for six months and, theoretically, entertain us.</p>
        <p>And for the last two months of the regular season, which ended Wednesday, it appeared that they tried to lose. The crazy thing is that their fans, the people shelling out the cash to make all this happen, seemed perfectly O.K. with this.</p>
        <p>The Celtics aren't alone; one could make a strong argument that the Milwaukee Bucks, the Memphis Grizzlies and the Atlanta Hawks fell over one another to do the same thing, a quixotic quest to rise below everyone else.</p>
        <p>The reason takes the form of two men: Greg Oden and Kevin Durant, a pair of spectral talents capable of changing the fortunes of even the most flaccid franchise for the next 10 years. Oden and Durant are all but certain to be the top two choices in the N.B.A. draft in June -- and the teams with the worst records have the best opportunity to employ them. (Yes, these two are causing several global corporations to turn their entire operations upside down, but they have yet to transform their labor into payment. Professional sports are odd.)</p>
        <p>It is easy to understand what might compel a team to strive for such a high standard of losing: the people who run these franchises are in constant fear of losing their jobs, and it's difficult to fire a guy who just drafted a superstar.</p>
        <p>Teams interested in setting themselves up to lose enjoy a variety of options, from placing their best players on the injured list to playing mismatched lineups designed to mesh poorly. (Tanking rarely involves anything as unseemly as purposely missed shots; that would run contrary to athletes' DNA.) What's difficult to comprehend is why a real fan, someone with a Larry Bird poster on the wall and a child named Red, could consciously cheer for his or her team to lose -- pragmatism notwithstanding.</p>
        <p>The temptation is real; late-season games for non-contenders are meaningless anyway, just one more loss added to a season full of them. But being a sports fan requires a finite amount of time and dedication. An N.B.A. team plays only 82 games a season, 82 times when you are faced with the fundamental moment of sports fandom: Will my team win, or lose?</p>
        <p>The beauty of sports is not in its grays; when my team wins, I am happy, and when they lose, I am sad. Introducing some sort of long-term plan and futures market to something as basic as a single basketball game is the opposite of what being a sports fan is all about. If you are sitting down to watch your team for two-and-a-half hours, and you are rooting for your team to lose, I question just how much a fan of that team you really are.</p>
        <p>Listen, I understand. I am a fan of the Arizona Cardinals, a wretched football franchise that hasn't played a meaningful game in November or December in a decade. Every year, I try to talk myself into accepting the losses, hoping they will allow the team to move up one more spot in the next draft, falling prey once again to the fan's fallacy that his/her team is perpetually just one  player  away.</p>
        <p>And then the ball is kicked off, and any context that might surround an individual game melts away. What, am I supposed to cheer for my guys to fumble? Trust me, they do plenty of that without my help. I am not thinking about the team the Arizona Cardinals could potentially be, if they just made the right pick at the right time; I am thinking about what they are, and that I want them to win. Because I am a fan. And if a fan doesn't root for his team to win, who is he, exactly?</p>
        <p>The N.B.A. playoffs begin today, so we have the welcome opportunity to see fans, at last, cheering for their teams rather than against them. The favorites are the Dallas Mavericks and the Phoenix Suns, two teams that have had just one top three draft pick between them in the last 20 years. They seem to be doing just fine. Maybe it helped having fans who, you know, actually wanted them to win.</p>
        <p>Just a theory.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Will Leitch is the author of ''Catch'' and ''Life as a Loser'' and the editor of the Web site Deadspin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Will Leitch is the author of ''Catch'' and ''Life as a Loser'' and the editor of the Web site Deadspin.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
