<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Old-Fashioned Guys For an Old-Fashioned Job</title>
    <meta content="21gels" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/nyregion/21gels.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841804"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Empire State Building (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Old-Fashioned Guys For an Old-Fashioned Job</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Some Old-Fashioned Guys for an Old-Fashioned Job</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before dawn yesterday, two electricians and a supervisor changed colors on the Empire State Building's north face during the test of new light-emitting diodes, or L.E.D.'s, to provide a visual comparison. To do it, they climbed out office windows to switch the colored filters called gels atop floodlights installed on the parapets.</p>
        <p>Changing the gels: it has been a way of life for maintenance workers at the building since its lighting was colorized in 1976, when red, white and blue celebrated the nation's Bicentennial. It will soon be a thing of the past, as the building installs a new, high-tech lighting system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Changing colored filters has been a way of life for maintenance workers at the Empire State Building since 1976, but that will soon be over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before dawn yesterday, two electricians and a supervisor changed colors on the Empire State Building's north face during the test of new light-emitting diodes, or L.E.D.'s, to provide a visual comparison. To do it, they climbed out office windows to switch the colored filters called gels atop floodlights installed on the parapets.</p>
        <p>Changing the gels: it has been a way of life for maintenance workers at the building since its lighting was colorized in 1976, when red, white and blue celebrated the nation's Bicentennial. It will soon be a thing of the past, as the building installs a new, high-tech lighting system.</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon a crew of five showed how it has been done for years, installing 15 blue gels in a bank of floodlights on the 72nd floor.</p>
        <p>The gels -- 30-inch-wide circles of weather-resistant Lexan plastic -- are the size of delivery pizzas and are designed to snap onto the 3-foot-tall drumlike floodlights with their metal halide lamps.</p>
        <p>Changing the gels is labor-intensive, requiring the effort of six workers toiling for six hours, while the lights themselves are electricity hogs. The new light-emitting diodes will give off less heat and last far longer than the metal halide lamps.</p>
        <p>''And you can program the lighting patterns on a keyboard,'' said Hani J. Salama, the building's director of operations.</p>
        <p>Though they need some maintenance, the new L.E.D.'s would significantly reduce the electricians' exposure to driving rain and slippery ice.</p>
        <p>Crews are accustomed to snow that floats heavenward in updrafts, and drifts that bury the building's parapets to the top of the floodlights.</p>
        <p>In early evening, bats have sometimes congregated on high, and ''there are also hawk attacks,'' said Bill Tortorelli, the building's 63-year-old chief electrician.</p>
        <p>Several electricians recalled the time a few years ago when they counted 21 hawks wheeling around the building; one of them dive-bombed, but missed, the workers, said Jake Nouel, 54, an electrician who has been changing the gels for 27 years.</p>
        <p>Then there was the time that ''one of the workers lost his teeth in the snow on the parapet, and we had to wait for the thaw to find them,'' Mr. Tortorelli recalled.</p>
        <p>After the L.E.D. installation is complete, most likely in 2008, the electricians will be reassigned to other maintenance duties, Mr. Tortorelli said, adding, ''No one will lose a job, because there's so much to do inside the building.''</p>
        <p>But, in a funny way, they will miss the gels. ''The views of the city, the fact that these colors were important to New York, and that we had a part in it -- well,'' Mr. Nouel said, ''it was fun, even when the hawks came at us.''</p>
        <p>He sighed. ''We'll do other things now, so it will be different. But it won't be as glamorous.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
