<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Labor Rights Issues Are Stalling Trade Pacts</title>
    <meta content="21trade" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/business/21trade.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slave Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Colombia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Panama</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rangel, Charles B (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisman, Steven R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Labor Rights Issues Are Stalling Trade Pacts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Labor Rights Issues Are Stalling Trade Pacts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hopes for bipartisan agreement between Bush administration and Congress leading to approval of several pending trade pacts have dissolved in burst of charges and countercharges over issue of labor rights; earlier optimism has vanished and been replaced by acrimony reflected in sharp exchange between business groups, who are supporting administration, and Rep Charles B Rangel, who is chairman of House Ways and Means Committee; failure to approve four trade deals with Colombia, Panama, Peru and South Korea could end possibility of trade talks for rest of Bush's term and deal a blow to any chances of global trade accord; at issue is Democratic demand that pending trade deals with four countries include provision guaranteeing certain rights for labor in trading partner countries, including ban of child and slave labor and right to organize; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hopes for a bipartisan agreement between the Bush administration and Congress leading to approval of several pending trade pacts have dissolved in a burst of charges and countercharges over the issue of labor rights.</p>
        <p>Administration officials and leading Democrats said there was still a chance for a compromise that could clear the way for passage of the trade deals and even for extension of President Bush's authority to negotiate a global trade accord and receive an expedited vote in Congress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several pending trade pacts have dissolved in a burst of charges and countercharges over the issue of labor rights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hopes for a bipartisan agreement between the Bush administration and Congress leading to approval of several pending trade pacts have dissolved in a burst of charges and countercharges over the issue of labor rights.</p>
        <p>Administration officials and leading Democrats said there was still a chance for a compromise that could clear the way for passage of the trade deals and even for extension of President Bush's authority to negotiate a global trade accord and receive an expedited vote in Congress.</p>
        <p>But the optimism heard last month has vanished and been replaced by acrimony reflected in a sharp exchange this week between business groups, who were supporting the administration, and Representative Charles B. Rangel, the New York Democrat who is chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee.</p>
        <p>''I really thought that everyone was on board with this,'' Mr. Rangel said, referring to his statements last month that the administration and Republicans in Congress were open to labor guarantees.</p>
        <p>''But there are some people,'' Mr. Rangel said, ''who hate unions so much, they can't see their way clear to supporting this provision.''</p>
        <p>A failure to approve the four trade deals -- with Colombia, Panama, Peru and South Korea -- could end the possibility of trade negotiations for the rest of Mr. Bush's term and deal a blow to any chances of a global trade accord.</p>
        <p>Without an agreement in the Democratic-led Congress on the president's so-called fast-track negotiating authority, which expires June 30, the administration would not be able to bring any global trade deal before lawmakers and get an up-or-down vote.</p>
        <p>Trade negotiations among 180 countries have been foundering since last summer, but the United States has joined with Europe, India and Brazil to try to revive them. More talks are expected next week in Washington, but trade officials said that the impasse between the Democrats and the administration on labor rights has clouded their chances.</p>
        <p>At issue is the Democratic demand that pending trade deals with Colombia, Panama, Peru and South Korea include a provision guaranteeing certain rights for labor in the trading partner countries, including a ban on child and slave labor and the right to organize.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Democrats want the accords to endorse general labor protections adopted by the International Labor Organization, like the right to organize.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration, backed by business groups, contends that this Democratic demand could lead to trading partners suing to overturn basic American labor practices, like teenage summer jobs or work on farms, or the practice in some American states of prisoners making consumer goods.</p>
        <p>Another fear is that governments in Latin America, perhaps inspired by anti-American figures like President Hugo Chávez of Venezuela, might use trade deals to try to overturn ''right to work'' laws in states, which bar employers from requiring workers to join unions.</p>
        <p>''Subjecting our labor system to foreign challenge is simply not something to which we can agree,'' said John Engler, a former Republican governor of Michigan who is president of the National Association of Manufacturers.</p>
        <p>''For state constitutions or laws to be subject to a foreign nation's challenge would be unacceptable,'' Mr. Engler said.</p>
        <p>The United States Chamber of Commerce sided with Mr. Engler but suggested that there was still a possibility of compromise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel and other Democrats said that the concern of Mr. Engler and other business leaders was bogus, noting that under the Democratic proposal only those laws that have an impact on trade might be challenged.</p>
        <p>He added that he was ''astounded'' that Mr. Engler would ''go to such lengths to jeopardize the hard work of so many in Congress and the administration who are negotiating these issues.''</p>
        <p>Republicans in Congress have tried to stay out of the fight between Mr. Rangel and the business groups. Both Representative Jim McCrery, a Louisiana Republican who is the ranking Republican member of House Ways and Means, and Senator Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, ranking Republican of the Senate Finance Committee, have said they were convinced that a compromise could be reached if the attacks stop.</p>
        <p>Administration officials have not spoken about Mr. Rangel's dispute with the National Association of Manufacturers, other than to say that they agree with the business groups.</p>
        <p>Organized labor sides with the Democrats, but officials at the A.F.L.-C.I.O. say that while the Republican fear of an effort to change American labor laws is far-fetched, there would be an advantage to the International Labor Organization putting pressure on the United States to change some laws.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day, no American change in U.S. labor laws is going to come through a bilateral trade agreement with Peru,'' said Thea Lee, chief international economist of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. ''But putting these provisions into a bilateral agreement does put additional pressure on the United States government.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lee and others noted that past trade agreements, like one with Jordan signed at the end of the Clinton administration and approved during President Bush's first year in office, had labor provisions that are similar to the ones the Democrats are seeking.</p>
        <p>Representative Sander Levin, a Michigan Democrat who is chairman of the Ways and Means trade subcommittee, said the administration's concern was ''a false issue'' because only governments could bring challenges to American labor laws.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Levin said the Democrats were still pressing for environmental protections and other issue to be put in the trade deals before Congress.</p>
        <p>''I think some in the administration doubt that Democrats are united on this,'' he said. ''We believe that putting worker rights in to trade agreements is a critical piece of shaping globalization in the world today.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
