<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Key Verdict Does Not End Corruption Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="21judge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/nyregion/21judge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hynes, Charles J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E7DB163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Key Verdict Does Not End Corruption Inquiry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Key Verdict Does Not End Corruption Inquiry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brick, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four years ago, the Brooklyn district attorney, Charles J. Hynes, turned against the single-party system he had navigated for decades, vowing to prove that seats of power at the courthouse were bought and sold for envelopes full of cash.</p>
        <p>Since then, he has earned convictions of the former Brooklyn Democratic party leader, Clarence Norman Jr., on charges of extortion, solicitation of illegal contributions and theft of $5,000 from his re-election committee. Those verdicts cost Mr. Norman the Assembly seat he had held for 23 years and control of the biggest Democratic organization east of Chicago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After winning a bribery conviction, Brooklyn district attorney Charles J. Hynes vowed to finish out his investigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four years ago, the Brooklyn district attorney, Charles J. Hynes, turned against the single-party system he had navigated for decades, vowing to prove that seats of power at the courthouse were bought and sold for envelopes full of cash.</p>
        <p>Since then, he has earned convictions of the former Brooklyn Democratic party leader, Clarence Norman Jr., on charges of extortion, solicitation of illegal contributions and theft of $5,000 from his re-election committee. Those verdicts cost Mr. Norman the Assembly seat he had held for 23 years and control of the biggest Democratic organization east of Chicago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hynes also secured an indictment on grand larceny and other charges, though they were later dismissed, against the Brooklyn Democrats' longtime executive director, Jeffrey C. Feldman; convicted or won guilty pleas from a divorce lawyer, Paul Siminovsky, and several courthouse assistants; and put judges on notice that their chambers could be wired for surveillance.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Mr. Hynes brought the investigation full circle by winning a bribery conviction against Gerald P. Garson, the former State Supreme Court justice who had offered Mr. Hynes his first big break in the broader inquiry.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Hynes vowed to see his investigation through, to show not just that a judge could be manipulated for money, but that a seat on the bench could be purchased from the Brooklyn Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>''It's been a long road, which is not finished,'' Mr. Hynes said in a telephone interview. ''It's now up to Norman and Garson to do something about the predicament they find themselves in.''</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, an appeals court allowed Mr. Norman to remain free while pursuing an appeal. Mr. Garson, who is being treated for cancer, has been ordered to report to a probation officer on Monday and to appear for sentencing on June 5. He faces a maximum sentence of 15 years in prison.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hynes has maintained that the two men could show that cash payments to the Democratic Party secured seats on the bench, a system the district attorney once called ''nothing less than a sham.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hynes said Mr. Garson remains a potential source of information in the broader inquiry. ''I would hope over the weekend that he's going to be thinking about this,'' Mr. Hynes said, ''that he has a choice.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Norman, the man at the center of the investigation, has said through his lawyers that he has no information to share with prosecutors because he never received payments from judges or judicial candidates. He has received three sentences, from one and three years in prison each, on his convictions, all to run consecutively, and has been acquitted in a fourth case. He is free on $110,000 bail by order of the Appellate Division of the Second Judicial Department.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for Mr. Garson, Michael S. Washor, could not reached by telephone yesterday. Anthony L. Ricco, a lawyer for Mr. Norman, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>At this point in the investigation, each conviction and sentence represents a missed opportunity, a potential cooperating witness gone silently to prison. And although some unrelated corruption cases await resolution, the bribery verdict against Mr. Garson closed the last publicly disclosed case in the judgeships-for-sale investigation.</p>
        <p>Questions remain concerning Mr. Feldman's role in the inquiry. He has signed a cooperation agreement with prosecutors, but Mr. Feldman has little obvious incentive to be of much help, since they have dropped all charges against him.</p>
        <p>For years, names of sitting judges have appeared in news accounts as suspects under investigation on suspicion that they bought their seats. Lawyers for Mr. Norman have accused Mr. Hynes of leaking the names to ratchet up the pressure, and the district attorney's office has denied the accusation. Most recently, in January, The Village Voice published a 4,700-word article detailing what the publication described as one judge's purchased path to power.</p>
        <p>As the pressure mounts on Mr. Hynes to make his big case, the district attorney's original leads are nearing five years old. Ending the case against Mr. Garson is a neat bit of symmetry: It was Mr. Garson who, when confronted with bribery evidence in early 2003, first told prosecutors of a scheme to sell judgeships and then agreed to wear a wire. In about five years on the bench, Mr. Garson, 74, had handled some 1,100 divorces, deciding child custody cases and dividing families' financial assets. On surveillance recordings, he has been seen accepting Dominican cigars and cash from Mr. Siminovsky.</p>
        <p>The fallout from the case against Mr. Garson has been smaller than expected, a spokesman for the court system, David Bookstaver, said yesterday. The state's chief administrative judge for matrimonial cases, Jacqueline W. Silbermann, received about 50 motions to reopen cases that had been handled by Mr. Garson, Mr. Bookstaver said. Of those, three or four were granted a hearing and eventually were settled, he said.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Mr. Norman was detained for a few hours as his third sentence was imposed. Calling him a ''common thief'' in court documents, prosecutors sought unsuccessfully to prevent his release.</p>
        <p>''He thinks this is a joke,'' Mr. Hynes said yesterday. ''I believe that he has information that is critical to this investigation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hynes paused to reconsider that assessment.</p>
        <p>''They're not critical to my investigation,'' he said of Mr. Norman and Mr. Garson, ''but they are substantial parts.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
