<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Benefit From Brodeur's Return to Form</title>
    <meta content="21devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/sports/hockey/21devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tampa Bay Lightning</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brodeur, Martin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE1D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Benefit From Brodeur's Return to Form</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Devils Benefit From Brodeur’s Return to Form</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur often had to drop to the ice Friday night, collecting snow on the seat of his black shorts while making one big save after another. The Tampa Bay Lightning made him scramble again.</p>
        <p>There was a difference, however, between this game and the previous four of the series: Brodeur stopped everything, often spectacularly, leading the Devils to a 3-0 victory before an adoring crowd of 18,096 at Continental Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Goaltender Martin Brodeur stopped everything, and often spectacularly, leading the Devils to a victory and a 3-2 lead in the best-of-seven series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur often had to drop to the ice Friday night, collecting snow on the seat of his black shorts while making one big save after another. The Tampa Bay Lightning made him scramble again.</p>
        <p>There was a difference, however, between this game and the previous four of the series: Brodeur stopped everything, often spectacularly, leading the Devils to a 3-0 victory before an adoring crowd of 18,096 at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>''Marty Brodeur is the great goaltender he is because of games like this -- when he finds a way to raise himself to a level that's needed to win,'' said Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' general manager and interim coach.</p>
        <p>Brodeur, who had allowed 12 goals in the first four games, made 31 saves as the Devils took a 3-2 lead in the best-of-seven series. Game 6 will be Sunday in Tampa, Fla.</p>
        <p>Brodeur posted the 22nd playoff shutout of his 13-season career. He needs one more to tie Patrick Roy for the most in N.H.L. history. The victory also was the 92nd in the playoffs for Brodeur, who tied Grant Fuhr for second place on the career list.</p>
        <p>Reminded of those milestones, Brodeur said, ''It's all about winning in the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>He attempted to share the credit with his teammates, often beginning answers about the way he played with the word ''we.'' But he also said he knew that those 12 goals he had allowed did not reflect well on him.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to hear it one way or another,'' he said. ''I know I'm not going to slip because people are watching me all the time.''</p>
        <p>Despite taking only 14 shots at Tampa Bay goaltender Johan Holmqvist, the Devils had goals from the rookie defenseman Andy Greene and right wing Brian Gionta, then an empty-netter from Scott Gomez.</p>
        <p>Then, as if to punctuate the victory, forward Mike Rupp decisively won a fight with Lightning left wing Andre Roy, tearing off his helmet, landing several overhand punches, then pulling off Roy's jersey and shoulder pads with one big tug.</p>
        <p>''Score an empty-net goal, and you know that's coming from a mile away,'' Rupp said of the fight.</p>
        <p>Rupp, a fourth-line wing, also got the Devils rolling. Zach Parise and Patrik Elias broke skate blades in the first period, forcing the Devils to shuffle their lines. Rupp ended up skating with Gionta and Gomez.</p>
        <p>With Lightning defenseman Filip Kuba tailing him, Rupp swept around the goal, pausing to fake a wraparound shot.</p>
        <p>Rupp then said he heard someone shouting at him from the blue line. It was Greene.</p>
        <p>With Gomez pestering Holmqvist, Rupp passed to Greene, who took a slap shot. The sliding puck did not hit anything until it ticked O'Brien's right skate and went in. It was the first playoff goal for the 24-year-old Greene, who played in his first N.H.L. game Jan. 12.</p>
        <p>''The offensive side is always a bonus,'' Greene said.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the period, Greene dived to deflect a shot taken by Martin St. Louis, who had formed a formidable two-on-one with center Vincent Lecavalier after a Devils power play. The puck never reached Brodeur.</p>
        <p>Holmqvist was not so magnificent. Midway through the second period, Gionta and Elias cruised toward him. Gionta fired a hard wrist shot that Gionta said hit Holmqvist in his left arm.</p>
        <p>Holmqvist looked at his glove. The puck was not there.</p>
        <p>The puck trickled past Holmqvist and wobbled into the goal. Gionta had his second goal in two games and his third goal of the series. Tampa Bay Coach John Tortorella watched a replay of the goal on a big screen and smirked.</p>
        <p>Gionta said, ''You have a lot more room to breathe with a 2-0 lead, and Marty played great.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur took over from there. Dan Boyle made a spin move from a face-off circle and shot, but Brodeur stopped the puck with his right pad. Later in the second period, he poke-checked the puck away from St. Louis. Another shot hit the goal post.</p>
        <p>''The guy sets the bar so high,'' Gomez said. ''He's been fine in the playoffs, but tonight he was awesome. He made the big saves. It was vintage Marty.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
