<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>French Voters Feeling Frustrated Despite a Not-So-Bad Economy</title>
    <meta content="21charts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/business/21charts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFF THE CHARTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chirac, Jacques (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Chirac, Jacques</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DB163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>French Voters Feeling Frustrated Despite a Not-So-Bad Economy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">French Voters Feeling Frustrated Despite a Not-So-Bad Economy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Floyd Norris Off the Charts column on French economy for last 12 years under Pres Jacques Chirac, who is leaving office, and as French presidential election begins; says unemployment remains high, but is lower than it was when Chirac took office; holds among people 25 to 49 years old, unemployment has fallen to 7.6 percent from more than 10 percent when Chirac took office; holds rate among those under 25 is still more than 21 percent; says businesses routinely denounce 35-hour workweek, approved in 1998 as way of creating more jobs, but any efforts to repeal it would ignite labor unrest; says there is widespread feeling that country has not done much to confront its real problems, which include two-tier system that leaves many with secure jobs and guaranteed pensions while others, particularly younger people and those from poor suburbs of Paris, have trouble finding work; says all major candidates have come up with proposed ways to lower unemployment, but have been reluctant to discuss how to pay for them; holds balance-of-payments surplus Chirac inherited has turned into deficit; holds economy grew at average rate of 2.1 percent per year; says national debt has risen sharply under Chirac, from less than half of gross domestic product to nearly two-thirds; graphs (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE French presidential election, which has its first round tomorrow, features a dozen candidates, none of whom seem to have much good to say about the performance of the man who is leaving office after 12 years in power, Jacques Chirac.</p>
        <p>A look at the economic performance of the country under Mr. Chirac does not easily explain the antipathy. Unemployment remains high, but it is lower than it was when he took office. Economic growth has lagged that of Britain and the United States, but it has outpaced that of Germany.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A look at the economic performance of the country under Jacques Chirac does not easily explain the antipathy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE French presidential election, which has its first round tomorrow, features a dozen candidates, none of whom seem to have much good to say about the performance of the man who is leaving office after 12 years in power, Jacques Chirac.</p>
        <p>A look at the economic performance of the country under Mr. Chirac does not easily explain the antipathy. Unemployment remains high, but it is lower than it was when he took office. Economic growth has lagged that of Britain and the United States, but it has outpaced that of Germany.</p>
        <p>But there is a widespread feeling that the country has not done much to confront its real problems, which include a two-tier system that leaves many with secure jobs and guaranteed pensions while others -- particularly younger people and those from the poor suburbs of Paris -- have trouble finding work.</p>
        <p>All the major candidates have come up with proposed ways to lower unemployment, but have been reluctant to discuss how to pay for them. Talk of reform tends to be gentle, with many in France fearful that reforms could lead to dismantling the system that has promised them good retirement benefits. But at the same time, they are concerned about France's ability to compete if it does not change. The balance-of-payments surplus Mr. Chirac inherited has turned into a deficit, albeit a much smaller one than that of the United States.</p>
        <p>Instead, much of the debate has centered on issues of national pride and identity.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow's voting will narrow the field to two. The favorites to survive to the second round are Nicolas Sarkozy, the former interior minister who famously called young Arab rioters ''scum,'' and Ségolène Royal, the Socialist candidate who has pushed for government subsidies to hire unemployed youths.</p>
        <p>A centrist challenger, François Bayrou, is also given a chance to slip into the top two, and some think the right-winger Jean-Marie Le Pen could confound the experts by getting into the runoff this time as he did in 2002.</p>
        <p>One reason for the hesitancy to offer really specific programs has been France's national debt, which has risen sharply under Mr. Chirac, from less than half of gross domestic product to nearly two-thirds. That is about the same figure as in the United States, but far higher than Germany, where debt is about 40 percent of G.D.P.</p>
        <p>Among people 25 to 49 years old, French figures show that unemployment has fallen to 7.6 percent from more than 10 percent when Mr. Chirac took over. But the rate among those under 25 is still more than 21 percent. Businesses routinely denounce the 35-hour workweek, approved in 1998 as a way of creating more jobs, but any efforts to repeal it would ignite labor unrest.</p>
        <p>During Mr. Chirac's terms, the French economy grew at an average rate of 2.1 percent a year, far below the 2.8 percent rate in Britain but surpassing the 1.5 percent rate in Germany.</p>
        <p>As a result, the per capita G.D.P. in France came to $36,463 last year. That is only 82 percent of the comparable figure in the United States, and 93 percent that of Britain, but it is higher than the figure in Germany.</p>
        <p>OFF THE CHARTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
