<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fears of Fraud Grow Before Nigerian Vote</title>
    <meta content="21nigeria" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/world/africa/21nigeria.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nigeria</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Polgreen, Lydia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Nigeria</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Obasanjo, Olusegun</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Abubakar, Atiku</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DB163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="426" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fears of Fraud Grow Before Nigerian Vote</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fears of Fraud Grow Before Nigerian Vote</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYDIA POLGREEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Polgreen, Lydia</byline>
      <dateline>KANO, Nigeria, April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Election officials in Nigeria deny opposition party's allegation that soldiers had seized truckload of ballots that had already been filled out in favor of governing party's presidential candidate; allegation raises fears that Nigeria's presidential election on April 21 will be marred by same kinds of irregularities that plagued recent state elections; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An opposition party claimed Friday that soldiers in northern Nigeria had seized a truckload of ballots that had already been filled out in favor of the governing party's presidential candidate, raising fears that Nigeria's presidential election on Saturday would be marred by the same kinds of irregularities that plagued state elections last week.</p>
        <p>Election officials denied the allegation, saying in a televised news conference that no one could have seized ballots, because the new ones, altered at the last minute to accommodate a candidate who had previously been barred from running, had only just begun arriving in the country after being printed abroad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An opposition party said that soldiers seized ballots that had already been filled out in favor of the governing party’s presidential candidate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An opposition party claimed Friday that soldiers in northern Nigeria had seized a truckload of ballots that had already been filled out in favor of the governing party's presidential candidate, raising fears that Nigeria's presidential election on Saturday would be marred by the same kinds of irregularities that plagued state elections last week.</p>
        <p>Election officials denied the allegation, saying in a televised news conference that no one could have seized ballots, because the new ones, altered at the last minute to accommodate a candidate who had previously been barred from running, had only just begun arriving in the country after being printed abroad.</p>
        <p>With voting scheduled to begin Saturday morning, either situation could be trouble. Distributing 61 million ballots over an area more than twice the size of California in less than 24 hours would be a daunting task in this country with just a handful of airports and rutted, traffic-clogged roads.</p>
        <p>Conversely, if falsely marked ballots were intercepted south of here, in Kaduna, as opposition members claimed, it would be a clear indication that the vote was rigged in advance to secure a victory for the governing People's Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>In a televised speech on Friday, Nigeria's departing president, Olusegun Obasanjo, barred by term limits from running again, said that the state elections held last Saturday had been at least somewhat flawed.</p>
        <p>''The execution was marred here and there in places,'' he said. Urging improvements, he added that ''the world is watching us and we cannot afford to disappoint ourselves, our friends and the world.''</p>
        <p>One senior Western election observer, who was not authorized to speak before the election, said the current confusion raised deep concerns that the outcome of Saturday's vote would lack legitimacy.</p>
        <p>''The whole process is out of whack,'' the observer said.</p>
        <p>Atiku Abubakar, the vice president and the candidate of the Action Congress Party, was removed from the ballot over corruption charges and then reinstated by a court ruling Monday with just days to go before the election.</p>
        <p>Maurice Iwu, chairman of the Independent National Electoral Commission, said new ballots had been printed, but because time was short, the pictures of the candidates were excluded. But he denied that any ballots had been stolen.</p>
        <p>Garba Shehu, Mr. Abubakar's spokesman, said Mr. Abubakar's campaign was preparing for a long legal battle, whatever the outcome of the voting on Saturday.</p>
        <p>''We now have the nightmarish picture that tomorrow will be no different than last Saturday,'' he said, referring to state elections that were marred by widespread irregularities in several states.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
