<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crisp Wins Some Fans With a Leap And a Triple</title>
    <meta content="21curry" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/sports/baseball/21curry.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Crisp, Coco</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E0D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crisp Wins Some Fans With a Leap And a Triple</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Crisp Wins Some Fans With a Leap and a Triple</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coco Crisp is in his second official season as part of the intense Yankees-Red Sox rivalry, but Crisp insisted that he had had insight into the Yankee-Red Sox rivalry for more than 15 years. Crisp played for a team called the Yankees in Sportsmen's Little League in Inglewood, Calif.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry to say we won back-to-back championships as the Yankees,'' Crisp said. ''I kind of came up through that rivalry.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coco Crisp has disappointed the Red Sox while trying to replace Johnny Damon. But he played a key role Friday night in Boston’s comeback victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Coco Crisp is in his second official season as part of the intense Yankees-Red Sox rivalry, but Crisp insisted that he had had insight into the Yankee-Red Sox rivalry for more than 15 years. Crisp played for a team called the Yankees in Sportsmen's Little League in Inglewood, Calif.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry to say we won back-to-back championships as the Yankees,'' Crisp said. ''I kind of came up through that rivalry.''</p>
        <p>When Crisp was asked if there was anything about the skirmishes between the Yankees and the Red Sox that he did not realize before joining Boston, he responded with a story about being a 12-year-old who played for the Yankees, liked the Red Sox and lived about 3,000 miles away from both major league teams.</p>
        <p>As endearing as Crisp's recollections were and as seriously as he thought the little Yankees and the little Red Sox treated their rivalry, it obviously could never be as powerful as the grown-up version. Crisp helped prove that Friday night during a thrilling game, the kind that has become routine for these teams.</p>
        <p>Crisp sliced a two-run triple off Mariano Rivera in the eighth inning to tie the score and the Red Sox went on to beat the Yankees, 7-6, at Fenway Park. Once Crisp reached third, he pumped his fists and flashed a scowl as the fans treated him like David Ortiz after a prodigious homer.</p>
        <p>It has been a long time since Crisp heard that much noise. It would have been difficult to anticipate Crisp's conquering Rivera since he had been 0 for 7 with five strikeouts against the closer. Crisp had studied videotape on Luis Vizcaino, the reliever who preceded Rivera, in the clubhouse, not expecting to face Rivera. But Crisp pounced on an inside cutter and sent it down the right-field line.</p>
        <p>''I got some advice that I'm not going to tell you about,'' Crisp said. ''I think that was the first hit I ever got off him in my career, so that was huge.''</p>
        <p>The always passionate, always demanding Red Sox fans are still waiting for Crisp, 27, to show that he can be as reliable as Johnny Damon. Crisp, who is only 10 for 52 this season, has caused some fans to feel uneasy. Some of that changed when he produced against Rivera. Some of it had already changed because of what Crisp did in the fifth inning.</p>
        <p>Alex Rodriguez, who seems to pound virtually every ball to the fence or over the fence these days, hit one toward center. Crisp hustled back, leaped at the right-field wall and tumbled over it trying to corral Rodriguez's shot.</p>
        <p>While Crisp is listed at 6 feet, he is probably about 5-9. Those three inches might have mattered. Crisp said the ball nicked off his glove before he landed with a thud in the Red Sox' bullpen.</p>
        <p>''It was very scary,'' his teammate Álex Cora said. ''He just disappeared.''</p>
        <p>Crisp said he thought he had stolen a three-run homer from Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>''The guy has been swinging a hot bat,'' Crisp said of Rodriguez. ''He got it so high that I couldn't get to it.''</p>
        <p>The Red Sox fans know Damon, the bearded and long-haired center fielder who helped lead Boston to the World Series title in 2004. Crisp is no Damon -- not now and maybe not ever. Even though the Red Sox fans boo Damon these days, only the most delusional fans would argue that Crisp has been anything close to what Damon was.</p>
        <p>After the Red Sox failed to re-sign Damon after the 2005 season and then watched him sign with the Yankees, they acquired Crisp from the Cleveland Indians and raved about him being younger, sleeker and more inexpensive than Damon. Crisp had an injury-plagued 2006 season, playing 105 games and hitting .264 with 8 homers and 36 runs batted in.</p>
        <p>While Crisp was trying to stay on the field, Damon was one of the main reasons the Yankees overpowered the Red Sox in a five-game sweep last August and won the American League East.</p>
        <p>Still, Manager Terry Francona said the Red Sox must be patient and Crisp would reward them. His words sounded prophetic Friday.</p>
        <p>''I can't help the perception of how the fans feel about him after 40 at-bats,'' Francona said. ''But if we give him enough at-bats and are patient, I'm pretty confident the fans will see the player we wanted. It'll happen.''</p>
        <p>Before the game, Crisp said he was trying to fill Damon's ''so-called shoes,'' but a few seconds later he retreated from the comparison. He said that baseball was a team game, unlike golf or tennis, so his job was to fit in and help the Red Sox win. Right now, it was Crisp's job to simply help Boston beat the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''I don't have to worry about being the star,'' Crisp said. ''Although it would be nice.''</p>
        <p>For one night, Crisp was a star.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
