<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wind-Whipped Blaze Rages in Southern Georgia</title>
    <meta content="21blaze" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/us/21blaze.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Brenda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Georgia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wind-Whipped Blaze Rages in Southern Georgia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wind-Whipped Blaze Rages in Southern Georgia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENDA GOODMAN; Rachel Pomerance contributed reporting from Waycross, Ga.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Brenda</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hundreds of firefighters from across Southeast place themselves between houses and wildfires in southern Georgia, trying to fend off blazes that have blackened 42,000 acres, destroyed 20 houses and forced hundreds of residents to evacuate; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of firefighters from across the Southeast placed themselves between houses and wildfires in southern Georgia on Friday, trying to fend off blazes that have blackened 42,000 acres, destroyed 20 houses and forced hundreds of residents to evacuate.</p>
        <p>For the 10th day, gusting winds whipped flames through drought-stricken pine forests and fields, threatening houses in many of the rural communities that dot the Georgia-Florida border region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the 10th day, gusting winds whipped flames through drought-stricken pine forests and fields near the Georgia-Florida border.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hundreds of firefighters from across the Southeast placed themselves between houses and wildfires in southern Georgia on Friday, trying to fend off blazes that have blackened 42,000 acres, destroyed 20 houses and forced hundreds of residents to evacuate.</p>
        <p>For the 10th day, gusting winds whipped flames through drought-stricken pine forests and fields, threatening houses in many of the rural communities that dot the Georgia-Florida border region.</p>
        <p>Forestry officials said they did not expect much relief in the days ahead from the dry conditions feeding the fires.</p>
        <p>Robert Armstrong, 36, a firefighter from Brunswick, said the huge blaze, named the Sweat Farm Road Fire, was among the worst that he had seen in 20 years.</p>
        <p>''In the areas that are burnt,'' Firefighter Armstrong said, ''there's nothing.''</p>
        <p>Gov. Sonny Perdue asked the federal government for assistance and announced that he would tour the area on Saturday.</p>
        <p>About 400 firefighters from at least four states tried to contain the blaze, which covers 58 square miles. Five aircraft, two helicopters and one United States Forest Service air tanker dumped retardant on the flames.</p>
        <p>Officials said they believed that the fire started on Monday when a tree toppled power lines.</p>
        <p>''The wind is not helping,'' said Eric Mosely, public information officer for the Georgia Forestry Commission.</p>
        <p>''Right now, we're looking at 35 percent containment, and we're trying to hold it there.'' Mr. Mosely said.</p>
        <p>About 1,000 residents of Ware County were removed earlier in the week, said Gordon Lowe, a site coordinator for the Georgia Emergency Management Agency who was working at a shelter at Ware County High School in Waycross, a city of 15,300 people on the northeastern edge of the burned area.</p>
        <p>''If you were here yesterday, there were just ashes falling all over us,'' Mr. Lowe said.</p>
        <p>Rows of tents were set up in the school parking lot for firefighters who were exhausted after days of 13-hour shifts.</p>
        <p>Volunteers collected food for workers on the front lines. Joyce Rittenhouse, 58, of Waycross, who with her granddaughters staffed a food tent, said she made sure each that firefighter ate three bananas each day.</p>
        <p>''You need potassium to fight fires,'' Ms. Rittenhouse said.</p>
        <p>Many Waycross residents returned to their houses after winds shifted on Friday and pushed the fire away from town.</p>
        <p>Forestry officials scrambled to get ahead of the blaze as it raced toward the Okefenokee National Wildlife Refuge, a wetland sanctuary.</p>
        <p>Firefighters warned residents in tiny communities like Fargo, Manor and others to be prepared to flee.</p>
        <p>''The smoke is rolling in,'' said John Corbitt, 65, a retiree in Manor who added that he could see flames over the tops of trees 8 to 10 miles from his house. ''We're sitting on red alert, ready.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corbitt, who had watched the winds and smoke shift around him for the last week, said he was not quite ready leave.</p>
        <p>''If it jumps the railroad and the highway, I'm leaving,'' Mr. Corbitt said.</p>
        <p>His neighbor Edward Oliver, 45, a blueberry farmer who has lived in Manor for 14 years, chose to stand his ground to protect his house.</p>
        <p>''I got a sprinkler on it right now,'' Mr. Oliver said. ''In case the ash will fall, you know.'' He also used a bulldozer to plow a four-foot-wide firebreak around his 10-acre property.</p>
        <p>''It's all going to depend on the wind,'' he added. ''This is my whole life. I hope it don't burn.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
