<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Money And Marriage Collide</title>
    <meta content="21instincts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/business/21instincts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASIC INSTINCTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunleavey, M P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E7DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Money And Marriage Collide</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When Money and Marriage Collide</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. P. DUNLEAVEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunleavey, M P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M P Dunleavey Basic Instincts column on when money and marri</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOBODY tells you what a big, unruly role money will play in your marriage.</p>
        <p>In fact, when I conducted a recent unscientific e-mail survey of married people I know, 10 out of 13 agreed that over the years, money has taken up far more energy and time than their sex life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The main hurdle is learning how to talk about your finances about a year into a marriage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOBODY tells you what a big, unruly role money will play in your marriage.</p>
        <p>In fact, when I conducted a recent unscientific e-mail survey of married people I know, 10 out of 13 agreed that over the years, money has taken up far more energy and time than their sex life.</p>
        <p>Of the remaining three, one person disagreed, one said ''Maybe'' and the last said, ''Not yet, thank God'' -- but she isn't quite 30, so you see what we're up against.</p>
        <p>The trouble with money and marriage isn't even the money, not at first. The main hurdle is just learning how to talk about your finances, as my husband and I discovered -- the hard way, of course -- about a year into our marriage.</p>
        <p>You would think that writing about money for a living would have helped me to approach the situation with a confident, clear-eyed logic. Instead, I crossed my fingers and closed my eyes and assumed that my abundant love for my spouse would lead to financial harmony, some day, preferably by magic.</p>
        <p>In the end, it was a friend who forced us to have a cards-on-the-table discussion by mocking me for being a phony and lacking any real financial intimacy in my marriage.</p>
        <p>I was mortified, but it was true. So my husband and I agreed to have the big money talk. It was excruciating. Neither his income nor mine was quite as robust as, apparently, we both had been hoping. He had no idea I had that much debt --but I didn't know he had that much either, O.K.?</p>
        <p>Our financial illusions about one another were in tatters, but our marriage survived -- and the whole experience helped me to understand how some couples can enter their 60s, the wife never having written a check, the husband having no idea that his wife managed to save $1.2 million in pin money during their marriage.</p>
        <p>Talking about money is a slowly and sometimes painfully acquired skill, but it is essential ''because legally speaking your spouse is your business partner,'' said Nihara K. Choudhri, the author of ''What to Do Before 'I Do': The Modern Couple's Guide to Marriage, Money and Pre-nups'' (Sphinx Books, 2004).</p>
        <p>Also, you want your marriage to be a profitable endeavor. That may sound calculating, but after five years together, my husband and I have both realized that the only way to achieve financial security and a comfortable lifestyle is to act as a team.</p>
        <p>For couples who blanch at the thought of baring their financial souls, Ms. Choudhri suggests skipping the hard numbers at first and starting with how you envision your life together. ''Money is all about dreams, whatever they may be: Do you dream of owning a home, having a child, starting a business, retiring by a certain age? Once you identify an area that's common ground, use that as a springboard for discussing your finances.''</p>
        <p>BASED on my experience, that discussion takes about four to five years -- during which you'll probably spend most of your time disagreeing. ''Most couples don't have one big blow-up,'' Ms. Choudhri said. ''It's like a long-running argument over a series of money issues or a particular theme.''</p>
        <p>That's because marriage seems to attract financial opposites -- and the sooner you and your mate accept this, the easier it will be to work together. ''You will always have areas of disagreement,'' she said, ''but try to narrow them as much as possible so each person can have a little freedom to operate.''</p>
        <p>The cliché is that savers typically marry spenders, but Dave Ramsey, who has written several best sellers, including ''The Total Money Makeover'' (Thomas Nelson, 2007), came up with what I found to be a more helpful model. ''Within most marriages there is a nerd and a free spirit,'' he said, and one has to learn to tolerate the other's foibles before financial progress can occur.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramsey also has a rule of thumb for maintaining productive financial communication that my husband and I now think is pure genius. ''Every week or every month, whatever you decide, hold a financial committee meeting -- but this meeting should not last more than 17 minutes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>To that, Ms. Choudhri would add another piece of advice. ''Keep money out of the bedroom,'' she said. ''You need a physical space in your home where money cannot be discussed.''</p>
        <p>Based on the results of my own recent survey, I think that's an excellent idea.</p>
        <p>BASIC INSTINCTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
