<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When a Student Is Mentally Ill</title>
    <meta content="l21virginia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841800"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Virginia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pies, Ronald (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Appleton, William S (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fine, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peck, James D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When a Student Is Mentally Ill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Four letters respond to massacre at Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Dr Ronald Pies says students who are discharged from psychiatric hospital should be required to continue mental health treatment; Dr William S Appleton says that college students should be required to sign privacy waiver covering serious mental illness; Robert Fine agrees with Bob Herbert April 19 Op-Ed discussing how natural it is for young men in US to find violent solutions to psychosocial problems inherent in growing up; James D Peck suggests security measures for classroom</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Laws Limit Colleges' Options When a Student Is Mentally Ill'' (front page, April 19):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Laws Limit Colleges' Options When a Student Is Mentally Ill'' (front page, April 19):</p>
        <p>As a psychiatrist who has consulted in the college mental health system for many years, I am aware of one weak link in the system that needs urgently to be repaired.</p>
        <p>You report on April 19 that after being discharged from a psychiatric hospital, a judge ordered outpatient treatment for Seung-Hui Cho but that ''officials said they did not know whether Mr. Cho had received subsequent counseling.''</p>
        <p>In such circumstances, colleges should be empowered by law to require continuing mental health treatment, with periodic review by appropriate officials. This should be a condition of the student's continuing to attend the college.</p>
        <p>Ronald Pies, M.D.  Lexington, Mass., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a clinical professor of psychiatry at Tufts University School of Medicine.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your article describing laws limiting colleges' options dealing with mentally ill students reminded me of how my doctors handle privacy. They require me to sign a form releasing sensitive information to insurance companies and others they deem fit.</p>
        <p>If I don't, insurance will not cover me. It goes to a central bank available to all insurers and can affect my ability to get life coverage in the future as well as other insurance.</p>
        <p>Corporate America is not as timid as college administrators. As an experienced psychiatrist practicing in Harvard Square, I would like to make a simple suggestion to the colleges. Entering students ought to be required to sign a privacy waiver covering serious mental and other illnesses under certain clearly defined conditions. Refusal to sign would mean failure to matriculate.</p>
        <p>While this might inhibit students from confiding certain matters, it would allow adults to deal with the obvious behaviors revealed by the severely mentally ill.</p>
        <p>It is inconceivable that parents and concerned administrators are not informed and permitted to act upon students who fall down drunk, take dangerous drugs, make suicidal attempts, lose weight in anorexic proportions, fail to get out of bed and go to class or stalk or threaten anyone in the college community.</p>
        <p>When I was a part-time university health service psychiatrist years ago, the psychotherapists talked too much. Now the pendulum has swung too far in the other direction.</p>
        <p>William S. Appleton, M.D.  Cambridge, Mass., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is an assistant clinical professor of psychiatry at Harvard Medical School.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''A Volatile Young Man, Humiliation and a Gun'' (column, April 19):</p>
        <p>Bob Herbert is right. How natural it is for adolescent boys and young men in this country to find violent solutions to the psychosocial problems inherent to growing up. Our culture offers it to them in the deluge of media swill that drenches us all.</p>
        <p>Of course it is popular, given the anesthetizing purpose it serves among those with shaky family and community connections. The magic of the gun rests in its holder's fleeting sense of omnipotence, so different from his actual life condition.</p>
        <p>When we add the easy availability of handguns to this caldron, it sheds light on why, since 1960, there have been more than 800,000 murders in this country, with few victims having been slapped to death.</p>
        <p>H. Rap Brown was a truth-teller when he said in the '60s that ''violence is as American as cherry pie.'' Our culture, with its political and economic priorities what they are, is the destructive enabler.</p>
        <p>Robert Fine  Tempe, Ariz., April 19, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a senior lecturer in religious studies and sociology at Arizona State University.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Building a Better Lockdown,'' by Christopher Whitcomb (Op-Ed, April 20):</p>
        <p>Every classroom or major work area should have a sturdy door that can be locked quickly from the inside. If the door has a window, the occupants should hide in a spot so that a glance from the outside indicates an empty room.</p>
        <p>There should be an institution-wide signal to indicate a lockdown like a sequence of siren blasts.</p>
        <p>Part of the employee or student handbook should be instructions to follow if gunfire is inevitable. Although hiding is the natural instinct, perhaps statistically it is better to collectively do something, like throw things at the shooter, yell loudly, put a book under your shirt as some protection or rush the shooter with makeshift weapons.</p>
        <p>Some of these may take inordinate daring, but at least they may provide more possibility of surviving an attack.</p>
        <p>James D. Peck  Monroe Township, N.J.  April 20, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
