<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tough Sell in the Stands, Nascar's Car of Tomorrow Is Put to the Test Again</title>
    <meta content="21nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/sports/othersports/21nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Burton, Jeff</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Jeff</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tough Sell in the Stands, Nascar's Car of Tomorrow Is Put to the Test Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Car of Tomorrow Is Put to the Test Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
      <dateline>AVONDALE, Ariz., April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock-car racing fans in the North Carolina heartland of the sport were asked by a Charlotte newspaper columnist last year to come up with a new name for the Car of Tomorrow, which, after years of development, was scheduled to debut in Nascar's Nextel Cup series this season.</p>
        <p>Among the blistering responses: the Edsel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nascar’s Car of Tomorrow has been billed as a safety upgrade that will lower costs and make races more competitive. But crews are questioning some of those very issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stock-car racing fans in the North Carolina heartland of the sport were asked by a Charlotte newspaper columnist last year to come up with a new name for the Car of Tomorrow, which, after years of development, was scheduled to debut in Nascar's Nextel Cup series this season.</p>
        <p>Among the blistering responses: the Edsel.</p>
        <p>Apparently, the Nascar-designed racecar has been a tough sell both in the stands and in the Nascar garage. The Car of Tomorrow, which features an unusual front-shelf design and an odd wing in the rear, has been billed as a safety upgrade that will lower costs and make races more competitive. But after using the car in two races, crews are questioning some of those very issues, including the car's safety and whether it will tighten competition.</p>
        <p>As the teams prepare for their third race using the Car of Tomorrow, the Subway Fresh Fit 500 Saturday night at Phoenix International Raceway, many of those concerns are at the forefront.</p>
        <p>''I believe this is a huge work in progress,'' the veteran driver Jeff Burton said before practice Thursday. ''We're definitely learning on the fly.''</p>
        <p>Officials say they have been pleased with the results from the first two races: March 25 at Bristol Motor Speedway in Tennessee and April 1 at Martinsville Speedway in Virginia. Each race featured a tight finish. A late-race pass by Burton against Jeff Gordon at Bristol was a sign of the new car's improved racing capabilities, said Gary Nelson, the former vice president for research and development for Nascar, who led the Car of Tomorrow project.</p>
        <p>Robin Pemberton, Nascar's vice president for competition, said: ''We've had great races. We had a great race at Martinsville with it. We had a great race at Bristol.''</p>
        <p>But even before those checkered flags, red flags were being raised by some drivers and crews. Foam attached to the new car's right side has melted under high heat and filled cars with smoke.</p>
        <p>The foam was supposed to improve safety by absorbing energy in side-impact crashes. Instead, it turned into a safety hazard because the tailpipe that runs under the foam generated enough heat to melt it.</p>
        <p>After the race at Martinsville, Nascar ordered changes. A smaller amount of foam and different installation procedures are being used and heat shields were added to keep the foam from melting. Pemberton said Nascar would not remove the foam because of the benefits it could provide during a crash.</p>
        <p>The driver Greg Biffle, who raised the foam issue with Nascar officials, said he was concerned that unleaded fuel, which burns hotter than leaded gasoline, caused flames to shoot from the tailpipe. He is also questioning how higher temperatures through the summer could affect the foam.</p>
        <p>''There may be some issues with the science of it as we go forward,'' Biffle said during a Car of Tomorrow test at Richmond International Raceway this month.</p>
        <p>Foam is not the only issue. Teams are also waiting to see if the car will reduce the costs of competing, which is what Nascar has suggested. So far, teams said, it has been an expensive transition. They have had to pay as much as $1 million to $2 million per driver to implement the new program.</p>
        <p>''Everything is new, all the parts and pieces are different from the older car,'' said Larry McClure, owner of the No. 4 Chevrolet driven by Ward Burton. His Morgan-McClure Motorsports is one of the smaller-budget teams that was supposed to benefit from the Car of Tomorrow. ''It's been expensive so far.''</p>
        <p>Teams that can use the same racecar from week to week, instead of building new ones for each track, are seeing long-term savings. Kevin Harvick will drive the same car at Phoenix that he raced at Bristol and Martinsville. That would have been impossible with the model he used before; those cars are still being used in 20 of 36 races this year during the Car of Tomorrow's phase in.</p>
        <p>Pemberton, the Nascar official, said he saw other signs of the playing field's leveling. He pointed out that a number of midlevel and small-team drivers raced among the leaders at Bristol, and that the practice times were close among first- and second-tier teams at Phoenix.</p>
        <p>Yet the races so far have been decidedly tilted in favor of a dominant team, Hendrick Motorsports. Hendrick drivers Kyle Busch and Jimmie Johnson won the races at Bristol and Martinsville. Teammate Jeff Gordon finished in the top three each time. Busch's crew chief, Alan Gustafson, credited the research, engineering and testing at Hendrick for the performance of its drivers.</p>
        <p>That kind of success costs money that small-budget teams do not have.</p>
        <p>''It's not going to level the playing field because the teams that have the biggest budgets and the most employees have the deepest bench,'' said Robbie Loomis, vice president for race operations at Petty Enterprises and a former crew chief for Gordon at Hendrick Motorsports. ''If anything, I think you'll see a bigger separation anytime you come out with something new.''</p>
        <p>Fans may not care if the Car of Tomorrow leads to closer races. But that was another question drivers had as they prepared for Phoenix. The track here is much different than the half-mile ovals at Bristol and Martinsville. Phoenix is a one-mile oval, and aerodynamics affect how the cars react to each other on the track.</p>
        <p>The driver Denny Hamlin said a boxier racecar would make it more difficult to pass other cars. He said he anticipated a long line of cars with little movement from back to front.</p>
        <p>For all the complaints, the car has also had its proponents, including Kyle Petty and Dale Earnhardt Jr. Petty's son Adam died in a Nascar crash in 2000. Earnhardt's father was killed at the Daytona 500 in 2001. Those wrecks led Nascar to design and develop a safer racecar.</p>
        <p>''The justification was safety,'' Pemberton said. ''That was first and foremost, bar none.''</p>
        <p>The ultimate payoff from the car might not come until the first major crash.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
