<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Young Tourists Pick Somalia, and a 3-Nation Ordeal Begins</title>
    <meta content="21benaouda" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/world/africa/21benaouda.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070426T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE SATURDAY PROFILE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Somalia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sweden</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mogadishu (Somalia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ethiopia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bonner, Raymond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benaouda, Saifa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Somalia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Ethiopia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Kenya</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EFDC163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1242" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Young Tourists Pick Somalia, and a 3-Nation Ordeal Begins</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Young Tourists Pick Somalia, and a 3-Nation Ordeal Begins</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND BONNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bonner, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>STOCKHOLM</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses ordeal of Saifa Benaouda, young tourist from Sweden who arrived in Mogadishu, Somalia, during fighting between Islamists and Ethiopian troops; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH a blend of naïveté and a love of travel, Saifa Benaouda flew into Somalia last December from Dubai, where she and her boyfriend had gone for an extended vacation. Barely 17, Ms. Benaouda, a feisty and independent high-school student, did not mention the Somalia trip to her mother, the leader of a moderate Muslim organization here and herself a bit of a rebel when she was younger.</p>
        <p>''We were only going to be there two weeks, and I thought I'd tell her after about my adventure,'' Ms. Benaouda said in an interview. Their timing, in a world obsessed with terrorism, could not have been worse or, in the eyes of the authorities, more suspicious.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saifa Benaouda flew into Somalia last December from Dubai and found more adventure than she wanted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH a blend of naïveté and a love of travel, Saifa Benaouda flew into Somalia last December from Dubai, where she and her boyfriend had gone for an extended vacation. Barely 17, Ms. Benaouda, a feisty and independent high-school student, did not mention the Somalia trip to her mother, the leader of a moderate Muslim organization here and herself a bit of a rebel when she was younger.</p>
        <p>''We were only going to be there two weeks, and I thought I'd tell her after about my adventure,'' Ms. Benaouda said in an interview. Their timing, in a world obsessed with terrorism, could not have been worse or, in the eyes of the authorities, more suspicious.</p>
        <p>They arrived in Mogadishu, the Somali capital, just as Muslims from various countries, some trained by Al Qaeda, were streaming into Somalia in response to a call from Islamist forces that controlled much of the country last year. The Islamists were briefly battling with Ethiopian troops who had intervened to take back Somalia for a weak Western-backed interim government.</p>
        <p>Ms. Benaouda (pronounced ben-OW-da), a Muslim, disavows any political or religious motive for her venture into Somalia, and says her boyfriend is also not political. She contends that they learned of the fighting only after they got to Mogadishu and found a country she did not like and more adventure than she wanted.</p>
        <p>With fighting raging nearby, they rapidly found themselves fleeing south toward Kenya, along with hundreds of other people. On the way, she said, an American woman -- the wife of Daniel Maldonado, who is currently on trial in Houston on terrorism-related charges -- died in her lap. Ms. Benaouda took over care of the woman's three small children, ages 7 months to 9 years old, surviving by eating rice and drinking muddy floodwater and hiding in the bush when military helicopters buzzed overhead.</p>
        <p>At the Kenyan border, she said in the interview, she was detained by soldiers, including three who had American flag patches on their uniforms. She ended up in Ethiopia, where she was held for several weeks and interrogated, she said, by Westerners.</p>
        <p>AFTER criticism from human rights organizations, led by Cageprisoners and Reprieve, which were instrumental in Ms. Benaouda's eventual release, the Ethiopian government acknowledged recently that it was holding 41 men and women it suspected of fighting with the Islamists. American officials have been allowed to interrogate the suspects, American officials have said, including Amir Mohamed Meshal, from New Jersey, who is expected to be released soon from prison there.</p>
        <p>Ms. Benaouda said she got the travel bug from her Moroccan father, who died eight years ago. When the family traveled -- she is the youngest of four children -- they avoided tourist spots. Her Finnish-Swedish mother especially sought more exotic places. ''When we went to Morocco, we didn't go to Casablanca, we went to the mountains,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Last year, Ms. Benaouda and her boyfriend, Munir Awad, a 25-year-old Swedish citizen of Lebanese origin, decided they wanted to visit a Muslim country during Ms. Benaouda's winter school break.</p>
        <p>They chose Dubai but were quickly disappointed: too many Asians, too many modern, tall buildings, too much shopping. ''We wanted something more authentic,'' she said. They met a man from Stockholm who was going to Somalia, and they decided to go, too.</p>
        <p>When they arrived, their baggage was missing. They were told they had to stay inside to be safe. She said they were treated badly because of their lighter skin. Then the fighting broke out, and they fled toward Kenya.</p>
        <p>Along the way, she and her boyfriend became separated, and she joined up with a group of women and children, including the American woman, who apparently had malaria. ''She was hallucinating,'' Ms. Benaouda recalled. ''She was saying goodbye to her kids, telling them she loved them.''</p>
        <p>After the woman died, the people in the convoy wrapped her body in a mat, and put it on the roof of the car. The children had fallen asleep, and when they awoke Ms. Benaouda told them that their mother had gone in another car.</p>
        <p>Ms. Benaouda said she learned only recently, from Cageprisoners, that Mr. Maldonado had been interrogated by the F.B.I. in Kenya this year, and then sent to Houston to face trial. (The children were ultimately sent to their grandparents in the United States.)</p>
        <p>After nearly three weeks on the run, Ms. Benaouda said, her group reached the Kenyan border, where they were surrounded by soldiers -- including the three with the American flag patches -- pointing rifles at them. ''We thought they were going to shoot us,'' she recalled. ''We began screaming.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Benaouda, who had begun to suspect, correctly as it turned out, that she was pregnant, was glad to meet someone who spoke English.</p>
        <p>She did not tell them she was pregnant, though, only that she was Swedish. She and her companions were handcuffed and blindfolded and flown to Nairobi, Kenya, where they were put in jail, she said. Then she and the others, including Mr. Meshal, were deported to Mogadishu, by then under the control of Ethiopian troops. After a few days there, they were sent to Addis Ababa, the Ethiopian capital.</p>
        <p>But her ordeal did not end there. She was interrogated again, she said, for as long as six hours on one day, mostly by two women, one of whom spoke English with what she said was an American accent. They demanded her e-mail address and password. She told them they were rude, but gave it to them. They showed her the names and photographs of some men and asked if she knew any of them. She did not. They demanded that she name any extremists she knew in Sweden.</p>
        <p>THEY said her boyfriend had recruited jihadists in Denmark in 2004.</p>
        <p>''I told them they were stupid,'' she said. ''I told them they were full of bull.'' Her boyfriend was not yet a Muslim in 2004 and had never been to Denmark, she said she told them.</p>
        <p>Her challenging manner earned her the nickname Crazy Inge from the other prisoners, she said. Ms. Benaouda said she spoke out because she had been brought up in Sweden, where women speak their minds.</p>
        <p>''She's crazy, but I love her,'' said her mother, Helena, who sat in on the interview but allowed her daughter to speak freely. Mrs. Benaouda, who started a Web site dedicated to her daughter's release (www.releasemychild.se),  said her only conditions were that her daughter not be photographed or described physically.</p>
        <p>Ms. Benaouda gave her only other interviews to the Swedish newspaper Svenska Dagbladet and Cageprisoners  (www.cageprisoners.com),  which is based in Britain.</p>
        <p>After several weeks, during which Ms. Benaouda kept a diary on pieces of toilet paper, the Ethiopians told her she was free to go. But she had learned that her boyfriend -- whom she called her husband -- was there, too, and refused to leave without him. Finally, the Ethiopians said if she did not go to Sweden, they would send her to Mogadishu. She agreed to go home and arrived there in late March. Her boyfriend is still being held in Ethiopia.</p>
        <p>While there is no telling whether there are similar adventures in store for Ms. Benaouda as she exercises her wanderlust, her immediate future promises to be uneventful. Her passport was taken by the American soldiers, and her mother said she had no intention of signing the parental consent form that a minor needed to get another one.</p>
        <p>THE SATURDAY PROFILE</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 26, 2007, Thursday  The Saturday Profile, about Saifa Benaouda, a Swedish Muslim who went to Somalia last December as the country was becoming a magnet for Islamic extremists, referred incorrectly to Daniel Maldonado, an American Muslim convert in Somalia arrested on the Kenya border and deported to the United States in February on terrorism-related charges. Mr. Maldonado pleaded guilty in Houston federal court last Thursday to receiving training from a foreign terrorist organization. He is not ''currently on trial.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 26, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>The Saturday Profile, about Saifa Benaouda, a Swedish Muslim who went to Somalia last December as the country was becoming a magnet for Islamic extremists, referred incorrectly to Daniel Maldonado, an American Muslim convert in Somalia arrested on the Kenya border and deported to the United States in February on terrorism-related charges. Mr. Maldonado pleaded guilty in Houston federal court last Thursday to receiving training from a foreign terrorist organization. He is not ''currently on trial.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
