<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corzine, Still at Risk, Is Breathing On His Own</title>
    <meta content="21corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/nyregion/21corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070507T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corzine, Still at Risk, Is Breathing On His Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine, Still at Risk, Is Breathing on His Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD G. JONES; Kareem Fahim contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fahim, Kareem; Jones, Richard G</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine was breathing on his own for the first time in a week on Friday after doctors removed a mechanical ventilator that had been helping him breathe since he was critically injured in a car accident.</p>
        <p>While the removal of the ventilator, at 12:25 p.m., was viewed as a significant step in Mr. Corzine's recovery, he is still listed in critical but stable condition, and doctors cautioned that the breathing tube could again be used if the governor encountered a setback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey was still in critical but stable condition, and doctors cautioned that a breathing tube could again be used for the governor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine was breathing on his own for the first time in a week on Friday after doctors removed a mechanical ventilator that had been helping him breathe since he was critically injured in a car accident.</p>
        <p>While the removal of the ventilator, at 12:25 p.m., was viewed as a significant step in Mr. Corzine's recovery, he is still listed in critical but stable condition, and doctors cautioned that the breathing tube could again be used if the governor encountered a setback.</p>
        <p>''His respiratory function will be closely monitored to ensure that he can continue to breathe on his own and cough efficiently,'' Mr. Corzine's spokesman, Anthony Coley, said in a statement released at 5 p.m. that was the first notification that the governor was off the ventilator. ''Doctors do not entirely rule out the possibility that the breathing tube will need to be reinserted.''</p>
        <p>For much of Friday, as Mr. Corzine began breathing completely on his own, his three children and an older brother, Allen, kept a vigil at Cooper University Hospital here. The governor has been in the hospital's intensive care unit since the sport utility vehicle he was riding in slammed into a guardrail on the Garden State Parkway last Thursday.</p>
        <p>Around midafternoon, the governor's companion, Sharon Elghanayan, arrived at the hospital, joining the familyin a waiting area on the second floor.</p>
        <p>In recent days, Mr. Corzine, 60, who fractured his breastbone, shattered his left femur and broke 11 ribs, his right collarbone and a lower vertebra, had been taking more breaths on his own; by Wednesday, doctors said he had been taking six breaths on his own for every eight supplied by the machine. Doctors had put him on the ventilator to alleviate the pain caused by breathing.</p>
        <p>Despite the removal of the breathing machine, a handful of veteran trauma physicians and orthopedic surgeons interviewed on Friday said the governor was entering a phase of recovery that was riddled with potential hazards common to those who have sustained similar injuries.</p>
        <p>The doctors, none of whom have treated Mr. Corzine or seen his medical records, did not offer an assessment on his prognosis, but described the outlook for patients who have sustained similar injuries.</p>
        <p>''He's a fairly fortunate fellow, given the constellation of the thoracic injuries and the femur fracture,'' said Dr. Thomas A. Santora, a surgeon at Temple University Hospital in Philadelphia. ''It's a major cluster of injuries.''</p>
        <p>Dr. David H. Livingston, the chief of the trauma division at University Hospital in Newark, said research showed that of a group of 100 men 60 years of age or older, as many as a third would have died of the kinds of injuries the governor sustained.</p>
        <p>Dr. Livingston said that a scoring system called the injury severity scale offered an indication of the seriousness of Mr. Corzine's injuries when he arrived at the hospital by helicopter after the crash, just outside Atlantic City. He said that on the scale, ranging from 0 to 75, with the highest number representing a lethal injury, the governor's injuries probably ranked 33 or 34.</p>
        <p>''That is huge,'' Dr. Livingston said. ''If you're over 9, you should be in a trauma center.''</p>
        <p>Among the potential recovery hazards the doctors cited are blood clots and pneumonia. In addition, there is a risk of infection from fluid that builds up in the body when it is largely immobilized for extended periods.</p>
        <p>So far, the governor's doctors have not indicated what, if any, complications Mr. Corzine has encountered. And the doctors interviewed said that Cooper University Hospital -- a nationally respected trauma center and one of the top three such facilities in New Jersey -- was undoubtedly taking precautions to prevent such problems.</p>
        <p>Blood thinners, for example, can be administered to prevent clots, they said, and patients can be placed in special hydraulic beds that shift weight and maneuver parts of the body to keep fluids from pooling and inviting infections.</p>
        <p>The governor's doctors, citing privacy concerns, have declined to describe in much detail the governor's treatment, but they have said that besides a feeding tube, four other tubes have been employed -- two to drain fluids and two to provide medicine.</p>
        <p>The governor's aides have said that tests so far show no signs of injury to his brain or spinal cord. Doctors say it is encouraging that he has continued to communicate -- through nods and other gestures -- even though he has been only semiconscious.</p>
        <p>Even without knowing the details of his condition, the doctors who were interviewed remarked that despite the extent and seriousness of his injuries, the governor was doing as well as could be expected.</p>
        <p>Patients in Mr. Corzine's situation face the greatest risk of death at three crucial periods after an accident like his, said Dr. Jeffrey S. Hammond, the director of the trauma center at Robert Wood Johnson University Hospital in New Brunswick, N.J., and the governor has already survived two of them: the initial accident, and the days immediately afterward.</p>
        <p>The third critical period is five to seven days after the accident, Dr. Hammond said, when there is a risk of organ failure from infection.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ken Rodriguez, chief of orthopedic medicine at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston, an affiliate of the Harvard Medical School, said there were several milestones after patients are removed from ventilators.</p>
        <p>When patients are well enough to leave intensive care, they are transferred to traditional rooms. Once they are discharged from the hospital, Dr. Rodriguez said, they often go directly to a physical therapy center for stays that can last from a few weeks to a few months.</p>
        <p>In cases like Mr. Corzine's, more rehabilitation is then required, Dr. Rodriguez said, noting that patients who have sustained such devastating injuries are often unable to return to normal activity for as long as a year.</p>
        <p>Initially, the governor's aides said that he might be able to return to work at the State House within a week or two of the accident.</p>
        <p>''That is very unlikely,'' Dr. Rodriguez said. ''If it was just the femur fracture, then the period of maximum medical recovery is a year.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 7, 2007, Monday  An article on April 21 about the removal of a mechanical ventilator from Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey eight days after he was seriously injured in a vehicular crash misstated the title of Dr. Ken Rodriguez of Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston, who discussed milestones for patients who have been removed from ventilators. He is the chief of orthopedic trauma, not orthopedic medicine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 7, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>An article on April 21 about the removal of a mechanical ventilator from Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey eight days after he was seriously injured in a vehicular crash misstated the title of Dr. Ken Rodriguez of Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston, who discussed milestones for patients who have been removed from ventilators. He is the chief of orthopedic trauma, not orthopedic medicine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
