<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prices Are Lower, but Profit Is Up at Xerox</title>
    <meta content="21xerox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/business/21xerox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copying Machines</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Xerox Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mulcahy, Anne M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Copying Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copying Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Equipment</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Xerox Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DB163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prices Are Lower, but Profit Is Up at Xerox</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Prices Are Lower, but Profit Is Up at Xerox</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Xerox reports revenue for first three months of 2007 was $3.8 billion, up 4 percent from last year; earned $233 million, 17 percent increase from comparable quarter in 2006; new focus on toners, ink and services seems to be working; chief executive Anne M Mulcahy comments (M)/</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometimes, low revenues portend good news.</p>
        <p>Take the Xerox Corporation. For the fifth quarter in a row, its revenues from copiers and printers have gone down. But ask Anne M. Mulcahy, the chief executive, what she plans to do about that, and her answer is, absolutely nothing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Xerox has been sharply cutting prices for its machines to focus on the sales of toners, inks and services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometimes, low revenues portend good news.</p>
        <p>Take the Xerox Corporation. For the fifth quarter in a row, its revenues from copiers and printers have gone down. But ask Anne M. Mulcahy, the chief executive, what she plans to do about that, and her answer is, absolutely nothing.</p>
        <p>Dollars from equipment sales may be down but Xerox is placing a lot of machines. And that, Ms. Mulcahy insists, is what counts.</p>
        <p>''We will not sacrifice profitability to grow equipment revenues,'' she said in an interview yesterday. ''But we will sacrifice equipment revenues to drive profitability.''</p>
        <p>In the document-processing world, that makes total sense. Printer and copier companies make the most money from sales of toners, inks and services. And those sales, of course, are directly proportional to the number of machines being used.</p>
        <p>Xerox has always known that, but it is finally acting on it. Since January it has introduced 19 new products, more than all of last year. And it has been sharply cutting prices for its machines -- hence the revenue declines -- to sell more of them.</p>
        <p>''For 30 years, Xerox raised prices so it wouldn't have to worry about costs,'' noted Ulysses S. Yannas, a broker at Buckman, Buckman &amp; Reid. ''Now it is doing the opposite.''</p>
        <p>The new approach is working. According to Infotrends, a research firm, Xerox accounts for half of the pages produced on high-speed digital color presses.</p>
        <p>Black and white printing is not doing nearly as well, but analysts note that color printing offers about five times the profit of monochrome for Xerox.</p>
        <p>''Xerox really has a strong, wide portfolio, and they've put in place the engines to drive top-line growth,'' said Angèle Boyd, a vice president of the research firm IDC.</p>
        <p>Xerox's quarterly numbers reflect the favorable skew. Revenue for the first three months of 2007 was $3.8 billion, up 4 percent from last year. About 70 percent came from supplies and services.</p>
        <p>Xerox earned $233 million, a 17 percent rise from the comparable quarter in 2006. That came out to 24 cents a share, which beat analysts' estimates by 4 cents.</p>
        <p>Costs are down, and will soon go down more -- Xerox is leaving its lush headquarters in Stamford, Conn., for sparser space in Norwalk.</p>
        <p>Xerox said it would earn $1.12 to $1.16 a share for the year -- and expected it would be closer to the high end.</p>
        <p>Investors applauded, sending Xerox shares up 52 cents, to $18.60.</p>
        <p>Still, some investors remain concerned that Xerox has not proved that it can deliver brisk growth.</p>
        <p>''The good quarter was driven by the cost structure, and we aren't convinced that the revenue situation has been resolved,'' said Jack L. Kelly, an analyst with Goldman Sachs.</p>
        <p>Neither is Timothy M. Ghriskey, chief investment officer at Solaris Asset Management. Mr. Ghriskey agrees with all of Ms. Mulcahy's strategies -- but he is not buying Xerox shares. ''The competition Xerox is facing for sales is just formidable,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Indeed it is. Xerox remains the dominant player in the market for high-speed printers, for example, but others are nipping at its heels. ''Xerox has been in the lead, but Kodak and Canon and Ricoh have been coming up fast,'' said Patricia Sorce, co-director of the Printing Industry Center at the Rochester Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>So has the Dutch company Oce. This week, Oce introduced a high-speed continuous feed printer -- the paper goes through on rolls rather than cut sheets -- that it plans to market to book publishers.</p>
        <p>And last year it introduced a high-speed cut-sheet machine that can simultaneously print on both sides of a sheet.</p>
        <p>Jan Hull, an Oce senior vice president, insisted that Oce is ''already ahead of plan'' to grab at least a 20 percent share of the high-speed market in the next four to five years.</p>
        <p>Ricoh, meanwhile, already commands a large share of the market for office printers, and has new high-speed printers coming out next year. Ricoh is also in the process of buying I.B.M.'s printing operations.</p>
        <p>''I.B.M. is really strong in the market for mission-critical applications like printing bills or checks,'' said Ron Potesky, vice president for corporate product marketing at the Ricoh Americas Corporation.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mulcahy seems unworried. ''Yes, there are a lot of people with aspirations, but we have a tremendous head start,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Xerox has been on a buying spree of its own. This month it announced it was spending $1.5 billion to buy Global Imaging, a major distributor of office equipment to small and medium-size businesses.</p>
        <p>Until now, Global sold almost all brands except Xerox, but analysts expect that its 200,000 customers will be easily persuaded to switch brands.</p>
        <p>''Global has always offered great service, and its customers care more about that than the brand of machine,'' said Shannon S. Cross, an analyst at Cross Research who rates Xerox shares a buy.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mulcahy points straight at Global when anyone questions her commitment to growth.</p>
        <p>''Buying Global was all about growing revenues,'' she said. ''So you could say we just invested $1.5 billion in a big catalyst for growth.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
