<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Medicare Privatization Scam</title>
    <meta content="21sat1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/opinion/21sat1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Medicare Privatization Scam</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Medicare Privatization Scam</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial notes that about fifth of elderly Americans belong to private Medicare Advantage plans, which--thanks to government subsidies--often charge less or offer more than traditional Medicare; says as Congress struggles to find savings that could offset costs of other important health programs, it should take long and hard look at those subsidies; contends that Congress ought to eliminate subsidies completely unless it is willing to subsidize same benefits--at enormous cost--for far greater number of people enrolled in standard Medicare</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If private health plans are supposedly so great at delivering high-quality care while holding down costs, why does the government have to keep subsidizing them so lavishly to participate in the Medicare program?</p>
        <p>About a fifth of elderly Americans now belong to private Medicare Advantage plans, which -- thanks to government subsidies -- often charge less or offer more than traditional Medicare. As Congress struggles to find savings that could offset the costs of other important health programs, it should take a long and hard look at those subsidies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is time to level the playing field and force private plans to really compete with traditional Medicare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If private health plans are supposedly so great at delivering high-quality care while holding down costs, why does the government have to keep subsidizing them so lavishly to participate in the Medicare program?</p>
        <p>About a fifth of elderly Americans now belong to private Medicare Advantage plans, which -- thanks to government subsidies -- often charge less or offer more than traditional Medicare. As Congress struggles to find savings that could offset the costs of other important health programs, it should take a long and hard look at those subsidies.</p>
        <p>The authoritative Medicare Payment Advisory Commission estimates that the government pays private plans 12 percent more, on average, than the same services would cost in the traditional Medicare fee-for-service program. The private plans use some of this money to make themselves more attractive to beneficiaries -- by reducing premiums or adding benefits not covered by basic Medicare -- and siphon off the rest to add to profits and help cover the plans' high administrative costs.</p>
        <p>Although the insurance industry insists that the subsidies are much lower and are warranted by the benefits provided, Thomas Scully, who headed the Medicare program for the Bush administration until 2003, told reporters recently that the subsidies were too large and ought to be reduced by Congress.</p>
        <p>The largest private enrollment is in health maintenance organizations, which typically deliver care a bit more cheaply than standard Medicare and should not need their 10 percent subsidies, on average, to compete. The biggest subsidies -- averaging 19 percent above cost -- go to private fee-for-service plans, which are the fastest-growing part of the Medicare Advantage program. Unlike the H.M.O.'s, which at least manage a patient's care and bargain hard with doctors and hospitals, these plans ride on the coattails of standard Medicare, typically providing access to the same doctors and paying them at the same rates. Thanks to the big subsidies they get, such plans are often a good deal for beneficiaries, charging less for the same benefits or adding benefits without raising prices.</p>
        <p>The main losers are the beneficiaries in the standard Medicare program, whose monthly premiums are roughly $2 higher to help pay for the subsidies, and the taxpayers who pick up part of the tab. The subsidies also erode the long-term solvency of Medicare, which needs to rein in costs, not increase them with handouts to insurance companies.</p>
        <p>When the Democrats first won control of Congress, it seemed possible that they might eliminate the subsidies -- saving some $54 billion over five years -- to finance a $50 billion expansion of a health insurance program for low-income children. But the insurance industry has mounted a furious lobbying campaign to head off any cuts.</p>
        <p>Congress ought to eliminate the subsidies completely unless it is willing to subsidize the same benefits -- at enormous cost -- for the far greater number of people enrolled in standard Medicare. It is time to level the playing field and force private plans to really compete with traditional Medicare.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
