<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bill Bradley, Ex-Senator, Returns To Producing</title>
    <meta content="21brad" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/theater/21brad.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bradley, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4DC163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bill Bradley, Ex-Senator, Returns To Producing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bill Bradley, Ex-Senator, Returns to Producing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAMPBELL ROBERTSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robertson, Campbell</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sure, win a Rhodes scholarship, help lead a team to a national basketball championship, become a United States senator and run for president. Congratulations.</p>
        <p>Now, want a real challenge? Try producing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sure, win a Rhodes scholarship, become a United States senator and run for president. Congratulations. Now, want a real challenge? Try producing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sure, win a Rhodes scholarship, help lead a team to a national basketball championship, become a United States senator and run for president. Congratulations.</p>
        <p>Now, want a real challenge? Try producing.</p>
        <p>Bill Bradley has, twice. The first time, in 1976, was a prison drama called ''The Poison Tree.''</p>
        <p>''It opened in Philadephia,'' Mr. Bradley said in an interview at his office in Midtown Manhattan, ''played a week there, then went to Chicago, where it played about a week or two, then it came to New York. I was on a western road trip with the Knicks, and I wasn't going to be able to see it until I got back on Friday, I think it was.''</p>
        <p>''By that time,'' he said, ''it had closed.''</p>
        <p>No backboard, no rebound, no Game 7. That's that in show business.</p>
        <p>But 31 years later, Mr. Bradley is giving it another try, having scouted out and now backing a one-man play called ''American Fiesta,'' which began previews last Saturday at the Vineyard Theater off Union Square.</p>
        <p>A longing for the greasepaint? Not really. ''It was a confluence of the right play at the right moment,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''American Fiesta'' is by Steven Tomlinson, an economics professor at the University of Texas. Mr. Tomlinson has had notable success writing plays, in which he often takes some facet of economics and refracts it. Past plays of Mr. Tomlinson, who is also a lay preacher in Austin, have explored the dramatic and moral implications of money management, real estate, even the tech stock bubble. Really. And they're often funny too.</p>
        <p>His latest work, Mr. Tomlinson said in an interview, arose out of three disparate preoccupations: the negativity whipped up by the 2004 election; the anxiety he felt telling his parents, Church of Christ members in Oklahoma, that he and his male partner were getting married; and his obsession with buying Fiestaware china online. A monologue on the basic agreement of Americans on the big issues, ''American Fiesta'' won raves during its run in Austin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley sits on the boards of several different companies, and was in Texas last summer for a meeting. He went to see Mr. Tomlinson's play on a recommendation. At the time Mr. Bradley was a few months into writing his new book, ''The New American Story,'' which deals with many of the same themes as ''American Fiesta.''</p>
        <p>''I was in the middle of doing this book, so I was thinking about this every day, and here it was in dramatic form,'' Mr. Bradley said. ''When I left, I thought, 'You know, this is something that more people should see.' So naturally my thought was: 'Get it to New York.' '' (He said the timing of the play's New York opening, coming weeks after his book hit stores, was coincidental.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley called Emanuel Azenberg, the longtime Broadway producer and an old friend, who was also a partner in his short-lived producing career in the 1970s.</p>
        <p>A few weeks later, Mr. Azenberg called Mr. Tomlinson and said he wanted to see the play. The problem was, ''American Fiesta'' had ended its run. So Mr. Tomlinson immediately decided to produce a one-week return engagement personally, for an audience, essentially, of one.</p>
        <p>''Within 48 hours, wheels were spinning to make it all happen,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Azenberg came and enjoyed it; he, Mr. Bradley and a few other investors put up some money; and now Mr. Tomlinson is beginning his run at the Vineyard.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Bradley is back in the theater game, though he played down his involvement. With ''The Poison Tree,'' he sat in darkened theaters through the summer, watching auditions and becoming engrossed in the other, finer points of producing.</p>
        <p>This time, he said, ''I'm just tagging along.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
