<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Cases Prove Test for Bush's Unwavering Loyalty</title>
    <meta content="21memo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/washington/21memo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WHITE HOUSE MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzales, Alberto R (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Bank</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Cases Prove Test for Bush's Unwavering Loyalty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Cases Are Test for Bush’s Unwavering Loyalty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG; Eric Lipton contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush has stood by his embattled but loyal lieutenants despite loud calls for their heads, but his ability to turn aside that kind of pressure is facing serious test as he confronts what to do about Atty Gen Alberto R Gonzales and World Bank pres Paul D Wolfowitz; how Bush moves to resolve situations is being watched closely in Democratic and Republican circles for what it says about his standing in capital's new power dynamic, as late-term president with low approval ratings and hostile and increasingly assertive Congress; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Time and time again, President Bush has stood by his most embattled but loyal lieutenants despite loud calls for their heads, at times defying the established physics of Washington (rapidly diminishing support in one's own party times the number of instances in which one has failed to convincingly explain away accusations of incompetence or malfeasance equals the certainty of rapid resignation).</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's ability to turn aside that kind of pressure is now facing a serious test as he confronts what to do about Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales and Paul D. Wolfowitz, the president of the World Bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush’s loyalty is now facing a serious test as he confronts what to do about Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales and Paul D. Wolfowitz, the president of the World Bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Time and time again, President Bush has stood by his most embattled but loyal lieutenants despite loud calls for their heads, at times defying the established physics of Washington (rapidly diminishing support in one's own party times the number of instances in which one has failed to convincingly explain away accusations of incompetence or malfeasance equals the certainty of rapid resignation).</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's ability to turn aside that kind of pressure is now facing a serious test as he confronts what to do about Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales and Paul D. Wolfowitz, the president of the World Bank.</p>
        <p>How Mr. Bush moves to resolve the situations is being watched closely in Democratic and Republican circles for what it says about his standing in the capital's new power dynamic, as a late-term president with low approval ratings and a hostile and increasingly assertive Congress.</p>
        <p>They are two very different cases in two very different worlds: Mr. Wolfowitz faces questions about favoritism toward his girlfriend; Mr. Gonzales is dealing with bipartisan criticism about his competence and questions about whether the Justice Department dismissed several federal prosecutors for political reasons.</p>
        <p>In each case Mr. Bush is standing by a loyalist with an evaporating base of support and a serious challenge to his credibility even among Republicans. And, two Republicans close to the administration said, in the case of Mr. Gonzales, even some of Mr. Bush's close aides think that his resignation would best serve the administration but do not find a like-minded view from the president, who is personally close to the attorney general.</p>
        <p>Yet, in a mark of his dwindling political capital, Mr. Bush has so far left Mr. Gonzales and Mr. Wolfowitz mostly to fend for themselves, pledging his continued confidence in them, but in each case saying it would fall to them to build back support among their core constituencies. And neither, to say the least, has made any visible progress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's unwavering -- some say stubborn -- sense of loyalty has at times helped him to build support within his own party. But it has also angered his fellow party members, most notably when he refused to cut loose Donald H. Rumsfeld as defense secretary as the Iraq war ground along and then forced him out after the 2006 elections, when many Republicans complained it was too late to do any political good.</p>
        <p>''Bush certainly goes against the grain of the cardinal rule of Washington politics, which is get rid of damage that can hurt the president and the presidency,'' said Hedrick Smith, author of ''The Power Game: How Washington Works.''</p>
        <p>''The other rule of the power game,'' Mr. Smith added, ''is to hang on; the president's got to look strong and can't look weak or the sharks will be in the water, and they will go after every chunk they can.''</p>
        <p>Throughout his presidency, Mr. Bush has seemed to keep the latter point top of mind, often projecting welcome strength to supporters in times of siege. But now there is some question of whether that same projection of fortitude in these circumstances is driving supporters away from him at a time when the White House needs all the friends it can get.</p>
        <p>On Friday, one day after Mr. Gonzales scored low marks from members of both parties for his testimony on Capitol Hill, Republicans seemed to have soured on him still more, voicing fears that his inability to rebuild credibility would ultimately harm administration efforts to nominate judges and push terrorism initiatives.</p>
        <p>''The nation would be better served by fresh leadership at the Justice Department,'' Representative Adam H. Putnam, Republican of Florida and chairman of the House Republican Conference, said Friday.</p>
        <p>Senator Jeff Sessions, Republican of Alabama, said in a statement: ''I think that the attorney general should take the weekend to consider Thursday's hearing and to determine whether he can reconstitute the Department of Justice and be an effective leader there If he and the president decide that he cannot be an effective leader moving forward, then he should resign.''</p>
        <p>Some Republicans close to the White House predicted he would do just that, but administration officials denied the reports, and one Justice Department official said that no matter how harsh the criticism of Mr. Gonzales during the hearing Thursday, there was at least some relief that Senator Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, the senior Republican on the Judiciary Committee, did not formally call for him to step down.</p>
        <p>The spectacle of Republican senators harshly questioning Mr. Gonzales in a televised hearing came roughly a week after officials at the World Bank heckled Mr. Wolfowitz with calls to resign. While the two cases have very different elements, both are feeding into Democratic assertions that the administration is adrift without an ethical compass.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the fate of Mr. Wolfowitz, who does not otherwise have a huge store of support from the neo-conservatives who once viewed him as an ally, would ultimately rest with the international board of directors of the World Bank over which it exerts only so much control. And one senior official, who requested anonymity to speak frankly, said that even if the White House believed Mr. Gonzales had done nothing wrong, the handling of the prosecutor dismissals and his incomplete explanations had created serious challenges for him and Mr. Bush's desire to protect him.</p>
        <p>''It served up a political combo-Grand Slam Denny's breakfast to be feasted on,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>WHITE HOUSE MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
