<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anger and Alternatives on Abortion</title>
    <meta content="21docs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/us/21docs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kolata, Gina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiff, Isaac (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anger and Alternatives on Abortion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anger and Alternatives on Abortion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINA KOLATA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kolata, Gina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court decision to uphold ban on partial birth abortion has huge political implications but, as practical matter, is unlikely to have much of effect; Dr Isaac Schiff, chairman of department of obstetrics at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston, says that there are safe and readily available alternatives to banned method; he expresses concern that decision may set precedent for further restrictions on abortion; several other doctors comment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court decision on Wednesday to uphold a ban on a type of abortion, has huge political implications but, as a practical matter, is unlikely to have much of an effect.</p>
        <p>The reason, said Dr. Isaac Schiff, chairman of the department of obstetrics and gynecology at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston, is that there are safe and readily available alternatives to the banned method, which the law calls partial birth abortion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court decision to uphold a ban on a type of abortion, has huge political implications but, as a practical matter, is unlikely to have much of an effect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court decision on Wednesday to uphold a ban on a type of abortion, has huge political implications but, as a practical matter, is unlikely to have much of an effect.</p>
        <p>The reason, said Dr. Isaac Schiff, chairman of the department of obstetrics and gynecology at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston, is that there are safe and readily available alternatives to the banned method, which the law calls partial birth abortion.</p>
        <p>''This law by itself, if it were the only law passed, would be a nonoccurrence,'' Dr. Schiff said.</p>
        <p>The concern, he added, is that the decision may set a precedent for further restrictions on abortion.</p>
        <p>His colleague, Dr. Frederic D. Frigoletto, vice chairman of obstetrics and gynecology at Massachusetts General and past president of the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, agreed and called for a different kind of effort among people who want to preserve women's right to abortion.</p>
        <p>''We are not in favor of this act, but now that it is here, we should prevent further intrusions'' by legislatures into medical practice, Dr. Frigoletto said, ''rather than spending a lot of energy saying things that are not very accurate about the impact of the ban itself on women's ability to have pregnancy terminations.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the political reverberations of the decision are leading to widely disparate pronouncements by groups on either side of the abortion debate, with continuing questions about what the ban means and how the Supreme Court could possibly regulate the practice of medicine. The law is perfectly clear, said Douglas Johnson, legal director for National Right to Life, which opposes most abortions. To violate it, Mr. Johnson said, a doctor has to plan to deliver vaginally a living fetus and then deliberately kill it when it is leaving the womb.</p>
        <p>It is permissible to kill the fetus while it is in the womb, Mr. Johnson said, adding, ''Anything goes inside the womb.''</p>
        <p>It is also permissible to deliver a fetus so immature that it could not draw a breath or otherwise show clear signs of life. And it is permissible to use the banned method to save the pregnant woman's life.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court decision is shameful and incomprehensible, said the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, which issued a statement about the decision. The organization added that the procedure, which it calls intact dilation and extraction, or D and E, ''is safest and offers significant benefits for women suffering from certain conditions that make non-intact D &amp; E especially dangerous.''</p>
        <p>The American Medical Association did not issue a statement. Its policy, which abbreviates dilation and extraction as D &amp; X, states: ''According to the scientific literature, there does not appear to be any identified situation in which intact D &amp; X is the only appropriate procedure to induce abortion, and ethical concerns have been raised about intact D &amp; X. The A.M.A. recommends that the procedure not be used unless alternative procedures pose materially greater risk to the woman.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Schiff said, ''Obviously, it's a very emotionally charged situation,'' but the new abortion law ''is very clear and specific,'' stating just what Mr. Johnson said it did.</p>
        <p>Although some doctors may feel more comfortable with the banned method, Dr. Frigoletto said alternatives include dismembering the fetus before extracting it from the uterus or killing the fetus first with a lethal injection of a drug and then inducing an abortion.</p>
        <p>The banned method, Dr. Frigoletto said, is typically used when a woman is 20 to 23 weeks pregnant and before the fetus is viable. Any earlier and it would be almost impossible to extract a live fetus and crush its head. The fetus would be so tiny that it would fall out of the uterus when the cervix is dilated, he explained.</p>
        <p>About 5,000 women a year have abortions in the middle of the second trimester, but there are no figures on what proportion use the banned method. Dr. Frigoletto estimated that it was a minority, though, because with the partial-birth method the woman has to endure several hours of labor.</p>
        <p>But some doctors prefer the banned method, he said, adding: ''Just like any surgical procedure, there are variations, and some surgeons feel more comfortable with one procedure than another, based on training and experience.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Frigoletto said there was a hypothetical situation in which the ban might endanger a woman's health. If a specific provider in a very remote area felt more comfortable with the banned method and the woman did not have access to anyone else to perform an alternative procedure and the provider she saw decided to try another method anyway.</p>
        <p>At Massachusetts General, about 100 women a year have abortions when they are 20 to 23 weeks pregnant, almost always because their fetuses had serious birth defects or chromosomal abnormalities. Partial-birth abortion, as defined in the law, is never used, Dr. Frigoletto said.</p>
        <p>Abortion providers were outraged at the idea that Congress could decide how they practice medicine.</p>
        <p>''The regulation of medicine is not under the jurisdiction of the U.S. Congress, unless you consider it interstate commerce, like trucking,'' said Dr. David Grimes, an abortion provider in Chapel Hill, N.C.</p>
        <p>But Dr. David Orentlicher, a law professor and co-director of the Center for Law and Health at Indiana University in Indianapolis, said it was not quite that simple.</p>
        <p>Congress, Dr. Orentlicher said, used the interstate commerce provision to prohibit racial discrimination by restaurants, arguing that if a substantial quantity of food crossed state lines or if interstate travelers were served, Congress could be involved. For abortion, the interstate commerce provision might apply if equipment, patients or doctors crossed state lines.</p>
        <p>There also is a precedent for legislatures to pass laws affecting medical decision making, Dr. Orentlicher said. States enacted laws making it difficult for parents to have their mentally retarded children sterilized. They enacted laws restricting electroconvulsive therapy for psychiatric patients.</p>
        <p>But, Dr. Orentlicher said, the court's ruling troubles him because it is different in spirit. This time, the law is very specific about the use of one particular procedure.</p>
        <p>Some abortion providers say doctors could be in legal jeopardy even if they made every effort to comply with the law.</p>
        <p>''Where is the borderline between a woman's health being at risk and her life being at risk?'' asked Dr. Paul D. Blumenthal, a professor of obstetrics and gynecology at the Stanford University School of Medicine. ''How is it made and how quickly is it made? When we're doing a procedure, we don't have a lot of time to find out whether someone thinks we're crossing a line.''</p>
        <p>NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
