<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OFF THE DRIBBLE</title>
    <meta content="21playoffs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OFF THE DRIBBLE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>History sometimes has a tangled sense of humor.</p>
        <p>Don Nelson, the Golden State Warriors' coach, was the last person to get the Warriors to the playoffs, in 1994, a year before he left Golden State to coach the Knicks. His point guard in 1994 was Avery Johnson, who replaced Nelson as the coach of the Dallas Mavericks in 2005. Nelson's son, Donnie, was an assistant in Dallas and is now the Mavericks' president. Now everyone will face one another in the first round of the N.B.A. playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>History sometimes has a tangled sense of humor.</p>
        <p>Don Nelson, the Golden State Warriors' coach, was the last person to get the Warriors to the playoffs, in 1994, a year before he left Golden State to coach the Knicks. His point guard in 1994 was Avery Johnson, who replaced Nelson as the coach of the Dallas Mavericks in 2005. Nelson's son, Donnie, was an assistant in Dallas and is now the Mavericks' president. Now everyone will face one another in the first round of the N.B.A. playoffs.</p>
        <p>''After spending 10 years in the Bay Area and knowing what those fans went through, to have Nellie come back and do that in a storybook-type scenario, I couldn't be happier for my dad,'' Donnie Nelson said Thursday in a telephone interview. ''All that being said, we're going to try to rip each other's throats out.''</p>
        <p>Golden State was the only team to sweep Dallas this season and no wonder, since Don Nelson nurtured the Mavericks' Dirk Nowitzki and Josh Howard and mentored Johnson. But while Donnie Nelson said that his father's institutional knowledge gives him an advantage, ''we're a different team than when he was here.''</p>
        <p>''We've constructed the Mavericks here to play with the Phoenixes and the Golden States of the world, as well as the East Coast teams,'' Donnie Nelson said.</p>
        <p>The Warriors were overjoyed just to reach the playoffs, clinching the No. 8 spot on the final day of the season. The No. 1-seeded Mavericks, meanwhile, are seeking to avenge their loss to Miami in last year's finals. ''Unless we accomplish the ultimate this year,'' Donnie said, ''in a lot of ways, it's a year for naught.''</p>
        <p>This season's Warriors team bears some resemblance to Nelson's 1994 version. Then, the Warriors' scoring average (107.9) was second in the N.B.A. to the Suns' (108.2). This year, the Warriors (106.5) were also second to the Suns (110.2).</p>
        <p>Don Nelson does not dwell on 1994. ''It wasn't a pleasant year,'' he said recently. ''Chris Webber was a rookie and he was very difficult for me to coach. We had a lot of injuries. We had Tim Hardaway out for the year.''</p>
        <p>Webber was traded and Nelson was fired by Golden State the next season, moving to New York. The Knicks fired him during a winning season and, beginning in 1997, Nelson grew the Mavericks from a perennial loser into a consistent offensive power.</p>
        <p>Nelson then returned to Golden State after a bitter parting with the Mavericks' owner, Mark Cuban.</p>
        <p>''In some respects, it's almost like a divorce,'' Donnie Nelson said. ''I care for and love both folks. It was a case where probably a parting of the ways is the best thing.''</p>
        <p>First-Round Redux</p>
        <p>Last year's first-round matchup between Cleveland and Washington ended in the sixth game with LeBron James's psych-out of Gilbert Arenas on the free-throw line. Knee surgery has now shelved Arenas, making this year's rematch between the two teams one that lacks sizzle.</p>
        <p>Chicago and Miami have the most compelling first-round matchup in the East, and it, too, is a repeat from last year's first round, which the Heat won in six games on the way to a title. The Bulls' Kirk Hinrich said his team should have won that series, and that he and his teammates are confident they will do so this time. They have home-court advantage and Ben Wallace in the middle.</p>
        <p>''They wanted us, they wanted this opportunity, so here it goes,'' noted the Heat's Dwyane Wade.</p>
        <p>There is one other first-round rematch: Phoenix vs. the Lakers, in a reprise of their thrilling seven-game series in 2006. But this time, Kobe bryant vs. the Suns will probably not have the same buzz. The Lakers lost 8 of their final 12 games, and the fast-paced Suns have two healthy post players, Amare Stoudemire and Kurt Thomas, who were not available last spring.</p>
        <p>You Again?</p>
        <p>Darko Milicic, the player the Pistons selected with the No. 2 pick of the 2003 draft, returns to Detroit in a familiar position: on the bench. Having been traded to Orlando last season, Milicic is nursing a sprained foot as the Magic prepares for a long-shot matchup against the No. 1-seeded Pistons in the first round. Orlando will miss Milicic's 7-foot shot-blocking presence. Meanwhile, there will be a real homecoming of sorts as Grant Hill, right, takes part in a playoff game for the Magic for the first time since he left Detroit to sign with Orlando in 2000. He first broke his ankle in Detroit, three games before the 2000 playoffs, and he has never been the same.</p>
        <p>New Man in Town</p>
        <p>Chris Bosh does not lend himself to nicknames, unlike his predecessor, Vince Carter. But Bosh, the unassuming fourth-year Toronto Raptors star, has effectively replaced Carter as a city icon, appearing on billboards around town.</p>
        <p>''That matchup, I welcome it,'' Bosh told reporters this week as he prepared to play Carter and the rest of the Nets in the first round. ''It's a turning point for this organization, and who better to play against than the guy who helped build this place up?''</p>
        <p>Bosh, 23, may be a reluctant self-promoter, but he understands how he is growing into a would-be superstar role. ''There's so many things that come with that job,'' Bosh said. ''I'm still trying to get into that superstar loop,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The McGrady Jinx</p>
        <p>Tracy McGrady, right, is zero for the first round, failing in the postseason five times with three teams: Toronto, Orlando and Houston. But when the Houston Rockets open at home against the Utah Jazz, McGrady will have the deepest, most experienced team he has ever been with in the postseason. And he has center Yao Ming, who is averaging 25 points a game. The prize for advancing would likely be a second-round matchup with Dallas.</p>
        <p>Hot Pairing</p>
        <p>The Denver Nuggets acquired Allen Iverson just for the playoffs and it took him a while to jell with Carmelo Anthony. But now the Nuggets are the hottest team in the N.B.A., entering the playoffs having won 10 of their past 11 games. Still, they will have to get past the San Antonio Spurs, who had the best record in the N.B.A. since the All-Star Game break, going 23-6.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
