<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hudson Gives Glimpse of Pitcher He Used to Be</title>
    <meta content="21mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/sports/baseball/21mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hudson, Tim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wright, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Willie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hudson Gives Glimpse of Pitcher He Used to Be</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hudson Gives Glimpse of Pitcher He Used to Be</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tim Hudson played in the American League until the 2005 season, and he never faced the Mets in an interleague game. So, most of the Mets know Hudson simply as a good pitcher, not as the intimidating right-hander with the all-galaxy splitter from his heyday with the Oakland A's.</p>
        <p>Hudson re-introduced himself last night: Mets, meet Hudson, circa 2001. He overwhelmed the previously scorching Mets with eight shutout innings before Rafael Soriano allowed three runs in the ninth in the Braves' 7-3 victory at Shea Stadium. In snapping the Mets' three-game winning streak, the Braves moved into first place in the division and improved to 3-1 against them this season. Hudson's success against the league has been even greater: Through four starts, he is 3-0 with a 0.62 earned run average.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tim Hudson overwhelmed the previously scorching Mets, shutting them out through eight innings before they scored three times in the ninth off Rafael Soriano.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tim Hudson played in the American League until the 2005 season, and he never faced the Mets in an interleague game. So, most of the Mets know Hudson simply as a good pitcher, not as the intimidating right-hander with the all-galaxy splitter from his heyday with the Oakland A's.</p>
        <p>Hudson re-introduced himself last night: Mets, meet Hudson, circa 2001. He overwhelmed the previously scorching Mets with eight shutout innings before Rafael Soriano allowed three runs in the ninth in the Braves' 7-3 victory at Shea Stadium. In snapping the Mets' three-game winning streak, the Braves moved into first place in the division and improved to 3-1 against them this season. Hudson's success against the league has been even greater: Through four starts, he is 3-0 with a 0.62 earned run average.</p>
        <p>''You make pitches like that, you bet you're going to feel confident,'' said Rick Peterson, who was Hudson's pitching coach in Oakland for five seasons before joining the Mets before the 2004 season.</p>
        <p>An offense that pounded 28 runs and 46 hits in its last three games mustered five singles off Hudson, who recorded 15 ground-ball outs and struck out three. He and Soriano also combined to hold David Wright without a hit for the first time in 26 games, ending his franchise-record streak.</p>
        <p>To make matters worse, Chipper Jones, the player Mets fans love to hate, hit a two-run homer and scored three times. And on a night when Manager Willie Randolph proudly wore No. 42 in honor of Jackie Robinson, his first time to show it off during the game was not a joyful one. It came in the seventh inning when he removed the reliever Pedro Feliciano with the bases loaded, two outs and the Braves leading, 5-0.</p>
        <p>Feliciano had relieved Mike Pelfrey, who allowed four runs and six hits in five innings and, for the second consecutive start, had difficulty with the command of his pitches. Last time, his sinker worked and his secondary pitches betrayed him. Last night, he threw some good sliders and changeups but could not locate his fastball. His sinker stayed up and prevented him from getting the ground-ball outs he is used to. The Atlanta hitters, not known for their patience, waited for a fastball count and then pounced.</p>
        <p>''I just kept missing,'' Pelfrey said. ''The ball kept running. It's just one of those things where if I can't locate it or put it where I want to, it's tough out there.''</p>
        <p>Kelly Johnson led off the game by driving a single to left, and with one out, Jones walked to the plate. Booed with every step, he calmly dug into the batter's box and proceeded to send a first-pitch fastball 430 feet, over the right-center field fence. It gave Jones 18 home runs and 48 runs batted in here, his most at a visiting ballpark. Is it any wonder that in 2004 Jones named his newborn son Shea?</p>
        <p>''I hope they are able to recreate it across the way,'' Jones said of the Mets' new ballpark, Citi Field, scheduled to open in 2009. But, he added, ''I am not going to name my kid Citi.''</p>
        <p>Pelfrey settled down temporarily and retired six consecutive batters into the third inning before walking Jones with two outs. He plunked the next hitter, Andruw Jones, in the midsection to provoke an angry glare. Brian McCann avenged the mistake by lining a ground-rule double into the right-field corner to score the Braves' third run. Pelfrey threw two quick strikes to the next hitter, Jeff Francoeur, but in his effort to waste a pitch, he bounced a slider past Paul Lo Duca to score Andruw Jones, and the Braves led, 4-0.</p>
        <p>''I was trying to get it down and away,'' Pelfrey said.</p>
        <p>By then, Hudson had not allowed a base runner. He retired the first 11 Mets before he gave up a two-out walk to Carlos Beltrán in the fourth and he did not allow a hit until Moises Alou's one-out single in the fifth. The Mets mounted their only threat in that inning, loading the bases with two outs for José Reyes, but he grounded sharply into a fielder's choice to waste their best opportunity.</p>
        <p>From 1999 to 2004, Hudson went 92-39 for Oakland, including a 20-6 season in 2000, when he finished second in the voting for the Cy Young award. Troubled on and off by injuries to his oblique muscle over his two inconsistent seasons in Atlanta, Hudson has resurrected his career. He is throwing harder, in the 93- to 94-mile-an-hour range, and has added a cutter to keep hitters honest. He is, Beltrán said, looking as dominant as he was earlier this decade, only in a different league. That is bad news for the Mets, who could see Hudson four more times this season.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Shawn Green hit a two-run homer in the ninth, his second hit of the game.  PAUL Lo DUCA went hitless in four at-bats last night, but at least he had a good day at the racetrack. Before coming to Shea Stadium, he watched his horse, a 3-year-old filly named Guts Game, win the second race at Aqueduct by ''about two lengths,'' he said. Lo Duca, who posed in the winner's circle with the filly, co-owns the horse with, among others, Patriots quarterback Tom Brady, the rapper Jay-Z and the ESPN sportscaster Kenny Mayne. It was Guts Game's first race in about four months, Lo Duca said, and she is training for a $100,000 stakes race at Belmont Park in mid-May. ''The racing secretary made the race earlier so I could go see it,'' Lo Duca said. ''That was great.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
