<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hurricane Tax Break Spurs Triple Projected Donations</title>
    <meta content="21donate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/us/21donate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Katrina (Storm)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Treasury Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E3DA163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hurricane Tax Break Spurs Triple Projected Donations</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Katrina Tax Break Spurs $11 Billion in Donations</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Treasury Dept estimates that tax break that was part of relief package to aid victims of Hurricane Katrina spurred $11 billion in donations to charity, more than triple what had been originally projected; incentive could cost government more than $3 billion in lost tax revenue, compared with $819 million estimated by Congress when it passed bill in 2005; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A tax break that was part of a relief package to aid victims of Hurricane Katrina spurred $11 billion in donations to charity, the Treasury Department has estimated, more than triple what had been originally projected.</p>
        <p>The incentive could cost the government more than $3 billion in lost tax revenue, compared with the $819 million estimated by Congress when it passed the bill in 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A tax break that was part of a relief package to aid victims of Hurricane Katrina could cost the government more than $3 billion in lost tax revenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A tax break that was part of a relief package to aid victims of Hurricane Katrina spurred $11 billion in donations to charity, the Treasury Department has estimated, more than triple what had been originally projected.</p>
        <p>The incentive could cost the government more than $3 billion in lost tax revenue, compared with the $819 million estimated by Congress when it passed the bill in 2005.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, ranking Republican on the Senate Finance Committee, said he was pleased that the incentive had produced a bonanza for charities.</p>
        <p>''A cost to the treasury to support charities is money well spent if the charities are providing good community service,'' Mr. Grassley said in a statement.</p>
        <p>The one-time tax break allowed donors who made cash gifts to almost any charity by the end of 2005 to deduct an amount equal to virtually 100 percent of their adjusted gross incomes, double the normal limit of 50 percent of income.</p>
        <p>The amount generated by the provision was disclosed by a Treasury Department official, David Joulfaian, in discussions with fund-raising consultants and researchers, several of them said. They insisted on anonymity because the figure had not been officially released.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Treasury Department, Andrew DeSouza, said Mr. Joulfaian cited the figure but cautioned that it was preliminary, ''an educated guess'' likely to change. Many charities mistakenly thought that the provision applied just to gifts to assist the hurricane victims.</p>
        <p>Other recipients, particularly universities, realized the potential and moved quickly. The American Technion Society, which raises money to support the Technion-Israel Institute of Technology in Israel, ran a direct-mail campaign promoting the potential tax benefits and posted information about it on its Web site.</p>
        <p>''We got about $6 million or $7 million worth of gifts that were directly attributable to that legislation, a significant portion of what we raised that year,'' Mark Hefter, director of planned giving at the society, said.</p>
        <p>American Technion received two $2 million gifts, far larger than its average gift of $75,000 to $100,000, Mr. Hefter said.</p>
        <p>Duke University received at least $3,602,835 as a result of the provision, and the law contributed to a 16 percent increase in the annual fund in 2005, said Leslie Trickey, an official in the Duke development office.</p>
        <p>''It was the first time we did a mass e-mail push from this office,'' Ms. Trickey said, ''and we got a very good response.''</p>
        <p>She said the university had similar success with a second e-mail alert to donors about another temporary incentive in the Pension Protection Act of 2006. It allows donors who are at least 70 1/2 years old to transfer up to $100,000 from their individual retirement accounts directly to charities without incurring the taxes that such withdrawals typically entail.</p>
        <p>Charities are trying to persuade Congress to make that incentive permanent, but the high cost of the hurricane provision may complicate that effort.</p>
        <p>New ''pay as you go'' budget rules require Congress to replace revenues lost to tax cuts with revenues raised elsewhere or through spending cuts. And lawmakers are already facing the need to cover a $1 trillion gap if they pass bills to shield all but the wealthiest taxpayers from the alternative minimum tax.</p>
        <p>''If lawmakers see that a charitable incentive they thought would cost X instead is costing four times X, it would not be surprising if they were more cautious in proceeding with any other charitable deduction,'' said Diana Aviv, president of the Independent Sector, a group that represents charities and foundations.</p>
        <p>''It will be up to the charitable community to demonstrate that extending the I.R.A. rollover provision won't similarly put them in a deeper hole than they anticipate,'' Ms. Aviv added.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Sharpe, a fund-raising consultant who had predicted that the hurricane tax break would generate up to $10 billion in donations, said he hoped that the increase in giving would help convince Congress that such incentives were beneficial.</p>
        <p>''Wealth is being concentrated among fewer and fewer people,'' Mr. Sharpe said. ''And it is absolutely ridiculous social policy to artificially limit how much wealthy people can give, especially at a time when the government is cutting social spending.''</p>
        <p>Patrick M. Rooney, director of research at the Indiana University Center on Philanthropy, said he was not sure that the hurricane tax break was evidence that giving could be expanded.</p>
        <p>''People are using these special incentives to pay off pledges early and make other gifts they were planning on making over the next several years,'' Mr. Rooney said. ''While there's no question that the Katrina tax break had a positive short-term impact, I don't know that anyone thinks this means charity will increase dramatically over the next several years.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
