<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toronto Hecklers Can't Wait to Welcome Back Carter</title>
    <meta content="21nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/sports/basketball/21nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toronto Hecklers Can't Wait to Welcome Back Carter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Toronto Hecklers Can’t Wait to Welcome Back Carter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Toronto Raptors hope to use the postseason as a steppingstone to something more. But first, they must prove they are over the Vince Carter era.</p>
        <p>Carter, meanwhile, would like to cleanse his reputation: Raptors fans have slighted him for what they perceive to be a lack of effort in his final days with the organization. He has played in front of heckling crowds in Toronto five times since he was traded to the Nets in 2004.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Toronto Raptors hope to use the postseason as a steppingstone to something more. But first, they must prove they are over the Vince Carter era.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Toronto Raptors hope to use the postseason as a steppingstone to something more. But first, they must prove they are over the Vince Carter era.</p>
        <p>Carter, meanwhile, would like to cleanse his reputation: Raptors fans have slighted him for what they perceive to be a lack of effort in his final days with the organization. He has played in front of heckling crowds in Toronto five times since he was traded to the Nets in 2004.</p>
        <p>Both sides can begin facing their challenges Saturday at Air Canada Center in a first-round N.B.A. Eastern Conference playoff series that features one of the most intriguing early subplots of the postseason.</p>
        <p>Carter said the jeers would not bother him. ''I enjoy it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, the Raptors' Chris Bosh, who has assumed the franchise-player role from Carter, was quoted in The Toronto Sun as saying that the series would be ''a turning point for this franchise, and who better to play against than the guy who helped build this place up?''</p>
        <p>Raptors Coach Sam Mitchell subsequently told his team not to comment about Carter.</p>
        <p>Despite the potential for drama, fans might have to work to see it. The first game of this best-of-seven series was given anything but a prime-time spot, 12:30 p.m. Game 2 on Tuesday will be televised on NBA TV, rather than ESPN or TNT.</p>
        <p>Every time Carter has played in Toronto since the trade, fans have booed him every time he has touched the ball. Two years ago, in Carter's first game in Toronto after the trade, many fans wore purple-and-white bibs bearing his No. 15. One fan mocked him by carrying crutches and wearing fake bandages. Another held up a sign that read, ''Half-man, Half-season,'' suggesting that Carter was injury prone.</p>
        <p>Carter said Raptors fans should overcome their bitterness.</p>
        <p>''They're the division champs,'' he said. ''They should feel good about that.''</p>
        <p>Some say such taunting will only fuel him. But the fans seemed to get into his head in the two games the Nets played in Toronto this season. The Nets lost both, and Carter averaged 14.5 points and shot 28.1 percent from the floor.</p>
        <p>But he is playing his best basketball of the season entering the playoffs. Over the Nets' nine games in April, he averaged 29 points, recorded two triple-doubles and received recognition as the Eastern Conference player of the month.</p>
        <p>''Whatever I need to do for the team, I'm going to do it,'' he said. ''And just set the tone from the beginning, and hopefully everybody just jumps on and we go from there.''</p>
        <p>Nets Coach Lawrence Frank said the series would not rest solely on Carter's shoulders.</p>
        <p>''We all have to rally behind him and stay in his corner,'' Frank said. ''If they boo him, they're booing all of us.''</p>
        <p>The sixth-seeded Nets (41-41) have at least one reason to be motivated to knock off the third-seeded Raptors (47-35): The Nets entered the season having won four of the previous five Atlantic Division titles, but the Raptors won it this season for the first time in franchise history. The Raptors have already unveiled their division-title banner.</p>
        <p>Jason Kidd, the face of the Nets, has insight into what Carter could face from Toronto's fans. During the 2002 Eastern Conference finals, the Boston Celtics' fans mercilessly taunted him and his family.</p>
        <p>''A lot of times, the great players, they never hear the crowd,'' Kidd said. ''It all depends on Vince. Does he have rabbit ears, or does he just go out there and do his job? I think Vince is up for this challenge.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
