<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>She Crashes the Boys' Club, Leaving Her Mark</title>
    <meta content="21carl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/arts/television/21carl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gugino, Carla</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DC163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>She Crashes the Boys' Club, Leaving Her Mark</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">She Crashes the Boys’ Club, Leaving Her Mark</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Doug Ellin was considering whom to cast in the role of Vince's new agent on the HBO hit ''Entourage,'' he realized that he had several tall orders to fill.</p>
        <p>The actor would have to portray a strong woman, one who could have a sharp business edge yet who, with her sexy demeanor, could still turn the adolescent-at-heart Vince and his hangers-on childhood buddies into so many wet noodles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carla Gugino returns to television as a strong, sharp agent in the HBO hit, “Entourage.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Doug Ellin was considering whom to cast in the role of Vince's new agent on the HBO hit ''Entourage,'' he realized that he had several tall orders to fill.</p>
        <p>The actor would have to portray a strong woman, one who could have a sharp business edge yet who, with her sexy demeanor, could still turn the adolescent-at-heart Vince and his hangers-on childhood buddies into so many wet noodles.</p>
        <p>The actor would also have to be able to hold her own against Jeremy Piven, who won an Emmy last year for his scenery-shredding portrayal of Ari Gold, the talent agent whose hubris both lifts Vincent Chase to stardom and causes Ari to fumble away his best client.</p>
        <p>And though Mr. Ellin plays down the consideration, he must have known that the presence of a powerful new female character would highlight the relative lack of strong female roles on the show, which has five male leads.</p>
        <p>''We needed someone who could be a strong, smart, powerful woman, sometimes sexy, and someone who made the guys feel like little boys,'' said Mr. Ellin, an executive producer and the creator of ''Entourage.''</p>
        <p>''We didn't know who that was when we were writing the script,'' he added, but it has quickly become clear that Carla Gugino is all those things, and more.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gugino, whose turn as Amanda, the new agent to Adrian Grenier's Vince, continues tomorrow, is not an actress whose experience would seem to have pointed toward her current role.</p>
        <p>She has starred on television, most famously as the lead in ''Karen Sisco,'' an ABC drama about a federal marshal that didn't last through its first season. Eleven years ago, one of her first big roles was as the girlfriend to Michael J. Fox's character in ''Spin City.'' To audiences of a certain, much younger, age, she is best known as the mother in the ''Spy Kids'' movie trilogy.</p>
        <p>All of which barely scratched the surface of her acting talent. She has impressed audiences and critics on Broadway with her performances in 2004 as Maggie in Arthur Miller's ''After the Fall'' and in 2006 as Catharine Holly in Tennessee Williams's ''Suddenly Last Summer.'' Ben Brantley, chief theater critic for The New York Times, said her performance as Catharine evoked ''memories of a young Elizabeth Taylor in the film version.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gugino, 35, said in an interview this week: ''I kind of knew it wasn't going to be until my 30s that I really hit my stride as an actor. I kind of always looked like an ingénue, but I never acted like one because as soon as I opened my mouth in those movies,'' and out came her husky, self-assured voice, ''it was, ooh, she's a little too much perhaps.''</p>
        <p>If her voice gives her older tint, it also lends her a smoldering quality that is in tune with the sex-charged atmosphere that is characteristic of ''Entourage.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not interested in playing a sexy character just for that reason, or playing a provocative character for that reason,'' she said. ''But if that's an aspect of a more interesting character, that's an aspect I want to explore.''</p>
        <p>She credits much of her self-assurance to a childhood that carried a certain variety of experience: she alternated between a so-called normal environment with her father, an orthodontist in Sarasota, Fla., and stints living with her bohemian mother in a tepee in Northern California. There was also a touch of Hollywood; she was steered toward her first acting class by her aunt, Carol Merrill, the hostess on ''Let's Make a Deal.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gugino was aware of the dangers of trying to compete with Mr. Piven, whose theatrics as Ari can sometimes threaten to crowd out everyone else on screen.</p>
        <p>''My tendency as an actor is, when there's a certain energy, I feel a challenge to match it, to come up to that plate and play on the same level,'' she said. ''What I realized with this is that this role wasn't about that; it was actually the opposite. I, as Amanda, had to watch Ari do all of his cartwheels and all of his everything, and then say, 'You're full of it.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gugino is careful to state that she believes that there are plenty of strong female actors on the show, including Beverly D'Angelo, who plays Ari's business partner, and Debi Mazar, Vince's publicist, who has been absent from the show recently but will return later this year. And, she noted, even the show's plentiful eye candy, the women who pop in and have affairs with the boys, are often played by funny and respected actors as well.</p>
        <p>But Amanda brings something different to the show. ''I do think it was a conscious choice of Doug to make a character who was a woman and who was strong and can go toe to toe with Ari,'' she said. ''She is commanding in her profession and she also has a sexual dynamic with the characters, and that I think is not that common on this show.''</p>
        <p>She said that she believed that the character of Amanda was very present in real-life Hollywood. ''Right now I think there is a new breed of women agents, and it probably carries over to other areas of business as well, where they are fully women: they're stylish, they're pretty, but they are incredibly good at what they do and incredibly well respected,'' she said. ''I think that there's a tendency for actors who play strong women to have them take on all the worst characteristics of men, to become cold and detached and hardened.''</p>
        <p>As will become evident beginning on tomorrow's show, Amanda is not afraid of addressing the sexual tension that hangs over her relationship with Vince. When we last saw her on screen, Amanda was being pushed around: Vince would not commit to a new movie, and his manager, Eric, would not return her phone calls.</p>
        <p>But this week, she pushes back.</p>
        <p>''I never heard Ari talk to Vince like that,'' says Turtle, one of the entourage, as the boys leave Amanda's office.</p>
        <p>Drama, Vince's brother and an actor wannabe, says: ''We could hear the screaming right through the door. Kinda hot.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Ellin and his writing staff decided how to address that heat, he said, there was considerable anxiety at how everyone would respond -- Ms. Gugino, HBO and the audience, particularly the female members.</p>
        <p>''We were beyond nervous,'' Mr. Ellin said. ''There were big fights at this office over how we did it.'' The dialogue includes a line that is certain to make viewers sit up straight. ''That line was written by a young female writer here,'' Mr. Ellin said, but it produced a level of angst ''more than any scene in the history of the show.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gugino said that when she got the script, ''I thought it was fantastic.''</p>
        <p>''This is a woman who thinks like an agent,'' she continued. ''There's a problem of chemistry that's going on here; Amanda is fine, she can work perfectly well under those circumstances, but Vince can't. So she realizes that this is not going to be good for a long-term relations, and she has a solution.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
