<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Isles' Late Comeback Falls Short, and Sabres Advance</title>
    <meta content="21islanders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/sports/hockey/21islanders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hill, Sean</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Miller, Ryan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dipietro, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0D9163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Isles' Late Comeback Falls Short, and Sabres Advance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Isles’ Late Comeback Falls Short, and Sabres Advance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO, April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the end, the Islanders still had a chance. The team that had to win its final four games of the regular season simply to qualify for the playoffs had a chance to tie Game 5 of its opening-round playoff series with nine seconds remaining on a shot from close range by Miroslav Satan.</p>
        <p>But Buffalo Sabres goaltender Ryan Miller stopped him on a brilliant sprawling save.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After pulling within a goal with seven minutes left, the Islanders pressed their attack, but they could not get the puck past Sabres goalkeeper Ryan Miller, who finished with 30 saves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the end, the Islanders still had a chance. The team that had to win its final four games of the regular season simply to qualify for the playoffs had a chance to tie Game 5 of its opening-round playoff series with nine seconds remaining on a shot from close range by Miroslav Satan.</p>
        <p>But Buffalo Sabres goaltender Ryan Miller stopped him on a brilliant sprawling save.</p>
        <p>With that, the Islanders lost, 4-3, and their season -- one in which they seemed to be continually trying to overcome bad breaks -- finally ended. The Sabres won the series, four games to one, after a furious Islanders rally fell short.</p>
        <p>The loss was the Islanders' third in a row, and it came on a day when the team was rocked by a suspension.</p>
        <p>Hours before the game, the National Hockey League announced that defenseman Sean Hill had become the first player suspended under the league's policy for testing for performance-enhancing drugs. The policy has been in effect since the new collective-bargaining agreement was signed in July 2005.</p>
        <p>With Hill out of the lineup, the Islanders finally cracked under strains that began to show earlier in the week. But not before mounting a comeback from a 3-0 deficit against the Sabres, who led the league in scoring and had the best record in the N.H.L. during the regular season.</p>
        <p>With seven minutes remaining, the Islanders pulled to 4-3 on a goal by defenseman Chris Campoli. They continued to pepper Miller, who made a number of clutch saves, none more important than his spectacular blind stop of Satan in the game's waning seconds.</p>
        <p>After that save, Miller smothered the puck, preventing Alexei Yashin from poking in the rebound. Miller finished with 30 saves.</p>
        <p>''We were close,'' said Ryan Smyth, the Islanders' leading scorer in the series with 4 points. ''Close isn't good enough. If you think that, that's the wrong mentality, in my mind.''</p>
        <p>Buffalo appeared to put the game away by jumping to a 3-0 lead. The rookie forward Drew Stafford scored first, wheeling into the slot with the puck and shoveling a backhand past Islanders goalie Rick DiPietro for his first career playoff goal.</p>
        <p>Buffalo took a 2-0 lead 39 seconds into the second period. Daniel Brière stripped the puck from Satan in the Islanders' zone, then fed a pass to Jason Pominville in the slot. Pominville beat DiPietro to the short side.</p>
        <p>Derek Roy scored Buffalo's third goal on a rebound at 11 minutes 29 seconds of the second.</p>
        <p>DiPietro was not as sharp as he had been in three previous games. He finished with 23 saves.</p>
        <p>The Islanders' offense came to life early in the third period. Satan scored at 4:22 when he sent a backhand along the ice.</p>
        <p>Just over two minutes later, Maxim Afinogenov restored the Sabres' three-goal lead.</p>
        <p>But Trent Hunter pulled the score to 4-2 at 9:43, putting in the rebound of a shot from the point by Bruno Gervais. Campoli scored three minutes later, setting up Miller's star turn.</p>
        <p>''We got to that point where we were holding on,'' Miller said of his save on Satan. ''That was a heck of a battle. They really turned it up in the third.''</p>
        <p>Last Saturday, the Islanders tied the series at one game apiece, receiving an emotional boost and a 3-2 victory in Game 2, when DiPietro returned after missing three weeks with postconcussion symptoms.</p>
        <p>But in Games 3 and 4 at Nassau Coliseum, the Islanders showed signs that they were coming unglued. A disputed goal by the Sabres in Game 3, and a disputed nongoal by the Islanders in Game 4, began a kind of bad luck theme.</p>
        <p>Then came the news that Hill was being suspended for 20 games for violating the league's policy on performance-enhancing drugs. Hill, 37, was in Buffalo on Friday, but he did not participate in the pregame skate.</p>
        <p>General Manager Garth Snow told reporters before the game that the Islanders supported the suspension. He refused to answer questions, and Hill's teammates refused to comment on the suspension.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
