<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Brief Walk Through Time At Scholastic</title>
    <meta content="21interview" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/21/business/21interview.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1841761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SATURDAY INTERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scholastic Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowling, J K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Harry Potter (Book Series)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Scholastic Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rowling, J K</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DB163EF932A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Brief Walk Through Time At Scholastic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Brief Walk Through Time at Scholastic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from interview with Scholastic Corp chairman-chief executive Richard Robinson; he stresses that Harry Potter book revenue makes up small part of company's total and intimates that there could be another best-selling series from Harry Potter author J K Rowling; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wandering through the headquarters of Scholastic in Manhattan is like taking a trip back through time and childish dreams, to a fantastical kindergarten with brightly colored columns and desk dividers and, at the very end, a huge playroom filled with toys like Clifford the Big Red Dog and Goosebumps and Captain Underpants and, of course, J. K. Rowling's books about Harry Potter and his comrades.</p>
        <p>The playroom, actually the company's conference room, was the site of an interview with Richard Robinson, 69, only the second chief executive the company has had in its 86-year history; the first was his father.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard Robinson, the chief executive of Scholastic, spoke about the success of the Harry Potter books and intimated that there could be another best-selling series to come  from the same author.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wandering through the headquarters of Scholastic in Manhattan is like taking a trip back through time and childish dreams, to a fantastical kindergarten with brightly colored columns and desk dividers and, at the very end, a huge playroom filled with toys like Clifford the Big Red Dog and Goosebumps and Captain Underpants and, of course, J. K. Rowling's books about Harry Potter and his comrades.</p>
        <p>The playroom, actually the company's conference room, was the site of an interview with Richard Robinson, 69, only the second chief executive the company has had in its 86-year history; the first was his father.</p>
        <p>Now chairman and chief executive of a $2.2 billion company, Mr. Robinson began by stressing that the Harry Potter book revenue makes up a small part of the company's total and he intimated that there could be another best-selling series to come -- from the same author.</p>
        <p>Following are excerpts of the conversation:</p>
        <p>Q. So where is Scholastic bound after the last Harry Potter book? Can we believe it's the last book?</p>
        <p>A. We can believe this is the last book on Harry Potter. We look at Harry Potter as a wonderful icing on top of the cake, but we are essentially a children's book and media company, with our own distribution network and book clubs. There's no question that Harry Potter gave us a big boost. It brought us name recognition, but Harry Potter never exceeded 8 percent of our total revenue.</p>
        <p>Q. How did you get Harry Potter in the first place -- it was first published in England, wasn't it?</p>
        <p>A. She had written her first book, and it was published in England. She then went through the English version of the Yellow Pages and looked for an agent. She says she just liked the name Christopher Little -- she's a whimsical character -- and he directed the auction for rights outside the U.K. We spotted the book -- Arthur Levine, an editor here, did -- and we bid $105,000, which was quite a bit for an unknown author.</p>
        <p>Q. Going back to our first question, I noticed you emphasized the words Harry Potter when you said Ms. Rowling's last book on Harry Potter. Do you have a first option on any other series she might be doing?</p>
        <p>A. No, but we refer to ourselves as her U.S. publisher and she's very loyal to us and we're very loyal to her. We'll keep working together. It's less likely we won't get it. It's more likely it won't be another Harry Potter.</p>
        <p>Q. The company your father founded is now 86 years old. Have you seen a lessening of interest in reading among children, with the Internet and all the new technologies?</p>
        <p>A. NAPE [National Assessment of Educational Progress] statistics will tell you there has been some reduction in reading skill. But there were always a lot of people who didn't read much.</p>
        <p>Q. So what are you doing in places like China and India?</p>
        <p>A. We are reaching out. We're a global company in 65 countries, and offices in 15 of them, including China, India and Southeast Asia. There is a different situation there, with a growing middle class with dedicated parents driving their kids to achieve, and the kids are desperate to learn and to succeed. It's that group we're focusing on in Asia. Our pricing there is quite low; they don't pay $5 for a book, they might pay $1 or $2.</p>
        <p>Q. So you're not bewailing the fact that kids are not reading as well, or as much, as they used to?</p>
        <p>A. No, not really. If you look at the deep research, you'll see that technology can help kids learn to read. After all, to get stuff off the search engines, you have to be able to read. I see this as a 20-year process that began maybe five years ago.</p>
        <p>Q. So you're optimistic?</p>
        <p>A. We've struggled with what I'd call words on a printed page, and with all the new technologies. I would say Scholastic is at the forefront of those new technologies.</p>
        <p>Q. Getting back to Harry Potter, when is the last book coming out?''</p>
        <p>A. Well, ''Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows'' comes out on July 21st. We think slightly more copies than the preceding ones, which have gone up every time.</p>
        <p>Q. Yes, speaking of how it ends, we've heard that two people get killed. Can you say who they are? And people also want to know if Harry and Hermione finally, er, get together in the end?</p>
        <p>A. (Laughs) I don't even know. Really. There's a small number who read the book. I don't.</p>
        <p>An extended version of this interview is online at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY INTERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
