<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thousands Are Laid Off. What's New?</title>
    <meta content="02carr" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/business/media/02carr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA EQUATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D91E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thousands Are Laid Off. What's New?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Thousands Are Laid Off at Circuit City. What’s New?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CARR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carr, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When executives at Circuit City decided last Wednesday to cut costs by laying off 3,400 of their most experienced salesclerks, they undoubtedly went through a number of calculations: that they could save $250 million over two years; that consumers are inured to bad service; and that the layoffs would be a one-day blip in the news.</p>
        <p>They were right about the last part. After hearing a fairly expansive report on public radio's Marketplace late Wednesday, I woke up the next morning eager to read more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Media outlets could not be blamed for having a little fatigue when it comes to layoffs. But with Circuit City, there are larger issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When executives at Circuit City decided last Wednesday to cut costs by laying off 3,400 of their most experienced salesclerks, they undoubtedly went through a number of calculations: that they could save $250 million over two years; that consumers are inured to bad service; and that the layoffs would be a one-day blip in the news.</p>
        <p>They were right about the last part. After hearing a fairly expansive report on public radio's Marketplace late Wednesday, I woke up the next morning eager to read more.</p>
        <p>USA Today ran a short article on the front page, The Wall Street Journal ran a brief on B4, The New York Times published a wire report inside its business pages, while The Washington Post and The Los Angeles Times gave the news a bit more room.</p>
        <p>Only the piece in The Baltimore Sun really explored the broader implications, while most of the coverage stuck to the usual suspects and themes. There were a few quick mentions on the evening news, but I saw no cable-talk umbrage at what this meant. And the next day, it was yesterday's news.</p>
        <p>Media outlets could not be blamed for having a little fatigue when it comes to layoffs, which have become an organic part of American life. With Detroit laying off more than 70,000 people in the last few years, the approximately 8 percent of Circuit City's work force who got the heave-ho as a result of a ''wage management initiative'' -- yet another advance in corporate-speak -- do not seem like a big deal. (Nor did the news have legs on Wall Street, apparently. On Friday, Circuit City closed at $18.53, down 25 cents from the week before.)</p>
        <p>But there are larger issues here. Circuit City, pushed by other big retailers and the consumer's desire for low prices, could not compete. So they fired the cream of their work force, not even giving those employees a chance to re-apply immediately for their job at lower wages until after a cooling-off period of 10 weeks. In doing so, the company engaged in a kind of domestic outsourcing.</p>
        <p>''The fact that this was a nonstory is as emblematic of our times as the firings themselves,'' said Harley Shaiken, a professor who teaches labor issues at the University of California, Berkeley. ''What makes this troubling is that this is not an auto parts supplier in Michigan under global pressure; this is a retail giant jettisoning its most experienced workers because it is under pressure from the Best Buy across the street. That is a big story.''</p>
        <p>In the 1980s and '90s, the heroic narrative of business reporting began to focus on executives, in which a new pantheon -- executives like Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates and, um, Jeffrey K. Skilling -- were touted as beings who had left the gravitational pull of traditional economics.</p>
        <p>Even now, the corner office is where reporters usually go when it's time to cover business. According to Christopher R. Martin, an associate professor of journalism at Miami University, of the top 25 newspapers in the country, only four have reporters assigned to the labor beat.</p>
        <p>''Newspapers have shifted from going after mass audiences to targeting upscale audiences. This is a great story,'' Mr. Martin said, referring to the Circuit City layoffs, ''but it's about working people. There have been dual wage systems before, but here you have something completely different -- the wholesale firing of people who did their jobs well.''</p>
        <p>Last summer, I needed some gadgets for a multimedia project, so I walked in to a Best Buy. A young man walked me around the floor, assembling a bag of components before promising me that it would all work. It did and I've been back to Best Buy twice since then, not because I checked prices, but because I knew they had well-priced merchandise with knowledgeable sales help.</p>
        <p>Circuit City seems to have forgotten that the customer interaction -- the user interface, to use contemporary language -- is their point of difference in an age when consumers can have perfect pricing information with the click of a mouse. ''In a service economy where all the books say you are supposed to put the customer first, Circuit City is doing exactly the opposite,'' Mr. Martin said.</p>
        <p>True, these aren't the kind of union jobs with benefits and wages that made America what it is today. But increasingly, America is nation of clerks -- not adolescents in their first jobs, but heads of households struggling to get by on the desiccated compensation that working in retail provides. Newsrooms, which should know something about layoffs, have trouble fathoming that many people work in retail because it is the only work they can find.</p>
        <p>In a bit of happy coincidence, The New York Times did have an article on Thursday in its business section demonstrating that the top 300,000 Americans had almost as much income as the bottom 150 million Americans. The explanation was just a flip of the page away in the brief about Circuit City.</p>
        <p>The Circuit City pratfall does have an executive level narrative as well: if you add up salary, bonus, stock options, and other perks, Philip J. Schoonover, chief executive, and W. Alan McCollough, chairman, received almost $10 million in various kinds of compensation last year for steering the company to its imperiled state.</p>
        <p>Circuit City retains a rhetorical commitment to the people it just axed on its Web site: ''Our associates are our greatest assets. We expect every associate to demonstrate that they respect and value others for their efforts, their knowledge and the diversity that they bring.''</p>
        <p>By Thursday, there was a lot less of that to go around. But it's clear the only time the clerk at a big-box store is going to get any ink is when he fetches you a replacement cartridge for your printer.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA EQUATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
