<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quake Hits South Pacific, Setting Off Tsunami</title>
    <meta content="02quake" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/world/asia/02quake.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tsunamis and Tidal Waves</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Solomon Islands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hawaii</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Geological Survey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Solomon Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Solomon Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tidal Waves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tidal Waves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Solomon Islands</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E7D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quake Hits South Pacific, Setting Off Tsunami</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Quake Hits South Pacific, Setting Off Tsunami</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS; Tim Johnston contributed to the story from Sydney, Australia, and Kenneth Chang from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth; Chang, Kenneth; Johnston, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>SINGAPORE, Monday, April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Powerful undersea earthquake strikes off Solomon Islands, sending tsunami crashing ashore and setting off warnings around South Pacific; several people are killed, dozens of buildings collapse and at least one coastal village is destroyed, but fears of major tsunami appear to be unfounded; earthquake is measured at about 8.0 by US Geological Survey in Hawaii; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A powerful undersea earthquake struck early Monday morning off the Solomon Islands, sending a tsunami crashing hundreds of yards onshore and setting off tsunami warnings around the South Pacific.</p>
        <p>Several people were killed in the Solomon Islands, dozens of buildings collapsed and at least one coastal village was destroyed, according to early news reports from the area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 8.0 quake off the Solomon Islands sent a tsunami crashing onshore, killing several people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A powerful undersea earthquake struck early Monday morning off the Solomon Islands, sending a tsunami crashing hundreds of yards onshore and setting off tsunami warnings around the South Pacific.</p>
        <p>Several people were killed in the Solomon Islands, dozens of buildings collapsed and at least one coastal village was destroyed, according to early news reports from the area.</p>
        <p>But fears of a major tsunami around the Pacific Rim, like the devastating tsunami of Dec. 26, 2004, appeared to be unfounded.</p>
        <p>Tsunami alerts were issued in Australia, Indonesia, Papua New Guinea and as far north as Hawaii but were later withdrawn. Beaches were closed and ferry services were suspended until the danger had passed in threatened coastal areas of Australia.</p>
        <p>The earthquake, measured at about 8.0 by the United States Geological Survey in Hawaii, struck at 7:40 A.M. local time (6:40 P.M. Sunday Eastern time) . The survey placed the epicenter 6.2 miles under the ocean and 25 miles from the coastline.</p>
        <p>Within minutes, residents reported, a wave several yards high flooded villages along the west coast of the Solomon Islands.</p>
        <p>Reports of death and damage were sketchy in the first hours after the earthquake.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press cited a man reached by telephone at the police station in Gizo, just 25 miles from the epicenter, as saying that up to eight people had died, including six children. The news agency said the line was cut before the man gave his name.</p>
        <p>Sky News, a British news service, cited Julian Mcleod of the National Disaster Management Office in the Solomon Islands capital, Honiara, as saying only three deaths had been reported.</p>
        <p>Reached by telephone, Jacob Pitisoba, 30, owner of Phoebe's Guesthouse in Gizo, the closest town to the epicenter, said two fatalities had been reported there -- an infant who drowned when the wave hit his house and a woman who was killed when a building collapsed.</p>
        <p>''The ground moved very strongly,'' he said. ''It was so big, so strong. It was lucky for all of us in Gizo because we were awake and weren't in our beds.''</p>
        <p>''It was supposed to be high tide, so when we saw the sea going out we ran up to the high ground,'' he said. ''All the buildings on the coast are gone, washed away by the tsunami. There's nothing left.''</p>
        <p>Harry Wickham, a hotel worker in Gizo, told New Zealand Television that a torrent of water 10 feet high poured through the town, smashing buildings along the waterfront.</p>
        <p>The earthquake was caused by a sudden slippage where the Australian and Pacific tectonic plates crash together near the Solomon islands, the National Earthquake information Center of United States Geological Survey reported.</p>
        <p>''It's not surprising for it to generate a tsunami,'' said Rafael Abreu, a geologist at the center.</p>
        <p>The center said on its Web site that the original earthquake was followed by severe aftershocks with magnitudes of 6.7 and 6.4 within an hour and a half.</p>
        <p>Mid-ocean earthquakes of a magnitude 8.0 can generate tsunamis that cause catastrophic damage close to the epicenter, and the shallow depth made it more likely that the quake lifted the ocean floor to create the wave.</p>
        <p>But generally a tsunami from an earthquake of that magnitude is not powerful enough to inflict damage thousands of miles away.</p>
        <p>In the case of the Solomon Islands earthquake, the sea floor was shallower to the north and deeper to the south.</p>
        <p>''Our simulation model indicates to us the beam of energy of the tsunami was going to be directed to the south,'' said Victor Sardina, a geophysicist at the Pacific Tsunami Warning Center in Hawaii. That spared the islands to the north and the waves' energy had largely dissipated before reaching Australia and New Zealand.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
