<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Avery Saves His Best for Rangers' Biggest Game of Season</title>
    <meta content="02rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/hockey/02rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Toronto Maple Leafs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Maple Leafs</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Avery Saves His Best for Rangers' Biggest Game of Season</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers’ Avery Saves His Best for Biggest Game of Season</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When his first shot flew into the Toronto net, Rangers forward Sean Avery pumped his fists with an intensity that stood out, even for him. He skated to the boards and pounded on the glass as the Madison Square Garden crowd roared. His goal came early, tying the score at 1-1 last night, but it set off a spark that pushed the Rangers to their biggest victory of the season.</p>
        <p>Avery ignited a 7-2 demolition of the Maple Leafs, a victory that puts the Rangers 2 points from clinching the playoff spot they have been chasing so desperately.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers are 16-5-5 since Sean Avery arrived in a midseason trade and helped them climb into the playoff race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When his first shot flew into the Toronto net, Rangers forward Sean Avery pumped his fists with an intensity that stood out, even for him. He skated to the boards and pounded on the glass as the Madison Square Garden crowd roared. His goal came early, tying the score at 1-1 last night, but it set off a spark that pushed the Rangers to their biggest victory of the season.</p>
        <p>Avery ignited a 7-2 demolition of the Maple Leafs, a victory that puts the Rangers 2 points from clinching the playoff spot they have been chasing so desperately.</p>
        <p>''We didn't win anything yet, but I think we made a huge step forward to make the playoffs,'' said the Rangers' captain, Jaromir Jagr, who then heaped praise on the player who has become the team's primary spark plug since he joined the Rangers in a midseason trade. ''He is playing great. He was the difference tonight, no question.''</p>
        <p>Avery finished with two goals and one assist and did a masterly job of irritating many of Toronto's players, including goading the Leafs agitator Darcy Tucker into a first-period fight. Avery played so hard that he seemed to lift his entire team with him, and the Garden crowd chanted his name in appreciation after he scored.</p>
        <p>''It's a passionate building, an amazing building to play in,'' Avery said. ''I'm just happy they enjoy what I bring to the team. I'm just playing hard.''</p>
        <p>Avery came into this game understanding just how important it was. The Rangers had not played well in losing to Montreal and remained sloppy in a victory against Philadelphia on Saturday night. They needed a momentum boost and badly wanted to use their second-to-last home game to solidify their playoff hopes.</p>
        <p>''I was definitely nervous this afternoon,'' Avery said.</p>
        <p>At lunch with Brendan Shanahan, he said: ''I was just thinking I wanted to play well and have a big game. I didn't really think I was going get a couple of goals or anything like that. I just wanted to really play well and try and be a difference.''</p>
        <p>A Shanahan shot led to Avery's first goal, when Leafs defenseman Carlo Colaiacovo failed to clear the puck and it ended up on Avery's stick. That set off the fist-pumping as he erased a 1-0 Toronto lead 5 minutes 19 seconds into the first period.</p>
        <p>The teams emerged from the period tied, 2-2, but the Rangers grabbed control of the game in the second. Forward Ryan Callahan had his shot bounce off Toronto goalie Andrew Raycroft, over his head, off his back and into the goal only 1:35 in, and Avery set up a goal by Martin Straka by diving to send the puck toward Straka after he had tripped and fanned on a shot. Avery's second goal came late in the second period, gave the Rangers a 5-2 lead and turned a game into a celebration.</p>
        <p>It was, largely, a celebration of Avery.</p>
        <p>Since he arrived in a trade Feb. 5, the Rangers are 16-5-5. He has 8 goals and 11 assists in those 26 games. But his impact is counted not only in points but in how much tougher the Rangers have become since he arrived.</p>
        <p>''What he's done, he's been able to elevate the passion meter in a lot of our players,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said. ''Not that it wasn't there in the first place, but he has served as the catalyst.''</p>
        <p>He has done it with the kind of spunk the Rangers could have only hoped for when they sent forward Jason Ward and two prospects to Los Angeles for him. He treats opponents with disdain, battering them with trash talk.</p>
        <p>He went hard on Tucker through the first period, finally baiting him into a fight, which Avery got the best of. He skated to the penalty box with a smile.</p>
        <p>He would not say what he said to get to Tucker. ''Darcy's always been a whiner,'' Avery, 26, said. ''You just say that you don't like his hair, and he'll be upset.''</p>
        <p>Thanks to the lopsided outcome, Tucker, like the rest of the Maple Leafs, could say little in response after the game. Tucker, in fact, complimented Avery on how well he played.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to take the high road,'' Tucker said. ''He is what he is.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers, on the verge of completing the playoff push they started when Avery arrived, appreciate all that.</p>
        <p>''I think he brings some confidence,'' goalie Henrik Lundqvist said. ''We don't have that many players that talk out there. He talks all the time, even in the locker room. What you see out there is pretty much who he is. He probably played his best game out there.''</p>
        <p>It could not have come at a better time, or on a bigger stage.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
