<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kohlberg Kravis Near Deal to Buy Credit-Card Processor</title>
    <meta content="02deal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/business/02deal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070403T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">First Data Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Merced, Michael J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit and Money Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">First Data Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E1D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kohlberg Kravis Near Deal to Buy Credit-Card Processor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kohlberg Kravis Near Deal to Buy First Data</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and MICHAEL J. de la MERCED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; De La Merced, Michael J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First Data, one of nation's biggest credit-card processing companies, is near deal to be sold for almost $27 billion to private equity firm Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Co (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>First Data, one of the nation's largest credit-card processing companies, is near a deal to be sold for nearly $27 billion to the private equity firm Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company, according to people involved in the transaction. The deal for First Data, which controls the STAR payment network, is expected to be announced this morning.</p>
        <p>First Data serves 4.9 million businesses and 1,900 card issuers. Its offerings run the gamut of payment methods, including credit and debit cards and Internet and mobile-phone commerce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The credit-card processor is near a deal to be sold for nearly $27 billion to the private equity firm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>First Data, one of the nation's largest credit-card processing companies, is near a deal to be sold for nearly $27 billion to the private equity firm Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company, according to people involved in the transaction. The deal for First Data, which controls the STAR payment network, is expected to be announced this morning.</p>
        <p>First Data serves 4.9 million businesses and 1,900 card issuers. Its offerings run the gamut of payment methods, including credit and debit cards and Internet and mobile-phone commerce.</p>
        <p>The company, founded in 1971, became one of the first processors of credit-card payments. It was acquired by American Express in chunks between 1980 and 1983. American Express spun off First Data as an independent company in 1992.</p>
        <p>The company is an attractive target for private equity firms like Kohlberg Kravis, which have increasingly sought out larger companies with steady cash flow.</p>
        <p>The deal, which would rank among the 10 largest buyouts ever, signals the continued might of private equity firms, aided by a flood of cheap debt and eager institutional investors like pension funds.</p>
        <p>Kohlberg Kravis, one of the largest private equity firms, has had a hand in several of them, including the $45 billion bid for the Texas energy utility TXU, the largest buyout ever; the $33 billion transaction for HCA, the hospital operator; and its $31 billion deal for RJR Nabisco, which was chronicled in the book ''Barbarians at the Gate.''</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the First Data deal, Kohlberg Kravis is expected to pay $34 a share in cash, which represents a premium of 26.4 percent over First Data's closing price on Friday of $26.90.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Kohlberg Kravis declined to comment. Representatives of First Data could not be reached.</p>
        <p>While First Data, based in based in Greenwood Village, Colo., is considered one of the leaders in the payment-processing industry, it has lost ground in recent years to its main rival, Total System Services, which modernized its processing systems at a faster pace. First Data lost prominent customers like JPMorgan Chase as a result.</p>
        <p>First Data had profit of $1.51 billion on revenue of $7.08 billion in 2006. The company has about 27,000 employees.</p>
        <p>In 2005, First Data brought Henry C. Duques, its former chairman and chief executive, out of retirement to replace his handpicked successor, Charles T. Fote, who had stepped down citing personal reasons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duques has since overseen the most ambitious effort to overhaul First Data. Last year, the company spun off Western Union, the 156-year-old money wire service and onetime telegraph courier. Acquired in 1995, Western Union quickly became First Data's crown jewel, growing at a torrid pace while other parts of the company faltered.</p>
        <p>First Data has recently pursued an aggressive acquisition strategy, buying four companies over the last two months to expand its network and its data analysis capabilities. In January, First Data became one of several companies under investigation by the New York attorney general's office for improperly sharing nonpublic information with hedge funds.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 3, 2007, Tuesday  An article yesterday about First Data, the credit-card processing company that is near a deal to be acquired by the private equity firm Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company, misidentified in some copies the payment network controlled by First Data. It is the STAR network, not the NYCE.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 3, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about First Data, the credit-card processing company that is near a deal to be acquired by the private equity firm Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company, misidentified in some copies the payment network controlled by First Data. It is the STAR network, not the NYCE.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
