<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="02diary" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/nyregion/02diary.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837530"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Intrepid Sea-Air-Space Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Working at the information desk of the Intrepid Sea, Air and Space Museum, we received requests for information not only about the aircraft carrier and other exhibits in the museum complex but also about the city itself.</p>
        <p>One day a young couple approached and asked me how to get to Greenwich Village. Using both subway and bus maps, I gave detailed instructions, adding that not only was the Village a charming place for an evening walk, but that it also had a wide variety of wonderful, inexpensive restaurants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Subway riders disagree on how best to direct a woman to the Brooklyn Academy of Music, until one takes charge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>Working at the information desk of the Intrepid Sea, Air and Space Museum, we received requests for information not only about the aircraft carrier and other exhibits in the museum complex but also about the city itself.</p>
        <p>One day a young couple approached and asked me how to get to Greenwich Village. Using both subway and bus maps, I gave detailed instructions, adding that not only was the Village a charming place for an evening walk, but that it also had a wide variety of wonderful, inexpensive restaurants.</p>
        <p>They listened attentively and then asked if there was anything else they should see while they were downtown.</p>
        <p>I asked if they had been to Chinatown, and they said they had not. Again using the maps, I encouraged them to go, again assuring them that they would love the sights and the abundance of excellent and inexpensive Chinese food.</p>
        <p>They thanked me, and as they turned to go I asked, ''So, where are you from?''</p>
        <p>The response: Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Marjorie Miller</p>
        <p>NEW YORK DINERS'  QUANDARY</p>
        <p>That tiny bistro prepares pike quenelles and hickory-grilled fish,</p>
        <p>And the Tea Room presents beluga, that classy, pricey dish --</p>
        <p>Steak houses serve up prime, aged beef with gobs of sauce béarnaise,</p>
        <p>While near the river, facing Brooklyn, menus feature bouillabaisse.</p>
        <p>Sashimi, linguine, rotelli, cassoulet,</p>
        <p>Mascarpone, chicken tikka, entrecôte, duck pâté,</p>
        <p>Pizza, paella, olives (kalamata),</p>
        <p>Vinaigrette, mignonette, radicchio, frittata.</p>
        <p>The problem: Where to go and what to spend when dining out;</p>
        <p>The economical solution: ''Hold the mustard, extra kraut.''</p>
        <p>Stephen J. Kudless</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I was walking with my friend Karen down Broadway when suddenly at 88th Street she stopped, gasped and brought her hand to her chest. She was staring across the street.</p>
        <p>''A Dunkin' Donuts,'' she said, in pleasant disbelief. ''We needed a Dunkin' Donuts.''</p>
        <p>Me: ''Why? How far away is the next closest Dunkin' Donuts?''</p>
        <p>Karen: ''Ninety-fifth Street.''</p>
        <p>Me: ''Don't you live on 92nd? Why wouldn't you go to that one?''</p>
        <p>Karen: ''I don't walk UPtown!''</p>
        <p>Laurie Adelman</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>As more people tried to squeeze into the last possible crevices of a particularly crowded Flushing-bound 7 train during the evening commute, few passengers were in good moods.</p>
        <p>That is, until we all heard in a drily sarcastic voice over the subway announcement system: ''This train is full. Please wait for the next one. There is another train behind us with empty seats, carpeting and color TV.''</p>
        <p>Cheryl Chan</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>On a recent trip heading east on the 23rd Street crosstown bus, I was seated near a gregarious woman. She held animated conversations with all the individuals who successively sat next to her. After the last of her new friends left the bus, she turned to have a conversation with me.</p>
        <p>Within the next few moments she asked me if I lived in Peter Cooper Village. When I told her I did not, she countered with: ''Are you sure? You look like someone who would live in Peter Cooper Village.''</p>
        <p>Marilyn Burkhardt</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>The scene: Approaching Bergen Street during the after-work rush hour on an F train in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>A woman, probably from the Caribbean and needing directions, asked, ''Is the train going to Broadway-Lafayette?''</p>
        <p>A helpful fellow passenger answered: ''You missed it. You have to transfer at the next stop for a train back to Manhattan.''</p>
        <p>But other passengers started worrying aloud that it is not possible to cross over to the other side for the next few stops. One passenger noted that you could indeed transfer to the other side at the south end of the Carroll Street station. A lively discussion among helpful strangers ensued.</p>
        <p>In the meantime the lost passenger started giving more details about her desired destination. ''I want to go to BAM. Isn't this near BAM?''</p>
        <p>''Oh, you want to go to the Brooklyn Academy of Music?''</p>
        <p>''Yes. Lafayette.''</p>
        <p>''Oh, THAT Lafayette!''</p>
        <p>Upon hearing that, several voices chimed in at once:</p>
        <p>''Transfer for the G next stop.''</p>
        <p>''No, she has to go back the other way on the G.''</p>
        <p>''But it's hard to transfer to the other side at Smith and Ninth.''</p>
        <p>''No, she needs go to Pacific Street.''</p>
        <p>Finally, one person took the Caribbean lady firmly in hand and loudly proclaimed to her (and the rest of us): ''I'm a native New Yorker. I know where you're going. I'll take you there. Come on.''</p>
        <p>And with that they exited the F together.</p>
        <p>Guenevere Knowles</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
