<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Olmert Invites Arab Leaders To Hold Talks</title>
    <meta content="02mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/world/middleeast/02mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershner, Isabel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olmert, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Olmert, Ehud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Olmert Invites Arab Leaders To Hold Talks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Olmert Invites Arab Leaders to Hold Talks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL KERSHNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershner, Isabel</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli Prime Min Ehud Olmert invites Arab leaders to join him for talks in regional peace meeting in Jerusalem; invitation is described as new initiative; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Olmert of Israel on Sunday invited Arab leaders to join him for talks in a regional peace meeting in Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert's invitation, made at a news conference in Jerusalem with Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany, was described by a spokeswoman as a ''new initiative.'' She said it resulted from the atmosphere created by an Arab summit meeting in Saudi Arabia last week. Participants at that meeting reaffirmed an Arab peace initiative from 2002, which calls for Israel to withdraw to its 1967 borders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Olmert of Israel invited Arab leaders to join him for talks in a regional peace meeting in Jerusalem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Olmert of Israel on Sunday invited Arab leaders to join him for talks in a regional peace meeting in Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert's invitation, made at a news conference in Jerusalem with Chancellor Angela Merkel of Germany, was described by a spokeswoman as a ''new initiative.'' She said it resulted from the atmosphere created by an Arab summit meeting in Saudi Arabia last week. Participants at that meeting reaffirmed an Arab peace initiative from 2002, which calls for Israel to withdraw to its 1967 borders.</p>
        <p>''I invite for a meeting all the heads of Arab states -- including, of course, the king of Saudi Arabia, who I see as a very important leader -- to hold talks with us,'' Mr. Olmert said at a news conference in Jerusalem with Ms. Merkel.</p>
        <p>''I do not intend to dictate to them what they should say, but I am certain they understand that we also will have something to say,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert has spoken of ''positive elements'' of the 2002 initiative, but he takes issue with certain of its elements, in particular the insistence that Palestinian refugees be allowed to return to Israel.</p>
        <p>Miri Eisin, the Olmert spokeswoman, said his announcement was ''influenced'' by the Arab leaders' talk of resolving the conflict with Israel through dialogue.</p>
        <p>Still, leaders of Arab states that have no diplomatic relations with Israel have always adamantly refused public meetings with Israeli officials.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Merkel met Sunday with Israeli and Palestinian leaders in Jerusalem and the West Bank city of Ramallah. She currently holds the rotating presidency of the European Union, which announced Saturday that it would maintain contacts with moderate members of the Palestinian government who are not members of Hamas, contrary to Israel's hopes that countries would boycott the government.</p>
        <p>Hamas, which came to power in elections last year and now has a fragile unity government with Fatah, is considered a terrorist organization by the United States, Israel and the European Union.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Merkel met with the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas, of Fatah, but her aides said she would not meet with any Palestinian cabinet ministers on this visit.</p>
        <p>Israel's head of military intelligence, Amos Yadlin, told cabinet officials on Sunday that Israeli intelligence had seen signs of defensive planning by Syria, Iran and the Lebanese militant group Hezbollah, all seemingly bracing for a possible attack by the United States in the coming months.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has repeatedly said it will rely on diplomacy to address international concerns over Iran's nuclear program. Last week, Under Secretary of State R. Nicholas Burns said in testimony to the Senate Foreign Relations Committee that the administration did not believe military conflict with Iran was inevitable.</p>
        <p>At the news conference on Sunday, held after Mr. Yadlin's comments, Mr. Olmert dismissed reports of a possible coordinated offensive by the United States and Israel against Iran, Syria and Lebanon as ''baseless, and an unfounded rumor with no foundation.''</p>
        <p>Also on Sunday, Fatah, the mainstream Palestinian movement, announced that it was working to unify its armed groups under one command in what seemed to be an effort to strengthen and impose discipline on its notoriously divided militias.</p>
        <p>A Fatah spokesman in Gaza, Maher Mekdad, said the restructuring was intended to prevent small splinter groups from taking ''individual decisions.''</p>
        <p>But the drive for unity is also being seen in Gaza as an attempt to beef up Fatah's power against Hamas. Fatah did not fare well in armed confrontations with Hamas in recent months. Hamas has a parallel police force, the Executive Force; members of that group clashed with the Palestinian Authority security branches, including the Presidential Guard, which is loyal to Mr. Abbas.</p>
        <p>Fatah's new unified military wing would not be a part of the Palestinian Authority security forces, which are supposed to represent all Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Fatah denies that it is preparing for another confrontation with Hamas. In response to a report on Sunday in the Israeli newspaper Haaretz that Fatah had so far recruited 1,400 fighters for a new Special Force in anticipation of further clashes, Mr. Mekdad told reporters, ''We are interested in maintaining our national unity.''</p>
        <p>In the months before the Feb. 8 agreement reached in Mecca between Hamas and Fatah to establish a unity government, more than 100 Palestinians died in factional fighting, mostly in Gaza. The unity government is dominated by Hamas but includes several Fatah members and independents. One of its main goals was to end the internal violence, but since the government was formed in mid-March, more than a dozen Palestinians have been killed in fighting between the groups.</p>
        <p>The Executive Force is a parallel police force intended to counter the control that Fatah exercises over the Palestinian Authority security forces. It has about 6,000 men according to Hamas and up to 10,000 according to Israeli military officials.</p>
        <p>Abdul Hakim Awad, a Fatah spokesman, told the Palestinian news agency Maan that the newly unified Fatah force would consist of about 5,000 men. The force is to be called Al Asifa, Arabic for ''the storm,'' which was the original name of Fatah's military wing when it was founded more than 40 years ago.</p>
        <p>The United States is planning to provide $59 million to support President Abbas and the Palestinian Authority forces loyal to him, Reuters reported in late March, but the financing is still awaiting approval by Congress. Much of the new security package is earmarked to ''transform and strengthen'' Mr. Abbas's presidential guard, according to American government documents that Reuters said it had obtained.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
