<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Confronting Early-Stage Alzheimer's</title>
    <meta content="l02alzheimers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alzheimer's Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Confronting Early-Stage Alzheimer's</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Living With Alzheimer's Before a Window Closes'' (front page, March 29):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Living With Alzheimer's Before a Window Closes'' (front page, March 29):</p>
        <p>Reading about people in the early stages of Alzheimer's was heartbreaking, because of the stigmas and stereotypes attached to the disease and the looming sentence that Alzheimer's implies.</p>
        <p>I have been watching a loved one suffer from dementia for several years, and have witnessed the devastating toll the disease takes. So many people would rather bury their heads in the sand than openly discuss how best to accommodate the changing needs of their loved ones stricken with the disease, most likely because it is just too painful to contemplate.</p>
        <p>While I applaud those who are working to engage patients and their loved ones in dialogue about the changes they are going through, it is my fervent hope that the need for such discussion will soon disappear with the discovery of a cure.</p>
        <p>Tova Stulman  Brooklyn, March 29, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It's good to call attention to the strengths and abilities of people with early-stage Alzheimer's. But they are not the only Alzheimer's patients with an experiential life.</p>
        <p>Long into the illness, individuals are conscious and can interact with others, albeit at a diminished level. They can still enjoy life as long as others are sensitive to their needs. This fact should guide both their everyday and general medical care.</p>
        <p>Many Alzheimer's patients are capable of feeling pain and distress, yet are unable to understand why they must undergo procedures like surgery. It can be hard to decide whether a treatment's benefits outweigh its burdens on the patient.</p>
        <p>With the aging of the baby-boom generation, we can expect many more of these ethically complicated situations.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Dresser  St. Louis, March 29, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer, a professor of law and ethics in medicine at Washington University, is a member of the President's Council on Bioethics.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your article brought into focus the fact that too often spouses are alone, and the burden on both seems overwhelming.</p>
        <p>My mother died of Alzheimer's a little more than five years ago after living in a care home for three years. Before she went to the care home, we could see the strain that the deterioration in my mother's mental health was having on my father: he was exhausted, losing weight, and his sense of humor was absent.</p>
        <p>Although he had the support of good doctors, he predeceased her by seven weeks of a heart attack. We think he died of a broken heart.</p>
        <p>Gerry O'Brien  Ottawa, March 29, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I have found that helping patients suffering from all the dementias and those with aphasias pinpoint what they are feeling (often by intuiting and articulating the feelings for them or by helping them understand more clearly what they are trying to say as only an analytically oriented therapist can) relieves them and helps them maintain a sense of the ''I.''</p>
        <p>Talented therapists can convey what these patients feel to family members, enhancing closeness.</p>
        <p>Frieda Plotkin  New York, March 30, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a psychotherapist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
