<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Starters, Sturdy Effort and Victory for Glavine</title>
    <meta content="02borzi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/baseball/02borzi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Glavine, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Starters, Sturdy Effort and Victory for Glavine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Starters, Sturdy Effort and Victory for Glavine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borzi, Pat</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One start, one-tenth of the way closer to his 300th victory. At this rate, Tom Glavine will reach his targeted milestone by the end of May and be back home in Georgia comfortably retired by the Fourth of July. Right?</p>
        <p>''Let's not go there yet,'' Glavine said after earning a 6-1 victory against the Cardinals on opening night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At this rate, Tom Glavine will reach his his 300th victory by the end of May.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One start, one-tenth of the way closer to his 300th victory. At this rate, Tom Glavine will reach his targeted milestone by the end of May and be back home in Georgia comfortably retired by the Fourth of July. Right?</p>
        <p>''Let's not go there yet,'' Glavine said after earning a 6-1 victory against the Cardinals on opening night.</p>
        <p>No one on the Mets, least of all Glavine, suggested this was anything more than it was: a workmanlike six innings from a veteran left-hander who needed every ounce of defense the Mets played behind him to limit the defending world champions to one run on six hits.</p>
        <p>But given the way the schedule opens for the Mets -- three games here with the team that stopped the Mets' run to the World Series last year, then three in Atlanta -- a efficient first-day effort was essential. The 41-year-old Glavine did his part, and the Mets turned two of their four double plays while he was in the game.</p>
        <p>''I thought he threw the ball well,'' Mets Manager Willie Randolph said. ''It was not a great game, but he pitched well enough to win the ballgame.''</p>
        <p>That is what the Mets have come to expect from Glavine, who has now made as many opening-day starts for the Mets (four) as he did for the Braves. Only Tom Seaver (11) and Dwight Gooden (8) have started more openers as a Met. Glavine is the first starter for a visiting team to beat the Cardinals on opening day since John Burkett of San Francisco in 1993.</p>
        <p>Glavine was not spectacular or awful. He made some good pitches but missed with some others, especially fastballs, like the 0-2 pitch that struck Scott Rolen in the lower left leg to load the bases in the sixth.</p>
        <p>Center fielder Carlos Beltrán had already saved Glavine by throwing out David Eckstein at the plate earlier in the inning. This time Glavine worked out of the mess himself, jamming Yadier Molina to produce a broken-bat, inning-ending popup to shortstop José Reyes.</p>
        <p>''My stuff was good,'' Glavine said. ''My location at times was O.K. Through the first three innings, everything was good. The last three innings I struggled, especially with the fastball. For some reason, I had trouble holding onto the ball a little bit. But I had a good change and I was able to throw it when I needed it.''</p>
        <p>Catcher Paul Lo Duca said: ''He just got a little tired toward the end. That's to be expected. He was really, really good. He made pitches when he had to.''</p>
        <p>The Cardinals have always been a good matchup for Glavine, regardless of the day. The victory made him 19-6 with a 3.55 earned run average against St. Louis; He is 11-2 with a 3.81 E.R.A. at the old and new Busch Stadiums.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to lie and tell you it's not important to go out and win the first one,'' Glavine said. ''I looked at the schedule. I know we've got some tough teams coming right off the bat. As a pitcher, you want to feel good about the way your year is starting out and not feel like you're digging out of a hole.''</p>
        <p>If Glavine can deliver consistently outings like this, especially with the gloves behind him, No. 300 is well within reach this year.</p>
        <p>''I guarantee nobody looked at me in 1988 and said, This guy's got a chance to win 300 one day,'' said Glavine, referring to his first full season with then-awful Braves, when his 17 losses led the National League.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
