<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Angling for a Fight On and Off the Ice</title>
    <meta content="02cherry" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/hockey/02cherry.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cherry, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1324" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Angling for a Fight On and Off the Ice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Angling for a Fight on and Off the Ice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Matt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Canada, and in some border cities like Buffalo and Detroit, the most powerful and influential commentator in hockey requires no introduction. He is besieged at airports, restaurants and hotels by autograph seekers. Some people, upon recognizing him, have even pulled their cars to the side of the road to get out and shake his hand.</p>
        <p>Don Cherry tends to stand out in public. These days, few others in North America favor green Scotch plaid double-breasted sport coats and button-down shirts with high stiff collars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For 25 years, Canadian broadcaster Don Cherry has used his television platform to advocate the role of fighting in hockey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Canada, and in some border cities like Buffalo and Detroit, the most powerful and influential commentator in hockey requires no introduction. He is besieged at airports, restaurants and hotels by autograph seekers. Some people, upon recognizing him, have even pulled their cars to the side of the road to get out and shake his hand.</p>
        <p>Don Cherry tends to stand out in public. These days, few others in North America favor green Scotch plaid double-breasted sport coats and button-down shirts with high stiff collars.</p>
        <p>When he is on television Saturday nights, Cherry helps lure an even bigger crowd of 1.2 million viewers, Canada's largest sports audience. The hierarchy of the National Hockey League, it seems fair to assume, is also watching.</p>
        <p>As Brian Burke, the general manager of the Anaheim Ducks, said, ''I've timed workouts to watch him.''</p>
        <p>Cherry, 73, is the star of ''Coach's Corner,'' a seven-minute segment between periods on the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation's ''Hockey Night in Canada.'' For 25 years, he has used this platform to advocate the role of fighting in hockey.</p>
        <p>Because of his immense popularity, his critics -- and they are legion -- say that he has played a major role in making the N.H.L. the only major professional sports league in North America that continues to allow opponents to beat on one another with their fists.</p>
        <p>After years of appearing to take a systematic approach toward reducing fighting in its games, the N.H.L. has in recent months signaled a new stance. In February, the league's 30 general managers voted to relax repercussions against players who instigate fights, beginning next season. Players will be able to accrue five instigator violations before being suspended, rather than the current three.</p>
        <p>And last week, after a series of fighting injuries that left some players carted off the ice on stretchers, Commissioner Gary Bettman reaffirmed the N.H.L.'s position that fighting was part of the game.</p>
        <p>Last week, Cherry said of Bettman's statements: ''All I can say is, he must be watching 'Coach's Corner.' I know he watches.''</p>
        <p>Cherry often addresses Bettman directly during broadcasts, exhorting him to keep the game tough while showing footage of brawls.</p>
        <p>''In some ways, he's held back the progress of hockey by spending all his time praising parts of the game that shouldn't be praised,'' said William Houston, a sports media columnist at The Globe and Mail in Toronto. ''To be brave, to be a real Canadian, you have to beat up people.''</p>
        <p>Cherry called his detractors politically biased.</p>
        <p>''The thing that gets me in trouble is Canada's media is left wing,'' he said. ''It's politically correct to say you don't like fighting. I come on and I show fights. This is the way you do it. You don't use your stick, kids. Don't fight until you get older.''</p>
        <p>But there is no argument over his popularity.</p>
        <p>In a national poll conducted by the CBC in 2004, Cherry was voted the seventh-greatest Canadian, ahead of Wayne Gretzky, Alexander Graham Bell and Sir John Macdonald, Canada's first prime minister.</p>
        <p>And his influence extends to the N.H.L.'s precincts of power.</p>
        <p>''He has direct access to the highest levels of the league,'' Burke said. ''There's not a general manager who won't take his call. He has access to the commissioner.''</p>
        <p>The first half of Cherry's life was less auspicious. Those times shaped his combative streak and informed the everyman views that have made him so popular with the public.</p>
        <p>''He speaks for the blue-collar and farm segments of the population in Canada,'' Burke said.</p>
        <p>Born in Kingston, Ontario, Cherry dropped out of school at 14. He wound up spending 16 seasons as a tough, brawling defenseman in the minors and played in one N.H.L. game, for the Boston Bruins during the 1955 playoffs.</p>
        <p>He retired in 1969, settling in Rochester, N.Y., with his wife and two children, working construction and selling used cars.</p>
        <p>''I was the world's worst car salesman,'' he said. ''I got down on my knees and said to the Lord: 'This is it, Lord. I'm finished. I'm 36 years old and I can't get a job, with no trade, no education, no nothing.' ''</p>
        <p>Hockey was his salvation. Cherry made a comeback with the American Hockey League's Rochester Americans during the 1971-72 season and was promoted to coach after his predecessor, he said, ''got punched in the head or something and quit.''</p>
        <p>Two and a half years later, he was hired to coach the Boston Bruins and the Hall of Fame defenseman Bobby Orr, a favorite subject on ''Coach's Corner.''</p>
        <p>Cherry feuded with Boston's ownership and General Manager Harry Sinden, and gave his players a sense that they were unappreciated, forging a team of scrappers into contenders for the Stanley Cup title.</p>
        <p>He was the N.H.L. coach of the year in 1976, so despite their growing rift, Sinden could not fire Cherry. He had become like a weed in Boston Garden.</p>
        <p>But after five seasons, Cherry was doomed after a disappointing playoff loss. He coached the Colorado Rockies the next season but finished last in the N.H.L. and was fired again.</p>
        <p>''I had just about burned all my bridges in coaching,'' Cherry said. ''They asked me on television, 'What happened in Colorado?' I said, 'It's pretty tough to fly like an eagle when you're surrounded with a bunch of turkeys.' ''</p>
        <p>Cherry's outspoken ways caught the attention of the executive producer of ''Hockey Night in Canada,'' Ralph Mellanby, and Cherry began providing color commentary on CBC during the 1980 playoffs. He immediately clashed by refusing to wear the blazers that were the show's uniform.</p>
        <p>''He was lucky to last two weeks,'' Mellanby said. ''The president and head of CBC wanted him fired because of his English.''</p>
        <p>In a country with the British monarch on its money, Cherry could not speak the king's English. His grammar is often poor, and he pronounces Toronto ''Ta-Ranna'' and the Rangers star Jaromir Jagr ''Yammy Yeah-gur.''</p>
        <p>''They told Ralph, 'We don't want him on television,' '' Cherry said of the executives at CBC. '' 'We owe it to the English-speaking children of Canada.' He said, 'If he goes, I go.' ''</p>
        <p>Such loyalty is the core of the Cherry creed, a view that nearly led to his firing when in March 2003 he criticized Canada's government on ''Coach's Corner'' for failing to commit troops to the war in Iraq. He saw it as Canada's duty to do so as an American ally.</p>
        <p>Then in 2004, during a discussion about whether visors should be mandatory for N.H.L. players -- Cherry believes they lead to more reckless stickwork -- he said disparagingly, ''Most of the guys that wear them are Europeans and French guys.''</p>
        <p>Cherry came under criticism for that remark but was vindicated somewhat by the fact that most visors in the N.H.L. were indeed worn by European and French Canadian players.</p>
        <p>''People do take him too seriously,'' Houston of The Globe and Mail said. ''I'm one of them. I wouldn't have much to write about, especially in the winter months when not much is going on. He makes for great copy.''</p>
        <p>One of many telling stories about Cherry took place during his coaching days with Boston. Defenseman Mike Milbury, who had played at Colgate, recalled returning to the Bruins' bench from his first N.H.L. shift.</p>
        <p>''I always worked hard,'' said Milbury, now an executive with the Islanders. ''But I was working particularly hard because I was so excited.''</p>
        <p>Cherry was not impressed. He ripped Milbury, calling him, among other things, a ''college commie pinko'' and a ''pansy.''</p>
        <p>Cherry, who delighted in telling his own version of the event, said he then told Milbury that during Boston's next game, against the Maple Leafs, he was to grab the first Toronto player he passed and pummel him, which Milbury did.</p>
        <p>''He was obviously sending a message that I could be more physical,'' Milbury said.</p>
        <p>Cherry has been accused of many things, but never ambiguity.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
