<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Seeks to Ban Investment in Iran</title>
    <meta content="02pension" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/us/02pension.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iran</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E7D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Seeks to Ban Investment in Iran</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">California Seeks to Ban Investment in Iran</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California bill would force state's public employees and teachers pension funds to remove $24 billion currently invested in foreign companies doing business in Iran; US firms are barred from such dealings; bill would lend weight to efforts to apply economic pressure to Iran (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is the kind of political movement that fits handily on a bumper sticker: Divest Iran.</p>
        <p>Over the past year, one state, Missouri, has opted to do just that, while several others, including New Jersey, have also begun to write or to consider legislation to divest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A bill would force two pension funds to remove their money from any foreign company doing business in Iran.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is the kind of political movement that fits handily on a bumper sticker: Divest Iran.</p>
        <p>Over the past year, one state, Missouri, has opted to do just that, while several others, including New Jersey, have also begun to write or to consider legislation to divest.</p>
        <p>But the nascent movement took on decidedly more weight last week with the preliminary success of a bill in the California Legislature. The measure would force two of the nation's largest pension funds -- devoted to the state's public employees and its teachers, with combined holdings of nearly $400 billion -- to remove their money from any foreign company doing business in Iran. American companies are already barred from such dealings.</p>
        <p>The author, Assemblyman Joel Anderson, a Republican from San Diego County, said the bill was meant to protect the $24 billion he estimates the two funds currently have invested in international companies with ties to Iran. Mr. Anderson said his concern was Iran's potential economic instability, not its current standoff with the West.</p>
        <p>''They've got a president that is talking one day about having nuclear bombs and saying he's not the next day, and taking hostages,'' he said on Friday, referring to the Iranian capture of 15 British sailors and marines. ''I'm not saying that we should take a foreign policy stance; I'm saying it's not a good place to invest our money.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson's language was notably more heated when he introduced the bill in January, raising the specter of the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks and calling money ''the mother's milk of terrorism.'' Last week, Mr. Anderson said he had toned down the terrorism angle in part because of legal concerns regarding divestment bills, which came into vogue in the 1980s as part of a movement to force pensions and money out of South African interests in protest of apartheid. More recently, divestment has been used to voice displeasure with tobacco companies and the atrocities in the Darfur region of Sudan.</p>
        <p>States are not the only entities trying to put pressure on Iran. On March 24, the United Nations Security Council imposed new, more stringent sanctions in an effort to stop the country's uranium enrichment program and to try to force it to rejoin negotiations. In Congress, Representative Tom Lantos, a Democrat from the San Francisco Bay Area, introduced legislation last month to impose additional economic sanctions on Iran. Mr. Lantos cited denials of the Holocaust by President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad of Iran and his comments that Israel should be ''wiped off the map.''</p>
        <p>Last year, California joined a roster of states that have opted out of investment in Sudan with a bill similar to the Iran bill, passed by a pension-related committee in the State Assembly on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Alberto Torrico, a Bay Area Democrat who cast the sole committee vote against the bill, said he thought it would find wide support in the Legislature despite his concerns about the plan's feasibility and vagueness. ''Our pension funds are invested in thousands of companies,'' Mr. Torrico said. ''I don't know how you're going to do it.''</p>
        <p>Officials at the funds agree that determining which companies might have financial dealings with Iran is a big and often complicated job.</p>
        <p>''That's always been the struggle,'' said Brad Pacheco, a spokesman for the California Public Employees Retirement System, who said the fund had asked the federal government for help in determining which companies were ''terror free.'' ''We don't necessarily have the resources or the expertise.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pacheco said the public employees' fund, known as Calpers, had no position on the bill yet. But officials with the California State Teachers Retirement System, with holdings of $159 billion, have already suggested they will oppose it.</p>
        <p>Some divestment bills have also been challenged in court. In February, a federal judge struck down an Illinois law that called for Sudanese divestment, saying it interfered with the federal government's ability to conduct foreign policy.</p>
        <p>William A. Reinsch, president of the National Foreign Trade Council, with offices in New York and Washington, which filed suit against the Illinois law, said divestment bills -- while morally laudable -- could sabotage diplomatic efforts to isolate Iran.</p>
        <p>''The companies that would be divested would be European and Asian companies,'' Mr. Reinsch said. ''It sticks a stick in the eye of the very people and the very countries we are trying to get to cooperate with us.''</p>
        <p>He added that while California's pension funds were powerful -- the public employees fund has holdings of $230 billion -- their economic influence was still smaller than that of other potential players in multilateral international sanctions.</p>
        <p>''I love Calpers, but I don't think the pressure their divestment would supply is anywhere near what we could get if we could get the European Union, China and Russia to all act in concert,'' Mr. Reinsch said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Anderson said he was more concerned with the bottom line than foreign policy.</p>
        <p>''If we get world peace out of it, I'm for world peace, and if we get human rights out of it, we get human rights,'' he said. ''But I just want to be able to look at our taxpayers and say I wasn't asleep at the switch.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
