<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports Organizations Try To Limit Online Reporting</title>
    <meta content="02sportpix" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/technology/02sportpix.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports Organizations Try To Limit Online Reporting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sports Organizations Try to Limit Online Reporting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Pan American Games start in Brazil in July, thousands of top athletes will run, wrestle and leap, but they will not be able to indulge in one popular daily exercise: blogging.</p>
        <p>Neither will their doctors, coaches or massage therapists, in a blanket ban affecting some 7,000 people during two weeks of competition ending July 29 in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>International sports institutions are imposing vigorous controls over the online use of game information and photographs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Pan American Games start in Brazil in July, thousands of top athletes will run, wrestle and leap, but they will not be able to indulge in one popular daily exercise: blogging.</p>
        <p>Neither will their doctors, coaches or massage therapists, in a blanket ban affecting some 7,000 people during two weeks of competition ending July 29 in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
        <p>The rule reflects a spreading trend among international sports institutions to impose vigorous controls over the online use of game information and photographs.</p>
        <p>In February, a dispute broke out between the International Rugby Board and the World Association of Newspapers over restrictions that will be imposed during the Rugby World Cup, which starts in Paris in September.</p>
        <p>In return for Rugby Cup press credentials, the rugby board is limiting the number of game photos that can be published in online news sites during competition. It is also demanding that headlines not be superimposed over photographs, a rule aimed at protecting corporate sponsors like Heineken and Toshiba.</p>
        <p>''We're not being draconian,'' said Greg Thomas, head of communications for the International Rugby Board, which is based in Dublin. ''It's just in some instances we need to protect ourselves if people step over the mark.''</p>
        <p>The Rugby Cup's executives argue that they are ''unashamedly'' guarding potential revenue during an expansion period for the sport. But critics have argued that sports institutions are also seizing more power to manage their images.</p>
        <p>''There's a natural trend among sports organizations to expand their territory,'' said Jens Sejer Andersen, director of Play the Game, a nonprofit sports ethics research group in Denmark. ''This is normal for any business that tries to expand its control of the market. But it goes to the core of the functioning of the independent media in our society. The danger is that no real discussion about events on and off the sports field can take place, reducing us to millions of passive sports-consuming robots.''</p>
        <p>Since the late 1990s, tension about online publication of game photos has often surfaced in connection with the media credentials issued by sports authorities. These authorities grant journalists access to games, provided the journalists abide by rules that are constantly evolving.</p>
        <p>In 1997, the National Football League threatened to revoke press credentials for The Florida Times-Union unless the paper signed waivers barring it from posting photographs of Jacksonville Jaguar games on its Web site. The Times-Union countered by warning that it would not cover the Jaguars, and the dispute sputtered out.</p>
        <p>Such saber-rattling has continued, from big game to big game, with both news organizations and sports institutions loath to press the issue in court and instead relying on other forms of leverage.</p>
        <p>In 2004, for example, British newspapers countered efforts by the dominant English Premier soccer league to seek more control over the online use of sports photos by shunning game shots that showed the logos of sponsors like Coca-Cola and Barclays.</p>
        <p>Last year, the World Association of Newspapers also successfully challenged FIFA, the international soccer association, by approaching top sponsors to complain about proposed restrictions on the use of game photos -- a tactic that it may also pursue in its current dispute with rugby officials.</p>
        <p>''We don't have any objection to their licensing agreements and the exclusive rights that they provide to broadcasters, '' said Larry Kilman, a spokesman for the newspaper association, which has 18,000 members. ''But we think that these restrictions are not needed and they're being overly cautious.''</p>
        <p>At stake for big-league sports organizers is the potential revenue from new forms of media. The International Rugby Board chose to limit the online publication of still photographs to five for each half of the game, in part because it wanted to protect the exclusivity of its own subscription-based ''match tracker,'' which features game commentary online along with a changing assortment of still photographs.</p>
        <p>For similar reasons, the authorities of the Pan American Games wanted to protect the exclusivity of their events by barring athletes from blogging or ''vlogging'' with audio or video content. Eloyza Guardia, a spokeswoman for the organizers, said they were simply following the lead of the International Olympic Committee, which imposed a similar ban during the Winter Olympics in Turin in 2006.</p>
        <p>Typically, there is a divide on this issue between dominant sports organizations and lesser-known competitions that are trying to build audiences. The America's Cup sailing match, which starts April 16 in Valencia, Spain, for instance, attracts less television coverage than some international events. It does not restrict blogging and allows liberal use of still photos; a maximum of three pictures a minute can appear online. The Volvo Ocean Race last year actually required its sailors to blog.</p>
        <p>Jeff Bukantz, captain of the United States fencing team, which is bound for the Pan American Games, was unaware until recently that competition blogging had been banned.</p>
        <p>In 2004, he published a running personal commentary when he was captain of the American Olympic fencing team, which won a gold medal. He describes athlete blogging in general as a cathartic outlet for competitors to release pent-up thoughts and feelings.</p>
        <p>''Our athletes will abide by whatever the local rules are,'' he said, but he called the blogging ban ''shocking.''</p>
        <p>''It's certainly an egregious form of censorship,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
