<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Met, and Closer, Looper Tries a New Role</title>
    <meta content="02looper" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/baseball/02looper.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Looper, Braden</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EED71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Met, and Closer, Looper Tries a New Role</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Former Met, and Closer, Looper Tries a New Role</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borzi, Pat</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some of the routines of a starting pitcher, the former Met Braden Looper already has down. He knows when to take a pregame shower, when to stop in the trainer's room for a rubdown and when to head out to warm up. But the really important stuff -- such as what to eat for lunch and where to eat it -- he has yet to settle on.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I'll have to have my wife make the same thing for me every day,'' Looper said before the Cardinals and the Mets opened the season Sunday night. ''I usually eat lunch with my wife and my two kids. I play with my kids, try not to think about the game, stay loose.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not since his first year of professional baseball has Braden Looper stood on the mound and thrown the first pitch of a game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some of the routines of a starting pitcher, the former Met Braden Looper already has down. He knows when to take a pregame shower, when to stop in the trainer's room for a rubdown and when to head out to warm up. But the really important stuff -- such as what to eat for lunch and where to eat it -- he has yet to settle on.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I'll have to have my wife make the same thing for me every day,'' Looper said before the Cardinals and the Mets opened the season Sunday night. ''I usually eat lunch with my wife and my two kids. I play with my kids, try not to think about the game, stay loose.''</p>
        <p>Looper had to learn -- or actually relearn -- a starter's routine because he has not been one in more than nine years. The 32-year-old Looper, once the Mets' closer, is scheduled to make his first major league start Wednesday night against them after 572 appearances as a reliever.</p>
        <p>Not since 1997, his first year of professional baseball, has Looper stood on the mound and thrown the first pitch of a game. Looper started 12 games that season for Class A Prince William in the Cardinals' system, going 3-6 with a 4.48 earned run average, before being made a reliever upon his promotion to Class AA Arkansas.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals' pitching coach, Dave Duncan, is the mad scientist behind the moves of Looper and Adam Wainwright to the rotation from the bullpen.</p>
        <p>In the aftermath of the Cardinals' world championship, three-fifths of their starting rotation signed free-agent deals elsewhere: Jeff Suppan with Milwaukee; Jeff Weaver, the National League Championship Series most valuable player, with Seattle; and Jason Marquis with the Chicago Cubs.</p>
        <p>Mark Mulder's return to the rotation is uncertain because he had rotator cuff surgery, and there are no other palatable options in their system, so the Cardinals decided to move Looper and Wainwright from the bullpen. Chris Carpenter, the 2005 Cy Young award winner, is the only sure thing in a rotation that includes the free agent Kip Wells, a former Pirate who is slated to face Orlando Hernández on Tuesday, and the second-year right-hander Anthony Reyes. And it also leaves uncertain how St. Louis will bridge the innings to closer Jason Isringhausen.</p>
        <p>Wainwright was a starter as recently as 2005, with Class AAA Memphis, before he was thrust into the closer's role last year after Isringhausen was injured and had surgery on his left hip. Wainwright, a rookie, showed his ability with four postseason saves, most notably in Game 7 of the N.L.C.S., when his big-breaking curveball froze Carlos Beltrán with the bases loaded for the final out of a 3-1 victory.</p>
        <p>But Looper? Mets fans best remember his failings as a closer in 2004 and '05, which prompted the Mets to sign Billy Wagner.</p>
        <p>''Our pitching coach never does anything lightly,'' Cardinals Manager Tony La Russa said. ''He's got a real good track record of coming up with ideas that work.''</p>
        <p>La Russa tries not to become too worked up about spring-training performances. But all five starters had a good camp; they combined for a 1.88 E.R.A. Looper's 2.18 E.R.A. in five appearances was third best among the starters, and even a little better than Carpenter's (2.60). Looper, who won both his spring training decisions, also rediscovered a cut fastball he had stopped throwing in 2001 because it adversely affected his best pitch, his sinker. He gave up one home run in 20 2/3 innings.</p>
        <p>Wainwright said of Looper: ''It's pretty amazing what he's done, really. It's tough enough for me to go from relieving to starting, but he hasn't done it in what, eight and a half years? He's done it pretty smoothly.''</p>
        <p>The rotation was one of several questions facing the Cardinals. Roles in the bullpen remained unsettled. Juan Encarnación (left wrist surgery) may not play until May. Although center fielder Jim Edmonds returned from toe and shoulder surgeries, and was also dealing with the effects of postconcussion syndrome, to start Sunday night, La Russa said that he was not sure how much he could count on him.</p>
        <p>La Russa may know more about his starting pitching by the end of the week. For Looper, facing the Mets in his debut provides extra incentive. ''I'd probably be lying if I said no,'' he said, although adding that the frequent derision of Mets fans is not part of the reason.</p>
        <p>''There's a number of things,'' he said. ''It's my first major league start, obviously. And there's that little extra want-to because it's the Mets, for a few reasons -- they're my former team and they're one of the best lineups in the league. It's going to be a lot of fun.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
