<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battle Over F.B.I. Policy Against Taping of Suspects Comes to Light in Firing Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="02taping" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/washington/02taping.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Confessions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charlton, Paul K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battle Over F.B.I. Policy Against Taping of Suspects Comes to Light in Firing Inquiry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Crime Intensifies Debate Over Taping of Suspects</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON and JENNIFER STEINHAUER; Eric Lipton reported from Washington, and Jennifer Steinhauer from Phoenix.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer; Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Dept dispute questions whether interviews with criminals should be tape-recorded; former US attorney in Arizona Paul K Charlton was ousted after protesting FBI policy that forbids taping of almost all confessions, in contrast to practice of many local law enforcement agencies nationwide; Charlton blames FBI policy for resulting plea bargain in 2005 Navajo reservation assault case; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The account, buried in a mountain of documents assembled for a Congressional investigation, describes a decidedly local yet brutal crime: a Navajo man charged with beating his girlfriend nearly to death and then hanging her by a rope outside their Arizona trailer home to make the attack look like a suicide attempt.</p>
        <p>The crime has none of the political intrigue of the other cases, mainly dealing with government corruption or voter fraud, before lawmakers as they examine the circumstances surrounding the dismissals of eight United States attorneys.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Justice Department has been embroiled in a dispute over a critical law enforcement question: Should interviews with criminal suspects be tape-recorded?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The account, buried in a mountain of documents assembled for a Congressional investigation, describes a decidedly local yet brutal crime: a Navajo man charged with beating his girlfriend nearly to death and then hanging her by a rope outside their Arizona trailer home to make the attack look like a suicide attempt.</p>
        <p>The crime has none of the political intrigue of the other cases, mainly dealing with government corruption or voter fraud, before lawmakers as they examine the circumstances surrounding the dismissals of eight United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>But the Arizona case has reached all the way from the Navajo reservation to the halls of Congress, part of a still-stewing dispute within the Justice Department over a critical law enforcement question: Should interviews with criminal suspects be tape-recorded?</p>
        <p>Paul K. Charlton, the United States attorney in Arizona, was ousted after spending months protesting a Federal Bureau of Investigation policy that, for practical purposes, forbids the taping of almost all confessions, in stark contrast to the practice of many local law enforcement agencies in Arizona and other locations across the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Charlton blamed the F.B.I. policy for the resulting plea bargain in the Navajo reservation assault case, as well as the acquittal of a defendant in a child sexual abuse case and a suspect in a prison murder indictment.</p>
        <p>Eight states, by law or court action, mandate taping of interviews with suspects in at least serious felony cases, turning a tape recorder or video camera into an important tool in convictions, like DNA tests, fingerprints and ballistics. More than 450 law enforcement agencies in major cities and smaller jurisdictions also require the taping of certain interrogations.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I., a division of the Justice Department, has strenuously resisted the practice unless special permission is granted by supervisors, under the theory that it may discourage suspects from talking and expose juries to interrogation methods that the department would rather not highlight.</p>
        <p>But the inability to tape suspects, especially those accused of sexual abuse and domestic violence, can seriously compromise a case, Mr. Charlton and other prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Charlton said the problem was particularly acute in Arizona, a state with 21 Indian reservations, where federal law enforcement officials handle major felony cases. In essence, he said, differing investigative practices have resulted in two distinct criminal justice systems. If a crime occurred off the reservation, the confession would be taped, but if it happened on tribal land, it would not.</p>
        <p>''That disparity in justice is unacceptable,'' Mr. Charlton said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I., in documents defending its policy, argued that taping was not always possible, particularly when agents were on the road, and that it was not always appropriate. Psychological tricks like misleading or lying to a suspect in questioning or pretending to show the suspect sympathy might also offend a jury, the agency said.</p>
        <p>''Perfectly lawful and acceptable interviewing techniques do not always come across in recorded fashion to lay persons as proper means of obtaining information from defendants,'' said one of the once-secret internal Justice Department communications made public as part of the investigation into the dismissals of the United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>The debate in Arizona began in early 2006, when Mr. Charlton sent a memorandum to all federal law enforcement agencies in the state notifying them that, as of March 2006, any cases directed to his office for prosecution in which a statement from an investigative target has been taken must, with few exceptions, be recorded.</p>
        <p>''A defendant's admission regarding his own criminal conduct is often the most single powerful piece of evidence in a case,'' he wrote, in explaining the new policy. The F.B.I. agent in charge in Arizona offered some flexibility, approving the uniform taping of interviews with child victims of sexual crimes. But the agency made clear that mandatory taping of all suspects' statements was a nonstarter.</p>
        <p>A policy dispute turned into a major tug of war.</p>
        <p>Two days before the policy went into effect, Mr. Charlton said, he was pulled aside by an official from the deputy attorney general's office while attending a Justice Department conference.</p>
        <p>''The F.B.I. is furious,'' he said he was told. ''You have to pull this program back.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Charlton, convinced that the dichotomy in the system was unfair to victims and suspects on Indian reservations, refused, and threatened to resign. As a compromise, Justice Department officials asked Mr. Charlton to submit a plan to test the policy, which would be adopted only after the F.B.I. and other federal law enforcement players would be given a chance to weigh in. Mr. Charlton cited the Navajo beating case in his March 2006 petition for the approval of the pilot project. The defendant in that case, Jimmie Neztsosie, had been charged in 2005 with assault with intent to commit murder for the attack on his live-in girlfriend.</p>
        <p>After the victim refused to cooperate, and investigators determined that she had once before tried to commit suicide, Mr. Neztsosie's two-and-a-half hour confession became the most critical piece of evidence. But that confession had been turned into a two-page written statement, which did not indicate if Mr. Neztsosie was intoxicated during the interview and if he had been questioned in English or in Navajo.</p>
        <p>''An audio and/or video recording of the statement would allow the jury to hear from the defendant's own mouth what he did,'' the prosecutor who handled the case wrote, explaining why the office decided to agree to a plea bargain. ''The jury would be able to hear and see that the agents did not put words in the defendant's mouth, that the defendant understood English and that he was not intoxicated.''</p>
        <p>The failure to tape suspect interviews has been blamed for several high-profile setbacks for federal and state prosecutors, including the failure to impose the death penalty against Terry L. Nichols, in connection with the Oklahoma City bombing in 1995. Instead, Mr. Nichols was sentenced to life in prison after the jury foreman questioned why his statement to investigators had not been recorded.</p>
        <p>''Having the offender speaking and saying, 'Yes, I did it,' helps,'' said David LaBahn, executive director of the District Attorneys Association in California, where mandatory taping statewide has been under consideration.</p>
        <p>But officials at the F.B.I. remain unconvinced.</p>
        <p>They disputed Mr. Charlton's claim that he lost cases, or was forced to offer plea bargains, because of the failure to tape convictions. Officials also questioned the cost of a broad recording and transcription effort and the likelihood that defendants might decline to offer statements if they knew they were being recorded.</p>
        <p>''We interview thousands upon thousands of people every day of the year,'' said the F.B.I. director, Robert S. Mueller III, explaining his objection to Mr. Charlton's plan during a Senate hearing last week. ''And some of them may end up as defendants, some may not. And it's not a question of just recording the interviews, but also who is going to -- if they're recorded, who is going to transcribe them?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Charlton said the most disconcerting argument to him -- and apparently at least one official at the Justice Department -- was the bureau's worry that its interrogation techniques might offend juries. ''So we want to hide the truth?'' wrote one unnamed Justice Department official in a handwritten note, scribbled alongside the FB.I.'s defense of its policy. ''Don't want the jury to reach its own judgment?''</p>
        <p>The Justice Department review of Mr. Charlton's taping proposal continued for months, even as department officials in Washington assembled a list of United States attorneys who would be dismissed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Charlton's name was not on the early versions of this list. It showed up only in September, as the review of the taping policy drew to a close. Around the same time, Mr. Charlton had a conflict with Justice Department officials over a homicide that he did not believe should be prosecuted as a death penalty case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Charlton was removed before officials in Washington gave him a final verdict on his proposal. After his dismissal they cited his adamancy about the taping and his position on the death penalty case as two major reasons for his dismissal.</p>
        <p>''In light of Paul C.'s departure, should this initiative still go forward?'' said a memorandum written by Deputy Attorney General Paul J. McNulty in January, referring to Mr. Charlton. The memorandum was included in the materials turned over to Congress.</p>
        <p>The answer, as least so far, has not been forthcoming from the Department of Justice.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
