<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Johnson Edges Gordon In a Battle to the Finish</title>
    <meta content="02nascar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/othersports/02nascar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Jimmie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gordon, Jeff</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Johnson Edges Gordon In a Battle to the Finish</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jimmie Johnson Edges Jeff Gordon in Martinsville</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
      <dateline>MARTINSVILLE, Va., April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jimmie Johnson rounded the final corner of the final turn of the Goody's Cool Orange 500, took a bump from behind and would not give in as his racecar wiggled and the finish line approached.</p>
        <p>But when Johnson took the checkered flag for the victory Sunday at Martinsville Speedway, perhaps no one was more frustrated than his car owner. Jeff Gordon, Johnson's teammate at Hendrick Motorports and officially the owner of Johnson's No. 48 Chevrolet, was forced to settle for second after a hearty battle for the lead. Gordon did everything but put Johnson into the wall to try to pass over the final laps, but Johnson never lost control or position on the racetrack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Johnson took the checkered flag for the victory Sunday at Martinsville Speedway, perhaps no one was more frustrated than his car owner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jimmie Johnson rounded the final corner of the final turn of the Goody's Cool Orange 500, took a bump from behind and would not give in as his racecar wiggled and the finish line approached.</p>
        <p>But when Johnson took the checkered flag for the victory Sunday at Martinsville Speedway, perhaps no one was more frustrated than his car owner. Jeff Gordon, Johnson's teammate at Hendrick Motorports and officially the owner of Johnson's No. 48 Chevrolet, was forced to settle for second after a hearty battle for the lead. Gordon did everything but put Johnson into the wall to try to pass over the final laps, but Johnson never lost control or position on the racetrack.</p>
        <p>''I'm speechless for that,'' Johnson said of outdueling Gordon, the driver who recommended that Rick Hendrick sign Johnson years ago. ''I've looked up to him my whole career, before I was even actually racing.</p>
        <p>''That was amazing there at the end. That was the hardest driving I have ever done. Then to have my bumper beat off by my teammate in a way that didn't jeopardize either one of us, really class act by Jeff.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Johnson should have thanked Gordon and his team for the victory. When the teams arrived at Martinsville for practice Friday, Johnson struggled while Gordon's racecar was strong. So Johnson's crew chief, Chad Knaus, went to Gordon's team for information. Johnson's racecar was set up more similarly to Gordon's, ultimately helping Johnson to beat Gordon.</p>
        <p>It was the third victory in six Nascar Nextel Cup races this season for Johnson, the defending series champion, who is turning 2007 into a repeat of 2006. He is trying to become the first driver to win consecutive titles since Gordon in 1997 and '98. But Gordon, who posted his third second-place finish of the year, retained the lead in this year's points race, ahead of Jeff Burton and Johnson.</p>
        <p>Gordon refused to put Johnson into the wall to win the race. Hendrick teammates are instructed not to wreck each other, and Gordon said that another driver might have wrecked Johnson to get the victory.</p>
        <p>''I'm really upset that I'm sitting here talking about second,'' Gordon said. ''Like I said, without wrecking him, there was no way I was going to get it done.''</p>
        <p>Hendrick racecars have won the past four races, and the team has three drivers in the top five in points, including Kyle Busch in fifth.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of one of those starts you dream about,'' Hendrick said.</p>
        <p>The victory was also a sign of Chevrolet's dominance this season; the manufacturer has won five of six races. Dodge and the newcomer Toyota have been shut out, with Ford managing one victory. At Martinsville, the top seven drivers raced in Chevrolets.</p>
        <p>Among those with a strong finish was Dale Earnhardt Jr., who gave his red-clad fans a rare treat this season when he moved into the lead right before the midway point. Earnhardt had spent one lap at the front of the pack through the first five races in a season that has included a drawn-out contract renegotiation with his race team, Dale Earnhardt Inc., and a late wreck in the season-opening Daytona 500.</p>
        <p>He led 137 laps Sunday and was in the lead when the race was stopped for 31 minutes because of rain. Earnhardt finished fifth to move to 11th place from 17th in the standings.</p>
        <p>But the race was not an unqualified success for the Car of Tomorrow, the Nascar-designed racecar developed to improve safety and competition and to reduce costs.</p>
        <p>It made its debut at Bristol Motor Speedway last week to mixed reviews, with the race winner, Busch, panning the boxier model for poor handling. There was also some significant concern about failures in the new tailpipes, which led to heat problems and carbon monoxide flowing into the racecar. Several drivers complained about feeling ill after driving the Car of Tomorrow.</p>
        <p>''Why would you want to be driving around for four hours with toxicity in the car?'' the Roush Fenway president, Geoff Smith, said before Sunday's race. Some team executives complained to Nascar this week, but series officials played down the problem.</p>
        <p>The tailpipes can also vibrate and increase heat throughout the racecar. They can be noisier, too.</p>
        <p>The heat generated from the new racecars has also caused the foam energy-absorbing inserts in the driver's-side door to melt on occasion. Matt Kenseth complained the foam melted and spewed toxic smoke into his racecar at Bristol. The foam melted in Kevin Harvick's racecar at Martinsville.</p>
        <p>''It's almost turning into a joke now,'' a disgusted Harvick said of the new racecar.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
