<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="02forsumm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070403T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E0D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11</p>
        <p>Al Qaeda Heals in Pakistan While New Leaders Rise  As Al Qaeda rebuilds in Pakistan's tribal areas, a new generation of leaders has emerged under Osama bin Laden and is cementing control over the network's operations, according to American intelligence and counterterrorism officials.  A1</p>
        <p>Unease Over Islam in Britain  A decision to turn a Christian church into a mosque has underscored Britain's unease with its Muslim population. It may continue to regard itself as a Christian nation, but practicing Muslims will likely outnumber church-attending Christians in several decades, according to a new survey. A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Keeps Pressure On Iran  The White House sought to increase pressure on Iran to return the eight detained British sailors and marines, but took care to defer to Prime Minister Tony Blair, who has said he is seeking a diplomatic solution. A9</p>
        <p>McCain Claims Progress in Iraq  At least 24 people, including 4 American soldiers, were killed in attacks across Iraq that coincided with a visit by a Republican congressional delegation led by Senator John McCain, who declared that the new security plan was ''making progress.''  A11</p>
        <p>A Crisis in Central Africa  In two years of fighting in the Central African Republic, thousands of people have been killed. The violence has caused hundreds of thousands of the country's four million people to flee their homes, and in their desperation, some have sought refuge in their country's war-torn neighbors, Chad and Sudan.  A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A14-21</p>
        <p>DNA Testing Is New Tool In Searching Family History  The advent of inexpensive genetic testing has prompted a frenzy among amateur genealogists, who trace their family trees and often resort to extreme measures to retrieve DNA samples.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Darfuri Community in Indiana  Years of village burning, rape and mutilation have driven 2.5 million people from their homes in the Darfur region of Sudan, and a community in Fort Wayne, Ind., has become one of the largest concentrations of Darfuri in the United States.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Crime Intensifies Taping Debate  A crime involving a Navajo man charged with severely beating his girlfriend and then trying to cover it up as a suicide has intensified a debate within the Justice Department over a critical law enforcement question: whether interviews with criminal suspects should be tape recorded.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Mormon Tabernacle Renovation  The Salt Lake Tabernacle, completed in 1867 by the faithful of the fledgling Mormon religion, reopened over the weekend after a two-year, top-to-bottom renovation. Some aspects of the tabernacle's renovation, like the replacement of its original pews, have drawn criticism.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Clinton's Fund-Raising Edge  Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton's campaign for the Democratic presidential nomination said that it had raised $26 million in the first quarter of this year, about three times as much as the previous record at this stage of a presidential race.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-5</p>
        <p>School Aid Fight Erupts As State Budget Passes  Almost immediately after state lawmakers passed a $120.9 billion budget, a dispute erupted over education spending. Governor Spitzer proposed doling out money to different districts based solely on need, but his plan appeared to fall short to some, with wealthier school districts faring better than poorer ones.  A1</p>
        <p>Newark's Overall Crime Falls  Three months into 2007, overall crime in New Jersey's largest city had dropped some 40 percent from the previous year, but even as they continue to see a drop in shootings, burglaries, rapes and assaults, the police in Newark remain stymied by the rise in homicides.  B1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-8</p>
        <p>Apple and EMI Conference  A joint news conference by the chief executives of Apple Inc. and the EMI Group has encouraged speculation that the two may be preparing an announcement on making the Beatles available on an iPod or making an even more radical shift toward selling digital music without copy protection.  C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES A25</p>
        <p>Paul J. Cohen  A mathematician whose groundbreaking work in the field of logic helped resolve a fundamental question of mathematics, winning him a Fields Medal, he was 72.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: Taxing private equity; a law not to be trifled with; common defense; Lawrence Downes on Texas and immigration.</p>
        <p>Columns: Columns: Bob Herbert, Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Bridge E2  Crossword E2  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E9  Weather A20</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11</p>
        <p>Al Qaeda Heals in Pakistan While New Leaders Rise  As Al Qaeda rebuilds in Pakistan's tribal areas, a new generation of leaders has emerged under Osama bin Laden and is cementing control over the network's operations, according to American intelligence and counterterrorism officials.  A1</p>
        <p>Unease Over Islam in Britain  A decision to turn a Christian church into a mosque has underscored Britain's unease with its Muslim population. It may continue to regard itself as a Christian nation, but practicing Muslims will likely outnumber church-attending Christians in several decades, according to a new survey. A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Keeps Pressure On Iran  The White House sought to increase pressure on Iran to return the eight detained British sailors and marines, but took care to defer to Prime Minister Tony Blair, who has said he is seeking a diplomatic solution. A9</p>
        <p>McCain Claims Progress in Iraq  At least 24 people, including 4 American soldiers, were killed in attacks across Iraq that coincided with a visit by a Republican congressional delegation led by Senator John McCain, who declared that the new security plan was ''making progress.''  A11</p>
        <p>A Crisis in Central Africa  In two years of fighting in the Central African Republic, thousands of people have been killed. The violence has caused hundreds of thousands of the country's four million people to flee their homes, and in their desperation, some have sought refuge in their country's war-torn neighbors, Chad and Sudan.  A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A14-21</p>
        <p>DNA Testing Is New Tool In Searching Family History  The advent of inexpensive genetic testing has prompted a frenzy among amateur genealogists, who trace their family trees and often resort to extreme measures to retrieve DNA samples.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Darfuri Community in Indiana  Years of village burning, rape and mutilation have driven 2.5 million people from their homes in the Darfur region of Sudan, and a community in Fort Wayne, Ind., has become one of the largest concentrations of Darfuri in the United States.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Crime Intensifies Taping Debate  A crime involving a Navajo man charged with severely beating his girlfriend and then trying to cover it up as a suicide has intensified a debate within the Justice Department over a critical law enforcement question: whether interviews with criminal suspects should be tape recorded.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Mormon Tabernacle Renovation  The Salt Lake Tabernacle, completed in 1867 by the faithful of the fledgling Mormon religion, reopened over the weekend after a two-year, top-to-bottom renovation. Some aspects of the tabernacle's renovation, like the replacement of its original pews, have drawn criticism.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Clinton's Fund-Raising Edge  Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton's campaign for the Democratic presidential nomination said that it had raised $26 million in the first quarter of this year, about three times as much as the previous record at this stage of a presidential race.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-5</p>
        <p>School Aid Fight Erupts As State Budget Passes  Almost immediately after state lawmakers passed a $120.9 billion budget, a dispute erupted over education spending. Governor Spitzer proposed doling out money to different districts based solely on need, but his plan appeared to fall short to some, with wealthier school districts faring better than poorer ones.  A1</p>
        <p>Newark's Overall Crime Falls  Three months into 2007, overall crime in New Jersey's largest city had dropped some 40 percent from the previous year, but even as they continue to see a drop in shootings, burglaries, rapes and assaults, the police in Newark remain stymied by the rise in homicides.  B1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-8</p>
        <p>Apple and EMI Conference  A joint news conference by the chief executives of Apple Inc. and the EMI Group has encouraged speculation that the two may be preparing an announcement on making the Beatles available on an iPod or making an even more radical shift toward selling digital music without copy protection.  C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES A25</p>
        <p>Paul J. Cohen  A mathematician whose groundbreaking work in the field of logic helped resolve a fundamental question of mathematics, winning him a Fields Medal, he was 72.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: Taxing private equity; a law not to be trifled with; common defense; Lawrence Downes on Texas and immigration.</p>
        <p>Columns: Columns: Bob Herbert, Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Bridge E2  Crossword E2  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E9  Weather A20</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 3, 2007, Tuesday  An entry in the News Summary yesterday, about increased pressure by the White House to persuade Iran to release a group of British sailors and marines, misstated the number being held. It is eight sailors and seven marines -- not a total of eight sailors and marines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 3, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An entry in the News Summary yesterday, about increased pressure by the White House to persuade Iran to release a group of British sailors and marines, misstated the number being held. It is eight sailors and seven marines -- not a total of eight sailors and marines.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
