<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not a Big-Name Champion, But a Big-Time Performance</title>
    <meta content="02tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/tennis/02tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Florida</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not a Big-Name Champion, But a Big-Time Performance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Big Names in Tennis Long Gone, a Teenager Fills the Void</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>KEY BISCAYNE, Fla., April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The final day of the Sony Ericsson Open had the feel of a V.I.P. room after the last bold-face name slips away from the party. Serena Williams, the four-time women's champion, had left the Crandon Park Tennis Center a day earlier and taken two of her bigger fans, the Miami Heat basketball star Dwyane Wade and the actress Kristin Davis, with her.</p>
        <p>The two main headliners among the men, Roger Federer and Rafael Nadal, were long gone, having made surprisingly early exits, precluding the much-anticipated rematch of their 2005 final.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Novak Djokovic dispatched Guillermo Cañas to become the youngest men’s champion in the tournament’s 23-year history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The final day of the Sony Ericsson Open had the feel of a V.I.P. room after the last bold-face name slips away from the party. Serena Williams, the four-time women's champion, had left the Crandon Park Tennis Center a day earlier and taken two of her bigger fans, the Miami Heat basketball star Dwyane Wade and the actress Kristin Davis, with her.</p>
        <p>The two main headliners among the men, Roger Federer and Rafael Nadal, were long gone, having made surprisingly early exits, precluding the much-anticipated rematch of their 2005 final.</p>
        <p>Into this vacuum stepped Novak Djokovic, a fresh-faced Serb who proceeded to give the tournament its second wind and tennis its newest personality.</p>
        <p>Displaying the youthful exuberance of a teenager and the polished game of a veteran, Djokovic dispatched Guillermo Cañas, 6-3, 6-2, 6-4, Sunday in his second Masters Series final in less than a month to become the youngest men's champion in the tournament's 23-year history.</p>
        <p>Djokovic, who is 19 years 9 months, lost to Nadal in the Pacific Life Open championship at Indian Wells, Calif., then traveled directly here. He avenged his loss to Nadal in the quarterfinals and became the first man since Ivan Lendl in 1989 to win the tournament without dropping a set.</p>
        <p>After whipping a forehand winner past Cañas on match point, Djokovic landed on the court as softly as any of his drop shots. He lay there for several seconds, his bliss as clear as the skies above.</p>
        <p>''On the last point I said, I'm going for the forehand, I don't care,'' Djokovic said. ''If I make a mistake, I break racket.'' He smiled. ''And then I just fell down to the ground. I was very happy.''</p>
        <p>He picked himself up and made his way to the net, where he wrapped his long arms around Cañas, who has not been warmly received by all of his competitors since returning from a 15-month doping suspension.</p>
        <p>A 29-year-old Argentine, Cañas was ranked No. 8 in the world in 2005 when he was barred from the Tour after testing positive for a banned diuretic. He returned to competition last fall, after winning an appeal, and upset Federer in the second round at Indian Wells last month.</p>
        <p>He had to play his way into the main draw here, and after he defeated five ranked players, including the top-ranked Federer, to reach the final, his legs did not have much spring left. ''I'm old,'' Cañas said, laughing. ''After nine matches, all my body hurts.''</p>
        <p>Cañas received treatment on his left thigh during a changeover late in the third set, and he was being tended to by the ATP trainer Bill Norris after the match as Djokovic circled his changeover area as if in shock.</p>
        <p>Djokovic shed his sweat-soaked yellow shirt and then his racket, handing it to a young woman who was standing in the front row of the stands, directly behind where he had played the match's final game.</p>
        <p>''It was a very emotional moment for me,'' said Djokovic, who added that he considered giving away ''my shoes and shorts and everything.'' He laughed. ''But I said, Television is here so I'll keep those on.''</p>
        <p>During the presentation of the trophies, Butch Buchholz, the tournament chairman, who has been involved in professional tennis for nearly 50 years, introduced Djokovic by saying, ''Tennis has a new star today: Novak.''</p>
        <p>When asked about Buchholz's pronouncement, Djokovic exhaled deeply and said: ''A big moment. I wanted to go there and kiss him.'' Laughing, he added: ''I feel very, very proud about it. And I just hope that I'll become the best player one day.''</p>
        <p>Djokovic's game has a fluidity and a medley of shots that remind people of a young Federer, the game's Swiss master. Unlike many of today's young players, Djokovic does not just nibble the lines as if the court were a piece of bread and the crust were the only thing worth tasting.</p>
        <p>Throughout the 2-hour-18-minute match, Djokovic was content to hit shot after shot to the middle of the court, patiently waiting for Cañas to feed him a ball that he could place just over the net or on the line or deep in the corner for a winner. He finished with 44 winners to Cañas's 20.</p>
        <p>Djokovic held his serve in 59 of 60 games in the tournament. He was not broken in the final, though in the sixth game of the second set, while serving into the sun, it took him 22 points, 8 deuces and 19 minutes to hold for a 4-2 lead.</p>
        <p>That game, he said, ''was probably a turning point.''</p>
        <p>With his rangy, athletic build, it is not hard to imagine the 6-foot-2 Djokovic challenging Michael Phelps in the swimming pool or Ohio State guard Mike Conley Jr. on the basketball court.</p>
        <p>His father, Srdjan, an uncle and an aunt were professional skiers, but Djokovic chose tennis after his first coach, Jelena Gencic, told him he had a special gift.</p>
        <p>Gencic once worked with Monica Seles, the former No. 1 player who won nine Grand Slam women's singles titles. When Gencic told Djokovic he could be No. 1 some day, he believed her.</p>
        <p>Seles spoke to Djokovic, who rose to No. 7 in the world rankings, on Saturday, then attended Sunday's match. Djokovic confessed he did not have a chance to talk to her afterward. There were too many people clamoring for his attention.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
