<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Steinbrenner Consortium Gives Up Racing Bid</title>
    <meta content="02racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/othersports/02racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Racing Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Steinbrenner Consortium Gives Up Racing Bid</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Steinbrenner Consortium Backs Out of Horse Racing Bid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group that includes the family of the Yankees' principal owner, George Steinbrenner, has withdrawn from Excelsior Racing, which is among four bidders to run racing at Aqueduct, Belmont and Saratoga, it was announced yesterday by the family spokesman, Howard Rubenstein.</p>
        <p>The move comes just days after it was announced that George Steinbrenner's daughter Jennifer and her husband, Steve Swindal, were divorcing. Swindal and the casino developer Richard Fields were considered the two key figures in the Excelsior team, and Swindal was expected to have a major role in the operation of the three tracks in the event Excelsior was selected to take over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group including the family of the Yankees principal owner has withdrawn from Excelsior Racing, which is among four bidders to run racing around New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group that includes the family of the Yankees' principal owner, George Steinbrenner, has withdrawn from Excelsior Racing, which is among four bidders to run racing at Aqueduct, Belmont and Saratoga, it was announced yesterday by the family spokesman, Howard Rubenstein.</p>
        <p>The move comes just days after it was announced that George Steinbrenner's daughter Jennifer and her husband, Steve Swindal, were divorcing. Swindal and the casino developer Richard Fields were considered the two key figures in the Excelsior team, and Swindal was expected to have a major role in the operation of the three tracks in the event Excelsior was selected to take over.</p>
        <p>''The Steinbrenner family and all of their related entities are withdrawing from the Excelsior bid,'' the statement read. ''The reason is to pursue other opportunities.''</p>
        <p>The Steinbrenner group, which was operating as the Kinsman Racing Club, included, among others, Swindal and his wife and George Steinbrenner's sons, Hank and Hal, and another Steinbrenner daughter, Jessica. The group owned a 47.5 percent interest in Excelsior. According to yesterday's announcement, Tishman-Speyer, a real estate development company that owned a 5 percent share in Excelsior, has also dropped out.</p>
        <p>Fields owns the remaining shares in Excelsior.</p>
        <p>Without the Steinbrenner name and the Steinbrenner fortune behind it, Excelsior's chances of being named the new operator of the tracks has been dealt a significant blow. But an Excelsior spokeswoman, Katie Burke, said yesterday that Excelsior had no intention of dropping its bid to run the three tracks. Late last year, a committee formed during the administration of Gov. George E. Pataki recommended that Excelsior take over New York racing when the New York Racing Association's franchise expires at the end of this year.</p>
        <p>The current governor, Eliot Spitzer, has assembled a new panel to consider the bids and Excelsior will be among the four groups making presentations to the Spitzer panel on April 10.</p>
        <p>''Details about the future of our bid are forthcoming, but the one thing I can say with certainty is that Excelsior is moving forward and we're excited about the presentation we are about to make to the panel,'' Burke said.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Excelsior Web site was still trumpeting the importance of having Swindal and the Yankee organization as part of its team.</p>
        <p>''Steve Swindal and the Steinbrenner family successfully transformed a losing organization into the Yankee dynasty, one of the best known sports franchises in the world,'' read a portion of the site.</p>
        <p>It is expected that Excelsior will reorganize with new partners joining Fields.</p>
        <p>''Our team has always been recognized for the integrity, experience and investment level that we bring to the table,'' Burke said. ''I don't think any of that will change. I think the details of our actual bid are still being worked out. Some of the details of our plan and our team will be forthcoming this week.''</p>
        <p>No longer among the candidates to run the three tracks, Swindal is also apparently out as Steinbrenner's successor to run the Yankees. Before the divorce announcement, Steinbrenner had said that Swindal would eventually succeed him as the head of the Yankee organization. Swindal's problems began with a drunken-driving arrest on Feb. 15.</p>
        <p>Though the three New York tracks have lost considerable amounts of money in recent years, the franchise has increased dramatically in value because slot machines are now permitted at New York racetracks. A proposed casino at Aqueduct has yet to open, but the project is expected to move along at a more rapid pace once the new operator of the tracks is named.</p>
        <p>Excelsior, the New York Racing Association, Empire Racing Associates and an Australian group, Capital Play, are the four bidders.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
