<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tribune Plans to Sell Chicago Cubs</title>
    <meta content="02cnd-cubs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="ContinuousNews" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DA1F30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tribune Plans to Sell Chicago Cubs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN SCHWARZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chicago Cubs' 2007 marketing slogan exclaims, ''Play Like There's No Tomorrow!'' That will be literally true for the Tribune Company, which announced Monday that it would sell the Cubs, its storied subsidiary, later this year as part of the company's overall sale to the Chicago billionaire Sam Zell.</p>
        <p>The company did not reveal any prospective ownership groups, only that it planned to complete the transaction after the 2007 baseball season. That moment usually comes before the October playoffs for the Cubs, who have not won a World Series since 1908 or even participated in one since 1945.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chicago Cubs' 2007 marketing slogan exclaims, ''Play Like There's No Tomorrow!'' That will be literally true for the Tribune Company, which announced Monday that it would sell the Cubs, its storied subsidiary, later this year as part of the company's overall sale to the Chicago billionaire Sam Zell.</p>
        <p>The company did not reveal any prospective ownership groups, only that it planned to complete the transaction after the 2007 baseball season. That moment usually comes before the October playoffs for the Cubs, who have not won a World Series since 1908 or even participated in one since 1945.</p>
        <p>According to Forbes magazine's 2006 assessment of franchise values, the Cubs placed fifth among baseball's 30 clubs at $448 million, with revenues of $179 million and a $7.9 million operating profit. (The team had been valued at $247 million in 2001, representing 12 percent annual growth.) With baseball's booming overall business, due in part to labor peace and successful international and Internet ventures, the Cubs are expected to fetch close to $600 million or more.</p>
        <p>All club sales are subject to the approval of Major League Baseball's other 29 owners, which typically lengthens the process to six to 12 months.</p>
        <p>Soon after Tribune's announcement Monday, several names emerged as possible candidates to buy the team, including Mark Cuban, who owns the Dallas Mavericks; and Jerry Colangelo, chairman of the Phoenix Suns. Colangelo, the former owner of the Arizona Diamondbacks, told The Associated Press in November that he would have ''great interest'' in buying the Cubs if they became available.</p>
        <p>The announcement comes at what already was a turning point in the franchise's history, which extends all the way back to the National League's birth in 1876.</p>
        <p>The Cubs finished with the National League's worst record (66-96) last season and fired its manager, Dusty Baker. The team then embarked on the league's wildest spending spree, committing almost $300 million in long-term contracts to the slugger Alfonso Soriano ($136 million over eight years), the third baseman Aramis Ramirez ($75 million over five years) and the left-hander Ted Lilly ($40 million over four years), among others.</p>
        <p>The Cubs have enjoyed only fleeting success in their 26 seasons under Tribune control. The team posted a .478 winning percentage and reached the playoffs only four times, with considerable local dissatisfaction over how the team payroll did not appear to measure up to its home market size and corporate owner's wherewithal -- until this winter, when the team made its biggest push ever to buy its way back into contention.</p>
        <p>John McDonough, the Cubs' president and chief executive officer, said in a statement, ''This transition will not impact our on-field performance.'' That outlook was shared by the team's general manager, Jim Hendry, in a telephone interview minutes before his team took the field for its opening day game at Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>''The Tribune is going to run the team this year, and I've been assured that we're going to run it the way that we planned on all off-season and all spring training,'' Hendry said. ''There won't be any distractions to the ball club. It's full speed ahead trying to win as many games as possible. We have the backing of the company and if we need to add some players during the season, in the pennant race, we'll do that.''</p>
        <p>The Tribune Co. has overseen a renaissance at the team's steadfast ballpark, Wrigley Field. Lights were finally installed in the nearly century-old stadium in 1988, allowing for night games, and both luxury and bleacher seats were added later. With a historical ballpark that in some ways has become more of a draw than the team that plays in it, the Cubs attracted more than 3 million fans in 2004 and haven't dropped under that total since.</p>
        <p>''While they didn't get to the World Series, which is how most people measure a team, they did a tremendous job and the fans should be thankful for their stewardship of Wrigley Field,'' Andy MacPhail, the team's president and chief executive officer from 1994 until his resignation last October, said in a telephone interview. ''They did a marvelous job in that area.''</p>
        <p>The Tribune Co. originally purchased the Cubs in June of 1981 for $20.5 million from William Wrigley, whose family -- known also for its chewing gum -- had owned the team for three generations since 1916. The Tribune's simultaneous ownership of the Cubs and cable superstation WGN, a synergy similar to that of Ted Turner's Braves and WTBS, was a source of immediate tension because its games could be broadcast into other teams' home markets. It also preceded an era in which media companies sought major league teams to leverage the content across various platforms, particularly television.</p>
        <p>With the Tribune's impending sale of the Cubs, that era appears to be waning. The Disney Company sold the now Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim in 2003, and one year later Rupert Murdoch's News Corp. unloaded the Los Angeles Dodgers. The Braves are currently in the process of being sold by AOL Time-Warner to Liberty Media.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
