<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beltrán Has Swing of a Superstar, Minus the Usual Swagger</title>
    <meta content="02roberts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/baseball/02roberts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Selena Roberts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Beltran, Carlos</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beltrán Has Swing of a Superstar, Minus the Usual Swagger</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Beltrán Has Swing of a Superstar, Minus the Usual Swagger</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The curveball of Adam Wainwright's life took the trajectory of a cliff diver when it arched and plunged by the still-life image of Carlos Beltrán as he took a dastardly third strike to end the Mets' 2006 season.</p>
        <p>Beltrán stood alone as the Cardinals raced to the mound, vacating the batter's box with every disbelieving eye inside Shea Stadium on him. But Game 7 of the National League Championship Series does not define the image of Beltrán.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a new season begins, it seems clear that Carlos Beltrán has become the Mets’ undetectable superstar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The curveball of Adam Wainwright's life took the trajectory of a cliff diver when it arched and plunged by the still-life image of Carlos Beltrán as he took a dastardly third strike to end the Mets' 2006 season.</p>
        <p>Beltrán stood alone as the Cardinals raced to the mound, vacating the batter's box with every disbelieving eye inside Shea Stadium on him. But Game 7 of the National League Championship Series does not define the image of Beltrán.</p>
        <p>It was not as if he was spooked by the past last night. From home plate, Beltrán could see the St. Louis Arch rising over the skyscrapers -- was that the Gateway to the West or another curveball coming his way? -- as the Mets opened the 2007 season against the team that disrupted their World Series destiny.</p>
        <p>Beltrán ignored all symbolism. He produced offensively in the Mets' 6-1 victory, but his defense created the memory. In the sixth inning, Beltrán fielded a single in short center field and threw a dart to catcher Paul Lo Duca, who didn't have to move a cleat to tag out David Eckstein at the plate.</p>
        <p>''Eckstein is aggressive,'' Beltrán said, adding, ''That play made me feel good because it probably stopped a rally.''</p>
        <p>True, Beltrán's bat did not morph into a divining rod in Game 7 last October, but he is not Alex Rodriguez. He is not a target of dissection.</p>
        <p>Beltrán had already made peace with his critics.</p>
        <p>There was a curtain call he was coaxed into by Julio Franco during the second game of last season, an instant that took the edge off Beltrán's sensitivity to fan angst about his uninspiring 2005 debut with the Mets. Beltrán hopped up a dugout step and tipped his cap quickly and ducked out of sight. And yet his acceptance of an olive branch from the Shea crowd does not define Beltrán's image, either.</p>
        <p>In each case, one low and one high, Beltrán was solo in the camera lens, a position of extreme discomfort for him. Vampires and Greta Garbo have enjoyed the spotlight more than Beltrán.</p>
        <p>After a year with 41 home runs and 116 runs batted in, Beltrán has no swagger to match his swing, no Big Papi moniker, not an Albert Pujols diva moment on his résumé.</p>
        <p>Beltrán is the undetectable superstar.</p>
        <p>He was forced to be the face of the Mets in 2005, or at least the four days out of every five that Pedro Martínez couldn't provide him cover. Unlike any other Met, Beltrán will not be packaged or processed for public consumption.</p>
        <p>The Teen Magazine reader who has visions of cruising the streets on a dream date with David Wright could look over her shoulder  and find Beltrán perfectly comfy in the back seat.</p>
        <p>The Doublemint twinning of Wright and José Reyes in Mets marketing sessions worthy of Coke and Pepsi advertising hype tend to leave Beltrán to the status of the un-Cola.</p>
        <p>Beltrán would rather be a third wheel than a big wheel. His choice.</p>
        <p>Beltrán's insistent use of his library voice can be very refreshing in a celebrity culture of YouTube fame grabs.</p>
        <p>But don't the Mets deserve more for their $119 million investment? Beltrán doesn't have to play rock-paper-scissors with Reyes to reveal his youthful exuberance or become a Madison Avenue darling to keep up with Wright's pop-culture ranking.</p>
        <p>He doesn't have to reveal himself to the masses. But what about asserting himself in private?</p>
        <p>''I'd like to see more fire out of him,'' said José Valentín, who watched Beltrán grow up in their hometown of Manati, P.R. ''Sometimes he's too humble, too quiet.</p>
        <p>''There are going to be some people who won't have mercy on you, sure. But sometimes you have to step up and say, I have to show emotion, too.''</p>
        <p>The Tony Robbins motivational gene isn't in every superstar.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if that's who Carlos Beltrán is,'' Mets General Manager Omar Minaya said. ''I don't think you can expect people to be who they're not.''</p>
        <p>Beltrán recoils at scrutiny. As 2005 proved, he doesn't react well when he is alone with expectations. He is better surrounded, with Carlos Delgado to lift him, with Wright and Reyes to deflect attention.</p>
        <p>That's why 2007 will be the best season of Beltrán's career. The Mets have added yet more buffering for Beltrán by bringing in Moises Alou.</p>
        <p>''We've added Moises, so I think you'll see even better things out of Carlos Beltrán this year,'' Valentín said, adding, ''People were behind the Mets when they signed him because he can be a great player. He can be phenomenal. He can be even better. He has speed, arm, glove, power. He's the complete package.''</p>
        <p>The Mets can survive the slumps of Wright or Reyes or Delgado, but if they are to take 2007 further than 2006, they will ride Beltrán's consistency.</p>
        <p>''I think he can still be a .300 hitter with all the other things he can do,'' Minaya said. ''He has been a guy with power and speed and fielding. He can be that kind of hitter, too.''</p>
        <p>Beltrán is set up to succeed. The Mets have not forced him into ad campaigns or pushed him into photo ops. They've let him be as reclusive as he wants to be, as square as a Chiclet.</p>
        <p>Beltrán would make a good nesting doll. Maybe that's the image that best defines him.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: selenasports@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
