<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Oden's Shadow, Conley Takes Charge</title>
    <meta content="02conley" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/ncaabasketball/02conley.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ohio State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Oden, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFD71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Oden's Shadow, Conley Takes Charge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Oden’s Shadow, Conley Takes Charge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY GLIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glier, Ray</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For most of their time together as teammates in middle school, high school and college, Mike Conley Jr. has been the coaster under the tall glass of drink named Greg Oden. That has been O.K. with Conley, but not O.K. with Oden.</p>
        <p>After they made their decision to attend Ohio State, Oden, an acclaimed 7-foot center, wondered if one of them should change his mind and go to a different college because Oden was obscuring Conley's game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For most of their time as teammates, Mike Conley Jr. has been the coaster under the tall glass of drink named Greg Oden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For most of their time together as teammates in middle school, high school and college, Mike Conley Jr. has been the coaster under the tall glass of drink named Greg Oden. That has been O.K. with Conley, but not O.K. with Oden.</p>
        <p>After they made their decision to attend Ohio State, Oden, an acclaimed 7-foot center, wondered if one of them should change his mind and go to a different college because Oden was obscuring Conley's game.</p>
        <p>Ohio State Coach Thad Matta has joked that he and Oden are the only people who know how good a point guard Conley is. But it was no joke to Oden, because he said he felt responsible for the lack of credit given to Conley.</p>
        <p>''Greg wanted me to go somewhere else so I could show off my talent because I wasn't getting as much attention as I should,'' Conley said at a news conference Sunday. ''He told me that one time. 'Are you sure you want me to come to school with you after we picked Ohio State?' ''</p>
        <p>Oden, without meaning to, has finally done something to help his friend get his picture in the newspaper and his name on the marquee. Oden has been in foul trouble in this N.C.A.A. tournament, playing 18 minutes against Tennessee, 24 against Memphis and 20 against Georgetown.</p>
        <p>That meant it was Money Mike to the rescue. Conley got the nickname from the Ohio State senior Ron Lewis because he resembled a character in the movie ''Friday After Next,'' but Conley could just as well have gotten the nickname because of his play during the late stages of the tournament.</p>
        <p>In Saturday's national semifinal victory against Georgetown, Conley played 39 minutes and had one turnover and six assists.</p>
        <p>Just as important, he had 15 points, 11 in the first half while Ohio State was hanging on with Oden on the bench in foul trouble.</p>
        <p>Oden scored only 9 points in a Round of 16 victory against Tennessee, but the 6-1 Conley was there again to pump up the Buckeyes with 17 points, 7 above his season average.</p>
        <p>In the regional final against Memphis, Oden played well, making 7 of 8 shots, but he was only on the floor for 24 minutes because of more foul trouble. Conley played all 40 minutes and scored 19 points.</p>
        <p>''It has taken on a whole new meaning with some of the shots he has hit this year,'' the reserve forward Matt Terwilliger said of Conley's nickname.</p>
        <p>What makes Conley more impressive is his floor game and the way he sets up his teammates. He does not allow Oden to disappear under a blanket defense because Conley makes sure Oden gets the ball near the basket.</p>
        <p>If Oden is out of the game, Conley is knifing through double-teams and making defenders scramble to contain him. That can leave a shooter open.</p>
        <p>''He has a gift, he knows how to play, I don't know how you explain it,'' said Dan Peters, an Ohio State assistant. ''He knows how to take care of the big guy. I mean, how many times does Greg come down the floor and not get touches? If you're hot, Mike makes sure the next time down the floor you are going to get a touch.''</p>
        <p>Peters said that after two preseason practices, Jamar Butler, a junior guard, said that the only player Butler guarded that had similar quickness was the former Illinois guard Dee Brown, who was all-Big Ten and considered a one-man fast break because of his speed.</p>
        <p>Conley and Oden grew up in Indianapolis and started playing together in middle school, but it was not until an A.A.U. tournament in 2005 that Conley felt he might have something to offer without Oden on the floor. Oden missed the tournament, but the team did well without him using Conley as the focal point.</p>
        <p>''I hadn't played without Greg a lot, so I felt a lot of it, the bulk of the game was on me,'' Conley said. ''I had to lift my teammates. I did a good job in that tournament, and it gave me a whole lot of confidence. Ever since then, I felt like I could handle myself even when he's out the game.''</p>
        <p>For the first time, on the big stage of the N.C.A.A. tournament, it is becoming obvious just how well Conley can handle himself without Oden around.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
