<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lacking Big-City Luster, Junior Miss Carves a Niche</title>
    <meta content="02pageant" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/us/02pageant.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837552"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beauty Contests</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">colton (wash)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kowal, Jessica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beauty Contests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty Contests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lacking Big-City Luster, Junior Miss Carves a Niche</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lacking Big-City Luster, Junior Miss Carves a Niche</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSICA KOWAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kowal, Jessica</byline>
      <dateline>COLTON, Wash.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Junior Miss scholarship program, celebrating 50th anniversary, is all but abandoned by city and suburban girls who favor beauty pageants; big national sponsors have gone, and fewer than 6,000 girls, all high school juniors, will participate in 2007, down from 12,000 in 1990s; program takes place mostly in small towns like in Colton, Washington; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The night after millions of people watched a rehabbed, alcoholic Miss USA crown her comely replacement on national television, six teenage girls competed in an alternate universe for the title of Colton-Uniontown Junior Miss.</p>
        <p>The smart money was on Celia Jeannette Becker, 16, an articulate, outgoing redhead known as CJ who described Junior Miss as a chance ''to shine.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not a beauty pageant but a scholarship program, Junior Miss has been all but abandoned by city and suburban girls, who favor bustier, lustier, Trump-owned contests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The night after millions of people watched a rehabbed, alcoholic Miss USA crown her comely replacement on national television, six teenage girls competed in an alternate universe for the title of Colton-Uniontown Junior Miss.</p>
        <p>The smart money was on Celia Jeannette Becker, 16, an articulate, outgoing redhead known as CJ who described Junior Miss as a chance ''to shine.''</p>
        <p>Emily Tilton, also 16 and painfully shy, seemed a long shot. She was the last to sign up, and stage fright nearly grounded her rendition of ''Rocket to the Moon,'' played on the Colton School's battered upright piano.</p>
        <p>But Junior Miss is not about shrewd bets or popularity or sex appeal, and it steers clear of the humiliations prized by reality television. It is a scholarship program, not a beauty pageant. Grades count, but there is no swimsuit competition. The winner receives a medallion, not a crown.</p>
        <p>That is why, as it celebrates its 50th anniversary, Junior Miss has been all but abandoned by city and suburban girls who favor bustier, lustier, Trump-owned contests like Miss USA and Miss Teen USA.</p>
        <p>Once broadcast by NBC and CBS and sponsored by Coca-Cola, Junior Miss counts Diane Sawyer and Debra Messing among its national and state winners, respectively. Yet big sponsors have evaporated, and officials announced that Junior Miss would end in 2005, before state and local volunteers demanded its resurrection.</p>
        <p>Fewer than 6,000 girls -- all juniors in high school -- will participate in 2007, down from 12,000 in the 1990s, said Becky Jo Peterson, the executive director of America's Junior Miss, the national program, which is based in Mobile, Ala.</p>
        <p>''Life in general is more shallow, and we've been pressured to do the swimsuits and to be the glitz and glamour,'' Ms. Peterson said. ''We're not going to do that.''</p>
        <p>What resurrection there is takes place mostly in small towns like Colton (population 415), a farming community in Eastern Washington where everyone knows everyone and most students do not put locks on their lockers.</p>
        <p>''We're more focused on getting along with each other and acting like ourselves, rather than having to glamour up to impress people,'' CJ said. ''Junior Miss is about how you see yourself as beautiful.''</p>
        <p>The school has 169 students in kindergarten through 12th grade. Emily, CJ and Ashley Nygreen, 17, had a slight advantage in the competition because they were on the school's high honor roll, Emily said.</p>
        <p>Colton is in the Palouse, a fertile, rolling expanse of farmland. But it is not a hick town. Washington State University and the University of Idaho are just down the road. The contestants all plan to attend college, and the $1,500 in scholarship money for the winner would come in handy.</p>
        <p>Two contestants' fathers farm thousands of acres with garbanzo beans, lentils, wheat and barley. Among the other parents are mechanical and civil engineers, a chemist, a librarian, a nurse, a stay-at-home mother and a lumber grader.</p>
        <p>Just before 6:30 on a recent Saturday night, Jane Ann Nagle gave the contestants one last pep talk. Ms. Nagle, 19, won the 2004 contest in nearby Pullman and jump-started the program in Colton. She organized weekly practices and recruited the contestants, including her 17-year-old sister, Pamela.</p>
        <p>''No matter what happens, girls, keep going, keep smiling -- and I want some sass!'' Ms. Nagle said.</p>
        <p>With a few hundred friends and relatives watching from folding chairs in the gym, the curtains parted for the opening number, a mild, hip-swaying ''Arabian Nights'' dance the girls performed in front of a painted palace and two camels.</p>
        <p>Next came the group fitness routine. The girls giggled during the kick line and forced smiles during push-ups, situps and twists. Then they rushed to the dressing room, a space ordinarily used for preschool, to put on their talent costumes.</p>
        <p>''Nerve-racking!'' Emily declared, after changing into a long red dress for her piano performance.</p>
        <p>Nearby, Bridget Wos, 17, said, ''I'm kind of regretting that my dad is in the front row.''</p>
        <p>Unlike Miss Teen USA, Junior Miss requires a talent, judging a routine's originality, technical ability and ''appropriateness.''</p>
        <p>Alisa Moehrle, 16, performed a flawless exhibition of basketball skills that ended with a reverse dunk into a low hoop.</p>
        <p>CJ's many fans cheered her off-tune piano skit inspired by Molly Shannon's nerdy Catholic schoolgirl character on ''Saturday Night Live.'' For her big finish, she dropped to one knee, threw her hands up and, as Ms. Shannon does, shouted, ''Superstar!''</p>
        <p>When Emily finished at the piano, she went backstage and took deep breaths to calm herself.</p>
        <p>The contestants then changed to evening gowns, some left over from the prom, for the final two events. To show poise, they glided across the stage in their heels. For self-expression, each was asked to interpret a quote from a random lot of luminaries, including Winston Churchill, Anne Frank and John Lennon.</p>
        <p>It was here that Emily showed her chops. Presented with a quote from Churchill about courage, Emily succinctly summed it up: ''Don't lose hope, and keep going.''</p>
        <p>The judges' deliberations were excruciatingly slow, forcing the girls to kill time in their preschool dressing room. Relieved that her performance was behind her, Emily twirled about in a gauzy, rose-pink gown. ''We're done, we're done!'' she said.</p>
        <p>CJ, in a periwinkle dress that matched her eyes, parked herself in a preschooler's chair and colored with felt-tip pens.</p>
        <p>Just before the M.C. announced the winner, the girls gathered in a circle and held out their palms to play ''Down by the Banks of the Hanky Panky,'' a hand-slapping game they learned as children. They slapped one another's hands to settle their nerves, then filed out to hear the results: The second alternate, with a $125 scholarship, was Ashley Nygreen. The first alternate, with a $250 scholarship, was CJ Becker.</p>
        <p>''And your 2007 Colton-Uniontown Junior Miss is  Emily Tilton!''</p>
        <p>Emily gave a small wave as she accepted a rose and the medallion. Then, with the sudden realization that she would have to perform again at the state competition, her mouth formed the words, ''Oh my God.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
