<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tribune Presses Real Estate Magnate to Increase His Bid</title>
    <meta content="02tribune" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tribune Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zell, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burkle, Ronald W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, Eli</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tribune Presses Real Estate Magnate to Increase His Bid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q; Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tribune Co, in last-minute negotiations, pushes Chicago real estate tycoon Sam Zell to increase his bid for company; if Zell makes high enough offer, Tribune seems prepared to sell to him; seems doubtful Tribune would accept bid from Los Angeles billionaires Eli Broad and Ronald W Burkle (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In last-minute negotiations yesterday, executives for the Tribune Company were pushing Sam Zell, the Chicago real estate tycoon, to increase his bid for the company, according to people close to the talks. If Mr. Zell were to make a high enough offer, the company seemed prepared to sell its 160-year-old media empire to him, they said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zell could still walk away from the talks. But even if he were to drop out, it seemed doubtful that Tribune would accept a rival bid from Ronald W. Burkle and Eli Broad, two Los Angeles billionaires; more likely, the board members would decide to restructure the company themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In last-minute negotiations yesterday, executives for the Tribune Company were pushing Sam Zell, the Chicago real estate tycoon, to increase his bid for the company, according to people close to the talks. If Mr. Zell were to make a high enough offer, the company seemed prepared to sell its 160-year-old media empire to him, they said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zell could still walk away from the talks. But even if he were to drop out, it seemed doubtful that Tribune would accept a rival bid from Ronald W. Burkle and Eli Broad, two Los Angeles billionaires; more likely, the board members would decide to restructure the company themselves.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. Zell's bid of $33 a share, which he already increased once, had been $1 below the Burkle-Broad bid.</p>
        <p>On Friday afternoon, Tribune executives told Mr. Zell that he would have to offer them more money if he wanted to buy the company, the people said; Mr. Zell came back with a new bid of close to $34 a share.</p>
        <p>The Tribune board met on Sunday morning and rejected Mr. Zell's latest offer, telling him he would have to increase it yet again and giving him 12 hours to do so. People close to the talks, who sought anonymity because they were not authorized to speak to the news media, said the board planned to meet late Sunday night, but it was not clear what Mr. Zell would do or whether he would return with an offer at all.</p>
        <p>The Tribune board has favored Mr. Zell over Mr. Burkle and Mr. Broad, in part because Mr. Zell's offer is further along and could be finished more quickly, these people said. In addition, the board would prefer to sell the company to a Chicagoan like Mr. Zell, rather than to people with ties to Los Angeles, where disputes between Tribune and its largest newspaper, The Los Angeles Times, have been played out on the public stage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zell, who has said his sole interest in buying Tribune is economic, not editorial, has made billions in real estate and has been known to walk away from deals that he thought were too expensive.</p>
        <p>Tribune, which also owns The Chicago Tribune, other papers and 23 broadcast outlets, has been on the auction block since September. There was little interest in it, although Mr. Broad and Mr. Burkle combined in January to offer $27 a share. The board dismissed that and began concentrating on a plan to have management restructure the company itself, including spinning off the television properties.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Zell entered the picture in February and has been negotiating back and forth over the last several weeks. The board has seesawed on his bid, perceiving it as still too low and also concerned that he would be putting in only $300 million of his own money and taking on too much debt. He centered his proposal on an employee stock ownership plan.</p>
        <p>Then last week, Mr. Broad and Mr. Burkle complained that in order for Mr. Zell to offer a stock ownership plan, he must have received financial information that they had not received earlier. They revived their plan, offering $34 a share and $500 million of their own money and also basing it on a stock ownership plan. That set a new bar for Mr. Zell.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
