<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Jamaican Politics, Just About Everything Is Cricket</title>
    <meta content="02kingston" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/world/americas/02kingston.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="KINGSTON JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cricket (Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jamaica (West Indies)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lacey, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simpson-Miller, Portia (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheil, Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Jamaica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Jamaica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cricket</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Jamaica</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Simpson-Miller, Portia</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E3D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Jamaican Politics, Just About Everything Is Cricket</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Jamaican Politics, Just About Everything Is Cricket</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY; Ross Sheil contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lacey, Marc; Sheil, Ross</byline>
      <dateline>KINGSTON, Jamaica, March 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jamaican Prime Min Portia Simpson-Miller is tying her political future to frenzy over Cricket World Cup competition, donning cricket apparel and using cricket vernacular in her political speeches; when she took over in Feb 2006, it was widely believed that she would call elections quickly, but she delayed and her party was hit by financial scandal; her advisers have decided that delay in election will be best strategy, allowing her to benefit from frenzy surrounding tournament; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Portia Simpson-Miller of Jamaica is not a member of the West Indies cricket team now competing in the World Cup. She neither bats nor bowls for the Windies.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Simpson-Miller, who doubles as the nation's sports minister, sure doesn't act that way sometimes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Portia Simpson-Miller, who doubles as Jamaica’s sports minister, is hardly the only politician in the country to go cricket-crazy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Portia Simpson-Miller of Jamaica is not a member of the West Indies cricket team now competing in the World Cup. She neither bats nor bowls for the Windies.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Simpson-Miller, who doubles as the nation's sports minister, sure doesn't act that way sometimes.</p>
        <p>She recently donned cricket apparel, complete with shin protectors, gloves and a bat, for a newspaper advertisement promoting the tournament, which is being played in Jamaica and on eight other Caribbean nations. In the ad, she appeared to be making solid contact with the ball, perhaps even propelling her side to victory.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simpson-Miller, known widely as ''Sista P,'' has also been lacing her political speeches these days with cricket vernacular. Just listen to her at a recent rally here in the capital called to gear up her party's faithful for coming elections:</p>
        <p>''We have many wickets to take,'' she exclaimed, prompting the People's National Party activists before her to jump up and down with glee.</p>
        <p>''I have the strength to swing the bat,'' she added later, eliciting even more raucous behavior in the audience.</p>
        <p>''Your captain is ready,'' she declared, bringing about full-fledged pandemonium.</p>
        <p>Then she uttered the word ''six,'' which is the equivalent of a grand slam in cricket, prompting her backers to lose complete control. The conference room where she spoke took on the rowdy air of Sabina Park, where the Windies beat Pakistan, Zimbabwe and Ireland early in the tournament. Some in the crowd held both hands in the air, three fingers out on each hand, giving a cricket referee's signal for a ''six.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Simpson-Miller is hardly the only Jamaican politician to go cricket-crazy.</p>
        <p>The late Michael Manley, who served for two periods as prime minister, from 1972 to 1980 and from 1989 to 1992, also leading the People's National Party, set sports records as a schoolboy. And he was the author of ''A History of West Indies Cricket,'' which explored the ties between the game and Caribbean nationalism.</p>
        <p>Not to be outdone, Mr. Manley's longtime rival, Edward Seaga of the Jamaica Labor Party, who was prime minister from 1980 to 1989, was a boyhood cricket player and member of the Kingston Cricket Club. He recently recounted his love of wicketkeeping and his two favorite shots, the pull and the hook.</p>
        <p>It was Ms. Simpson-Miller's predecessor, P. J. Patterson, who played a crucial role in bringing the World Cup to the Caribbean this year, the first time the region has been the host of the tournament since it began in 1975. The West Indies won that first cup, incidentally, and managed to win the second one, too.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Patterson stepped down last year and Ms. Simpson-Miller, using the slogan ''Come to Mama,'' beat three male competitors within the ruling party to take the prime minister post, she inherited the big event.</p>
        <p>And she is making the most of it. As the party chairman, Robert Pickersgill, told The Gleaner, Jamaica's principal newspaper, recently, ''With the bounce we are now getting from the cricket, the opposition is stumped.''</p>
        <p>The Gleaner took umbrage at the remark and suggested that politics had better stay off the cricket pitch. ''Hosting cricket, we assumed, was a national rather than a partisan matter,'' the paper said. ''Any government that decided to spend upward of $120 million on the event would have done so because they believe it would be good for Jamaica.''</p>
        <p>That spending has been criticized by Bruce Golding, the leader of the opposition. He has suggested that the money that went to build a new stadium would have been better spent upgrading the hospitals, which lack basic medicines, or supporting the police, who often have no transportation to get to the scene of the crime in time.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simpson-Miller's government, however, has argued that the effects of cricket will be long-lasting. There has been some disappointment with ticket sales, and the flood of tourists that had been expected never materialized. But Ms. Simpson-Miller notes that the pretournament refurbishment that Jamaica received will not go away when the cup is awarded -- hopefully to the Windies, of course.</p>
        <p>She has not let on when she will call elections, although she is obligated to do so by October. Cricket has clearly been a factor in the scheduling.</p>
        <p>The conventional wisdom when she took over in February 2006 was that she would set the date soon to take advantage of her enormous popularity as Jamaica's first female prime minister. But she delayed, and then a financial scandal hit her party when it was discovered that a Dutch-based commodities firm, Trafigura Beheer BV, which does business with the government, had secretly donated nearly half a million dollars to her campaign.</p>
        <p>With the World Cup looming, her advisers decided that a delay in the election would be the best strategy, allowing her to benefit from the frenzy surrounding the tournament.</p>
        <p>Whether that calculation will work is uncertain. Her popularity has dropped considerably over the last year as the opposition has smeared her government as corrupt and ineffectual. And tying her fortunes to cricket carries risk.</p>
        <p>[The Windies, after winning their first three matches, have dropped contests with Australia and New Zealand in Antigua. On Sunday, playing in Guyana, the Windies lost to Sri Lanka. Taking the tournament appears to be a long shot.]</p>
        <p>And on top of that, the killing of Bob Woolmer, the Pakistani cricket coach, on March 18, after his team lost a key match against Ireland and was ousted from the World Cup, has filled newscasts and front pages with the kinds of death-in-paradise stories that Jamaica hates.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simpson-Miller acknowledged to reporters recently that the killing had ''cast a pall'' over the tournament. But in the next breath, she expressed confidence in the investigation, which has produced no suspects, and discussed the fact that the best way to honor Mr. Woolmer was to focus on the game he loved.</p>
        <p>She is certainly taking her own advice. Here is another excerpt from her political speech, delivered in her typical rousing style, ''Get out there and prepare the field to ensure that when I call the match, when I win the toss, when I elect to bat first, we're ready.''</p>
        <p>KINGSTON JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
