<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tick, Tock, Or Maybe Tock, Tick</title>
    <meta content="02robe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/arts/music/02robe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">St Louis Symphony Orchestra</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Robertson, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Graham, Susan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EED91E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tick, Tock, Or Maybe Tock, Tick</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tick, Tock, or Maybe Tock, Tick</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I can't think of a conductor who brings more interesting music on his visits to New York City than David Robertson. For years in Europe in the middle of every new-music enterprise imaginable, and now deepening his acquaintance with the standard repertory as music director of the St. Louis Symphony, Mr. Robertson has found ways to keep our minds from wandering.</p>
        <p>On Friday and Saturday at Carnegie Hall he and his St. Louis players did six pieces, with only the Sibelius Second Symphony describable as a day-in-day-out affair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>I can’t think of a conductor who brings more interesting music on his visits to New York City than David Robertson, the music director of the St. Louis Symphony.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I can't think of a conductor who brings more interesting music on his visits to New York City than David Robertson. For years in Europe in the middle of every new-music enterprise imaginable, and now deepening his acquaintance with the standard repertory as music director of the St. Louis Symphony, Mr. Robertson has found ways to keep our minds from wandering.</p>
        <p>On Friday and Saturday at Carnegie Hall he and his St. Louis players did six pieces, with only the Sibelius Second Symphony describable as a day-in-day-out affair.</p>
        <p>New to most of us was George Benjamin's ''Sudden Time,'' a title certain to get the interpretive side of the brain working. Its 15 minutes of music, if freed of analytical baggage, were to be enjoyed just as much viscerally.</p>
        <p>The invention of ticking clocks changed the way people thought about time and to a degree the way music thought about itself. Mechanical clocks were at least one reason free-flowing meter and melody began to be fenced off by bar lines and time signatures. Mr. Benjamin's piece acknowledges that with fast travel, time zones and daylight saving plans, not to mention Einstein and relativity, things temporal have grown more complicated.</p>
        <p>''Sudden Time'' begins like a collection of clocks and watches, each set in its own way. Booming pendulum strokes emerge and retreat through layers of different movements. Elsewhere, if it is 9:30 in the oboes, it might be 10:45 in the second violins. The accumulated sounds are lovely, colored by sinking, sighing slides between pitches. The unbroken legato later splits into shorter segments more harshly colored. A soft, steady hum underlies a lot of this piece, as if to reassure us that someone somewhere does know what time it is.</p>
        <p>After the Benjamin came Bartok's First Piano Concerto, its almost violent solo part played by the amazing Pierre-Laurent Aimard. Bartok celebrates Hungarian dance rhythms as if he were making war. The music is organized barbarism, disagreeable if played by a lesser talent but very satisfying here.</p>
        <p>The other soloist was Susan Graham singing Ravel's ''Shéhérazade'' on Saturday. Ms. Graham's mezzo-soprano is beautifully managed, but it is her utter delight in the physical act of singing that brings the musicianship forward. ''No sex, please, we're musicians,'' is the usual rule of the concert hall. Statuesque, always dignified, Ms. Graham steps over the line.</p>
        <p>Spending two evenings with this orchestra generates a genuine fondness for it. The sound is big, warm and very intense -- pleasingly plump if not a little overweight. The horns responded beautifully to a series of challenges. The St. Louis is not very good at clearly articulated string playing, but you can't help sharing its enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>The orchestra made all the wonderful big noises in John Adams's ''Harmonielehre'' on Saturday, but it was less successful at rhythms that must be sharp enough to cut. It seemed to swim through the Sibelius on Friday, every edge rounded, every texture smothered in love.</p>
        <p>The players found a friend in the Adagio movement of Mahler's otherwise unfinished 10th Symphony, devastating music made even more devastating by standing alone. The beauty of ruins -- and the Mahler is both ruined and beautiful -- might best be honored here. Attempts to ''finish'' this piece are presumptuous and unwise. Would reattaching arms and legs to torsos from antiquity make them more perfect? I think we have made peace with their abridged and mutilated state and like them as they are.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
