<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bumpy Ride to the Top for an Athletic Director</title>
    <meta content="02gators" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/ncaabasketball/02gators.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFD71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bumpy Ride to the Top for an Athletic Director</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Florida’s Athletic Director, a Bumpy Ride to the Top</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE; Pete Thamel contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the N.C.A.A. championship game between Ohio State and Florida on Monday night at the Georgia Dome, Gators Athletic Director Jeremy Foley said that he would touch his good-luck charm frequently.</p>
        <p>It was given to him two years ago by a friend in Columbus, Ohio; it is a nut that fell from a Buckeye tree (aesculus glabra), the state tree of Ohio. Foley said Sunday that it did not bother him that his totem of happy fortune represented the nickname of the opposing team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a championship team in football and a contender for the men’s basketball title, the Gators’ athletic director is enjoying his success.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During the N.C.A.A. championship game between Ohio State and Florida on Monday night at the Georgia Dome, Gators Athletic Director Jeremy Foley said that he would touch his good-luck charm frequently.</p>
        <p>It was given to him two years ago by a friend in Columbus, Ohio; it is a nut that fell from a Buckeye tree (aesculus glabra), the state tree of Ohio. Foley said Sunday that it did not bother him that his totem of happy fortune represented the nickname of the opposing team.</p>
        <p>''They were the Buckeyes on Jan. 8, too,'' Foley said, referring to the date this year when the Florida football team beat Ohio State for the national championship. Monday's game could be the first time that the same Division I university has won both titles in the same academic year.</p>
        <p>The Gators won the basketball title last season, and they are favorites to win again and become the first team to repeat since Duke in 1992. Foley, who started at Florida as a ticket-office intern in 1976, is at the top of a competitive profession.</p>
        <p>''Gator fans should enjoy the success,'' Foley said Sunday. ''It's hard to do. You can't ever take it for granted. It isn't always going to be like it is today.'' Things were worse for Foley in 2004, when he fired the football coach Ron Zook, who had replaced Steve Spurrier with less success.</p>
        <p>In those days, people would yell at Foley through open car windows when he jogged on the campus in Gainesville, Fla. ''That's part of the gig, sometimes,'' he said. ''I just put down my head and kept running.'' On the highway, he saw a billboard calling for his firing.</p>
        <p>The criticism stopped after Foley beat out Notre Dame to hire Urban Meyer from Utah in December 2004. Among the people who helped convince Meyer and his wife, Foley said, were Billy Donovan, the basketball coach, and his wife.</p>
        <p>But with Donovan on the verge of a second title in his 11th year, Foley may have to replace him next. Donovan has neither denied nor discouraged reports that he is a candidate at Kentucky to replace Tubby Smith, who has moved to Minnesota.</p>
        <p>Foley refused several times Sunday to discuss the possibility of another coaching change, although he did reflect with humor on his differences with Donovan. ''He's a Yankees fan, and I'm a Red Sox fan,'' Foley said. Donovan is from Long Island; Foley is from New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>They discovered their baseball allegiances shortly after Donovan was hired while they chatted at a Gators baseball game.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Wait a minute, you're not a Yankee fan are you?' '' Foley said, recalling that Donovan replied, ''Does the name 'Bucky Dent' mean anything to you?''</p>
        <p>Foley, 54, has close-cropped silver hair and an athletic build, giving him the look of a retired astronaut. His father worked in the State Department. Foley has twice run the Boston Marathon. He speaks in rapid bursts of words and often uses the word ''obviously'' when answering questions.</p>
        <p>Twice divorced and currently unmarried, Foley has acknowledged in the past that he was too harsh on people while rising through the athletic department. Along with selling tickets, Foley's first duties included parking cars and cleaning restrooms.</p>
        <p>His career stalled for a few years in part because of an abrasive personality. That improved after the president of the booster club, Leonard Levy, offered him some advice.</p>
        <p>''Some people told me what a jerk this guy was,'' Levy said Sunday in a telephone interview from Tampa, Fla. ''He had taken apart an assistant coach. I said: 'You want to be an athletic director? You'll never make it.' He'd gotten a little authority, and it went to his head.''</p>
        <p>A few weeks later, Levy said, he got a different report when someone told him, ''You've never seen a guy change so much in your life.'' Later, Levy helped Foley get the top post in 1992. ''He's an extraordinary person,'' Levy said. ''What a tremendous job he's done.''</p>
        <p>Foley, reflecting on his changes, said Sunday: ''Obviously, I can still be harsh on people. And I don't take pride in that. Sometimes, your temper gets the better of you. I try to be more respectful of people. It's much more effective.'' But his sports programs are harmonious.</p>
        <p>Donovan, when asked why the football and basketball programs had enjoyed simultaneous success, said, ''We all get along really well, and I don't think that's the case necessarily at all places.'' Meyer said Sunday that Foley ''wouldn't put up with'' friction between the programs.</p>
        <p>''He creates an environment of excellence,'' Meyer said of Foley. Meyer said one university tried to hire him by giving him eight books to read. Foley, Meyer said, gave him one binder filled with family-oriented information. ''There wasn't a wasted page,'' Meyer said.</p>
        <p>Foley once said that his mother told him of mistakes, ''A gentleman never says he is sorry, he just never does it again.'' Recalling that Sunday, Foley offered a different view.</p>
        <p>''I don't have any problem saying I'm sorry,'' he said. ''When you make a mistake, apologize for it.''</p>
        <p>Of course, when a university wins as much in major sports as Florida has lately, there are fewer reasons to say you are sorry.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
