<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Stringer, Only One Thing Left to Do</title>
    <meta content="02araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/ncaabasketball/02araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837613"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Stringer, C Vivian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Stringer, Only One Thing Left to Do</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Stringer, Only One Thing Left to Do</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cleveland</p>
        <p>C. Vivian Stringer goes back to an N.C.A.A. women's basketball final tomorrow night, 25 years after she coached in the first one ever played, when her Cheyney State team opened an era by losing to Louisiana Tech, when she was reminded that a coach's life isn't always fair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like it or not, championships are the basis of the definitive performance appraisal in big-time college sports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cleveland</p>
        <p>C. Vivian Stringer goes back to an N.C.A.A. women's basketball final tomorrow night, 25 years after she coached in the first one ever played, when her Cheyney State team opened an era by losing to Louisiana Tech, when she was reminded that a coach's life isn't always fair.</p>
        <p>''I was substituting a 5-11 and Louisiana Tech was substituting a 6-3,'' she said. ''You heard of Dennis Rodman? You know how great a rebounder Dennis Rodman was, right?''</p>
        <p>Well, guess what? Stringer said. His sister, Debra, wasn't half-bad either.</p>
        <p>Ancient history now, especially after Rutgers's 59-35 demolition of Louisiana State at LeBron's house, otherwise known as Quicken Loans Arena, set up a championship matchup against Tennessee, a 56-50 comeback winner against North Carolina.</p>
        <p>It's possible that even King James would not have leveled the playing court last night, when Matee Ajavon and Essence Carson shot Rutgers to an 18-point halftime lead; when Kia Vaughn and the Knights laid a scarlet blanket on L.S.U.'s Sylvia Fowles; when Stringer's team held the Lady Tigers to a Final Four-record low in points and moved within one victory of what has eluded her for 35 years.</p>
        <p>''Wow,'' was the first word out of Stringer's mouth in the interview room. ''The best way to describe what's happening here.''</p>
        <p>The most scrupulous coaching evaluation would be based on graduation rates, on the number of quality people sent out into the world. But those results are not talked  about often enough, nor do they play well as sports-television theater.</p>
        <p>Like it or not, championships form the basis of the definitive performance appraisal in the big-time college arena, even when your instincts tell you that few people have ever come out of a Stringer program and not been better prepared to be a winner, or at least a survivor.</p>
        <p>How could most young women not grow from being around Stringer, given her trails walked and tribulations endured?</p>
        <p>She notched her 777th career victory against L.S.U. and Bob Starkey, a 47-year-old head-coaching veteran of five games, all in the N.C.A.A. tournament after the abrupt resignation of Pokey Chatman.</p>
        <p>Starkey -- a pleasant tactician who could pass for Karl Rove's younger brother -- had answered, ''Not at all,'' to the question of whether he could imagine himself being called an N.C.A.A. championship coach. But somehow it seemed fair that he, of all people, didn't go forward instead of Stringer.</p>
        <p>Not after her long runs at three different programs, all of them taken to a Final Four but never to the promised land, to the victory that Tennessee Coach Pat Summitt, a six-time champion, said would be ''an exclamation point'' to Stringer's career.</p>
        <p>''I just want to know what it feels like,'' Stringer said. ''How could I not?''</p>
        <p>The odds have been rising with each succeeding year, with more universities investing the necessary dollars to get in the game.</p>
        <p>''You need eight players and you consider what the talents need to be and all things need to be right,'' Stringer said. ''But along with that, you have to be lucky on the other side of it, too.''</p>
        <p>Someone -- last night it was Carson, who went down in the second half with a cramp in her right quadriceps -- could always get hurt. Carson said she would play tomorrow, but it was a reminder that at any time, on the court and off, life can intrude on what seems to be a perfectly legitimate opportunity.</p>
        <p>Stringer has pushed forward for three-plus decades despite family tragedy ranging from her daughter's contracting spinal meningitis as an infant to the death of her husband at 47 on Thanksgiving  15 years ago; from the involvement of one son in a serious auto accident to another's indirect involvement in the shooting death of a fellow student at North Carolina State.</p>
        <p>For all the undeserved stress visited upon L.S.U. and Starkey in the wake of Chatman's departure for what has been reported to be allegations of an improper relationship with a player or players on past teams, how could anyone but Stringer, the daughter of a Pennsylvania coal miner, be the sentimental favorite here?</p>
        <p>How could the N.C.A.A. not be relieved to have the Chatman story off the championship stage?</p>
        <p>This season won't be remembered fondly in women's coaching circles, not after the messy resignations of Chatman from L.S.U. and Rene Portland from Penn State. Portland's concluded a 27-year run after years of trying to live down allegations of policies discriminatory to lesbians.</p>
        <p>People often refer to the gay issue in women's sports as the elephant in the room, but let's remember that the Portland and Chatman cases can be seen as abuse of position and power, a far-too-common occurrence in all walks of sport.</p>
        <p>These issues tend to become more polarizing for women, played out in  complicated, surreptitious ways. Whether Chatman's improprieties at L.S.U. were of a sexual nature or not, don't think for a second they won't be cited by coaches willing to lower the strategic recruiting bar.</p>
        <p>In this dog-eat-dog world, it takes an alpha personality to do this year after year, to suffer the rejections, the disappointments, the harsh judgments. Charlene Vivian Stringer has managed even longer than Summitt, titleless as she is.</p>
        <p>''I guess I'm often times amazed that that's the standard that people look at as to whether or not that coach is legit,'' said Summitt, Stringer's close friend and much to Summitt's  dismay, Stringer's opponent tomorrow. ''But she's a great coach, regardless of whether or not that happens.''</p>
        <p>Stringer, 58, speaks in energized bursts, occasionally not finishing one thought before starting another. On the bench, her face is perpetually clenched with intensity.  She still has passion for her work, as evidenced by her ability to lather up her senior-less team for its smackdown of the Lady Tigers and Fowles, who just last week destroyed Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''I'll always pursue excellence,'' Stringer said. ''And excellence is a national championship.''</p>
        <p>One more step, one more victory, from the idealistically superficial but realistically supreme measure of a college basketball coach.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
        <p>E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
