<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Call Me Mister Correspondent</title>
    <meta content="02wilm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/arts/television/02wilm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Comedy Central</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stewart, Jon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EED91E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Call Me Mister Correspondent</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">They Call Me Mister Correspondent</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Felicia R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Larry Wilmore, one of the newer fake reporters on ''The Daily Show With Jon Stewart,'' stakes out his comic targets with the glee and democracy of a kid in a candy store.</p>
        <p>He was seen on this Comedy Central late-night news satire last week embarrassing white people on Manhattan's Upper West Side by seeking their opinion of the ''n-word,'' which he used. A few nights ago, commenting on Disney's announcement of its first black princess character, he jested, ''Well, we have overcome.'' Mr. Wilmore treated viewers to film clips of Disney's ''Dumbo,'' which caricatured black people as goofy crows, and ''Song of the South,'' with its stereotypical Uncle Remus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Larry Wilmore, one of the newer fake reporters on “The Daily Show With Jon Stewart,” stakes out his comic targets with the glee and democracy of a kid in a candy store.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Larry Wilmore, one of the newer fake reporters on ''The Daily Show With Jon Stewart,'' stakes out his comic targets with the glee and democracy of a kid in a candy store.</p>
        <p>He was seen on this Comedy Central late-night news satire last week embarrassing white people on Manhattan's Upper West Side by seeking their opinion of the ''n-word,'' which he used. A few nights ago, commenting on Disney's announcement of its first black princess character, he jested, ''Well, we have overcome.'' Mr. Wilmore treated viewers to film clips of Disney's ''Dumbo,'' which caricatured black people as goofy crows, and ''Song of the South,'' with its stereotypical Uncle Remus.</p>
        <p>Such provocations get the tall Mr. Wilmore, 45, noticed on the street these days, after more than 15 years spent mostly behind the camera. He wrote for shows like the sketch comedy ''In Living Color'' and the sitcom ''The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air''; was a creator and producer of ''The PJs,'' a prime-time animated series; and served as executive producer for ''The Bernie Mac Show,'' which won him an Emmy for writing.</p>
        <p>''I'll take love or hate,'' he said during a recent early-morning interview punctuated by sips of coffee and bites of croissant. ''It's indifference that's the bad one.''</p>
        <p>Since August Mr. Wilmore, who lives outside of Los Angeles with his wife and two children, has put in a handful of appearances as a contributor to ''The Daily Show.'' He's a low-key, earnest contrarian in wire-rimmed glasses and a suit, mouthing off in unexpected ways. For instance, when asked if Black History Month served a purpose, he replied, ''Yes, the purpose of making up for centuries of oppression with 28 days of trivia. I'd rather we got casinos.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilmore began his tenure on the show with a jab at one of the conceits of media. Mr. Stewart introduced him as the ''black correspondent,'' and he demanded that Mr. Stewart address him as ''senior black correspondent.'' He is now known as the resident ''senior black correspondent.'' The joke is that Mr. Wilmore is the show's only black correspondent.</p>
        <p>He is an easygoing guy who grew up Catholic in suburban Los Angeles (his father is a doctor), developing a taste for social humor.</p>
        <p>''Part of that niche on the show is covering some of the topics 'The Daily Show' has never had a chance to cover because sometimes you can take it better when it's from somebody who's your own kind,'' Mr. Wilmore said. ''A lot of times when something happens in a black neighborhood, they will send the one black correspondent to cover it. That was our satirical jumping-off point.''</p>
        <p>In some ways his new visibility on a show that has made stars of white male comics like Steve Carell, who now plays the lead on ''The Office'' on NBC, and Stephen Colbert, who has his own Comedy Central fake news show, ''The Colbert Report,'' is telling. ''The Daily Show'' satirizes racial typecasting, but it also has a paucity of nonwhite voices.</p>
        <p>Of six full-time correspondents and four contributors who appear on ''The Daily Show,'' all but three are white males. The exceptions are Samantha Bee, a female senior correspondent; Aasif Mandvi, a native of India who is also relatively new to the show; and Mr. Wilmore.</p>
        <p>''While it might be tempting to say 'The Daily Show's' lack of diversity is a deliberate result of the white-male dominated media they parrot, the truth is the new guard looks a lot like the old boys' club,'' said Matthew T. Felling, media director for the Center for Media and Public Affairs, a Washington organization that also studies diversity.</p>
        <p>''The Daily Show'' declined to respond to Mr. Felling's assertion but sent an e-mail message listing the names of women and African-Americans who have been contributors and correspondents on the show.</p>
        <p>David Javerbaum, the show's executive producer, commented on Mr. Wilmore in an e-mail message. ''Joe Biden's description of him was accurate: Larry really is 'the first mainstream African-American ''Daily Show'' correspondent who is articulate and bright and clean and a nice-looking guy,' '' he wrote, with an implied joke about Senator Biden's description of Senator Barack Obama, the presidential candidate.</p>
        <p>Peter B. Aronson, a longtime associate who worked with Mr. Wilmore on ''In Living Color,'' ''The PJs'' and ''The Bernie Mac Show,'' said: ''He has a completely unique comic point of view, which is now on display. It's smart and manages to be racially sensitive and completely mainstream at the same time. I think he gives them a whole new audience.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilmore said he believes he was hired at a time when the show wanted to add different kinds of people and he was seeking to re-energize his performing career. ''I just thought it would be fun to be on 'The Daily Show,' and we called Jon Stewart,'' Mr. Wilmore said of the unusually smooth process his managers used to get him on the show.</p>
        <p>It was ''serendipitous,'' he said, that ''The Daily Show'' was hiring, and that he and Mr. Stewart hit it off.</p>
        <p>In the last two years Mr. Wilmore has also appeared as Mr. Brown, the diversity consultant on ''The Office,'' a show for which he has written and is a consulting producer. His younger brother Marc Wilmore is a writer for ''The Simpsons.''</p>
        <p>Larry Wilmore was a theater major at California State Polytechnic University but dropped out to get his Actors' Equity Association card and begin his career as a stand-up comedian. He tried his hand at acting but spent the early 1980s in a kind of Hollywood shuffle, he said, being woefully miscast because of his race. ''I would just read for the part of the fast-talking ex-con,'' Mr. Wilmore said, laughing.</p>
        <p>He turned to working behind the scenes, getting big breaks like helping create ''The PJs,'' Eddie Murphy's animated series about life in the projects, in 1999.</p>
        <p>He said he remains proud of ''The Bernie Mac Show'' but contends that the Fox network never really understood it, and that the sitcom was mired in a TV landscape that ghettoized black shows. He said he is baffled that the CW show ''Everybody Hates Chris,'' which has the imprimatur of a major star like Chris Rock, never made it to a major network. (''I always call CW the Negro Leagues of CBS,'' Mr. Wilmore said. CBS is a part owner of CW.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilmore seldom does stand-up now but plans to do so soon, and he has a few TV projects in the works. His varied background allows him to handle transitions from writing to acting to producing, he said.</p>
        <p>''I think most writers are masochists in some ways. Most actors are sadists in many ways. So I have that sadomasochistic thing going on,'' he said, smiling.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
