<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hoping to Move Guitar Notations Into the Legal Sunshine</title>
    <meta content="02ecom" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/technology/02ecom.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="E-COMMERCE REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/E-Commerce</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/E-Commerce Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E6D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hoping to Move Guitar Notations Into the Legal Sunshine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hoping to Move Guitar Notations Into the Legal Sunshine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB TEDESCHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tedeschi, Bob</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF budding guitarists fail to master ''Stairway to Heaven'' in the coming months, they can no longer blame the music publishers.</p>
        <p>Because of an agreement in March between MusicNotes, an online music publisher and the Harry Fox Agency, which represents 31,000 music publishers, guitar tablature -- a popular system for teaching and learning guitar -- will enter the legitimate business realm for the first time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A popular system for teaching and learning guitar will enter the legitimate business realm for the first time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF budding guitarists fail to master ''Stairway to Heaven'' in the coming months, they can no longer blame the music publishers.</p>
        <p>Because of an agreement in March between MusicNotes, an online music publisher and the Harry Fox Agency, which represents 31,000 music publishers, guitar tablature -- a popular system for teaching and learning guitar -- will enter the legitimate business realm for the first time.</p>
        <p>Last year popular sites like Olga.net, MxTabs.net and others -- where users post tablature, usually called ''guitar tabs,'' for rock songs -- suspended operations after the music publishing industry threatened them with copyright infringement lawsuits. Under the new initiative, MxTabs, which is owned by MusicNotes, will share an undisclosed portion of advertising revenue with music publishers, who in turn will give a portion to artists.</p>
        <p>The effort could face a chicken-or-egg problem, in that publishers may balk if they do not see enough potential for advertising revenue, and advertisers may balk if publishers do not free enough of their music to attract a big audience. Advertising analysts suggest the revenue could be significant, but even a little is better than none.</p>
        <p>''It's a huge opportunity, in that this is a revenue stream publishers haven't had before,'' said Gary L. Churgin the chief executive of Harry Fox Agency. ''In a sense, the sky's the limit.''</p>
        <p>The initiative is still in the early stages, and Mr. Churgin has not yet formally asked publishers if they would like to participate. Artists are even less familiar with the agreement.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Churgin said, he has not yet encountered resistance. ''We're a step and a half away from knowing how much it will be embraced,'' he said. ''But the informal feedback we've gotten since the announcement has been enthusiastic.''</p>
        <p>Irwin Z. Robinson, chief executive of Famous Music, Viacom's music publishing division, said: ''This gives us, for the first time, the opportunity to get something that's been given away or stolen for all these years. I'm very positive about it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson, whose company represents Linda Perry, a songwriter for Christina Aguilera and Pink among others, said that about 2 percent of the songs in the company's catalog have licensed guitar tablature associated with them.</p>
        <p>For the remaining songs in Famous Music's catalog -- and the vast majority of the music publishing industry's collective catalog -- there is insufficient demand to justify the costs of publishing tablature.</p>
        <p>As a result, guitarists who want to know how to play less mainstream songs have gone to sites where amateurs post tablature. Under this agreement, MusicNotes, publishers and artists will essentially earn money from an army of volunteers, who are creating content that the publishers are not creating on their own.</p>
        <p>Tim Reiland, chairman and chief financial officer of MusicNotes, which is based in Madison, Wis., said publishers would receive ''a very healthy split'' of the advertising dollars.</p>
        <p>''We've got lots of work here to get the publishers signed up, but we think they should,'' Mr. Reiland said. ''We think it's a good deal.''</p>
        <p>MusicNotes bought MxTabs.net, one of the most popular guitar tablature sites, last year as it came under legal attack by music publishers. Publishers claimed that even incorrect versions of music notation violate copyright laws, since the postings represent ''derivative works'' related to the original compositions, to use the legal parlance.</p>
        <p>The guitar tablature sites were typically small operations, running on little more than revenue gleaned from Google text ads. Many shut down rather than challenge the publishers in court. (Ultimate-Guitar.com, which has a New Jersey phone number but claims that it is based in Russia and that it complies with Russian copyright laws, still operates. Its advertisers include AOL, T-Mobile and Dell, among others.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Reiland said MxTabs has more than 100,000 tabs in its files. Those tabs will remain under wraps until the site's re-emergence this summer -- assuming his company can clear at least 50,000 of those tabs with publishers. ''We'd have to have at least that many to make it a good experience for the customer,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reiland and Kathleen Marsh, the chief executive of MusicNotes, are now making plans to sell advertising. That is a new realm for the company, since it has subsisted until now on fees charged to users for downloading sheet music and a small number of guitar tablatures generated by publishing houses.</p>
        <p>Ms. Marsh said the site ''already has a lot of interest'' from advertisers. ''This demographic -- teenage boys to young adults -- is very similar to the demographic for gaming. There are a lot of advertisers who are interested in that group.''</p>
        <p>Shar VanBoskirk, an analyst with Forrester Research, said tablature sites could also join other online publishers and anonymously track the Internet travels of their users. The budding guitar players might somehow show that they were shopping for a car, for instance, or other expensive goods. Suddenly, she said, ''these users are really valuable targets for sellers of all kinds.''</p>
        <p>Lauren Keiser, the president of the Music Publishers' Association, and the chief executive of Carl Fischer, a music publisher in New York, said he would offer the MusicNotes proposal to his board this month to gauge their reaction. ''As a publisher, I want to see this baby walk,'' he said. ''And we'll see. There might be a whole bunch of other deals coming out of this.''</p>
        <p>Representatives from Ultimate-Guitar did not respond to calls seeking comment. Cathal Woods, the director of Olga, wrote via e-mail that he had, in the past, approached Harry Fox, the Music Publishers' Association and the National Music Publishers' Association with similar business deals.</p>
        <p>Those groups ''have always rejected out-of-hand any requests about licensing,'' Mr. Woods wrote. ''I'm somewhat surprised by this.''</p>
        <p>E-COMMERCE REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
