<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Two Years of Work, An Updated Tabernacle</title>
    <meta content="02mormon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/us/02mormon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mormons (Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tabernacle (Salt Lake City)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Salt Lake City (Utah)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolz, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah/Salt Lake City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mormons (Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Salt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Salt Lake City (Utah)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Mormon Tabernacle Choir</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Two Years of Work, An Updated Tabernacle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Two Years of Work, an Updated Tabernacle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN STOLZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolz, Martin</byline>
      <dateline>SALT LAKE CITY, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Salt Lake Tabernacle, completed in 1867 by Mormon pioneers, reopens after two-year renovation; Mormon church draws criticism from preservationists for replacing original pews; project money came from members' tithes; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Salt Lake Tabernacle, completed in 1867 by the faithful of the fledgling Mormon religion and home of the world-famous choir, reopened over the weekend after a two-year top-to-bottom renovation.</p>
        <p>The Mormon church has drawn criticism from preservationists for replacing the tabernacle's original pews, made from pine and ''grained'' by artisans with paint and etchings to appear like oak, the wood favored by Brigham Young, the pioneer Mormon leader. The new pews are made of oak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The egg-shaped Salt Lake Tabernacle, completed in 1867, reopened over the weekend after a two-year renovation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Salt Lake Tabernacle, completed in 1867 by the faithful of the fledgling Mormon religion and home of the world-famous choir, reopened over the weekend after a two-year top-to-bottom renovation.</p>
        <p>The Mormon church has drawn criticism from preservationists for replacing the tabernacle's original pews, made from pine and ''grained'' by artisans with paint and etchings to appear like oak, the wood favored by Brigham Young, the pioneer Mormon leader. The new pews are made of oak.</p>
        <p>The president and prophet of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, Gordon B. Hinckley, in rededicating the egg-shaped tabernacle on Saturday, said, ''With this undertaking, we hope and pray that its historical features have not been destroyed.''</p>
        <p>The tabernacle's famed acoustics, which legend has it enabled a listener to a hear a pin drop from 250 feet away, were measured before the renovation began, modeled on computers and then assessed again recently, said Roger P. Jackson, the project's lead architect. Mr. Jackson said he expected the building's enveloping sound would be preserved.</p>
        <p>''Acoustics is a science and an art,'' he said, ''but it's also guesswork. Anything you do has an impact.''</p>
        <p>Church officials declined to talk about the project's cost but said the money came from members' tithes, or 10 percent of all income. The church says it has about 12 million members, including 6 million in the United States.</p>
        <p>The church spared few expenses on the tabernacle in its seismic retrofitting, especially since seeing the project completed was a personal objective of Mr. Hinckley, 96.</p>
        <p>The wooden roof trusses have been girded with steel. The roof's 44 stone support piers have new steel and concrete reinforcements. Fourteen layers of paint, including one of bird's-egg blue, were removed from the ceiling. The rostrum, where nearly 100 church leaders sit facing the audience during religious services, can now be lowered with a hydraulic lift and replaced with a stage for an orchestra.</p>
        <p>The 350 members of the Mormon Tabernacle Choir have new cushioned seats surrounding the freshly gilded casing of the 11,623-pipe Aeolian-Skinner organ, along with air-conditioning vents beneath each singer's chair. The church updated its television and radio equipment inside the hall and added a recording studio in the basement.</p>
        <p>More visibly modern are dozens of large flat-screen televisions, from which audience and church leaders watched Saturday's program.</p>
        <p>The replica pews are spaced farther apart, adding leg room but reducing seating capacity by more than a thousand, to about 3,500. The tabernacle has two rows of original pews, while hundreds more are in storage. Their future has yet to be decided, said Bishop David Burton, who oversaw the renovations.</p>
        <p>''The historicity of the building has been largely left intact,'' Mr. Burton said.</p>
        <p>But Robert Charles Mitchell, a Mormon who lives in Logan and publicly lobbied the church last year to explain why it would replace the pews, disagreed: ''If you maintain historicity, you don't rip out the pews; you maintain them.''</p>
        <p>''I knew saving them was a lost cause,'' Mr. Mitchell said. ''The benches were such an integral part of the building. But people are satisfied with whatever is shiny, bright and new. Preservation is a real fight, and it's a collision of values.''</p>
        <p>The building's most distinctive feature, an egg-shaped roof spanning 150 feet with no interior supports, shows the ingenuity of Mormon pioneers, said Richard Oman, a curator at the Museum of Church History and Art.</p>
        <p>During the tabernacle's construction, Britain was building the similar-size Royal Albert Hall in London with steel from factories and labor drawn from a large and skilled population.</p>
        <p>Mormon pioneers, isolated on the frontier and numbering but a few thousand, had none of Britain's resources, not even a trained architect among them. Yet they began ''building the impossible,'' Mr. Oman said, with trees, rocks and ox hair. What resulted was then the world's largest indoor auditorium.</p>
        <p>Brigham Young, a carpenter, reportedly made a model for the tabernacle with an egg and toothpicks. But formulating a way to actually construct the roof fell to Henry Grow, a Mormon convert and bridge builder who moved in the 1850s to Utah from Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>The roof's timbers were carved into curves and assembled in a system of lattices held together with wood pegs and rawhide ribbons, examples of what Mr. Oman called the ''parsimonious use of resources'' of the Mormon pioneers. The tabernacle's roof design led the American Society of Civil Engineers to designate it a National Engineering Landmark in 1971. The tabernacle was listed on the National Register of Historic Places the year before.</p>
        <p>During Saturday's service, many worshipers and speakers cried.</p>
        <p>''What wonderful memories this brings back,'' Linda Halverson, 65, of Ogden said as she hugged her friend, Evelyn Menchin, 84, of Calgary, Alberta.</p>
        <p>A group of girls from the Brighton High School chorus attracted attention outside the tabernacle for their floor-length fuchsia gowns. Many stood on tip-toe to watch the service or catch a glimpse of Mr. Hinckley through the tabernacle's windows.</p>
        <p>Laura Potter, 16, a first soprano from the suburb of Cottonwood Heights, said she hoped to sing someday in the Mormon Tabernacle Choir.</p>
        <p>''You can sing next to the prophet,'' she said with the kind of enthusiasm others her age might feel at being in the presence of a rock star. ''And in the tabernacle, the revelations are so strong.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
