<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Karma and Scoreboard Favor Mets in Their Opener</title>
    <meta content="02mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/baseball/02mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri/St. Louis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">St Louis (Mo)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">St Louis Cardinals</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Karma and Scoreboard Favor Mets in Their Opener</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Karma and Scoreboard Favor Mets in Their Opener</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets opened their season here of all places, the site of a few miserable memories last October, and let the record show that when the Cardinals' world championship banner was raised at 6:44 p.m. Sunday night, they did not avert their eyes or start sobbing. The Cardinals' march to the title, which passed through Shea Stadium, happened more than five months ago. As far as the Mets are concerned, there are no cliffhangers, no ellipses, nothing to be continued.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals may have won the last game of 2006, but the Mets took the first one of 2007, sending a frenzied capacity crowd home displeased after winning, 6-1, at Busch Stadium. If things go this well for the Mets every time Tom Glavine pitches, he will fulfill a prophecy he made in jest during spring training: 10 starts, 10 victories. As it was, he earned career victory No. 291 with metronomic efficiency, allowing one run and six hits in six innings and benefiting from some timely two-out hitting and superior defense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cardinals may have won the last game of 2006, but the Mets took the first one of 2007.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets opened their season here of all places, the site of a few miserable memories last October, and let the record show that when the Cardinals' world championship banner was raised at 6:44 p.m. Sunday night, they did not avert their eyes or start sobbing. The Cardinals' march to the title, which passed through Shea Stadium, happened more than five months ago. As far as the Mets are concerned, there are no cliffhangers, no ellipses, nothing to be continued.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals may have won the last game of 2006, but the Mets took the first one of 2007, sending a frenzied capacity crowd home displeased after winning, 6-1, at Busch Stadium. If things go this well for the Mets every time Tom Glavine pitches, he will fulfill a prophecy he made in jest during spring training: 10 starts, 10 victories. As it was, he earned career victory No. 291 with metronomic efficiency, allowing one run and six hits in six innings and benefiting from some timely two-out hitting and superior defense.</p>
        <p>''That's how we envision ourselves winning,'' Glavine said.</p>
        <p>After the way last season -- and spring training this year, for that matter, with the franchise-record 21 losses -- ended, the Mets may have been overdue for some good karma. They turned four double plays, held Albert Pujols and Scott Rolen hitless, and mashed the Cardinals' ace, Chris Carpenter, for five runs -- all with two outs -- and nine hits in six innings.</p>
        <p>Shawn Green, whose .149 average in spring training was the lowest among team regulars, had two hits and scored a run. Moises Alou, the 40-year-old left fielder who was not acquired, shall we say, for defensive purposes, somehow ran down Adam Kennedy's shallow fly ball to make a diving backhanded catch. Carlos Beltrán, who was last seen staring at Adam Wainwright's wicked curveball to end Game 7 of the National League Championship Series, went 1 for 4, scored a run, drove in a run and threw out a runner at home plate.</p>
        <p>Yadier Molina, whose ninth-inning homer propelled the Cardinals to the World Series, popped out in a two-out bases-loaded situation in the sixth. And Aaron Heilman, who surrendered that homer to Molina, wiggled free from a bases-loaded jam in the eighth, although to be fair, second baseman José Valentín deserves the credit.</p>
        <p>Rolen smacked Heilman's one-out pitch up the middle for what seemed like a sure single. Playing to the right of his normal position, Valentín reacted immediately, diving to his right to spear the sharp grounder. He flipped the ball to José Reyes, who stepped on second base and threw to first for the double play.</p>
        <p>''The only way I can make that play is playing where I was playing,'' Valentín said. ''He hit that ball so hard that I felt it in my fingers when I caught it.''</p>
        <p>During the hour-long pregame ceremony, the actor Billy Bob Thornton announced the players -- in the Mets' case, only their starting lineup, to Paul Lo Duca's displeasure -- and Cardinals players drove past their trophy in a motorcade. From the beginning, it was a different kind of opening day for the Mets, although not much has changed for them since that brisk October night when the Cardinals won the N.L. pennant.</p>
        <p>The Mets' infield is still intact, as is two-thirds of the outfield and most of the starting pitching. Their bullpen is remodeled, featuring four newcomers, including Joe Smith. A sidearming right-hander, Smith made his major league debut in the eighth inning, but Manager Willie Randolph revisited the familiar formula of Heilman and Billy Wagner to close out Glavine's performance.</p>
        <p>Making his eighth opening-day start, Glavine says he still becomes nervous after all these years. He stayed calm before the game by munching on a bowl of Cheerios and watching golf. Until the sixth inning, his only sign of frustration came when he could not figure out how to turn on a clubhouse television.</p>
        <p>To that point, Glavine had allowed three base runners: two were erased on double plays, and the other was tagged out on a botched suicide squeeze attempt. And then, after Alou's diving catch, the Cardinals rapped three consecutive hits off Glavine. The third, a Preston Wilson single, sizzled up the middle to Beltrán, who, noticing David Eckstein touching third base, threw home in one breathtakingly fluid motion. The ball popped into Lo Duca's mitt as David Eckstein was sliding into him.</p>
        <p>''I didn't have to do nothing,'' Lo Duca said.</p>
        <p>Glavine's control, so pinpoint during the first five innings, had seemingly vanished. He walked Pujols. He hit Rolen to load the bases. The crowd, practically silent since the third inning, roared as Molina stepped to the plate. Glavine jammed Molina with a cutter, and the soft pop-up settled into Reyes's glove in shallow center. That was the last batter Glavine faced.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't totally thrilled with it, but the good part was that I made good pitches when I had to and got some ground balls,'' Glavine said.</p>
        <p>The Mets' offensive woes last October had everything to do with the Cardinals' second-tier pitchers, Jeff Suppan and Jeff Weaver, and nothing to do with their ace, Carpenter, whom they tagged for seven runs in two N.L.C.S. starts. After setting down the first five hitters Sunday, Carpenter started struggling, allowing two hits in the second that preceded the Mets' two-run third.</p>
        <p>With one out and Lo Duca on first, Beltrán waited on a 76-mile-an-hour curveball and launched it a few feet foul of the right-field pole. He was hit by Carpenter's next pitch, putting runners on first and second for Carlos Delgado. Since returning from a five-day paternity leave, Delgado has had four at-bats against major league pitching, more than enough, he said with a smile Saturday, to be ready for the opener. He stayed back on an 0-1 changeup and poked it the other way, off the left-field wall for a two-run double.</p>
        <p>In the fourth, as Carpenter continued to labor, Green and Valentín hit consecutive one-out singles. Glavine bunted over Green, and Reyes walked. Lo Duca followed by waiting out a seven-pitch at-bat, lining a bases-loaded single up the middle to drive in two runs. Beltrán followed by shooting a sharp grounder up the middle to score another run, increasing the Mets' lead to 5-0.</p>
        <p>As the fans shifted in their seats, dumbfounded at what was happening to their world champions, the Mets whooped it up in the dugout. They made it through one pregame ceremony and have another to go Tuesday, when the Cardinals will receive their rings. Again, they will notice but not pay it much mind.</p>
        <p>''Maybe when the season ends, that'll be us next year,'' Glavine said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
