<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Man's Biodiversity Is Another Man's Lunch</title>
    <meta content="02biza" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/arts/television/02biza.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Travel Channel</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Man's Biodiversity Is Another Man's Lunch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Man’s Biodiversity Is Another Man’s Lunch</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Susan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just as you can't judge a stewed eel by its looks (otherwise who would eat one?), you can't judge a series by its name. ''Bizarre Foods With Andrew Zimmern,'' tonight on the Travel Channel, is smarter than its lame title implies, thanks to the charm and intelligence of its host.</p>
        <p>The gimmick: Mr. Zimmern, a Minneapolis chef, food writer and radio host, travels the globe eating grubs, grouper throats and mammalian unmentionables, all to demonstrate that offal isn't so bad. The reality: By taking an anthropological approach to food, Mr. Zimmern broadens his subject, conveying a vivid sense of place and a serious appreciation for social and culinary diversity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This new series is smarter than its lame title implies, thanks to the charm and intelligence of its host.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just as you can't judge a stewed eel by its looks (otherwise who would eat one?), you can't judge a series by its name. ''Bizarre Foods With Andrew Zimmern,'' tonight on the Travel Channel, is smarter than its lame title implies, thanks to the charm and intelligence of its host.</p>
        <p>The gimmick: Mr. Zimmern, a Minneapolis chef, food writer and radio host, travels the globe eating grubs, grouper throats and mammalian unmentionables, all to demonstrate that offal isn't so bad. The reality: By taking an anthropological approach to food, Mr. Zimmern broadens his subject, conveying a vivid sense of place and a serious appreciation for social and culinary diversity.</p>
        <p>Now back to those grouper throats, and mullet gizzards, tongue and chitlins. That was the Gulf Coast, last week. Before that Mr. Zimmern went to Ecuador, where he ingested guinea pig (''absolutely fall-off-the-bone delicious''), ''lemony tasting'' live ants in the rain forest and grubs, served on banana leaves at a family feast.</p>
        <p>Then came Spain, home of ham. Mr. Zimmern, who ''reveres the pig,'' is not embarrassed to use the word ''hamtastic.'' In Madrid he dined on suckling pig, cutting his lip as he sucked out the brain, and praising the eyes: ''wonderful, especially schmeared on a little bit of bread.''</p>
        <p>I'll take his word for it. ''Bizarre Foods'' would be disappointing if it weren't disgusting. But it transcends its own repulsiveness. Mr. Zimmern ate those pig eyes in a 300-year-old restaurant. It was a short history lesson, just as his ant picnic in the rain forest was seasoned, however lightly, with environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>Tonight Mr. Zimmern travels in Britain, which he calls the ''snout to tail society.'' He has haggis in Scotland, jugged hare in Oxfordshire, cockles and faggots (mashed liver and pig parts) in Wales. He ends in London, where, after a meal of grilled ox heart with marrow at a restaurant called Roast, he kisses the chef. Maybe he is just glad to be out of the rain forest.</p>
        <p>Disappointingly, Mr. Zimmern doesn't visit St. John, the London restaurant that started the offal craze. In Spain he sampled pine cone cream (''I just ate a tree!'') at the food temple El Bulli, but did nothing to verify or counteract suspicions that the chemistry experiments of its chef, Ferran Adrià, bear less resemblance to actual food than does a fried mullet tail (''an oceanic potato chip,'' Mr. Zimmern raved, when he had one in Pensacola, Fla.).</p>
        <p>There are food snobs on both the high and low ends of the dining spectrum, and Mr. Zimmern, treading lightly, insults none of them. He's never patronizing, and while he occasionally finds a dish ''horrible'' or ''an acquired taste,'' he's always hopeful (an important trait when your job entails eating entrails).</p>
        <p>Less dangerous than Anthony Bourdain, less annoying than Rachael Ray and less cloying than Paula Deen, Mr. Zimmern is a delight. My only concern is for his health. A professional eater whose vocation is organ meat had better make sure his life insurance is paid up. I hope that on his days off he sticks to salad.</p>
        <p>Bizarre Foods With Andrew Zimmern</p>
        <p>Travel Channel, Mondays at 9 p.m, Eastern and Pacific times; 8 p.m, Central time</p>
        <p>Colleen Steward, executive producer for Tremendous! Entertainment; Myleeta Aga and David Gerber, executive producers for the Travel Channel.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
