<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cellphones for Little Kids? Can We Talk?</title>
    <meta content="l02cellphone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837538"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="380" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cellphones for Little Kids? Can We Talk?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Child Wants Cellphone; Reception Is Mixed'' (Thursday Styles, March 29):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Child Wants Cellphone; Reception Is Mixed'' (Thursday Styles, March 29):</p>
        <p>I didn't get a cellphone until I was well out of high school, and I understood that it wasn't something that humans needed as an essence of their survival, but rather a luxury that was very convenient.</p>
        <p>At this point, my cellphone is an 11th finger, and it is a personal travesty when I forget it at home for even a few hours.</p>
        <p>To see these kids -- barely out of diapers -- romping around with cutesy cellphones makes me a little repulsed.</p>
        <p>For one thing, no 7-year-old should be in a position not to have the supervision of an adult. And it makes me a little insecure to think that 7-year-olds have a social life similar to mine, in the way that they should need a cellphone, as I do.</p>
        <p>At this rate, we're going in the direction of giving our dogs cellphones.</p>
        <p>Emily Loubaton  New York, March 29, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As both a parent and a psychologist, I find the cellphone debate of great interest. My 7- and 10-year-old boys have been clamoring for cellphones, and for the moment, I have managed to hold out.</p>
        <p>While I appreciate that parents have to make choices that best suit their families, I feel strongly that it all boils down to being able to tolerate the frustration of not having what ''all the kids have'' (the refrain heard in my household), as well as not being in constant and immediate contact with friends and family.</p>
        <p>Contrary to the opinion cited in your article, a cellphone is not a ''transitional object,'' as the term implies, and giving a cellphone to a young child would seem to hinder the process of tolerating being apart from family.</p>
        <p>My children will get cellphones when they can appreciate the responsibility associated with ownership, and when they are at an age where they won't be under the constant supervision of an adult.</p>
        <p>Until then, I will have to tolerate the frustration of the ''but everyone has one'' refrain, and my children will have to make due with all of the gadgets they just had to have, now buried in their closets.</p>
        <p>Ellen Westrich  New York, March 29, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
