<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sign in 'Idol' Audience May Have Skirted Rules</title>
    <meta content="02idol.1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/business/media/02idol.1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Signs and Symbols</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sign in 'Idol' Audience May Have Skirted Rules</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sign in ‘Idol’ Audience May Have Skirted Rules</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIA MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Lia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>People who watch ''American Idol'' are accustomed to seeing a muddle of handwritten posters in the studio audience with mawkish messages aimed at the contestants (''Marry me Blake'') or the judges (''Simon U Tiger.'')</p>
        <p>But last Tuesday, the placards also included some with a corporate logo, which are forbidden under the show's rules. Four former colleagues of one of the front-running contestants, LaKisha Jones, who used to be a bank teller, stood near the front of the stage with signs that had some professional printing on them and said ''Provident Bank is banking on LaKisha to win.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former colleagues of “American Idol” contestant LaKisha Jones held up placards that included a corporate bank logo which is forbidden under the show’s rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>People who watch ''American Idol'' are accustomed to seeing a muddle of handwritten posters in the studio audience with mawkish messages aimed at the contestants (''Marry me Blake'') or the judges (''Simon U Tiger.'')</p>
        <p>But last Tuesday, the placards also included some with a corporate logo, which are forbidden under the show's rules. Four former colleagues of one of the front-running contestants, LaKisha Jones, who used to be a bank teller, stood near the front of the stage with signs that had some professional printing on them and said ''Provident Bank is banking on LaKisha to win.''</p>
        <p>Vicki Cox, a spokeswoman for Provident, a community bank based in Baltimore, said there had been no deliberate effort to get free publicity. Rather, she said, some friends of Ms. Jones, who had been a teller for six months but left to be on ''Idol,'' had thought that the format would be more visible to Ms. Jones.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to make sure that she knew that the place where she used to work supported her, and that she knew we were behind her all the way,'' she said. Ms. Cox said Ms. Jones was welcome to return to the bank, though she doubted that the new star would do so.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for ''American Idol'' said that there was a strict rule against advertising in any form on the signs in the audience and that, in the past, such signs had been removed. ''Of course, the signs are checked before the show goes live,'' said the spokesman. ''These signs must have slipped through the process.''</p>
        <p>Melba Czosnowski, the manager of the branch in Millersville, Md., where Ms. Jones used to work, said that while cellphones and cameras had been confiscated before the show, ''they never inspected signs.'' Ms. Czosnowski said that Ms. Jones had loved the signs and even kept one for herself.</p>
        <p>''Our customers come in and say, 'I've never watched the show before, and now I'm going to watch,' '' Ms. Czosnowski said. ''It's drawn some excitement.''</p>
        <p>Last week, after Ms. Jones performed a well-received rendition of Donna Summer's ''Last Dance,'' the cameras zoomed in three times on her supporters and the signs, each shot lasting at least one second -- and therefore giving Provident Bank brief visibility on some of the most highly coveted broadcast time around.</p>
        <p>The show, on the Fox network, is seen by 30 million viewers. Forbes magazine recently reported that a 30-second spot during ''American Idol'' costs an average of $745,000, so to purchase those three seconds from Fox would have cost Provident around $74,500.</p>
        <p>Kevin Byrnes, the president and chief operating officer of Provident Bank, said that no formal decision had been made to use those particular posters. He called it a grass-roots idea that did not involve anyone outside the Millersville branch. Ms. Jones's success, he said, was the talk of the bank.</p>
        <p>''The staff came up with the idea,'' he said. ''They thought it was important to show that everybody at Provident was behind her. The sign was for LaKisha.''</p>
        <p>When asked about any unintended boost that the national publicity might give to the bank, Mr. Byrnes seemed puzzled. ''We're a bank that only targets Maryland and Virginia,'' he said.</p>
        <p>LIA MILLER</p>
        <p>MEDIA TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
