<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City to Lose $308 Million In Assistance for Just a Year</title>
    <meta content="02city" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/nyregion/02city.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DECISIONS IN ALBANY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City to Lose $308 Million In Assistance for Just a Year</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">City to Lose $308 Million in State Aid for Just a Year</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY RIVERA; David M. Herszenhorn contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rivera, Ray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bloomberg administration says state's new budget will leave New York City scrambling to replace $308 million in lost aid, but deal is worked out to restore aid to full levels next year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The state's record $120.9 billion budget will leave the city scrambling to replace $308 million in lost aid, the Bloomberg administration said yesterday.</p>
        <p>But worries that the aid package would be permanently lost were alleviated with a negotiated deal that will restore it to full levels next year, one of several compromises that allowed New York City to come out ahead of where it stood under Gov. Eliot Spitzer's initial proposal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A negotiated budget deal ensures that New York City will receive full levels of aid next year, although the city will still have to find new revenue this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The state's record $120.9 billion budget will leave the city scrambling to replace $308 million in lost aid, the Bloomberg administration said yesterday.</p>
        <p>But worries that the aid package would be permanently lost were alleviated with a negotiated deal that will restore it to full levels next year, one of several compromises that allowed New York City to come out ahead of where it stood under Gov. Eliot Spitzer's initial proposal.</p>
        <p>Working with a Democratic governor for the first time since Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, a Republican, took office in 2002, city officials said the final budget worked out by the parties was a hopeful sign for future negotiations. That could prove especially important in 2009 and beyond when the city expects the opulent surpluses it enjoys now to be replaced by shortfalls.</p>
        <p>''The fact that the governor and governor's office had an open door to the city and gave us a fair hearing on all the issues that we raised is a positive sign going forward,'' said Deputy Mayor Edward Skyler, who was heavily involved in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>Highlights for the city included an increase in state education aid of $3.3 billion over the next four years, which will come on top of a city match of $2.2 billion. The increase includes $712 million more in state aid this year alone, city officials said, though the city got less control over the money than it wanted. The city also got clearance to create 50 charter schools, and its public hospital system was protected from Medicaid cuts affecting private hospitals.</p>
        <p>Paul E. Francis, the governor's budget director, said the city fared ''significantly'' better in the negotiated budget than in the governor's original proposal.</p>
        <p>''On the most important issues, we were really on the same side,'' Mr. Francis said, referring to education spending and long-term financing for the city's public hospital system.</p>
        <p>The city's fiercest battle was against the governor's plan to stop $328 million in annual unrestricted aid payments. The proposal drew sharp rebukes from the mayor and his budget staff, who warned that it would produce an enormous gap in the city's budget. While small compared with the mayor's $57.1 billion preliminary budget, the revenue sharing aid is seen as a critical revenue source because the city can spend it however it wishes.</p>
        <p>The compromise, which restores $20 million of discretionary aid this year and returns the aid to its full level next year, relieved the mayor's concern that the cuts could become permanent. But the mayor's aides said yesterday that the city would still have to find new revenue this year. Last month the mayor warned his agency heads that they might have to cut 1.5 percent from their budgets for this fiscal year and 4 percent next year. The possible cuts were attributed to a slowdown in the national economy, volatility in the stock market and new labor agreements. But it seemed also clear that the mayor's budget staff was anticipating some shortfalls in money they had expected from the state.</p>
        <p>City officials were cautious yesterday about saying what the state's overall budget would mean for the city until they fully analyze the budget agreement.</p>
        <p>The city's bargaining position against the cuts was strained because the city is doing so well financially with projected surpluses of $3.9 billion this year and $1.4 billion next year. According to people familiar with the negotiations, the city received support from the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, and other Senate Republicans.</p>
        <p>''We were very supportive of what the mayor was looking for in this budget,'' said the majority leader's spokesman, John McArdle.</p>
        <p>City negotiators along with Senate Republicans were also partly successful in cutting the number of proposed corporate tax loopholes the governor wanted to close from 13 to 4.</p>
        <p>The governor had said that closing the loopholes would even the playing field for businesses and in turn produce enough revenue for the city to offset his proposed cuts in aid. But the mayor warned that they would encourage large financial services companies to move jobs out of the city.</p>
        <p>As part of the compromise, the governor agreed to cut the state's corporate tax rate to about 7.1 percent from 7.5 percent, which was expected to generate about $75 million in tax relief. Senate Republicans also threw in another $75 million cut in the franchise tax on manufacturers, which budget watchers said would mainly benefit businesses upstate.</p>
        <p>''The tax cut is modest compared to the impact of what the four loophole closures will cost New York City business,'' said Kathryn S. Wylde, president of the Partnership for New York City, which represents many of the city's largest businesses. ''But at least it indicates some responsiveness to business concerns about the high tax rate in New York.''</p>
        <p>Diana Fortuna, president of the Citizens Budget Commission, a business-backed research organization, said the loophole compromise appeared to be more of a victory for the governor.</p>
        <p>Among the loopholes closed were two the mayor had expressed particular concern about: one that would require corporations with out-of-state subsidiaries to file joint tax returns in New York, thus preventing companies from funneling profits to states with lower tax rates; and one that had allowed a deduction for certain subsidiary dividends received by a parent company from real estate investment trusts.</p>
        <p>Together, the governor estimated that the two provisions would generate $319 million for the state -- far more than the $75 million offset by the tax cut.</p>
        <p>The mayor lost his fight to stop a $30 million increase in what the state charges the city to administer the city's personal income tax.</p>
        <p>City officials described the budget negotiations as perhaps the toughest since 2003, when the city successfully fought for a $1.79 billion aid package to refinance debt emanating from the fiscal crisis of the 1970s, overcoming a veto by Gov. George E. Pataki.</p>
        <p>DECISIONS IN ALBANY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
