<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Phelps Matches Spitz With Seventh Gold Medal</title>
    <meta content="02swimming" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/othersports/02swimming.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SWIMMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Melbourne</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Melbourne (Australia)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Phelps, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E7D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1125" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Phelps Matches Spitz With Seventh Gold Medal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Phelps Matches Spitz With Seventh Gold Medal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>MELBOURNE, Australia, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were other powerful images on the last day of these world championships: the bedraggled, besieged Ian Thorpe walking into an overstuffed news conference with the digital cameras hissing; and Katie Hoff crying in the pool after breaking the final world record of the meet.</p>
        <p>But the sight that best summarized the last eight days and nights was the stretch of open water that separated Michael Phelps from his closest pursuers as he stroked his way to the finish of the 400-meter individual medley and his seventh gold medal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael Phelps set another world record Sunday, and his seventh gold in a major meet tied Mark Spitz’s 1972 haul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were other powerful images on the last day of these world championships: the bedraggled, besieged Ian Thorpe walking into an overstuffed news conference with the digital cameras hissing; and Katie Hoff crying in the pool after breaking the final world record of the meet.</p>
        <p>But the sight that best summarized the last eight days and nights was the stretch of open water that separated Michael Phelps from his closest pursuers as he stroked his way to the finish of the 400-meter individual medley and his seventh gold medal.</p>
        <p>In a sport in which the numbers after the decimal point usually make the difference between first place and second, Phelps overwhelmed the paradigm at age 21, routinely pulverizing world records by a second or two and routinely pulverizing the opposition by more, even when allegedly weary.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, a lot of it tonight was really about adrenaline,'' Phelps said.</p>
        <p>The only parts of his body that do not look aquadynamic are his protruding ears, but the rest of it undulates through the water at a historic clip, and he made plenty of swimming history here. He passed Thorpe's record of six gold medals in a world championships and joined Mark Spitz as the only man to win seven times in a major meet.</p>
        <p>Spitz, who was in Melbourne on a promotional tour last week, piled up his gold in a bigger, fancier fish bowl: the 1972 Olympics. But Spitz did not break five world records along the way like Phelps, and Spitz swam only freestyle and butterfly. Phelps swam all four strokes, establishing personal bests or world records in every event in which he competed. Though he won eight medals, six of them gold, at the 2004 Olympics, the true tour de force came here.</p>
        <p>''His performance this week was the greatest performance of all time,'' said the United States' head coach, Mark Schubert.</p>
        <p>''I guess I don't really look at it by the medals. I look at it by the dominance and by the records, and the way he handled it from event to event. I just didn't notice any weak points.''</p>
        <p>Phelps won both freestyle relays and five individual events: the 100 butterfly, the 200 butterfly, the 200 freestyle, the 200 individual medley and, finally, the 400 individual medley, which he broke open on the third leg with his weakest stroke, the breaststroke, and finished in 4 minutes 6.22 seconds.</p>
        <p>That was 2.04 seconds ahead of his world record at the 2004 Olympics and 3.52 seconds ahead of his American teammate Ryan Lochte, who won the silver medal.</p>
        <p>''I didn't expect to be two seconds under my world record tonight,'' said Phelps, who later embraced his mother, Debbie, in the stands. ''I'm definitely happy with how this turned out. This is definitely the best-case scenario for what we had in mind.''</p>
        <p>That was not quite correct. When the final day began, Phelps looked well on his way to passing Spitz and winning eight gold medals. But when the American medley relay team was disqualified in the morning heats after Ian Crocker started one hundredth of a second too early, Phelps lost his chance to go for an eighth gold in the evening.</p>
        <p>''Team U.S.A. goes into a meet as one and that's how we exit; everything can't be perfect,'' Phelps said. ''It definitely wasn't intentional. They all wanted to swim and get us in the finals.''</p>
        <p>The Americans, with no automatic berth in next year's Olympic medley relay, will now have to qualify outside these championships, perhaps as early as this week's dual meet with Australia in Sydney.</p>
        <p>Croker spoke at a team meeting later that evening during which his coach Eddie Reese said he received lots of moral support.</p>
        <p>There has been plenty of the same for Thorpe in Australia since it emerged that a doping test administered to him last May is being formally questioned by swimming's world governing body, FINA, and still being assessed by the Australian Sports Anti-Doping Authority.</p>
        <p>No officials involved in the inquiry have confirmed that Thorpe is the swimmer in question. But Thorpe, who retired in November at age 24, confirmed it Sunday in an emotional news conference in Melbourne in which he denied doping, vowed to clear his name and expressed outrage at the fact that his identity had been leaked even though his test had not been ruled positive.</p>
        <p>''That's the hardest thing to take,'' he said. ''So, you know, my reputation probably is tarnished now. What's important is to actually get the facts out there and for the right result to come out, which will be a negative test.''</p>
        <p>Thorpe, the finest middle-distance freestyler in history, won five Olympic gold medals and has become one of Australia's most revered sportsmen. Thorpe said he had been informed by the Australian Anti-Doping Authority on Saturday that his test had shown unusually high levels of testosterone and luteinizing hormone, a substance produced by the pituitary gland that aids in testosterone production.</p>
        <p>Thorpe will now be asked by the authority to provide medical information that might help explain the high levels.</p>
        <p>''Both of these substances are naturally occurring substances,'' Thorpe said. ''There are many innocent physiological and pathological reasons why a test may return unusual levels of these substances.''</p>
        <p>Richard Ings, the chairman of the Australian authority, said that despite FINA's appeal to the Court of Arbitration for Sport seeking clarification of the test results, the Australian inquiry had never been closed. ''I was in complete shock,'' Thorpe said of his reaction when informed of the questionable test on Saturday. ''I think I sat in my room, you know, physically shaking.''</p>
        <p>The Americans tied their best performance at a world championships with 20 gold medals and 36 overall medals, the same totals as in 1978. Australia was second in the standings with 9 gold medals and 21 overall medals. Libby Lenton of Australia was the leading women's swimmer here, winning five gold medals, including the 50 freestyle on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Other winners on the final night included the Australian men in the medley relay, Jessica Hardy of the United States in the women's 50 breast stroke, Hoff in the women's 400 individual medley and Mateusz Sawrymowicz of Poland in the men's 1,500 freestyle.</p>
        <p>Hoff won by the Phelpsian margin of 7.25 seconds, in 4:32.89, breaking the record of 4:33.59 set by Yana Klockhkova of Ukraine at the 2000 Olympics. It was the 14th world record to fall here, but 14 will not be the number that will define Melbourne's championships. The defining number will be seven, and the even more remarkable part is that it could have been, should have been, eight.</p>
        <p>Bring on Beijing. ''I think we're all very excited for next year,'' Phelps said.</p>
        <p>SWIMMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
