<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Campaign Shows An Early Fund-Raising Edge</title>
    <meta content="02campaign" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirkpatrick, David D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zeleny, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Campaign Shows An Early Fund-Raising Edge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK; Adam Nagourney contributed reporting from Washington, and Jeff Zeleny from Iowa.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D; Nagourney, Adam; Zeleny, Jeff</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen Hillary Rodham Clinton's campaign for Democratic presidential nomination says it has raised $26 million during first quarter 2007, about three times as much as previous record at this stage of presidential race; other canidates' fund-raising totals noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton's campaign for the Democratic presidential nomination said Sunday that it had raised $26 million during the first quarter of this year, about three times as much as the previous record at this stage of a presidential race.</p>
        <p>Officials from several other Democratic primary campaigns voluntarily announced their fund-raising totals as well, just hours after the quarter closed at midnight on Saturday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton's campaign for the Democratic presidential nomination said Sunday that it had raised $26 million during the first quarter of this year, about three times as much as the previous record at this stage of a presidential race.</p>
        <p>Officials from several other Democratic primary campaigns voluntarily announced their fund-raising totals as well, just hours after the quarter closed at midnight on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Former Senator John Edwards raised over $14 million, about twice what he raised in the same quarter for his 2004 presidential race. Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico raised $6 million. Senator Christopher J. Dodd of Connecticut raised $4 million. Senator Joseph R. Biden of Delaware raised $3 million.</p>
        <p>The campaign of Senator Barack Obama of Illinois, Mrs. Clinton's biggest rival for Democratic donors, said it was not ready to disclose its results, suggesting he may have a big announcement in store. The leading Republican candidates declined to disclose their results as well.</p>
        <p>This year's first-quarter fund-raising totals have emerged as a pivotal test of strength in the 2008 race. For the first time since the Watergate-era adoption of public financing of presidential campaigns, all the top candidates are preparing to reject public money -- and the spending limits that come with it -- in favor of collecting as much as they can from private donors.</p>
        <p>The early statements confirm that the leading primary candidates are on track to raise as much as $100 million each even before the election year begins.</p>
        <p>The statements on Sunday amounted to the opening of an elaborate poker game. First-quarter fund-raising reports to the Federal Election Commission are not due until April 15, so the campaigns are choosing when and how to disclose selected details in an effort to show off strengths and obscure weaknesses.</p>
        <p>In the logic of the game, Sunday was an opportunity for Mrs. Clinton to call attention to a record-breaking quarter. Her campaign also announced the transfer of $10 million from her Senate campaign account, bringing total receipts for the quarter to $36 million.</p>
        <p>Others may have used her announcement to distract attention from their own relatively low numbers. Mr. Obama's decision to wait may be a signal that his campaign hopes to make a splash of its own with an unexpectedly rich quarter.</p>
        <p>The early totals also suggest that none of the Democrats will enjoy the kind of commanding financial edge that George W. Bush carried into the 2000 Republican primary. Rejecting public financing for the primary season but not the general election, Mr. Bush, then governor of Texas, announced the start of his campaign around the beginning of March 1999, raised over $7 million by the end of the first quarter about a month later and took in an additional $30 million the second quarter. What is more, Mr. Bush was soliciting contributions only for the primary and capped by law at $1,000 per donor.</p>
        <p>In contrast, candidates can now solicit up to $4,600 per donor -- $2,300 per donor for the primary and $2,300 per donor for the general.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's campaign declined to disclose how much of her $26 million was marked for the Democratic primaries and how much for the general election. It is a detail that could indicate how dependent her campaign might be on a relatively small number of big donors as well as how many of her supporters have already hit the limits on their donations to her primary campaign.</p>
        <p>The law allows a candidate who wins the party's nomination to roll leftover primary donations into general election coffers, but until the nominating convention is over no candidate can tap money raised for the general election, said Marc Elias, a Democratic campaign finance lawyer. So campaigns generally direct the first $2,300 from each donor to the primary campaign fund and then direct contributions above that amount to the general election.</p>
        <p>Dependence on big donors -- the ones who write checks for more than $2,300 early in a campaign -- could be a political liability for Mrs. Clinton. Mr. Obama is citing his relatively large number of small donors as evidence of his broad appeal.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mrs. Clinton's campaign said that it had received contributions from 50,000 donors and that 80 percent had given less than $100 each.</p>
        <p>The Edwards campaign, in contrast, said that out of its total take of over $14 million, less than $1 million was marked for the general election.</p>
        <p>In a conference call with reporters at 5 p.m. -- three hours after the Clinton campaign announced its totals -- the Edwards campaign defended its lesser total. ''History has clearly indicated that having the most money is not the key to winning the nomination,'' said Jonathan Prince, the Edwards deputy campaign manager.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards should know. In 2003, he set a record for first quarter fund-raising by a Democrat outside the White House with $7.4 million in contributions, thanks in part to the generosity of his fellow trial lawyers. At the start of his presidential campaign in 1999, Vice President Al Gore raised nearly $8.9 million, another record.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
