<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ohio State Has Scores To Settle in a Rematch</title>
    <meta content="02buckeyes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/sports/ncaabasketball/02buckeyes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ohio State University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5D61E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ohio State Has Scores To Settle in a Rematch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ohio State vs. Florida, a New Rivalry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jenkins, Lee</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Florida Gators and the Ohio State Buckeyes have built a rivalry in 100 days.</p>
        <p>It was born Dec. 23 in Gainesville, Fla., when the Florida basketball team defeated Ohio State by 26 points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After getting thrown together on the largest stages in college sports, the Buckeyes and the Gators have developed a healthy hatred for each other.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Florida Gators and the Ohio State Buckeyes have built a rivalry in 100 days.</p>
        <p>It was born Dec. 23 in Gainesville, Fla., when the Florida basketball team defeated Ohio State by 26 points.</p>
        <p>It grew Jan. 8 in Glendale, Ariz., when the Florida football team defeated Ohio State by 27 points.</p>
        <p>And it will turn 100 days old when the Gators and the Buckeyes meet Monday night for college basketball's national championship, having met less than three months ago for college football's national championship.</p>
        <p>Ron Lewis, Ohio State's senior guard, set the backdrop for the game Sunday afternoon, claiming that the Buckeyes were great and the Gators were simply good.</p>
        <p>Never mind that Florida has blown out Ohio State in both major sports and holds both national titles. Lewis, like most of central Ohio, is sick of bowing down to the Gators.</p>
        <p>Florida's natural rival is Florida State. Ohio State's natural rival is Michigan. The Buckeyes and the Gators play in different conferences and recruit different areas.</p>
        <p>But they keep getting thrown together on the largest stages in college sports. As a result, they have developed a healthy hatred for each other in record time.</p>
        <p>When Lewis was asked Sunday why he does not consider Florida one of the greats, he said with a smile: ''They're a good team to me. That's all I can say about it.''</p>
        <p>One of Lewis's close friends happens to be Ted Ginn Jr., the former Ohio State receiver, who started the national championship game against Florida with a 93-yard kickoff return for a touchdown.</p>
        <p>As Ginn crossed the goal line, the Ohio State basketball team was in Wisconsin, riding a bus to the team hotel. Players cheered wildly on the bus.</p>
        <p>But when they made it to the hotel and went into a conference room to watch the game on television, they learned that Ginn's teammates had injured him in the celebration. Florida reeled off seven of the next eight touchdowns.</p>
        <p>''We felt sorry for those guys,'' said Mike Conley Jr., the Ohio State point guard. ''We wanted to get a chance at Florida again. We want to win for our football team.''</p>
        <p>The hardwood Buckeyes learned two lessons watching that game in their hotel -- celebrations can be dangerous and upsets can happen. Ohio State was favored in Glendale, just as Florida is favored in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>This weekend, Ohio State basketball players received text messages from football players that included: ''You got what you wanted'' and ''Time for revenge.''</p>
        <p>Ginn, who has recovered from his sprained left foot and is now preparing for the N.F.L. draft, plans to watch Monday's game with his family in Cleveland.</p>
        <p>''I am more excited because it's Florida,'' Ginn said. ''I think it's becoming a good rivalry.''</p>
        <p>To make things competitive, the Buckeyes are going to have to win soon. When the basketball teams met in December, the game started evenly enough. The score was tied in the second half, 40-40.</p>
        <p>But Greg Oden, Ohio State's freshman center, was basically playing one-handed, still recuperating from his injured right wrist. The O'Connell Center, Florida's raucous home arena, buzzed with a record crowd.</p>
        <p>The Gators went on a 30-7 run in the second half that decided the game and sent the Buckeyes into a quiet Christmas break. When Ohio State players returned from vacation, Coach Thad Matta welcomed them with a videotape of the Florida game.</p>
        <p>''It taught us a lot about who we were,'' Matta said. ''We were not a very good basketball team on Dec. 23. It gave us a point of reference.''</p>
        <p>Florida and Ohio State have more in common than a couple of recent matchups. Both are renowned football universities that have emerged as basketball powers, mainly because of one landmark recruiting class.</p>
        <p>Florida's 2004 recruiting class included Joakim Noah, Al Horford and Corey Brewer, who teamed up for last year's title and returned to win another. Ohio State's 2006 recruiting class included Oden, Conley and Daequan Cook, who are one game away.</p>
        <p>Matta was asked Sunday if he thought that college basketball would again see three decorated underclassmen make a joint decision to bypass the N.B.A. draft and stay in school. ''Hopefully next year,'' he cracked.</p>
        <p>While Conley laughed along with his coach, Oden did not. Monday night could mark the last college game for Oden, Noah, Horford and Brewer, all of whom will probably be picked in the first round.</p>
        <p>Noah could not leave his final pregame news conference without delivering a few memorable sound bites. Asked about Lewis's evaluation of the Gators -- good, not great -- Noah sounded surprised and amused.</p>
        <p>''Oh my God,'' Noah said. ''He said that? No. What a bad person. I don't even know what else to say. I really don't know.''</p>
        <p>Noah did manage to come up with some more talking points, saying that he did not agree with the politics of President Bush, but loved the United States and appreciated the country's infatuation with sports.</p>
        <p>That infatuation will be on full display Monday night, as two national powers vie for another title. The football teams from both universities are playing a unique role. The one at Ohio State is clamoring for redemption. The one at Florida is eyeing a streak.</p>
        <p>When Florida football players left for Glendale last winter and prepared to take on Ohio State, Noah sent them off with a message. Now, they are reminding him what he said: ''We the Gators. We got to come back with the ring.''</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
