<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Misfired Memo Shows Close Tabs on Reporter</title>
    <meta content="02wired" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Relations and Publicity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D81E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Misfired Memo Shows Close Tabs on Reporter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANGELA MACROPOULOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macropoulos, Angela</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Journalists have an uneasy awareness that public relations professionals keep tabs on them, the better to hone the way they pitch and spin ideas for articles. And while the extent of this practice normally is not aired in public, it was last week when Wired magazine posted a long memo  about one of its reporters that had been sent by e-mail to him by Microsoft, accidentally.</p>
        <p>In February, during the course of reporting on a video blogging initiative at Microsoft called Channel 9, Fred Vogelstein inadvertently received a 13-page, 5,500-word internal memo from Waggener Edstrom Worldwide, a firm that represents Microsoft. The document, which was meant to prepare Microsoft executives for interviews, contained frank details, including some less-than-flattering observations (''Fred's stories tend to be a bit sensational, though he would consider them to be balanced and fair''), scripted responses to questions and a strong-arm list of the points the agency expected to see in the piece.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Journalists have an uneasy awareness that public relations professionals keep tabs on them, the better to hone the way they pitch and spin ideas for articles. And while the extent of this practice normally is not aired in public, it was last week when Wired magazine posted a long memo  about one of its reporters that had been sent by e-mail to him by Microsoft, accidentally.</p>
        <p>In February, during the course of reporting on a video blogging initiative at Microsoft called Channel 9, Fred Vogelstein inadvertently received a 13-page, 5,500-word internal memo from Waggener Edstrom Worldwide, a firm that represents Microsoft. The document, which was meant to prepare Microsoft executives for interviews, contained frank details, including some less-than-flattering observations (''Fred's stories tend to be a bit sensational, though he would consider them to be balanced and fair''), scripted responses to questions and a strong-arm list of the points the agency expected to see in the piece.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vogelstein, a contributing editor at Wired, was described as ''tricky'' in interviews. ''He looks deeply for any dirt around whatever topic he is focused on and generally is tight-lipped about the direction he will take for his stories, sometimes even misleading you to throw you off,'' the memo said. ''It takes him a bit to get thoughts across, so try to be patient.''</p>
        <p>The memo also said that Microsoft's publicity team would get a chance to vet the article (''We should have a look at it in early March and it should run late March for the April issue''), a practice shunned by journalists. Both Wired, which is part of Condé Nast, and Waggener Edstrom say that did not happen.</p>
        <p>Frank Shaw, the president of Waggener Edstrom in charge of the Microsoft account, said that the person who made the blunder ''feels awful, and there was no action. It was the kind of mistake anyone could make.'' Microsoft, he said, ''was not upset with Waggener Edstrom for the contents of the mail.''</p>
        <p>Noting that the article Mr. Vogelstein wrote was about a Microsoft project that permits employees to blog about the company's corporate doings -- a concept called ''radical transparency'' -- Mr. Shaw said, ''In a lot of ways, it was irresistible to Wired to bring attention to it. To show it as the polar opposite of the transparency piece they were working on.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Vogelstein said in a telephone interview that the memo, which made its way into an e-mail message about appointment scheduling, gave him a weird sense of voyeurism.</p>
        <p>''We all want to know what everybody thinks about us, but I think most of us, if we found out, would be sorry,'' he said. ''Some of the stuff I was totally fine with, but I objected to being called 'tricky' and I thought, 'Wow -- they really think that?' ''</p>
        <p>Chris Anderson, the editor in chief of Wired, wrote in his personal blog  that the memo's command-and-control message showed that Microsoft's ''old company culture'' lingers. It was, he said, an ironic counterpoint to the openness promoted by Microsoft's senior managers in Mr. Vogelstein's article.</p>
        <p>Evan Cornog, associate dean for academic affairs at the Columbia Graduate School of Journalism and publisher of The Columbia Journalism Review, said that the memo gave the public a useful glimpse of how journalism works. ''Readers need to know the kind of terrain reporters have to negotiate to get a story,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One comment on Mr. Anderson's blog said the most striking thing was that Waggener Edstrom spent hundreds of hours on controlling the message, but that one wrong keystroke seemed to have trumped the agency's efforts. It concluded, ''On one hand, you have 3,500 rank-and-file bloggers creating good will for an embattled company. On the other, you have a few highly paid P.R. guys burning that good will as fast as their retainer.''</p>
        <p>ANGELA MACROPOULOS</p>
        <p>MEDIA TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
