<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SCHOOL AID FIGHT ERUPTS IN ALBANY AS BUDGET PASSES</title>
    <meta content="02budget" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/nyregion/02budget.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DECISIONS IN ALBANY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Education (Handicapped)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rebates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rebates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Education (Handicapped)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SCHOOL AID FIGHT ERUPTS IN ALBANY AS BUDGET PASSES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">School Aid Fight Erupts in Albany as Budget Passes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM and DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny; Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State lawmakers pass $120.9 billion budget, missing March 31 deadline by one day, but almost immediately after final vote Gov Eliot Spitzer's staff and Legislature begin to dispute education spending, most contentious portion; dispute underscores secretive nature of negotiations; New York City will receive more money for schools, but will have to reduce class sizes and meet additional requirements; Long Island is getting more than half of nearly $21 million in new aid for special education and about $70 million of nearly $100 million in new education aid for districts with high taxes, leaving Westchester legislators feeling shortchanged, especially as county has among highest property taxes; budget accomplishes some of Spitzer's key objectives, even as he cedes ground to Senate Republicans on some issues; budget includes $1 billion in Medicaid cuts, $1.3 billion in school property tax rebates and expansion of state-financed health care coverage to 400,000 currently uninsured children; Spitzer succeeds in creating new school aid formula that gives high-need districts greater proportion of school aid than in past, although distribution this year does not follow new formula because of objections from Long Island legislators; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawmakers finished passing an estimated $120.9 billion budget Sunday morning that they had not had time to read and had barely debated. But almost immediately after the final vote, the governor's staff and the Legislature began to dispute what was written in the most contentious portion of the budget -- education -- underscoring the secretive nature of the negotiations that led to thousands of pages of legislation.</p>
        <p>Though New York City will receive more money for schools, the final product left questions about how substantially its share of state education aid had grown and how far the city would have to go in reducing class sizes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The governor’s staff and the Legislature began to dispute the portion on education of the $120.9 billion budget.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawmakers finished passing an estimated $120.9 billion budget Sunday morning that they had not had time to read and had barely debated. But almost immediately after the final vote, the governor's staff and the Legislature began to dispute what was written in the most contentious portion of the budget -- education -- underscoring the secretive nature of the negotiations that led to thousands of pages of legislation.</p>
        <p>Though New York City will receive more money for schools, the final product left questions about how substantially its share of state education aid had grown and how far the city would have to go in reducing class sizes.</p>
        <p>And while school districts across the state will receive more money, sometimes much more, Westchester legislators were left wondering whether Long Island had made off with some of their county's rightful share.</p>
        <p>Certainly, there were oddities in the fine print.</p>
        <p>More than half of nearly $21 million in new aid for special education went to Long Island, less an indication of a surge in students with disabilities than of a political deal the governor made to get Senate Republicans to approve more school money for New York City.</p>
        <p>Similarly, about $70 million of nearly $100 million in new education aid for districts with high taxes went to Long Island. But only about $1.2 million went to Westchester, which has some of the highest school property tax rates.</p>
        <p>The treatment of Westchester ''came very close to blowing the whole budget,'' Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver said Sunday night.</p>
        <p>Despite objections from Westchester lawmakers, the budget was passed by 11 a.m., accomplishing several of Gov. Eliot Spitzer's key objectives even as he ceded ground to Senate Republicans. As expected, it included $1 billion in Medicaid cuts, $1.3 billion in school property tax rebate checks and an expansion of state-financed health care coverage to the 400,000 children in the state who are currently uninsured.</p>
        <p>The Legislature, long known for delayed budgets, had made its midnight March 31 deadline the previous two years. The missing of the deadline this year was largely symbolic and did not affect state operations.</p>
        <p>''When all the surrounding dust settles and the public looks at what we accomplished, they will see this budget hit every one of the objectives I had laid out over the course of the prior two months,'' the governor said on Sunday morning after walking through the Assembly to shake hands with members.</p>
        <p>Though the fight over the governor's proposed health care cuts was more visible, because of a bruising media campaign by the health care lobby, as is often the case it was education that was most controversial inside the Capitol.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer had proposed to take the politics out of school financing and send money to districts based solely on need, in large measure to comply with an order by the state's highest court to send more aid to New York City schools.</p>
        <p>In the end, though, the governor's plan appeared to fall short by some measures, with Long Island receiving roughly the same share it had in previous years and some of the wealthier school districts faring better than poorer ones.</p>
        <p>But the governor did succeed in creating a new school aid formula that gives high-need districts a greater proportion of school aid than in the past.</p>
        <p>The budget also required New York City to devise plans for reducing class sizes, and it doubled the maximum number of charter schools, to 200, including up to 50 new schools in New York City.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer also succeeded in passing new measures aimed at raising accountability for schools and toughening state oversight. Among them, the state must also seek to identify 5 percent of schools statewide as failing and develop more intensive strategies to improve them.</p>
        <p>And he obtained even more education spending than he had sought. The $1.76 billion in new education aid will bring total spending close to $20 billion. New York City will get a substantial increase, pleasing city officials, though the governor's staff and Senate Republicans vigorously disputed each other's analysis of the budget.</p>
        <p>The governor and his staff, and several education advocates, said their biggest gain was, in the words of Paul Francis, the state budget director, ''implementing a permanent foundation formula that distributes aid based on a district's educational needs and local ability to support education.''</p>
        <p>Their claim is that by creating an underlying formula based on data, instead of divvying up money based on political objectives, they had changed the system.</p>
        <p>In the end, however, the distribution of money this year did not follow the new formula, because the governor had to add roughly $400 million to appease objections, particularly by Republican senators from Long Island.</p>
        <p>Senate Republicans said that little had fundamentally changed from years past, when education spending held up the budget.</p>
        <p>''We expect that it won't be any different next year,'' said John E. McArdle, a spokesman for the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno. ''We fight this fight and are successful year in, year out, and we expect next year to be no different.''</p>
        <p>The governor's staff said that 41 percent of new school aid this year would go to New York City, compared with its existing 38.86 percent, and with the 46 percent share of increased aid that was originally proposed by the governor.</p>
        <p>The Senate leadership, sensitive to any suggestion that New York City had received a favor, said that the city's new aid share was lower and that the governor's staff was including money from a program approved last year. The governor's aides said they were including that money because it was being spent this year.</p>
        <p>The governor had proposed that only 8 percent of new aid go to Long Island, but the ultimate amount was on the order of the 12 to 13 percent that Nassau and Suffolk Counties usually receive.</p>
        <p>''The governor created the central tool we need to divide school aid fairly, which is the foundation formula,'' said Billy Easton, executive director of the Alliance for Quality Education, which has lobbied for increased school aid for New York City.</p>
        <p>''This year, we're using it partially,'' he added. ''Next year, we need to use it fully.''</p>
        <p>Most upset were Assembly Democrats from Westchester, who voted against the education portion of the budget, saying their districts were being punished as part of a political deal to appease the Senate.</p>
        <p>Six Assembly members drafted a letter to the governor to complain of what they called a ''gross injustice.''</p>
        <p>''We've singled out communities to help before; we've never before singled out a community to hurt,'' said Assemblyman Richard L. Brodsky, a Westchester Democrat. ''It's an unconscionable, discriminatory addition to the school aid formula.''</p>
        <p>Westchester's allocation appeared to result from language deep in the budget that described a school district's eligibility for the high-tax aid ''pursuant to Subparagraph 2 of Paragraph A of Subdivision 4 of this section, in excess of one and three-tenths, in which the quotient of the residential real property tax levy, divided by the adjusted gross income, computed to five decimals without rounding,'' and so on.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brodsky also said he believed that the defeat in November of Senator Nicholas A. Spano, a veteran Westchester Republican, meant that Senate Republicans had no incentive to continue pushing for aid for Westchester.</p>
        <p>Mr. McArdle said the Senate had supported more aid for Westchester but had been rebuffed by the Assembly leadership.</p>
        <p>SpeakerSilver disputed that assertion, saying the Senate had proposed no high-tax aid for Westchester at all.</p>
        <p>''I went down to the governor's office personally,'' said Mr. Silver, a Democrat from Manhattan, adding, ''I said this is unacceptable and I am not accepting this.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver said the result was the restoring of a total of roughly $3 million in aid for Westchester.</p>
        <p>Another reason the budget was delayed was a last-minute standoff over the Assembly's insistence that New York City be required to reduce class sizes in exchange for the increase in education aid.</p>
        <p>City officials, particularly Schools Chancellor Joel I. Klein, had resisted restrictions on the new money.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Silver and the teachers' union wanted the budget bill to address class size, an issue of perennial concern to parents and educators.</p>
        <p>City officials also had other concerns about the budget bill, including the possibility that it would leave the city vulnerable to lawsuits over class sizes and would bar the city from reducing its education budget even in the event of a fiscal crisis.</p>
        <p>With patience fraying on all sides, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg dispatched Deputy Mayor Dennis M. Walcott to help broker a settlement, which will require the city to develop a plan for reducing class sizes over five years but does not set specific targets, either in terms of the number of children in each class or the amount of money the city will have to spend.</p>
        <p>The deal also protected the city from lawsuits over class size, requiring any disputes to be adjudicated by the state education commissioner.</p>
        <p>The compromise had all sides claiming victory.</p>
        <p>''The language is clear, it's not ambiguous, class size has to be part of the foundational plan for reform,'' said Randi Weingarten, the president of the city teachers' union.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walcott said the requirements would not tie the administration's hands. ''All of us want small class size,'' he said. ''We feel it's important to have the flexibility.''</p>
        <p>The Bloomberg administration also praised the lifting of the state's limit on charter schools, but there were compromises on that front, too, including a provision that automatically unionizes the employees of any charter school serving more than 250 students in its first two years.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Chancellor Klein said of the budget, ''It's obviously a very solid deal for us.''</p>
        <p>''There is no doubt that if we infuse over the next four years the kinds of money that Albany has committed to, that we will be able to achieve our goals,'' he said, ''including an overall considerable reduction in class size.''</p>
        <p>DECISIONS IN ALBANY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
