<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crime Drops In Newark, But Murders Keep On Rising</title>
    <meta content="02newark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/02/nyregion/02newark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1837567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Booker, Cory A (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Muggings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Muggings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Booker, Cory A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2D71E30F931A35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crime Drops In Newark, But Murders Keep On Rising</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Crime Drops in Newark, but Murders Are Flat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Overall crime rate has dropped in Newark in first three months of 2007, but there have been 24 murders, up from 22 during first three months of 2006; shootings, burglaries, rapes and assaults are down, but police remain stymied by homicides; some criminal experts say that homicides tend to be driven by very small population and that group concentrated in low-income neighborhoods can make homicide numbers go up; Mayor Cory A Booker says he still believes that by end of this year city will be one of most exciting crime-reduction stories in country; photo; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Cory A. Booker looked at the police statistics in front of him and let out a relieved sigh. Three months into 2007, overall crime here in New Jersey's largest city had dropped some 40 percent from the previous year. Shootings were down 42 percent, rapes 27 percent.</p>
        <p>After years on the rise, it seemed as if Newark's tide of violence might be ebbing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After years on the rise, Newark’s tide of violence might be ebbing and Mayor Cory A. Booker is hopeful the trend will continue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Cory A. Booker looked at the police statistics in front of him and let out a relieved sigh. Three months into 2007, overall crime here in New Jersey's largest city had dropped some 40 percent from the previous year. Shootings were down 42 percent, rapes 27 percent.</p>
        <p>After years on the rise, it seemed as if Newark's tide of violence might be ebbing.</p>
        <p>Sitting in a City Hall conference room at his weekly public safety briefing three weeks ago, Mr. Booker turned to his police director, Garry F. McCarthy, and beamed. ''These numbers are phenomenal,'' Mr. Booker said. ''Let's hope they hold.''</p>
        <p>Then he joked to the half-dozen aides gathered: ''If any of you guys get shot over the next few weeks, please just make sure you don't die.''</p>
        <p>But the last half of March brought bad news. Although crime continued to fall overall, five people were killed in the month's final two weeks, bringing the number of murders this year to 24, up from 22 during the first three months of 2006.</p>
        <p>''I don't even know what to say, because it doesn't make sense,'' Mr. McCarthy told Mr. Booker as they studied the murder figures last Tuesday. ''Considering how far all the other numbers have come, it feels like bad luck.''</p>
        <p>Even as they continue to see a drop in shootings, burglaries, rapes and assaults, the police here remain stymied by homicides. Except for a handful of exceptions, the authorities said, most of the victims were young and had criminal records, gang affiliations and connections to the drug trade.</p>
        <p>Last year, there were 105 killings in Newark, the highest number since 1990, when the crack epidemic was raging and 114 people lost their lives to violence.</p>
        <p>A number of other cities saw murders climb last year after a decade of decline, but crime experts say Newark's situation is unusual because shootings, which often run parallel to homicides, have plummeted since January. Other usual barometers of falling crime, such as gun seizures and arrests of all sorts, have increased in recent months.</p>
        <p>Armando B. Fontura, the Essex County sheriff, has his own theory about why homicides in Newark remain high in the face of an overall drop in crime. Guns are plentiful, he said, and those who own them have little compunction about settling disputes with weapons.</p>
        <p>''If they think you've violated their territory or disrespected someone and one of these thugs marks you for death, the next day you're dead,'' Sheriff Fontura said. ''Even if you put more police on the street, you're not going to stop an assassination.''</p>
        <p>David Kennedy, the director of the Center for Crime Prevention and Control at John Jay College of Criminal Justice, said that in many of the cities where homicides were rising, like Newark, the violence was concentrated in low-income neighborhoods where guns were abundant and both suspects and victims had criminal histories.</p>
        <p>''The homicides tend to be driven by a very small population, and so while a city as a whole can be getting safer, this tiny, superheated group of people can make the homicide numbers go in the wrong direction,'' Mr. Kennedy said.</p>
        <p>Such explanations offer little comfort to Mr. Booker, who repeatedly tells residents and reporters alike that public safety should be the main measure of his success as mayor.</p>
        <p>Although he is frustrated by the lack of progress in lowering the number of murders -- and reacts emotionally to news of each death -- Mr. Booker tries to remind people that the average Newarker is far less likely to be mugged, shot or have a car stolen than a year ago.</p>
        <p>He urges patience. ''I still believe that by the end of the year we'll be one of the most exciting crime-reduction stories in the country,'' said Mr. Booker, who took office in July.</p>
        <p>The outcome will rely heavily on Mr. McCarthy, the police director, who has been working to revamp a department bruised by political infighting, allegations of corruption, decaying station houses and criticism of its policing style.</p>
        <p>Since last fall, when he was hired away from the New York Police Department, Mr. McCarthy has created a central narcotics division, transferred 150 officers from desk jobs to patrol work and begun a fugitive squad that has captured 9 of the city's 12 most wanted suspects. Morale, many officers on the 1,300-member force say, has never been higher.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCarthy, whose forte as New York's deputy commissioner of operations was tactics and intelligence, also has been pushing an aggressive quality-of-life policing campaign in the hope it will do for Newark what it did for New York. Officers here have been issuing so many tickets for public drinking and littering -- nearly 4,000 since January -- that some precincts have almost exhausted their supply of forms.</p>
        <p>But it is not clear whether such a crackdown can put a dent in homicides. ''This is a work in progress,'' Mr. McCarthy said.</p>
        <p>It is at the ComStat meetings, a gathering every Thursday of commanding officers and division heads, where Mr. McCarthy's crime-fighting strategy is most clearly on display.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCarthy and his chief of criminal investigations, Samuel DeMaio, prod veteran detectives and precinct commanders about recent crimes and exhort them to think about tackling their jobs in new ways. ''Your shootings are looking good, but your homicides are horrible,'' he said to one commander whose precinct investigated a double homicide last week.</p>
        <p>He explained that a new criminal intelligence unit would begin collecting data on every arrested gang member, illegal social club and outdoor drug bazaar. The idea, he said, is to stop crimes before they occur. ''The work we do before something happens is just as important as the work we do after something happens,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Then he reminded the gathering that mundane tactics, like giving out parking tickets to double-parked cars in known drug locations, can pay off. ''A lot of cops say, 'I don't do parkers or movers,' '' he said, using police lingo for parking and moving violations. ''But if someone goes in to buy a dime bag of weed and they get a $65 parking ticket, that dime bag just cost them $75. Chances are, they're not coming back.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
