<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Medium, the Message, The Drama of TV's Q &amp; A</title>
    <meta content="26frost" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/theater/26frost.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Nixon, Richard Milhous</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Frost, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E1DF153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1134" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Medium, the Message, The Drama of TV's Q &amp; A</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Medium, the Message, the Drama of TV’s Q &amp; A</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The conversations between David Frost and Richard Nixon that are the basis of Peter Morgan's ''Frost/Nixon,'' newly on Broadway, took place over 28 hours 45 minutes during 12 days in March 1977. Distilled into four 90-minute segments and broadcast later that year, the interviews were shot in California, near Nixon's San Clemente estate, in a rental house whose appointments seemed a threat to whatever dignity the former president might have hoped to reconstruct.</p>
        <p>The journalist and his adversary faced each other on a white shag rug in moiré armchairs the color of an unwashed taxi. The effect of the arrangement is startling now, and it prompts us to consider just how deep into the crevices of American life the big Nixonian mess seemed to cast its dust. The whole louche, chaotic, regrettable aesthetic of the 1970s is on display, and right along with it, the visual logic implies, the culprit of all the disorder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The conversations between David Frost and Richard Nixon that are the basis of the play “Frost/Nixon” must be seen to be fully appreciated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The conversations between David Frost and Richard Nixon that are the basis of Peter Morgan's ''Frost/Nixon,'' newly on Broadway, took place over 28 hours 45 minutes during 12 days in March 1977. Distilled into four 90-minute segments and broadcast later that year, the interviews were shot in California, near Nixon's San Clemente estate, in a rental house whose appointments seemed a threat to whatever dignity the former president might have hoped to reconstruct.</p>
        <p>The journalist and his adversary faced each other on a white shag rug in moiré armchairs the color of an unwashed taxi. The effect of the arrangement is startling now, and it prompts us to consider just how deep into the crevices of American life the big Nixonian mess seemed to cast its dust. The whole louche, chaotic, regrettable aesthetic of the 1970s is on display, and right along with it, the visual logic implies, the culprit of all the disorder.</p>
        <p>''Frost/Nixon,'' which establishes the setting of the talks more soberly, invests itself primarily in dramatizing the back story of Mr. Frost's efforts to secure the interview with Nixon and ultimately wrest from him an apology for transgressions of the public trust. In that vein, the play borrows only a small fraction of the material from the actual televised discussions (parts of which can be seen online, though not dependably, on DVD and at the Museum of Television and Radio, which will screen highlights on May 5 and 6). At the level of pure form, the interviews, which I watched before seeing the play, must be seen to be fully appreciated -- for their languorous pace, for the somnolent expression that crosses Mr. Frost's face, for the interviewer's habit of massaging his fingertips, a nervous gesture Mr. Frost manages to indulge with the odd serenity of someone merely waiting to see his accountant.</p>
        <p>In a significant sense, the triumph of the Frost-Nixon interviews is far more extensive than Mr. Morgan, who confines it to Nixon's statement of guilt, is willing or able to allow. The venture's impact stretched far beyond the straight fact of Nixon's admission of wrongdoing. It embodied the triumph of an idea -- that every performance of contrition is an exercise of renewal. Some historians have argued that Nixon revisionism slowly began the moment the just-resigned president stepped into his helicopter and left the White House lawn. But nothing solidified the initiative quite like the image of Nixon, three years after his fall, visibly sorrowful and unmoored, still in the full grip of his legendary delusions, insecurities and piffling resentments. (Nixon, as he makes clear in the complete interviews, still could not get over that the Kennedys, during their tenure in the White House, had never asked him to lunch.)</p>
        <p>The language and culture of therapy and self-help -- in full, mass-market paperback swing by the mid-1970s -- redounded to the former president's advantage. Suddenly the ordinary person could understand his moral lassitude in terms of a greater sense of desperation. Nixon was no longer merely corrupt; he was interesting. And the interviews seemed to demand that Americans extend their sympathy to him on the sheer grounds of his psychological complexity.</p>
        <p>''Frost/Nixon'' goes further, equating that complexity with charm. So committed is the play to the idea of Nixon's likability that it may be one of the great victories of Nixon revisionism. But in compressing dialogue, rearranging chronology and shifting some of Nixon's disclosures out of their original context, ''Frost/Nixon'' loses one of the most poignant moments of the talks. In one portion of the interviews, Mr. Frost asks Nixon about life after resignation, and Nixon responds dismally: ''You feel, gee, isn't it just great to have enough money to afford a nice house, to be able to play golf and have nice parties and good clothes and shoes and suits, etc., etc., to travel if you want to. And the answer is, if you don't have these things, they can mean a great deal to you. When you have them, they mean nothing to you.''</p>
        <p>The play has Nixon expressing a similar sentiment to his agent, Swifty Lazar, and the effect is dissipated. As the journalist Murray Kempton once wrote, Nixon ended his 1960 campaign ''wandering limply and wetly about the American heartland begging votes on the excuse that he had been too poor to have a pony when he was a boy.'' When Nixon expressed his boredom to an audience of millions, he was exploiting class sentiments once again. Nixon essentially began his career in presidential politics asking people to feel sorry for him because he once had no money with which to idly divert himself; he ended it asking them to feel sorry for his having way too much.</p>
        <p>Much of the drama of ''Frost/Nixon'' rests on the idea that Nixon was a consummate stonewaller and Mr. Frost a glitz-hound and possible nincompoop, incapable of the obduracy required for such a reportorial effort. But one of the many points at which that interpretation of Mr. Frost falls apart, upon a fresh viewing of the actual interview tapes, takes place during an exchange about the war in Southeast Asia. Mr. Frost, inquiring whether Nixon felt that the invasion of Cambodia fueled the growth of the Khmer Rouge, uses the word ''concatenate.'' Concatenate. (It isn't just that we are unable to imagine Meredith Viera using a word like that with Meg Ryan. It is nearly as unfathomable to think of Charlie Rose pulling it out of his dictionary for Cormac McCarthy.)</p>
        <p>On the subjects of the Spiro Agnew scandal and the C.I.A.'s involvement in removing Salvador Allende from his leadership of Chile, Mr. Frost in the televised interviews remains persistent. Nixon defends the United States involvement there by quoting an Italian businessman who once conveyed to him a fear of a ''red sandwich'' in Latin America. ''But that's madness of him to say this,'' Mr. Frost responds, determined to get Nixon to acknowledge the horrors of Augusto Pinochet's dictatorship. ''If you had to use a word to describe the Pinochet regime,'' Mr. Frost continues, ''what adjective would you use, brutal?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Frost did have difficulty securing august advertisers for his project, as the play claims, and this is undoubtedly so. The footage of the interviews available at the Museum of Television and Radio includes the commercials, many of which have the strange subliminal effect of reminding us that we are watching a man try to unsully himself. There are ads for Weed Eaters, Certs breath mints, Ban roll-on antiperspirant and another product that establishes the era's mood of revelation. ''Millions know him as the Fonz, but Henry Winkler feels trapped by his TV fame,'' the ad begins. It implores viewers to learn the deep truth about him in ''a bold new picture magazine.'' The magazine is called Us.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
