<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study Says Hispanics Alter U.S. Catholicism</title>
    <meta content="26hispanic" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/us/26hispanic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pew Hispanic Center</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodstein, Laurie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E1DE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study Says Hispanics Alter U.S. Catholicism</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Study Says Hispanics Alter U.S. Catholicism</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE GOODSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodstein, Laurie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study by Pew Hispanic Center and Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life finds influx of Hispanic immigrants to US is transforming Roman Catholic Church; finds 50 percent of Hispanic Catholics practice form of charismatic Catholicism that includes practices often associated with Pentacostalism; finds 66 percent of Hispanics choose to worship in Spanish-speaking congregations with Hispanic clergymen (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The influx of Hispanic immigrants to the United States is transforming the Roman Catholic Church as well as the nation's religious landscape, according to a study of Hispanics and religion released yesterday.</p>
        <p>The study, conducted by the Pew Hispanic Center and the Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life, found that half of Hispanic Catholics practice a ''distinctive form'' of charismatic Catholicism that includes speaking in tongues, miraculous healings and prophesying -- practices more often associated with Pentecostalism. Among Catholics who are not Hispanic, only 12 percent are involved in these practices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The influx of Hispanic immigrants to the U.S. is transforming the nation’s religious landscape, according to a study.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The influx of Hispanic immigrants to the United States is transforming the Roman Catholic Church as well as the nation's religious landscape, according to a study of Hispanics and religion released yesterday.</p>
        <p>The study, conducted by the Pew Hispanic Center and the Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life, found that half of Hispanic Catholics practice a ''distinctive form'' of charismatic Catholicism that includes speaking in tongues, miraculous healings and prophesying -- practices more often associated with Pentecostalism. Among Catholics who are not Hispanic, only 12 percent are involved in these practices.</p>
        <p>The study also found that two-thirds of Hispanics choose to worship in ''ethnic congregations'' that have Hispanic clergymen and Spanish-language services, and where a majority of congregants are Hispanic. These congregations are cropping up throughout the country, even in areas where Hispanics are sparse.</p>
        <p>Hispanics are the fastest-growing ethnic group in the United States, doubling from 1980 to 2000, and projected to more than double between 2000 and 2020, Pew researchers said. As of 2005, there were 42 million Hispanics in the United States, about 14 percent of the population.</p>
        <p>According to the survey, 68 percent of Hispanics are Catholic, 15 percent are born-again or evangelical Protestants, 5 percent are mainline Protestants, 3 percent are identified as ''other Christian'' and 8 percent are secular (1 percent refused to answer).</p>
        <p>Among non-Hispanic Americans, the largest groupings are 20 percent Catholic, 35 percent evangelical Protestant and 24 percent mainline Protestant.</p>
        <p>The religious identity of Hispanics will affect politics, the report says. The Hispanic electorate is largely Democratic (63 percent), despite being conservative on social issues like abortion and homosexuality. But Hispanic evangelical Protestants -- whose numbers are growing -- are twice as likely as Hispanic Catholics to be Republicans. This is a far greater gap than exists between white evangelical Protestants and Catholics.</p>
        <p>About one-third of Catholics in the United States are now Hispanic.</p>
        <p>Roberto Suro, director of the Pew Hispanic Center, said in an interview that Hispanic Catholics looked different from typical white suburban Catholics. ''They are different in terms of beliefs, practices, language and culture, but they remain very Catholic,'' Mr. Suro said. ''The open question here is, Does the institution adapt to them, or do they adapt to the institution?''</p>
        <p>The study also found that conversion is a common experience for many Hispanics. Nearly one in five changed either from one religion to another, or to no religion at all.</p>
        <p>The biggest loser from all the conversions is the Catholic Church, while evangelical Protestant churches are the beneficiaries.</p>
        <p>Despite the departures, it is Hispanics who are replenishing Catholic ranks, Luis E. Lugo, director of the Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life, said in a news conference.</p>
        <p>''The gains for the Catholic Church in this country among Latinos, from immigration and higher fertility rates, are more than making up for those Latino Catholics, particularly in the second generation, who go to other churches or turn secular,'' Mr. Lugo said.</p>
        <p>The study, ''Changing Faiths: Latinos and the Transformation of American Religion,'' is based on several surveys -- the main one conducted from Aug. 10 to Oct. 4, 2006 -- that involved more than 4,600 adult Hispanics. The margin of error is plus or minus 2.5 percentage points.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
