<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I'd Like To Get Off The Stage Right Now</title>
    <meta content="26baldwin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/fashion/26baldwin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070503T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wireless Communications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFD6143EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I'd Like To Get Off The Stage Right Now</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">I’d Like to Get Off the Stage Right Now</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHARON WAXMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waxman, Sharon</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DID anybody really want to hear Alec Baldwin call his 11-year-old daughter a ''thoughtless little pig,'' an ugly, private moment now shared with the rest of the world?</p>
        <p>It doesn't matter. Prepare for the next frontier in high-impact celebrity shenanigans: you-are-there depictions of divorce fights, drunken brawls, on-the-set tirades, slips of the tongue, flings of the wineglass and flings of the other kind, too. The digital age has thrown down the gauntlet to all who might wield something as innocuous as a cellphone and let the world see for itself. You record. And you decide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thanks to the digital age, Hollywood’s dirty laundry no longer remains only in Hollywood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DID anybody really want to hear Alec Baldwin call his 11-year-old daughter a ''thoughtless little pig,'' an ugly, private moment now shared with the rest of the world?</p>
        <p>It doesn't matter. Prepare for the next frontier in high-impact celebrity shenanigans: you-are-there depictions of divorce fights, drunken brawls, on-the-set tirades, slips of the tongue, flings of the wineglass and flings of the other kind, too. The digital age has thrown down the gauntlet to all who might wield something as innocuous as a cellphone and let the world see for itself. You record. And you decide.</p>
        <p>The leaking to a Web site, TMZ.com, of Mr. Baldwin's phone message berating his daughter Ireland, whence it bounced all over the media biosphere, may just set a new benchmark for material that can be expected to come careering into the public domain, courtesy of calculating lawyers, nosy bystanders or unscrupulous spinmeisters (is there any other kind?).</p>
        <p>In the voicemail, Mr. Baldwin called his daughter a ''rude, thoughtless little pig'' because she didn't answer her phone when called at a prearranged time. He warned that she would never humiliate him again, and threatened to fly to Los Angeles to ''straighten'' her out.</p>
        <p>Whose business was it? Everyone's, apparently. By the time the message hit the Internet a week ago, the New York-based actor had already apologized to his daughter, a spokesman said. But now he had to apologize to the rest of the world. He did that on his Web site, alecbaldwin.com, saying that he was worn down by years of fighting over Ireland with his former wife, Kim Basinger.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry, as everyone who knows me is aware, for losing my temper with my child,'' he wrote. ''I have been driven to the edge by parental alienation for many years now.''</p>
        <p>And the world answered back, too. The comments on Mr. Baldwin's Web site testify to the newfound entitlement of perfect strangers to participate in every aspect of the private lives of public figures. ''Children are not sounding boards for adult frustration,'' scolded someone identified as ''ka.'' ''If you act that way, GET COUNSELING.'' Val, however, urged Mr. Baldwin to ''try to stay strong for Ireland and believe in yourself and your love for her as a dad. You are awesome!!!''</p>
        <p>None of this would have been possible a very short time ago. ''The dark side of all this wonderful technology is that things that by their nature would have remained private as recently as 10 years ago are now available for, literally, almost everyone in the world to see and hear,'' said Allan Mayer, a partner in the publicity firm 42West, who specializes in crisis control.</p>
        <p>''We're way past what's fair or not,'' he continued. ''It's simply about the fact that these situations would never have gone beyond a small circle of eyewitnesses, and even then, they wouldn't have had the same impact.''</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, Hollywood's dirty laundry remained in Hollywood. People inside the entertainment industry knew the juicy details of the latest ugly divorce, or the latest star tantrum on a set, or in a restaurant. But almost no one else did.</p>
        <p>The celebrity age widened the circle considerably, making us privy to Britney's every heartbreak, Lindsay's every stumble. But what until recently was the province of tabloids and the paparazzi and private investigators is now the domain of the average schmoe. The digital era and the rise of YouTube means that recording this material, and then viewing it over and over, is no longer off limits to anyone.</p>
        <p>The other day, those with nothing better to do could see a picture of Vince Vaughn apparently having a tantrum at a popular sushi location near the Warner Brothers' lot, as captured by the cellphone of a fellow diner. Or they could watch the notorious cellphone video of Michael Richards using a racial slur at a Los Angeles comedy club. Meanwhile, tens of thousands clicked to watch the director David O. Russell eviscerate Lily Tomlin on the set of ''I Heart Huckabees,'' from video taken during the shoot four years ago and which was uploaded to the Internet a couple of weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Who leaked it and why? The very same could be asked about Mr. Baldwin's phone message. Motives matter, so does context, neither of which can be discerned in a selected two-minute rant.</p>
        <p>Ms. Basinger denied being the source of the phone message leak. The actress ''did not release the voicemail. Additionally, the voicemail was not sealed under a court order,'' said a spokeswoman in a statement this week. The actress took the recording into court, and a judge barred further contact between Mr. Baldwin and his daughter until a hearing on May 4.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Baldwin's spokesman, Matthew Hiltzik, said: ''Alec has always preferred to keep private matters private. Unfortunately, the mother or someone acting on her behalf chose to make this tape public.''</p>
        <p>Regardless, the impact on Ireland is unlikely to be positive. ''Whoever leaked it did not think about the child,'' said Daniel B. Rubanowitz, a family-law lawyer in Los Angeles. ''I don't know who had access to the message, but whoever put it on the air clearly didn't think about the child who is going to be exposed to this, and what effect it will have on her and both her parents. People need to be a little more child focused.''</p>
        <p>Raul Felder, a divorce lawyer who has represented Rudolph W. Giuliani and Robin Givens, lamented: ''What happened here is private tragedy becomes a public agony.'' He added: ''There's no way to prevent this except with people showing judgment. And divorce cases are not where sound judgment rules, it's where passions rule.''</p>
        <p>By Tuesday, Mr. Baldwin's head was spinning enough that he fired his agents at Creative Arts Agency, the same company that represents Ms. Basinger. His spokesman said he could give no reason for it, and suggested the decision might not be final.</p>
        <p>But in the field of damage control, the rapid shifts in access to every personal foible and ill-considered phrase of the rich and famous is the equivalent of flying without a net.</p>
        <p>And the truth? The truth is a diminishing resource, easily bludgeoned by the facts.</p>
        <p>''You can say, 'Be transparent,' '' said Mr. Mayer, the expert in crisis control, ''but you're seeing all these things ripped out of context, that's the scary thing about it. There is the illusion when you're watching a video that you're seeing the whole truth. As anyone who's followed court cases, or been in the news business knows, looking at different outtakes you get different realities. And this powerful illusion of reality is far more misleading than any distorted account.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 3, 2007, Thursday  An article last week about technology's intrusion on celebrities' privacy misspelled the first name of a divorce lawyer who has represented prominent clients. He is Raoul Felder, not Raul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 3, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article last week about technology's intrusion on celebrities' privacy misspelled the first name of a divorce lawyer who has represented prominent clients. He is Raoul Felder, not Raul.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
