<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In French Race, 2 Vote-Getters Feel the Scorn Of an Also-Ran</title>
    <meta content="26france" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/world/europe/26france.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842984"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennhold, Katrin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bayrou, Francois</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Royal, Segolene</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bayrou, Francois</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Royal, Segolene</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E2DE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In French Race, 2 Vote-Getters Feel the Scorn Of an Also-Ran</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In French Race, 2 Rivals Feel Scorn of an Also-Ran</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATRIN BENNHOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennhold, Katrin</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Francois Bayrou, who won 18 percent of vote in first round of French presidential election, is being aggressively courted by two front-runners, Nicolas Sarkozy and Segolene Royal; he says he will acept Royal's invitation for public debate, but only if it is televised; such a debate would present unusual challenge for Royal, who must strike balance between preserving credibility with her core supporters and making concessions to Bayrou, whom she recently dismissed as rightist with no program; Bayrou's offer to debate Sarkozy was declined after Bayrou criticized him in particularly harsh terms at news conference; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The defeated ''third man'' in the race for the French presidency seems to be calling the shots ever since he lost on Sunday.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday the candidate, François Bayrou, who won 18 percent of the vote in the first round and has been aggressively courted by both the Socialist candidate, Ségolène Royal, and the conservative front-runner, Nicolas Sarkozy, held a one-and-a-half-hour news conference where he unleashed a torrent of criticism against both candidates and refused to endorse either of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>François Bayrou, the defeated “third man” in the race for the French presidency, is signaling that he intends to retain some influence in the contest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The defeated ''third man'' in the race for the French presidency seems to be calling the shots ever since he lost on Sunday.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday the candidate, François Bayrou, who won 18 percent of the vote in the first round and has been aggressively courted by both the Socialist candidate, Ségolène Royal, and the conservative front-runner, Nicolas Sarkozy, held a one-and-a-half-hour news conference where he unleashed a torrent of criticism against both candidates and refused to endorse either of them.</p>
        <p>In a sign that Mr. Bayrou intends to retain some influence in the contest, he said he would accept an invitation from Ms. Royal for a public debate before her May 6 runoff against Mr. Sarkozy.</p>
        <p>Ms. Royal reacted by proposing that Mr. Bayrou join her Friday when she meets the regional press, but appeared to back away when he insisted the debate be televised.</p>
        <p>If a debate occurs, it would present an unusual challenge -- and opportunity -- for Ms. Royal, who must strike a balance between preserving credibility with her core supporters and making concessions to Mr. Bayrou, whom as recently as Sunday she had dismissed as a rightist with no program. She would need to use the debate to reach his voters, even as she argued with him about her platform.</p>
        <p>Even an indirect endorsement from Mr. Bayrou could prove decisive in the race to succeed President Jacques Chirac. A poll by TNS Sofres that was published Wednesday in the daily Figaro showed support running at 51 percent for Mr. Sarkozy and 49 percent for Ms. Royal. Other polls taken since the first round on Sunday had given Mr. Sarkozy a wider lead, showing him with about 54 percent, to Ms. Royal's 46 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bayrou offered to hold a similar debate with Mr. Sarkozy, but Mr. Sarkozy, the former interior minister, declined after Mr. Bayrou criticized him in particularly harsh terms at a news conference.</p>
        <p>''Nicolas Sarkozy, through his proximity to business circles and media powers, through his taste for intimidation and threats, will concentrate power as it has never been before,'' Mr. Bayrou said. ''Through his temperament and the themes he has chosen to stir up, he risks aggravating the tears in the social fabric, notably through policies that give an advantage to the richest.''</p>
        <p>He said that Ms. Royal appeared ''to have better intentions as far as democracy is concerned,'' but that her economic program perpetuated the illusion that the state could take care of everything. That, he said, was ''the opposite of the orientations needed for our country and its economy to get back their creativity and equilibrium.''</p>
        <p>Asked how he would vote, Mr. Bayrou replied, ''At this point I don't know what I'll do, because what is striking is that the French are caught between two risks.'' But he said much could happen to clarify the positions of the candidates on important issues, ''notably after the debate that I will have with Madame Royal'' and a televised Sarkozy-Royal debate on May 2.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
