<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Pomp and Symbolism, Yeltsin Is Buried From a Cathedral</title>
    <meta content="26yeltsin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/world/europe/26yeltsin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070503T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwirtz, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George (Former Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Major, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Funerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Yeltsin, Boris N</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Pomp and Symbolism, Yeltsin Is Buried From a Cathedral</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Pomp and Symbolism, Yeltsin Is Buried From a Cathedral</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL SCHWIRTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwirtz, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boris N Yeltsin, Russia's first democratically elected president, is buried after somber, symbolic funeral service; Pres Vladimir V Putin and rest of Russia's political elite attend, as do current and former world leaders including former Presidents George Bush and Bill Clinton and former British Prime Min John Major; Kremlin-controlled media gives extensive, emotional coverage of proceedings; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boris N. Yeltsin, Russia's first democratically elected president, was buried Wednesday after a somber, symbolic funeral service attended by Russia's political elite, current and former world leaders, family and close friends.</p>
        <p>The service was held in full accordance with Orthodox Christian tradition in the ornate Christ the Savior Cathedral, which was destroyed by the Soviet government in 1931, the year of Mr. Yeltsin's birth, and reconstructed with his approval. It was the first time since the death of Czar Aleksandr III in 1894 that the Orthodox church officially presided over the funeral of a head of state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boris N. Yeltsin, Russia’s first democratically elected president, was buried Wednesday after a somber, symbolic funeral service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Boris N. Yeltsin, Russia's first democratically elected president, was buried Wednesday after a somber, symbolic funeral service attended by Russia's political elite, current and former world leaders, family and close friends.</p>
        <p>The service was held in full accordance with Orthodox Christian tradition in the ornate Christ the Savior Cathedral, which was destroyed by the Soviet government in 1931, the year of Mr. Yeltsin's birth, and reconstructed with his approval. It was the first time since the death of Czar Aleksandr III in 1894 that the Orthodox church officially presided over the funeral of a head of state.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin's open coffin lay beneath the cathedral's vast frescoed dome, draped with the Russia tricolor. Clerics intoned prayers over the body, as a teary-eyed Naina I. Yeltsin, Mr. Yeltsin's widow, and his two daughters looked on.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin, who helped bring down the Soviet Union as an opposition leader and then served nine tumultuous years as Russia's president, died Monday of heart failure at a hospital in Moscow. He was 76.</p>
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin attended the funeral, along with most members of the government, including the two first deputy prime ministers (and potential successors), Sergei B. Ivanov and Dmitry A. Medvedev.</p>
        <p>A number of foreign dignitaries were present, including former Presidents George Bush and Bill Clinton, and John Major, the former British prime minister.</p>
        <p>After the ceremony, Mr. Yeltsin's body was taken under military guard to the Novodevichy Cemetery. There, to the strains of the Soviet national anthem -- which Mr. Yeltsin had retired but Mr. Putin quickly restored -- he was interred.</p>
        <p>At the cemetery, he will lie in the company of other mavericks, cultural and political, including the Soviet writers Mikhail A. Bulgakov and Boris L. Pasternak, and Nikita S. Khrushchev, the Soviet leader who, like Mr. Yeltsin, left office humbled and with a taint of official shame.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin, whom Mr. Yeltsin appointed as head of state when he resigned on New Year's Eve in 1999, declared Wednesday an official day of mourning, and in a sign of the Kremlin's increasing grip on the media, ordered television stations to cancel entertainment programs and to broadcast the funeral.</p>
        <p>Beginning Tuesday afternoon, thousands of Russians and foreigners came to the cathedral to pay their respects to Mr. Yeltsin.</p>
        <p>Awaiting entrance to the cathedral on Tuesday was Kirill B. Mikhailov. In August 1991, at the age of 18, Mr. Mikhailov spent three days outside the White House in Moscow, supporting Mr. Yeltsin's drive against the organizers of a coup to oust the Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>''He rid us of Communism,'' Mr. Mikhailov said of Mr. Yeltsin. ''He gave us freedom.''</p>
        <p>But he will also be remembered as the man who, after his initial triumph over the Soviet Union, led Russia into a corrupt, chaotic and increasingly lawless era.</p>
        <p>''Yeltsin was the embodiment of a new freedom, a new spirit,'' said Vera A. Colman, who also came to say goodbye. ''Then began a period of banditry.''</p>
        <p>His order to shell the Communist-controlled Parliament in 1993, his decision to invade Chechnya in 1994, the rise of a rapacious oligarchy, and the financial collapse in 1998 weakened him and marred his legacy.</p>
        <p>In a sign that political scars from the 1990s have yet to heal, members of the Communist Party, Mr. Yeltsin's main political opponents during his presidency, refused to rise during a moment of silence before the start of Wednesday's session at Parliament. Some of the party's deputies walked out.</p>
        <p>President Putin's Kremlin, which has been strongly critical of the Yeltsin era, has adopted a respectful, if reserved, tone.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a Kremlin reception after the funeral, Mr. Putin said Mr. Yeltsin had inspired historic changes in Russia and had transformed the world. ''Boris Nikolayevich was able to do this without once retreating or deviating from or betraying the people's choice or his own conscience,'' Mr. Putin said.</p>
        <p>The Kremlin-controlled media gave extensive, emotional, even intimate coverage of the proceedings. At the cemetery, state television showed Mrs. Yeltsin approach her husband's open coffin, pat his head and give him a last kiss.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 3, 2007, Thursday  An article last Thursday about the burial of Boris N. Yeltsin, Russia's first democratically elected president, at Novodevichy Cemetery, erroneously included a writer among other Russian notables interred there. Boris L. Pasternak is buried in a writers' village in Peredelkino.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 3, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article last Thursday about the burial of Boris N. Yeltsin, Russia's first democratically elected president, at Novodevichy Cemetery, erroneously included a writer among other Russian notables interred there. Boris L. Pasternak is buried in a writers' village in Peredelkino.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
