<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Triathlon Finds A Fountain of Youth</title>
    <meta content="26Fitness" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/fashion/26Fitness.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Triathlon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Triathlon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0D6143EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Triathlon Finds A Fountain of Youth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Triathlon Finds a Fountain of Youth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY GLIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glier, Ray</byline>
      <dateline>TUSCALOOSA, Ala.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE swimmers burst out of the water to become cyclists, and it looked like any triathlon transition until the athletes started peeling off their generic black wet suits to reveal bright school colors.</p>
        <p>As fans -- mostly family and friends -- recognized the hues of the bike-and-run uniforms, the cheering started. The blue and orange of the University of Florida prompted yells of ''Go Gators.'' The blue and gold of the Navy prompted (what else?) ''Go Navy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once the domain of the middle-aged, the triathlon has taken off on campus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE swimmers burst out of the water to become cyclists, and it looked like any triathlon transition until the athletes started peeling off their generic black wet suits to reveal bright school colors.</p>
        <p>As fans -- mostly family and friends -- recognized the hues of the bike-and-run uniforms, the cheering started. The blue and orange of the University of Florida prompted yells of ''Go Gators.'' The blue and gold of the Navy prompted (what else?) ''Go Navy.''</p>
        <p>The event, the 2007 Collegiate National Championships, was a yardstick for triathlon growth in the United States. Because triathlon is a club sport on the college level, it does not fall under the umbrella of the National Collegiate Athletic Association. But though a sport on the margin on campus, the national championships, on April 21, drew 1,000 competitors from 77 institutions. That is almost double the draw at the 2005 championship, which featured 555 competitors from 58 schools.</p>
        <p>The available spots for the 2007 contest were filled in February, and some clubs, with as many as 100 active members, had to hold tryouts for the official team traveling to the championship, which the Navy won.</p>
        <p>''We thought collegiate triathlon had potential, but we didn't think it would double in numbers in just two years,'' said Tim Yount, the vice president for communications for USA Triathlon, the governing body of the sport. ''Once we got the support of coaches and team leaders from schools around the country, we were able to put on some good events to draw people into the sport.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, triathlon has been regarded as the domain of 35- to 44-year-old overachievers. But at the USA Triathlon dinner for athletes the night before the collegiate championships, the pasta ran out. It could have been poor planning, but the culprit also could have been the sudden popularity of the sport among the 18- to 24-year-old demographic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yount said universities and colleges fielded 95 club triathlon teams last year, up from 80 in 2005.</p>
        <p>Still, triathlon is not to be confused with mega-sports on campus like football or basketball.</p>
        <p>Last October, when Florida's football team traveled to Jacksonville to play the University of Georgia, the Gators stayed in a luxury hotel the night before the game. The night before he won the national triathlon men's title, Kevin Collington, a junior at the university, and the other 43 members of the Gators team slept in tents at a campground.</p>
        <p>Such is the life of even the most talented college triathletes. They wear uniforms emblazoned with their school colors (for which they pay $85 to $100 each), but they remain second-class citizens on campus.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there is going to be a crowd waiting for me when I get back to Gainesville like there was for the football and basketball teams after they won national titles,'' said Mr. Collington, a mechanical engineering major.</p>
        <p>He shrugged. ''I see a lot of those guys on the basketball team when I run around the coliseum, and they wave, but they think I'm on the track team,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Most college triathlon teams can afford to stay in hotels for meets; they just have to raise most of the money themselves. The night before the triathlon championships, the team from the University of California, Santa Barbara, slept four to a room in a Hampton Inn in Bessemer, Ala., an hour from the Tuscaloosa start point. Except for Matt Elke, a graduate student. He slept in a van near the race start to make sure the bikes were not stolen. To cover expenses, the team held a fund-raiser -- a triathlon, of course. The event attracted 500 participants at $40 each.</p>
        <p>Santa Barbara's coach, Mateo Mercur, 33, is paid $24,000 a year by the team members out of dues and other fund-raisers; he also has a private training business.</p>
        <p>Some triathlon club teams do receive money through student fees. This year, the University of Alabama started a triathlon club, and received $1,200 for its 42 members, said Kendrick Gibson, the club's president.</p>
        <p>The team, called, of course, the Crimson Tide, is working through a probationary period; the university requires that members do a certain number of hours of community service and keep a log of volunteer hours. As the club matures, the university will contribute more.</p>
        <p>Even established triathlon teams scramble for money. Kirk Nelson, the coach at the University of Colorado, regarded as one of the superpowers in college triathlon, said his athletes work in the concession stands at football games. Triathletes also send ''beg letters'' soliciting donations.</p>
        <p>Yet, with three sports to master between classes, many college triathletes don't train any less hard than varsity sportsmen.</p>
        <p>Josh Matter, who was on the dean's list for chemical engineering at Michigan State, said he practices his sports roughly 20 hours a week. Varsity athletes, according to N.C.A.A. regulations, are allowed to practice 20 hours a week at most.</p>
        <p>The difference between the Haves and the Have Nots could not have been more vivid last Saturday at the finish line on the grassy quadrangle of the University of Alabama campus.</p>
        <p>As the triathletes walked off their muscle burn munching a banana or bagel, two men in crisp white shirts and black aprons hoisted platters of food on their shoulders and snaked through their midst. They were caterers taking food to the football fans tailgating on the quad before the spring football game.</p>
        <p>The football game, a mere scrimmage, drew more than 92,000 people, some of whom walked to the finish line to gawk at the multisport stars.</p>
        <p>''They don't know what to make of us,'' said Lauren Helton, a member of the Crimson Tide triathlon team. ''Maybe they're mad we're taking up their tailgate space.''</p>
        <p>The surge in the number of college triathletes has inspired a debate about whether triathlon should become an N.C.A.A. sport, or remain a club enterprise governed by individual schools and the national triathlon association.</p>
        <p>Fifty institutions would have to agree to sponsor triathlon on the varsity level before N.C.A.A. member schools would be able to vote on adding it as a sport, said Gail Dent, an N.C.A.A spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>At first glance, it would seem that athletes would prefer varsity status because it means official university recognition and funding.</p>
        <p>But for graduate students now competing on club teams, varsity status may be unwelcome. Under N.C.A.A. rules, many graduate students would not be eligible to compete if triathlon becomes a varsity sport. Some would have used up their four years of eligibility and others would be too old.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't be here,'' said Dave Holder, 25, who is studying medicine at Ohio State. ''The majority of the graduates who are in this race don't want varsity status because we couldn't compete for a national championship.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson, the Colorado coach, worried that going varsity would mean devoting his time to a handful of recruits. ''We have 130 paid members of our club,'' he said. ''I can't imagine, as a varsity sport, limiting our team to 10 or 15 athletes because of scholarship requirements.''</p>
        <p>Others worry that male triathletes would suffer. ''You would see the men's club teams disappear,'' said Mr. Collington of Florida. ''The women would be getting all the money because of Title IX.''</p>
        <p>On the other side of the argument, Ms. Helton, a freshman at Alabama, said the Crimson Tide triathlon team would welcome varsity status because it means more financial support.</p>
        <p>''The school could pay for entry fees, maybe some coaching,'' Ms. Helton said.</p>
        <p>The national triathlon association is lobbying the N.C.A.A. to include triathlon as a varsity sport, Mr. Yount said. Varsity status would create scholarship opportunities for triathletes, he said.</p>
        <p>''The N.C.A.A. is going to have to look at us because of how rapidly triathlon is expanding,'' Mr. Yount said. ''Triathlon has outlived its life as a club sport and we need to take that next step.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
