<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alan Ball, 61, a Key Member Of England's Only Cup Winner</title>
    <meta content="26BALL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Obituaries; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/soccer/26BALL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Alan Ball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Ball, Alan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alan Ball, 61, a Key Member Of England's Only Cup Winner</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Alan Ball, 61, a Key Member of England’s Only Cup Winner, Is Dead</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alan Ball, a crafty 5-foot-6 soccer midfielder who at 21 was the youngest member of the team that won England its only World Cup, in 1966, died yesterday in Warsash, Hampshire. He was 61.</p>
        <p>Ball collapsed in his garden during the night while trying to put out a compost heap fire and apparently died of a heart attack, his son, Jimmy, told The Associated Press.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alan Ball was a crafty 5-foot-6 soccer midfielder who at 21 was the youngest member of the team that won England its only World Cup in 1966.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alan Ball, a crafty 5-foot-6 soccer midfielder who at 21 was the youngest member of the team that won England its only World Cup, in 1966, died yesterday in Warsash, Hampshire. He was 61.</p>
        <p>Ball collapsed in his garden during the night while trying to put out a compost heap fire and apparently died of a heart attack, his son, Jimmy, told The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>The 1966 squad, called the Wingless Wonders, was the host team when it defeated West Germany, 4-2 after extra time, in the final.</p>
        <p>''He was probably the best player on that day, and if it had not been for his impact, the result could have been totally different,'' Sir Bobby Charlton, a member of the World Cup-winning team, told the BBC. ''He was a sensational little player with great touch and great vision. He had great close control, and although he wasn't a fast player, he didn't need to be. He could see things clearly and always made the right decisions.''</p>
        <p>Ball also played for his country in the 1970 World Cup in Mexico. He made 72 international appearances for England, scoring eight goals.</p>
        <p>He played for some of the top professional teams in England during a career that lasted more than 20 years. He signed first with Blackpool after his father, Alan Sr., who was also a professional soccer player, asked an old friend to give his son a tryout. Ball made his professional debut in August 1962 and went on to score 40 goals for Blackpool over four seasons.</p>
        <p>He moved to Everton from 1966 to 1971, making 208 appearances and scoring 66 goals; then Arsenal from 1971 to 1976 (177 games, 45 goals) and Southampton for two seasons (132 games, 9 goals).</p>
        <p>He crossed the Atlantic in 1978 and played three seasons for the Philadelphia Fury and the Vancouver Whitecaps in the North American Soccer League.</p>
        <p>After his playing career, Ball managed seven English clubs, including the bitter rivals Southampton and Portsmouth, from 1980 to 1999. For his service to the game, Queen Elizabeth II made Ball a Member of the British Empire in 2000.</p>
        <p>England's players will honor Ball by wearing a black armbands in their first game at the new Wembley Stadium in London, a friendly match against Brazil on June 1.</p>
        <p>Besides his son, Jimmy, his survivors include two daughters, Mandy Byrne and Keely Allan, and three grandchildren. His wife of more than 36 years, Lesley, died in May 2004.</p>
        <p>In May 2005, Ball put up for auction his World Cup winners' medal and other items to raise money for his family. They sold for $280,000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
