<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Collaboration Recalls An Isolated Rural America</title>
    <meta content="26skag" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/arts/music/26skag.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842951"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Kentucky Thunder</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Skaggs, Ricky</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hornsby, Bruce</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E1DF153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Collaboration Recalls An Isolated Rural America</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Collaboration Recalls an Isolated Rural America</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The music headed for the hills when Ricky Skaggs and Bruce Hornsby led Mr. Skaggs's band, Kentucky Thunder, at the New York Society for Ethical Culture auditorium on Tuesday night. Those hills would be the increasingly mythic Appalachians that spawned old-timey and bluegrass music, a place where fiddlers held forth on porches and string bands played Saturday-night barn dances -- not where satellite dishes pick up ''American Idol'' and Country Music Television.</p>
        <p>Whether they were playing Mr. Hornsby's songs or reworking Bill Monroe's repertory, the arrangements often reached back to Celtic drones and modal fiddle tunes, the sounds of an isolated rural America. Kentucky Thunder is a string band, with acoustic instruments and no drums; it has two more guitarists than a standard bluegrass lineup, but it still prizes classic high vocal harmonies and flashes of virtuoso picking. With Mr. Hornsby on piano, another Americana also peeked in: the polytonality of Aaron Copland and of modal jazz harmony, which happens to dovetail with those Celtic drones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The music headed for the hills when Ricky Skaggs and Bruce Hornsby led Mr. Skaggs’s band, Kentucky Thunder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The music headed for the hills when Ricky Skaggs and Bruce Hornsby led Mr. Skaggs's band, Kentucky Thunder, at the New York Society for Ethical Culture auditorium on Tuesday night. Those hills would be the increasingly mythic Appalachians that spawned old-timey and bluegrass music, a place where fiddlers held forth on porches and string bands played Saturday-night barn dances -- not where satellite dishes pick up ''American Idol'' and Country Music Television.</p>
        <p>Whether they were playing Mr. Hornsby's songs or reworking Bill Monroe's repertory, the arrangements often reached back to Celtic drones and modal fiddle tunes, the sounds of an isolated rural America. Kentucky Thunder is a string band, with acoustic instruments and no drums; it has two more guitarists than a standard bluegrass lineup, but it still prizes classic high vocal harmonies and flashes of virtuoso picking. With Mr. Hornsby on piano, another Americana also peeked in: the polytonality of Aaron Copland and of modal jazz harmony, which happens to dovetail with those Celtic drones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Skaggs and Mr. Hornsby collaborated on an album, ''Ricky Skaggs &amp; Bruce Hornsby'' (Sony Legacy), that brings Mr. Hornsby's ear to Kentucky Thunder's music. On Tuesday night, trading off lead vocals in most songs, they played through the album's lineup and added the bluegrass standard ''Uncle Pen'' and Mr. Hornsby's well-known songs like ''The Way It Is'' and ''The End of the Innocence.''</p>
        <p>Instead of upbeat, three-chord bluegrass, Mr. Hornsby and Mr. Skaggs concentrated on the modal harmonies and stoic, storytelling lyrics of mountain ballads and their latter-day descendants. Their version of Mr. Hornsby's ''Mandolin Rain'' turned the song (which mentions listening to a bluegrass band) into a minor-key reminiscence. Mr. Skaggs had introduced Mr. Hornsby to old songs like Roscoe Holcomb's eerie, keening, drone-based ''Across the Rocky Mountains,'' about a lover who goes to war.</p>
        <p>The concert had little of the gospel proselytizing that sometimes fills Mr. Skaggs's own efforts -- just one song, ''Come On Out,'' which also has an Appalachian-flavored melody and foreboding imagery: ''You're going to run out of ammo/Empty shells just like you.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hornsby, who is fluent in piano idioms from gospel to modern jazz, aligned his solos with bluegrass timing -- fast, twinkling, unsyncopated lines, sometimes playing parallel to Andy Leftwich's fiddle parts -- but also, at some points, refracted the harmonies through dissonance-laced jazz chords. Mr. Skaggs, who plays all sorts of stringed instruments, usually stuck to mandolin, playing solos that darted and twanged at sometimes dizzying speed or trading breaks with Mr. Leftwich, Cody Kilby on guitar and Jim Mills on banjo. They gently stretched the mountain-music idiom in songs like ''Stubb,'' which distantly hints at Eastern music, and ''Gulf of Mexico Fishing Boat Blues,'' with a chorus in odd meter, 5/4 time.</p>
        <p>They played the album's novelty song: an upbeat, bluegrass remake of Rick James's ''Super Freak'' that almost made its kinky sex scenarios sound wholesome. But most of the concert conjured a more thoughtful place, a neverland where rural purity embraces modern convolutions.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
