<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alone, Awash, Then Borne Aloft by Helping Hands</title>
    <meta content="26jane" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/garden/26jane.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Close to Home"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Disasters</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hastings-on-Hudson (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Disasters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DF153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alone, Awash, Then Borne Aloft by Helping Hands</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Alone, Awash, Then Borne Aloft by Helping Hands</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>HASTINGS-ON-HUDSON, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane Gross Close to Home column on local handymen in Hastings-on-Hudson, NY, who not only do home repairs and renovations but are also good neighbors, making sure everyone is safe and taken care of during floods and other disasters; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO be a spinster in the suburbs, especially one who lives in a 150-year-old house, is too osteoporotic to climb ladders and doesn't have a toolbox, is to appreciate old-fashioned chivalry, small-town style.</p>
        <p>Through 10 years of basement floods, fallen tree limbs, rotting fences and jammed windows, I've enjoyed the tender ministrations of a group of local tradesmen (and, yes, all are men), who are second- or third-generation villagers. Like many of my neighbors, I have been their loyal customer for renovations and home repairs, because these guys finish jobs on schedule and recall off the tops of their heads the age of a hot-water heater or a porch roof because they probably did the work themselves. They know the location of our hide-a-keys and we know their home telephone numbers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is what good men do: They work hard, and help out their women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO be a spinster in the suburbs, especially one who lives in a 150-year-old house, is too osteoporotic to climb ladders and doesn't have a toolbox, is to appreciate old-fashioned chivalry, small-town style.</p>
        <p>Through 10 years of basement floods, fallen tree limbs, rotting fences and jammed windows, I've enjoyed the tender ministrations of a group of local tradesmen (and, yes, all are men), who are second- or third-generation villagers. Like many of my neighbors, I have been their loyal customer for renovations and home repairs, because these guys finish jobs on schedule and recall off the tops of their heads the age of a hot-water heater or a porch roof because they probably did the work themselves. They know the location of our hide-a-keys and we know their home telephone numbers.</p>
        <p>But I often feel less like their customer than a damsel in distress -- most recently last week, when they saw me through a northeaster that left my basement knee deep in a soup of raw sewage and groundwater. Just as they did after Hurricane Floyd in 1999, they arrived en masse, with industrial-size pumps, sandbags, hip-waders and soothing words as the flood, not once but three times, made its way up the basement steps toward my living room.</p>
        <p>This time I was not as dumbstruck by their attention: pumping, coming back to check up on me, pumping some more, checking up on me again and so on into the wee hours of a Sunday night and then through the day on Monday. In between visits, they called. Was I O.K.? Had the water level dropped enough to relight the furnace? If the rain stopped and the water receded, I was to let them know, no matter how late. They didn't want me in a cold house until morning.</p>
        <p>When I first moved into this old carriage house in 1997, after decades in Manhattan and California, I wondered about the motives of these attentive men, even though I am decades older than most of them and nothing special to look at.</p>
        <p>Then I thought they must pity me, left to shovel my own snow while women up and down the street were inside making grilled cheese sandwiches and hot cocoa for the men of the house, as my mother and I once did for my father and brother. Most of my neighbors have husbands to deal with the heavy work of homeownership (although the tradesmen tell me that the busiest day of the week for them is Monday, when they get calls from wives whose helpmates couldn't finish what they started on Sunday, or managed to turn a small problem into a big one).</p>
        <p>But when I listened to these guys talk about their wives, sisters and mothers, I realized something that hadn't occurred to me before. In their world, good men look after their women. They open doors and carry heavy packages. They change the oil in the car and label the circuit breakers.</p>
        <p>They work hard -- at the local hardware store or the Department of Public Works, or running landscaping or plumbing businesses -- so their wives can stay home with the children, their sisters can feel safe even if they marry scoundrels and their mothers know they'll want for nothing in old age. In what little free time they have, many of them serve as volunteer firemen or E.M.T.'s. What they do for me, the lady all by herself in an old house, is exactly what they'd do for their female kin if, God forbid, they wound up alone.</p>
        <p>Sexist? I suppose. But also welcome. The contractor comes by if I can't open a window. The painter changes light bulbs in outdoor spotlights beyond my reach. The auto mechanic jumps my battery every time I leave a map light on overnight. No big deal, all of them tell me. They were in the neighborhood anyway. Pay them for five minutes of work? Don't be ridiculous.</p>
        <p>The lawn guy, who plows driveways in the winter, kept me shoveled out whether I asked for help or not the winter when my mother's health was failing and midnight runs to the emergency room were routine. When I needed a new fence, he rounded up a few friends and put it up on consecutive Sundays. When a hot tub couldn't be repaired, he hatcheted it to pieces and carted it away.</p>
        <p>Last week, when the northeaster sent the Saw Mill River spilling over its banks and overwhelmed the village drainage system, sewage backed up into houses, and a derelict toilet in my basement became a water cannon.</p>
        <p>The first round of pumping was done by the volunteer firemen, who arrived at my door with sirens wailing and lights flashing. The second round was done by pretty much the same gang, this time in civilian clothes, driving their own trucks but possessed of pumps as impressive in size and suction as the fire department's. The third round brought a few extras, armed with sandbags to block yet another onslaught from the sewage system.</p>
        <p>The sandbags remain. Someone will come back for them. Someone else will remove and cap the toilet. Another of these able and kind men will install a valve in the sewer line so water can flow in only one direction. One of them is getting rid of the ruined washer and dryer, and ordering and delivering new ones. Everything here is taken care of, except for the power-washing and disinfection of the basement, but that part of the job must be done by a cleaning service selected by my insurance company.</p>
        <p>Still, the phone rings daily. My posse of protectors want me to know that the insurance adjuster has all the estimates. They think I should replace the water heater, which was coddled back into operation but probably not for long. They suggest I stay out of the basement until it's disinfected. But if I must go down there, I'm to immediately clean my hands and feet with Clorox. If I need some, they'll be happy to drop it off.</p>
        <p>Close to Home</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
