<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haunted by That Troublemaker in the Attic</title>
    <meta content="26eyre" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/theater/reviews/26eyre.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Acting Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zinoman, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccallum, Davis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cabell, Hannah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kawa, Carie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jane Eyre (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Acting Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Teale, Polly</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bronte, Charlotte</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Jane Eyre (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DF153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="457" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haunted by That Troublemaker in the Attic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Haunted by That Troublemaker in the Attic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON ZINOMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinoman, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jason Zinoman reviews Acting Company production of Jane Eyre, directed by Davis McCallum; Hannah Cabell and Carie Kawa star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As much as you would like to ignore her, there's just no getting around the mad lady in the attic.</p>
        <p>One of the most unforgettable and controversial figures in Charlotte Brontë's ''Jane Eyre,'' Bertha Mason haunts the title character, as well as the many adaptors of the 1847 novel who struggle to make sense of this thinly drawn Jamaican who seems to be a symbol of Victorian confinement and gothic horror as much as a real person.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Acting Company’s engaging new version of “Jane Eyre” is receiving a brisk, persuasively acted production.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As much as you would like to ignore her, there's just no getting around the mad lady in the attic.</p>
        <p>One of the most unforgettable and controversial figures in Charlotte Brontë's ''Jane Eyre,'' Bertha Mason haunts the title character, as well as the many adaptors of the 1847 novel who struggle to make sense of this thinly drawn Jamaican who seems to be a symbol of Victorian confinement and gothic horror as much as a real person.</p>
        <p>Jean Rhys's ''Wide Sargasso Sea,'' a prequel of sorts, went so far as to imagine a back story for Bertha, but the Acting Company's engaging new version of ''Jane Eyre'' keeps her as an evocative mystery. From the beginning of the play, which is staged as a kind of psychological drama by Davis McCallum, Bertha (Carie Kawa) stands right alongside Jane, a figment of her fevered imagination. The women -- one rational, modest and in control; the other wild, sexual and almost demonic -- make up a portrait of a mind at war with itself.</p>
        <p>At times this conceit appears overly literal, but it's easily forgiven since this brisk, persuasively acted production is presented with little fuss. The clunky transitions and excess exposition that are the hallmark of page-to-stage translations are mercifully absent. Faithful without being reverent, it reminds audiences of the dark undertones of this novel, and in that sense this ''Jane Eyre'' provides a counterpoint to the bloated Broadway musical from 2000 and the many chest-heaving screen versions that cast glamorous stars as the quintessential plain Jane.</p>
        <p>Polly Teale's adaptation prunes the novel to its essence: sometimes, in the scenes at school, for instance, the action flies by too fast to register emotionally. But Mr. McCallum slows down at the right places, as in the development of the central relationship between Jane and Mr. Rochester at the end of Act I. As Jane, Hannah Cabell, whose alert, intelligent eyes and flushed cheeks communicate more than a dozen soliloquies, delivers a marvelously contained performance of an almost pathologically restrained woman who refuses to let down her guard.</p>
        <p>And why would she? With tousled hair, Christopher Oden's overripe Mr. Rochester comes off as a bit of an infantile rogue, and even in the most heated moments you never forget that he is twice her age. Fluidly staged like a dream on an empty black stage interrupted with slivers of light, this ''Jane Eyre'' is a romance without an overly romantic view of the world. ''Come out of the shadows,'' Mr. Rochester urges Jane, but in this production it's clear that that is easier said than done.</p>
        <p>''Jane Eyre'' is at the Baruch Performing Arts Center's Nagelberg Theater, 55 Lexington Avenue, at 25th Street, (212) 279-4200, through May 5.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
