<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Terrorists Reel In a Pawn From Small-Town Iraq</title>
    <meta content="26masl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/books/26masl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Khadra, Yasmina</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Sirens of Baghdad, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EFD6143EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Terrorists Reel In a Pawn From Small-Town Iraq</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Terrorists Reel in a Pawn From Small-Town Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Sirens of Baghdad  By Yasmina Khadra  307 pages. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $19.95.</p>
        <p>''The Sirens of Baghdad'' completes Yasmina Khadra's trilogy of histrionic, disturbing novels about Islamic fundamentalism. All three of these books (the other two are ''The Swallows of Kabul'' and ''The Attack'') owe as much of their impact to the brutal realities they crystallize as they do to the author's narrative talents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“The Sirens of Baghdad” completes Yasmina Khadra’s trilogy of histrionic, disturbing novels about Islamic fundamentalism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Sirens of Baghdad  By Yasmina Khadra  307 pages. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $19.95.</p>
        <p>''The Sirens of Baghdad'' completes Yasmina Khadra's trilogy of histrionic, disturbing novels about Islamic fundamentalism. All three of these books (the other two are ''The Swallows of Kabul'' and ''The Attack'') owe as much of their impact to the brutal realities they crystallize as they do to the author's narrative talents.</p>
        <p>The author likes to adopt the perspective of a naïve figure who is suddenly forced to understand war. (Yasmina Khadra is a female pseudonym for a former Algerian army officer, Mohammed Moulessehoul, who lives in France and whose work has once again been overheatedly translated by John Cullen.) In this case, the unworldly narrator is a young man of about 20 who comes from a small, sheltered Iraqi village. He left this place, Kafr Karam, to begin his university education in Baghdad, but then was sent back home because of the American invasion.</p>
        <p>As the novel begins he is in Beirut, for reasons that will take a while to explain. First, this book must flash back to describe the wartime deterioration of life in Kafr Karam, step by step and outrage by outrage. Though the narrator is a trusting, open-minded soul, he absorbs the village venting, which is bitter but not unexpected. ''He was a monster, yes, but he was our monster,'' one speaker says of Saddam Hussein. ''Look what they've made of our country: hell on earth,'' he adds.</p>
        <p>A philosophy professor, also party to this discussion at the local barbershop, adds that ''the world is run by the forces of international finance, for which peace is equivalent to layoffs,'' and that ''bringing Iraq to its knees would make it possible for Israel to dominate the Middle East.'' As for hope in this bleak region, ''dreams serve no purpose when all horizons are bare.''</p>
        <p>''The Sirens of Baghdad,'' with its double-edged title referring to both Baghdad's allure and its state of crisis, then provides stark illustrations of its ideological arguments. The village's simple-minded boy, ''a pure and innocent creature closer to the Lord than the saints,'' is mowed down by goonlike American soldiers, one of them literally foaming at the mouth. A joyous local wedding (''at last we could look forward to a happy event that would compensate for the chronic emptiness of our daily lives!'') becomes a bloodbath when it is hit by a missile.</p>
        <p>''And then one night, the sky fell in on me again,'' the young man tells the reader. In the most monstrous outrage of all, he is forced to see his father left helpless and half-naked after a raid by ''those bleating, dim-witted cowboys,'' a group of thuggish G.I.'s. ''That sight was the edge of an abyss,'' he writes of being forced to gaze upon his father's genitals. ''And beyond it, there was nothing but the infinite void, an interminable fall, nothingness.'' As a result, ''I was swept up in a tornado and tossed from one tumult to another, caught in a waking nightmare like a sleepwalker assailed by poltergeists.'' And: ''I opened my mouth, but all that came out was something that sounded like a wild beast's death rattle.''</p>
        <p>The cumulative effect of these events turns the narrator into a numb yet still melodramatic automaton, ready to be used by the forces of terrorism and vengeance. ''Such a smooth transition!'' he says. ''I had gone to bed a docile, courteous boy, and I'd awakened with an inextinguishable rage lodged in my very flesh.'' That anger becomes ''all that remained to me in this false, unjust, arid and cruel life.'' He come to think that ''men are pathetic, narrow creatures, blood brothers of Sisyphus, built for suffering; their vocation is to undergo life until death ensues.'' That last outburst offers at least some idea of why this author is sometimes compared to Camus.</p>
        <p>As the rest of the novel propels its protagonist toward becoming a ''Manchurian Candidate''-style pawn in the terrorists' game, it remains heavy-handed. ''Goodbye, Maarwan! We'll meet again in heaven'' is not considered a self-explanatory farewell. The narrator must spell out the fact that Maarwan is a suicide bomber.</p>
        <p>The terrorist half of this book offers a visceral illustration of the difference between suspense and surprise. Suspense is there: ''The Sirens of Baghdad'' is nerve-racking despite its excess verbiage. And it shows real momentum as it propels its main character toward ''the most important revolutionary mission undertaken since man learned to stiffen his spine!'' But it remains essentially unsurprising until a final twist affects its outcome. The documentary-style details of this story offer all too familiar, credible illustrations of what real terrorists do and say.</p>
        <p>If ''The Swallows of Kabul'' remains the most wrenching and imaginative book in this trilogy, ''The Attack'' now seems the most artificial and didactic. ''The Sirens of Baghdad'' falls somewhere in between, with a blunt story line that has real passion behind it. The author's ear for Iraqi despair, fury and violation is keen, even as he manipulates the book's ideological posturing to reflect different points of view. In the end, this cautionary tale sounds more like real history.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
