<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Enter This Door at the Risk of a Loss of Sanity</title>
    <meta content="26game" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/technology/26game.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1207" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Enter This Door at the Risk of a Loss of Sanity</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Enter This Door at the Risk of a Loss of Sanity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES HEROLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herold, Charles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Do you ever wonder why things look better with the skin off?'' It's a question that in real life would have you edging out of the room, especially when the guy goes on to say the bones are calling to him. But when it was asked in The Elder Scrolls IV: Shivering Isles, I thought, this is someone I need to have a chat with.</p>
        <p>Isles is an expansion pack from Bethesda Softworks for the action/role-playing game Elder Scrolls IV, which adds a single mysterious door in the middle of the original game's world. A guard stands by the door, not to keep people out but because adventurers who enter return as gibbering homicidal maniacs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Elder Scrolls IV: Shivering Isles adds a single mysterious door in the middle of the original game’s world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Do you ever wonder why things look better with the skin off?'' It's a question that in real life would have you edging out of the room, especially when the guy goes on to say the bones are calling to him. But when it was asked in The Elder Scrolls IV: Shivering Isles, I thought, this is someone I need to have a chat with.</p>
        <p>Isles is an expansion pack from Bethesda Softworks for the action/role-playing game Elder Scrolls IV, which adds a single mysterious door in the middle of the original game's world. A guard stands by the door, not to keep people out but because adventurers who enter return as gibbering homicidal maniacs.</p>
        <p>What sort of idiot would walk through a door at the risk of his own sanity? I walked through the door to find out.</p>
        <p>Shivering Isles is populated by an entertaining mix of paranoids, psychopaths and sociopaths ruled over by Sheogorath, the cheerfully murderous Prince of Madness. The prince's lands are divided into two provinces: the bright colorful Mania, and the dark, twisted Dementia.</p>
        <p>The two regions are nicely differentiated visually, with sunlight and color in Mania and storms and giant twisted trees in Dementia. Even flames burn differently; Dementia's fires are yellow-orange, Mania's bluish white.</p>
        <p>While Sheogorath's subjects fret about being watched or complain incessantly about the evilness of cats, the prince is more concerned with the coming of Graymarch, a kingdom-decimating event that occurs once every thousand years. Coincidentally, the player arrives just about a thousand years since the last one.</p>
        <p>Sheogorath promptly recruits the player to save his kingdom, which over the course of the game involves cutting keys out of the stomach of an invincible gatekeeper, assassinating royalty and leading troops into battle.</p>
        <p>The quests that make up the game vary in quality. Some are rather ingenious, as when you must explore a dungeon that can be entered only by taking an addictive substance that will ravage the player's health if not regularly ingested. And there is an intriguing side quest where you must help ghosts continuously reliving a lost battle to win it at last. But there are too many times where you simply have to go fetch some artifact in some dungeon, battling monsters with swords or magical staffs or creatures that you can summon into battle, and then go fetch something else.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, this is still a lot of fun because Elder Scrolls IV was a brilliant game and Isles stays very much in the spirit of the original. There are some fun new weapons, like a sword that becomes more powerful as it takes lives, and I was amused by the prince's rants like: ''The cat's out of the bag. Who puts cats in bags? Cats hate bags.''</p>
        <p>When not battling monsters, the player is asked to take on some unsavory tasks. At one point, the player becomes a grand inquisitor who uses torture to gain information. I was disappointed that the game didn't offer less evil alternatives; Elder Scrolls IV allowed players to decide how moral they wanted to be, but Isles just wants you to be bad.</p>
        <p>The game does ask the player to make choices, but they seem best decided by a coin toss, as there are no practical or moral reasons to choose a particular path. While a theme of duality runs through the game, it is more narrative conceit than game-play enhancement.</p>
        <p>While Isles lacks moral depth, Intelligent Systems' ingenious Super Paper Mario manages to show a great deal of depth while remaining paper thin.</p>
        <p>At first glance, Super Paper Mario looks like an old-fashioned two-dimensional arcade platformer as Mario the plumber jumps from platform to platform or bounces on monsters to vanquish them. But Mario has the ability to look at this two-dimensional world in three dimensions. Suddenly, Mario is looking down a hallway at monsters as thin as a slip of paper that he can casually walk by</p>
        <p>Seemingly solid platforms turn out to be several different platforms carefully arranged so that from a side view they appear as a single entity. Previously hidden passages are revealed in the floor or running off at right angles, and objects can be found behind paper-thin boulders.</p>
        <p>It's a brilliant idea that feels a little like conceptual art, a commentary on superficiality and hidden depth that is also a wonderful game-play mechanism.</p>
        <p>Like a lot of Mario games, this one begins as the villainous King Bowser kidnaps the lovely Princess Peach. Before Mario can save her, the crisis is interrupted by Count Bleck, a mysterious figure who randomly uses ''bleck'' as an adjective, adverb or noun and who is bent on destroying the universe.</p>
        <p>Mario soon learns that he is the prophesied hero of a book called The Light Prognosticus and the only one able to stop Count Bleck. Unless, of course, the true book is The Dark Prognosticus, in which case the universe is doomed. To find out which book is truly prophetic, Mario must find seven artifacts called Pure Hearts to counter Count Bleck's Chaos Heart.</p>
        <p>Mario is helped in this quest by Pixls, odd little creatures that tag along and let Mario blow things up or shrink himself to the size of a pea. He is also joined by companions with various skills; Princess Peach, for example, can use her parasol like a hang glider to bridge long gaps.</p>
        <p>Eighty percent of Super Paper Mario is wonderful, so it's a shame that the other 20 percent is so annoying. Every time Mario finds a Pure Heart he must return to the town of Flipside to attach it to a heart pillar. Pillars are distributed throughout Flipside, and finding them is a grind. In town you can also buy health and attack items, but if you want to get their full effect you will have to take them to a cook who will transform each item during a dull animation that you must sit through over and over again.</p>
        <p>At times the game goes out of its way to annoy the player, as when you must hit a series of floating blocks following a tiresome series of instructions or type out the word ''please'' over and over on a virtual keyboard. Parts of the game are remarkably tedious, like a series of easy duels that wears out its welcome by the first duel. The game also refuses to let you skip expository scenes you've already witnessed, which is particularly unfortunate since the story and dialogue are rather dull.</p>
        <p>While all this keeps Super Paper Mario from being a great game, the imaginative level design, clever ideas and varied locations still make it a very good one. And the central 3-D gimmick is endlessly amusing; it's fascinating to see what's beneath the surface. Which, to answer the question so elegantly posed at the beginning of this column, is why things look better with the skin off.</p>
        <p>THE ELDER SCROLLS IV: SHIVERING ISLES  Developed by Bethesda Game Studios and published by Bethesda Softworks and 2K for Windows XP and Xbox 360; for ages 17 and up; $29.99.</p>
        <p>SUPER PAPER MARIO  Developed by Intelligent Systems and published by Nintendo for the Wii; for all ages; $49.99.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
