<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Theater Holds a Hearing on Blair, Then Stages It</title>
    <meta content="26tric" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/theater/26tric.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (England)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Tricycle Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0DF153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Theater Holds a Hearing on Blair, Then Stages It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Theater Holds a Hearing on Blair, Then Stages It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The premise behind the political plays often presented by the 240-seat Tricycle Theater in North London is that complex events and situations can at times be understood better when dramatized onstage than when recounted as news in dailies and on television.</p>
        <p>With this in mind, the Tricycle's plays often re-enact excerpts from public inquiries into political controversies. In 2004, with ''Guantánamo: 'Honor Bound to Defend Freedom,' '' it investigated the plight of British citizens imprisoned at Guantánamo, using the words of their relatives, some freed prisoners and British and American officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Tricycle Theater in London has “indicted” Tony Blair for his handling of the war in Iraq in a new play, “Called to Account.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The premise behind the political plays often presented by the 240-seat Tricycle Theater in North London is that complex events and situations can at times be understood better when dramatized onstage than when recounted as news in dailies and on television.</p>
        <p>With this in mind, the Tricycle's plays often re-enact excerpts from public inquiries into political controversies. In 2004, with ''Guantánamo: 'Honor Bound to Defend Freedom,' '' it investigated the plight of British citizens imprisoned at Guantánamo, using the words of their relatives, some freed prisoners and British and American officials.</p>
        <p>The public and critical response to many of these tribunal and verbatim plays seems to have vindicated the theater's approach. Several of its productions have later been televised in Britain. ''Guantánamo'' transferred to the West End and was produced in New York.</p>
        <p>Now the Tricycle and its artistic director, Nicolas Kent, have gone a step further by creating their own event around an issue still high on the political agenda here. Did Prime Minister Tony Blair manipulate intelligence and lie to justify Britain's involvement in the American-led invasion of Iraq?</p>
        <p>The new play, which runs here through May 19, has been given an elaborate name that explains its purpose: ''Called to Account: The Indictment of Anthony Charles Lynton Blair for the Crime of Aggression Against Iraq -- A Hearing.''</p>
        <p>''We started from the position that there is a case to answer because there has not been a public or a parliamentary investigation into what happened,'' Mr. Kent explained. ''I felt that doing the play was necessary because none of us has been given answers as to why this war was undertaken in the name of the British people.''</p>
        <p>Like earlier Tricycle plays, ''Called to Account'' uses the real words of real people. But in this case, the theater organized the hearing that is the play's source material, naming two British lawyers, Philippe Sands and Julian Knowles, as prosecutor and defense counsel, respectively, and inviting 15 witnesses with direct experience of the run-up to the Iraq war to provide evidence behind closed doors.</p>
        <p>Some 30 hours of testimony were then edited down to a 130-minute play by Richard Norton-Taylor, a journalist at The Guardian of London, with actors playing the roles of the two lawyers and their assistants as well as 11 expert witnesses whose testimonies were selected.</p>
        <p>''This is not the trial of Tony Blair,'' Mr. Sands insisted. ''It is a preliminary process. It's looking at whether there is a case to answer and whether it should go further.''</p>
        <p>That said, given the unpopularity of the Iraq war in Britain as well as widespread public hostility toward Mr. Blair, who is expected to leave office in the coming weeks, it seemed unlikely that the prime minister would emerge unscathed in the play. For that reason, the Tricycle decided against asking the audience to vote on Mr. Blair's guilt or innocence at the end of the performance.</p>
        <p>In theatrical terms, with the performers doing little more than sitting behind desks and talking, this is not the stuff of visual drama. Yet as the witnesses file in and out, they gradually build a picture of the secret meetings and ambiguous documents that preceded Mr. Blair's decision to back the Bush administration's policy of regime change in Iraq.</p>
        <p>''What is impressive is the way the gravest of issues is handled with such forensic sobriety,'' Michael Billington, The Guardian's theater critic, wrote. ''No voices are raised. No one shouts 'war criminal.' We see a patient, detailed search for truth.''</p>
        <p>Clare Short, a former secretary of international development in Mr. Blair's cabinet, was perhaps the most contemptuous of the prime minister's maneuvering, saying that he used ''lies, half truths, deceit, hints'' when claiming ''nothing had been decided'' long after he had promised his support to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't sit down and say, 'I'm going to tell a lie here,' '' says Ms. Short, played by Diane Fletcher. ''He's so much kind of -- I can charm my way through this, I can, I can just sort of tell Clare this, or tell the Cabinet that, and get through it, and he thinks that's what politics is. He doesn't see it as lies, but I'm afraid it is lies.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sands, played by Thomas Wheatley, also concentrates on trying to find an explanation for why Britain's attorney general, Lord Goldsmith, questioned the legality of the war on March 7, 2003, and approved it 10 days later. ''I don't know why he changed his mind,'' says Sir Murray Stuart-Smith (William Hoyland), a senior British intelligence official, ''but he did change his mind.''</p>
        <p>Richard Perle, a former Reagan administration official who served as chairman of the Defense Policy Board Advisory Committee from 2001 to 2003, was called as a witness for the defense. And played here by Shane Rimmer, he reiterates the intelligence community's ''great conviction'' that Iraq possessed weapons of mass destruction.</p>
        <p>But perhaps most telling was his description of the inner workings of the Bush administration, which are, he says, ''unique in my experience in that the president is less in command of his administration that any president I have ever observed.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Perle went on: ''He's got a, he's had a method of operating in which he is the chief executive, and that he expects things to happen, and he doesn't superintend them very closely, and a significant number of people who are nominally working for him don't agree with him, don't work very hard to implement his policies and in some cases even work against him, and that was certainly true at the State Department. It was certainly true at the C.I.A.''</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Blair, it was left to Sir Michael Quinlan, a former top official at Britain's Defense Ministry, to explain how the prime minister could have described evidence of Iraq's weapons of mass destruction as ''extensive, detailed and authoritative.'' It was hard not to hear sarcasm in Sir Michael's response, delivered in the play by Mr. Hoyland. ''I'm sure there was not coldblooded, deliberate mendacity,'' he says.</p>
        <p>In a debate that followed Monday's performance, Sir Menzies Campbell, the leader of the opposition Liberal Democratic Party, offered a different explanation. ''Tony Blair is imbued with a sense of evangelism in foreign affairs,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And, in a way, that may have served as Mr. Blair's best defense. ''I think that a jury would conclude that the charge of the crime of aggression is not proven,'' Mr. Kent said of the play, ''but that Tony Blair is morally guilty.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
