<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After First Steps, Saudi Reformers See Efforts Stall</title>
    <meta content="26saudi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/world/middleeast/26saudi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070528T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fattah, Hassan M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Saudi Arabia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E3DE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After First Steps, Saudi Reformers See Efforts Stall</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Saudis’ First Steps, Efforts for Reform Stall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HASSAN M. FATTAH; Rasheed Abou Alsamh contributed reporting from Riyadh.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fattah, Hassan M</byline>
      <dateline>JIDDA, Saudi Arabia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic change is put on back burner in Saudi Arabia just two years after country holds its first elections; elections were for municipal councils, were held in small number of cities and only men could vote, but they were held at urging of Bush administration and hailed as emblems of change; Saudi advocates of such change attribute stalled effort to economic boom fueled by high oil prices and more aggressive regional foreign policy; government over past year has cracked down on advocates of change, placed restrictions on their meetings and even scrapped some long-promised initiatives; elected city councils have proved powerless in face of country's ingrained governmental bureaucracy and vague mandate; but some change has occurred; dreaded vice police force has been forced to tone itself down, and some of most overbearing restrictions on day-to-day life for women have eased, though they are still forbidden to do things most woment take for granted; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a scene to warm the heart of any democrat. Here in this autocratic kingdom, elected city councilmen vowed to stand up for poor fishermen and ask the government to ensure that a large section of seafront on which a new university is planned be left accessible to local residents.</p>
        <p>After an hour of vigorous discussion recently, Jidda's City Council actually passed a resolution calling for the waterfront to remain open to the people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recently the government has cracked down on advocates of change and scrapped some long-promised initiatives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a scene to warm the heart of any democrat. Here in this autocratic kingdom, elected city councilmen vowed to stand up for poor fishermen and ask the government to ensure that a large section of seafront on which a new university is planned be left accessible to local residents.</p>
        <p>After an hour of vigorous discussion recently, Jidda's City Council actually passed a resolution calling for the waterfront to remain open to the people.</p>
        <p>But there was a catch: The resolution is nonbinding, its wording will not be made public, and it is unlikely to have any impact on the government's plans.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, largely at the urging of the Bush administration, the first elections in Saudi history were held for municipal councils in a small number of cities, including Jidda, Riyadh and Mecca. Only men could vote and only half the members were elected, but still the elections were hailed as emblems of change.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, however, the councils are being dismissed as symbols of the opposite: political stagnation.</p>
        <p>''We thought all you do is call for elections and you're done,'' lamented Abdullah al-Otaibi, an advocate of political change who gave up and moved to Dubai last year to help open a research center. ''Now we know things won't work that easily.''</p>
        <p>There are many reasons that democratic change has been put on the back burner, including an economic boom fueled by high oil prices and a more aggressive regional foreign policy, Saudi advocates of such change say.</p>
        <p>''The curse of the oil money is that it has stopped all reforms,'' said Sulaiman al-Hattlan, editor in chief of Forbes Arabia, based in Dubai, and a Saudi advocate. ''The more money you have, the more arrogant you become, because you think you can implement anything your way.''</p>
        <p>Over the past year, the government has cracked down on advocates of change, placed restrictions on their meetings and even scrapped some long-promised initiatives. The city councils have proved powerless in the face of Saudi Arabia's ingrained governmental bureaucracy and a decidedly vague mandate. According to one council member, more than half the decisions made by the councils have not been carried out. Most of the others have been in support of the central government.</p>
        <p>''The people in the councils want to make you think that they're working, but ultimately they are powerless,'' said Bassim Alim, a prominent Jidda lawyer and an advocate of change. ''The rest is all for show,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It was not supposed to be this way.</p>
        <p>After 15 Saudis took part in the attacks of 9/11, and a wave of terrorism hit the kingdom itself from 2004 to 2005, many Saudis argued that stifling political and economic conditions here had turned Saudi Arabia into fertile ground for extremism.</p>
        <p>King Abdullah -- at the time, the crown prince -- set out on a campaign for change, spearheading national dialogues, beginning new programs and popularizing the language of reform. The environment reinvigorated campaigners throughout the country who began openly calling for political change.</p>
        <p>In 2005, the government held elections for new city council bodies, allowing for half the 14 members of each council to be elected by the local population and the rest to be appointed by the government.</p>
        <p>Some change has occurred. The country's dreaded vice police force has been forced to tone itself down, and women have seen some of the most overbearing restrictions on day-to-day life eased, though they are still forbidden to do things most women take for granted, like driving. King Abdullah has also put into effect an important constitutional change that provides for senior members of the royal family to elect a crown prince from among candidates named by the next king.</p>
        <p>Some laws pertaining to public gatherings and criminal procedures were also changed, Mr. Alim said. The city council elections, meanwhile, proved to be a symbolic step that has encouraged more Saudis to step forward and complain, council members say.</p>
        <p>Still, many political reform efforts have slowed considerably, if not come to a halt, advocates say. As the fruits of high oil prices flooded the country's coffers and allowed the government to reassert its position as a cradle-to-grave patron of its people, the sense of crisis has ebbed and the impetus for many changes has subsided, they say.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Saudi Arabia's newly assertive foreign policy, focused on quelling the Middle East's numerous crises while responding to Iran's encroachment into the region, has focused Saudis' attention outside their borders, further damping the impetus for change.</p>
        <p>Advocates for political change also point to a longstanding split within the royal family itself. Matrouk al-Falleh, a prominent Saudi change advocate in Riyadh, said he noticed the split after he and a group of his compatriots presented King Abdullah, then the crown prince, with a petition calling for a constitutional monarchy in early 2003. The prince encouraged the men, but two weeks later, Prince Naif, Saudi Arabia's mercurial interior minister, appeared to squelch the discussion, noting in an interview with the Kuwaiti newspaper Al Seyassa that the men had ''misunderstood Prince Abdullah.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Falleh said: ''The future of reform depends on the senior princes and how they deal with matters of state. As the older generation dies out and the number of newer princes and princesses grows, I see a diminishing cake for them to share. This will lead to further conflict over power and money in the near future.''</p>
        <p>In addition to all the internal dynamics, waning attention from the Bush administration for democratization has further damped interest in Western-style political change.</p>
        <p>Many Saudis have abandoned the change agenda, political analysts say, focusing instead on more easily attainable social goals, or simply jumping on the sectarian bandwagon and riding fears of Iran.</p>
        <p>Government officials still make a point of mentioning reform and praise change, but they uniformly emphasize that it must come slowly and gradually. In the meantime, security officials have grown less tolerant of calls for things like a constitutional monarchy and elections of the consultative Shura Council. In February, Saudi Arabia's security forces rounded up 10 men connected to the country's reform movement in two cities, Jidda and Medina, charging them with financing terrorism.</p>
        <p>Security officials said the men, whose names were not initially disclosed, were collecting money and smuggling it to ''suspicious bodies'' in Iraq. But a day later it emerged that at least three of the men signed a petition directed at the king calling for a new constitution based on Islamic law, curbs on the powers of the Interior Ministry, an election of members of the Shura Council and a more equitable allocation of Saudi Arabia's wealth and land.</p>
        <p>Shocked reform advocates saw the arrests as a signal of how low their fortunes had fallen. The group did submit the petition to the king in April, but members said they had heard no response.</p>
        <p>''You see the absurdity of calling some of these men terrorists,'' Mr. Falleh said. ''They are just doing this to kill off the reform movement and prevent any sympathy toward those were arrested.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Alim, who represents several of the men, does acknowledge that one of them had been to Iraq twice under the auspices of the Saudi Red Crescent but insists that his visits were strictly humanitarian. Mr. Alim said he, too, would have been arrested if he had signed the petition. Instead, he said, the government has barred him from traveling abroad.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hattlan of Forbes Arabia said: ''Some people feel it's a hopeless case, that the government is the only force for change. People don't want to enter a losing war. Society is not on your side, and you have a long way to go.''</p>
        <p>Jidda's City Council, like other city councils around the country, has gone to great lengths to try to bring about some change, but many councilmen admit they are trying to make the most of a difficult situation. By their own admission, however, the councilmen have yet to make a mark on municipal decision-making. They insist, however, that they may well be the real catalysts for change in the country. But first, their powers must be expanded.</p>
        <p>''The picture is not very rosy, but it is not all that gloomy either,'' insisted Hussain al-Bar, who was elected to Jidda's council in 2005. ''The problem is that people here expect to see fast wins. But what we do, real change, takes time, and a lot of it.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 28, 2007, Monday  A front-page article on April 26 about the restricted activities of city councilmen chosen in municipal elections in Saudi Arabia two years ago attributed an erroneous distinction to those elections. While they were the first in which all men outside the military could vote (women are not allowed to vote), the elections were not the first ever held in Saudi Arabia. (A far more limited form of voting was introduced in Mecca in 1925, which lasted for roughly a decade. In later years, until the 1960s, some councilmen were elected in selected cities by small groups of voters.) A reader pointed out the error in an e-mail message the day the article ran; this correction was delayed for research.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 28, 2007, Monday</p>
        <p>A front-page article on April 26 about the restricted activities of city councilmen chosen in municipal elections in Saudi Arabia two years ago attributed an erroneous distinction to those elections. While they were the first in which all men outside the military could vote (women are not allowed to vote), the elections were not the first ever held in Saudi Arabia. (A far more limited form of voting was introduced in Mecca in 1925, which lasted for roughly a decade. In later years, until the 1960s, some councilmen were elected in selected cities by small groups of voters.) A reader pointed out the error in an e-mail message the day the article ran; this correction was delayed for research.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
