<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting Territorial Out in the Hall</title>
    <meta content="26halls" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/garden/26halls.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Storage</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Penelope</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Storage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0DF153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting Territorial Out in the Hall</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Getting Territorial Out in the Hall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENELOPE GREEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Green, Penelope</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Yorkers are creating tensions with neighbors by using their apartment hallways as storage space, decorative accent and even as playground; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the annals of hallway malfeasance, the Nanny Incident looms large.</p>
        <p>Ben Harvey, 28, is a program host at here!, a gay cable television network based in Manhattan, where he works late-afternoon and evening hours and so tends to be home a lot during the day. A year or so ago, a few months after he moved into a glassy new high-rise in Chelsea, he began to be aware that the common hallway on his floor was awfully full most days, not with the usual hallway annoyances -- armies of shoes, the lone umbrella hanging around too long after the storm -- but with little people: the neighbor's young son, his baby sitter and their friends. Balls were thrown, games played.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In congested cities like New York, the hallway may be one of the most hotly contested spaces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the annals of hallway malfeasance, the Nanny Incident looms large.</p>
        <p>Ben Harvey, 28, is a program host at here!, a gay cable television network based in Manhattan, where he works late-afternoon and evening hours and so tends to be home a lot during the day. A year or so ago, a few months after he moved into a glassy new high-rise in Chelsea, he began to be aware that the common hallway on his floor was awfully full most days, not with the usual hallway annoyances -- armies of shoes, the lone umbrella hanging around too long after the storm -- but with little people: the neighbor's young son, his baby sitter and their friends. Balls were thrown, games played.</p>
        <p>''The weirdest was the morning I woke up and there was a lot of crying in the hall,'' Mr. Harvey said. ''It was about 7 a.m., and I was, like, 'Enough!'</p>
        <p>''So I go out in my boxers, and the nanny's holding the little boy, who's howling, and I said, 'Is there any way you could take him inside the apartment?' All the nanny said was, 'She's taking a shower, and we can't go in until she's done.'</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to be this whistle-blowing, annoying guy, and because I do stay home in the day I didn't want them to think I was this slacker loser. But these are nice apartments. I know they have room to spare. It's a public space in the hallway, and they were using it as their private nursery.''</p>
        <p>There are few places in America where public and private collide so incessantly, or confusingly, as in the common apartment hall, or where the terms yours, mine and ours seem so hard to define. In congested cities like New York, where a square foot of residential real estate has never been so expensive, the hallway may be one of the most hotly contested spaces.</p>
        <p>It is the pause, the anteroom from elevator or stair to your front door, the space that's a little bit yours, with your newspaper lying on the doormat you picked out in the colors you like from Crate &amp; Barrel. Maybe you let your cat out when you come home, to stretch his legs in your ''yard.'' But maybe that drives your neighbors crazy. Because it's their yard, too.</p>
        <p>Resentments run deep, and can be mysterious when you're on the receiving end. Who knows the injury first felt by the woman who lived down the hall from a young family in a Midtown luxury apartment building?</p>
        <p>It all started, said Lori S., who works in television, when her baby was born.</p>
        <p>''We began to get letters from the managing agent saying our son was riding a bike in the hall,'' said Lori, who requested anonymity because, she said, the experience still rattled her. That was impossible, ''because our son was only a few months old,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Then we got letters saying we were leaving stuff out in the hall, and it was a fire hazard, but the only thing we'd ever left out was an umbrella once when it was raining.</p>
        <p>''We knew it was her: we could tell by her behavior. She would duck her head when she saw us. On weekends, she thought we opened our door too many times. She'd open her door three inches, just to look at us, and then slam it shut.''</p>
        <p>Physical proximity amplifies and distorts the behavior of others, and can make even innocuous activities seem offensive. One design professional living in the Christadora, an East Village apartment building, fantasized about banning cooking in his building, because he can't bear the smell of other people's food in the hall.</p>
        <p>''If it's Sunday and you smell roast chicken, it's fantastic if it's yours,'' he said. ''But if it's not, why should you have to smell it, unless you're being invited for dinner?'' He has installed ''superfans,'' he said, in his own kitchen, ''so we wouldn't have our smells in the hallway.'' (And he asked to remain anonymous because, he said, he realizes his cooking-ban fantasy ''sounds insane.'')</p>
        <p>The most common irritants, though, tend to be more concrete. Stuff in the halls, blocking escape, is the No. 2 reason that people call the Fire Department's complaint line, said Francis X. Gribbon, the deputy commissioner for public information. (Combustible garbage -- in hallways and elsewhere -- is No. 1.) The building code, Mr. Gribbon said, ''includes language that says, 'Corridors shall be kept readily accessible at all times, free of combustible items.' ''</p>
        <p>Gregory Coster is a jewelry designer and art collector who has lived in the same one-bedroom apartment for 29 years, in a Sheridan Square building designed by Emery Roth. Aesthetics, as he put it, are his business, particularly objects from the 1920s and '30s, the period his building dates from.</p>
        <p>And since the day he moved in he has cared for the hallway outside his door. He painted the walls a deep mauve. Framed an enormous Champagne poster from the '20s and hung it on the wall facing the elevators. Set out a bench, a wood veneer French buffet and a wide gilded mirror, as well as a marble sculpture of a woman's torso and backside that sits on its own pedestal.</p>
        <p>After the building was sold about 10 years ago, Mr. Coster said, the new management's brokers liked to take prospective renters to his floor to see what it looked like. ''The rest of the building was a dump then,'' he said. Soon, he added, the building's other floors were decorated in a remarkably similar style, as they still are today: the framed posters, the dark walls, the gilded mirrors and benches are now building-wide.</p>
        <p>A few years ago Mr. Coster received a letter from the managing agent demanding the removal of the little Art Nouveau buffet, ''because they said it was a fire hazard,'' he said. The other wooden objects remain on his and other floors.</p>
        <p>Recently he received a letter demanding that his sculpture go, too. The charge? ''That it was obscene,'' Mr. Coster said. ''The real reason is that there are a lot of rent-control tenants in this building, and the landlord would like us out. This is one of a series of small harassments.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coster said that he and his neighbors signed a letter saying that they liked the art and didn't find it obscene, and questioning the landlord's ability to make what Mr. Coster considered an aesthetic valuation.</p>
        <p>Reached by telephone yesterday, the building's managing agent, James Vest of SDG Management, said that Mr. Coster's point about harassment was ''completely false.''</p>
        <p>''The hallways are common areas,'' he said. ''A lot of times tenants confuse the fact that they rent their apartments, and that they don't own the building.</p>
        <p>''It's not a question of taste. The owner should decide what is in the public halls and what isn't.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coster and his landlord are at the sort of standoff where most hallway disputes seem to end up: ambiguous conclusions for ambiguous spaces. At a converted factory in Park Slope, Brooklyn, many residents remember the Case of the Migrating Jogging-Stroller, which has been closed and reopened more than once.</p>
        <p>Here's how Elizabeth Raymond tells it:</p>
        <p>''I was in business school, home all day, 'the complete condo wife,' my husband called me,'' she said. She had plenty of time to notice what was going on around her, and what she noticed on her own floor was the jogging-stroller at the other end of the hall. ''It's the Park Slope fashion accessory,'' she said. ''Everyone has it; nobody uses it.''</p>
        <p>This particular stroller belonged to someone who, like Ms. Raymond, had a duplex. ''The stroller used to live in the sixth floor hall, until those neighbors banished it, and then it appeared on the fifth floor,'' she said. When she realized that the stroller wasn't just out there temporarily, Ms. Raymond began to play little games with it, ''stealing it and putting it in different places.''</p>
        <p>''I was hoping the owner would worry it would get stolen and bring it inside,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Why didn't she confront the wrongdoer, or at least ask the managing agent to?</p>
        <p>''Because she'll hate us?'' Ms. Raymond ventured. ''Because we do things that are against the rules, like leave things on our terrace or have barbecues. Finally I did call the management company. They wrote a letter and threatened a fine, and when they came to check she had put it in the trash room, and the next day she put it back in our hall.''</p>
        <p>It stayed five months longer, until two years ago. Then last year, it made a reappearance in someone's parking space downstairs. That individual, Ms. Raymond said, put up a notice saying she'd found a stroller and was ready to throw it away unless it was claimed. Which it was. ''So it reappears on our floor, and I start pushing it away, and then it went under the stairway downstairs. I haven't seen it in a while.''</p>
        <p>The same building was also the site of the Piñata Episode, in which a family made themselves so comfortable in their common hall that they held a birthday party there. A downstairs neighbor recalled it ruefully: ''Our son had just been born, we were exhausted from no sleep, and one afternoon we finally get him down. And then we hear footsteps, running, back-and-forth.</p>
        <p>''The running doesn't stop, and my wife goes to see what's going on. The elevator opens, and he's hanging a piñata above a crowd of kids. She's dumbstruck, and says something like: ''Our child is ill. We just got him to sleep. Could you please be quiet or go in your apartment or something?'' And the man says, 'The party will be over in half an hour.' And walks away to get the stick, leaving her there with her mouth open.''</p>
        <p>COMMUNAL living requires a particular social contract: a constructed set of behaviors known as politeness. It is said that good fences make good neighbors; in apartment buildings, your ''fence'' can be a certain blank expression into which you arrange your features, the way you pretend not to see your neighbor sneak out naked for his paper, or try not to open your door at the same time the family at the other end does. It's why you smile at the woman who leaves her entire shoe wardrobe in the hall, and then call the managing agent.</p>
        <p>''The vast majority of New Yorkers figure it out,'' said James O'Connor, president of Douglas Elliman Property Management, which manages 53,000 apartment buildings, most of them in Manhattan. He has been in the business for more than 30 years, and while he will tell you that no one likes the neighbors' floor mats -- ''no one,'' he repeated emphatically -- his office handles few complaints.</p>
        <p>Really?</p>
        <p>''Really,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''It's just that 5 percent of New Yorkers are crazy,'' he added, ''and that just carries over'' into bad hall behavior. ''Look around you next time you take a walk down the street.''</p>
        <p>That may be a bit optimistic. Not all transgressions in the realm of the hallway can be excused with the insanity defense. Charles von Simson, a Manhattan intellectual property lawyer who is to all appearances a sane, upstanding citizen, took a conversation with a reporter as an opportunity to come clean about an eight-year-old crime.</p>
        <p>At the time he and his wife were living in a four-unit brownstone in Cobble Hill, Brooklyn, their first child had just been born and they were bursting out of their tiny apartment. ''We were the bad seeds,'' he said. ''We were always in trouble for leaving the stroller in the hall.</p>
        <p>''You know it's bad behavior, but you're desperate. You feel the walls closing in on you, and you just feel you have no choice. We were stuffed with stuff -- we didn't know what to do with all that plastic baby stuff, the seats, the stroller -- and right outside our front door was this juicy closet.'' He clearly savored the memory.</p>
        <p>Mr. von Simson said that hallway closet, filled with some old paint cans and the empty stereo boxes of a pair of ''roommate guys'' down the hall, was keeping him awake at night because he wanted to use it too.</p>
        <p>''I asked the dudes if they would move their boxes, and they said no,'' he said. ''And I asked the landlord, and he said he didn't want to get involved.''</p>
        <p>There ensued a series of Wile E. Coyote-Road Runner shenanigans, Mr. von Simson said, as he would move his stuff in and theirs out, and they would do the same with his things. And then one night, he said, he broke down and hauled the boxes out and threw them in the basement.</p>
        <p>''And of course one of the roommate dudes stormed over and confronted me,'' Mr. von Simson said. ''And I lied to his face. He said, 'Do you know who took my boxes?' He was really mad, and I didn't blame him.</p>
        <p>''I looked him straight in the eye and said: 'That's terrible. If you ever find the guy, you should beat him up. I would help you beat him.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
