<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ROOM TO IMPROVE</title>
    <meta content="26room" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/garden/26room.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cleansers, Detergents and Soaps</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waxes and Polishes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milioti, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFDF153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ROOM TO IMPROVE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Room to Improve</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Milioti</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Milioti, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Room to Improve column on best products to clean and maintain wood; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. What is the best way to clean and maintain wood?</p>
        <p>A. First, please back slowly away from the Lemon Pledge. It is great for slick, piano-finish wood furniture with a smooth surface, like an Ikea dresser, but not for a walnut dining table. The waxy chemicals in a traditional aerosol polish or protectant leave residue that settles into tiny cracks and mars the wood's original beauty. What you need is a natural, no-wax product.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What is the best way to clean and maintain wood?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. What is the best way to clean and maintain wood?</p>
        <p>A. First, please back slowly away from the Lemon Pledge. It is great for slick, piano-finish wood furniture with a smooth surface, like an Ikea dresser, but not for a walnut dining table. The waxy chemicals in a traditional aerosol polish or protectant leave residue that settles into tiny cracks and mars the wood's original beauty. What you need is a natural, no-wax product.</p>
        <p>Wood for Good from Method Home ($5 for 12 ounces at Target stores or from methodhome.com) is an excellent, nontoxic polish with natural oils from palm and coconut trees that act as vitamins on woods like walnut, cherry or pine. It can be sprayed directly on the wood and rubbed in with a microfiber duster like a Swiffer cloth (experts suggest doing this about every other week). Another good natural polish is Orange Glo ($5 for 16 ounces), which is made from orange oils and is safe for all but the most delicate woods.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, though, it is best to use nothing at all. ''On my own natural wood furniture, I don't use any products,'' said Paul Schulman, a Chicago-based designer. ''I simply dust them every week or two.'' Mr. Schulman, whose company, Paul Schulman Design (paulschulman.com), makes pieces like a cherry-wood bench that doubles as a radiator cover, explained that there is ''almost always some kind of protective treatment, usually a natural oil, applied during the manufacturing process.'' Over time, dust can erode this coating and dull the surface, so your first step should be always be dusting with a soft, nonabrasive cloth, like an old T-shirt, he said, especially if you plan to use a product, or you'll simply push the dirt into the wood's tiny nooks.</p>
        <p>Another important aspect of wood care is controlling temperature, humidity and sunlight.</p>
        <p>''Temperature-wise, the ideal circumstance for wood is to be in an indoor environment that's 70 to 72 degrees, and 50 to 55 percent humidity, all year round,'' Mr. Schulman said. Wood does fine in slightly less than ideal conditions, as long as there are no major temperature fluctuations, he said.</p>
        <p>You might want to consider buying a dehumidifier. ''It's the humidity, more than the actual temperature, that changes the dimension of the wood,'' said Tyler Hays, the owner of BDDW, a store in SoHo that specializes in handmade tables. ''In places like New York the humidity in your home can go from 25 percent relative humidity in the winter with an electric heater to 80 percent or higher in the summer with no air conditioning and the windows open.''</p>
        <p>A simple dehumidifier like the Soleus CFM-40E costs about $200 (soleusair.com) and can remove up to 40 pints of moisture from the air every day. For homes in humid climates with wood paneling or lots of wood furniture, Humiditrol home dehumidification systems from Lennox (lennox.com), which start at around $7,500, can be helpful. They can be installed in the ducts of existing air-conditioning systems and keep moisture levels balanced without emitting ozone.</p>
        <p>Try to keep furniture out of the sun. ''Sunlight, quite simply, dries out wood,'' Mr. Schulman said. ''Any wood in direct sunlight is prone to fading, especially walnut and cherry,'' he added. ''If you put any accessories on the wood -- even for a few days -- and it's in direct sunlight, the result will not be good.''</p>
        <p>If you've just inherited or bought an older piece, it may require more serious care. ''There are good refinishing shops everywhere where you can get someone to come over'' and give you an estimate on repair or refinishing, Mr. Hays said. (One online resource for finding a refinisher in your area is servicemagic.com.)</p>
        <p>If your wood does not show signs of deterioration but just doesn't look the way it once did, that is not necessarily a bad thing.</p>
        <p>''Fine wood, especially when it's used regularly, can develop a beautiful patina, and you wouldn't want to destroy that,'' said Alon Langotsky, the owner of a New York-based company called Chista that specializes in raw wood furniture and sculptural pieces. ''It's just aging over time. That's what it's supposed to do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
