<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Narrow Window Into the Future</title>
    <meta content="26Online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/fashion/26Online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFD6143EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Narrow Window Into the Future</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Narrow Window Into the Future</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIchelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE last time I needed a white shirt, I bought it at the mall.</p>
        <p>This may sound like a shameful confession, coming from someone who shops online all day, but the reality is that when it comes to fashion, Web sites never have been as good at organizing apparel as an old-fashioned mall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to fashion, Web sites never have been as good at organizing apparel as an old-fashioned mall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE last time I needed a white shirt, I bought it at the mall.</p>
        <p>This may sound like a shameful confession, coming from someone who shops online all day, but the reality is that when it comes to fashion, Web sites never have been as good at organizing apparel as an old-fashioned mall.</p>
        <p>Consider that a keyword search for ''white shirt'' last week turned up 18 million results at Google (the first being stock photo images of white shirts), roughly 20,000 results at Froogle (the first page of which consisted entirely of eBay auctions) and 15,554 results at Yahoo Shopping, including a mishmash of men's shirts, children's shirts and, inexplicably, N.Y.P.D. T-shirts.</p>
        <p>That's why I was excited last week to test an unusual, new fashion search site called Glimpse.com, which aims to mimic a one-stop shopping mall online by creating a central place where shoppers can sort through merchandise from a few dozen well-known stores, ranging from Saks Fifth Avenue to Old Navy.</p>
        <p>It's an ambitious goal. Researchers who study how humans interact with computers say that online searches for apparel can quickly turn confusing.</p>
        <p>''It's frustrating for people to have to think of the right keywords to type in a shopping experience where what they might be looking for is not something they can easily describe,'' said Mark S. Ackerman, an associate professor in the School of Information at the University of Michigan. ''For instance, if I want I a tie, I go to a store and wear the shirt because I wouldn't know what keyword except 'tie' to type to describe something that would match it.''</p>
        <p>The way Glimpse.com proposes to get around that problem is by creating the first online mall where virtual stores like Bluefly.com and Shopbop.com sit next door to stores from your local mall like Neiman Marcus and Nordstrom.</p>
        <p>Glimpse collects, categorizes and displays merchandise from about 100 stores on a Web site where shoppers can look at images side by side in a single screen, eliminating the need to open a zillion pop-up windows to view each store's inventory separately. ''It searches strategically through a relatively small number of sites rather than searching the entire universe,'' said Frank Han, the founder of Glimpse. ''What we're trying to do is bring a point of view that keeps the shopper from feeling overwhelmed.''</p>
        <p>When a shopper clicks on a thumbnail image of an item, a smaller window pops up linking directly to the store that sells the merchandise.</p>
        <p>Glimpse.com organizes items in a few categories -- clothing, shoes, jewelry, beauty and home décor (included because ''shoppers think of it as fashion for the home,'' Mr. Han said). Much of the merchandise -- from thousands of manufacturers like Tory Burch and Joe's Jeans -- is aimed squarely at the tastes of single female shoppers age 24 to 32.</p>
        <p>''This is a shopper who connects with shopping as a hobby, in a phase of life where she's taking care of herself more than taking care of lots of people around her,'' Mr. Han said. ''She is a member of a gym. Does spa days, manicures and pedicures. More likely than not to have a MySpace page.''</p>
        <p>That didn't sound like me. But it definitely sounded like the me I pretend to be when I shop.</p>
        <p>To test Glimpse, I started at its homepage, which looks like a magazine spread with a handful of high-quality product photographs (shoes, dresses, earrings) and clickable headlines like ''Best Sales and Steals'' and ''Editors' Shopping Picks.''</p>
        <p>One of the site's strengths is that its clean design and relatively limited selection of merchandise make it equally easy to hunt either through keyword searches or by clicking on category names or thumbnail photos to focus eventually on an item.</p>
        <p>It's particularly important for fashion search sites to allow for a variety of search methods because a clothing shopper tends to browse and compare before settling on a single item, said Jaime Teevan, a researcher at Microsoft who as part of her recent doctoral research studied online search strategies.</p>
        <p>For window shoppers who browse for merchandise by relying on orienteering techniques, Glimpse displays pictures of celebrities and offers shoppers the chance to purchase their styles, for instance.</p>
        <p>Shoppers on Glimpse can limit a search to merchandise sold by a specific store or manufacturer (or to a few designated stores or manufacturers) and then, within those limits, narrow the search further by category of clothing.</p>
        <p>''That sort of supporting feedback from your environment helps you find what you're looking for,'' Ms. Teevan said.</p>
        <p>I'm more of a directed searcher. I rely on keywords to get the ball rolling. I typed ''white shirt'' and got 37 results on Glimpse (accompanied by thumbnail images).</p>
        <p>That's a lot. But it wasn't overwhelming like the results at other, more general sites, because these were relevant; the top row of thumbnails included pictures of a Craig Taylor white shirt from Saks ($155) and a satin-check white on white shirt from Thomas Pink ($130) and a what was described as a ''perfect white shirt'' from J. Jill (marked down to $29.99.).</p>
        <p>Before Glimpse, I would have had to visit each of those stores' sites individually, along with, say, Nordstrom.com, Zappos.com, Saks.com and Oldnavy.com, and after awhile my computer screen would look cluttered and I would eventually have lost track of who was selling what for how much.</p>
        <p>Now, however, Glimpse.com streamlined the process by performing in seconds the same search task that used to take me several minutes at multiple sites and by displaying the results side-by-side in a single window.</p>
        <p>My only real concern is whether the site will grow too big, adding stores and brands until it becomes plagued with the sort of irrelevant results that clutter more general search sites.</p>
        <p>Mr. Han said that won't happen. ''We'll continue to have a real point of view in merchandising on the site,'' he said. ''We'll have more pages, that dig deeper, to organize merchandise into 60 top sellers or 40 editors' picks, to organize it for shoppers.''</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail: Slatalla@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Slatalla@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
