<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Motive Yet For Rampage, Police Report</title>
    <meta content="26virginia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/us/26virginia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1842992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Blacksburg (Va)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hauser, Christine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cho, Seung-Hui</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Motive Yet For Rampage, Police Report</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Motive Yet for Rampage, Police Report</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTINE HAUSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hauser, Christine</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKSBURG, Va., April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Virginia police say they are no closer to determining motive for Seung-Hui Cho's shooting rampage at Virginia Tech after sifting through evidence for 10 days and interviewing scores of people; investigators continue to pursue leads (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After sifting through evidence for 10 days and conducting scores of interviews, the Virginia police said Wednesday that they were no closer to determining a motive for Seung-Hui Cho's shooting rampage last week at Virginia Tech.</p>
        <p>But police officials said it had taken them five minutes to break into the classroom building where Mr. Cho shot 30 of the 32 people he killed, longer than had previously been disclosed. They attributed that to the need to break through the chains Mr. Cho had used to block three of the building's doors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Virginia police said that they were no closer to determining a motive for Seung-Hui Cho’s shooting rampage last week at Virginia Tech.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After sifting through evidence for 10 days and conducting scores of interviews, the Virginia police said Wednesday that they were no closer to determining a motive for Seung-Hui Cho's shooting rampage last week at Virginia Tech.</p>
        <p>But police officials said it had taken them five minutes to break into the classroom building where Mr. Cho shot 30 of the 32 people he killed, longer than had previously been disclosed. They attributed that to the need to break through the chains Mr. Cho had used to block three of the building's doors.</p>
        <p>Investigators said they had pored over hundreds of pieces of evidence, including computer hard drives, e-mail messages from the university's servers and cellphone records, and had conducted interviews with students, faculty members and Mr. Cho's family. But nothing has provided any indication of why Mr. Cho committed the worst mass shooting in American history, in which he killed 27 students and 5 teachers before committing suicide.</p>
        <p>''We talk about possible motives and theories, but we don't have any evidence to support anything,'' said Col. W. Steven Flaherty, the superintendent of the state police, at a news conference.</p>
        <p>Colonel Flaherty said that investigators were still pursuing leads, but that so far they had not determined whether anyone assisted Mr. Cho in the April 16 attacks, in which he shot two students at a dormitory, West Ambler Johnston, and 30 people in classes at Norris Hall before killing himself. He said Mr. Cho fired more than 170 rounds in about nine minutes at Norris Hall.</p>
        <p>Investigators, who are still trying to determine why Mr. Cho started at the dormitory, have not established a connection between Mr. Cho and his first two victims, Emily J. Hilscher and Ryan Clark, who were killed in the dormitory.</p>
        <p>Officials did say that Mr. Cho was seen outside the dormitory around 7 a.m., when Ms. Hilscher returned to the building.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clark, the resident adviser in the building, apparently went to Ms. Hilscher's aid when he and other students heard a commotion outside her room shortly after 7 a.m., the police said. Each student was shot once with a 9 millimeter Glock pistol.</p>
        <p>Court documents filed Monday said Mr. Cho's family told investigators in an interview that he normally called them by cellphone every Sunday evening. But the police at the news conference did not provide other details about what Mr. Cho's parents have said or where they are, saying only that they were interviewed by the F.B.I.</p>
        <p>Investigators said Mr. Cho returned to his dormitory between the first and second shootings, but did not at that time record the package of videos, pictures and writings that he sent to NBC News.</p>
        <p>The package had been made before April 16, and the police said they did not know whether he mailed it himself.</p>
        <p>The police had previously said they initially questioned Ms. Hilscher's boyfriend, Karl D. Thornhill, in connection with the first shootings, although they later dismissed him as a suspect. On Wednesday, Wendell Flinchum, campus police chief, said that as officers were conducting that interview, a 911 call reported gunshots at Norris Hall at 9:42 a.m.</p>
        <p>It took officers three minutes to reach the Norris Hall area, he said, and five minutes more to break through the chains that Mr. Cho had used to lock the building's doors, and then make their way through the building and up the stairs. A Virginia State Police spokeswoman, Corinne N. Geller, said part of that time was taken up by police officers who had to coordinate a team response to the gunman.</p>
        <p>Shooting the locks, the police then made their way up to the second floor, hearing a shot on the way.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
