<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Europe, Growing Frenzy For Closing Takeover Deals</title>
    <meta content="26deal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/business/worldbusiness/26deal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <org class="online_producer">ABN AMRO Holding NV</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Europe, Growing Frenzy For Closing Takeover Deals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Europe, Growing Frenzy for Takeover Deals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, April 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most years, the United States handily beats Europe for bragging rights in deal making, based on the total value of mergers and acquisitions.</p>
        <p>But this year, Europe is pulling ahead. The current takeover battle in banking, the biggest in the industry's history, is just the latest sign of the growing deal frenzy on the Continent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ABN Amro takeover battle, the biggest in banking’s history, is the latest sign of the deal frenzy in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most years, the United States handily beats Europe for bragging rights in deal making, based on the total value of mergers and acquisitions.</p>
        <p>But this year, Europe is pulling ahead. The current takeover battle in banking, the biggest in the industry's history, is just the latest sign of the growing deal frenzy on the Continent.</p>
        <p>That frenzy is prompting changes in corporate behavior. European companies are scrambling to put themselves in play, or fend off unwanted approaches, much like American companies did in the 1980s.</p>
        <p>Europe's deal mania reflects a number of trends: more active shareholders, particularly hedge funds; an influx of private equity money; low interest rates; and a wealth of European companies with valuable assets that are ripe for the picking, in some cases because they have been poorly managed.</p>
        <p>''Shareholder activism and hedge funds are acting as a trigger to doing more restructuring kinds of deals,'' said Alexander Dibelius, the head of Goldman Sachs in Germany. ''In combination with private equity and cheap money, this adds to the perceived increase in deal making."</p>
        <p>It is more than just perception. So far this year, the value of mergers and acquisitions announced in Europe is $656.4 billion, compared with $601.4 billion in the United States, according to Thomson Financial (Europe also led in 1990, 1991 and 2002).</p>
        <p>Europe's new economic buoyancy is also providing a tailwind to dealmakers here.</p>
        <p>Growth rates in Europe are approaching those in the United States, and Europe may outperform the United States this year if the American economy slows.</p>
        <p>Germany, in particular, is booming, with soaring investor confidence and heavy capital spending. Companies are reporting record profits, as they reap the benefits of years of painful overhauls.</p>
        <p>Having retrenched thoroughly, European companies are emerging with leaner cost structures and loftier ambitions. The German energy giant, Eon, for example, made a 42 billion euro ($57 billion) bid for its Spanish counterpart, Endesa -- a deal that eventually collapsed because of resistance by the Spanish.</p>
        <p>That deal underscores a hurdle to deals in Europe, particularly cross-border ones: protectionism is alive and well.</p>
        <p>Political leaders in France, Italy, and Spain speak unabashedly about keeping national assets from foreign buyers. Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative front-runner for the French presidency, promises to maintain France's tradition of defending ''national champions'' in crucial industries.</p>
        <p>In Germany, the former head of the Social Democratic Party, Franz Muntefering, scored points during the last election by referring to foreign hedge funds and private equity investors as heuschrecken, or locusts, intent on plundering German assets and mistreating workers.</p>
        <p>While European executives are generally more open to cross-border deals than politicians, some play the nationalist card when it suits them, to ward off unwanted suitors.</p>
        <p>Porsche, the German sports car maker, has amassed a more than 30 percent stake in Volkswagen, justifying its action by saying it is trying to fend off a potential takeover by foreign private-equity investors.</p>
        <p>Fears of hostile approaches by financial investors have helped fuel the efforts of DaimlerChrysler to unload its money-losing Chrysler division, according to executives at the company.</p>
        <p>They may have even played a role in the abrupt ouster Wednesday of the chief executive of Siemens, the engineering giant, which has been hit by a corruption scandal.</p>
        <p>People with ties to Siemens said members of its board were worried that if it did not get past the scandal, the company would be vulnerable to a takeover bid by a private equity firm.</p>
        <p>There is ample evidence that hedge funds and other foreign investors are shaking Europe out of it old habits.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro's negotiations with Barclays were started in part by pressure from the Children's Investment Fund, a London-based hedge fund, which owns less than 3 percent of ABN Amro.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, bankers here said, it would have been inconceivable for a hedge fund to force one of Europe's largest banks to, in effect, put itself in play.</p>
        <p>But in 2005, the Children's Investment Fund waged a fax and e-mail campaign against the management of Deutsche Börse, the German stock exchange, which was seeking to take over the London Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>Not only did Deutsche Börse end up having to abandon the bid, but the company's chief executive and its chairman were forced to resign.</p>
        <p>The European Central Bank has done its part to keep business humming. While the bank began tightening credit at the end of 2005, its key rate of 4 percent is still below that of the Federal Reserve.</p>
        <p>Most economists expect that the bank will move cautiously in raising rates further.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
