<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TROOPER IS SLAIN AND 2ND IS HURT IN CATSKILL TOWN</title>
    <meta content="26troopers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/nyregion/26troopers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tear Gas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Margaretville (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santos, Fernanda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkerhoff, David C (State Trooper)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mattson, Richard G (State Trooper)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gombasi, Matthew (State Trooper)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trim, Travis D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Felton, Preston L (Supt)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TROOPER IS SLAIN AND 2ND IS HURT IN CATSKILL TOWN</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Suspect in N.Y. Trooper’s Death Is Presumed Dead</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO and FERNANDA SANTOS; Lisa W. Foderaro reported from Margaretville and Fernanda Santos from White Plains. Reporting was contributed by Nick Confessore in Coxsackie, Laura Drake in North Lawrence, Danny Hakim in Albany and Jennifer Medina in New York City.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santos, Fernanda; Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <dateline>MARGARETVILLE, N.Y., April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State trooper is killed, two others are wounded and suspect is thought to be dead after farmhouse where he is hiding in Margaretville, NY, catches fire during police siege; slain trooper David C Brinkerhoff and wounded trooper Richard G Mattson encounter suspect Travis Trim while responding to burglar alarm at farmhouse; Trim is suspect in day-earlier shooting of another trooper, Matthew Gombasi; New York State Police acting superintendent Preston L Felton says officers fired several tear-gas canisters into house, possibly causing fire; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One New York State trooper was killed and another was wounded near this tiny Catskill Mountains town on Wednesday morning as they tracked down a suspect who the authorities said had shot and wounded another trooper the day before.</p>
        <p>The suspect, Travis D. Trim, 23, is now thought to be dead, the authorities say, after the farmhouse where he was hiding caught fire later on Wednesday as the police were besieging it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Catskill farmhouse where the suspect was believed to be hiding erupted in flames as the police were besieging it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One New York State trooper was killed and another was wounded near this tiny Catskill Mountains town on Wednesday morning as they tracked down a suspect who the authorities said had shot and wounded another trooper the day before.</p>
        <p>The suspect, Travis D. Trim, 23, is now thought to be dead, the authorities say, after the farmhouse where he was hiding caught fire later on Wednesday as the police were besieging it.</p>
        <p>About 90 minutes after the fire broke out, the authorities went into the house, when they felt it was safe to do so. The acting superintendent of the New York State Police, Preston L. Felton, said: ''At 7:35 p.m., we located what appears to be a badly charred body in the residence. The body was slumped in the doorway holding a rifle. We will make attempts to ID the body in the coming days.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''There's a possibility that our actions caused the fire,'' noting that officers had fired several tear-gas canisters into the house.</p>
        <p>The authorities identified the slain trooper as David C. Brinkerhoff, 29, a member of the agency's mobile response team.</p>
        <p>Trooper Brinkerhoff and another member of the assault team, Richard G. Mattson, went into the farmhouse, about 110 miles northwest of New York City, to help other troopers who were responding to a burglar alarm about 8 a.m. Wednesday. They were looking for Mr. Trim, who was suspected of shooting another trooper, Matthew Gombosi, the previous day.</p>
        <p>The authorities said Mr. Trim then shot Trooper Brinkerhoff in the head, and Trooper Mattson in the left arm. They were both taken by helicopter to Albany Medical Center.</p>
        <p>On learning of the slaying of the trooper, the second member of the mobile response team to be killed in a manhunt since September, Gov. Eliot Spitzer canceled a planned lunchtime speech in Manhattan, asking his wife, Silda Wall Spitzer, to fill in for him. He returned to Albany and in a brief statement issued by his office, he said, ''One of our best has fallen and another has been seriously wounded in the line of duty.''</p>
        <p>In the Capitol, Republicans and Democrats were moving swiftly, but in different directions, in response both to the trooper shootings as well as the shootings at Virginia Tech last week.</p>
        <p>The Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, called on the governor to pressure the Democratic-led Assembly to pass legislation that would bring back the death penalty for those who kill law enforcement officers, as well as terrorists. The governor has supported both ideas in the past, but a similar bill was voted down in the Assembly on Tuesday, 96 to 47.</p>
        <p>''I'm asking the governor to use his considerable influence with the Assembly,'' Mr. Bruno said.</p>
        <p>Senator John J. Bonacic, a Republican whose district includes Margaretville, said of the governor: ''I know you're a law and order guy, I know you are, I know you care about the safety of our families. Get the Assembly to do what they must do.''</p>
        <p>But Charles Carrier, a spokesman for Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, reiterated that Assembly Democrats oppose the death penalty.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Assembly passed a number of antigun measures on Wednesday, including bills banning assault weapons and armor-piercing ammunition.</p>
        <p>The events that led to the shooting of the three officers began last Friday, when Mr. Trim, of North Lawrence, near the Canadian border, was said to have stolen a van.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday afternoon in Margaretville, 270 miles south of where the van was taken, Trooper Gombosi pulled Mr. Trim over because the van was missing a license plate, Mr. Felton, the acting superintendent, said.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Trim failed to provide identification, Trooper Gombosi told him he was under arrest. At that point, Mr. Trim pulled a handgun from his waistband and fired once at the trooper, Mr. Felton said. The trooper was hit in the lower ribs, but the police said his body armor saved him from serious injury.</p>
        <p>''He was disoriented and he could not produce any identification,'' Mr. Felton said of Mr. Trim. One investigator said that Mr. Trim was looking at a map when he was pulled over, as if he were lost.</p>
        <p>The police later found the abandoned van a few miles from where the confrontation with Trooper Gombosi took place.</p>
        <p>By Tuesday night, the authorities said troopers had converged on the rural area -- stopping cars and trucks and using police dogs -- in search of Mr. Trim.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday morning, the burglar alarm drew them to the farmhouse, where they found a backpack, clothing and identification. A short time later, the authorities said, the troopers exchanged gunfire with Mr. Trim, and Troopers Brinkerhoff and Matson were shot.</p>
        <p>Before long, scores of heavily armed troopers surrounded the farmhouse where Mr. Trim was believed to be hiding. Armored vehicles moved in, snipers took position behind stone walls, and other officers spread across the roads and hilltops overlooking the house.</p>
        <p>At one point, troopers shot tear-gas canisters inside the home, eliciting no response. Then, a robot with a camera rolled in, and scanned the house for the suspect.</p>
        <p>Late in the afternoon, troopers began moving in and once again fired tear gas canisters. The house erupted in flames, driving back the officers.</p>
        <p>''It's unbelievable,'' said Anna Carli, a retired nurse who has lived in Margaretville for 40 years. ''This is a little town. This kind of thing doesn't happen here.''</p>
        <p>In the section of Coxsackie, just outside Albany, where Trooper Brinkerhoff -- an eight-year veteran of the State Police -- lived with his wife, Barbara, and their 7-month-old daughter, the police kept the press and the curious away.</p>
        <p>The events on Wednesday reminded many of the five-month manhunt last year for Ralph J. Phillips, during which three troopers were shot, one fatally. The hunt began after Mr. Phillips escaped from the Erie County jail on April 2, 2006.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, outside Albany Medical Center, where he had met with relatives of Trooper Mattson's, the Rev. James LeFebvre, chaplain of the Albany Police Department, described his reaction when he heard the news of Trooper Brinkerhoff's death: ''You say, 'Give me the good news.' And they say, 'There isn't any good news,' and you say, 'No, not again.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
