<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Lions, Opportunity Is Knocking In the Draft</title>
    <meta content="26lions" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/football/26lions.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Detroit Lions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Lions</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Millen, Matt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rogers, Charles</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Harrington, Joey</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Lions, Opportunity Is Knocking In the Draft</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Lions, Opportunity Is Knocking in the Draft</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>ALLEN PARK, Mich., April 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to the N.F.L. draft, practice has not made perfect for the Detroit Lions.</p>
        <p>Coming off their sixth consecutive losing season, the Lions find themselves in a familiar position. They hold the No. 2 pick on Saturday, and their frustrated fans are holding their breath. First-round flops have been commonplace since Matt Millen became the team president in 2001. Quarterback Joey Harrington was the No. 3 overall pick in 2002; wide receiver Charles Rogers was No. 2 in 2003; and wide receiver Mike Williams was No. 10 in 2005. Harrington was traded after three unsuccessful seasons, Rogers is no longer in the N.F.L., and Williams may be on his way out, after catching only 8 passes last season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coming off their sixth consecutive losing season, the Detroit Lions find themselves in a familiar position as they prepare for this weekend’s N.F.L. draft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When it comes to the N.F.L. draft, practice has not made perfect for the Detroit Lions.</p>
        <p>Coming off their sixth consecutive losing season, the Lions find themselves in a familiar position. They hold the No. 2 pick on Saturday, and their frustrated fans are holding their breath. First-round flops have been commonplace since Matt Millen became the team president in 2001. Quarterback Joey Harrington was the No. 3 overall pick in 2002; wide receiver Charles Rogers was No. 2 in 2003; and wide receiver Mike Williams was No. 10 in 2005. Harrington was traded after three unsuccessful seasons, Rogers is no longer in the N.F.L., and Williams may be on his way out, after catching only 8 passes last season.</p>
        <p>After the Oakland Raiders make a decision with the No. 1 pick, the Lions will be on the clock, and Millen will be on the hot seat -- again. ''Fire Millen!'' has become a familiar chant at Ford Field, with the Lions having the worst record in the N.F.L. (24-72) over the past six seasons. Millen, however, is still in charge, and he seems to handle the criticism better than he has handled the draft.</p>
        <p>''I took this job with my eyes open, so I know what goes with the territory,'' Millen said Wednesday at the Lions' practice facility. ''You don't live in a vacuum. You see it. I understand it. But the way to get rid of it, to take care of it, is to win. The equation's not difficult. The winning part is difficult.''</p>
        <p>What the Lions do depends greatly on what Oakland does. The Raiders are expected to take quarterback JaMarcus Russell of Louisiana State or wide receiver Calvin Johnson of Georgia Tech.</p>
        <p>If the Lions take Johnson at No. 2, he would be the fourth wide receiver in five years whom Millen has taken with a first-round pick. Would Millen take another wide receiver? He made it sound that way, largely because Johnson is rated so highly by scouts, a receiver with size, speed, and reliable hands.</p>
        <p>''Calvin Johnson is unique,'' Millen said. ''We wouldn't hesitate with him at all. If you line a guy up like that, it changes everything. 'What are you going to do with your safeties? How are you going to handle this guy? What are you going to do when we go to multiple sets?' ''</p>
        <p>But if the Raiders take Johnson, Millen will face another set of variables. Drafting a quarterback like Russell or Brady Quinn of Notre Dame would not address immediate needs, because Millen and Coach Rod Marinelli seem satisfied with Jon Kitna as the starter.</p>
        <p>Neither Millen nor Marinelli ruled out taking a quarterback, but Russell or Quinn would most likely sit behind Kitna for at least a year or two, and Marinelli sounded reluctant to use the No. 2 pick on someone who would probably spend his rookie season holding a clipboard.</p>
        <p>''Stacking players, one behind the other, that doesn't make sense to me,'' Marinelli said. ''You get a first-round pick and he doesn't play this year, that's not smart.''</p>
        <p>The Lions need a pass rusher, which would make defensive end Gaines Adams of Clemson a potential choice. But many scouts do not view Adams as a player worthy of the contract that the No. 2 pick will command. That raises the possibility of the Lions trading the pick, allowing them to move down several spots, where they could still draft Adams, and perhaps acquire additional later-round picks.</p>
        <p>Millen said that he had hardly engaged in trade talk this week, but that he would not be surprised to get a last-minute phone call after the Raiders make their decision.</p>
        <p>''When you're on the clock, who knows what happens?'' Millen said. ''There may be a bunch of picks that you hadn't even considered from somebody way down. There's all kinds of things that happen. You just have to be ready. Some teams really value picks, they throw them around like manhole covers. Other ones are like, 'Here, take these.' ''</p>
        <p>Asked why the Lions have been unable to become a winner during his tenure, Millen said, ''If there was one reason, it'd be easy to fix.''</p>
        <p>Marinelli believes the Lions made strides in his rookie season, though it was not obvious looking at his 3-13 record. Many of the players who Marinelli inherited are gone, as he attempted to change the culture of losing.</p>
        <p>''You find out who wants to do it your way,'' Marinelli said of his first season. ''The players who didn't fit, boom, I moved them out.''</p>
        <p>The Lions still need to move in more talent, not only with their first-round pick, but also with their later picks. Millen made a solid choice with his first-round pick last year, taking linebacker Ernie Sims, who led the team in tackles and started all 16 games. But on Saturday, Millen faces even more pressure.</p>
        <p>''Put a target on me,'' Millen said, smiling. ''I understand.''</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
