<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Many in the Department, A Link to a Proud Tradition</title>
    <meta content="26history" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/nyregion/26history.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flags, Emblems and Insignia</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Trymaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flags, Emblems and Insignia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E5DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Many in the Department, A Link to a Proud Tradition</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">To Many in the Department, a Link to a Proud Tradition</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRYMAINE LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Trymaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patches worn by New York City firefighters relate to fire company's history or community; eagle on patch of Engine 216 in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, is throwback to early 1900s, when its firehouse was on Segal Street and its firefighters were known as Segal Eagles; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Collectively, patches worn by New York City firefighters form a quilt, a tapestry intertwining the history of the city and that of the Fire Department, an institution with century-old standing in some of the city's oldest neighborhoods, the affluent and the afflicted alike.</p>
        <p>There are the Harlem Hose Trotters of Engine 36. And Engine 55 in Little Italy, known as Cinquenta Cinque, and Engine 34's 38th Street Mutts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Collectively, patches worn by New York City firefighters form a quilt, a tapestry intertwining the history of the city and that of the Fire Department, an institution with century-old standing in some of the city’s oldest neighborhoods, the affluent and the afflicted alike.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Collectively, patches worn by New York City firefighters form a quilt, a tapestry intertwining the history of the city and that of the Fire Department, an institution with century-old standing in some of the city's oldest neighborhoods, the affluent and the afflicted alike.</p>
        <p>There are the Harlem Hose Trotters of Engine 36. And Engine 55 in Little Italy, known as Cinquenta Cinque, and Engine 34's 38th Street Mutts.</p>
        <p>In Brooklyn, there are the Lords of Flatbush of Engine 310. In Queens there are Engine 301, the Hollis Hogs, and Engine 324's Queens Burros. Engine 94 and Ladder 48 in the Bronx represent the Hunts Point neighborhood as the Hunts Point Devils, and their borough brethren at Engine 64 are the Castle Hill Gang.</p>
        <p>In the turbulent 1970s, when arson and outrage engulfed the South Bronx, it was the men of Engine 82 and Ladder 31 at La Casa Grande, or The Big House, who quelled the flames. Those firefighters were chronicled in the 1972 BBC documentary ''Man Alive: The Bronx Is Burning,'' which told the companies' tale.</p>
        <p>In Williamsburg, Brooklyn, at the firehouse of Engine 216 and Ladder 108 (the Pride of Williamsburg), Firefighter John Orlando sat in a lounge with others from the two companies.</p>
        <p>Behind them were three large murals, depictions of the patches of the battalion chief and the engine and ladder companies housed there.</p>
        <p>For the ladder company, the mural showed a large flying eagle, its wings spread wide in front of a streaming American flag as flames rise beneath it.</p>
        <p>For the engine company, the mural depicted a water hose wrapped around a Maltese cross, whose arms contained a hook, a ladder, a shamrock and a fire hydrant.</p>
        <p>The company's eagle is a throwback symbol from the early 1900s, when the engine's firehouse was on Segal Street. The firefighters were known as the Segal Eagles back then. But the company was forced to its current address, on Union Avenue, by budget cuts and civil unrest in the turbulent 1970s and 1980s. Frustrations and tensions in Brooklyn then broke out in occasional violence between those at the firehouse and members of the community.</p>
        <p>''Our patch, it's something that gives a message to everyone else,'' Firefighter Orlando said. ''Company pride. It's about the people that have come before us, through our house. It's not so much for us.''</p>
        <p>It is for firefighters like Danny Suhr of Engine 216, the first firefighter confirmed to have been killed on Sept. 11, firefighters there said. And like William Baldwin, who was part of Engine 116, the predecessor of 216, who in 1880 became the first member of the Brooklyn Fire Department to be killed on duty. .</p>
        <p>''Your patch is your patch,'' said Glenn Tracy, a fourth-generation firefighter in Ladder Company 108. ''This is your house, where you started. And it's about passing on the tradition to the young firefighters, about the guys who walked through this same door and wore the same patch.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
