<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Is Lax On Loans, Cuomo Says</title>
    <meta content="26loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/us/26loans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cuomo, Andrew M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Is Lax On Loans, Cuomo Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Is Lax on Loans, Cuomo Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN D. GLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glater, Jonathan D</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Atty Gen Andrew M Cuomo accuses federal Education Dept of being lax in regulating student loan industry; says criminal charges might result from his continuing investigation into ties between universities and lenders (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York's attorney general on Wednesday accused the federal Education Department of being lax in regulating the student loan industry and said that criminal charges might result from his continuing investigation into ties between universities and lenders.</p>
        <p>In testimony before the House education committee, the attorney general, Andrew M. Cuomo, said that as the housing secretary in the Clinton administration he was ''not quick to criticize'' a federal agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York’s attorney general accused the federal Education Department of being lax in regulating the student loan industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York's attorney general on Wednesday accused the federal Education Department of being lax in regulating the student loan industry and said that criminal charges might result from his continuing investigation into ties between universities and lenders.</p>
        <p>In testimony before the House education committee, the attorney general, Andrew M. Cuomo, said that as the housing secretary in the Clinton administration he was ''not quick to criticize'' a federal agency.</p>
        <p>''However,'' he said, ''I believe in this case, the Department of Education has been asleep at the switch.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo also announced that two more banks, JPMorgan Chase and Bank of America, had signed on to a code of conduct barring lenders from giving financial incentives to universities, or payments or trips to university officials, to win favor for the lender.</p>
        <p>Representative George Miller, the California Democrat who is chairman of the committee, said that he had asked Education Secretary Margaret Spellings to testify and criticized the department's ''slowness to react to the situation.'' Ms. Spellings is scheduled to appear May 10.</p>
        <p>Ms. Spellings, in a statement, said she shared Mr. Cuomo's concerns about lender practices but called his testimony ''ill-informed on the department's actions and on federal law.''</p>
        <p>She said it was ''misleading'' to suggest that a violation of state law on fraud or deceptive trade practices was also a violation of federal law governing lenders participating in the guaranteed student loan program.</p>
        <p>She also said the department was investigating, ''whether, in fact, there have been'' such violations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo said his investigation into the $85 billion student loan industry had uncovered abuses concerning both private loans -- those that are not guaranteed by the federal government -- and those in the federal program that the department regulates. ''This is one of those situations that cries out for a federal response,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo recounted instances of colleges receiving payments from lenders based on the amount students borrowed; of financial aid administrators receiving trips and other benefits from lenders; and of loan companies operating call centers on their behalf. Such relationships are not disclosed to students, said Mr. Cuomo, whose inquiry began in January.</p>
        <p>In response to questions, he said that some of his findings could result in criminal charges.</p>
        <p>He said there was ''significant evidence'' of abuse in the federal loan program. He said that a Columbia University financial aid officer now on leave had obtained stock in a federally subsidized lender which was placed on the list of loan companies recommended to students.</p>
        <p>Both Democrats and Republicans on the committee are calling for legislation to toughen regulation of the loan industry, and Ms. Spellings has created a task force to make recommendations to her by the end of next month.</p>
        <p>The questioning of Mr. Cuomo also indicated that a battle is brewing over competing federal loan programs -- one in which the government gives out loans directly to students, the other in which it pays subsidies to private companies that give out loans and guarantees them against default.</p>
        <p>Representative Ric Keller, a Florida Republican, showed his skepticism toward the direct loan program in his questioning of Mr. Cuomo. If the Education Department was so lax, he asked, ''Why should we put the federal Department of Education in charge of all student loans?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo did not take a stand in favor of either program, but said that the department ''retrospectively and prospectively should be doing a better job of oversight'' of the guaranteed loan program.</p>
        <p>Separately on Wednesday, Johns Hopkins University joined the growing list of institutions that have adopted Mr. Cuomo's code of conduct. It also announced that a financial aid director, Ellen Frishberg, had more consulting arrangements than previously reported and that she had not cleared them with the university.</p>
        <p>She had already been put on leave after Mr. Cuomo's office had found that she had worked as a consultant for one company, Student Loan Xpress, now a unit of CIT Group, and that the company had paid for part of her graduate school tuition.</p>
        <p>Ms. Frishberg could not be reached for comment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
