<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As War Grinds On, So Does the Sparring</title>
    <meta content="l26iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0DE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As War Grinds On, So Does the Sparring</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bush and Cheney Chide Democrats on Iraq Deadline'' (front page, April 25):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Bush and Cheney Chide Democrats on Iraq Deadline'' (front page, April 25):</p>
        <p>The Congressional Democrats are doing exactly what I voted for them to do: trying to rein in the excesses of this disastrous war in Iraq, and beginning the arduous process of cutting our losses.</p>
        <p>I firmly believe that President Bush and Vice President Dick Cheney are trying to run out the clock so that they do not have to admit to failure while in office. Of course, once they are out of office, they will blame subsequent events on their successors.</p>
        <p>Their accusations of political motivation by Democrats are transparent and inexcusable. How much more of other people's blood are they willing to spill to save face, and to continue to deny the will of the American people?</p>
        <p>Jonathan Gordon  New York, April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>After the president has wielded his threatened veto, the Democrats should go back to the drawing board and propose the following:</p>
        <p>We ask the Iraqi government and Parliament to decide formally whether they want coalition forces to stay or go. If Parliament does not have a majority for a request that we stay, we will pack up and leave as quickly as possible in a safe, orderly manner.</p>
        <p>If the government and Parliament go on record as wanting coalition forces to stay, we would leave a force large enough to provide Iraqi forces with needed training, reconstruction and logistic support, intelligence support in tracking foreign fighters, and its own force protection.</p>
        <p>It would stay as long as both sides agree that it is necessary and desirable, with no timetable for departure. It would have no combat role in dealing with internal sectarian conflict.</p>
        <p>A force of 50,000 to 70,000 would probably suffice. I don't believe that the president could sustain a veto against such a course of action.</p>
        <p>Ronald I. Spiers  South Londonderry, Vt.  April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer was assistant and under secretary of state and ambassador in the Middle East in Republican and Democratic administrations.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The president accuses Democrats of making military decisions that should be left to the generals, but isn't that what he and his team have done since the war planning started and a large reason we're in the mess we're in now?</p>
        <p>And why should anyone listen to the president or his supporters? They've had more than four years to resolve the situation and have done nothing but botched it, with no end in sight.</p>
        <p>Calvin Hilton  Jacksonville, Fla., April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Given the low regard in which President Bush has historically held bills passed by Congress with his signing statements, I am mystified by his sudden desire to start respecting the legislative process.</p>
        <p>If he disagrees with only the timetable part of the bill, why does he suddenly hesitate to single out this provision with a signing statement, as he has with every other legislative provision that has not been to his liking?</p>
        <p>The president's sudden appreciation for process strikes me as both cynical and ineffective in the face of public opinion.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Statmore  San Francisco, April 25, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
