<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buffalo's Vanek Makes Sure Playoff Return Is Not Just Repeat</title>
    <meta content="26sabres" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/hockey/26sabres.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EEDC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buffalo's Vanek Makes Sure Playoff Return Is Not Just Repeat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vanek Makes Sure His Return to Playoffs Is Not Just a Repeat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT HIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Higgins, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO, April 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Buffalo Sabres wing Thomas Vanek takes nothing for granted anymore. Not after what happened during last year's playoffs. So on the morning before the Sabres played the Rangers in Game 1 of their Eastern Conference semifinal series, Vanek suggested he could be benched.</p>
        <p>''Who knows?'' he said. ''In the second round it might happen again.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thomas Vanek scored two goals, including the winner in a 5-2 Buffalo win Wednesday night to take a 1-0 lead in their series with the Rangers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Buffalo Sabres wing Thomas Vanek takes nothing for granted anymore. Not after what happened during last year's playoffs. So on the morning before the Sabres played the Rangers in Game 1 of their Eastern Conference semifinal series, Vanek suggested he could be benched.</p>
        <p>''Who knows?'' he said. ''In the second round it might happen again.''</p>
        <p>After Vanek's performance Wednesday night, that is unlikely. Vanek scored two goals, including what proved to be the winner, as Buffalo won, 5-2. Game 2 is here Friday.</p>
        <p>The first period was scoreless Wednesday, but the Sabres produced three goals 4 minutes 5 seconds apart late in the second period.</p>
        <p>''I think we played well,'' Rangers goalie Henrik Lundqvist said, ''but when they scored the first goal, they played smart. Maybe we tried to tie the game right away and pinched a little bit more, and they went the other way and scored two goals pretty fast.</p>
        <p>''We know they're a fast team. We have to be aware of how we have to play out there, manage the puck well. Every time we lose it, they come hard.''</p>
        <p>It seemed a long time ago that Vanek, a first-round draft pick in 2003, sat out 8 of Buffalo's final 11 playoff games last season during a run to the Eastern Conference finals. But the sting of being benched still bothers him, and he prefers not to discuss it, especially when it seems like such ancient history.</p>
        <p>This season, Vanek led the Sabres with 43 goals, and he led the N.H.L. in plus-minus at plus-47. With such staggering numbers, it would be difficult to imagine Sabres Coach Lindy Ruff benching Vanek. But Ruff has not coddled him.</p>
        <p>''It's been a learning year,'' Ruff said of Vanek's second N.H.L. season. ''It's been a growing year. It's been a maturing year, and I still feel it is.''</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Vanek gave the Sabres a 1-0 lead with 5 minutes 41 seconds to play in the second period. With Buffalo on the power play, Vanek tipped a blast from the point between Lundqvist's pads.</p>
        <p>Ales Kotalik made it 2-0 two minutes later, and Vanek's second goal gave the Sabres a three-goal lead with 1:36 to play in the period.</p>
        <p>Vanek raced to the left of Lundqvist, and when defenseman Paul Mara slid to prevent a pass, Vanek stepped around him into the slot and snapped the puck high into the net.</p>
        <p>Vanek made a similar nifty play to help clinch the Sabres' opening-round series against the Islanders. Then, rushing up the left side, he faked a move inside and put the puck between defenseman Tom Poti's legs. He then dropped a pass to Maxim Afinogenov, who scored the winning goal.</p>
        <p>''I named it 'Vanek's move,' '' Kotalik said. ''That's what he does that's so great. He makes the defenseman think he's going to cut to the middle, and then he puts it through his legs.''</p>
        <p>The turnaround for Vanek came after a commitment to conditioning last off-season.</p>
        <p>''He was frustrated, obviously,'' Kotalik said. ''He was the second-best scorer on the team before the last playoffs. Then he got sat in some of the series. It frustrated him.''</p>
        <p>Vanek scored 25 goals as a rookie in 2005-6, but he was minus-11. And in the playoffs, he had two goals, with no assists, in 10 games.</p>
        <p>But he arrived at training camp in better shape with a renewed determination this season, Ruff said.</p>
        <p>''He's become a tremendous two-way player,'' Ruff said. ''His play away from the puck has gotten a lot better. I think it all started with conditioning. He put himself in that position, and he rewarded himself by believing that you get in that type of shape and it will help your game.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
