<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Walker, Corzine Takes First Steps Since Accident</title>
    <meta content="26corzine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/nyregion/26corzine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seat Belts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Trenton (NJ)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E1DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Walker, Corzine Takes First Steps Since Accident</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Corzine Takes His First Steps Since Car Crash</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN; Nate Schweber contributed reporting from Camden, N.J.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Gov Jon S Corzine takes his first steps with assistance of a walker since he was seriously injured in car accident; is still receiving pain medication and antibiotics to prevent any infection to his left leg; could be released from hospital on April 30; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the assistance of a walker, Gov. Jon S. Corzine took his first steps on Wednesday since he was seriously injured in a car accident two weeks ago, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>In his daily e-mail update on Mr. Corzine's condition at Cooper University Hospital in Camden, Anthony Coley, Mr. Corzine's communications director, also said that signs of the governor's having suffered a possible infection to the trachea, or windpipe, had cleared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey is still receiving pain medication, and antibiotics to prevent any infection in his left leg, which was fractured in two places.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the assistance of a walker, Gov. Jon S. Corzine took his first steps on Wednesday since he was seriously injured in a car accident two weeks ago, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>In his daily e-mail update on Mr. Corzine's condition at Cooper University Hospital in Camden, Anthony Coley, Mr. Corzine's communications director, also said that signs of the governor's having suffered a possible infection to the trachea, or windpipe, had cleared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine is still receiving pain medication, and antibiotics to prevent any infection in his left leg, which was fractured in two places during the accident. But Tom Shea, Mr. Corzine's chief of staff, said that the governor could be released from the hospital as soon as Monday.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Corzine, a Democrat in his second year in office, was feeling strong enough on Wednesday to take a call from someone with whom he has disagreed vehemently over policy in recent years: President Bush.</p>
        <p>''They spoke casually for a few minutes, and the governor thanked the president for his call and well wishes,'' Mr. Coley said in the e-mail statement.</p>
        <p>As with any recovery from a serious injury, progress is often measured by small victories, and the fact that Mr. Corzine took a few steps on two occasions Wednesday -- although he was left exhausted by the effort -- was celebrated as a milestone by his staff. After all, it was only last Friday that Mr. Corzine was disconnected from the ventilator that had helped him breathe for more than a week, and only Monday that he was moved from the intensive care unit.</p>
        <p>Doctors worried that he might remain vulnerable to infection, but Mr. Shea said on Wednesday that everyone was amazed by the pace of the governor's recovery. On Tuesday, Mr. Corzine, who also broke 11 ribs, his sternum and a collarbone in the crash, sat upright in a chair for the first time, for more than an hour -- something doctors had said a day earlier would probably not happen until the end of the week.</p>
        <p>Doctors also removed a catheter from Mr. Corzine's back on Tuesday, which was earlier than expected.</p>
        <p>He is back on a normal diet, and the fact that Mr. Corzine, a confirmed carnivore, consumed a cheeseburger and a milkshake on Monday was proof that his taste buds had not changed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, 60, was not wearing a seat belt when his sport utility vehicle collided with a pickup truck and slammed into a guard rail on April 12. The trooper who was driving, at 91 miles per hour with emergency lights flashing, and the aide in the back seat both escaped with only minor injuries.</p>
        <p>The governor's aides have refused to allow reporters or photographers to see him, and it remains unclear when he will greet visitors beyond the small circle of family, friends and aides who have been in to see him so far.</p>
        <p>It is still too early to say when Mr. Corzine will be back in charge. Nor is it clear where the governor will undergo the rehabilitation that his doctors and aides have said will be arduous and likely to last for several months. But legislators, lobbyists and administration officials say that it would be preferable for Mr. Corzine to be closer to Trenton than his apartment in Hoboken, given the expectation that his mobility and energy will be limited.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
