<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Infant Deaths: Shame of a Nation</title>
    <meta content="l26south" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stress (Human)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EFDE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Infant Deaths: Shame of a Nation</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''In Turnabout, Infant Deaths Climb in South'' (front page, April 22):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''In Turnabout, Infant Deaths Climb in South'' (front page, April 22):</p>
        <p>When my colleagues and I started a community health center in the Mississippi Delta in the 1960s, we estimated the actual black infant mortality rate in our area at nearly 60 per thousand live births.</p>
        <p>The causes were abysmal poverty, wide unemployment, crumbling shacks, outright malnutrition, contaminated water and lack of transportation.</p>
        <p>We addressed those problems, in addition to providing desperately needed medical care. The infant mortality rate dropped sharply.</p>
        <p>Those causes persist, now worsened by deep cuts in Medicaid and welfare.</p>
        <p>The consequence of shredding the social safety net is more dead black (and white) babies. No health service can overcome the effects of social policies that devastate the lives of the poor.</p>
        <p>This is not just a health problem; it is a measure of our moral commitment to a fair chance for survival. We should be enraged, and ashamed, that these preventable excess deaths continue, and increase, among us.</p>
        <p>H. Jack Geiger, M.D.  Brooklyn, April 25, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer was a founding member and national coordinator of the Medical Committee for Human Rights.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It is troubling that progress in reducing the black infant mortality rate has stagnated and that the rate is rising in Mississippi.</p>
        <p>For half a century, the black infant mortality rate has been approximately double the white rate. This disparity is complex and cannot be explained solely by medical or socioeconomic factors.</p>
        <p>We know that the mortality rate of infants of foreign-born black women in this country is significantly lower than for infants of native-born black mothers and that Hispanics, in spite of high poverty and very low education rates, have infant mortality similar to whites.</p>
        <p>It is likely that this new trend among blacks in areas of the South is related, in some fashion, to chronic emotional stress secondary to persistent poverty, a feeling of hopelessness, racial discrimination and health conditions.</p>
        <p>A comprehensive approach beyond just the medical model is called for.</p>
        <p>Patrick Dowling, M.D.  Los Angeles, April 24, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is a professor and chairman of the department of family medicine, David Geffen School of Medicine at U.C.L.A.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your article shows what many in the public health community have long known to be true: reductions in public health services and insurance programs, especially on a state or community level, have very real health consequences. Infant mortality is the most sensitive measure of that health impact.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more important, however, is your portrayal of the strong connection between health and poverty. While aggregate health measures in the United States have greatly improved over the last century, there remain vast regional, racial and economic health inequities, as your article demonstrates.</p>
        <p>To target these inequities, public policy must adopt a broader perspective that recognizes the importance of the socioeconomic determinants of health.</p>
        <p>Alexander Hertel-Fernandez  Evanston, Ill., April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a medical student at an inner-city hospital, I see poverty all the time, but not the poor black towns in your article. We have pockets worthy of the third world in our midst, and no one has noticed it until now! It's about time that health care is brought back to the forefront of the political ground; no mother should bury a baby just because somewhere along the way, somebody forgot that people like her need help.</p>
        <p>Farheen Qurashi  Mission, Kan., April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Everywhere across this country, you will find similar issues associated with the infant mortality: pre- and post-natal care, poverty, access to medical care, health insurance and so on.</p>
        <p>When we conducted our analysis of infant mortality in Tennessee last year, we found that even when we controlled for income, African-American mothers had a higher infant mortality rate than white mothers. Why is this? We need to look at other plausible risk factors like intergenerational stress among African-American populations.</p>
        <p>Pramod Dwivedi  Nashville, April 22, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer, an epidemiologist at the Tennessee Department of Mental Health and Developmental Disabilities, was formerly with the Tennessee Department of Health.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Sometimes, people reject help because of the manner in which it's offered. I discovered in the course of a long career as a community mental health worker that it is vitally important to avoid making potential service recipients feel even more inferior than many already feel, albeit mistakenly.</p>
        <p>It is quite easy, sadly, to rush to judgment in the helping professions. When that happens, we can expect that some people we are offering to help will view refusal as the best means of preserving their dignity.</p>
        <p>Vanessa Whippo  Danville, Ill., April 22, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
