<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dues Paid, Stringer Is Realizing Rewards</title>
    <meta content="26araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/ncaabasketball/26araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stringer, C Vivian</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schiano, Greg</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFDC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dues Paid, Stringer Is Realizing Rewards</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dues Paid, Stringer Is Realizing Rewards</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The contract renegotiation, as stipulated by the existing deal before its year of expiration, was being considered for months and was a subject raised publicly in Cleveland at the Final Four.</p>
        <p>''The book situation,'' as C. Vivian Stringer referred to the sale of her autobiography last week to Crown Publishing, was a project she had been working on for more than a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rutgers women’s basketball Coach C. Vivian Stringer signed a contract extension that will pay her the same base salary that Greg Schiano, the football coach, receives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The contract renegotiation, as stipulated by the existing deal before its year of expiration, was being considered for months and was a subject raised publicly in Cleveland at the Final Four.</p>
        <p>''The book situation,'' as C. Vivian Stringer referred to the sale of her autobiography last week to Crown Publishing, was a project she had been working on for more than a year.</p>
        <p>These were the timelines she apparently felt compelled to share during a telephone news conference yesterday to announce that she would continue coaching at Rutgers, earning up to $950,000 a season, the score of her life, for the next seven years.</p>
        <p>Fair enough, she said, pointing out that she had spent the first third of her 36-year career at Cheyney State, where she ''didn't make a dime.''</p>
        <p>Now Stringer's base pay of $450,000, more than doubled, equals that of the Rutgers's football savior, Greg Schiano. Now her compelling life story, still lacking a national championship, has a defining moment -- thanks to the radio shock jock Don Imus, who couldn't let Stringer and her players enjoy their moment of celebrity and success.</p>
        <p>With his crude remarks, Imus unwittingly made Rutgers the most prominent team and Stringer the most recognizable coach in the women's game.</p>
        <p>Pat Summitt, the industry's longtime queen, could win 70 more titles to go with the seven she already has and she won't get the national exposure Stringer received earlier this month after losing to Summitt and Tennessee in the national championship game.</p>
        <p>To answer Imus, Stringer got up in front of the country April 10, talked nonstop for 36 minutes -- one for every year as a head coach -- with the unbridled passion she demands from her players on the defensive side of the ball. Here was her chance to win a different kind of national title and Imus, a megamillionaire talkie, didn't stand a chance.</p>
        <p>In the blogosphere and beyond, Stringer has since been criticized for monopolizing the stage, for using it to market her program. Did she carry on too long? She always has. Anyone who knows her -- or so much as sat through one of her news conferences -- expected no less.</p>
        <p>With an audience that was finally bigger than the modest congregation that passes for the women's basketball news media, Stringer was just being herself, long winded and emotional and feisty. The Pennsylvania coal miner's daughter, who has kept talking, kept coaching, despite enough tragedy in her life to fill 500 pages of an autobiography.</p>
        <p>Some have suggested that Rutgers's best response would have been no response at all. A brilliant idea, if only Imus's show had no impact in shaping public opinion. But why else were politicians and authors begging to get on all these years? Not because they had nothing better to do in the morning.</p>
        <p>''How else were we going to do it, send it on a doggone e-mail?'' Stringer said. ''I don't think so.''</p>
        <p>If there has been criticism against Rutgers in general and Stringer in particular for ''Stepping Up and Standing Tall'' (tentative book title), she said it was news to her and she didn't much care. Then again, at times on the telephone yesterday, she sounded a bit too defensive, wary of being labeled an opportunist.</p>
        <p>That was unfortunate. Stringer and her players are the last people with any explaining to do. And if her leverage soared as a result of the controversy, if Rutgers was under pressure to pay and the publishers suddenly realized she no longer needed the title to sell books, more power to her. She's paid her dues.</p>
        <p>Timing is everything, as it was for Schiano, when one victory over a top 10 opponent, Louisville, was enough for Miami to want him and for Rutgers to make sure he was happy enough to stay.</p>
        <p>How many college coaches sign an extension and walk away from the deal 20 minutes later? The latest was Joanne P. McCallie, declaring her signed loyalty to Michigan State one week, fleeing to Duke the next, more proof that the women's game is well on its way to becoming too much like the men's.</p>
        <p>For her part, Stringer, the throwback, said she had no conversations with the big-time programs that had coaching vacancies this spring. She never promised not to. She just didn't.</p>
        <p>She left Cheyney State for the University of Iowa after her young daughter was left severely disabled by spinal meningitis. Stringer returned to Rutgers 12 years ago to escape the sadness after the death of her husband.</p>
        <p>''My moves were for personal reasons, not professional,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Sometimes personal and professional interests become impossibly tangled and that's just the way it is. Stringer stood up for her players, spoke from the heart. America stopped to listen. Imus got fired. Hillary Clinton turned Rutgers into a campaign stop on the presidential trail. Stringer's story became publishable. She became one of the highest-paid women's coaches in the country, without having won the big prize.</p>
        <p>''We do have coaches that have stepped in, won one national championship and faded out for life,'' she said, again playing her trademark defense.</p>
        <p>No need to, really. No need to apologize or rationalize the contract, the book and especially the long speech. Much as she likes to talk, Stringer didn't go looking for the forum. It found her. She was just who she is.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
