<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Johnson Has No Baggage and a Seat in First Class</title>
    <meta content="26draft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/football/26draft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070428T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Calvin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFDC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1443" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Johnson Has No Baggage and a Seat in First Class</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Johnson Has No Baggage and a Seat in First Class</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Calvin Johnson's favorite is the one-handed, behind-the-back grab from his freshman year at Georgia Tech. It is an Internet hit, too, a did-he-just-do-that beauty from a career that has wrapped surpassing brilliance on the field in a quiet cocoon of politeness.</p>
        <p>With Johnson, there is no trash-talking. No arrests. No celebrations. The best wide receiver -- perhaps the best player -- in this weekend's N.F.L. draft has created a few local legends, but no legendary outbursts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Calvin Johnson, the best wide receiver and perhaps the best player in this weekend’s N.F.L. draft, has created a few local legends, but no legendary outbursts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Calvin Johnson's favorite is the one-handed, behind-the-back grab from his freshman year at Georgia Tech. It is an Internet hit, too, a did-he-just-do-that beauty from a career that has wrapped surpassing brilliance on the field in a quiet cocoon of politeness.</p>
        <p>With Johnson, there is no trash-talking. No arrests. No celebrations. The best wide receiver -- perhaps the best player -- in this weekend's N.F.L. draft has created a few local legends, but no legendary outbursts.</p>
        <p>He once sat down a high school teammate in the lane of the basketball court, and with a running start leapt over him and dunked a basketball -- while wearing a backpack. As a freshman at Georgia Tech, he outjumped the vertical jump machine.</p>
        <p>But when Johnson said that his third-down catch on a ball thrown well behind him against North Carolina State is ''the best catch I've ever made,'' it is as close as he comes to bragging. There is nothing on the game film to signify how remarkable the catch was.</p>
        <p>When Johnson attempted a leaping high-five of a teammate after another particularly breathtaking reception, Johnson accidentally jumped too close and all 239 pounds of him hit his teammate so hard that the teammate nearly sailed into a back flip. That, his roommate Taylor Bennett said, was the end of the celebrations.</p>
        <p>Johnson is the player who may return humility to elite wide receivers and who may soothe Commissioner Roger Goodell's soul when the N.F.L. begins its draft Saturday. In the league's nascent era of tough love, Johnson would be an apt first overall pick, fitting as neatly into a campaign for good behavior as he does in Nike's ubiquitous campaign featuring the top draft prospects.</p>
        <p>That the 6-foot-5 Johnson is a beguiling combination of chiseled size, speed (an astounding 4.35 in the 40-yard dash) and leaping ability (a 42 1/2-inch vertical jump, an 11-foot-7-inch long jump) is what the scouts notice first. But next comes the humility, so seemingly out of place for a player who could wind up as a teammate of the famously outspoken malcontent receivers Randy Moss and Jerry Porter on the Oakland Raiders.</p>
        <p>''I'm just riding the wave,'' Johnson said yesterday, so reserved that he could barely be heard over the din of sirens in Chinatown. ''It's something I picked up from my home training.''</p>
        <p>There, he was in the cradle of a family that stressed education; one sister is in medical school. He said that his father, Calvin Johnson Sr., a railroad conductor, ''wouldn't tolerate a lot of being foolish.''</p>
        <p>Johnson attended high school in Tyrone, Ga., a suburb of Atlanta, in a school district regularly ranked among the highest achieving in Georgia. It was why he chose Georgia Tech instead of the University of Georgia, where he surely would have played with a better quarterback who could have helped boost his statistics. It was why his mother, Arica, made clear that he was not going to enter the Major League Baseball draft out of high school despite scouts being interested in him as a shortstop. And it was why he would not play both sports in college after she discussed the nonstop athletic calendar with Georgia Tech coaches.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't going to let him be drafted, anyway,'' said Arica, who has a doctorate and works in the Atlanta public school system. ''He needed to grow and mature.''</p>
        <p>By then, it was clear that Johnson had N.F.L. potential. As a high school senior, he went to a camp at Georgia Tech and ran a 40-yard dash. His high school coach, Chip Walker, said that he had timed him in 4.3 seconds. Georgia Tech, he said, had him at 4.1. He was already 6-4 and about 205 pounds.</p>
        <p>Johnson played immediately as a freshman at Georgia Tech in 2004. He was an all-American as a sophomore and a junior despite playing with a quarterback whose completion percentage usually hovered around 50 percent. Georgia Tech Coach Chan Gailey, a former coach of the Dallas Cowboys, has said that Johnson is the best he has ever had, a sweeping statement that encompasses the Hall of Famer Michael Irvin.</p>
        <p>''It's the combination of size, speed and character that has made him a special young man,'' Gailey said. ''The worst thing in the world is to have one of your premier players being someone that nobody likes or trusts or that you can believe in. Those character issues are very big, in my opinion, especially for top draft choices you're going to invest a ton of money in.''</p>
        <p>Only two receivers have been the top overall pick since 1970 -- Irving Fryar in 1984 and Keyshawn Johnson in 1996 -- but Calvin Johnson has the potential to be the third, especially because the ever-unpredictable Raiders hold the top pick.</p>
        <p>According to Gil Brandt, the former personnel chief for the Cowboys who analyzes the draft for NFL.com, the biggest area of failure in the first round is at wide receiver. By his count, 29 receivers were selected in the first round from 1997 to 2003. Fourteen are no longer in the league. Only four have made the Pro Bowl. Those numbers give general managers shivers, especially because the best receivers only touch the ball perhaps 10 times a game.</p>
        <p>But Johnson has overwhelmed those doubts. Brandt compares Johnson physically with Terrell Owens, before adding quickly that Johnson does not drop passes. Tampa Bay Coach Jon Gruden, who is thought to covet Johnson (the Buccaneers pick fourth), joked at the recent N.F.L. meetings that he tried to find something Johnson could not do. Gruden patted his head and rubbed his stomach at the same time, wondering if Johnson could do that. Raiders Coach Lane Kiffin said that Johnson ''seems perfect.''</p>
        <p>Bruce Arians, the Pittsburgh Steelers' offensive coordinator, said: ''In my 15 years, he is probably the best-looking prospect at his position that I have seen. His numbers are astronomical, but his play is even better. This guy is special.''</p>
        <p>Teams have certainly tried to find some dirt, their scouts calling Walker for information. Walker tells them that Johnson is the best blocker he has ever had at any position, embracing an anonymous and brutal role that most elite receivers avoid. And he tells them that Johnson still responds with ''Yes, sir.''</p>
        <p>''With Calvin, there's no baggage,'' Walker said. ''Some of the things that may be important to athletes today, the big time of having your face on TV, being at the biggest party, being at big events, those things do not fit Calvin's personality. Those are things he wouldn't care about. It's hard to get him to talk about himself.''</p>
        <p>Last week, Pro Football Weekly reported that Johnson was one of three top prospects who acknowledged in confidential interviews with team officials that they had smoked marijuana. The leak of information has upset the league, but draft analysts and team executives say that the revelation should be spun in his favor, a testament to his honesty.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't nervous about it,'' Johnson said. ''That was just an incident of trying to hurt my stock in the draft. I had nothing to hide. I'm an honest guy.''</p>
        <p>It was, though, part of the draft circus that has descended on Johnson and his family. Johnson Sr. still seems to marvel that nobody else in the family is particularly athletic. He said that when Calvin was younger, the family never sent him to elite camps to prepare to be a football player. Johnson's natural reticence means that despite his star power, he has never courted headlines. And so the avalanche of attention paid to him now seems especially incongruous.</p>
        <p>''It's surreal,'' Johnson Sr. said in a telephone interview. ''I sit here and I have the TV on, and I hear his name called constantly, andpeople want to ask me about my son. I joke with my daughter -- she's interested in cancer research -- that she put all the years in medical school and he's going to beat her.''</p>
        <p>But Johnson seems to be approaching his life-changing moment with the same equanimity with which he took what will soon be the second-most intriguing job he has had: trying to design a better latrine to reduce disease in poor countries.</p>
        <p>Johnson, who is about a year and a half of class work away from a degree in management, volunteered for a project to help design a latrine that could heat-treat human waste, built from materials that cost less than $100. Maybe there is a metaphor there for how Johnson will handle the sometimes seamy temptations that have bedeviled so many professional athletes.</p>
        <p>''It was interesting,'' Johnson said. ''I've got nothing to be ashamed of.''</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 28, 2007, Saturday  Because of an editing error, a sports article on Thursday about receiver Calvin Johnson on the eve of the N.F.L. draft misattributed a quotation about the influence of his family's values on Johnson. It was Johnson's father, Calvin Sr. -- not Johnson himself -- who said the family ''wouldn't tolerate a lot of being foolish.'' The article also referred imprecisely to Johnson's leaping ability. He performed an 11-foot-7-inch standing long jump, not just a long jump.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 28, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a sports article on Thursday about receiver Calvin Johnson on the eve of the N.F.L. draft misattributed a quotation about the influence of his family's values on Johnson. It was Johnson's father, Calvin Sr. -- not Johnson himself -- who said the family ''wouldn't tolerate a lot of being foolish.'' The article also referred imprecisely to Johnson's leaping ability. He performed an 11-foot-7-inch standing long jump, not just a long jump.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
