<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Durable-Goods Picture Shows Surprising Strength</title>
    <meta content="26econ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/business/26econ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Durable Goods (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Durable Goods (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DD153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Durable-Goods Picture Shows Surprising Strength</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Durable-Goods Picture Shows Surprising Strength</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY W. PETERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peters, Jeremy W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the housing market dragged yet again last month, business picked up much of the slack and helped keep the economy on track.</p>
        <p>Data released yesterday allayed fears that business investment was about to falter, raising expectations that decent economic growth can continue while the pullback in residential real estate runs its course.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New data on durable goods orders raised expectations that decent economic growth can continue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the housing market dragged yet again last month, business picked up much of the slack and helped keep the economy on track.</p>
        <p>Data released yesterday allayed fears that business investment was about to falter, raising expectations that decent economic growth can continue while the pullback in residential real estate runs its course.</p>
        <p>Businesses placed more orders last month for heavy-duty items like machinery and electrical equipment, the Commerce Department reported. Coming the same day as lackluster new home sales data and a survey by the Federal Reserve that described growth in most regions of the country as modest, the report helped lift stocks to a record close.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department's monthly survey of durable goods spending found that orders rose 3.4 percent in March, to $214.9 billion, a larger figure than Wall Street had expected.</p>
        <p>Even more notable was a closely watched component of durable goods spending that tracks orders apart from those for military goods and aircraft, known as core capital goods and often viewed as the most useful measure of corporate investment spending plans. It rose 4.7 percent after falling 6.2 percent in January and 2.3 percent in February.</p>
        <p>''The rebound in core capital goods orders is an extremely welcome development,'' Brian Bethune, an economist with Global Insight, a research firm, wrote in a report. The gain, he added, ''should alleviate fears that business investment was on the cusp of spiraling downwards.''</p>
        <p>Over the previous two months, weakening durable goods orders had raised concerns among some analysts that the slowing economy might be on the edge of a downturn. Overall orders plunged 8.8 percent in January and initially showed only a weak gain in February.</p>
        <p>But the Commerce Department said yesterday that February was not as bad as it first calculated, and it revised the figures up 0.6 percentage points to a gain of 2.4 percent.</p>
        <p>The evidence on durable goods, together with healthy profit reports, stoked a broad rally on Wall Street yesterday that propelled the Dow Jones industrial average to close above the 13,000 mark for the first time and brought the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index within striking distance of its all-time record.</p>
        <p>By comparison, when January's durable goods numbers were released Feb. 27, they helped precipitate the stock market's biggest daily percentage loss since 2003.</p>
        <p>Separately, the Commerce Department released its monthly report on new home sales, which showed gains in sales and prices. The seasonally adjusted annual sales rate for new homes rose 2.6 percent in March to 858,000, after declines in January and February. The median price of a new home rose 6.4 percent compared with a year earlier, to $254,000.</p>
        <p>The lift that developers experienced in March, however, was tempered by new data showing that sales in December, January and February were weaker than first thought. Initial calculations overcounted the sales rates in those months by 48,000 homes. That left February as the worst month for new home sales since September 1999.</p>
        <p>Given the problems in the subprime mortgage market, where lenders to people with poor credit histories are now tightening loan standards, economists said that the March data might not tell the full story.</p>
        <p>''It seems very likely that the subprime woes hitting the headlines have hurt consumer confidence, driving the number of contract cancellations higher,'' Dimitry Fleming, an economist with ING Financial Markets, wrote in a research report.</p>
        <p>The new home sales figures do not account for buyers who may have backed out of their contracts. And they only modestly improved the picture offered Tuesday by the National Association of Realtors on sales of previously owned homes; that report found the sharpest monthly drop since 1989 in sales of existing homes, which account for about 80 percent of all homes sold.</p>
        <p>The Fed's beige book report, released yesterday, noted that residential real estate activity throughout the country ''continued to weaken.'' The survey, based on statistical and anecdotal evidence from all 12 Fed district banks, found that the Midwest was the hardest hit, with the Chicago, Minneapolis and St. Louis districts reporting the biggest decreases in home building. In the Minneapolis-St. Paul area, housing permits were down 54 percent in March compared with a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Outside of residential real estate, however, the economy appeared to expand moderately from the end of February to mid-April, the Fed report said. The tone of the report was slightly more upbeat than earlier surveys, referring to growth generally as ''modest or moderate,'' a step up from the ''modest'' but ''some slowing'' noted in the previous beige book.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
