<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Report Criticizes Iraq On Detainees' Treatment</title>
    <meta content="26iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/world/middleeast/26iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Semple, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mizher, Qais</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fathi, Nazila</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7DD153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Report Criticizes Iraq On Detainees' Treatment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.N. Report Criticizes Iraq on Detainees’ Treatment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK SEMPLE; Reporting was contributed by Qais Mizher in Baghdad, Iraqi employees of The New York Times in Kut and Kirkuk, and Nazila Fathi in Tehran.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fathi, Nazila; Mizher, Qais; Semple, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations accuses Iraqi government of failing to 'seriously address' problems of detainee abuse, including torture, and to ensure timely and fair prosecution of detainees; for first time in nine months UN report omits civilian death tolls, saying Iraq is withholding information; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Nations accused the Iraqi government on Wednesday of failing to ''seriously address'' problems of detainee abuse, including torture, and to ensure the timely and fair prosecution of detainees.</p>
        <p>In its latest human rights report on Iraq, the organization expressed special concern about the ''apparent lack'' of judicial guarantees for suspects arrested during the latest security plan for Baghdad, which went into effect in mid-February. The emergency regulations governing the joint Iraqi and American crackdown permit arrests without warrants and open-ended pretrial detentions, the report said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The U.N. accused the Iraqi government of failing to “seriously address” problems of detainee abuse, including torture, and to ensure the timely and fair prosecution of detainees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United Nations accused the Iraqi government on Wednesday of failing to ''seriously address'' problems of detainee abuse, including torture, and to ensure the timely and fair prosecution of detainees.</p>
        <p>In its latest human rights report on Iraq, the organization expressed special concern about the ''apparent lack'' of judicial guarantees for suspects arrested during the latest security plan for Baghdad, which went into effect in mid-February. The emergency regulations governing the joint Iraqi and American crackdown permit arrests without warrants and open-ended pretrial detentions, the report said.</p>
        <p>More than 3,000 people were taken into custody under the security plan during its first seven weeks, the United Nations said. An Iraqi government monitoring group reported late last month that hundreds of people detained in the security crackdown had been jammed into woefully overcrowded detention centers.</p>
        <p>The United Nations report also criticized the government for failing to monitor its security forces sufficiently for human rights violations and to prosecute military and police officials suspected of torturing and abusing detainees.</p>
        <p>''The continuing failure to take decisive action in this regard can only serve to encourage a climate of impunity that prevails today, undermining the government's own efforts to restore law and order and ensure respect for the rule of law,'' said the report, released here by the United Nations Assistance Mission for Iraq.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi government immediately criticized the report, saying it ''lacks credibility in many of its points and lacks balance in its presentation of the human rights situation in Iraq,'' according to a statement issued by the office of Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki. The government did not offer a more specific critique of the document.</p>
        <p>The report was also notable for what it did not include.</p>
        <p>Beginning last summer, reports from the United Nations Assistance Mission for Iraq became the only publicly accessible source of information regarding civilian death tolls in Iraq. But for the first time in nine months, the report issued Wednesday did not contain the death statistics.</p>
        <p>In explaining the omission, United Nations officials said the Iraqi government was now withholding the information.</p>
        <p>The government did not provide the United Nations with an official reason for its decision, Said Arikat, a United Nations spokesman, said in an interview. In ''private conversations,'' the government said it believed that the figures were being used to convey a grim picture of Iraq, Mr. Arikat said, adding, ''But we don't buy that.''</p>
        <p>''It's very important that the public -- the Iraqi public, above all -- knows what's going on,'' he said. ''It's the government's way of showing the public that it's transparent and accountable.''</p>
        <p>In its last human rights report, in January, the United Nations said more than 34,000 Iraqis were killed in 2006. The organization arrived at its figure using reports from morgues, hospitals and municipal authorities across Iraq, though the government called it exaggerated.</p>
        <p>The United Nations said its concerns about the Iraqi detention system also extended to the Kurdish autonomous region in northern Iraq, where, according to the report, hundreds of detainees in have been held ''for prolonged periods, some for several years'' without referral to an investigative judge or without charges being brought against them.</p>
        <p>The report also reiterated the United Nations' long-held concerns about the lack of due process in Iraq's judicial system, saying the criminal courts ''consistently failed to meet minimum fair trial standards.''</p>
        <p>Also on Wednesday, President Jalal Talabani, a Kurd, and the anti-American Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr added their voices to the chorus of criticism concerning a three-mile-long, 12-foot-high wall of concrete barriers the American and Iraqi militaries had begun building along one side of the predominantly Sunni Arab neighborhood of Adhamiya.</p>
        <p>''I do not agree on such barriers,'' Mr. Talabani said while visiting the Kurdish city of Sulaimaniya, according to Agence France-Presse. ''I don't believe this is something good. We can set up less harsh barriers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadr said in a statement read by an aide in Najaf that the wall was ''sectarian, racist and unjust.''</p>
        <p>The plan has provoked a multisectarian groundswell of opposition, prompting Mr. Maliki to order a temporary halt to the wall's construction. On Wednesday, he issued a statement saying that the government was studying alternative solutions to providing security for the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>In Tehran, Iran's foreign minister, Manouchehr Mottaki, said that his country had not decided whether to join a May summit meeting in Egypt about Iraqi security but that it would announce its decision in a few days.</p>
        <p>Hoshyar Zebari, the Iraqi foreign minister, was in Tehran on Wednesday as part of an effort to persuade Iran to take part in the conference. He is also scheduled to meet with President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad.</p>
        <p>The American military command said Wednesday that American forces had killed a top operative of the Islamist insurgent group Al Qaeda in Mesopotamia on Friday. The operative, Muhammad Abdullah Abbas al-Issawi, was the organization's ''security emir'' in the eastern part of Anbar Province, the military said in a statement, adding no further details or confirmation.</p>
        <p>In Diyala Province on Wednesday, a suicide bomber detonated his charge near the front gate of a police station in Baladruz, killing four police officers and wounding 16 people, a police official said. Elsewhere in the province, gunmen killed an Iraqi Army captain, a police official said.</p>
        <p>At least five people were killed and more than a dozen wounded in assorted attacks around Baghdad, including a shooting in the Hurriya neighborhood, a roadside bombing in Shaab and a mortar shell explosion in Disheer, an Interior Ministry official said. An Iraqi soldier died in clashes between the Iraqi Army and insurgents in Amiriya, the official added, and at least 18 bodies were found around the city.</p>
        <p>Two police officers were killed by a roadside bomb south of Kirkuk, police officials said, and two headless bodies, both with multiple bullet holes and signs of torture, were found floating in the Tigris River near the southern city of Kut.</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
