<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Prospect Is in a Spot That Clemens May Fill</title>
    <meta content="26vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/baseball/26vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hughes, Phil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Prospect Is in a Spot That Clemens May Fill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Is Yankee Prospect Holding Space for Clemens?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Torre mentioned Dwight Gooden as an example of a pitcher who was so good, so young. Fans of another generation might come up with Bob Feller. Nobody is expecting Phil Hughes, two months short of his 21st birthday, to be that kind of prodigy, but Hughes will have pressure on him nevertheless when he makes his major league debut tonight.</p>
        <p>With some Yankee fans growing restive, blaming Torre for the injuries to three starting pitchers, Hughes will try to stop the slide that has reached five straight losses. With the Red Sox coming in for the weekend, Andy Pettitte was pushed back until tomorrow after last night's rainout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phil Hughes is being asked to do his part in making the Yankees a team that Roger Clemens could be proud of and want to pitch for.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Torre mentioned Dwight Gooden as an example of a pitcher who was so good, so young. Fans of another generation might come up with Bob Feller. Nobody is expecting Phil Hughes, two months short of his 21st birthday, to be that kind of prodigy, but Hughes will have pressure on him nevertheless when he makes his major league debut tonight.</p>
        <p>With some Yankee fans growing restive, blaming Torre for the injuries to three starting pitchers, Hughes will try to stop the slide that has reached five straight losses. With the Red Sox coming in for the weekend, Andy Pettitte was pushed back until tomorrow after last night's rainout.</p>
        <p>Torre had talked this spring about not bringing up Hughes, the best pitching prospect in their system, until much later in the season, but now the Yankees need a healthy arm. Then there is a broader issue: everybody must do their part to make this a Yankee team that Roger Clemens could be proud of.</p>
        <p>What with Chien-Ming Wang still building back his arm, and Mike Mussina off to a rehabilitation start in the minors and Carl Pavano -- well, who knows about Pavano? -- the Yankees are going to need pitching. Hughes could step in and be the second coming of Whitey Ford or Ron Guidry. Right now the Yankees would settle for the second coming of Aaron Small. They're still going to need pitching down the line.</p>
        <p>Clemens is hardly sitting at an intersection bearing a sign, ''Will Pitch for Food.'' He doesn't sign with just anybody. He's back home near Houston, still insisting he probably won't return, but frankly, who believes he won't be pitching by July?</p>
        <p>The thing is, Roger is picky. He's not part of anybody's youth movement, nor is he particularly interested in being a sideshow, merely selling tickets. If he comes back, Clemens wants to win another championship -- a ring, as the players call it. That criterion pretty much narrows it down to two teams -- the Red Sox and the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Clemens is on record that he will want a Yankees cap on his eventual Hall of Fame plaque, but that doesn't mean he wouldn't do a New England nostalgia tour -- particularly if the Sox were half a dozen games ahead of the Yankees when decision time comes. Getting out of last place would seem like the best approach to recruiting the big guy. Otherwise, they could give Robinson Canó's No. 22 back sooner rather than later.</p>
        <p>Hughes seemed poised in his news conference at Yankee Stadium last night, saying he didn't feel pressure to straighten out the Yankees all by himself.</p>
        <p>''It's not like I can pitch every day,'' he said. ''I just want to give them a little help and see what happens.''</p>
        <p>Hughes arrives after the Yankees lost three straight in Boston and two in Tampa Bay. The hard-core fans are not deriving much joy from Alex Rodriguez's home runs. Torre insulates himself from the clamor in the papers and on the airwaves, but he knows that fans can be impatient, particularly early in the season, when losing streaks are magnified.</p>
        <p>There was the spring when Mariano Rivera looked shot, and another spring when Derek Jeter looked to be in a terminal slump, and then there was a losing streak in 1998, ''when the sky was falling,'' Torre recalled. But now, the last championship was in 2000, and some fans are starting to blame the slide on Torre, saying it's time for younger men (Don Mattingly or Joe Girardi) to motivate the Yankees. None of this seems very serious up close, but it is real to the fans.</p>
        <p>''If you sat on the bench, you'd see how hard the guys are trying,'' Torre said last night.</p>
        <p>Torre volunteered that ''in retrospect'' he should have given Rivera more work after he gave up a game-ending homer in Oakland. Instead, Rivera's next game came five days later in Boston, when Torre changed his stated plan and used Rivera in the eighth inning because he could feel the game getting away.</p>
        <p>The fans are also unhappy that Torre removed Wang after 80 pitches Tuesday night in his first start after being on the disabled list. Torre said, ''That was our plan all along,'' and added that Wang took a line drive off the left thigh, which made the Yankees even more cautious. That reasoning sounds totally prudent.</p>
        <p>Then the fans are itchy because Torre has used Pettitte twice in relief, which indicates exactly what Torre thinks about his bullpen at the moment. If Casey Stengel or Billy Martin sprang a surprise on everybody, that would be a sign of genius, or at least flexibility.</p>
        <p>Martin was known to use a certain left-handed starter named Guidry from the bullpen for an out or three. Guidry, who made 27 relief appearances from 1977 through 1988, some of them under Martin, is now the Yankees' pitching coach who had something to do with Pettitte's brief and apparently harmless relief appearances.</p>
        <p>Now Torre and Guidry get a look at Hughes. They don't expect Feller or Gooden, just a pitcher who can give them some innings, still very early in a long season.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
