<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Selling Out One Thing The Devils Can't Do</title>
    <meta content="26devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/hockey/26devils.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Tampa Bay Lightning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brodeur, Martin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Selling Out One Thing The Devils Can't Do</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Selling Out One Thing the Devils Can’t Do</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>WEST ORANGE, N.J., April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils played their first three home playoff games before a total of nearly 6,300 empty seats, but goaltender Martin Brodeur could have sworn Continental Arena was packed to the rafters.</p>
        <p>''I think the towels made it,'' Brodeur said with a smile Tuesday, referring to the white towels given to fans to spin over their heads in the playoffs. ''It fills up the empty seats.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another run to the Stanley Cup arrived for the Devils this season, but none of the three first-round home games against the Tampa Bay Lightning were sold out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils played their first three home playoff games before a total of nearly 6,300 empty seats, but goaltender Martin Brodeur could have sworn Continental Arena was packed to the rafters.</p>
        <p>''I think the towels made it,'' Brodeur said with a smile Tuesday, referring to the white towels given to fans to spin over their heads in the playoffs. ''It fills up the empty seats.''</p>
        <p>Another run to the Stanley Cup has arrived for the Devils, and some of their fans, again, seem to be withholding their enthusiasm. None of the three first-round home games against the Tampa Bay Lightning were sold out.</p>
        <p>This was not exactly stunning news. The Devils averaged 14,176 during the regular season. Only St. Louis (12,521), Chicago (12,734), the Islanders (12,886) and Washington (13,930) averaged fewer fans in the N.H.L. ''If the crowd is good, who cares?'' Brodeur said. ''That's our philosophy. The people supporting us are great. That what we ask for as hockey players.''</p>
        <p>The Devils, who open their second-round series at home Thursday night against Ottawa, have yet to sell out this season at 19,040-seat Continental Arena -- a 26-year-old building with the all the charm of a warehouse. The Devils say they play hard no matter what, but the empty seats start conversations. ''It's brought up,'' center Scott Gomez said. ''It's something that's definitely noticed. How can you not notice it?''</p>
        <p>Brodeur said that Continental Arena, with the ninth-largest seating capacity in the N.H.L., had always been too roomy for the team's fan base. Gomez said the fans who came to the games against Tampa Bay whipped up a pretty good din.</p>
        <p>''We certainly want to sell out, but the crowds we've had there were fantastic,'' said Lou Lamoriello, the Devils' chief executive, president, general manager and interim coach. ''You'd never know it wasn't a sellout on the bench.''</p>
        <p>Xanadu, an enormous shopping and entertainment complex, is being built around Continental Arena, and the Devils scheduled to move next season to the Prudential Center, a 17,625-seat arena under construction in downtown Newark.</p>
        <p>The Devils are, in effect, short-term tenants in a building in the middle of a dusty construction zone. As Xanadu expands, the parking lots around the arena seem to be shrinking.</p>
        <p>''That's why we're moving,'' Jeffrey Vanderbeek, the team's principal owner, said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Vanderbeek is convinced the situation will improve once the Devils get to the Prudential Center. Besides, he pointed out, the Devils averaged 16,941 for the three games against the Lightning, which would be close to a full house in the new arena.</p>
        <p>Each of the last two games against Tampa Bay drew more than 18,000 people, which is more than the capacities at the arenas of five of the other 15 teams that made the playoffs. The Devils drew 18,231 last Saturday, or 31 more than the capacity at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''Eighteen thousand is a lot of people,'' Vanderbeek said. ''We'll have 19,000 soon.''</p>
        <p>Vanderbeek did not want to pinpoint when that day would come. The Devils' next opponents, the Senators, stir far less passion in Devils fans than the Rangers or the Philadelphia Flyers.</p>
        <p>The Devils played the Senators in a regular-season game at home on April 3, a Tuesday night, the day after Lamoriello replaced Claude Julien as coach. They drew 11,642, their smallest crowd in the last 11 home games of the season.</p>
        <p>The encouraging news, Vanderbeek said, is that Game 2 against Ottawa on Saturday will begin at 8 p.m., and the weather is expected to be fair, making it easier for fans to get to the parking lots early and hold tailgating parties before the game.</p>
        <p>The identity of the opponent really does matter, although the Devils did not sell out any of their four regular-season home games against the Rangers, either. The first of the four games, in fact, drew only 17,759 on Jan. 2.</p>
        <p>Something else to consider is the three Stanley Cups the Devils have won since 1995.</p>
        <p>''One of my neighbors once told me, 'We're so spoiled here,' '' Gomez said. ''He was joking around when he said, 'I wait until the conference finals to get interested,' but they've experienced the best here.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Left wing Patrik Elias, the Devils' captain, missed his second consecutive practice with a cold Wednesday, creating concern that he may not be available for Game 1. Elias saw a team doctor and was told to remain at home and away from the team. (AP)</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
