<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer Pushing Bill to Shore Up Abortion Rights</title>
    <meta content="26spitzer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/nyregion/26spitzer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFDC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer Pushing Bill to Shore Up Abortion Rights</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spitzer Pushing Bill to Shore Up Abortion Rights</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM; Kate Hammer contributed reporting from Manhattan.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov Eliot Spitzer will seek to shore up abortion rights in New York, even as several other states move to tighten restrictions on abortion and US Supreme Court upholds ban on so-called partial birth abortion; Spitzer will introduce legislation to overhaul state's pioneering but antiquated abortion law; his bill would remove abortion from criminal statutes and make it matter of professional and medical discretion; his effort will take on much broader significance if Supreme Court ever returns abortion law to discretion of states; but it is far from certain that his bill will pass Republican-led State Senate; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer said Wednesday that he planned to introduce legislation to overhaul the state's pioneering but antiquated abortion law, shoring up abortion rights in New York.</p>
        <p>The proposal follows the United States Supreme Court's decision last week to uphold the federal Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act, at a time when several other states are moving to tighten restrictions on abortion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The plan could take on broad significance if the Supreme Court ever returns abortion law to states’ discretion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer said Wednesday that he planned to introduce legislation to overhaul the state's pioneering but antiquated abortion law, shoring up abortion rights in New York.</p>
        <p>The proposal follows the United States Supreme Court's decision last week to uphold the federal Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act, at a time when several other states are moving to tighten restrictions on abortion.</p>
        <p>New York took an early role in legalizing abortion, and the governor's plan could take on much broader significance if the Supreme Court ever returns abortion law to the discretion of the states. Still, it is far from certain that the legislation will pass the Republican-led State Senate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's bill, the Reproductive Health and Privacy Protection Act, would update current law, which, for example, does not include a provision allowing for abortions late in pregnancies to protect a woman's health. New York state laws on the books also treat abortion as a homicide, but with broad exceptions that allow the procedure in many cases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's proposal would remove abortion from criminal statutes and make it a matter of professional and medical discretion. It would also repeal an old statute ''that criminalizes, among other things, providing nonprescription contraception to minors,'' according to the governor's office.</p>
        <p>''Even if the Supreme Court does not understand the law, we do,'' Mr. Spitzer said, appearing briefly at a Manhattan luncheon held by Naral Pro-Choice New York. ''New York State will continue to be a beacon of civil rights and protection of women's rights.''</p>
        <p>The governor cut short his appearance after learning of the shooting death of a state trooper in upstate New York on Wednesday morning, leaving his wife, Silda Wall Spitzer, to deliver the text of his speech, which calls for legislation that ''would enshrine the protections of Roe v. Wade into New York State law.''</p>
        <p>New York's abortion law, signed in 1970 by Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller, a Republican, predates the Roe v. Wade decision by three years and made New York the second state after Hawaii to broadly legalize the procedure and the first to allow abortions for out-of-state residents. In the first two years, more than half the women having abortions came from out of state.</p>
        <p>But the law is now considered out of date by abortion rights advocates.</p>
        <p>The issue is clearly a personal one for the governor. His mother, Anne, is a board member of a foundation affiliated with Naral and received a lifetime achievement award at the luncheon.</p>
        <p>Abortion rights advocates hailed the proposed legislation as a critical step in light of the Supreme Court's ruling, but it is also one whose purpose could be seen as insurance if the Supreme Court upholds stricter regulation of abortion. The state bill would not change current abortion practices, nor would it have any effect on the procedure covered by the federal ban, which is known medically as ''intact dilation and extraction.''</p>
        <p>''New York's laws have to be impeccable,'' said JoAnn Smith, president and chief executive of Family Planning Advocates of New York State. ''The Supreme Court said last week that a woman's health doesn't matter, and with very carefully crafted legislation today, Governor Spitzer said it does.''</p>
        <p>But Lori Kehoe, a spokeswoman for the New York State Right to Life Committee, called the governor ''a bully with an insatiable appetite and tunnel vision to accomplish his fierce agenda.''</p>
        <p>''We can only hope the Senate will get back their courage and begin to stand up for the children with as much fervor and devotion as Governor Spitzer has shown for making sure they can be destroyed,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Neither the Assembly nor the Senate was familiar with the details of the proposal, though it could be expected to be received warmly in the Democratic-led Assembly and much less so in the Senate, whose majority is Republican.</p>
        <p>John McArdle, a spokesman for the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, said: ''The governor's top issues for the rest of the session are overturning an abortion decision that has not been made, delivering same-sex marriage and campaign finance reform. Our priorities continue to be dealing with the state's economy, jobs, reducing taxes and making sure cops don't get killed when they're on the job.''</p>
        <p>The federal Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act that was upheld last week allows an abortion to save the woman's life, but not simply when her health is at risk, a step that dismayed groups like the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wall Spitzer said, ''Eliot's bill would encapsulate protections similar to those afforded by Roe, that a pregnant woman has the right to an abortion in two circumstances; first, prior to viability of the fetus, and second, at any time when necessary to protect her life or her health.''</p>
        <p>Eve Gartner, deputy director of litigation and law of the Planned Parenthood Federation of America, said that although state law could not supersede the Supreme Court's ruling last week, she believed that the governor's proposals would make doctors feel more secure when considering a range of abortion procedures.</p>
        <p>''I think that without having this clear health exception, they would feel that maybe they might delay treatment for a little while until the woman worsened,'' she said. ''If New York law had a clear health exception, I think they would feel more comfortable that they could proceed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
