<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Higher Graduation Rates in City, but 'More Work to Do'</title>
    <meta content="26graduation" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/nyregion/26graduation.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Department (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Klein, Joel I</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Higher Graduation Rates in City, but 'More Work to Do'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Higher Graduation Rates in City, but ‘More Work to Do’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Education Dept reports that half of New York City's high school students graduated on time in 2006, up from 47 percent in 2005, while statewide graduation rate barely budged, rising to 67 percent from 66 percent; state and city have calculated graduation rates differently, but city has agreed to use state's method of counting from now on; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Half of New York City's high school students graduated on time in June 2006, up from 47 percent the year before, according to figures released yesterday by the New York State Education Department.</p>
        <p>The figures also showed that statewide, the four-year high school graduation rate barely budged, rising to 67 percent from 66 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Half of New York City’s high school students graduated on time in June 2006, up from 47 percent the year before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Half of New York City's high school students graduated on time in June 2006, up from 47 percent the year before, according to figures released yesterday by the New York State Education Department.</p>
        <p>The figures also showed that statewide, the four-year high school graduation rate barely budged, rising to 67 percent from 66 percent.</p>
        <p>At a brief news conference yesterday afternoon, Schools Chancellor Joel I. Klein greeted the results with subdued happiness. He called the numbers ''very encouraging news for our city'' and said, ''This shows real progress and a system moving forward.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Klein acknowledged that having only half of the city's high school students graduating on time was hardly much to crow about. ''I would be the first to say we have a lot more work to do,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Of the students who did not graduate on time last year, 28 percent are still enrolled, and 20 percent have dropped out, the state said.</p>
        <p>For years, the state and the city have calculated graduation rates differently, with the city including students who graduate in August after summer school and some students who earn equivalency degrees. The city also excludes special education students who largely fail to earn diplomas and would lower the overall graduation rate. By the city's most recent measure, 59 percent of the class of 2006 graduated on time.</p>
        <p>The state education commissioner, Richard P. Mills, who announced the new figures yesterday at a news conference in Albany, said the city had agreed to use the state's counting method from now on. Mr. Klein said that the city would continue to publish graduation rates using its own formula, though merely for comparison purposes.</p>
        <p>The city has been compiling data for more than 20 years -- far longer than the state. ''I want to make sure people can see the picture historically,'' Mr. Klein said of continuing to publish the city's system.</p>
        <p>The chancellor said he believed the two systems could and should be ''harmonized.'' But he added, ''Under either approach, New York City is moving forward.''</p>
        <p>On that count, he had no argument from Commissioner Mills, who lavished the city with praise yesterday. He said the city's gains reflected a ''systemic approach to raising achievement,'' and credited Mr. Klein and Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg with establishing a consistent mission in the nation's largest school system.</p>
        <p>''It's going up at a rate that seems reasonable, three percentage points a year, year after year,'' Mr. Mills said. ''I know it's real because I have visited so many schools. I have talked to so many superintendents and principals. I can see what people are doing. I can see that they are applying themselves.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''When I hear the same message from a principal or superintendent that I hear from the chancellor, I know there is consistency.''</p>
        <p>The commissioner's staff members said that in the future the state would note August graduates in its four-year report, changing the current practice of including them as fifth-year graduates. June and August graduates would be noted separately, they said.</p>
        <p>The news for the rest of the state was somewhat less optimistic. The numbers showed some of the same vast disparities -- between poor cities and rich suburbs, and also between white students and their black and Hispanic counterparts -- that have persisted for years, with rich children and white children more likely to graduate on time.</p>
        <p>Statewide, 45 percent of Hispanic students and 47 percent of black students graduated on time in 2006, compared with 79 percent of white students. And while the on-time completion rate was 91 percent in the wealthiest school districts, it was only 45 percent in Buffalo, Rochester, Syracuse and Yonkers, the big cities other than New York.</p>
        <p>The numbers also highlighted the enduring challenges for students with disabilities; only 37 percent statewide graduated on time, and only 48 percent did so after six years.</p>
        <p>The results yesterday highlighted the complex and often messy process of tabulating graduation rates. Mr. Mills announced that the state had revised New York City's graduation rate for the class of 2005, to 47 percent from 43.5 percent, based on updated information from the city.</p>
        <p>And he said that the statewide on-time graduation rate for the class of 2000 had been adjusted down, to 66 percent from 67 percent, while the rate for the class of 2001 had been adjusted up, to 66 percent from 64 percent.</p>
        <p>Modest gains were shown in the suburbs, with the on-time graduation rate up slightly in Westchester, Nassau and Suffolk Counties.</p>
        <p>For both New York City and the state, the numbers showed an increase in students graduating after five and six years. In New York City, for instance, 44 percent of the class of 2004 graduated after four years, Mr. Mills said, while 53 percent graduated within five years and 56 percent graduated within six years.</p>
        <p>City education officials said that the increasing number of fifth- and sixth-year graduates, and the fact that yesterday's numbers included results from only the first 15 of more than 200 small schools that the Bloomberg administration has opened, provided reason to expect sizable jumps in the city's graduation rate in coming years.</p>
        <p>But with the city's graduation numbers having long been a matter of dispute, some critics of the Bloomberg administration expressed skepticism about the latest tally and emphasized the overall grim situation.</p>
        <p>''Regardless of the number, we can all agree that our on-time graduation rate is an embarrassment,'' said Betsy Gotbaum, the city's public advocate. ''And the rate among black and Hispanic students is a disaster.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
