<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tornado Ravages Sister Cities on Rio Grande</title>
    <meta content="26storms" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/us/26storms.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tornadoes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Eagle Pass (Tex)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Piedras Negras (Mex)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tornadoes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EEDE153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tornado Ravages Sister Cities on Rio Grande</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tornado Ravages Sister Cities on Rio Grande</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Strong tornado southwest of San Antonio, Tex, kills at least 10 people on both sides of Mexican border, injuring many others and destroying or damaging hundreds of homes; twister hits Eagle Pass, Tex, and sister city Piedras Negras; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A fierce tornado southwest of San Antonio killed at least 10 people on both sides of the Mexican border Tuesday night, injured many others and destroyed or damaged hundreds of homes.</p>
        <p>Fear remained Wednesday that the death toll could rise, as more than 500 searchers scoured the rubble in Eagle Pass, a financially struggling city of 22,400, which was pounded along with Piedras Negras, its sister city across the Rio Grande.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A fierce tornado southwest of San Antonio killed at least 10 people on both sides of the Mexican border Tuesday night, injured many others and destroyed or damaged hundreds of homes</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A fierce tornado southwest of San Antonio killed at least 10 people on both sides of the Mexican border Tuesday night, injured many others and destroyed or damaged hundreds of homes.</p>
        <p>Fear remained Wednesday that the death toll could rise, as more than 500 searchers scoured the rubble in Eagle Pass, a financially struggling city of 22,400, which was pounded along with Piedras Negras, its sister city across the Rio Grande.</p>
        <p>At least seven people died in Eagle Pass. Four of them appeared to have been members of one family living in a mobile home struck by the twister, said the Maverick County judge, Jose A. Aranda Jr. The three other dead were killed nearby, Mr. Aranda said.</p>
        <p>Mayor Chad Foster said 76 people had been hospitalized, with 32 later discharged. Four of the injured were said to be in critical condition.</p>
        <p>About 40 homes were destroyed, Mayor Foster said, and 350 people were being put up in shelters.</p>
        <p>In Piedras Negras, a city of 200,000, 3 people were killed and 26 injured, 6 of them critically, said Mayor Jesús Mario Flores.</p>
        <p>Piedras Negras was the scene of a flood three years ago that killed more than 30 people. But the tornado Tuesday night was even more severe in terms of material damage, and Mr. Flores said the Villa de Fuente section had taken the brunt of it.</p>
        <p>''There are about 300 houses that are completely destroyed'' there, the mayor said. ''They were wooden houses, and all the roofs are gone.''</p>
        <p>Two hundred homes suffered lesser damage in another part of the city, he said.</p>
        <p>The tornado struck about 6:30 p.m., after heavy hail, and cut a swath of destruction nearly five miles wide.</p>
        <p>Gov. Rick Perry toured the area, 130 miles southwest of San Antonio, on Wednesday afternoon and later issued disaster proclamations for Maverick County.</p>
        <p>''It's a devastating event,'' said Jack Colley, chief of the Governor's Division of Emergency Management, who was coordinating relief efforts from Austin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Colley said search and rescue teams from the Texas National Guard and other emergency response units were looking for other victims and survivors.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately,'' he said, ''we're very good at this.''</p>
        <p>Two schools in Eagle Pass, Rosita Valley Elementary and the kindergarten next door, the Rosita Valley Literacy Academy, were destroyed, said Lalo Trevino, assistant superintendent for the school district. But the school day was already over, and the buildings were empty.</p>
        <p>''When I got there, they were completely demolished,'' Mr. Trevino said. ''The Literacy Academy, it was just shredded -- just nothing there, just gone. All of it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trevino said the tornado had also ''completely wiped out'' two housing subdivisions about five miles from town.</p>
        <p>He said that the school district had quickly mobilized buses and evacuated about 400 people to a junior high school and that assistance from surrounding counties had been enormous.</p>
        <p>A lifelong resident of Eagle Pass, Mr. Trevino, 58, said he had never seen a storm so strong. In a region parched by drought, the onset of it was welcome. Then came the realization of what it was ushering in.</p>
        <p>''I was out there watching the rain,'' Mr. Trevino said. ''We were so glad to get the rain. But we had no idea this was going on.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
