<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain Announces for President, With a Critique of the Current One</title>
    <meta content="26mccain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070428T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1266" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain Announces for President, With a Critique of the Current One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY and MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael; Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>MANCHESTER, N.H., April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arizona Republican Sen John McCain formally starts his second bid for presidency with thinly veiled critique of Bush administration; pledges he will restore competence to foreign and domestic policy and welcomes compromise with Democrats; remarks suggest sharp strategic shift after months of trying to build support with conservative voters in part by presenting himself as Bush champion and his natural heir; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, formally began his second bid for the White House on Wednesday with a thinly veiled critique of the Bush administration, pledging that he would restore competence to foreign and domestic policy and welcome compromise with Democrats.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain lamented the ''many mistakes'' in Iraq, alluded to Hurricane Katrina and the government's failure to ''rescue the infirm from a hospital with no electricity,'' criticized ''substandard care and indifference for our wounded veterans'' and called for reining in what he termed wasteful federal spending over six years of Republican rule.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, formally began his second bid for the White House on Wednesday with a thinly veiled critique of the Bush administration, pledging that he would restore competence to foreign and domestic policy and welcome compromise with Democrats.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain lamented the ''many mistakes'' in Iraq, alluded to Hurricane Katrina and the government's failure to ''rescue the infirm from a hospital with no electricity,'' criticized ''substandard care and indifference for our wounded veterans'' and called for reining in what he termed wasteful federal spending over six years of Republican rule.</p>
        <p>And in an interview with Larry King taped in a conference room at a Concord hotel Wednesday afternoon, he said he thought Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzalez should resign ''out of loyalty'' to President Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, trying to reinvigorate a campaign that has been dogged by problems, said Americans were wary of ''old politics'' with partisan infighting and petty brawling.</p>
        <p>He repeatedly said -- in a state where independent voters are allowed to vote in either primary -- that a McCain presidency would be marked by an effort to reach accommodations with political opponents.</p>
        <p>''Americans are acutely aware of our problems,'' he said, ''and their patience is at end for politicians who value incumbency over principle, and for partisanship that is less a contest of ideas than an uncivil brawl over the spoils of power.'' He added, ''They're tired of it.''</p>
        <p>Although he did not mention Mr. Bush by name in his 20-minute speech, delivered under slate-gray skies and before an often listless crowd in Portsmouth, Mr. McCain systematically distanced himself from the White House and from his major Republican competitors.</p>
        <p>His remarks suggested a sharp strategic shift after months of trying to build support with conservative voters in part by presenting himself as a champion of Mr. Bush and his natural heir.</p>
        <p>That strategy has exposed him to questions about his ideological consistency and whether he had sacrificed his political identity in an effort to overcome skepticism about him among the conservatives who helped Mr. Bush win the White House twice.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain at first only hinted that on Thursday he might call for the resignation of Mr. Gonzales. Asked by reporters if he still supported Mr. Gonzales, he responded, ''I'll tell you tomorrow,'' explaining that he did not want to ''step on my message.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. McCain stepped on his message hours later when he sat down to tape an interview with Mr. King for CNN. When Mr. King asked if he thought Mr. Gonzalez should step down, Mr. McCain responded, ''I think that out of loyalty to the president that that would probably be the best thing that he could do.''</p>
        <p>His criticisms seemed aimed not only at the record of the Bush administration but also at the political strategy that became its hallmark in 2000 and 2004: winning by pumping up support among base voters.</p>
        <p>''I'm running for president of the United States,'' Mr. McCain said. ''Not yesterday's country, not a defeated country, not a bankrupt country, not a timid and frightened country, not a country fragmented into bickering interest groups with no sense of the national interest, not a country with a bloated, irresponsible and incompetent government.''</p>
        <p>''To keep those promises, I can't just win this election by a few votes in a few counties in a few states,'' he said. ''I need a mandate from you big enough to convince Congress that Americans want this election to be different. You want to change the politics of selfishness, stalemate and delay; move this country forward and stake our claim on this century as we did in the last.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's aides said that though distancing himself from Mr. Bush, he was to some extent insulated from a backlash from Mr. Bush's supporters because of his defense of the president's decision to send more troops to Iraq.</p>
        <p>They also suggested that in talking about such issues as the response to Hurricane Katrina, the quality of care for military personnel at Walter Reed Medical Center and the management of the war, he was giving voice to the opinions of even Mr. Bush's strongest supporters.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain spoke at a pivotal time in a candidacy that has gone through some difficult days. He has spent three years preparing for a campaign in which he had long been viewed as the presumptive front-runner for his party's nomination.</p>
        <p>But the announcement Wednesday had the feel of a restart, reflecting Mr. McCain's relative weakness in some early measures of strength, including his fund-raising.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, 70, made reference to his age as an issue, but tried to turn it against his main rivals. ''I'm not the youngest candidate,'' he said. ''But I am the most experienced.''</p>
        <p>He delivered his announcement speech in Portsmouth, speaking in flat tones and in front of just a few hundred people who turned up for the outdoor event. He repeated it at the end of the day in Manchester to a crowd pelted by a cold rain and where he was interrupted by a small but loud group of war protesters.</p>
        <p>In the speech, he devoted only a few sentences to Iraq, the issue that as much as any has defined his candidacy, though he answered extensive questions from reporters on the topic later.</p>
        <p>He affirmed his contention that the war was justified and said he was not giving any thought to what impact it might have on his political ambitions.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's speech was also notable for not mentioning issues of concern to social conservatives, including abortion.</p>
        <p>At one point, Mr. McCain appeared to take a jab at Rudolph W. Giuliani, the former mayor of New York, whose early success as candidate for the Republican nomination -- a candidacy built in large part on Mr. Giuliani's handling of the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks -- has proved troublesome for Mr. McCain.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain noted that emergency workers at the World Trade Center in New York on the day of the attacks were unable to communicate with one another as well as they should have been able to.</p>
        <p>''When Americans confront a catastrophe, natural or man-made, they have a right to expect basic competence from their government,'' he said. ''They won't accept that firemen and policemen are unable to communicate with each other in an emergency because they don't have the same radio frequency.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's aides later said that the remark, which echoed some criticism that has been directed at Mr. Giuliani concerning New York's preparedness for a catastrophe, was not aimed at Mr. Giuliani, but rather at the federal government for its role in regulating the assignment of radio frequencies.</p>
        <p>John McCain  In His Own Words  In announcing his candidacy for the presidency, Senator John McCain of Arizona alluded yesterday to his age, but also highlighted his experience. A full transcript: nytimes.com/politics.</p>
        <p>''I'm not the youngest candidate. But I am the most experienced. I know how the military works, what it can do, what it can do better and what it should not do. I know how Congress works, and how to make it work for the country and not just the re-election of its members. I know how the world works. I know the good and the evil in it. I know how to work with leaders who share our dreams of a freer, safer and more prosperous world, and how to stand up to those who don't. I know how to fight and how to make peace. I know who I am and what I want to do.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 28, 2007, Saturday  An article Thursday about the formal start of Senator John McCain's campaign for the Republican presidential nomination misspelled the surname of the United States attorney general, whom Mr. McCain urged to resign, in two of four references. The attorney general is Alberto R. Gonzales, not Gonzalez.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 28, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article Thursday about the formal start of Senator John McCain's campaign for the Republican presidential nomination misspelled the surname of the United States attorney general, whom Mr. McCain urged to resign, in two of four references. The attorney general is Alberto R. Gonzales, not Gonzalez.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
