<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Comments About Apple Chief, Questions of Motive</title>
    <meta content="26anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/technology/26anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Apple Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Anderson, Fred D</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jobs, Steven P</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DD153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Comments About Apple Chief, Questions of Motive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Comments About Apple Chief, Questions of Motive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF and MATT RICHTEL; Eric Dash contributed from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markoff, John; Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Fred D. Anderson abruptly left Apple's board last October as questions about the company's stock options practices grew, a former federal regulator said it looked as if the board ''threw Fred under the bus.''</p>
        <p>This week Mr. Anderson has been somewhere closer to the driver's seat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former Apple board member kept suspicions about Apple’s options-backdating policies swirling around Steven P. Jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Fred D. Anderson abruptly left Apple's board last October as questions about the company's stock options practices grew, a former federal regulator said it looked as if the board ''threw Fred under the bus.''</p>
        <p>This week Mr. Anderson has been somewhere closer to the driver's seat.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the day he agreed to settle a lawsuit brought against him by the Securities and Exchange Commission in its options-backdating investigation, Mr. Anderson threw an extraordinarily sharp elbow at Apple's chief executive, Steven P. Jobs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson, the company's former chief financial officer, neither admitted nor denied wrongdoing in a 2001 options grant that the S.E.C. found to have been fraudulently dated. But he asserted that he had advised Mr. Jobs about the accounting issues and potential consequences and had received assurances in return.</p>
        <p>A statement issued through his lawyer said Mr. Anderson had been misled by Mr. Jobs: ''Fred relied on these statements by Mr. Jobs and from them concluded the grant was being properly handled.''</p>
        <p>With Mr. Anderson's case behind him but a legal cloud remaining over Mr. Jobs, it was the shot heard round Silicon Valley.</p>
        <p>The two men combined their marketing and financial talents during the late 1990s to save Apple when it was at the brink of bankruptcy. When Mr. Anderson left as chief financial officer in 2004 to become a venture capitalist, they were on good terms.</p>
        <p>''Steve and Fred were great buddies from 1997 to 2004,'' said Charles Wolf, president of Wolf Insights, an investment consulting company that has covered Apple for years.</p>
        <p>Many in Silicon Valley, therefore, were scratching their heads on Wednesday. Why would Mr. Anderson go out of his way to tarnish Mr. Jobs after he had been let off with a relatively light penalty? Although he was forced to give back $3.5 million, that is a fraction of the tens of millions that he garnered in his time at Apple.</p>
        <p>One widely discussed possibility was that the Justice Department was still considering a case against Mr. Jobs, and that Mr. Anderson had waited until his own case was settled to avoid suspicion that he was testifying to save himself.</p>
        <p>But there was an equally held belief that Mr. Anderson had simply been stewing for months, outraged at his forced resignation from the board in the wake of an internal investigation.</p>
        <p>''Fred's reputation was impugned by Apple,'' said Roger McNamee, a managing director at Elevation Partners, the venture capital firm where Mr. Anderson is a colleague. ''All he is doing now is responding -- with facts. And he is doing so in the most diplomatic way possible.''</p>
        <p>On Wednesday afternoon, Apple's board responded, issuing a statement reiterating that Mr. Jobs had cooperated with Apple's own inquiry and with federal investigators.</p>
        <p>''The S.E.C. investigated the matter thoroughly and its complaint speaks for itself, in terms of what it says, what it does not say, who it charges, and who it does not charge,'' the board's statement said.</p>
        <p>Moreover, a crucial S.E.C. official in the agency's San Francisco office emphasized Mr. Anderson's own responsibility.</p>
        <p>''From our standpoint, the key fact in assessing Mr. Anderson's liability is that regardless of what he may or may not have believed, he had before him e-mails that stated the price was picked with hindsight and that the board's authorization was dated on a date when no event occurred,'' said Marc J. Fagel, associate regional director for the commission. ''Based on that, he should have done more to ensure the financial statements were accurate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf, the investment consultant, said Mr. Anderson was viewed as a straight shooter with stand-up ethics. But he said that the suggestion that blame for the backdating problems lay with Mr. Jobs did not wash. Whatever Mr. Jobs might have told Mr. Anderson about the handling of options, ''it's Fred's responsibility to take care of the issue,'' Mr. Wolf said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson came to Apple from the minicomputer and data processing industries and was instrumental in keeping the company afloat during its darkest days before Mr. Jobs returned to Apple in 1997.</p>
        <p>The computer maker then revived during the dot-com boom. But in 2000, when the Internet bubble was bursting, Apple's stock took an immense tumble, and Mr. Jobs and Mr. Anderson worked together to bring stability and to rebuild the company around the consumer electronics industry and the wildly successful iPod.</p>
        <p>After leaving Apple in 2004 to become a co-founder of Elevation Partners, based on Sand Hill Road in Menlo Park -- Silicon Valley's venture-capital row -- Mr. Anderson was involved again in a potential crisis when the stock-option backdating issue exploded last summer. Still a member of Apple's board, he volunteered to spend a month sorting out the company's past stock-option practices, an associate briefed on the events said.</p>
        <p>The associate said Mr. Anderson did so at the time not because Apple was suspected of having a problem but because many major companies were trying to understand their practices in case they did face scrutiny or accusations.</p>
        <p>Last fall, however, the accusations around Apple's practices started to snowball. In October, Mr. Anderson resigned from the board. Several people close to Apple's investigation said he had essentially been forced out.</p>
        <p>At the time, the company said its stock-option accounting problems were attributable to two former employees, an allusion that was widely interpreted as referring to Mr. Anderson and the former general counsel, Nancy R. Heinen, who was also sued by the S.E.C. this week.</p>
        <p>In October, with the assistance of his partners at Elevation, Mr. Anderson retained the public relations firm Sard Verbinnen, which is often called in to help in hardball situations like litigation and mergers and acquisitions. (Among its contributions on Wednesday was this testimonial to Mr. Anderson from the Irish rock star Bono, a managing director and co-founder of Elevation: ''He is a man to whom you would give the keys to your life and know it would be calmer, tidier and better organized every day he was in it.'')</p>
        <p>Mr. McNamee, his Elevation colleague, said in an interview that Mr. Anderson had been deeply hurt by insinuations from Apple that he was responsible for the option accounting problems.</p>
        <p>He said the comments by Mr. Anderson's lawyer were an attempt to clear Mr. Anderson's name and ''set the record straight in a way that has not been possible because of the pending legal action.''</p>
        <p>John Shoch, a veteran venture capitalist at Alloy Ventures in Palo Alto, Calif., was trying to sort it all out.</p>
        <p>''You get into this he-said, she-said situation and you have to worry about who was paying attention and what the subtleties were,'' he said. ''This whole thing may reflect a smoking gun somewhere.'' But he conceded that he had no idea where it might be.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
