<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trees Lost to a Buffalo Snowstorm Live as Objects of Art and Civic Pride</title>
    <meta content="26trees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/nyregion/26trees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buffalo (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carvings for a Cause (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pratt, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Buffalo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Buffalo (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFDC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trees Lost to a Buffalo Snowstorm Live as Objects of Art and Civic Pride</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trees Lost to a Buffalo Snowstorm Live as Objects of Art and Civic Pride</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN BELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belson, Ken</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carvings for a Cause hires artist Rick Pratt to create wood sculptures of famous residents of Buffalo from some of nearly 4,000 trees lost to freakish snowstorm that hit city in October 2006; is charging businesses $7,500 to display one-ton statues in order to pay Pratt and buy new trees to plant throughout city; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rick Pratt used a 12-inch chain saw to give Millard Fillmore his version of the presidential treatment. Quick, precise jabs sheared chunks from a length of century-old silver maple, followed by several long strokes and another round of short slices. As the sawdust settled, the cheeks, nose and chin of America's 13th president were revealed.</p>
        <p>It would take Mr. Pratt another week of carving, sanding and staining before the 10-foot version of the mostly forgettable Fillmore joined the growing wooden pantheon of Buffalo icons, including Frederick Law Olmsted; Frank Lloyd Wright, who built a series of houses here; and, of course, a buffalo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trees that were felled in Buffalo during last October’s freakish snowstorm become art with one man’s chain saw.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rick Pratt used a 12-inch chain saw to give Millard Fillmore his version of the presidential treatment. Quick, precise jabs sheared chunks from a length of century-old silver maple, followed by several long strokes and another round of short slices. As the sawdust settled, the cheeks, nose and chin of America's 13th president were revealed.</p>
        <p>It would take Mr. Pratt another week of carving, sanding and staining before the 10-foot version of the mostly forgettable Fillmore joined the growing wooden pantheon of Buffalo icons, including Frederick Law Olmsted; Frank Lloyd Wright, who built a series of houses here; and, of course, a buffalo.</p>
        <p>Several dozen trunks sat near his shed in the shadow of an abandoned mill, waiting to be transformed into, among other figures, Marlin Perkins of ''Mutual of Omaha's Wild Kingdom,'' Tim Russert of ''Meet the Press'' on NBC and Bob McAdoo, a star on the old Buffalo Braves basketball team.</p>
        <p>Making so many totems of Buffalo's beloved is a chain saw artist's dream, especially for Mr. Pratt, who grew up in western New York and spent 14 years cutting down trees for a living. But the task is tinged with sadness, since the trees are some of the nearly 4,000 of Buffalo's finest felled in last October's freakish snowstorm.</p>
        <p>By letting the dead elms, oaks and maples live on as monuments to nearby natives and significant figures like the author Joyce Carol Oates and the actor James Whitmore, Mr. Pratt and the organizers of Carvings for a Cause, who hired him, are trying in some small way to make this battered city whole again.</p>
        <p>''With tree work, you make a big empty spot, but with carving, you're creating something,'' said Mr. Pratt, 44, who is as soft-spoken as his chain saw is noisy. ''These trees are being resurrected not just as trees. You're giving them another life.''</p>
        <p>Therese Forton-Barnes, a Buffalo native who started Carvings for a Cause soon after the storm, is charging businesses $7,500 to display these one-ton statues in front of their offices. (She accepts requests for subject matter; a local power company, for example, is considering a Thomas Edison carving.) The money will help pay Mr. Pratt -- who charges $3,000 per statue, about 60 percent of his normal rate for carving bears, eagles and American Indians -- and buy new trees to plant throughout the city.</p>
        <p>''I just couldn't see 200-year-old trunks going to the dump,'' Ms. Forton-Barnes said. ''These trees are like everyone's babies. They are like the roots of the families who live here.''</p>
        <p>The to-be-carved list is a work in progress: Buffalo Bob Smith, host of ''The Howdy Doody Show,'' made it, but O. J. Simpson, the longtime Buffalo Bills running back, was skipped to avoid controversy.</p>
        <p>Some potential subjects have admittedly tenuous connections to the Queen City. William McKinley, the 25th president, is included because he was shot by an anarchist assassin while visiting the Buffalo Pan-American Exposition; Gov. DeWitt Clinton, because he was the father of the Erie Canal, which dumps out here.</p>
        <p>The monuments are just one of the ways Buffalo, known for decades as the City of Trees, is trying to salve the deep scars the storm left in the local landscape and civic psyche. City leaders have donated tens of thousands of dollars to replanting efforts, and hundreds of residents have volunteered to plant bare-root trees starting this month.</p>
        <p>As those efforts get under way, the sound of chain saws and chippers is filling the still-chilly air. Dozens of crews have fanned out across Buffalo and surrounding towns to remove trees that remain hazards to homes and utility lines. On many streets, stumps are interspersed with trees that were strong enough to withstand the blizzard that broke some of their brethren down the middle. The storm, which dropped more than 22 inches of snow in 16 hours, was particularly devastating because it hit before most trees had lost their leaves, which added significant weight.</p>
        <p>Many residents assumed that any tree that survived the winter would be spared, but as the crews have gone after trees marked for removal with orange ribbons tied around their trunks or X's spray-painted on their bark, neighbors are realizing that they will soon be without many of their leafy old friends.</p>
        <p>One recent morning, Thomas Jones emerged from his house in the University District to find a five-man team from Schneck's Tree Removal cutting down a maple across the street. The city's forest manager, Arthur V. Traver III, pulled up an aerial map of the block on his laptop and showed Mr. Jones that the tree was among six on the street to be toppled that day, explaining that even though buds were poking from its branches, the tree would ultimately wither because so much of its canopy had been lost.</p>
        <p>''You kind of persuaded me, but I'm still going to miss it,'' Mr. Jones said. ''I was thinking that at least I still have a little shade.''</p>
        <p>Residents citywide are getting this kind of crash course in arboriculture -- one they have not had since Dutch elm disease wiped out nearly 100,000 of Buffalo's trees in the 1960s and '70s. This time, about 4,000 trees are to be removed from the city's rights of way; thousands more are being cut down in parks, on private property and in surrounding towns.</p>
        <p>The Federal Emergency Management Agency will pay to remove many of the trees, but not their stumps, which are sometimes as expensive to grind or uproot. Several groups have sprouted to train volunteers -- one, Re-Tree WNY, plans to plant 30,000 trees over five years -- and donations have poured in from foundations, companies and citizens of all stripes.</p>
        <p>But since many trees grow only about a foot a year, those lost will take decades to really replace, adding urgency to Mr. Pratt's efforts.</p>
        <p>His trunks-to-totems project will remind Buffalo residents how large some of their lost trees were.</p>
        <p>Like the trees themselves, the chain saw sculptures are seen as a tangible link to the city's past: Among the local heroes waiting to be carved are Harold Arlen, who wrote songs like ''Stormy Weather'' and ''Over the Rainbow''; the aviation pioneer Glenn H. Curtiss; and Grover Cleveland, mayor of Buffalo, governor of New York and president of the United States.</p>
        <p>''Energy never dies, it just transforms into a different shape,'' Mr. Pratt said. ''We hope people will slow down for a minute and look at things differently.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
