<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Young Man's Troubled Path From Pride of His Family to Murder Suspect</title>
    <meta content="26sidebar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/nyregion/26sidebar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843075"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Margaretville (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trim, Travis D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gombasi, Matthew (State Trooper)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkerhoff, David C (State Trooper)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mattson, Richard G (State Trooper)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Medina, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santos, Fernanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Young Man's Troubled Path From Pride of His Family to Murder Suspect</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Young Man’s Troubled Path From Pride of His Family to Murder Suspect</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER MEDINA and FERNANDA SANTOS; Laura Drake contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Medina, Jennifer; Santos, Fernanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travis D Trim dropped out of SUNY Canton and had several run-ins with law before allegedly shooting three New York State troopers, one of them fatally, in Margaretville, NY; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This was supposed to be the year in which Travis D. Trim worked his life out. He told his probation officer and his grandmother that he was returning to college at SUNY Canton, not far from his hometown in northern New York.</p>
        <p>Instead, at one turn after another, his actions led him to the police's attention. First, in September, it was helping a group of minors get some beer. Then, the next month, possession of marijuana. A few weeks later Mr. Trim dropped out of school, where he was learning to repair motorcycles and all-terrain vehicles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This was supposed to be the year in which Travis D. Trim worked his life out. He told his probation officer and his grandmother that he was returning to college at SUNY Canton, not far from his hometown in northern New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This was supposed to be the year in which Travis D. Trim worked his life out. He told his probation officer and his grandmother that he was returning to college at SUNY Canton, not far from his hometown in northern New York.</p>
        <p>Instead, at one turn after another, his actions led him to the police's attention. First, in September, it was helping a group of minors get some beer. Then, the next month, possession of marijuana. A few weeks later Mr. Trim dropped out of school, where he was learning to repair motorcycles and all-terrain vehicles.</p>
        <p>And on Monday, a student on the Canton campus reported his Dodge Caravan stolen. The police say they believe Mr. Trim took the vehicle and was using it Tuesday when he was stopped by a trooper, whom he shot .</p>
        <p>Mr. Trim, 23, grew up in North Lawrence, N.Y., a speck of a town near the Canadian border where the main street has little more than a diner, a bar and a small gas station and grocery. His parents had grown up there. When he graduated from Hermon-DeKalb Central School in 2002 with a Regents diploma, his family thought his future was bright.</p>
        <p>When he was about 11, his parents separated and he lived with his mother and maternal grandfather. Problems did not surface for some time. Along with his parents and sister, Mr. Trim worked at repairing cars and dreamed of starting a family business, family members said.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, his paternal grandmother, Ruth Trim, offered a grim assessment of the boy who once made her swell with pride.</p>
        <p>''I'm ashamed of him,'' Mrs. Trim, who lives in nearby Dickinson Center, said in an interview. ''He was a good kid and I don't know what happened to him.''</p>
        <p>In 2005, Mr. Trim was convicted of driving while intoxicated and aggravated unlicensed operation of a vehicle in the town of Malone, a half-hour's drive from North Lawrence. He was sentenced to three years' probation. St. Lawrence County officials said yesterday that there was no history of violence and that he was considered a ''low-risk'' offender.</p>
        <p>But in December, Mr. Trim did not show up for a routine meeting with his probation officer, and the Canton Village Court issued a warrant for his arrest.</p>
        <p>''He definitely had an issue with law enforcement,'' said Chris Flint, a police officer who arrested Mr. Trim last September after he was spotted in his car with minors and beer. ''He just had this attitude with law enforcement.''</p>
        <p>Alan Mulkin, the police chief in Canton, said that despite Mr. Trim's combative behavior, ''we really had no idea that he would be capable of taking another person's life.''</p>
        <p>Marquis L. Wilkie, a student at SUNY Canton, told the police on Monday that his Dodge Caravan had been stolen late Friday, but shared few details. Yesterday, Officer Flint, who was investigating the theft, said the police believed that Mr. Wilkie was hesitant to report that Mr. Trim, who was a friend, had stolen the van.</p>
        <p>The police said Mr. Wilkie probably thought at first that Mr. Trim would return the vehicle.</p>
        <p>Mark Hill, one of Mr. Trim's instructors at SUNY, told The Associated Press that despite persistent run-ins with police officers, Mr. Trim seemed to do well as a student.</p>
        <p>''He had no bad dealings here,'' Mr. Hill said, according to the wire service. ''He got along with everyone and worked well in team settings.''</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Trim, his grandmother, said that there were other warning signs. He did not show up for Thanksgiving or Christmas last year. Nobody from his hometown had heard from him in weeks.</p>
        <p>''I always scolded him about drugs and liquor,'' Mrs. Trim said in an A.P. interview before the final confrontation. ''I don't think there's any way for this to turn out good now. Not after shooting a trooper.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
