<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pelfrey's Grip on His Rotation Spot Is Becoming Tenuous</title>
    <meta content="26mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/baseball/26mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Colorado Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Colorado Rockies</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pelfrey, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE6DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pelfrey's Grip on His Rotation Spot Is Becoming Tenuous</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pelfrey’s Grip on His Rotation Spot Is Becoming Tenuous</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets have seen Mike Pelfrey dominate. They have seen him pump fastballs past major league hitters and befuddle them with his sinker. They have seen him turn over tough lineups. They just have not seen him do it recently. Not for a while, actually.</p>
        <p>Since winning the fifth starter's job in spring training, Pelfrey has pitched progressively worse. The struggles continued in yesterday's 11-5 loss to the Colorado Rockies at Shea Stadium, when he was lifted for a pinch-hitter after allowing six runs and eight hits in three innings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since winning the fifth starter’s job in spring training, Mike Pelfrey has pitched progressively worse. The struggles continued in Wednesday’s loss to the Colorado Rockies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets have seen Mike Pelfrey dominate. They have seen him pump fastballs past major league hitters and befuddle them with his sinker. They have seen him turn over tough lineups. They just have not seen him do it recently. Not for a while, actually.</p>
        <p>Since winning the fifth starter's job in spring training, Pelfrey has pitched progressively worse. The struggles continued in yesterday's 11-5 loss to the Colorado Rockies at Shea Stadium, when he was lifted for a pinch-hitter after allowing six runs and eight hits in three innings.</p>
        <p>For a team that has championship aspirations, the Mets may need to decide whether developing a young pitcher outweighs their chances of winning every fifth day. With a few starters pitching exceedingly well at Class AAA New Orleans, Pelfrey's grip on his job is growing increasingly tenuous.</p>
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph would not say much about Pelfrey's status after the game besides reminding reporters that ''right now, he's my fifth starter.'' General Manager Omar Minaya, who has repeatedly said that he is not afraid to give young pitchers a chance, did not say whether he would be inclined to take away that chance anytime soon.</p>
        <p>''You have to keep your eyes on him and see where you are,'' Minaya said. ''Right now, he's going to get another start. But I reserve the right to speak to my manager. I haven't spoken to him yet about today's outing.''</p>
        <p>Here would be the main theme of that conversation: Pelfrey consistently left his fastball up and over the plate. With the exception of John Mabry's three-run homer, which capped the Rockies' five-run third, every one of Colorado's hits off him came on belt-high fastballs.</p>
        <p>''I was too stubborn to throw anything else,'' Pelfrey said. ''I just kept throwing them, and they kept hitting them.''</p>
        <p>Overcoming this misguided determination is a natural part of his development. The fastball is his best pitch, so naturally, he reverts to it in times of trouble, hoping it will stop betraying him at some point.</p>
        <p>The same thing happened with John Maine last year, and it took him awhile to conquer the temptation. In fact, Maine will acknowledge that he is still trying to be less dependent on his fastball.</p>
        <p>Pelfrey (0-2) is only 23 and in his second year of professional baseball, the product of being fast-tracked through the minor leagues. With his size (6-foot-7, 210 pounds), ability and mental fortitude, Pelfrey fits the profile of the successful major league starter the Mets expect him to become. But there is no shame in needing more time to develop. Last year at this time, Pelfrey had yet to throw a pitch above Class A St. Lucie.</p>
        <p>''The biggest issue with young pitchers is the big gap between doing your best and trying your best,'' said Rick Peterson, the Mets' pitching coach. ''In the bullpen and his side sessions, he's doing his best. In the game, he's trying his best, and there's a definite difference.''</p>
        <p>Until the third week of March, Pelfrey was having the best spring training of any starter. But he was hit hard in his penultimate start, against Houston, then rocked by Tampa Bay in the exhibition finale. When the Mets headed north to St. Louis for the opening series, Pelfrey stayed in Florida, where he had an average start in his Class A tuneup before joining the team for his April 13 debut against Washington.</p>
        <p>His outings have been increasingly shorter -- five and two-thirds to five to three yesterday -- while allowing more runs in each start. He has given up 12 earned runs in 13 2/3 innings for a 7.90 earned run average.</p>
        <p>''Whatever I'm doing, it's not working,'' Pelfrey said.</p>
        <p>Randolph said: ''It is a growing experience. He needs to continue to find a way to compete at this level.''</p>
        <p>At 13-7, the Mets can afford to give him time to work out of his struggles. Their other four starters are pitching well, which takes pressure off any one man in the rotation.</p>
        <p>During the fateful third inning, Pelfrey allowed consecutive singles to Josh Fogg, the pitcher, and Willy Taveras, who went 5 for 6. With one out, Matt Holliday and Todd Helton hit back-to-back run-scoring singles. Peterson came out to talk to Pelfrey, but the talk did not appear to help much. Mabry blasted a 1-0 changeup 390 feet over the fence in right-center field, and the Rockies led, 6-0. Pelfrey allowed another single before coaxing a popout to end the inning. On his way to the dugout, the announced crowd of 33,522 showered Pelfrey with boos, and he slammed his glove against a wall.</p>
        <p>The most likely situation is that the Mets keep Pelfrey in the rotation through his next start, on Monday against the Florida Marlins, then decide after that whether to keep him in the majors. If they send Pelfrey to New Orleans, their most credible internal options are Jorge Sosa and another first-round pick, Philip Humber. Sosa has recovered from a miserable spring training to go 3-0 with a 1.38 E.R.A. for New Orleans while striking out 24 in 26 innings.</p>
        <p>Humber, recently selected as the Pacific Coast League pitcher of the week, is 2-1 with a 3.00 E.R.A. It is possible that the Mets would replace one first-round pick with another, but Humber might benefit from gaining more minor league experience. Of course, that is something the Mets would rather not have to think about in the first place.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Shawn Green drove in the Mets' first three runs with a bases-loaded triple in the sixth, and Endy Chávez hit a two-run double in the ninth.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
