<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Los Angeles, Lakers Are Losing to Impatience</title>
    <meta content="26lakers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/basketball/26lakers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Phoenix Suns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bryant, Kobe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0DD153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Los Angeles, Lakers Are Losing to Impatience</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Los Angeles, Lakers Are Losing to Impatience</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>EL SEGUNDO, Calif., April 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A relentless, pounding anxiety permeates the Los Angeles Lakers' training center. Phil Jackson senses it. Mitch Kupchak feels it. Kobe Bryant exudes it.</p>
        <p>It would be there even if the Lakers were not down 2-0 to the Phoenix Suns in a first-round playoff series, which they are. It would be there even if they had not just absorbed a 126-98 rout in Phoenix on Tuesday, which they did. And it will be there even if the Lakers win Thursday's Game 3 at Staples Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lakers officials are quietly speaking of the shrinking window for returning to contender status before Kobe Bryant begins to decline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A relentless, pounding anxiety permeates the Los Angeles Lakers' training center. Phil Jackson senses it. Mitch Kupchak feels it. Kobe Bryant exudes it.</p>
        <p>It would be there even if the Lakers were not down 2-0 to the Phoenix Suns in a first-round playoff series, which they are. It would be there even if they had not just absorbed a 126-98 rout in Phoenix on Tuesday, which they did. And it will be there even if the Lakers win Thursday's Game 3 at Staples Center.</p>
        <p>The problem goes to the heart of who the Lakers are and what they hope to be and the one player who can get them there: Kobe Bryant.</p>
        <p>It has been five years since the Lakers raised a championship banner (a painful drought by their standards), and three years since they won a playoff series.</p>
        <p>They have perhaps the greatest player in the game in Bryant and a Hall of Fame coach in Jackson. But they had a lackluster 42-40 season and appear headed for a second consecutive first-round exit from the playoffs.</p>
        <p>These would be small concerns if not for the nagging questions that tug at Lakers officials day and night: How much longer can Bryant play at an otherworldly level before his skills erode? Can the Lakers squeeze in another parade or two before it happens? How long can the notoriously impatient Bryant wait for his young teammates to develop?</p>
        <p>''He's antsy,'' Kupchak, the Lakers' general manager, said. ''And we recognize that we've got a talented and gifted guy that could get us to that level. We don't want to waste that.''</p>
        <p>Bryant is just 28 but, as he often says, it is not the age but the mileage that counts. Bryant, who entered the N.B.A. as a teen prodigy, just completed his 11th pro season. He has logged 128 playoff games -- the equivalent of another season and a half. He will be 30 when he starts his 13th N.B.A. season in the fall of 2008.</p>
        <p>For comparison's sake, Michael Jordan played just 13 seasons at an elite level, not counting the season and a half he sat out to play baseball. Jordan was older when he entered the league, but, like Bryant, he taxed his body with a high-flying, high-impact approach to the game.</p>
        <p>Lakers officials quietly speak of the shrinking window for returning to contender status before Bryant begins to decline. That he has had to overextend himself, averaging more than 30 points a game the last two seasons just to get them to the playoffs, does not help.</p>
        <p>Since the moment the Lakers exiled Shaquille O'Neal to Miami in July 2004, the franchise has been defined by Bryant's otherworldly talents. When Jackson returned in 2005, after a one-year sabbatical, expectations were instantly raised.</p>
        <p>The talent level, however, has not been. After Bryant, the Lakers have just one All-Star-caliber player, the often-injured forward Lamar Odom. Their most promising prospect, center Andrew Bynum, is only 19.</p>
        <p>The hope is that Bynum blossoms into a dominant low-post player while Bryant is still in his prime. Until then, the roster remains sorely lacking in star power. Luke Walton, a third-year pro, is a terrific role player. Jordan Farmar, the rookie point guard, has shown some promise.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Jackson himself wondered aloud if the team made a mistake by standing pat last summer after the Lakers' spirited seven-game series against the Suns.</p>
        <p>Bryant's patience is showing signs of wear. He has noted several times in the past week that ''we're not the most talented team in the world.'' The frustration was evident in his taut expression on the bench Tuesday night, and in his piercing stare as he emerged from the training room after Wednesday's practice.</p>
        <p>''I think now is the time,'' Bryant said.</p>
        <p>''We've had three years here where we're trying to do some things. This upcoming summer and next season, this is really the time to start pushing a little bit and get to that contender level.''</p>
        <p>Bryant feels an urgency that he did not five years ago, when he and O'Neal alternately feuded and dominated on the way to three consecutive title. His championship teammates have all moved on or retired.</p>
        <p>There are times when Bryant seems wistful for that veteran cast as he prods, encourages and occasionally berates his young teammates. There is indeed a window, Bryant acknowledges, but said, ''I don't know what that window is.''</p>
        <p>The Lakers' effort to rebuild on the fly, without salary-cap space, has brought uneven results. Two years ago, they traded the swingman Caron Butler to Washington (where he has become an All-Star) for the enigmatic and frequently injured center Kwame Brown. Last summer, they signed the veteran shooting specialist Vladimir Radmanovic to a five-year, $30 million contract.</p>
        <p>In January, Brown was accused of grabbing a stranger's $190 birthday cake and throwing it outside of a Hermosa Beach club. In February, Radmanovic was fined $500,000 by the team after he separated his shoulder in a snowboarding accident and then lied about it.</p>
        <p>The Lakers' best shot at improving quickly would be to trade Odom or Bynum. But team officials consider those two players untouchable. Attempts to acquire the Nets All-Star Jason Kidd in February reportedly failed because the Lakers refused to include Bynum.</p>
        <p>''He's not in our plans to trade,'' Kupchak said. ''It's one of those deals where you kind of don't know what you have. You hate to do something too soon.''</p>
        <p>Jackson has his own window. He has one year left on the three-year, $30 million contract he signed in 2005. His agent has opened negotiations on an extension with the team owner, Jerry Buss. Those talks will certainly take into account whether the Lakers have any hope of making a major move in the next few years.</p>
        <p>''They're paying me a championship salary to do what?'' Jackson said. ''Not to get to the playoffs -- to get somewhere in the playoffs. I have accountability in that direction, too.''</p>
        <p>The question remains one of acquiring or developing elite talent, and soon.</p>
        <p>''They've got some decisions to make, if they want to build a contender now, or if you want to hold onto these pieces for five years from now,'' Bryant said. ''They got some tough choices.''</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
