<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Publicity About Tirade, Actor Asks to Leave '30 Rock'</title>
    <meta content="26alec" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/arts/26alec.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nbc Universal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baldwin, Alec</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Basinger, Kim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">30 Rock (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Baldwin, Alec</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DD153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Publicity About Tirade, Actor Asks to Leave '30 Rock'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amid Publicity About Tirade, Actor Asks to Leave ‘30 Rock’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alec Baldwin, who plays lead role in NBC's new comedy 30 Rock, asks to be let out of his contract in wake of whirlwind of negative publicity he received for tirade he unleashed at his 11-year-old daughter in message recorded by phone answering machine and leaked to press; is in custody battle with his former wife, Kim Basinger; NBC expresses confidence that he will return to show (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NBC was hit yesterday with the news that one of its important stars, Alec Baldwin, who plays a lead role in the network's promising new comedy ''30 Rock,'' had asked to be let out of his contract on the show.</p>
        <p>The network immediately expressed confidence that Mr. Baldwin would return to the show next season. The news came after a whirlwind of negative publicity directed at Mr. Baldwin for a tirade of anger he unleashed at his 11-year-old daughter, Ireland, in a message recorded on a phone answering machine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alec Baldwin, who plays a lead role in NBC’s new comedy “30 Rock,” asked Wednesday to be let out of his contract on the show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NBC was hit yesterday with the news that one of its important stars, Alec Baldwin, who plays a lead role in the network's promising new comedy ''30 Rock,'' had asked to be let out of his contract on the show.</p>
        <p>The network immediately expressed confidence that Mr. Baldwin would return to the show next season. The news came after a whirlwind of negative publicity directed at Mr. Baldwin for a tirade of anger he unleashed at his 11-year-old daughter, Ireland, in a message recorded on a phone answering machine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin, who is in the midst of a long and bitter custody battle with Ireland's mother, the actress Kim Basinger, called his daughter ''a thoughtless little pig'' in the voice mail message, which was leaked to the press last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin was upset because his daughter had not called him as arranged. Ms. Basinger denied leaking the message. On his Web site, Mr. Baldwin issued an apology for his outburst.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin had already announced this week that he was quitting his talent agency, Creative Artists. His press representative said that the decision was made for ''personal reasons'' and said it was not related to the work of his agents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin contacted NBC yesterday and said he wanted to discontinue his commitment to ''30 Rock,'' which is shot in New York.</p>
        <p>NBC executives reacted by urging him not to do anything hasty. They said last night that they had no doubt he would remain in the role of Jack Donaghy.</p>
        <p>In an official statement, NBC said: ''Alec Baldwin remains an important part of '30 Rock.' We look forward to having him continue in the role.''</p>
        <p>''30 Rock,'' despite struggling in the ratings this season, is an important show for NBC because it has been praised by critics and has had good word-of-mouth reaction from its fans. Mr. Baldwin's performance has won almost universal praise, and he won a Golden Globe award for playing the character.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Baldwin nor his press representative could be reached for comment. But NBC executives said they were aware that Mr. Baldwin taped an appearance for ABC's ''The View,'' scheduled to be shown tomorrow morning, during which he stated that he intended to end his television career and might leave the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baldwin, 49, the eldest of four acting brothers from Long Island, had issued a statement before the 2004 election saying that he would leave the country if President Bush were re-elected. Mr. Baldwin did not change his residence.</p>
        <p>One senior NBC executive said: ''We think this is an emotional moment for him. We're confident he'll be back. He's still under contract.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
