<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dow Surge Puts 13,000 In the Past</title>
    <meta content="26stox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/business/26stox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS AND BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Industrial Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bajaj, Vikas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1356" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dow Surge Puts 13,000 In the Past</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Run on Wall Street Sends Dow Above 13,000</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIKAS BAJAJ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bajaj, Vikas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Jones Industrial average closes above 13,000 mark for first time; is up 6 percent for month, its best performance in single months since December 2003; index rises 135.95 points, or 1.05 percent, to 13,089.89; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index jumps 15.01 points, or 1 percent, to 1,495.42; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Far from being the cruelest month, April has turned out to be one of the most profitable in recent memory for investors in the stock market.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average, the widely followed index of 30 large companies, closed above the 13,000 mark yesterday for the first time and is up 6 percent for the month, its best performance in a single month since December 2003.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rally has defied skeptics who thought stocks were due for a harder slog as the economy slows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Far from being the cruelest month, April has turned out to be one of the most profitable in recent memory for investors in the stock market.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average, the widely followed index of 30 large companies, closed above the 13,000 mark yesterday for the first time and is up 6 percent for the month, its best performance in a single month since December 2003.</p>
        <p>The index rose 135.95 points, or 1.05 percent, to 13,089.89. The broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index closed up 15.01 points, or 1 percent, to 1,495.42, and is up 5.3 percent for the month.</p>
        <p>The rally has been broad and strong and has defied skeptics who thought stocks were due for a harder slog as the economy slows, corporate earnings grow at a less robust pace and the housing market, the engine of the recent expansion, struggles with a glut of unsold properties and problems in the mortgage business. In fact, since Feb. 27, when the Dow dropped more than 400 points because of a market slump in Asia, the index has rebounded 7.2 percent.</p>
        <p>While investors say they are keeping an eye on the potential stumbling blocks, Wall Street seems to be far more focused on positive indicators like the announcement earlier this week by I.B.M. that it would spend $15 billion more to buy back its own shares or the $25 billion buyout of Sallie Mae by private equity firms and two big banks.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot of money sloshing around,'' said James P. Dunigan, chief investment officer for the wealth management business of PNC. ''It continues to be about liquidity.''</p>
        <p>Investors are betting, in effect, that the economy will make the financial equivalent of a rolling stop -- growth will slow briefly without turning into a recession, and the pace will start quickening again as early as next year.</p>
        <p>They note, for instance, that the problems in the mortgage business have been limited to loans that were made to people with weak, or subprime, credit, who account for a sliver of consumer spending. (Default rates for loans to people with better credit have also been rising, but they remain low by historical standards.)</p>
        <p>Furthermore, investors are betting that the Federal Reserve will stimulate economic activity sometime this fall by cutting its benchmark interest rate, which it has left unchanged at 5.25 percent since last summer.</p>
        <p>Skeptics note that investors are banking on a rare economic feat, the so-called soft landing. They contend that the nation has not yet felt the full brunt of the problems in housing. Construction employment, for instance, remains at its boom-era levels, even though spending on residential building has fallen sharply. Also, profit growth has only recently begun to slow for some companies.</p>
        <p>''It took a long time for housing to have the positive impact that it did,'' said Marc D. Stern, chief investment officer at Bessemer Trust. ''And it is likely to take a long time for housing to have a negative impact.''</p>
        <p>It is worth noting that even with the recent rally, stocks remain far cheaper than they were during the technology-fueled boom of the late 1990s. The price-to-earnings ratio, a commonly used measure of how expensive stocks are, relative to corporate earnings, was 17.6 for the stocks in the Dow as of yesterday, down from 25.5 in January 2000 and roughly the same as the average for the last 15 years.</p>
        <p>The relative value of stocks today, optimists say, signals that the market still has room to run. They note that most of the money that has poured into the market in recent years has come from institutional investors, rather than individuals. In the three weeks that ended April 18, for instance, investors withdrew $3.3 billion from domestic stock funds, according to AMG Data Services, a research firm. By contrast, investors put $7.3 billion into nondomestic stock funds and $4.8 billion into taxable bond funds.</p>
        <p>''The whole rally here has been driven by institutional investors and companies themselves doing share buybacks,'' said Jeffrey Kleintop, chief market strategist for LPL Financial in Boston. ''That's taking a lot of stock off the table if you will.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kleintop says he thinks that the market will move higher as individual investors return their attention to domestic stocks. He and other specialists say they believe that many Americans shifted their focus away from the stock market to housing over the last few years in reaction to the bear markets of 2001 and 2002 and because low interest rates touched off the housing boom. Many investors have also turned to commodities like gold, and international stocks, which have outstripped their American peers in part because the dollar has lost ground against the euro and British pound.</p>
        <p>''Now the pendulum is swinging back,'' Mr. Kleintop said.</p>
        <p>Still, other specialists caution that many individual investors may not have the financial wherewithal to jump into the stock market, especially if the values of their homes are declining. Many homeowners will also have to contend with rising house payments because of the resetting of adjustable-rate mortgages. Even those who are able to refinance into a fixed-rate mortgage will pay somewhat more for housing because interest rates, while still near historic lows, are higher now than they were in recent years.</p>
        <p>The recent rally that has pushed the Dow to 13,000 has been led by a group of industrial stalwarts like Alcoa, the aluminum maker that has been considered a potential takeover target, and Honeywell, the maker of aircraft and automotive parts and chemicals, both of which are up about 30 percent since October, when the Dow reached 12,000. Altogether, 27 of the 30 Dow stocks have posted gains during that period.</p>
        <p>The bigger Dow stocks are benefiting from strong growth in Europe and Asia and the weaker dollar, which makes American exports cheaper on the world market. ''Export growth and the services side of the economy is quite healthy,'' said Liz Ann Sonders, the chief investment strategist at Charles Schwab.</p>
        <p>However, 17 of the Dow stocks, including I.B.M., General Electric and Coca-Cola, still have not returned to the levels they were trading at in January 2000, near the peak of the broader stock market.</p>
        <p>The Dow average is calculated by adding up the stock prices of the 30 stocks and dividing them by a divisor that is adjusted occasionally to account for changes in the index and stock splits. A $1 change in a stock like 3M that trades at about $76 a share has the same effect on the index as a $1 rise in Microsoft that trades at about $28, even though Microsoft's market value is about five times that of 3M.</p>
        <p>By contrast, broader indexes like the S.&amp; P. are weighted by market value, so moves in the value of a bigger company's shares will have a bigger influence on the index than changes in those of smaller ones. If the Dow was calculated like the S.&amp; P., the index would be about 12 percent lower than the high it set in January 2000, according to calculations by Howard Silverblatt, senior index analyst at Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
        <p>Still, the Dow, measured as a simple average, remains one of the most watched and quoted market barometers, in large part because it is the oldest of the major stock market indexes. And over the long run, its performance has tracked closely with the broader S.&amp; P., which includes all of the Dow's 30 members.</p>
        <p>''Over time, the S.&amp; P. and Dow correlate very well,'' Mr. Silverblatt said. But ''over several years, you can get big variations.''</p>
        <p>The S.&amp; P. 500 is still about 2.1 percent from its record of 1,527.46, which it reached in March 2000. And the Nasdaq composite remains about 50 percent from its high.</p>
        <p>Following are the results of yesterday's auction of two-year Treasury notes:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>High Price: 99.799  High Yield: 4.606  Low Yield: 4.550  Median Yield: 4.590  Accepted at low price: 39%  Total applied for: $57,545,216  Accepted: $22,777,336  Noncompetitive: $702,092  Interest set at: 4 1/2 %</p>
        <p>The 2-year notes mature April 30, 2009.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS AND BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
