<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coming From Behind, Curlin Emerges as a Favorite</title>
    <meta content="26racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/othersports/26racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0DD153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coming From Behind, Curlin Emerges as a Favorite</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Coming From Behind, Curlin Emerges as a Favorite</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The racing card at Gulfstream Park on Feb. 3 was loaded with big races and quality horses. They ran six stakes races that day and the competition included the 2006 Horse of the Year, Invasor, and the highly regarded 3-year-old Nobiz Like Shobiz. But the horse that made the biggest impression on Steve Asmussen was a maiden winner named Curlin.</p>
        <p>Then trained by Helen Pitts, Curlin ran off from his seven rivals in a 12 3/4-length victory that was both dominant and brilliant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The enticing possibility that Curlin will emerge as racing’s next super horse will be among the themes of this year’s Kentucky Derby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The racing card at Gulfstream Park on Feb. 3 was loaded with big races and quality horses. They ran six stakes races that day and the competition included the 2006 Horse of the Year, Invasor, and the highly regarded 3-year-old Nobiz Like Shobiz. But the horse that made the biggest impression on Steve Asmussen was a maiden winner named Curlin.</p>
        <p>Then trained by Helen Pitts, Curlin ran off from his seven rivals in a 12 3/4-length victory that was both dominant and brilliant.</p>
        <p>''That race was an acknowledgment of what he could be,'' Asmussen said.</p>
        <p>Less than three months later, Asmussen, now the trainer of Curlin, still does not know how good this horse is. Neither, really, does anybody else. But after he followed up his initial victory with equally impressive victories in the Rebel Stakes and the Arkansas Derby, the enticing possibility that Curlin will emerge as racing's next super horse will be among the themes of this year's Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>''What he has done to this point is extraordinary,'' Asmussen said. ''For him to have not started at age 2 and then win a graded stakes in his second race out and $1 million race in his third race out, when you put that on paper, it is pretty amazing to look at. Then there's the way he's done it -- very easily.''</p>
        <p>Less than a week after Curlin won his first race, the prominent owners Jess Jackson and Satish Sanan swept in and bought a majority interest in the colt from Midnight Cry Stable. Sanan said the purchase price was about $3.5 million. Midnight Cry had bought Curlin at a yearling sale for $57,000.</p>
        <p>Midnight Cry Stable is a partnership between the lawyers William Gallion and Shirley Cunningham Jr. Gallion and Cunningham have been accused of misappropriating $64.4 million after helping their clients win a $200 million settlement with the makers of the diet drug fen-phen, which has been found to lead to heart defects. Neither returned phone calls seeking comment as to why they sold the horse.</p>
        <p>Pitts still trains some horses for Midnight Cry Stable, but not the colt that might have given her a Kentucky Derby victory. She admits it has not been easy watching Curlin emerge as the likely favorite for the Derby on May 5.</p>
        <p>''It's been hard, very hard,'' she said. ''I understand that in this game you've got to do what you've got to do. I wish them all the best luck, and I feel honored to have been part of his career at some point.''</p>
        <p>The new owners turned Curlin over to Asmussen, who plotted an aggressive route to the Kentucky Derby. Though inexperienced and stretching out in distance for the first time, Curlin romped in the Rebel, winning the mile-and-a-sixteenth race by five and a quarter lengths. Four weeks later, he captured the mile-and-an-eighth Arkansas Derby at Oaklawn Park, a race won in recent years by such Triple Crown standouts as Smarty Jones and Afleet Alex, by 10 1/2 lengths. The winning margin was the largest in the race's 71-year history.</p>
        <p>Asmussen is convinced that the horse has yet to reach his full potential.</p>
        <p>''When we acquired him, our worry was that he had been all out mentally or physically,'' Asmussen said. ''It's been anything but. Baby Huey would be a better description of him. I definitely think there's more to come. Watch the Arkansas Derby -- he could have done more. That's the amazing part.''</p>
        <p>As talented as Curlin might be, he is far from a sure thing in the Kentucky Derby, a grueling race that has been hard on horses that lack experience.</p>
        <p>The last horse to win the Kentucky Derby without having run as a 2-year-old was Apollo, in 1882. Since 1977, 27 horses that did not race as a 2-year-old have started in the Derby, though only a few were considered serious contenders. The best result was the second-place finish by Strodes Creek in 1994.</p>
        <p>The last horse to win the Derby with three or fewer prior starts was Regret, in 1915. Since 1977, only eight Derby horses entered the race with such a limited background. Of that group, none finished in the top three.</p>
        <p>Pitts said Curlin's debut was delayed because of minor shin problems and because she was in no rush to start a horse who was slow to develop.</p>
        <p>''He was just real big and he had some shin problems here and there,'' Pitts said. ''We figured it would be more worthwhile letting him fill out and be right rather than running him when he wasn't ready.''</p>
        <p>Barbaro was also going against some history last year when he became the first horse since 1956 to win the Derby off a layoff of five weeks or more, which proved that not every Derby winner has to fit a certain pattern.</p>
        <p>Like Curlin, Barbaro was also undefeated going into the Derby. And like Barbaro, Curlin could be a horse that has enough talent to overcome any of the disadvantages he may face. If he does, racing will have the intriguing new star that it needs.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
