<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agency Building New Jersey Schools Says Funds Are Too Low for All Projects</title>
    <meta content="26schools" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/nyregion/26schools.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070501T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Schools Construction Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Scott A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agency Building New Jersey Schools Says Funds Are Too Low for All Projects</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Agency Building New Jersey Schools Says Funds Are Too Low for All Projects</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Schools Construction Corp, which has been embattled for last two years for its failure to complete projects, says that it has money to build or rehabilitate 32 schools in poor districts rather than 59 projects outlined by officials in summer of 2006; Scott Weiner, chief of corporation, says planning for remaining 27 projects willl continue in hopes that State Legislature would eventually authorize money to complete them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Schools Construction Corporation, embattled for the last two years for its failure to complete projects, said on Wednesday that it had the money to build or rehabilitate 32 schools in poor districts rather than the 59 projects that New Jersey officials outlined last summer.</p>
        <p>Scott Weiner, chief executive of the corporation, said planning for the remaining 27 projects from last year's list would continue gradually in hopes that the State Legislature would eventually authorize the money to complete them. Nine of those were scheduled to start this summer but will now be deferred.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Obtaining any new funding  or significant support from Gov. Jon S. Corzine’s administration  has been difficult of late for the much-criticized schools construction agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Schools Construction Corporation, embattled for the last two years for its failure to complete projects, said on Wednesday that it had the money to build or rehabilitate 32 schools in poor districts rather than the 59 projects that New Jersey officials outlined last summer.</p>
        <p>Scott Weiner, chief executive of the corporation, said planning for the remaining 27 projects from last year's list would continue gradually in hopes that the State Legislature would eventually authorize the money to complete them. Nine of those were scheduled to start this summer but will now be deferred.</p>
        <p>Obtaining any new funding -- or significant support from Gov. Jon S. Corzine's administration -- has been difficult of late for the much-criticized schools construction agency. The agency has been undergoing a sweeping reorganization since a 2005 inspector general's report found that it was ''vulnerable to mismanagement, fiscal malfeasance, conflicts of interest, and waste, fraud and abuse.''</p>
        <p>The agency began in 2002 with more than $6 billion in borrowed funds to build or rehabilitate about 400 schools in the 31 poorest school districts in the state, known as Abbott districts because of a landmark court case. But as a result of the problems cited by the inspector general and other shortcomings, the agency found in 2005 that it had enough money to complete only 59 of the projects, delaying 315 others.</p>
        <p>Now, the agency has about $639 million on hand -- enough to finish the 32 projects, but about $600 million short for all 59.</p>
        <p>That shortfall itself ballooned from $400 million last summer, a change that Mr. Weiner attributed to emergency spending, inflation and construction delays. He said, however, that the agency had gotten better about prioritizing projects based on educational needs and construction logistics.</p>
        <p>More than $5 billion, apparently, has been spent in the past five years on land acquisition and planning; no projects have been completed.</p>
        <p>The inspector general's revelations started widespread criticism of the agency among lawmakers who continue to question, even with the pending reorganization, whether it is up to the task of building schools.</p>
        <p>The new plan by the agency comes two weeks after the Education Law Center, a nonprofit advocacy group based in Newark, filed suit to compel the Legislature to authorize new funds for the construction effort.</p>
        <p>The center represented children in the state's poorer districts in a 1998 court case that led to state borrowing to finance the construction agency. David G. Sciarra, executive director of the center, said Wednesday's school construction report should be ''a wake-up call'' to the lawmakers.</p>
        <p>''We have kids and teachers in schools under conditions that should not be tolerated,'' he said. ''The state is legally obligated to fully fund improvements in the poorer districts, and the longer the wait, the more the costs increase.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 1, 2007, Tuesday  An article on Thursday about a reduction in the number of schools that the New Jersey Schools Construction Corporation says it can build or rehabilitate with the money it has on hand referred incorrectly to the status of the agency's previous projects and to their costs. Fifty-six -- not zero -- projects have been completed in the past five years, including 30 new schools and 26 major renovations. The more than $5 billion spent so far includes $1.25 billion for these projects as well as land acquisition and planning for others; the $5 billion was not spent on land purchases and planning costs alone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 1, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about a reduction in the number of schools that the New Jersey Schools Construction Corporation says it can build or rehabilitate with the money it has on hand referred incorrectly to the status of the agency's previous projects and to their costs. Fifty-six -- not zero -- projects have been completed in the past five years, including 30 new schools and 26 major renovations. The more than $5 billion spent so far includes $1.25 billion for these projects as well as land acquisition and planning for others; the $5 billion was not spent on land purchases and planning costs alone.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
