<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Banks in a Bidding War for ABN Amro</title>
    <meta content="26bank" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/business/26bank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Bank of Scotland Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Santander Central Hispano</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fortis Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barclays Bank Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abn Amro</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Werdigier, Julia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <org class="online_producer">ABN AMRO Holding NV</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Royal Bank of Scotland Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Barclays Plc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1259" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Banks in a Bidding War for ABN Amro</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rival Bid for ABN Amro Is $98.5 Billion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA WERDIGIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Werdigier, Julia</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Royal Bank of Scotland, Banco Santander Central Hispano and Fortis make unsolicited cash offer of 72.2 billion euros ($98.5 billion) for ABN Amro; offer beats bid made by Barclays; either bid, if accepted, would rank among largest worldwide merger deals; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Royal Bank of Scotland, the British bank, and two other European lenders on Wednesday opened the biggest takeover battle in banking industry by offering 72.2 billion euros, or $98.5 billion, for ABN Amro, the largest Dutch bank.</p>
        <p>Royal Bank of Scotland, together with Banco Santander Central Hispano, Spain's largest bank, and Fortis, a Belgian banking group, made an unsolicited offer of 39 euros a share in stock and cash for ABN Amro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The offer by the Royal Bank of Scotland and other lenders trumps the Barclays bid in the biggest takeover battle in banking industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Royal Bank of Scotland, the British bank, and two other European lenders on Wednesday opened the biggest takeover battle in banking industry by offering 72.2 billion euros, or $98.5 billion, for ABN Amro, the largest Dutch bank.</p>
        <p>Royal Bank of Scotland, together with Banco Santander Central Hispano, Spain's largest bank, and Fortis, a Belgian banking group, made an unsolicited offer of 39 euros a share in stock and cash for ABN Amro.</p>
        <p>Their offer, 70 percent in cash and the rest in Royal Bank of Scotland stock, trumps a 36.25 euros all-share offer made by Barclays, another British bank, on Monday. Either offer, if completed, would still result in one of the world's largest combinations ever.</p>
        <p>Royal Bank of Scotland is seen as an aggressive institution, expanding rapidly in recent years under its chief executive, Fred Goodwin, who along the way has gained the nickname Fred the Shred. ABN officials worry that any sale to the Royal Bank of Scotland group would lead to a breakup of the Dutch bank, so they have staunchly supported the offer from Barclays.</p>
        <p>''While Barclays may struggle to match the Royal Bank offer, it is likely to continue to emphasize the simplicity and friendly nature of its offer,'' said Jean-Pierre Lambert, an analyst at Keefe Bruyette &amp; Woods in London.</p>
        <p>Barclays has some room to improve its current bid for ABN Amro but a bid of more than 43 euros a share would be ''value destructive'' for Barclays, according to Alex Potter, an analyst at Collins Stewart in London.</p>
        <p>However the contest unfolds, ABN Amro and Barclays are likely to face pointed questions from shareholders on Thursday at their general annual meetings. The rival bid by the Royal Bank of Scotland group is contingent on ABN Amro keeping LaSalle Bank, its American operation that is one of the main attractions, the group said Wednesday. In what was widely seen as an attempt to discourage an approach by the Royal Bank of Scotland consortium, ABN Amro announced on Monday that it had agreed to sell LaSalle for $21 billion to Bank of America.</p>
        <p>On a conference call Wednesday evening attended by top executives of ABN Amro and the three banks, ABN Amro agreed to grant the Royal Bank of Scotland group access to the some of its financial information the group had asked for. The request was granted even though ''the consortium has provided few additional details with respect to its proposal,'' ABN said in a statement Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The Royal Bank of Scotland group has yet to tell shareholders how it will finance a bid.</p>
        <p>The takeover would be the world's third largest, according to data from Thomson Financial. Vodafone AirTouch's $203 billion merger with Mannesmann in 1999 is the world's biggest and is followed by America Online's acquisition of Time Warner in 2000.</p>
        <p>ABN Amro shares rose 3.5 percent to 36.21 euros Wednesday in Amsterdam. Barclays' shares rose 1.6 percent to 724 pence and shares in Royal Bank fell 0.8 percent to 19.98 pounds both in London.</p>
        <p>Rijkman W. J. Groenink, ABN Amro's chief executive, has in the past said that he would reject any plans to split up ABN Amro, where he has spent almost his entire career. And on Monday, Mr. Groenink said that he did not think dividing the bank up made financial sense.</p>
        <p>Analysts agreed that the Royal Bank of Scotland group would be able to pay more for ABN Amro than Barclays because it could generate higher cost savings. They added that Barclays' offer may be less attractive because it was all in Barclays stock.</p>
        <p>But the battle for ABN Amro may not be decided on price because of Mr. Groenink's eagerness to avoid a division of the bank. He could argue, analysts said, that there is more long-term value for shareholders if ABN Amro merges with Barclays to create a larger bank instead of being split among three rivals.</p>
        <p>The counteroffer raised questions about the real intentions of Mr. Goodwin. Some analysts questioned whether Mr. Goodwin, who has the reputation of being an aggressive deal maker, really wants anything more than to spoil an attempt by a close rival to create a global bank.</p>
        <p>''If he really wanted ABN, why didn't he make a move earlier?'' said Howard Wheeldon, a senior strategist for BGC Partners, a brokerage firm, in London. ''He is a very acquisitive man and has moved Royal Bank up the rankings, but we now have to ask whether he can get this one through to the bank's own shareholders or whether it's just one challenge too far.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Goodwin has turned a small Scottish bank, founded in 1727 in Edinburgh, into a global player by spending more than $15 billion on takeovers in the last five years. Mr. Goodwin, who has run the bank since 1998, purchased Charter One Financial in the United States for $10.3 billion in 2004 and combined it with Citizens Financial Group, based in Providence, R. I., which Royal Bank of Scotland bought in 1988. Royal Bank of Scotland shares suffered after the Charter One Financial acquisition because it came just before an increase in interest rates in the United States, and the acquisition started to weigh on the group's earnings.</p>
        <p>The bank has since focused on building its capital markets unit, which accounts for one-third of pretax profit, and expanding into equity derivatives and commodities by hiring staff.</p>
        <p>Profit in the second-half rose 12 percent to 3.22 billion pounds, or $6.4 billion, more than analysts had expected, as its growing corporate lending business offset the bank's exposure to Britain's growing consumer debt, the bank said last month.</p>
        <p>In 2006, Royal Bank of Scotland leapfrogged Citigroup to become Europe's biggest arranger of syndicated loans and planned to increase revenue in Asia to offset slower growth at home and lower margins in America. In 2004, Royal Bank of Scotland bought a $1.57 billion stake in Bank of China.</p>
        <p>Barclays' bid for ABN Amro may have reawakened Mr. Goodwin's eagerness to do deals and brought back memories of the fight for National Westminster Bank in 2000, when Royal Bank of Scotland, already then backed by Banco Santander, won the battle for the bank with a bid of £23.6 billion. Royal Bank of Scotland and its two partners, which are advised by Merrill Lynch, argued Wednesday that execution risk would be lower than in a deal with Barclays because all three banks have ''proven capabilities in delivering transaction benefits'' and together they have experience in all of ABN Amro's markets.</p>
        <p>Other analysts said that shareholders might still opt for the higher takeover offer.</p>
        <p>The Children's Investment Fund, an activist hedge fund investor in ABN Amro whose pressure on the bank's management board to bolster the share price prompted the start of takeover talks with Barclays this year, called the offer Wednesday by the Royal Bank of Scotland consortium ''compelling.''</p>
        <p>The London-based fund, which owns less than 3 percent in the Dutch bank, also said that ABN Amro must now allow the Royal Bank of Scotland group full access to the same financial information it has already given to Barclays.</p>
        <p>It said that ABN Amro should recommend the offer and terminate the sale of LaSalle.</p>
        <p>Yet, some investors are skeptical that Mr. Goodwin and his partners can make a deal work that involves combining assets in four countries, with different cultures and in different jurisdictions. Mr. Wheeldon, the senior strategist at BGC Partners, said, ''The regulatory process may very well grind the Royal Bank bid to a halt in the end.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
