<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Curious, It's Open House Season</title>
    <meta content="26WEBtour" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EFD91531F935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="4640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Curious, It's Open House Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHELLY FREIERMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 2007 season of show houses and house and garden tours runs through fall, with several events every weekend.</p>
        <p>Visitors -- dreamers, planners, would-be master builders and just plain oglers -- can peer into rooms that have been painstakingly restored to period detail, fancifully concocted with the latest whimsy and stuffed with owners' collections of artworks great and knickknacks small. They can gaze at the flowers, trees, mosses, grasses, ferns and fountains that have transformed backyards into seasonal Edens, smell the scent of blooms and feel the soft breezes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 2007 season of show houses and house and garden tours runs through fall, with several events every weekend.</p>
        <p>Visitors -- dreamers, planners, would-be master builders and just plain oglers -- can peer into rooms that have been painstakingly restored to period detail, fancifully concocted with the latest whimsy and stuffed with owners' collections of artworks great and knickknacks small. They can gaze at the flowers, trees, mosses, grasses, ferns and fountains that have transformed backyards into seasonal Edens, smell the scent of blooms and feel the soft breezes.</p>
        <p>Here, starting in New York City, are all manner of house tours, show houses and garden tours. Unless otherwise noted, each is self-guided.</p>
        <p>New York City</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN, THROUGH MAY 22 The 35th annual Kips Bay Decorator Show House is open in a 1904 Beaux-Arts mansion built by C.P.H. Gilbert, at 14 East 82nd Street. The participants include 20 designers; Monica Rich Kosann, a portrait photographer; and three painters. The show house is open Monday through Saturday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. (until 8 p.m. on Tuesdays and Thursdays), and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. No children under 6. Tickets, to benefit the Kips Bay Boys and Girls Club, $30. More information: (718) 893-8600, extension 245 and kipsbay.org.</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN HEIGHTS, MAY 12 Five houses will be open from 1 to 5 p.m. in this neighborhood, which was designated New York's first historic district in 1965. One is a former carriage house built in 1846 and converted to residential use 100 years later. It is decorated with Biedermeier, Asian and American antiques, and its garden features a brick folly surrounded by weeping cherry trees and rose bushes. A Renaissance Revival house overlooking the East River and the Manhattan skyline, and an 1833 wooden Federal house that has just been restored also will be featured. No children under 13 except infants in front packs. Reservations are recommended for tickets, $30, at (718) 858-9193 and brooklynheightsassociation.org. On the day of the tour only, tickets will be sold starting at 12:30 p.m. at 129 Pierrepont Street (near Clinton Street).</p>
        <p>PARK SLOPE, BROOKLYN, MAY 20 Eight houses will be open from noon to 5 p.m. during the 48th annual edition of the Park Slope Civic Council house tour, along with the St. Francis Xavier Church, a Gothic Revival building designed by Thomas Houghton, which will be open from 1:15 to 5 p.m. Guided tours will be offered in the church, which features a rose window and the only known stained glass window based on a Peter Paul Rubens painting.</p>
        <p>The houses on the tour include a 1909 neo-Italian Renaissance home decorated with African dowry objects and a collection of prints and paintings; a 1903 Arts and Crafts style house with Mission furniture, several chandeliers and an unusual split staircase; and an 1895 converted carriage house with an interior courtyard.</p>
        <p>No children under 10 except infants in front packs. Tickets are $25, at Eighth Avenue and Garfield Place. Advance tickets, $20, and information: (718) 832-8227 and parkslopeciviccouncil.org.</p>
        <p>HAMILTON HEIGHTS, MANHATTAN, JUNE 3 Ten to twelve houses will be open from 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. On June 2 at 11 a.m., there will be a guided walking tour in the neighborhood. Tickets for June 3, $25, at Hamilton Grange National Monument, Convent Avenue at 141st Street. Tickets for the guided tour on June 2 are $15. Information: (212) 281-4442 and hamiltonheights.org.</p>
        <p>PROSPECT LEFFERTS GARDENS, BROOKLYN, JUNE 3 Eight houses and the garden of a local landscape designer will be open from noon to 5 p.m. The properties include a three-story 1904 brownstone which is decorated with the owners' collection of 19th- and 20th-century Asian and English antiques, with front and backyard gardens, a greenhouse, large spa-like baths and a children's playroom. There is also a contemporary renovation inside a 1906 house damaged by fire in the 1970s, with a slate bathroom suite featuring cascading water and a skylight, a stainless-steel kitchen and a music room. A 98-year-old restored limestone row house with its original parquet floors and plaster ceilings and moldings is accented by such salvaged artifacts as a marble back-splash from the Biltmore Hotel, and mahogany doors from the onetime AT&amp;T building, which have been made into a desk. Infants in front packs only. Tickets, $25, at Mike's International Restaurant, 552 Flatbush Avenue (Maple Street). Advance tickets, $20, and information: (718) 284-6210 or (718) 462-0024; by e-mail to plghousetour@earthlink.net and at leffertsmanor.org.</p>
        <p>PROSPECT HEIGHTS, FORT GREENE AND CLINTON HILL, BROOKLYN, JUNE 3 At least 15 private gardens will be open from 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. for the 10th annual Brownstone Brooklyn Garden District's Garden Walk. They include a children's play garden; two ''endangered'' gardens, which are within the footprint of the proposed Atlantic Yards development; and a double garden surrounding a brick cottage. There will also be several community gardens, planted with vegetables, flowers, herbs and ornamentals.</p>
        <p>Tickets, $20, at the Forest Floor, 659 Vanderbilt Avenue (Prospect Place) in Prospect Heights; at the Brooklyn Academy of Music garden, Lafayette Avenue at St. Felix Street in Fort Greene; and at Tillie's, DeKalb and Vanderbilt Avenues in Clinton Hill. Advance tickets, $15, and information: (718) 707-1277. There is no Web site.</p>
        <p>JACKSON HEIGHTS, QUEENS, JUNE 9 AND 10 On June 9, nine private gardens will be open from noon to 4 p.m. The gardens are found in the interior courtyards of the 1920's apartment buildings that make up the neighborhood. They include the Chateau, Elm Court, Hampton Court and Hawthorne Court. The largest gardens feature classical designs, with sitting areas, fountains and paths with columns. There will also be a display of historic photographs and student art, and an illustrated lecture on the history of Jackson Heights at 10:45 a.m. and 12:15 p.m.</p>
        <p>On June 10, a guided neighborhood tour will be offered starting at noon. Tickets for the guided tour must be reserved or purchased in advance. Tickets for one tour, $10; both, $15. All events take place or begin at the Community Church, 35th Avenue at 82nd Street. Information: (718) 565-5344 and jhbg.org.</p>
        <p>MOUNT MORRIS PARK, HARLEM, JUNE 10 A tour from 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. will feature several historic brownstones as well as new apartments and several places of worship. There will also be a guided tour in Marcus Garvey Park at 11 a.m. and guided tours of the neighborhood with John Reddick, a historian, at noon and 2 p.m. Tickets, $30, Pelham Fritz Community Center, West 122nd Street and Mount Morris Park West. Advance tickets, $25; or tour events and a reception, $40, and information: (212) 369-4241 and harlemmtmorris.org.</p>
        <p>FLATBUSH, BROOKLYN, JUNE 10 Ten to twelve houses will be open for the 31st annual Victorian Flatbush house tour, from 1 to 6 p.m. The Flatbush area is home to four historic districts, with tree-lined streets and Craftsman, Victorian, Colonial Revival, Tudor and Queen Anne houses on large lots, with wrap-around porches and interiors boasting carved woodwork and patterned floors. Tickets, $20, at Temple Beth Emeth, 83 Marlborough Road (near Church Avenue). Advance tickets, $15, and information: (718) 859-3800 and fdconline.org.</p>
        <p>PROSPECT HEIGHTS, BROOKLYN OCT. 14 Several residences, including Neo-Romanesque and Renaissance Revival townhouses from the second half of the 19th century, and at least one contemporary home, will be open from noon to 5 p.m. Tickets, $20, at the Forest Floor, 659 Vanderbilt Avenue (Prospect Place). Advance tickets, $15, and information: (718) 707-1277 and phndc.org.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
        <p>SEA CLIFF, MAY 20 A Sears kit house overlooking Hempstead Harbor is one of seven properties open from noon to 4 p.m. There will also be an 1880 Italianate house decorated with the owners' collections of cranberry glass, bird prints and green Fire King glass objects. Tickets are $25. Advance purchase is suggested by May 13, by check with a self-addressed, self-stamped envelope, to Sea Cliff Landmarks Association, 19 Locust Place, Sea Cliff, N.Y. 11579. Tickets, if available on the day of the tour, at the village green at Sea Cliff and Central Avenues; (888) 216-6779. There is no Web site.</p>
        <p>LAUREL HOLLOW, COLD SPRING HARBOR, HUNTINGTON BAY AND CENTERPORT, MAY 23 A 1916 40-room mansion, with 14 fireplaces, ornate moldings and black walnut paneling in the living room, will be the centerpiece of a tour of five houses, from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Tickets, to benefit the Family Service League of Long Island, $55, at the Thatched Cottage, 445 East Main Street (near Washington Avenue) in Centerport. Lunch, by reservation, is available for $25. Advance tickets, $50, and information: (631) 427-3700, extension 255 and fsl-li.org.</p>
        <p>SOUTHAMPTON, JUNE 9 AND 10 The theme of this year's symposium and tour is photography and the garden. The symposium, on June 9, from 8:30 a.m. to 1 p.m., will be held at the Parrish Art Museum, 25 Job's Lane (Main Street). Five gardens on the East End, including one at the site of an 1850s hay barn that features dense perennial beds, native species and a wildflower field, will be open for a tour on June 10 from 10 a.m. to 3 p.m. Tickets: $175, $125 for members; (631) 283-2118, and parrishart.org.</p>
        <p>BRIDGEHAMPTON, JULY 22 THROUGH SEPT. 3 There will be a show house to benefit Southampton Hospital. Open daily, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. No children under six. Tickets, $30. A preview party will take place on July 21 at 6 p.m. Tickets are $250. More information, closer to the event, at (631) 745-0004 or hamptondesignershowhouse.com.</p>
        <p>Westchester and Putnam Counties</p>
        <p>GARRISON AND COLD SPRING, JUNE 3 Eight houses will be open from 11:30 a.m. to 5 p.m., including a house designed by Russel Wright's companion, Joe Chapman, which has stunning Hudson River views. Tickets, including a box lunch, in advance only: $125; (845)424-3812 and russelwrightcenter.org.</p>
        <p>PLEASANTVILLE, JUNE 4 The tour offered by the Neuberger Museum of Art will focus on the Usonia community, a 100-acre development designed by Frank Lloyd Wright for middle-class families. The day will start with a lecture and light breakfast at 8:30 a.m. at the museum, which is on the campus of Purchase College, part of the State University of New York, 735 Anderson Hill Road, in Purchase. It will be followed by a guided tour of five houses in Usonia, including the three wholly designed by Wright. No children under 16. Tickets, in advance only, are $120 ($100 for museum members): (914) 251-6114 and neuberger.org.</p>
        <p>Dutchess County</p>
        <p>FISHKILL, JUNE 9 Six houses and churches rich with Revolutionary War history will be open for the Silver Ribbon Tour, from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tickets: $35, at 401 Route 52 (south of Interstate 84). Advance tickets: $35 ($30 for members of the Dutchess County Historical Society); (845) 471-1630 and dutchesscountyhistoricalsociety.org.</p>
        <p>Orange County</p>
        <p>GOSHEN, JUNE 16 Six private gardens will be open from 10 a.m. to 3 p.m., including one with bird feeders, birdhouses, and plants that attract birds; a small walled garden; and the property of an 1853 mansion designed by Calvert Vaux, which still has some of its original plantings and where the owners will host a sculpture exhibition. Tickets, $35, will include lunch, a music performance and a display by the Mid-Hudson Orchid Society. Information: (845) 294-6225, or Orange County Tourism, at (845) 291-2136. There is no Web site.</p>
        <p>MONTGOMERY, DEC. 9 At least eight houses will be open in the historic area of Montgomery, which was settled in the early 18th century, from 1 to 5 p.m. A shuttle bus will be offered in case of bad weather. Tickets, in advance, $10; day of tour, $12. Inquires for ticket purchase by e-mail only, after Oct. 1, to jbucksmith@pioneeris.net.</p>
        <p>New Jersey</p>
        <p>RUMSON, THROUGH MAY 31 Scothigh Farm, a Colonial Revival house built in 1926 as a summer estate, will be the site of a show house to benefit the Visiting Nurse Association of Central Jersey. No children under 12. Open Tuesday through Sunday, from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., at 142 Bingham Avenue (near Rumson Road). Admission: $35; $20 for 65 and older. Advance tickets: $25 before May 1; (732) 224-6791 and statelyhomesbythesea.com.</p>
        <p>BOONTON, MAY 12 The Boonton Historical Society and Museum will sponsor a tour of 10 sites from 11:30 a.m. to 4 p.m. The tour will include an 1898 house with original pocket doors, fireplaces, plaster moldings and stair railings, along with new porch, kitchen cabinetry and remodeled top-floor bathroom, and St. John's Episcopal Church, an 1863 structure with three stained glass windows by Louis Comfort Tiffany. Tickets, $25, at the museum, 210 Main Street (Route 202). Information: (973) 316-0976 or by e-mail to boontonhistory@yahoo.com. There is no Web site.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR AND UPPER MONTCLAIR, JUNE 1 AND 2 Seven private gardens will be open from 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. for the Roses to Rock Gardens tour sponsored by Van Vleck House and Gardens, which will also be on the tour. The private gardens include one with an eclectic mix of perennial beds, roses and hydrangeas, set around a meditation hut; another with a collection of 40 varieties of David Austin roses, which have been developed in England in the last 15 years; and a secluded garden with a path made from black Mexican stone leading past flower beds to a fountain and wall covered with a cascade of cotoneaster.</p>
        <p>The event will begin with a coffee reception and lecture on June 1 at 9:30 a.m. at Van Vleck, 21 Van Vleck Street (North Mountain Avenue), Montclair. Reservations are required for the lecture. Tickets, $40 (members, $35). A box lunch will be available on a first-come first-served basis, for $10. Information: (973) 744-4752 and vanvleck.org.</p>
        <p>HOBOKEN, JUNE 3 Eight gardens will be included on a guided tour leaving from the Hoboken Historical Museum every half hour between 9 a.m. and 4 p.m., from shade-tolerant to sun-hungry gardens, from yards covered in waves of ground cover to one with a precise checkerboard pattern. The rain date is June 10. Tickets, $25, to benefit the museum, at 1301 Hudson Street (13th Street). Advance ticket purchase, $20, is recommended: (201) 656-2240, extension 6 and hobokensecretgardens.com.</p>
        <p>LITTLE SILVER, RUMSON AND LOCUST, JUNE 8 THROUGH 10 The 13th annual Two Rivers Antiques Show and Garden Tour is centered around a tour of six private gardens, which will be open on June 9, from 9 a.m. to 4 p.m., and on June 10, from 11:30 a.m. to 3:30 p.m. They include a Japanese-style garden with a pond and seven waterfalls; a butterfly garden at the edge of Hartshorne Woods, a large public park; and a formal garden on the banks of the Shrewsbury River, which, along with the Navesink, is one of the two rivers that give the event its name.</p>
        <p>The antiques show will open with a preview party at the Red Bank Armory Ice Complex, 76 Chestnut Street (Maple Street) in Red Bank, on June 8, at 6:30 p.m. It will also be open June 9, from 10 a.m. to 6 p.m., and June 10, from 11:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Proceeds from the tour and antiques show will benefit the Jacqueline M. Wilentz Comprehensive Breast Center at Monmouth Medical Center.</p>
        <p>Admission to the tour and show is $35; tickets to the preview party are $175; admission to the antiques show only is $10. Advance tickets, $30 ($150, preview party), and information: (732) 923-6886 and tworivershow.org.</p>
        <p>EDGEWATER, JUNE 10 Ten houses, including the 1906 Victorian-style house of Eide Hinners, the first mayor of Edgewater, which has its original interior woodwork and lighting fixtures, will be open from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. The tour will also include Tapestry Looms and Gardens, a former factory which has been converted into four houses, as well as several gardens and the town's Revolutionary War cemetery. The two town churches, one a Romanesque Revival and the other a Gothic Revival, both of which are celebrating their centennials, will also be open to visitors. Tickets, $15, at Veterans Field Park, River Road about 2 miles south of the George Washington Bridge. Tickets in advance, $15, and information: (201) 313-9977 and betteredgewater.com.</p>
        <p>CAPE MAY, JUNE 30 THROUGH OCT. 14 The Memucan Hughes House, an 1847 sea captain's manor house with 11 bedrooms, formal parlors, a library and wrap-around porches, will be the site of a show house by 25 designers. The grounds include a restored carriage house and several garden spaces. Open daily, at 608 Hughes Street (two blocks north of Beach Avenue), from 10 a.m. to 3 p.m., and Monday through Friday, 7 to 9 p.m. Admission is $20. Information: (609) 884-5404 and capemaymac.org.</p>
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY, SEPT. 28 THROUGH NOV. 4 A show house in Bergen County, open from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. daily, will benefit the Hackensack University Medical Center. Admission, $30. More information, closer to the event, at designershowhousenj.com.</p>
        <p>Pennsylvania</p>
        <p>LAHASKA, THROUGH MAY 27 Foxbriar Farm, a fieldstone house, will be the site of the Bucks County Designer Show House, to benefit Doylestown Hospital and the Village Improvement Association of Doylestown. Foxbriar is on Upper York Road (Route 263), between Route 202 and Street Road. Open Monday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. (Wednesday through Friday until 8 p.m.); Sunday, noon to 6 p.m. No children under 10. Admission: $25; $20 for 62 and older. Information: (215)345-2191 and buckscountydesignerhouse.org.</p>
        <p>MT. GRETNA, AUG. 4 Eight to ten houses will be open from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. in the lakeside community, the site of the Mt. Gretna camp meeting, a revival center for the Methodist Church founded in 1892, and later the site of summer cottages and homes built in the early 1900's. Proceeds will benefit Gretna Music, a classical and jazz music festival. Tickets, $15, in front of the Mt. Gretna Post Office, Princeton Avenue and Chautauqua Drive (Route 117). Advance tickets, $12, and information: (717) 361-1508 and mtgretna.com/music.</p>
        <p>Maryland</p>
        <p>TIMONIUM, THROUGH MAY 20 A four-story 1920 Georgian house will be the site of a show house to benefit the Baltimore Symphony Orchestra. More than 25 areas will be furnished, including a dining room featuring blue-and-white Canton China dinnerware; a library with mahogany paneled walls and a trompe l'oeil ceiling; an office decorated with French, Italian and Portuguese antiques; and a polka-dotted nursery. The show house, at 2525 Pot Spring Road (near Dulaney Valley Road), will be open Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. (Thursdays until 8 p.m.), and Sunday, noon to 4 p.m. Timonium is north of Baltimore. Tickets, $20. Tickets purchased offsite and before arrival at the show house, $15, and information: (410) 783-8000 and baltimoresymphony.org.</p>
        <p>PRINCE GEORGE'S COUNTY, MAY 5, AND FOUR OTHER COUNTIES THROUGH MAY 19 The next event in the Maryland House and Garden Pilgrimage, a series of daylong tours held during several weekends in April and May, will be on May 5, with nine sites in Prince George's County. They include a small 1850's house on the Patuxent River, which is decorated with the owners' collection of antiques and paintings; and a two-story gable-roof frame house built in 1790 and enlarged in 1840, furnished with antiques and contemporary furniture and art, and surrounded by oak, chestnut and sycamore trees.</p>
        <p>The Pilgrimage continues in Baltimore County on May 12; Somerset and Worcester counties on May 13; and the southern part of Anne Arundel County on May 19.</p>
        <p>The hours each day of the pilgrimage will be 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission for each day of the tour, $25, at any of the sites and pilgrimage headquarters, 1105-A Providence Road, behind the Maryland Presbyterian Church in Towson. A list of the tour sites can be found online. Information: (410) 821-6933 and mhgp.org.</p>
        <p>Connecticut</p>
        <p>GREENWICH, MAY 11 THROUGH JUNE 17 A 1929 French-style manor house will be the site of a show house by 20 designers, at 200 Stanwich Road (near Rustic View Road). The show house will be open daily, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Tickets, $30, to benefit the Integrative Medical Program at Greenwich Hospital. There will be a preview party on May 10 at 6 p.m. Tickets, $250. Information: (203) 869-6809 and greenwichdesignershowhouse.com.</p>
        <p>GUILFORD, JUNE 9 Eight private gardens will be on the Secret Gardens of Guilford tour, including an English-style garden on the property of an 18th-century saltbox house on the village green, which is planted with antique roses and English perennials. There is a site on the banks of the West River overlooking the salt marsh, down a driveway lined with pear and sugar maple trees, which is planted with climbing roses, daphne, daffodil patches, grasses, inkberry holly, hostas, Russian sage, lavender, hybrid roses and day lilies. The gardens will be open from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Tickets, to benefit Guilford ABC, a social services organization, $20, on the village green at Whitfield and Broad Streets. Tickets in advance, $15, and information: (203) 458-6516 and guilfordabc.org.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts</p>
        <p>BOSTON, MAY 17 Eleven gardens will be open from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. for the Hidden Gardens of Beacon Hill tour. They include a double garden, created in 1928, that was on the first tour, in 1929: the original pool, pergola and fountain remain. Advance ticket purchase, $25, is suggested. Information: (617) 227-4392 and beaconhillgardenclub.org.</p>
        <p>NEWTON, MAY 20 The 25th annual house tour, to benefit the Newton Historical Society, will take place from noon to 5 p.m. There will be seven private houses on the tour, which will take place in several Newton neighborhoods, as well as a 1905 Gothic Revival church, and the Durant-Kenrick House, a Revolutionary War-era house built in 1732. Tickets, $35 (members, $25) at the Newton History Museum, 527 Washington Street (Jackson Street). Advance tickets, $30 (members, $20), and information: (617) 796-1450 and newtonhistorymuseum.org.</p>
        <p>BOSTON, JUNE 16 Twenty private and community gardens, from patio spaces to rooftop gardens, will be open from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. for the 14th annual South End Garden Tour. Proceeds from the tour benefit the South End/Lower Roxbury Open Space Land Trust, which owns and maintains 16 community gardens in Boston. Tickets, $20, at the Boston Center for the Arts, 539 Tremont Street (Clarendon Street). Advance tickets, $17, and information: (617) 437-0999. There is no Web site.</p>
        <p>RICHMOND, MASS., AND NEW CANAAN, N.Y., JULY 7 Several sites will be open from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., including one with a homemade grape arbor, exotic chickens and a vegetable garden with beehives; and a six-acre estate with rock, woodland, water, container and lavender gardens. Tickets, $35, at Richmond School, Route 41, Richmond. A box lunch will be available by advance reservation for $18. Advance tickets, $30, and information: (413) 298-3089. There is no Web site.</p>
        <p>Rhode Island</p>
        <p>PROVIDENCE, JUNE 1 AND 2 Ten houses from the 18th and 19th centuries along George, Manning and Cooke Streets on the city's East Side will be open for a tour on June 2, from 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., to benefit the Providence Preservation Society. There will also be a reception and tour on June 1, from 6 to 9 p.m. Tickets for June 1, in advance only, are $150. Tickets for June 2, $35 (members, $30), at the Brown University Orwig Music Building, 1 Young Orchard Avenue (Hope Street). Advance tickets, $30 (members, $25), and information: (401) 831-7440 and ppsri.org.</p>
        <p>NEWPORT, JUNE 15 THROUGH 17 The annual Secret Garden Tour, of 8 to 10 gardens, will take place in the Historic Point neighborhood. The tour hours will be June 15, noon to 5 p.m., and June 16 and 17, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tickets, good for all three days, $25, at 33 Washington Street (near Bridge Street). Advance tickets, $20, and information: (401) 847-0514 and secretgardentours.org.</p>
        <p>Here is a sampling of tours and show houses beyond the Northeast.</p>
        <p>South</p>
        <p>ATLANTA, THROUGH MAY 20 Whitehall, a 1989 Greek Revival-style house on five acres with formal gardens, will be the site of a show house by 29 designers to benefit the Atlanta Symphony Orchestra's education program.The house will be open Monday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m.; Thursday, 6 to 8 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. Admission is $25. A shuttle service will be provided from the I.B.M. building at 4111 Northside Parkway (Mount Paran Road) to the house, which is at 4795 Harris Trail. Information: (404) 733-4935 and decoratorsshowhouse.org.</p>
        <p>HILLSBOROUGH, N.C., MAY 19 AND 20 Eight private and public gardens will be open, including one inspired by Colonial kitchen gardens with plants historically used for culinary and medicinal purposes and an English-style garden planted with perennial borders, heritage roses and a kitchen garden. Tour hours are May 19, from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., and May 20, from 1 to 5 p.m. Tickets, to benefit the Alliance for Historic Hillsborough, $20, at the Orange County Visitors Center, 150 East King Street (South Churton Street). Children age 12 and younger, free. Advance tickets, $15, and information: (919) 732-7741 or (877) 732-7748 and historichillsborough.org.</p>
        <p>Central</p>
        <p>INDIANAPOLIS, THROUGH MAY 13 The 46th annual Decorators' Show House and Garden Walk, sponsored by St. Margaret's Hospital Guild, will take place at a three-story 1914 house built in the Arts and Crafts style, and remade as a Tudor in the late 1920's. The house has an indoor pool, an outdoor pool and a greenhouse. Open Tuesday through Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. The show house is at 4201 North Washington Boulevard (East 40th Street) in the Mapleton neighborhood. Tickets, $20 at the door; those 65 and older, $17; children ages 2 to 12, $5. Information: (317) 767-0390 and showhouseindy.com.</p>
        <p>LAKE FOREST, ILL., THROUGH MAY 20 A 1925 French-style country manor designed by Edwin Hill Clark, a Chicago architect, will be the site of a show house to benefit the Infant Welfare Society of Chicago. The propery also has a coach house, a guest house and a pool on 3.5 acres. Open Monday through Friday, 9:30 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Saturday and Sunday, 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. No children under 8 years old. Shuttle service will be provided from a parking lot at Barat College, 700 East Westleigh Road (Sheridan Road). Tickets, $30. Information on the Web only: lakeforestshowhouse.com.</p>
        <p>KANSAS CITY, MO., THROUGH MAY 20 A Tudor-style three-story brick and stucco house built in 1917 will be the site of a show house to benefit the Kansas City Symphony. Open Tuesday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. (Thursday until 8 p.m.); Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. No children under 8 years old. Tickets, $15. The house is located at 829 West 55th Street, just east of State Line Road. Information: (816) 968-9711 and showhouse.org.</p>
        <p>West</p>
        <p>NAPA VALLEY, MAY 19 Six houses in the Napa Valley will be open from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. in the eighth annual tour to benefit the Napa Valley Symphony. Tickets, $55, at the information booth at Vintage 1870, 6525 Washington Street in Yountville. Advance tickets, $50, and information from the Napa Valley Symphony League: (707) 255-2700 and napavalleysymphony.org.</p>
        <p>MARIN AND SONOMA COUNTIES, MAY 20 A Build It Green house tour, of new houses and remodeled homes, will be open from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. The 15 homes will highlight such environmentally friendly practices as solar electrical systems; natural flooring materials like cork and bamboo; salvaged woods; and super-insulated materials. Tickets, $15, at a green building fair at Goodman Building Supply, 775 Redwood Highway (Route 101), south of Route 131 in Mill Valley. Advance tickets and information: (510) 845-0472 and builditgreen.org.</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES, JUNE 3 Four houses in the Palisades section of the city will be included on the American Institute of Architects annual house tour, from 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Tickets, $75 ($65, A.I.A. members), at (213) 639-0777 and aialosangeles.org. Tickets will be mailed one week prior to the tour.</p>
        <p>On May 30, from 6:30 to 8 p.m. there will be a free forum with the architects whose houses are featured on the tour, at Toto, 606 North Almont Drive in West Hollywood. Reservations are required by May 23.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
