<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Bank Woos Those Who Trust Only Cash</title>
    <meta content="26branch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/nyregion/26branch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Queensbridge Houses (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island City (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amalgamated Bank of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Ellen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gioia, Eric (Councilman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Queens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Bank Woos Those Who Trust Only Cash</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Bank Courts in Queens Neighborhood Where Many Have Long Trusted Only in Cash</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELLEN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Ellen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amalgamated bank opens branch in Long Island City for residents of Queensbridge Houses, public housing project that is home to 15,000 people, many of whom have never used a bank; will offer courses on banking to fifth graders and hold seminars on home ownership and credit repairs for adults; effort to open bank branch was led by Councilman Eric Gioia (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By yesterday's opening, the building on 21st Street in Long Island City, Queens -- once home to a Kentucky Fried Chicken outlet -- seemed distinctly banklike. Four tellers waited at their stations, deposit slips were lined up in neat stacks, and easy-listening music was playing over the sound system. The only thing missing was customers.</p>
        <p>They filtered in to the Amalgamated Bank branch slowly, like explorers. Jacqueline Williams, 48, has never had a bank account; she keeps her money in a tight roll inside a hollowed-out prayerbook. Sylvia Williams, 50, has never had one either: for 27 years, she has taken her paycheck to the same check-cashing business. ''I'll break it to him easy,'' she said, beaming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Amalgamated Bank branch opened Wednesday in Long Island City, part of an effort to wean many residents off an all-cash economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By yesterday's opening, the building on 21st Street in Long Island City, Queens -- once home to a Kentucky Fried Chicken outlet -- seemed distinctly banklike. Four tellers waited at their stations, deposit slips were lined up in neat stacks, and easy-listening music was playing over the sound system. The only thing missing was customers.</p>
        <p>They filtered in to the Amalgamated Bank branch slowly, like explorers. Jacqueline Williams, 48, has never had a bank account; she keeps her money in a tight roll inside a hollowed-out prayerbook. Sylvia Williams, 50, has never had one either: for 27 years, she has taken her paycheck to the same check-cashing business. ''I'll break it to him easy,'' she said, beaming.</p>
        <p>She said she could not wait to tell her relatives who already use A.T.M. cards that she would soon be opening an account and joining their ranks. ''Now I'm going to have the plastic, too,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A year and a half ago, when Councilman Eric Gioia and the East River Development Alliance, a group that represents public housing residents, commissioned a survey of people living in the Queensbridge Houses, a public housing project that is home to 15,000 people, they found that more than a third had never used a bank account.</p>
        <p>They began a campaign to bring a bank to Queensbridge residents, who they said live more than a mile from the nearest bank. The effort culminated quietly, on Wednesday, with the opening of the Amalgamated branch, near 36th Avenue.</p>
        <p>Josh Andre, the soft-spoken branch manager, is a veteran of ''underbanked'' neighborhoods -- he has headed branches in Harlem and Jamaica -- and he did not expect to be mobbed the first day. People who have never used banks are fearful: fearful that the bank will disappear overnight, or freeze their assets, or be robbed. Some just do not trust banks. Mr. Andre's plan is to begin walking the neighborhood's streets and explaining himself.</p>
        <p>''I just want to create the feeling: This is what banks are for,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gioia, who represents Long Island City and the surrounding neighborhoods, has long worried about his constituents' financial health; at one point, after some of his constituents received checks for the Earned Income Tax Credit, he realized that many of them were planning to store the whole sum -- thousands of dollars in some cases -- in cash.</p>
        <p>People who live in an all cash-economy can damage their credit profiles, foreclosing opportunities to buy homes, he said, so a bank account ''can literally change the trajectory of a family's life.''</p>
        <p>In January 2006, Mr. Gioia and the Rev. Mitchell Taylor, of the East River Development Alliance, led a march of several hundred residents through the neighborhood, chanting: ''We don't need a liquor store! We don't need a check casher! We need a bank!''</p>
        <p>Amalgamated offered to open a branch there last June, and the state designated the area a Banking Development District, offering banks that moved there tax incentives, employee training and public-funds deposits.</p>
        <p>Derrick D. Cephas, Amalgamated's president and chief executive, said he expected it to turn a profit within a year.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's a gamble that we don't understand,'' he said. ''This is what we should be doing.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Mr. Gioia and other community leaders will act ''almost like a dating service,'' he said, offering courses on banking to fifth graders and holding seminars on homeownership and credit repair for adults. The effort was aided, he said, by the delayed mail delivery of 1,800 Social Security checks to people in Queensbridge Houses last month. When Social Security recipients realize that direct deposit of their checks is more reliable, he said, it will nudge them further toward having bank accounts.</p>
        <p>''If this works the way I think it will, I think we have a model here,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Jacqueline Williams, an analyst for a telephone company, said that having a bank account would relieve the panic she feels when she forgets where she stashed her money and the exasperation of hearing another lecture from her boyfriend, who will not let her forget the ''thousands and thousands of dollars'' in fees she has paid to check-cashing businesses.</p>
        <p>Walking out of the bank yesterday afternoon -- she was the only customer at the time -- she said an employee there had been more than encouraging.</p>
        <p>''He was all in there: 'Can I help you do this? Can I help you do that?' '' she said, with a look of mild alarm. She said she had gone in to find out about an account for her son, Tyquan, who is 10, and has saved $130, and expects to open accounts for each of them soon.</p>
        <p>''He's thrilled about the interest'' he will earn, she said. ''He doesn't believe they're going to give him this money for nothing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
