<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rainout Won't Push Hughes Back a Day</title>
    <meta content="26pins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/26/sports/baseball/26pins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1843038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hughes, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5DC153EF935A15757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rainout Won't Push Hughes Back a Day</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">All Eyes on Yankees’ Pitching Prospect</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although the Yankees' game against Toronto last night was rained out, the postponement will not delay the major league debut of the right-hander Phil Hughes, who is considered one of the top pitching prospects in baseball.</p>
        <p>Hughes, 20, will pitch tonight, as previously scheduled, against the Blue Jays at Yankee Stadium, Manager Joe Torre said last night. The most inconvenienced player will be Andy Pettitte, the veteran left-hander, who has been the steadiest Yankees starter during the recent upheaval of the staff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phil Hughes, considered one of the top pitching prospects in baseball, will take the mound tonight against the Blue Jays at Yankee Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although the Yankees' game against Toronto last night was rained out, the postponement will not delay the major league debut of the right-hander Phil Hughes, who is considered one of the top pitching prospects in baseball.</p>
        <p>Hughes, 20, will pitch tonight, as previously scheduled, against the Blue Jays at Yankee Stadium, Manager Joe Torre said last night. The most inconvenienced player will be Andy Pettitte, the veteran left-hander, who has been the steadiest Yankees starter during the recent upheaval of the staff.</p>
        <p>Pettitte, who was to start last night, will instead pitch tomorrow, when the Yankees are scheduled to open a three-game series at home against the Boston Red Sox. The Yankees (8-11) have lost their past five games, including three at Boston last weekend, and they are in last place in the American League East.</p>
        <p>Torre said he was concerned about making Hughes wait another two days and putting him into what he called ''a circus-like atmosphere'' against a bitter rival.</p>
        <p>''If I had my druthers, I'd probably like to stay away from that,'' Torre said even before the postponement was announced.</p>
        <p>In a news conference, Hughes said it was ''definitely exciting'' to be in New York. ''I'm more anxious than anything,'' Hughes said. ''I've been thinking about it for a couple days.</p>
        <p>''I feel like I've been ready to do this. I just can't wait.''</p>
        <p>Hughes's last appearance was April 18, when he struck out 10 in six innings for Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre in a 4-0 victory against Syracuse. He was 2-1 there with a 3.94 earned run average. Hughes, who was selected in the first round of the 2004 draft, went 10-3 at Class AA Trenton last season and 2-3 at Class A Tampa.</p>
        <p>Torre had said as recently as last week that the Yankees did not want to rush Hughes to the major leagues and that he would probably not be called up until late in the season. But that was before Chase Wright and Jeff Karstens, also rookies, had difficulty at Boston.</p>
        <p>Pettitte, who pitched one inning last Sunday in relief at Boston and six and a third innings last Friday as a starter, said he was content with Torre's decision. But he said that he was ready to pitch yesterday or today and that he did not see the extra two days of rest as a blessing in disguise.</p>
        <p>''That's fine,'' Pettitte said of Torre's decision. ''I feel great. I would have loved to have pitched. They just asked me if I'd throw Friday, and I said, 'I'll pitch whenever you want me to pitch.' '' Pettitte is 1-0 with an earned run average of 1.78 in 251/3 innings.</p>
        <p>Brian Cashman, the Yankees' general manager, said no date had been set for the postponed game, although it would probably be played when the Blue Jays return to Yankee Stadium for a four-game series from July 16-19.</p>
        <p>Since the teams are scheduled to play four games in four days, it is very likely that the extra game would be added as part of a day-night doubleheader on one of those dates.</p>
        <p>The addition of Hughes is the latest development in the Yankees' starting rotation, which has had several players injured, including Karstens, Mike Mussina, Carl Pavano and Chien-Ming Wang.</p>
        <p>Karstens and Wang have since returned. Mussina, with a hamstring injury, is expected to make a minor league rehabilitation start tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Pavano, 1-0 in two starts this season, threw from flat ground yesterday and reported improvement but lingering discomfort in his sore arm.</p>
        <p>He is expected to throw again on flat ground today. If he shows further improvement, Torre said, the Yankees would consider a rehabilitation assignment in the minors.</p>
        <p>Kei Igawa, another rookie, lost Monday night at Tampa Bay. Either Karstens or Igawa will pitch Saturday against the Red Sox. Sunday's starter will be Wang, who was charged with Tuesday's 6-4 defeat to Tampa Bay after giving up four runs in six and a third innings.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>To make room on the roster for Phil Hughes, the Yankees sent the right-hander Colter Bean to Class AAA Scranton/Wilkes-Barre.  Yankees shortstop Derek Jeter, who left Tuesday's game at Tampa Bay after he was hit on the left thigh by a pitch, was in the starting lineup for last night's game with Toronto before it was postponed. Manager Joe Torre said Jeter was taking treatment and might have been replaced had the game been played on wet ground. Jeter was not available for comment.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
