<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Housing Authority Is Facing $225 Million Deficit in '07</title>
    <meta content="11housing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/nyregion/11housing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Housing Authority</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EFD6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Housing Authority Is Facing $225 Million Deficit in '07</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Housing Authority Is Facing $225 Million Deficit in ’07</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANNY SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, Janny</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One year after announcing plans to raise rents, cut costs and appeal to federal and state officials for help in closing a $168 million budget gap, the New York City Housing Authority is facing an even bigger budget shortfall.</p>
        <p>The agency, which serves as landlord to more than 400,000 low-income New Yorkers and is the largest public housing authority in the country, is confronting a $225 million deficit in its operating budget for the 2007 calendar year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Housing Authority is facing an even bigger budget shortfall one year after announcing plans to save money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One year after announcing plans to raise rents, cut costs and appeal to federal and state officials for help in closing a $168 million budget gap, the New York City Housing Authority is facing an even bigger budget shortfall.</p>
        <p>The agency, which serves as landlord to more than 400,000 low-income New Yorkers and is the largest public housing authority in the country, is confronting a $225 million deficit in its operating budget for the 2007 calendar year.</p>
        <p>Authority officials blame a continuing rise in expenses like pensions over which they have no control, a widening gap between operating costs and federal subsidies, and their inability to get federal permission to cover day-to-day expenses with money usually intended for other purposes.</p>
        <p>The authority has asked to be allowed to use 8,400 vouchers from another rent subsidy program known as Section 8 to operate authority units built -- but no longer subsidized -- by the city and state. The authority also wants to use federal money earmarked for capital improvements to cover operating expenses if necessary.</p>
        <p>So far, neither request has been granted, and officials do not seem optimistic.</p>
        <p>Agnes Rivera, a longtime resident of the Wagner Houses in East Harlem, said she feared that the widening budget shortfall, first reported yesterday in The Daily News, would force the authority to sell the 21 developments that the state and the city built but stopped subsidizing on an annual basis in the late 1990s.</p>
        <p>''For me, they're trying to do the best they can with nothing,'' Ms. Rivera said of the authority. She added, ''We're not all bad that live here in N.Y.C.H.A. I'm not sure how the city, state and federal government are seeing us. Are they seeing us as humans?''</p>
        <p>Douglas Apple, general manager of the authority, said in a statement yesterday: ''Our goal is to preserve public housing and not lose one unit. We intend to achieve that goal through ongoing legislative and financial efforts combined with internal cost-saving steps.''</p>
        <p>The authority, which operates 344 developments with more than 179,000 apartments, has an annual budget of $2.8 billion. Last year, authority officials said they hoped to raise $38 million from rent increases, and to get $23 million in Section 8 money and $78 million by using other federal funds to cover operating expenses.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Apple said the authority was unable to get federal permission to use that $78 million. In addition, it received only 83 percent of the federal subsidy officials say the authority needed. And extensive public hearings delayed implementation of the rent increases, reducing the amount of increased rent revenue that was expected.</p>
        <p>The authority is now hoping to make up its shortfall from other sources. In February, Senator Charles E. Schumer and Representative Nydia M. Velásquez introduced legislation to ''federalize'' the orphaned state and city developments -- a move they say could produce an additional $100 million annually in federal operating money.</p>
        <p>''This is their salvation, and not on a one-year basis but on a permanent basis,'' Senator Schumer said yesterday, predicting that the bills had a good chance of passing this summer.</p>
        <p>In Albany, state legislators have introduced bills that would raise the so-called shelter allowance for the 27,000 public housing families on full or partial public assistance. Mr. Apple said the authority received less than $200 a month for each family while private landlords received $400; the authority is asking the Legislature for parity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Apple said the authority was also cutting costs through partial hiring freezes, shrinking the staff through attrition, reducing overtime for cleaning crews on weekends, and cutting back on purchases of supplies and vehicles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
