<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Algerian Temptations, Speaking a Little French</title>
    <meta content="11unde" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/dining/reviews/11unde.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">East Village (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Algeria</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7D7153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Algerian Temptations, Speaking a Little French</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Algerian Temptations, Speaking a Little French</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Meehan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meehan, Peter</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I LIKE cookies. You probably like cookies. Cookies are likable.</p>
        <p>But cravable, eye-opening cookies are not an everyday thing. Maybe that's why, thinking back on my meals at Nomad, a new French-North African restaurant on Second Avenue in the East Village, I'm thinking first about the things I ate last: cookies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At Nomad in the East Village, you’ll find aggressively and expertly spiced Algerian sausages and cravable, eye-opening pastries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I LIKE cookies. You probably like cookies. Cookies are likable.</p>
        <p>But cravable, eye-opening cookies are not an everyday thing. Maybe that's why, thinking back on my meals at Nomad, a new French-North African restaurant on Second Avenue in the East Village, I'm thinking first about the things I ate last: cookies.</p>
        <p>A plate of four cookies and minipastries is $8 and, should you go to Nomad, please consider it required eating. Will the little diamond of rosewater-spiked baklawa (not so different from baklava) be your favorite? Or will it be the cherek, a crescent of house-made puff pastry cradling a sugary almond filling? Chocoholics, such a predictable bunch, will fall hard for the bniin, a nut-sprinkled nugget of hazelnuts, walnuts, biscotti, halvah and chocolate ganache.</p>
        <p>A sweet little cigar-shaped pastry might round out the four-cookie offering; other nights it might be a samsa, a fried triangle of phyllo dough filled with ground nuts and honey. There's no going wrong, whatever the selection.</p>
        <p>Salima Zebentout, wife of Mehenni Zebentout, the restaurateur behind the place, makes the cookies much the way she learned to make them in the kitchen of her grandparents' restaurant in Theniet el Had in the Atlas Mountains of Algeria. And when she's not pitching in at her husband's restaurant, she's studying for her endocrinologist's certification.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Zebentout makes the cookies, and Hisham Khiri makes the sausages. Mr. Khiri, a Casablanca-born chef, stuffs a batch of his own merguez every couple of days. The resulting sausages, incorporated into various dishes or grilled on their own as a $5 ''tapa,'' are plump torpedoes of lamby goodness, aggressively and expertly spiced.</p>
        <p>He also oversees the production of some of the better specimens of labor-intensive savory North African pastries around.</p>
        <p>Boureks, crispy pastries stuffed with a juicy beef and lamb, are done as they would be in Algeria, said Mr. Zebentout, who called himself ''Algerian-Algerian'' when I inquired as to his nationality.</p>
        <p>Briwats are stuffed with ground almonds and pulled chicken, as they would be in Morocco. No matter where they are from, the ones I tried were unimpeachably good.</p>
        <p>Pastillas, entree-size savory pastries, are put together with a deft hand. None I tried evinced even the faintest sogginess; as my fork cut through the decorative crosshatch of cinnamon atop the sugar-dusted pastry, it crackled and shattered and gave way to a layer of buttery, fatty ground almonds and a moist and richly seasoned chicken filling.</p>
        <p>The menu has a few French standbys, including steak frites with a peppercorn sauce ($18), as good as any at other modest local bistros.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khiri trained in Brussels after leaving Morocco before coming to New York, which might be one reason the frites are so good. They fare equally well as a main ingredient in a tajine of chicken, olives and French fries that proves that conscientiously fried potatoes used as a vegetable are a good thing.</p>
        <p>The narrow space that Nomad inhabits is broken into dining rooms and a bar space, and festooned to within an inch of overkill with North African lamps, murals and decorations. Angle for a table in the back room or the little fenced-in garden if it's good weather (and if the peace and quiet isn't yet obliterated by the hum of air conditioners sagging from windowsills). Either would be more comfortable than the tables crammed into the front room.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zebentout said there won't be any belly dancing, so there's no threat that the comfortably tight space will turn uncomfortably intimate. And you won't have to guard your lamb and couscous royal -- a huge helping topped with merguez, lamb, chicken and more ($16) -- against whirling tassels or scarves.</p>
        <p>Nomad  78 Second Avenue (Fourth Street), East Village; (212) 253-5410.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES -- All the savory pastries; cookies; grilled merguez with anything.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers and salads, $5 to $9; main courses, $12 to $18; dessert, $6 to $8.  CREDIT CARDS -- American Express only.  HOURS -- 3 to 11 p.m. Sunday through Thursday; 3 p.m. to midnight Friday and Saturday. Mehenni Zebentout, the proprietor, said he plans to extend the hours to noon to midnight daily at the end of April.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Accessible.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
