<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Subpoenas More U.S. Attorney Files</title>
    <meta content="11attorneys" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070412T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzales, Alberto R (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDF123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Subpoenas More U.S. Attorney Files</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON; Allison Cowan contributed reporting from Stamford, Conn.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>House Democrats subpoena more Justice Dept documents pertaining to personnel matters surrounding dismissals of eight US attorneys; demand for new documents comes as Atty Gen Alberto R Gonzales prepares for his upcoming Senate Judiciary Committee hearing; supporters and critics alike say hearing could determine whether he remains in office (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>House Democrats on Tuesday subpoenaed more documents from the Justice Department, ratcheting up efforts to obtain unedited copies of hundreds of documents pertaining to personnel matters surrounding last year's dismissals of eight United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>The new demand for more documents came as Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales spent nearly five hours working with aides in preparation for his appearance next Tuesday before the Senate Judiciary Committee. Defenders and critics alike say the hearing could determine whether he remains in office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>House Democrats on Tuesday subpoenaed more documents from the Justice Department, ratcheting up efforts to obtain unedited copies of hundreds of documents pertaining to personnel matters surrounding last year's dismissals of eight United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>The new demand for more documents came as Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales spent nearly five hours working with aides in preparation for his appearance next Tuesday before the Senate Judiciary Committee. Defenders and critics alike say the hearing could determine whether he remains in office.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Gonzales announced a significant personnel decision, naming as his new chief of staff Kevin J. O'Connor, the United States attorney in Connecticut. Mr. O'Connor, 39, will at least temporarily hold both jobs. His selection appeared to be an effort by Mr. Gonzales to solidify his standing among prosecutors who have been restive in the aftermath of the dismissals.</p>
        <p>Justice Department officials said the new subpoena issued by the House Judiciary Committee was ''unfortunate'' and sought documents, already the subject of a separate request by the Senate, for information about United States attorneys who are still on the job. Brian Roehrkasse, a department spokesman, said many of the documents, in unedited form, had already been reviewed at the department by Congressional staff members.</p>
        <p>As the public efforts by House Democrats to obtain more documents intensified in advance of Mr. Gonzales's testimony, Congressional investigators also worked behind the scenes, preparing for interviews with other Justice Department officials, including William Mercer, the acting associate attorney general, and Michael A. Battle, formerly the director of the agency's liaison office for United States attorneys. The interviews, to be held Wednesday and Thursday, would not be conducted under oath, but a transcript would be kept, Congressional officials said.</p>
        <p>In a separate development, Senate Democrats asked Mr. Gonzales to turn over documents related to a prosecution of a state contracting official in Wisconsin. In a case involving corruption charges brought by Steven Biskupic, the United States attorney in Milwaukee, the official, Georgia Thompson, was convicted.</p>
        <p>But last week, after an appeals court heard oral arguments, a federal appeals court took the unusual step of ordering Ms. Thompson's immediate release from prison. The senators sought all documents at the Justice Department in connection with the case, which was the subject of intense political advertising last fall against Gov. James E. Doyle, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Connor, the new chief of staff to Mr. Gonzales, grew up in West Hartford, Conn., and graduated from the University of Notre Dame and the University of Connecticut School of Law. After a yearlong clerkship for Judge William H. Timbers of the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit and time in private practice, he worked for the Securities and Exchange Commission from 1995 to 1997.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Connor, who ran unsuccessfully as a Republican candidate for the House in 1998, was confirmed as a United States attorney in 2002. His office has pursued successful investigations against predators of children, corporate polluters and corrupt public officials, including the inquiry that ultimately forced out Gov. John G. Rowland, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Connor recused himself from the Rowland case, citing ties he had to the former governor as well as ties his wife, Kathleen, had stemming from the time she served as a deputy counsel in Mr. Rowland's office, and other reasons.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 12, 2007, Thursday  An article yesterday about Congressional investigations of the Justice Department decision to dismiss eight United States attorneys gave an incorrect job description in some copies for a Wisconsin official who was convicted of corruption charges brought by the United States attorney in Milwaukee. The official, Georgia Thompson, was a purchasing official in the state's Department of Administration, not an aide to Gov. James E. Doyle. (After a federal appeals court heard oral arguments in the case last week, it ordered her immediate release from prison.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 12, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about Congressional investigations of the Justice Department decision to dismiss eight United States attorneys gave an incorrect job description in some copies for a Wisconsin official who was convicted of corruption charges brought by the United States attorney in Milwaukee. The official, Georgia Thompson, was a purchasing official in the state's Department of Administration, not an aide to Gov. James E. Doyle. (After a federal appeals court heard oral arguments in the case last week, it ordered her immediate release from prison.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
