<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. Assesses Lengthy Bans For Misconduct</title>
    <meta content="11nfl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/sports/football/11nfl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839589"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Cincinnati Bengals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tennessee Titans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tennessee Titans</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cincinnati Bengals</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jones, Pacman</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Goodell, Roger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFDE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. Assesses Lengthy Bans For Misconduct</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tougher N.F.L. Suspends Two Players for Conduct</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saying the integrity of the National Football League had to be protected, Commissioner Roger Goodell yesterday suspended Tennessee Titans cornerback Pacman Jones without pay for the 2007 season and Cincinnati Bengals receiver Chris Henry for the first eight games for repeated off-the-field conduct problems.</p>
        <p>Goodell is probably not finished with his crackdown on the N.F.L.'s most notorious offenders. Chicago Bears defensive tackle Tank Johnson sits in an Illinois prison, serving a four-month sentence for a probation violation, with more gun charges pending. When he is released, Johnson will most likely face Goodell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Titans’ Pacman Jones was suspended for the entire 2007 N.F.L. season and the Bengals’ Chris Henry was suspended for the first eight games for violating the leagues personal conduct policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Saying the integrity of the National Football League had to be protected, Commissioner Roger Goodell yesterday suspended Tennessee Titans cornerback Pacman Jones without pay for the 2007 season and Cincinnati Bengals receiver Chris Henry for the first eight games for repeated off-the-field conduct problems.</p>
        <p>Goodell is probably not finished with his crackdown on the N.F.L.'s most notorious offenders. Chicago Bears defensive tackle Tank Johnson sits in an Illinois prison, serving a four-month sentence for a probation violation, with more gun charges pending. When he is released, Johnson will most likely face Goodell.</p>
        <p>''Your conduct has brought embarrassment and ridicule upon yourself, your club and the N.F.L., and has damaged the reputation of players throughout the league,'' Goodell wrote in letters to Jones and Henry. ''You have engaged in conduct detrimental to the N.F.L. and failed to live up to the standards expected of N.F.L. players.''</p>
        <p>Moments after Jones and Henry became the public faces of Goodell's law-and-order campaign, the N.F.L. announced a stricter personal conduct policy. It calls for increased education and support programs for players and gives Goodell sweeping powers to issue lengthy suspensions.</p>
        <p>Goodell told Jones and Henry that if they failed to comply with the conditions of their suspensions, they could face additional penalties, including the possibility of lifetime banishment from the N.F.L. Jones, the sixth overall pick in the 2005 draft, will lose $1.29 million in base salary. Henry could lose as much as $230,000 in base salary.</p>
        <p>''I must emphasize to you that this is your last opportunity to salvage your N.F.L. career,'' Goodell wrote.</p>
        <p>The players could appeal, but Goodell decides appeals, too, and his move toward tough sanctions has enjoyed the public support of many players and Gene Upshaw, the head of the players union.</p>
        <p>Jones's status will be reviewed after the Titans' 10th regular-season game, and there is a possibility that the suspension could be reduced. Jones would have to comply with a lengthy list of provisions of his suspension. And he would have to avoid charges against him in Las Vegas, where the police have recommended he be charged with a felony after labeling him an ''inciter'' of a melee at a strip club during N.B.A. All-Star weekend that resulted in a triple shooting in which one man was paralyzed.</p>
        <p>Jones will probably have to be cleared of a felony obstruction charge in Georgia stemming from an altercation in February 2006, in which he is accused of biting a police officer on the hand. Since he was drafted, Jones has been arrested five times and questioned by the police in 10 episodes.</p>
        <p>Jones's lawyer, Manny Arora, was not available for comment yesterday. Henry's agent, Marvin Frazier, did not return a call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Upshaw said last night that he was not surprised by Jones's yearlong suspension. Upshaw said he had told Jones's advisers to focus on the reviews after the 10th game rather than an appeal as the best hope to get the suspension reduced.</p>
        <p>''He wanted to give him an option and give him something to really fight for, to live for,'' Upshaw said of the commissioner.</p>
        <p>Jones may not participate in practices or organized workouts during the suspension. Beginning in June he must meet once a week with the Titans' player development director, who will also develop a program of community service for Jones. Jones will be allowed to spend one day a week at the team facility for conditioning and film study.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued by the Titans, the owner, Bud Adams, indicated that Jones was not guaranteed his job when his suspension ends. The Titans have signed the former Colts cornerback Nick Harper as Jones's most likely replacement.</p>
        <p>''We will need assurances from the player on a number of issues before we are comfortable having him return to the team,'' Adams said. ''Until we see a change in behavior through his actions and until he shows the ability to avoid controversy off the field, we will move forward with the possibility that he may not return to this team.''</p>
        <p>Henry was arrested four times between December 2005 and June 2006 and has already served a two-game suspension that Goodell issued last season. Henry can participate in training camp and preseason games, and during the regular season can be at team meetings, although he cannot attend or participate in practice. Henry was one of nine Bengals arrested in a nine-month span.</p>
        <p>''We support the commissioner's ruling,'' Bengals Coach Marvin Lewis said in a statement. ''And while we regret the circumstances that called for it, it's good for both Chris and the Bengals to have the matter resolved. Our team will move forward, and now it is up to Chris to acquire a more mature understanding of his responsibilities as a player for the Bengals and a representative of the N.F.L.''</p>
        <p>The N.F.L.'s new personal-conduct policy includes banishment and significant fines for repeat offenders, even before cases have been resolved by the judicial system. A players advisory council will discuss issues with Goodell. The policy also threatens punishment for franchises that repeatedly sign problem players.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
