<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Top Players Help Nets' Bottom Line</title>
    <meta content="11nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/sports/basketball/11nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Washington Wizards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Wizards</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Top Players Help Nets' Bottom Line</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Top Players Help Nets’ Bottom Line</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets are far from cleansing themselves of the bad habits that have caused them to be such an unstable team this season.</p>
        <p>Tuesday night's game against the Wizards was filled with the offensive clumsiness and defensives lapses that have placed the Nets near the bottom of the Eastern Conference playoff race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets finally seem to be getting the best out of their stars, and it is helping them achieve the results they have been seeking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nets are far from cleansing themselves of the bad habits that have caused them to be such an unstable team this season.</p>
        <p>Tuesday night's game against the Wizards was filled with the offensive clumsiness and defensives lapses that have placed the Nets near the bottom of the Eastern Conference playoff race.</p>
        <p>But the Nets seem to be getting the best out of their stars, and the team is finally earning the only result it cares about: victories.</p>
        <p>Powered by a season-high 35 points from small forward Richard Jefferson and 31 points from Vince Carter, the Nets defeated the Wizards, 96-92, at Verizon Center. The Nets (37-40) are only two games behind the Wizards (39-38) for the sixth seed in the East with five games remaining.</p>
        <p>''We're getting close to where we need to be as a team,'' Jefferson said. ''We're starting to close out games, we're starting to come back and finish fourth quarters like we should.''</p>
        <p>Jefferson played perhaps his best game of the season. He almost single-handedly led a 14-4 run early in the second half that helped the Nets build a 10-point lead. In one stretch, the Nets scored on seven consecutive possessions, and Jefferson accounted for five of those baskets.</p>
        <p>Jefferson's two biggest baskets came when the Nets were trailing in the final minute of the game. After Wizards forward Darius Songaila missed a jumper, Jefferson scored a transition layup that pulled the Nets to within a point. On the Wizards' next possession, guard DeShawn Stevenson missed a driving layup, and Jefferson again got out for a fast-break layup, giving the Nets a 90-89 lead with 30 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>The Nets sealed the victory when Stevenson missed another layup on the Wizards' next possession, allowing Carter to get a fast-break dunk.</p>
        <p>With two free throws toward the end of the second half, Carter surpassed the Nets' single-season scoring record (1,911 points), which he set last season.</p>
        <p>Although he scored only 4 points, Nets point guard Jason Kidd controlled the tempo with 14 rebounds and 11 assists. He also forced Stevenson into difficult shots toward the end of the game.</p>
        <p>''They lead our team; they're our difference makers,'' Nets Coach Lawrence Frank said of Kidd, Carter and Jefferson. ''That's what separates us from the teams we play. It's like a Broadway play. You have stars, you have supporting actors. Everyone kind of plays their part. That's how we're made up.''</p>
        <p>Still, the Nets have been so enigmatic this season that it is difficult to make much of a game when their stars turn in big performances.</p>
        <p>Kidd and Carter had triple-doubles in Saturday night's game against the Wizards, but the Nets needed overtime to win. On Tuesday night, the Nets needed all of Jefferson's points, in addition to Carter's firepower, to pull out the victory.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is that your record always tells you who you are,'' Frank said after practice Monday. ''The key is paying the price each and every game. Every team suits up to win the game. So, if you're not willing to do all the little things necessary to win, if you're not willing to outlast the opponent, if you're not willing to have the proper approach, then what happens is any team in this league, they're going to lose.''</p>
        <p>The Nets' commitment to doing things right has often been up for debate. It was lacking late in the third quarter Tuesday when they blew a 10-point lead in three minutes. The Wizards went on a 12-0 run, and the Nets went nearly the final five and a half minutes of the third quarter without a field goal. A 3-pointer by Bostjan Nachbar with 7.8 seconds left in the quarter cut the Wizards' lead to 67-65 entering the fourth.</p>
        <p>The Nets also had six turnovers in the fourth, some at crucial moments. Antonio Daniels stole the ball from Jefferson for a fast break and a 77-72 Wizards lead; Jarvis Hayes later stole the ball from Jefferson for another Daniels fast break; and Nets center Mikki Moore set an illegal screen to help the Wizards maintain a 3-point lead with just over three minutes remaining.</p>
        <p>But the Nets found a way to win, and that is the main thing they will take from this game.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Nets canceled practice Wednesday so that they could visit patients at the Walter Reed Army Medical Center.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
