<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playoff Wish: Beautiful Goals And Creative Play</title>
    <meta content="11nhl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070412T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY: PLAYOFF SHOOTOUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playoff Wish: Beautiful Goals And Creative Play</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF Z. KLEIN and KARL-ERIC REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Jeff Z; Reif, Karl-Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the Stanley Cup playoffs are anything like the just concluded regular season, hockey fans are in for a treat. Despite some persistent problems -- an epidemic of head injuries from legal but malicious checks, a pro-fighting backlash against new rules designed to reduce violence and lagging attendance in several cities -- the hallmark of the 2006-7 season has been an abundance of beautiful, creative goal-scoring.</p>
        <p>Buffalo and Detroit have scored those beautiful goals most often, the main reason they finished first in their conferences and are the favorites to win the Stanley Cup. Many of the Sabres' goals have come from gorgeous clockwork passing on full-tilt rushes to the net, reminiscent of the great Soviet teams of the 1970s. Many of the Red Wings' goals have come from precision combination play in tight spaces, an ingenious game of high-speed tic-tac-toe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the Stanley Cup playoffs are anything like the just concluded regular season, hockey fans are in for a treat. Despite some persistent problems -- an epidemic of head injuries from legal but malicious checks, a pro-fighting backlash against new rules designed to reduce violence and lagging attendance in several cities -- the hallmark of the 2006-7 season has been an abundance of beautiful, creative goal-scoring.</p>
        <p>Buffalo and Detroit have scored those beautiful goals most often, the main reason they finished first in their conferences and are the favorites to win the Stanley Cup. Many of the Sabres' goals have come from gorgeous clockwork passing on full-tilt rushes to the net, reminiscent of the great Soviet teams of the 1970s. Many of the Red Wings' goals have come from precision combination play in tight spaces, an ingenious game of high-speed tic-tac-toe.</p>
        <p>These goals bring fans to their feet and smiles to their faces, even if hockey commentators do not seem to have the vocabulary to describe them, and instead speak in old tropes about mistakes and toughness and physical sacrifice and hard hitting. Those things will still be factors in the playoffs, but this spring, most of all, it will be about beautiful goals.</p>
        <p>Here are a few other things it will be about:</p>
        <p>GOALIES' EXPERIENCE -- The only goalies in the playoffs who have won a Stanley Cup are Martin Brodeur of the Devils, and Dominik Hasek and Chris Osgood of the Red Wings. Among the others, only a couple have been to the Cup final (Miikka Kiprusoff of the Flames and Jean-Sébastien Giguère of the Ducks), and the rest lack a great deal of postseason experience.</p>
        <p>But there are two other goalies who have won important games as professionals in recent years. Niklas Backstrom of the Wild won Finnish championships with Karpat Oulu in 2004 and 2005. And the Rangers' goalie, Henrik Lundqvist, won Swedish titles with Frolunda in 2003 and 2005 and an Olympic gold medal for Sweden in 2006. Backstrom and Lundqvist may well carry their unheralded teams a long way.</p>
        <p>MANDATORY SUFFERING -- It is a fact that teams must suffer in their quest for hockey's Holy Grail, the Stanley Cup.</p>
        <p>And almost every team that wins the Cup must first meet with crushing disappointment at least once, more often several times.</p>
        <p>Eventually, they learn from it and come back stronger. Detroit fell disappointingly short in the early 1990s before finally winning in '96, and has since alternated embarrassing early playoff exits with Cup championships. The Devils' long crawl from the expansion ooze earned them a bitter playoff loss to the Rangers in 1994 that in turn spurred them in '95 to the first of three Cup triumphs.</p>
        <p>But it does not work for every team. Some seem conditioned to failure, despite their strengths. San Jose and Ottawa have struggled upward from their woeful births in the early '90s and they have become perennial forces in the regular season, but both seem doomed once the playoffs roll around. Have the Sharks and Senators suffered enough to win, or have they learned how to lose too well?</p>
        <p>FORCE VERSUS FINESSE -- Yes, checking gets a little closer in the postseason, and the intensity level is ramped up -- but fighting almost disappears. Carolina won the Cup last year after becoming the N.H.L.'s third-highest scoring team and one of its least-penalized teams.</p>
        <p>This season, 8 of the 10 teams that engaged in the most fights failed to qualify for the playoffs. Meanwhile, 8 of the 10 highest-scoring teams are vying for the Cup, but only one of its lowest-scoring teams (the Devils) is in the playoff mix. All this points to a postseason advantage for clubs that tone down the rough stuff and concentrate on creating goals.</p>
        <p>Anaheim's truculent No. 2 Ducks led the league in fights by a whopping margin (71 to 47 for runner-up Phoenix). They meet Jacques Lemaire's disciplined No. 7 Wild in the opening round in the Western Conference. Minnesota engaged in only 14 fights (10 of those Derek Boogaard's), second least in the N.H.L., and gave opponents the fourth-fewest power plays during the season. That series could produce the biggest surprises of the first round.</p>
        <p>YOU WIN AT EVEN STRENGTH -- Emphasis is placed on the power play, but most of the game is played at even strength. How you do when the sides are even is almost always the best gauge of how you do as a team.</p>
        <p>That precept will be put to the test in the opening-round series between two offensive powerhouses, Ottawa, starring Daniel Alfredsson, Jason Spezza and the 50-goal man Dany Heatley, against Sidney Crosby and the young guns of Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>The Senators ranked second in the league both in overall scoring and in scoring at even strength. The Penguins ranked third in overall scoring, but only 15th at even strength.</p>
        <p>The Pens' potent power play is a thing of fearsome beauty. But will it be enough to overcome an apparent disadvantage at full strength?</p>
        <p>A RIDDLE, WRAPPED IN A MYSTERY, INSIDE AN ENIGMA -- The Rangers, Islanders and Devils -- the three teams in the news media capital, where the N.H.L. craves attention most -- are playing separate first-round series for the first time. Why did the league schedule most of the games in each series to be played virtually simultaneously?</p>
        <p>At least one thing remains constant about the playoffs: You will never figure out the N.H.L.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY: PLAYOFF SHOOTOUT</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 12, 2007, Thursday  A report in the Playoff Shootout hockey roundup yesterday, about the disappointments that some N.H.L. teams experience before winning the Stanley Cup, referred incorrectly to the Detroit Red Wings' breakthrough championship. It was in 1997, not 1996. (The Colorado Avalanche won the Cup that year.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 12, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>A report in the Playoff Shootout hockey roundup yesterday, about the disappointments that some N.H.L. teams experience before winning the Stanley Cup, referred incorrectly to the Detroit Red Wings' breakthrough championship. It was in 1997, not 1996. (The Colorado Avalanche won the Cup that year.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
