<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trial Starts in Case of Couple Who Robbed Mob, and Paid for It</title>
    <meta content="11mob" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/nyregion/11mob.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFD6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trial Starts in Case of Couple Who Robbed Mob, and Paid for It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trial Starts in Case of Couple Who Robbed Mob, and Paid for It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brick, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It stands to reason that the Mafia took responsibility for killing Thomas and Rose Marie Uva, a young couple shot to death near their home in Ozone Park, Queens, on Christmas Eve 1992.</p>
        <p>The Mafia had been humiliated by Mr. and Mrs. Uva, prosecutors said in Federal District Court in Brooklyn yesterday. For as long as it lasted, the Uvas had made a peculiar and precarious living from robbing Mafia social clubs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It stands to reason that the Mafia took responsibility for killing Thomas and Rose Marie Uva, a young couple shot to death near their home in Ozone Park, Queens, on Christmas Eve 1992.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It stands to reason that the Mafia took responsibility for killing Thomas and Rose Marie Uva, a young couple shot to death near their home in Ozone Park, Queens, on Christmas Eve 1992.</p>
        <p>The Mafia had been humiliated by Mr. and Mrs. Uva, prosecutors said in Federal District Court in Brooklyn yesterday. For as long as it lasted, the Uvas had made a peculiar and precarious living from robbing Mafia social clubs.</p>
        <p>Several times in several boroughs, prosecutors said, Mrs. Uva, 31, waited in the car while Mr. Uva, 28, entered the clubs. Interrupting captains and soldiers of organized-crime families as they played cards and plotted crimes, Mr. Uva used an Uzi submachine gun to demand money and jewelry.</p>
        <p>''He made the individuals in the club drop their pants,'' said a federal prosecutor, Joseph Lipton. ''They earned the nickname Bonnie and Clyde on the street, just like the brazen robbers from the 1930s.''</p>
        <p>When the Uvas were found dead in their car, each with three gunshots to the head, the Bonanno and the Gambino crime families both claimed credit for the killing, according to court documents.</p>
        <p>Opening the murder and racketeering case yesterday, prosecutors sought to assign responsibility to the Gambino family. Mr. Lipton said that John A. Gotti, who has acknowledged running the Gambino family in the 1990s, approved the killings. Mr. Gotti is named as a co-conspirator but not charged in the case.</p>
        <p>As he delivered his opening statement, Mr. Lipton pointed across the courtroom at Dominick Pizzonia, described as Skinny Dom, a captain of the Gambino family who ran a social club that was robbed by the Uvas.</p>
        <p>The defendant, Mr. Pizzonia, 65, and a co-defendant, Alfred DiCongilio, 77, known as Freddy Hot, are also charged with the murder of Frank Boccia in 1988. Mr. Boccia, by the account of prosecutors, was a Gambino family associate, a killer and a drug abuser. He had angered his bosses, Mr. Lipton said, by punching his mother-in-law, the wife of a Gambino captain, Angelo Ruggiero, known as Fat Andy.</p>
        <p>''Hitting your mother-in-law is bad,'' Mr. Lipton said, ''but when it's the wife of a made member of the Gambino crime family, it's fatal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lipton said he would prove that Mr. Pizzonia and Mr. DiCongilio had lured Mr. Boccia to a social club, shot him several times, reloaded the gun, shot him some more, loaded his body onto a boat, drove the boat until the land vanished behind them, punctured Mr. Boccia's lungs to let out any remaining air and sank his body in the ocean.</p>
        <p>Six months later, he said, Mr. Pizzonia was formally promoted into the Gambino family. When the social club robberies later became an embarrassment, he said, ''Pizzonia vowed to find the couple and make them pay with their lives.''</p>
        <p>Mr. and Mrs. Uva, Mr. Lipton said, ''were left in the street as an example of what happens when you cross the Gambino family.''</p>
        <p>A lawyer for Mr. Pizzonia, Joseph R. Corozzo Jr., deplored the promised prosecution witnesses, Mafia turncoats testifying in exchange for leniency, as multiple murderers, untrustworthy by nature. He said some witnesses had been ''tortured for their testimony.''</p>
        <p>He invoked the biblical trial of Christ, saying, ''The tactic of buying your witnesses and not considering the contradictions in their testimony continues to this day.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corozzo told jurors that a boss and an underboss of the Bonanno family would testify that their soldiers, too, had claimed credit for killing the Uvas. The government, Mr. Corozzo said, has known of those claims for years but declined to prosecute the Bonanno soldiers.</p>
        <p>''Where are these people?'' Mr. Corozzo asked. ''Why is Mr. Pizzonia here?''</p>
        <p>The Uvas, he added, ''were wanted by many, many people in the New York City area.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
