<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Back to Roots For Retailer In Canada</title>
    <meta content="11weston" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/business/worldbusiness/11weston.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Loblaw Companies</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weston, Galen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weston, W Galen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Loblaw Companies Limited</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEEDF123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Back to Roots For Retailer In Canada</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Purveyor to the Queen Faces Test From Wal-Mart</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Austen, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, April 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wal-Mart Stores is moving into groceries in Canada and Loblaw, whose food company holdings span entire industry and much of world, has lost its way; company on March 15 reported loss of 219 million Canadian dollars for 2006 ($190.3 million), first annual loss in 19 years; botched attempt last year at improving its distribution systems left shelves empty in many of chain's 1,100 stores, with inventory pile-ups at its 26 warehouses; company has recently introduced food products that have not been hit with shoppers, and its new nonfood items have fared even worse; task of preparing investors for recent run of bad news fell to Gallen G Weston, who succeeded his father W Galen Weston, as executive chairman five months ago; Weston addressed analysts in late February, saying company needs to improve every key driver of business; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Queen Elizabeth needs groceries, her staff usually sends out to Fortnum &amp; Mason. Household goods at Buckingham Palace often come from the Selfridges department store. And the tea poured at royal tea parties is likely to have been blended by R. Twining &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>These three companies fall into the large corporate basket of the Weston family, as close to Canadian royalty as anyone here comes. The royal warrants granted those companies proclaim: ''by appointment to HM The Queen.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Loblaw Companies, Canada’s largest grocery chain and once one of North America’s most innovative retailers, is struggling with inventory problems and its first annual loss in 19 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Queen Elizabeth needs groceries, her staff usually sends out to Fortnum &amp; Mason. Household goods at Buckingham Palace often come from the Selfridges department store. And the tea poured at royal tea parties is likely to have been blended by R. Twining &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>These three companies fall into the large corporate basket of the Weston family, as close to Canadian royalty as anyone here comes. The royal warrants granted those companies proclaim: ''by appointment to HM The Queen.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, if the queen has any complaints about her purchases, she could just call on Prince Charles, who is a polo partner and friend of W. Galen Weston, the scion of the family.</p>
        <p>But these days, the focus of the Weston family, whose food company holdings span the entire industry and much of the world, is sliding fast from the heights of British nobility and Buckingham Palace to the level of ordinary Canadians -- and to Bentonville, Ark. The foundation of the fortune that allows the Westons to fraternize with royalty is the Loblaw Companies, Canada's largest grocery chain and once one of North America's most innovative retailers.</p>
        <p>Now, Wal-Mart Stores is moving into groceries in Canada, and Loblaw has lost its way. On March 15, the company reported a loss of 219 million Canadian dollars for 2006 ($190.3 million). That was its first annual loss in 19 years.</p>
        <p>Last year, a botched attempt at improving its distribution systems left shelves empty in many of the chain's 1,100 stores, with inventory pile-ups at its 26 warehouses.The company has recently introduced food products that have not been a hit with shoppers, and its new nonfood items have fared even worse, leading to a write-down in inventories in December of 120 million Canadian dollars. In January, its expansion in Quebec through the purchase of a regional grocery chain resulted in a further write-down of nearly 900 million Canadians dollars.</p>
        <p>The task of preparing investors for the recent run of bad news fell to Galen G. Weston, 34, who succeeded his father, W. Galen Weston, as executive chairman five months ago. In late February, the younger Mr. Weston addressed analysts at Toronto's former hockey shrine, Maple Leaf Gardens, which is to become a Loblaw superstore.</p>
        <p>''We need to improve virtually every key driver of the business,'' Mr. Weston said. ''We have not been focused on our core strength of being the best food retailer in Canada. Our organization is too complex and is ineffective and slow to respond to the customer and to the competitive environment.''</p>
        <p>Various Loblaw executives presented analysts with candid PowerPoint presentations that included snapshots of chaotic Loblaw stock rooms that would be straightened out. Mr. Weston then reminded them that his family had saved the company once before.</p>
        <p>At that time, 34 years ago, Mr. Weston's father was about the same age as the younger Mr. Weston is now, when he became head of the chain. The situation back then was far worse than today. One consultant then even suggested that the family, which has been in the food business since 1882, close most of the outlets and cash out by selling the real estate.</p>
        <p>''One of the reasons that the family has been successful is because we're prepared to take very tough decisions, very difficult decisions that may impact the short-term performance of an organization, to make sure that it is successful for the long term,'' Mr. Weston told the crowd.</p>
        <p>The earlier turnaround of Loblaw owed a great deal to Dave Nichol, a college roommate of the older Mr. Weston who was working as a consultant at McKinsey &amp; Company. Mr. Nichol left Loblaw in December 1993 to start a private brand consulting business, Dave Nichol &amp; Associates, but he remains in touch with the family. Today, when Mr. Nichol visits a Loblaw's outlet, he finds little to praise.</p>
        <p>''It's a sad shadow of its former self,'' Mr. Nichol said of the situation. He blames bad advice from the senior management team that was recently purged, as well as the older Mr. Weston's being distracted by Selfridges, which he acquired in 2003.</p>
        <p>''Galen loves his department stores,'' Mr. Nichol said. ''Giorgio Armani is more interesting than Kraft dinner.''</p>
        <p>The essential innovation introduced by Mr. Nichol that helped the previous turnaround was to transform its house brands into premium brands under the name President's Choice.</p>
        <p>It was a strategy that involved seasonal magazine-style fliers -- their advertising pitches written by Mr. Nichol himself -- to promote the President's Choice offerings. A large internal staff also created, among other things, a chocolate chip cookie with more chocolate than anything on the market.</p>
        <p>It was also immensely profitable. Before President's Choice, Mr. Nichol said that coffee sold at Loblaw stores produced about a 10 percent gross margin for the retailer. After the new house brand appeared, including a heavily promoted blend made with an unusual decaffeination process, the entire category's margin rose to 35 percent.</p>
        <p>''You'd kill your mother for a tenth of a point in this business, so that was big news,'' Mr. Nichol said.</p>
        <p>Loblaw eventually expanded its President's Choice business and now offers the product line through retailers in 22 countries, including Jewel-Osco, a grocery chain in the United States. (The Westons, through a publicly traded holding company, George Weston, are a major presence in baking in the United States, where their brands include Entenmann's, Freihofer's, Thomas', Stroehmann and Arnold.)</p>
        <p>With Wal-Mart's expansion into the Canadian grocery market, Loblaw's previous management decided it was time for another change. The execution of that plan, however, did not run as smoothly as the moves during the Nichol era.</p>
        <p>The company, Mr. Nichol and many others argue, mistakenly tried to respond to Wal-Mart by becoming more like Wal-Mart. Loblaw stores were known for attractive, inviting designs. But after reaching a wage concession with its unions, Loblaw began building a new group of stores under the Real Canadian Superstore banner that are mostly notable for their Wal-Mart-like vastness.</p>
        <p>More problematic, however, were the new nonfood products that filled the increased floor space. John Chamberlain, a retail analyst with the debt rating service DBRS in Toronto, said that leading retailers in Europe had demonstrated that expanding beyond food is an effective tool for fending off Wal-Mart. And Loblaw itself had achieved success in parts of Western Canada with general merchandise.</p>
        <p>But when the televisions, flashlights, air-conditioners, arm chairs, camping gear and small appliances began rolling into Loblaw stores in the central Ontario market, few of them went out the door in customers' shopping carts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chamberlain attributes that to several factors. Not only was Loblaw unable to match the prices of Wal-Mart, many of its nonfood offerings put the stores directly in competition with other aggressive and successful retailers, including Canadian Tire of Toronto which, despite its name, offers a wide array of nonautomotive products.</p>
        <p>''They've got to find a niche away from Wal-Mart, just like Target did,'' Mr. Chamberlain said. ''There's no oxygen trying to be cheaper than them.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, the move into general merchandise and the bungled warehouse revamping led Loblaw to take its eye off the food business, even as it promoted new high-profit house brand items.</p>
        <p>That loss of direction came at a bad time. Other Canadian grocers like Sobeys, a chain of 1,296 stores, and Metro in Montreal, which is not connected to the German retailer of the same name and which also sells under the A&amp;P name in Canada, were building up their private-label businesses to compete with Loblaw. They were also making a successful push into prepared foods, an area Loblaw had neglected.</p>
        <p>To perhaps everyone's relief, Mr. Weston told the investment meeting that food would again be Loblaw's focus. Correspondingly, the company will narrow its efforts in nonfood products and concentrate on a line of inexpensive clothing sold under the Joe Fresh brand.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weston later pleaded with the analysts to stay for the fashion show: ''Sit down; sit down,'' he said. ''I know some of you are not superkeen on Joe Fresh, but we're going to give you a hint of what we can do for spring.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weston's parents, while not publicity seekers, have relatively high public profiles in Canada. His Irish-born mother, Hilary M. Weston, was Ontario's lieutenant governor, Queen Elizabeth's official representative, for six years. During that time, the elder Mr. Weston gamely attended the public building openings and community events that came with his wife's position.</p>
        <p>Until his appointment to Loblaw's top spot, the younger Mr. Weston, who is sometimes called G2, was mostly known for establishing the Spoke Club, a private club in Toronto, in 2004 with a partner and his sister, Allanah, who is now the creative director of Selfridges.</p>
        <p>While the Spoke Club originally catered to members of the city's arts and cultural communities, its current membership appears to be mostly made up of young professionals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weston previously held a variety of nonsenior jobs at Loblaw. One fact, however, has already set him apart from John Lederer, who was removed as president in September on the same day that Mr. Weston was promoted.</p>
        <p>According to securities filings, Mr. Lederer was paid 22 million Canadian dollars, including severance, outstanding pay and bonuses when he was removed from office. Mr. Weston, however, has agreed that he is not entitled to any severance payments, and he can be dismissed by the company at any time, for any reason.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Weston tries to work the family's healing magic on Loblaw again, he will be closely watched by his father, who remains chairman and president of the family holding company, which is also the largest Loblaw shareholder.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Nichol, Mr. Weston's success or failure will most likely hinge on the advice he receives from the executives who surround him, many of them from department stores.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nichol also suggested the factor that saved the company from its near collapse in the 1970s was also likely to be in play again: ''Pride,'' Mr. Nichol said. ''The Westons have really always been the biggest food people in Canada. And they didn't want to see the business go under. So, thankfully, the resources were there. If the money hadn't been there, we wouldn't have gone anywhere.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
