<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Charged in Texas State School Abuse Case</title>
    <meta content="11youth" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/us/11youth.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pyote (Tex)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brookins, Ray E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, John P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Texas</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Texas Youth Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFD6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Charged in Texas State School Abuse Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2 Charged in Texas State School Abuse Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, April 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ray E Brookins and John P Hernandez, former administrators at Texas state school for juvenile offenders, are arrested on charges of deviate sexual intercourse with six boys ages 16 to 19; two were named in 2005 investigation into accusations of sexual abuse at school in Pyote, but findings came to light only with recent news accounts, causing statewide public outcry, legislative inquiry and revamping of Texas Youth Commission; both administrators resigned without criminal charges, and state investigators are examining why commission records remained secret and whether they might have been altered to hide evidence of accusations; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former assistant superintendent and a former principal at a Texas state school for juvenile offenders were arrested Tuesday on charges of deviate sexual intercourse and other sexual contact with six boys ages 16 to 19.</p>
        <p>The two, Ray E. Brookins, 42, and John P. Hernandez, 41, administrators serving the Texas Youth Commission, were named two years ago in a Texas Rangers investigation into accusations of sexual abuse at the West Texas State School in Pyote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former assistant superintendent and a former principal at a school for juvenile offenders were arrested on charges of having sexual contact with six boys.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former assistant superintendent and a former principal at a Texas state school for juvenile offenders were arrested Tuesday on charges of deviate sexual intercourse and other sexual contact with six boys ages 16 to 19.</p>
        <p>The two, Ray E. Brookins, 42, and John P. Hernandez, 41, administrators serving the Texas Youth Commission, were named two years ago in a Texas Rangers investigation into accusations of sexual abuse at the West Texas State School in Pyote.</p>
        <p>But the findings, cited in internal reports, came to light only with news accounts in February, setting off a statewide outcry, legislative inquiries and a revamping of the Youth Commission. More than 2,100 complaints of mistreatment have been received on a hot line and families have filed civil lawsuits.</p>
        <p>''With today's indictments, the victims of sexual abuse at West Texas State School are a step closer to the justice they deserve,'' said the Texas attorney general, Greg Abbott, who took over the prosecution after complaints that the local district attorney had let the case languish.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brookins, who had been acting superintendent in charge of the West Texas State School, was arrested at his Austin home and ordered held on $100,000 bond at the Travis County jail, the attorney general's office said.</p>
        <p>The office said Mr. Hernandez was arrested at his parents' home in Fort Stockton and ordered held on $600,000 bond at the Pecos County jail there.</p>
        <p>Neither man has appeared in court to offer a plea, a spokesman for Mr. Abbott said late Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hernandez, in a phone conversation weeks ago, said he would plead not guilty if indicted. His lawyer, Albert Valadez, said Tuesday that Mr. Hernandez ''maintains his innocence.''</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Brookins nor a lawyer could be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>The indictments were brought by a Ward County grand jury after the part-time district attorney, Randall W. Reynolds, ceded jurisdiction April 4 to Mr. Abbott and three other prosecutors from his office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brookins and Mr. Hernandez were charged with 13 instances of using their mouths and hands on the genitals of youths detained at the school in 2004 and 2005. The youths' names were withheld.</p>
        <p>The indictments were called ''excellent'' by Jay Kimbrough, a former deputy state attorney general and the special conservator named by Gov. Rick Perry and legislative leaders to change the Youth Commission.</p>
        <p>According to documents that have emerged in recent weeks, the Youth Commission knew as early as February 2005 that a Texas Ranger had visited the school to investigate a math tutor's report that students had complained of being sexually abused by Mr. Brookins. The Ranger, Brian Burzynski, corroborated the accusations, along with similar complaints against Mr. Hernandez.</p>
        <p>Both administrators resigned without criminal charges, and state investigators are examining why commission records remained secret and whether they might have been altered to hide evidence of the accusations.</p>
        <p>Before transferring to West Texas, Mr. Brookins had been disciplined at another Texas youth facility for having pornography on his computer.</p>
        <p>Both men were reported to superiors for taking boys from the dorms at night for trysts behind closed doors, official reports later documented.</p>
        <p>After resigning from the state school, Mr. Hernandez was hired at a charter school in Midland.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
