<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Imperial Nights in Tunisia, With Mythology Underfoot</title>
    <meta content="11mosa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/arts/design/11mosa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070414T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Tunisia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Tunisia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Africa</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Getty, J Paul, Museum</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Caesar, Julius</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3D7153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1327" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Imperial Nights in Tunisia, With Mythology Underfoot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Imperial Nights in Tunisia, With Mythology Underfoot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabrikant, Geraldine</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Athena, the Greek goddess of wisdom, sits gazing languorously at herself in the river after a musical solo on an aulos, an ancient double-reed pipe. The river itself is symbolized by an elderly yet muscular man sitting across from her.</p>
        <p>Athena looks vaguely unhappy, perhaps because the constant playing, which involved using her mouth as a kind of bagpipe, has distorted the shape of her lips. Today she might opt for Restylane or Botox injections, but in the ancient mythological tale, she threw the instrument on the ground in anger. The satyr Marsyas, depicted in the right-hand corner of this mosaic, picked it up and challenged Apollo to a competition. Infuriated by his arrogance, Apollo had Marsyas flayed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Stories in Stone: Conserving Mosaics of Roman Africa,” now at the J. Paul Getty Museum, sheds light on how wealthy Romans once lived in North Africa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Athena, the Greek goddess of wisdom, sits gazing languorously at herself in the river after a musical solo on an aulos, an ancient double-reed pipe. The river itself is symbolized by an elderly yet muscular man sitting across from her.</p>
        <p>Athena looks vaguely unhappy, perhaps because the constant playing, which involved using her mouth as a kind of bagpipe, has distorted the shape of her lips. Today she might opt for Restylane or Botox injections, but in the ancient mythological tale, she threw the instrument on the ground in anger. The satyr Marsyas, depicted in the right-hand corner of this mosaic, picked it up and challenged Apollo to a competition. Infuriated by his arrogance, Apollo had Marsyas flayed.</p>
        <p>The narrative in this mosaic, discovered in 1974, traverses Greek and Roman mythology and would have been familiar to citizens of fourth-century Kelibia (now in northeastern Tunisia). It is among 26 mosaics -- among the finest in Tunisian museum collections -- that the J. Paul Getty Museum, with the Institut National du Patrimoine in Tunisia, have brought to the United States for the first time. The exhibition runs through April 30 at the Getty Villa in Pacific Palisades, Calif., home to the museum's sprawling collection of Greek, Roman and Etruscan artifacts.</p>
        <p>Muscular gods ride chariots drawn by superb sea horses; voluptuous, half-nude women pour jugs of water down their own backs. Rabbits eagerly nibble grapes, and ferocious lions devour their prey. The panoply of tales told in stone sheds some light on how a wealthy Roman elite lived in North Africa between the second and sixth centuries.</p>
        <p>''The exhibition came about from a longstanding relationship with our colleagues in Tunisia,'' the Getty's associate curator of antiquities, Janet Grossman, said in an interview. Over the last decade the Getty Conservation Institute has worked with the Tunisian institute to train technicians to restore mosaics that remain in situ, sometimes buried beneath the rubble of ancient Roman villas and public buildings.</p>
        <p>All of the mosaics on view at the Getty Villa were unearthed over the last 200 years and carefully preserved in Tunisia's museums.</p>
        <p>By the second and third centuries, the North African region that is now Tunisia was one of the crown jewels of the Roman Empire. Rich in olives and grain, it had become a wealthy outpost of Rome, and Carthage, its sprawling port, was fast growing into a cultural and economic hub.</p>
        <p>Julius Caesar had assured Rome's dominion over North Africa in the battle at Thapsus of 47 B.C., where troops vanquished forces led by his archrival Pompey. In the following centuries, upwardly mobile citizens across Tunisia vied to imitate the Romans, their gods, their culture, their clothes and their lifestyles. And like conspicuous consumers everywhere, wealthy Tunisians wanted impressive homes: some of these villas were as large as 21,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>Americans who amass new fortunes today race to cover their walls with art that proclaims their status, but the status symbols of ancient North Africa's megawealthy lay literally at their feet. And aside from the prestige value, mosaic floors helped cool interior temperatures in an area of the globe that could be relentlessly hot.</p>
        <p>Archaeologists have found mosaics not just in villa reception rooms, but also in dining rooms and bedrooms. Only the floors of the servants' quarters were left bare. Although mosaics were occasionally created on walls, ''the medium was really viewed as an efficient floor covering, waterproofed, durable and easy to walk on,'' said another expert, Christine Kondoleon, a senior curator of Greek and Roman art at the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</p>
        <p>Despite the obsessive focus on Rome, experts say, the mosaics were also molded by the African experience. They were more colorful and exuberant than other mosaics of that period because of the stones in the area, Ms. Kondoleon said.</p>
        <p>If North Africans were eager to show off their knowledge of Rome, there was a highly practical incentive. Aicha Ben Abed, a scholar at the Tunisian institute, writes in the book ''Tunisian Mosaics: Treasures From Roman Africa'' that a legal statute compensated citizens on the basis of how well they adhered to the values of Roman civilization. Cities that complied most admirably were treated as colonies, which meant that their denizens had the same rights as Roman citizens.</p>
        <p>A third-century mosaic depicting two lions ferociously tearing apart a boar was found in the dining room of a home in El Jem, inland in southern Tunisia. That same room also revealed a nine-foot-long floor portrait of a procession with Bacchus as its centerpiece. (Although the Getty had planned to include the larger piece in its show, experts decided that possible damage made it too risky to remove from the wall of the El Jem Museum in northeast Tunisia, which has one of the world's richest collections of Roman mosaics.)</p>
        <p>In Roman mythology, Bacchus, the god of wine and fertility, was thought capable of subduing the forces of nature and wild animals. The lions devouring the boar have fierce paws but somewhat human faces, characteristic of animals in mosaics from that part of the world.</p>
        <p>Kris Kelly, a senior curator at the Getty, said that North African mosaics tended to be more colorful than those from other parts of the Roman Empire because the terrain yielded a wider variety of colored stones and glass. The works also reflect the region's focus on sea fishing along the coast, and hunting and agriculture further inland.</p>
        <p>A 5-by-7-foot mosaic of Neptune driving two horses while holding his trident was found in 1904 in the coastal city of Sousse; an imposing head of Oceanus, with lobster claws darting from his hair and dolphins swimming out of his beard, was discovered in 1953 in the baths of Chott Merien, another Mediterranean port.</p>
        <p>Although scholars are well versed in the ancient myths animating the mosaics, they are unsure how much of the actual work was done on site. Ms. Ben Abed says that only a single bas-relief from ancient Roman culture, found in ancient Ostia, depicts a mosaic workshop. In Thuborbo Majus archaeologists found a trove of stone chips and tesserae that made it clear that mosaics were laid on site there.</p>
        <p>Archaeological work began in Tunisia in the early 1800s, when the first excavations in Carthage were carried out by a Dutch military engineer, Jean Emile Humbert. After Tunisia became a French protectorate in 1881, the French government underwrote annual archaeological investigations.</p>
        <p>In 1921 legislation made the Tunisian protectorate the owner of all newly discovered antiquities, with the goal of discouraging private foraging by foreigners.</p>
        <p>Organizing and shipping the mosaics to the Getty was a challenge. They were taken to Carthage, then shipped by boat to Marseille. From there, they were taken by truck to an airport and flown to Los Angeles. Upon arrival at the Getty Villa in Malibu, which reopened in January 2006 after an expansion and redesign, the mosaics were cleaned.</p>
        <p>Archaeologists emphasize the importance of leaving mosaics in situ so that scholars can consider the role each played in the society where it existed. In the exhibition and catalog, the Getty has gone to great pains to explain that it is collaborating with Tunisia to teach workers and experts how to conserve the works where they are found. (The show coincides with negotiations by the Getty with the governments of Greece and Italy, which argue that some Greek and Etruscan items in the museum's collection were looted from their soil.)</p>
        <p>Maintaining Tunisian mosaics in situ is hardly an easy task, given that so many are exposed to the elements in largely undeveloped areas. In some cases workers have had to rebury mosaics to protect them from the elements until conservation is possible.</p>
        <p>For now, Americans have the chance to savor fully restored specimens at the Getty.</p>
        <p>''Stories in Stone: Conserving Mosaics of Roman Africa'' runs through April 30 at the Getty Villa, 17985 Pacific Coast Highway, Pacific Palisades, Calif; (310) 440-7300 or getty.edu.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 14, 2007, Saturday  An article in The Arts on Wednesday about an exhibition of Roman mosaics from Tunisia at the Getty Villa in Pacific Palisades, Calif., misstated the date of the battle of Thapsus, in which Julius Caesar ensured Roman control of North Africa. It took place in 46 B.C., not 47 B.C. Because of an editing error, the article also misidentified the commander of Caesar's opponents. They were led by Pompey's father-in-law, not by Pompey, who had been murdered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 14, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in The Arts on Wednesday about an exhibition of Roman mosaics from Tunisia at the Getty Villa in Pacific Palisades, Calif., misstated the date of the battle of Thapsus, in which Julius Caesar ensured Roman control of North Africa. It took place in 46 B.C., not 47 B.C. Because of an editing error, the article also misidentified the commander of Caesar's opponents. They were led by Pompey's father-in-law, not by Pompey, who had been murdered.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
