<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Trail of Wholesome Pet Dinners</title>
    <meta content="11pets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/us/11pets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pet Foods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organic Foods and Products</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Menu Foods (Canadian Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zezima, Katie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Menu Foods</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Trail of Wholesome Pet Dinners</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Recall, Dog and Cat Owners Seek Out Organic Food</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATIE ZEZIMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zezima, Katie</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stores that sell organic and raw pet food say sales have risen sharply since major recall of pet food on March 16; Menu Foods, which made most of recalled food, has expanded its recall for second time, prompting fearful pet owners to seek organic food for their dogs and cats; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The health-conscious customers at the store in the trendy South End neighborhood want wholesome food: vegetable and fruit chews; high-protein, low-carb nuggets; and organic meals containing cottage cheese.</p>
        <p>The nutritious fare, however, is not for them; it is for their dogs and cats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stores that sell pet food made from free-range meat, organic vegetables and brown rice say business has increased since a recall of contaminated food.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The health-conscious customers at the store in the trendy South End neighborhood want wholesome food: vegetable and fruit chews; high-protein, low-carb nuggets; and organic meals containing cottage cheese.</p>
        <p>The nutritious fare, however, is not for them; it is for their dogs and cats.</p>
        <p>The store, Pet Shop Girls, specializes in organic, holistic and raw pet food, and its sales have gone up sharply since a major recall of pet food was announced March 16.</p>
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration found melamine, a slow-release fertilizer also used to make plastics, in wheat gluten that may have gotten into the recalled food. The F.D.A. said there were 16 confirmed pet deaths from contaminated food, including nine from a routine company taste test, but officials said the number was likely to be much higher.</p>
        <p>Banfield Pet Hospital, which operates 615 hospitals nationwide, said it had confirmed that six more pets had died from contaminated food. The hospital said it had treated about 1,600 pets believed to have eaten recalled food in the past three weeks.</p>
        <p>''Because of the recall, people are asking more questions, wondering what is in this bag of food,'' said Jen Buhler, manager of The Pet Shop Girls, which sells homemade ''muttzoh balls'' -- mashed dry dog food boiled in chicken broth -- and bacon bon-bons made with bacon, wheat flour and cheddar cheese.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Menu Foods, which made most of the recalled food, expanded its recall for the second time in less than a week, adding 34 varieties of cat food.</p>
        <p>The company said the food was manufactured at a Canadian plant in December 2006 and January 2007 with a batch of wheat gluten potentially contaminated with melamine. The gluten was shipped to the Ontario facility from its Emporia, Kan., plant. The previously recalled food was manufactured there, and at a plant in Pennsauken, N.J., the company said.</p>
        <p>Lists of recalled foods are available online at www.menufoods.com/recall.</p>
        <p>Stores and Web sites that sell pet food made from free-range meat, organic vegetables and brown rice say business has increased markedly since the recall, which affected both low- and high-end brands.</p>
        <p>Shelley Gunton, a co-owner of Castor and Pollux Pet Works, a natural and organic pet supplies company in Clackamas, Ore., said Web traffic had increased tenfold since mid-March and sales were up nearly 50 percent.</p>
        <p>''Somebody feeding brand X at the moment will call and say they want to switch to a more organic product, but they want to understand the difference, what it means to be a certified organic pet food,'' Ms. Gunton said. ''We want to make sure people feel comfortable purchasing organics and won't go to bed worrying about their pets.''</p>
        <p>For pet food to be labeled organic, at least 95 percent of the ingredients must be certified organic for human consumption, said Andrea Caroe, chairwoman of the National Organic Standards Board, which is part of the Food and Drug Administration.</p>
        <p>According to a survey by the Organic Trade Association, organic pet food sales totaled $30 million in 2005, a 46 percent increase from the previous year. Sales were expected to grow by about 36 percent in 2006, and at least 25 percent each year until 2010, the group said.</p>
        <p>Andi Brown, founder of Halo Pet Foods, which says it takes a holistic approach to pet care, selling food made from human-grade ingredients as well as herbal grooming aids and supplements, said sales of certain food products had increased by more than 90 percent since mid-March. Internet orders have doubled, Ms. Brown said.</p>
        <p>''It's very sad that it had to come to this,'' Ms. Brown said. ''People are fearful, scared out of their wits.''</p>
        <p>Bree Weasner, who runs preciouspets.org, which sells natural pet products, said food sales had more than doubled.</p>
        <p>''I've always worked seven days a week, but since the recalls I've never worked so many hours,'' Ms. Weasner said.</p>
        <p>John Gigliotti, owner of waggintails.com, which sells natural dog, cat and bird food, said business was up 30 percent to 40 percent, spurred mostly by word of mouth. Many customers he talks to are disturbed that officials still do not know whether the melamine made pets sick, he said, and Mr. Gigliotti said he thought the recall would lead to a long-term rise in organic pet food sales.</p>
        <p>''When the dust settles and we know what happened, it will simply reinforce what we've been talking about for years, which is economy-minded manufacturers use economy ingredients,'' Mr. Gigliotti said. ''Now people want to know all the behind-the-scenes stuff.''</p>
        <p>Scott Andrews, 45, a tax accountant from Boston, said he did not know what to feed his beagle, Sam. Mr. Andrews said for the time being he planned to give Sam food that was organic or made in New England by small manufacturers.</p>
        <p>''Every time I open a can, I think of the recall,'' Mr. Andrews said in Pet Shop Girls as Sam sniffed around. ''I just don't know what to trust, I guess.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
