<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reader Responses</title>
    <meta content="11leonhardt-response" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7D7123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1636" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reader Responses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The following are excerpts of reader responses to David Leonhardt's April 11 column on the relative merits of buying and renting a home:</p>
        <p>I have been a Real Estate Broker in Central Florida for over 25 years and based on my experience you are totally wrong. You make it sounds like people are better of putting their money in to the stock market then buying a home. Well, let me tell you anyone that has put their money into the market lost lots more then the person that put it into real estate in the early 80s. Your information may be correct for New York or some other large city but not for the rest of the country. Owning real estate is one sure way for people to save money as they pay off their home. - Rosa Holloway</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The following are excerpts of reader responses to David Leonhardt's April 11 column on the relative merits of buying and renting a home:</p>
        <p>I have been a Real Estate Broker in Central Florida for over 25 years and based on my experience you are totally wrong. You make it sounds like people are better of putting their money in to the stock market then buying a home. Well, let me tell you anyone that has put their money into the market lost lots more then the person that put it into real estate in the early 80s. Your information may be correct for New York or some other large city but not for the rest of the country. Owning real estate is one sure way for people to save money as they pay off their home. - Rosa Holloway</p>
        <p>As an independent residential real estate broker/investor in Atlanta with 12 years experience, I concur with your advice, overall. (I have never been a "Realtor"/member of the local board of Realtors, because they do over blow their horns, and collect very high membership fees.) I suspect that Atlanta markets have faired slightly better overall in your analysis than South Florida and many of the others. I focus on inner city gentrifying areas of Atlanta/Decatur, and while these homes have slowed in the last few years in appreciation over 1994-2004, many of the neighborhoods here are still doing quite brisk business. (Lengthening traffic commutes from the suburbs is presently driving the inner city gentrification locally here that began in the mid '90's.)</p>
        <p>You make one statement I would suggest is perhaps too broad. "But in a stark reversal, it's now clear that people who chose renting over buying in the last two years made the right move." (Perhaps "it's now clear that most people...." is more accurate.) I come across savvy clients every day who wish they bought in the last few years instead of renting, given that they are now nearly priced out of the market. - Don Bayliss</p>
        <p>We have owned homes twice before, the first, in Greenwich, Conn., returned us a big fat zero return even after 12 years of ownership. We sold our second home, originally purchased in 2001, at a nice profit this time two years ago. For now, we're happily sitting on the sidelines. Our home equity is parked in the stock market and our rent, net of tax considerations and all, is about half what it would cost us to own the same home. - Cal Mann</p>
        <p>The idea of having a property of your own brings a lot of joy and energy to improve your living conditions. I bought 5 homes from 2001-2004; they all appreciated in value by a lot (I live in Washington DC area), and I renovated most of them, adding more value to these properties. I have tenants in all of those homes. What strikes me is that they all act like they are in a rush, living from day to day. They have no stability, they cannot enjoy buying a piece of nice furniture, they will think twice about having a child. When one couple moved out, they almost had no personal belongings - they packed a few bags with their clothes.</p>
        <p>I came to the U.S. 15 years ago from an impoverished country and my dream was to have a house of my own. Now I have five. I am sorry for those Americans who have lived in this country for so long, have been educated in home ownership by their parents and still think about renting!!!! - Ilir Ikonomi</p>
        <p>I have lived in Brooklyn my whole life and never bought a house. I live in a well maintained, safe, affordable building. I believe that people like myself are much better off financially paying rent. Your article did not go into the other big expenses of home ownership that can put a big hurt on middle income wage earners. If the roof goes, or the plumbing, they are in a big hole. How about the high cost of heating the home? The landscaping, etc.?</p>
        <p>I am a teacher. Many of my colleagues live in New Jersey or Long Island and have to be in their cars anywhere from 2 to 3 hours a day commuting. I think that too is an added expense of home ownership since most teachers can't even think about owning a home in New York City. - Mike Davis</p>
        <p>Your column makes perfect sense -- I've bucked the trend down here for the past few years by continuing to rent rather than buy. There are homes for sale all over my area, now sellers are trying to rent some of them. I don't see myself buying in the near future, I have freedom and affordability now, an unbeatable combination. And the money I'm saving goes into excellent mutual funds -- so I'm making money each month, not waiting and praying that my home appreciates. - Holly Hand</p>
        <p>Often confused with the financial logic is the cultural belief that homeownership is a civic virtue. I have nothing against a values-based argument for buying a home, as long as it's logically separated from the financial analysis, but I also think it's time that we recognized other values as well. Homeownership sparks civic pride, but it also inspires NIMBY responses to necessary public projects and letting undesirables like families (who drive up property taxes) into the neighborhood. What's more, homeownership spurs profligate spending on remodeling and similar luxuries, which is rarely considered part of the cost. Then again, frugality has lost its appeal as an American virtue, replaced instead by the notion that deficit spending is both the nation's and the citizen's patriotic duty. - Gene Koo</p>
        <p>Have you checked the Hoboken, NJ market lately? Prices have already gone up again and the inventory is down by about 200 since December 2006. And so have the average days on market. I find it hard to believe that Hoboken is the only city in the country with this trend. Your report is very one sided and doesn't serve the consumer. There's always 2 sides to every story. - Isabel Vasso</p>
        <p>You argue: "prices may not yet have fallen far enough for buying to look better than renting today, except for people who plan to stay in a home for many years." But isn't it more a matter of staying in the same housing market, not the same home, that counts? If you switch homes before the market recovers or exceeds its original strength, then it's true that you have not yet benefited from much if any appreciation of your equity, but that equity appreciation is likely to happen with the new home (or some subsequent home), to which you have in effect transferred your equity. Admittedly, you will incur additional agents' fees and closing costs each time you sell and buy, but if you have faith in the long-term potential of a given housing market, you should be O.K. as long as you get into that market and stay there over the long term, even if you move your equity from one house to another within that market. - C. Peter Herman</p>
        <p>Thank you for a smart piece on the real estate market today. I understand the position of the Realtor's Association, and it certainly would not help their cause to sound alarm bells or issue notes of caution, but I find their pitch too saccharine.</p>
        <p>An underside to your story could be the new home buying of young professionals, aided by their baby boomer parents. Reports are surfacing in my area of Vancouver, B.C. that baby boomer parents are helping their children buy new homes and apartments, financing the down payment or even making mortgage payments. I am willing to bet that the Realtor's Association is eager to win these young converts and their moneyed parents to their cause of real estate as the "you can't lose" investment. Most children of the boomers can't remember the bottom of the real estate market in the early '80s, and would only be dimly aware of the early '90s. - Steve Devereux</p>
        <p>I've been telling people for 3 years now what was going to happen and that they were buying at the top of the market -- using third grade math to explain it, I still couldn't get anyone to believe me that renting was better for the near future. Your article will help! - Greg Kyle</p>
        <p>Thanks for your interesting article today. As someone who is looking for a house now, I found it very helpful. I had two additional thoughts:</p>
        <p>1. I believe realtors frequently overstate the tax benefits of buying. Because the standard deduction has increased, many people will not have enough deductions, even with a mortgage, to itemize deductions. I was in this situation last year. To be more conservative, estimates of tax deductibility should subtract the standard deduction from mortgage interest paid.</p>
        <p>2. On the other hand and contrary to the article, I believe that renters do pay mortgage interest, it is just included in the rent and therefore they do not get a tax deduction. - Christopher M. Cox</p>
        <p>Sarasota, Fla., Realtors have launched a happy-talk campaign called Time2BuyNow. The prevailing theory here is that a coming tsunami of retiring baby boomers with re-ignite the market. The Realtors apparently didn't get the memo that a third of the boomers in the soon-to-retire cohort have less than $25,000 saved, $9,200 in credit card debt, and a tapped-out home equity line of credit threatening to take their net worth negative as prices fall. Plus there are 15 million fewer GenXers behind the boomers to buy the oversized houses they will need to sell to move down here. - Wayne Harris</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
