<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Artist's Underground Flowering</title>
    <meta content="11atla" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/movies/11atla.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seitz, Matt Zoller</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jordan, Mary</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6D7153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Artist's Underground Flowering</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Artist’s Underground Flowering</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT ZOLLER SEITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seitz, Matt Zoller</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matt Zoller Seitz reviews Mary Jordan documentary Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's gratifying when an influential underground artist is profiled in an accessible, entertaining documentary. For that reason alone, Mary Jordan's film ''Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis,'' whose subject is an antiestablishment director, is worth seeing -- even though Ms. Jordan dices Mr. Smith's films into snippets that don't convey their languorous rhythms, and seems content to mythologize rather than dissect.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith, who died of AIDS-related causes in 1989, was a New York-based photographer, filmmaker and performer. His films were infused with stereotypically ''exotic'' imagery, much of it drawn from his experience as a gay man in postwar America and his childhood infatuation with old Hollywood features, particularly those starring Maria Montez, the basis for one of Mr. Smith's favorite performers, the transvestite Mario Montez.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It’s gratifying when an influential underground artist is profiled in an accessible documentary. For that reason alone, “Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis” is worth seeing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's gratifying when an influential underground artist is profiled in an accessible, entertaining documentary. For that reason alone, Mary Jordan's film ''Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis,'' whose subject is an antiestablishment director, is worth seeing -- even though Ms. Jordan dices Mr. Smith's films into snippets that don't convey their languorous rhythms, and seems content to mythologize rather than dissect.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith, who died of AIDS-related causes in 1989, was a New York-based photographer, filmmaker and performer. His films were infused with stereotypically ''exotic'' imagery, much of it drawn from his experience as a gay man in postwar America and his childhood infatuation with old Hollywood features, particularly those starring Maria Montez, the basis for one of Mr. Smith's favorite performers, the transvestite Mario Montez.</p>
        <p>The Atlantis in the title refers to a Maria Montez film, ''Siren of Atlantis,'' which enraptured Mr. Smith and serves as a metaphor for the world he tried to conjure -- one where the exotic was commonplace, sexuality was mutable, and people were free to seek happiness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith influenced generations of avant-garde artists, including the filmmakers John Waters, Nick Zedd and Andy Warhol. Warhol filched key ideas from Mr. Smith's heavily improvised, experimental films, including the ''superstar'' (a beautiful-grotesque parody of Hollywood glamour) and the ''factory'' (a bohemian studio, presided over by a director-guru). You could make a case that Mr. Smith's omnisexual movie ''Flaming Creatures'' -- banned in many states in the early 1960s for its profanity, nudity and Bacchanalian vibe -- was the work that inspired much of Warhol's film output. (Warhol even lured away Mario Montez to work in the Factory.)</p>
        <p>According to the documentary, Mr. Smith thought Warhol was a hustler who reproduced the surface of his films but not their innocent, revolutionary soul. He accused the critic (and later, Anthology Film Archives founder) Jonas Mekas of exploiting ''Flaming Creatures'' for professional gain, redefining it as a First Amendment cause célèbre and obliterating its utopian intent.</p>
        <p>The latter part of Mr. Smith's career, during which he spontaneously re-edited his movies while they were unspooling, is presented as an attempt to control his art by making it ephemeral.</p>
        <p>For all the Technicolor fecundity of Mr. Smith's photographs, and the still splendid silliness of his movies, Ms. Jordan's film makes Mr. Smith seem an impassioned cliché -- the resentful fringe artist who sabotages his career rather than give up the right to accuse others of selling out.</p>
        <p>Surely this was not Ms. Jordan's intent, but the fawning approach begs for a between-the-lines reading. ''Jack Smith'' doesn't merely celebrate Mr. Smith; it presents him as a visionary angel born to a world that didn't deserve him.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jordan lets a few subjects contradict the image of Mr. Smith as martyr, but the overall tone is worshipful verging on reductive. You come away impressed by Smith's charisma, versatility and integrity, while also wondering if a man so abrasively self-important could have made such playful art.</p>
        <p>Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Mary Jordan; directors of photography, Ms. Jordan and Jon Fordham; edited by Alex Márquez; music by Joel A. Diamond, Robert Aaron, Thurston Moore and Devendra Barnhart; produced by Ms. Jordan and Kenneth Wayne Peralta. At the Film Forum, 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village. Running time: 95 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
