<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PROPERTY VALUES: What You Get for ... $800,000</title>
    <meta content="11GH-SUBwhat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Denver (Colo)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oahu (Hawaii)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgia</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Denver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PROPERTY VALUES: What You Get for ... $800,000</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA BAHNEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richmond Hill, Ga.</p>
        <p>WHAT: Three-bedroom house</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Richmond Hill, Ga.</p>
        <p>WHAT: Three-bedroom house</p>
        <p>HOW MUCH: $775,000</p>
        <p>PER SQUARE FOOT: $344.44</p>
        <p>This 2,250-square-foot low-country raised cottage sits on the Lincoln River along the Georgia coast with views of salt marshes and St. Catherine's and Ossabaw Islands. Situated about 20 miles south of Savannah and about four and a half hours southeast of Atlanta, Richmond Hill is a growing community named after</p>
        <p>the winter estate that Henry Ford once owned nearby. It offers hiking, biking, golf and boating activities as well as access to beaches, the ocean and the Intracoastal Waterway. The house has pine floors and cypress siding. A large porch looks out on the river, which has a floating dock in deep water. Built in 1992, the three-story house has a two-car garage and a workshop on the ground floor. There are three and a half baths and a fireplace. Taxes are $2,800 a year. The homeowners association fee is $150 a year. Celia Dunn, Celia</p>
        <p>Dunn Sotheby's International Realty (912) 844-5901; www.sothebysrealty.com</p>
        <p>Denver</p>
        <p>WHAT: Two-bedroom condo</p>
        <p>HOW MUCH: $795,000</p>
        <p>PER SQUARE FOOT: $575.67</p>
        <p>This downtown Denver condominium is in a building called the Museum Residences, designed by the architect Daniel Libeskind and completed last year. The building features the architect's angled geometry and uses metallics and coated glass, similar to the architecture across its plaza in Mr. Libeskind's Frederic C. Hamilton Building, an expansion of the Denver Art Museum. The condominium is near the Colorado state capitol as well as the downtown area called LoDo, which has restaurants, shops, nightlife and Coors Field, the home of the Colorado Rockies baseball team. The 1,381-square-foot apartment is on the fourth floor of the 55-unit, seven-story building and has mountain and city views. The kitchen, which is open to the living room, has stainless steel cabinets and Bosch appliances. The floors are hardwood and tile; the space has been designed with nooks and angles to place sculpture and art. The apartment has two full baths and a terrace and comes with custom-size window coverings and one parking place in a guarded garage. Taxes have not yet been assessed. The condo association fee is $510 a month. Sharon Parson, Preferred Properties Inc. (303) 778-8222, ext. 113; www.preferreddenver.com</p>
        <p>Hauula, Hawaii</p>
        <p>WHAT: Three-bedroom house</p>
        <p>HOW MUCH: $799,000</p>
        <p>PER SQUARE FOOT: $447.87</p>
        <p>In a rural area on the northeastern coast of Oahu, this 1989 house has views of the Pacific Ocean and the mountains. Hauula offers snorkeling at a coral reef a quarter mile offshore, and hiking on trails in nearby parks. About an hour north of Honolulu International Airport, Hauula is near the village of Laie, known for its Polynesian Cultural Center, and is about 10 miles from Kualoa Ranch, which offers activities like horseback riding and jungle tours. The 1,784-square-foot, two-story house is five homes in from the ocean. The family room has an expansive view through floor-to-ceiling sliding glass doors that open to a lanai. The house has contemporary architectural details, including a decorative ceiling in the family room and built-in shelves. The furniture is available for sale but is not included in the price. There are two full baths. Taxes are $1,656 a year. Donna Maier, Coldwell Banker Pacific Properties (808) 227-4799; www.cbpacific.com/donnam</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
