<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Criticizes Democrats For Delay in Iraq Spending Bill</title>
    <meta content="11prexy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/washington/11prexy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zeleny, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reid, Harry (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E1DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Criticizes Democrats For Delay in Iraq Spending Bill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Criticizes Democrats for Delay in Iraq Spending Bill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG and JEFF ZELENY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zeleny, Jeff; Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush accuses Democrats in Congress of behaving irresponsibly in not passing emergency Iraq spending bill unencumbered by timetable for withdrawal; invites leaders of both parties to White House to 'discuss the way forward' but makes clear he has no intention of using session to negotiate or compromise; Sen Harry Reid, Democratic majority leader, says Democrats will not acquiesce on issue of timetable; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush, at loggerheads with Congress over an emergency Iraq spending bill, accused Democrats on Tuesday of behaving irresponsibly, as the two sides moved closer to confrontation over whether -- or how far -- lawmakers could push Mr. Bush toward withdrawing troops.</p>
        <p>With the Senate back at work after a weeklong Easter recess, Mr. Bush chose a favorable venue -- an American Legion post in Fairfax, Va. -- to renew his threat to veto any measure that included a timetable for withdrawal. The speech included some of his most pointed language to date.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush accused Democrats of behaving irresponsibly as the two sides moved closer to confrontation over withdrawing troops from Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush, at loggerheads with Congress over an emergency Iraq spending bill, accused Democrats on Tuesday of behaving irresponsibly, as the two sides moved closer to confrontation over whether -- or how far -- lawmakers could push Mr. Bush toward withdrawing troops.</p>
        <p>With the Senate back at work after a weeklong Easter recess, Mr. Bush chose a favorable venue -- an American Legion post in Fairfax, Va. -- to renew his threat to veto any measure that included a timetable for withdrawal. The speech included some of his most pointed language to date.</p>
        <p>''Democratic leaders in Congress are bent on using a bill that funds our troops to make a political statement about the war,'' Mr. Bush said. ''They need to do it quickly and get it to my desk so I can veto it, and then Congress can get down to the business of funding our troops without strings and without further delay.''</p>
        <p>The House and Senate have each passed spending bills that include withdrawal language; the chambers must now reconcile the bills and send the final product to Mr. Bush. The White House has been publicly counting the days -- Tuesday was Day 64 -- since the president sent his spending request to Congress, as part of an effort to paint Democrats as the party of delay.</p>
        <p>''It is irresponsible for the Democratic leadership in Congress to delay for months on end while our troops in combat are waiting for the funds they need to succeed,'' Mr. Bush said, adding that he is inviting leaders of both parties to the White House next week to ''discuss the way forward.''</p>
        <p>But the White House made clear that Mr. Bush had no intention of using the session to negotiate or compromise, and Democrats reacted harshly. Senator Harry Reid of Nevada, the majority leader, said Democrats would not acquiesce to the president's demands of removing the troop withdrawal provision.</p>
        <p>''By our Constitution, we have equal say that he has,'' Mr. Reid said. ''And he's got to listen to us, because we are speaking for the American people. He isn't.''</p>
        <p>As Democrats brace for the confrontation over war spending, hoping to persuade the administration to change its Iraq strategy, the party is also seeking to navigate its own internal fissures over how vigorously to press the president. Aides to Mr. Reid and to the House speaker, Nancy Pelosi of California, said the two had not yet decided whether to meet with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Democratic leaders are facing pressure from the left to hold their ground. Liberal Democrats like Senator Russell D. Feingold of Wisconsin say that if Mr. Bush carries out his veto threat, Democrats should pursue legislation to curb financing for the military operation by March 31, 2008. But other more moderate Democrats, including Senator Carl Levin of Michigan, the Armed Services Committee chairman, have said they do not favor that approach.</p>
        <p>The White House and the Democrats are betting they can blame each other for any delay in getting money to the troops. Democrats believe, as Mr. Reid said, that the public is on their side, while the White House is banking on support from veterans like those who attended Tuesday's speech. Yet even there, some confessed to doubts about the nation's continued involvement in the war.</p>
        <p>''I'm conflicted a little about it,'' said Dan Dellinger, who served during the Vietnam era as a captain in the Army. ''We're noble in what we're doing to help out another country, but everybody hates to see lives lost.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Dellinger, like others who attended, said that in the end he came down in support of the president. ''I think Congress should listen to him,'' he said.</p>
        <p>With the House still on recess for another week, it remained an open question how -- and when -- the confrontation would be resolved. The work of reconciling the bills cannot begin until the House returns, and in the meantime, Mr. Bush warned that the Pentagon would soon have to transfer $1.6 billion from other military accounts ''to cover the shortfall'' caused by the lack of a bill.</p>
        <p>He ticked off a series of cutbacks he said the military would be forced to consider if a bill was not approved soon, including curtailing training for National Guard and Army Reserve forces if there was no measure by mid-April, and curtailing training for active duty forces if there was no bill by mid-May.</p>
        <p>But Democratic leaders rejected the notion that the money for the troops was on the verge of running out. ''The urgency is only in the president's head,'' Mr. Reid said, walking through the Capitol after a news conference. ''We'll get something done soon.''</p>
        <p>Still, Republicans said it would not be soon enough. Senate Republicans sent a letter to Ms. Pelosi on Tuesday, urging her to call the House back into session to deal with the Iraq spending bill. (Mr. Bush, though, did not echo that call in his speech.) Aides to Ms. Pelosi rejected the Republican letter as political posturing.</p>
        <p>Senator Mitch McConnell of Kentucky, the Republican leader, seized on the differences emerging among some Democrats. ''This debate among Democrats is another reason why this could be dragged out entirely too long and needs to be dealt with now,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
