<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Inquiry In Loan Case Is Questioning Stock Transfer</title>
    <meta content="11loans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/education/11loans.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Student Loan Xpress</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cit Group Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Balestri, Fabrizio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burt, Lawrence W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charlow, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Catherine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fontana, Matteo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Edward M (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Student Loan Xpress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EED6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Inquiry In Loan Case Is Questioning Stock Transfer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Senate Inquiry in Loan Case Is Studying Stock Transfer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN D. GLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glater, Jonathan D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate aides say that Education Dept official and financial aid directors at three universities who received stock in Student Loan Xpress from company's Pres Fabrizio Balestri may have violated securities law; Balestri described stock transfers as gifts in several documents, but at least one recipient of shares has said he paid for stock; Sen Edward Kennedy calls for inquiry into transactions; Balestri transferred stock to Lawrence Burt, David Charlow, Catherine Thomas and Matteo Fontana; all four have been put on leave by their employers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Education Department official and financial aid directors at three universities received stock in a student loan company from the company's current president in what may have been a violation of securities law, Senate aides looking into the transactions say.</p>
        <p>In various documents that have been turned over to staff members working for Senator Edward M. Kennedy, the president of the company described the transfers as gifts. But at least one recipient of the shares has said he paid for the stock.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Financial aid directors at three universities received stock in a student loan company in what may have been a violation of securities law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Education Department official and financial aid directors at three universities received stock in a student loan company from the company's current president in what may have been a violation of securities law, Senate aides looking into the transactions say.</p>
        <p>In various documents that have been turned over to staff members working for Senator Edward M. Kennedy, the president of the company described the transfers as gifts. But at least one recipient of the shares has said he paid for the stock.</p>
        <p>Because the executive, Fabrizio Balestri of Student Loan Xpress, had acquired the shares in a private placement of stock that restricts how it can be transferred, the gifts -- or sale -- may have run afoul of federal securities laws, said Mr. Kennedy, the Massachusetts Democrat who heads the Senate education committee. Yesterday he called on federal regulators to investigate the transactions.</p>
        <p>''The facts surrounding these transactions warrant an inquiry,'' Mr. Kennedy wrote in a letter to the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>''It particularly concerns me,'' he added, ''that Mr. Balestri apparently later sent a 'memorandum of gift' to each of the recipients of the stock, purporting to show that he had given them the shares for free when all had bought the shares from him,'' at a discounted price.</p>
        <p>The senator's staff has been investigating relations between loan companies and universities. The disclosures last week that the financial aid administrators owned the stock have prompted concerns that they had an incentive to steer students to the loan company. The government official helped oversee lenders in the federal student loan program.</p>
        <p>The documents describing the transfers of stock as gifts were signed by Mr. Balestri and his wife. They contradict what one financial aid director said in an interview last week. That official, Lawrence Burt of the University of Texas at Austin, said he had paid $1,000 for 1,500 shares. Mr. Burt could not be reached for comment last night.</p>
        <p>The documents, turned over to the Senate staff by Student Loan Xpress's parent company, which has been cooperating with Mr. Kennedy's inquiry, show that Mr. Balestri received the stock in 2001 through a private placement. Such an offering by a company is exempt from many of the rules on public offerings and is generally restricted to sophisticated investors. In such transactions, the purchaser may not turn around and sell the shares to others; that could be the equivalent of a public offering of stock.</p>
        <p>''We want to make sure the initial private placement is real,'' said Jill E. Fisch, director of the Center for Corporate, Securities and Financial Law at Fordham University's law school. ''We don't want to give it to some people and then have those people distribute it.''</p>
        <p>Senate aides said Mr. Balestri might have tried to characterize the stock transfers as gifts in an effort to get around the requirement that he hold the shares for a set period of time. A call to the office of Mr. Balestri was not returned. C. Curtis Ritter, a spokesman for CIT Group, which acquired Student Loan Xpress in 2005, declined to answer questions about the stock transactions. CIT has placed Mr. Balestri on leave.</p>
        <p>Mr. Balestri transferred stock not only to Mr. Burt but also to David Charlow, financial aid director for Columbia's undergraduate college and its engineering school; Catherine Thomas, director of financial aid at the University of Southern California; and Matteo Fontana, general manager in a unit of the Office of Federal Student Aid at the Department of Education. In recent days, all four have been put on leave by their employers.</p>
        <p>Senate aides said that for each $10,000 in the private placement, investors had received 10,000 shares and 5,000 warrants, or options to purchase additional stock before a certain date, in Education Lending Group, which was then the parent of Student Loan Xpress. Mr. Balestri obtained $80,000 worth of stock and kept none of it, according to the documents. In a personal list called ''memorandums of gift,'' he wrote that he gave away 80,000 shares to 16 people on Dec. 31, 2001. That was one day before he began work at the company as its president.</p>
        <p>The 2001 private placement raised $3.7 million for Education Lending and was authorized by that company's chief executive, Robert deRose. At the time, the stock was trading between $1 and $2 a share. It is not clear who purchased the rest of the shares or whether anyone else at the company had knowledge of Mr. Balestri's transfers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
