<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Become Infuriated As Bulls Pour On the Points</title>
    <meta content="11knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/sports/basketball/11knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bulls</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Curry, Eddy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFDE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Become Infuriated As Bulls Pour On the Points</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Knicks Become Infuriated as Bulls Pour On the Points</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just about every negative emotion washed over the Knicks on Tuesday night. It started with frustration, which quickly gave way to humiliation and finally rage.</p>
        <p>They endured their worst loss of the season, a 98-69 rout by the Chicago Bulls at the United Center. It was worse than the 29-point margin would indicate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Eddy Curry planted on the bench for most of the evening, the Knicks, who once had modest playoff aspirations, moved to the brink of elimination Tuesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just about every negative emotion washed over the Knicks on Tuesday night. It started with frustration, which quickly gave way to humiliation and finally rage.</p>
        <p>They endured their worst loss of the season, a 98-69 rout by the Chicago Bulls at the United Center. It was worse than the 29-point margin would indicate.</p>
        <p>Eddy Curry, newly minted as the Knicks' franchise savior, played one of his worst games of the season, in his hometown and against the team that gave up on him. Isiah Thomas, who has boasted of Curry's growth this season, did not bother to play him for most of the second half.</p>
        <p>The loss pushed the Knicks (32-46) within an inch of elimination from the playoff race, although that has seemed a formality for some time. Amid the embarrassment, the Knicks snapped.</p>
        <p>Nate Robinson and Steve Francis walked toward the Chicago bench and yelled at the Bulls after the final buzzer, before Thomas pulled them away. There was a loud commotion in the hallway leading to the locker rooms, but the teams avoided a physical altercation.</p>
        <p>The Knicks were infuriated by the Bulls' late 3-point tries, by an alley-oop attempt for Tyrus Thomas in the final two minutes and by a full-court press early in the third quarter, when Chicago pushed the lead to 30 points.</p>
        <p>''As a veteran, I've been in the league long enough, and I know when people are trying to run the score up on you,'' Francis said. ''And I told their players that if I was in the game, it'd have been something different, if it was a threat or whatever. I'm a veteran, and I won't do that to nobody. And I don't expect nobody to try to do that to the younger players on my team.''</p>
        <p>In the final minutes, the crowd cheered wildly for a final Bulls basket, which would have pushed the score to 100 and provided free Big Macs for everyone in attendance. The playoff-bound Bulls (47-32) were apparently trying to appease them.</p>
        <p>''I think they definitely were trying to rub it in,'' said Curry, who had 4 points and 7 rebounds in 22 minutes, among his worst performances this season. ''But we'll see them next year. It is what it is. The whole crowd wanted 100 points.''</p>
        <p>A perceived lack of respect has driven the Knicks for much of the season, and at times it has pushed them to extremes. It played a role as well in their December melee with the Denver Nuggets, an incident that also had Robinson at its center.</p>
        <p>While his players gave an honest appraisal of their emotions, Isiah Thomas declined to acknowledge any issue.</p>
        <p>''I thought our guys were just trying to compete and Nate was just trying to compete and he got a little excited,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Knicks were playing their fourth game in five nights and are showing signs of wear without their injured players, Stephon Marbury, Jamal Crawford, David Lee and Quentin Richardson.</p>
        <p>It was a bad night to be Curry -- the center of a 2005 blockbuster trade between these clubs -- or Thomas, who orchestrated that trade. The Bulls, the No. 2 team in the Eastern Conference, continued their charge toward the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The Knicks, who once had modest playoff aspirations, would be eliminated from the playoff chase with their next loss or the next victory by the Orlando Magic (36-41). The moment could come as early as Wednesday night, when the Magic plays in Detroit.</p>
        <p>That only makes Tuesday's result more satisfying for the Bulls. As the final piece of the Curry trade, Chicago has the right to swap first-round draft picks this June. The deeper the Knicks fall in the standings, the higher the pick becomes -- and the greater the chance that the Bulls could win the No. 1 pick in the lottery.</p>
        <p>Coach Scott Skiles, who soured on Curry and has frequently derided him, had harsh words for the Knicks after hearing of their complaints. The Bulls scored only 20 points in the fourth quarter. The margin, which was as high as 35 points, was mostly due to the Knicks' inability to score.</p>
        <p>''I have never been accused of running up the score,'' Skiles said before turning acerbic. ''From everything I hear, the Knicks are on the verge of becoming a great team. So they are probably a team we will be playing over and over again in the years to come.''</p>
        <p>Just three nights earlier, Curry had a career-best 43 points. But against the Bulls, he picked up two quick offensive fouls and never found a rhythm. He had a layup attempt blocked by Tyrus Thomas, whom the Bulls acquired in last year's draft using the Knicks' first-round pick.</p>
        <p>Before the game, Skiles played down Curry's breakout season. Curry entered the game averaging career highs in points (19.6) and rebounds (7.1).</p>
        <p>''I don't want to minimize Eddy's year, but I mean, he's averaging roughly 3 more points a game than he did here,'' Skiles said. ''Eddy's having a very good year, but it seems like he's being put on a pedestal awful quickly here.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>David Lee did not travel with the team, and it appears his season is over. ''He's just not healthy enough to play right now,'' Isiah Thomas said. ''Our future's really bright, and we definitely don't want to damage your future by doing something in the present right now that could end up hurting you down the road.'' ... Renaldo Balkman (stomach virus) also did not travel with the team. ... Steve Francis expressed regret for being ejected from Monday night's loss to Detroit. The Knicks were still in the game when Francis received two technical fouls for berating the referee Steve Javie. ''It was dumb,'' Francis said.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
