<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rutgers Women Send Imus an Angry Message</title>
    <meta content="11rutgers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/sports/ncaabasketball/11rutgers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stringer, C Vivian</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Vaughn, Kia</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Carson, Essence</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E0DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rutgers Women Send Imus an Angry Message</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rutgers Women Send Imus an Angry Message</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>PISCATAWAY, N.J. April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It had all the appearances of a pep rally: Louis Brown Athletic Center was jammed with spectators and reporters Tuesday morning as the Rutgers women's basketball team strode onto the noisy court behind the university's president, the athletic director, their coach and her assistants.</p>
        <p>But instead of celebrating a season that had taken them to the N.C.A.A. championship game, the players were defending their honor after Don Imus, the radio talk show host, had derided them as ''nappy-headed hos'' on the air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an emotional news conference, Rutgers’ players spoke about their hurt and anger after Don Imus, the radio talk show host, derided them as “nappy-headed hos.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It had all the appearances of a pep rally: Louis Brown Athletic Center was jammed with spectators and reporters Tuesday morning as the Rutgers women's basketball team strode onto the noisy court behind the university's president, the athletic director, their coach and her assistants.</p>
        <p>But instead of celebrating a season that had taken them to the N.C.A.A. championship game, the players were defending their honor after Don Imus, the radio talk show host, had derided them as ''nappy-headed hos'' on the air.</p>
        <p>In an emotional news conference, the players and their coach, C. Vivian Stringer, spoke about their hurt, anger and wounded pride. Imus has offered repeated public apologies since making the remark last week. The team agreed to meet with him, but declined to specify when.</p>
        <p>''Who amongst you could have heard these comments and not be upset?'' Stringer said in a 15-minute speech that was met with ''amens'' and ''oh, yeses'' from the audience.</p>
        <p>Stringer, like 8 of her 10 players, is black. She told of how, when she was 16, she was at first embarrassed by the attention of being recognized by her school board for having good grades and for being the first minority cheerleader at her high school. Tears welled in her eyes as she talked about personal traumas, including her daughter's meningitis and her husband's death after a heart attack, both of which struck as she took previous teams to the Final Four.</p>
        <p>''For 25 years, I wanted to come to a championship game happy, and now this,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In what seemed at times to be more revival meeting than news conference, Richard L. McCormick, the Rutgers president, and Robert E. Mulcahy III, the athletic director, took turns talking about Imus. Then two players spoke.</p>
        <p>''Our moment here was taken away, our moment to celebrate our success,'' said Heather Zurich, a sophomore forward and one of the white players on the team. She added, referring to her teammates Matee Ajavon and Kia Vaughn, ''What hurts most about this situation is that Mr. Imus doesn't know one of us personally -- that Matee is the funniest person you will ever meet, and Kia is the best big sister you never had but always wanted.''</p>
        <p>Essence Carson, a junior and the team captain whom Mulcahy introduced as ''a straight-A student, who could walk out of here and play 'Moonlight Sonata' on the piano without looking at the notes,'' said that it was a close call about whether to ignore Imus or to respond publicly.</p>
        <p>''At first we thought to let it slide, but when we read the transcript, we decided it was unacceptable,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Stringer noted that the team had a combined B-plus grade point average. ''Let me put a human face on this,'' she said. ''These young ladies are valedictorians of their class, future doctors, musical prodigies and, yes, even Girl Scouts. They are all young ladies of class. They are distinctive, articulate.''</p>
        <p>The night before the news conference, the team met with Gov. Jon S. Corzine of New Jersey, a former high school basketball player, who had attended the Final Four in Cleveland.</p>
        <p>''The Rutgers Scarlet Knights women's basketball team embodies all that is great about New Jersey: intelligence, toughness, tenacity, leadership and, most of all, class,'' Corzine said in a statement. ''What we must do now is address this situation as a community. We must start a dialogue that not only helps to heal the wounds that this type of hateful language renews, but also brings us to a better place as a society.''</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
