<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Bodies Are Found in a Town Where 'These Things Don't Happen'</title>
    <meta content="11barrel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/nyregion/11barrel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EEDF123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Bodies Are Found in a Town Where 'These Things Don't Happen'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Bodies Are Found in a Town Where ‘These Things Don’t Happen’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STABA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Staba, David</byline>
      <dateline>COLDEN, N.Y., April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Geraldine Jackson was getting ready to have her family, including two great-grandchildren she doted on, over for Christmas dinner at her house in the hills outside Buffalo when it burned down on the morning of Dec. 22.</p>
        <p>Firefighters searched the house, then rescuers combed the surrounding fields and forests, but Mrs. Jackson, an 87-year-old former antiques dealer who lived alone, was not there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The town of Colden, N.Y., was stunned after police found the badly decomposed bodies of two women stuffed into sealed barrels in a small barn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Geraldine Jackson was getting ready to have her family, including two great-grandchildren she doted on, over for Christmas dinner at her house in the hills outside Buffalo when it burned down on the morning of Dec. 22.</p>
        <p>Firefighters searched the house, then rescuers combed the surrounding fields and forests, but Mrs. Jackson, an 87-year-old former antiques dealer who lived alone, was not there.</p>
        <p>''We were all hoping she was sick and had gone to the doctor or something when the fire broke out,'' said Ted Gavin, a neighbor of 35 years. A day earlier, he had gone grocery shopping for Mrs. Jackson, a petite woman who he said liked to have a beer and a sandwich at the local bar.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Jackson never returned.</p>
        <p>About 20 miles away in Marilla, on Jan. 14, Nancy Phelps left her weekly Bible study group. Three days later, her family reported her missing, but all the police turned up was a tooth outside the house where Mrs. Phelps, 69, lived by herself.</p>
        <p>With the spring thaw came an anonymous tip. As the authorities searched the area around Mrs. Jackson's home on March 31, they found the badly decomposed bodies of both women stuffed into sealed barrels in a small barn on property owned by the town justice. Autopsies showed that Mrs. Jackson had died of asphyxiation, and Mrs. Phelps from a blow to the head.</p>
        <p>The discovery, less than a half-mile from the charred shell of Mrs. Jackson's house, stunned residents of this crossroads town of about 3,300.</p>
        <p>''It's just a nice rural town where these things don't happen,'' said Alice M. Wangelin, the town clerk, who has lived in Colden for 53 of her 66 years. ''When I leave for work, my husband always says, 'Take your cellphone.' I say: 'What for? I know everybody along the route. If I have a problem, I'll just walk to the next place.' ''</p>
        <p>But 82-year-old John Holnbeck, who was renewing his fishing license at the one-story brick town hall here one recent afternoon, said he had noticed a difference. ''Years ago, everybody knew everybody,'' he said. ''But times have changed now.'' People just do not visit their neighbors anymore, he said.</p>
        <p>For now, a relative newcomer to Colden, Robert J. Henchen, 42, a parolee who served 18 years in prison for severely beating an elderly man during a robbery, is the only suspect in the killings, according to Frank Clark, the Erie County district attorney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Henchen, who lives across the street from the barn where the bodies were found and where he stored a tractor, was arrested and held for violating his parole a day after Mrs. Phelps was reported missing. Since then, he has been indicted on suspicion of breaking into the home of an elderly woman in Orchard Park, about nine miles away.</p>
        <p>Mr. Henchen's lawyer, John Molloy, and Mr. Clark said they expect a grand jury to consider murder charges against Mr. Henchen, perhaps as soon as this week.</p>
        <p>Erie County Sheriff Timothy Howard said the first break in the case came after Mrs. Phelps was reported missing, and the police began questioning her relatives in the area. ''Our investigators noted that she had family across the street from Mrs. Jackson,'' Sheriff Howard said. ''That was kind of, 'Whoa, wait a minute. Let's get down there and look.' ''</p>
        <p>As it turns out, Mr. Henchen -- who his lawyer says has a history of mental illness -- married Mrs. Phelps's niece Darlene Blancks soon after his release about two years ago, and moved into her home, across the road and about a half-mile from Mrs. Jackson's.</p>
        <p>The police found a purse belonging to Mrs. Phelps on the Henchen property Jan. 18, the sheriff said, adding that as they were searching, Mr. Henchen returned home after his court-mandated curfew. When he saw the police, he tried to flee, Sheriff Howard said.</p>
        <p>Now residents are questioning how the bodies could have gone undiscovered across the road from Mr. Henchen's home for more than two months after he became a suspect, and why the justice, Carolyn Siegel, did not tell the police that he had access to her barn.</p>
        <p>Ms. Siegel, a lawyer who was elected town justice in 2004, has declined to be interviewed. Her family released a statement to a local television station saying that she thought the police knew that Mr. Henchen had been in her barn and that they had repeatedly searched it after Mrs. Jackson's disappearance.</p>
        <p>''Carolyn Siegel did all she could to assist law enforcement in their search for Mrs. Jackson and Mrs. Phelps, and she is consumed with grief over the fact that their bodies were not discovered sooner,'' the statement read. ''She will forever live with the horrible trauma of knowing that the person who callously took the lives of those two ladies decided to dispose of their bodies on her property, and her family home will never be the same for her again.''</p>
        <p>Maj. Christopher Cummings of the state police said troopers conducted a ''visual inspection'' of the barn in late December to make sure Mrs. Jackson had not sought shelter there after fleeing her burning house.</p>
        <p>''It was a different kind of search, where you were looking for Mrs. Jackson to be in an open area and not concealed,'' Major Cummings said.</p>
        <p>Larisa Scott, a friend of the Henchens who owns a general store in town, said the last time she saw the couple was several weeks before Mrs. Jackson's disappearance. ''They stopped in and he was acting strange,'' she said, ''and Darlene said his doctor had changed his medication and this was not right for him.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Jackson's grandson said that while the discovery of the women's bodies provided some closure, it added to the horror -- particularly for his 7-year-old daughter.</p>
        <p>''She knows her great-grandma's gone,'' said the grandson, Andrew Jackson. ''I try to keep the details from her, but kids at school say things like, 'I heard they found your grandma with no head.' What do you say to her?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
