<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Japanese All-Star Game And a Reunion at Fenway</title>
    <meta content="11redsox" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Japanese All-Star Game And a Reunion at Fenway</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Ichiro Suzuki took his position in center field for the Seattle Mariners on Tuesday at Fenway Park, he noticed an advertisement behind him. The sign featured a Dunkin' Donuts coffee cup with ''Welcome to Fenway'' written in Japanese. ''Just by looking at that,'' Suzuki said, ''I can tell it's something big.''</p>
        <p>The event that is big here, and bigger in Japan, is the first confrontation between Suzuki and Daisuke Matsuzaka, the dynamic pitcher for the Red Sox. When Matsuzaka makes his first start at Fenway on Wednesday night, he will throw his first pitch to Suzuki, who hails from Matsuzaka's former baseball home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Ichiro Suzuki took his position in center field for the Seattle Mariners on Tuesday at Fenway Park, he noticed an advertisement behind him. The sign featured a Dunkin' Donuts coffee cup with ''Welcome to Fenway'' written in Japanese. ''Just by looking at that,'' Suzuki said, ''I can tell it's something big.''</p>
        <p>The event that is big here, and bigger in Japan, is the first confrontation between Suzuki and Daisuke Matsuzaka, the dynamic pitcher for the Red Sox. When Matsuzaka makes his first start at Fenway on Wednesday night, he will throw his first pitch to Suzuki, who hails from Matsuzaka's former baseball home.</p>
        <p>So Matsuzaka, the latest Japanese icon, will oppose Suzuki, the Japanese icon whose relocation to the United States in 2001 helped influence Matsuzaka's decision to follow suit. If Roger Clemens signed with the Red Sox and pitched to Derek Jeter of the Yankees, it would nearly be as monumental an occurrence as Matsuzaka versus Suzuki.</p>
        <p>''This is the No. 1 sports topic in Japan now,'' said Gaku Tashiro, a writer for Sankei Sports, a daily newspaper. ''The Japanese people are very proud of them. They want to see the best Japanese pitcher against the best Japanese hitter on the major league stage.''</p>
        <p>The Red Sox said 350 members of the news media would cover the game, including 170 from Japanese organizations.</p>
        <p>''I just hope it's not going to be 400 people,'' Suzuki said through an interpreter.</p>
        <p>Once the Red Sox finished batting practice, Matsuzaka and Hideki Okajima, Boston's Japanese reliever, trotted in from right field and spoke with Suzuki by the third-base dugout. They shook hands and chatted for about 30 seconds. In the Japanese culture, it is customary for younger players to show respect for older players by initiating contact.</p>
        <p>After the Red Sox acquired Matsuzaka's negotiating rights, he said that the major leaguer he was most eager to face was Suzuki. They had some interesting confrontations when Suzuki was with the Orix Blue Wave and Matsuzaka pitched for the Seibu Lions in Japan's Pacific League. Suzuki hit 8 for 34 (.235) with one home run, one walk and four strikeouts against Matsuzaka in the two seasons they played in Japan.</p>
        <p>In their first meeting on May 16, 1999, the 18-year-old Matsuzaka struck out Suzuki three times and walked him once. Suzuki, who was in the midst of winning seven consecutive batting titles, told The Seattle Times that he struck out on a fastball in the first at-bat, then whiffed on two sliders that were unlike any other pitches he had ever seen.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't vanquished, but he clearly toyed with me,'' Suzuki told the newspaper.</p>
        <p>Even though Suzuki struck out only one more time in his next 31 at-bats against Matsuzaka, Matsuzaka's accomplishment was stunning. Since Suzuki has been with Seattle, he has struck out three times against the same pitcher twice: on Sept. 19, 2003 against Tim Hudson of the Oakland Athletics and, coincidentally, on Tuesday against Josh Beckett in a 14-3 Red Sox victory.</p>
        <p>Mariners catcher Kenji Johjima has more of a history against Matsuzaka in Japan; he was 32 for 118 (.271) with 5 homers and 11 runs batted in. While Matsuzaka was praised for pitching seven effective innings in a 4-1 victory over the Kansas City Royals last week, Johjima called that outing typical.</p>
        <p>If Johjima ever gave teammates a scouting report on Matsuzaka, he said through an interpreter, it would be brief.</p>
        <p>''The first thing that I think we all have to keep in mind is pray to God,'' Johjima said. ''That's what I do first.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
