<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>4 Serbs Guilty In Execution Of 6 Bosnians</title>
    <meta content="11serbia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/world/europe/11serbia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839490"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Srebrenica (Bosnia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wood, Nicholas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Srebrencia (Bosnia)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4D6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>4 Serbs Guilty In Execution Of 6 Bosnians</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">4 Serbs Guilty in Execution of 6 Bosnians</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wood, Nicholas</byline>
      <dateline>LJUBLJANA, Slovenia, April 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Serbian war-crime court convicts four former paramilitary officers in July 1995 killings of six Bosnia Muslims from Srebrenica; imposes sentences ranging from 5 years to 20 years; acquits fifth defendant; videotape that gave rise to trial was watershed within Serbia because it confronted Serbs with firsthand evidence of involvement of their security forces in Bosnian killings; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Serbian war-crimes court on Tuesday convicted four former paramilitary officers in the July 1995 killings of six Bosnian Muslims from Srebrenica, where thousands of Muslims were killed the same week.</p>
        <p>The ruling was the first time anyone had been convicted in a Serbian court for crimes that human rights groups linked to the killings in Srebrenica, in eastern Bosnia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four former paramilitary policemen were sentenced to up to 20 years in jail for the killings of six Bosnian Muslims from Srebrenica.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Serbian war-crimes court on Tuesday convicted four former paramilitary officers in the July 1995 killings of six Bosnian Muslims from Srebrenica, where thousands of Muslims were killed the same week.</p>
        <p>The ruling was the first time anyone had been convicted in a Serbian court for crimes that human rights groups linked to the killings in Srebrenica, in eastern Bosnia.</p>
        <p>The trial, which began in Belgrade 15 months ago, was prompted by a videotape that surfaced in June 2005 showing the Serb security men, part of a unit known as the Scorpions, taking six Muslim prisoners from a truck near the Bosnian village of Trnovo and executing them.</p>
        <p>The judge, Gordana Bozilovic-Petrovic, said the killers acted against defenseless civilians, ''showing off their power and showing no remorse.'' Yet she also said no evidence tied the killings to the massacre of nearly 8,000 Muslim men and boys in Srebrenica, 90 miles away.</p>
        <p>The judge imposed 20-year sentences on Slobodan Medic, the commander of the unit, and his assistant, Branislav Medic. The only defendant to plead guilty, Pera Petrasavic, was given a sentence of 13 years, and another, Aleksander Medic, received a five-year term. A fifth defendant, Aleksander Vukov, was acquitted.</p>
        <p>The video was first shown in June 2005 during the trial of the former Serbian president Slobodan Milosevic at the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia in The Hague. The tape was regarded as a watershed within Serbia because it confronted Serbs with firsthand evidence of the involvement of their security forces in Bosnian killings. Until then, most Serbs did not believe that the massacre had taken place.</p>
        <p>But a leading Serbian human rights lawyer and relatives of the dead said they were disappointed by the verdict and accused the judge of trying to distance the killings in Trnovo from the massacre.</p>
        <p>''Both from a moral and factual point of the view, this is not justice,'' said Natasa Kandic, the human rights lawyer who first uncovered the videotape and passed it on to prosecutors in The Hague.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kandic, the director of Serbia's leading human rights group, the Humanitarian Law Center, said that wherever Serbian security forces have faced charges of war crimes -- whether in Croatia, Bosnia or Kosovo -- the government has rebutted accusations that the state was in any way responsible.</p>
        <p>She said the judge seemed to follow the same line of thought. ''It's a pity,'' she said. ''The tape changed Serbian society, and the trial could have had a similar role.''</p>
        <p>The video shows the unit traveling from a part of Croatia under Serb control to central Bosnia. Before they leave, each member is blessed by a Serbian Orthodox priest.</p>
        <p>The tape shows what happened to the six captives. They are told to jump from the back of a truck with their hands cuffed behind them and forced to lie in a ditch while the Scorpions shout obscenities. The prisoners are led to a clearing where the four younger men are shot, one by one, in the back. The two older men are told to drag the bodies to a nearby building where they, too, are shot.</p>
        <p>The judge said it was not clear that the victims came from Srebrenica, dismissing prosecutors' contentions that they had been taken from there after it was seized by Serbian forces, and handed over to the Scorpions.</p>
        <p>The release of Mr. Vukov -- which the judge said was because of insufficient evidence -- and the sentence for Aleksander Medic also dismayed relatives of the victims. The two men were not shown shooting the prisoners but were seen with them shortly before they died. The convicted have a right to appeal within 30 days.</p>
        <p>The tribunal in The Hague has convicted members of the Serb security forces of taking part in the Srbebrenica massacre, but no other cases are before the Serbian court.</p>
        <p>Safeta Muhic was one of about 30 relatives of the victims to attend the verdict. Her brother, Safet Fejze, was 16 when he died; she said she only learned of his fate when the video was broadcast.</p>
        <p>Referring to Aleksander Medic's sentence, she said in a telephone interview, ''I can't understand how it's possible to release someone after just five years.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
