<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Motto Is: Try, Try Again</title>
    <meta content="11rest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/dining/reviews/11rest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070418T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">East Village (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E7D7153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Motto Is: Try, Try Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where the Motto Is: Try, Try Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Bruni</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT some point I began to brace for a hailstorm, and to wonder if the locusts would sweep in after that. The E.U. was plagued, on a scale that was almost biblical.</p>
        <p>Where to begin? Maybe with the liquor license, by which I mean the restaurant's unusually protracted struggle to get one. As the E.U. readied to open -- for the first time -- early last year, it confronted both an East Village community board in a killjoy mood and a State Liquor Authority in a withholding phase.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the E.U. , the East Village gastropub that was plagued with problems in its infancy, still has a few problems and some reliable virtues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT some point I began to brace for a hailstorm, and to wonder if the locusts would sweep in after that. The E.U. was plagued, on a scale that was almost biblical.</p>
        <p>Where to begin? Maybe with the liquor license, by which I mean the restaurant's unusually protracted struggle to get one. As the E.U. readied to open -- for the first time -- early last year, it confronted both an East Village community board in a killjoy mood and a State Liquor Authority in a withholding phase.</p>
        <p>So the restaurant tried to make a booze-less go of it, presenting its vision of an elevated gastropub with only two of those three syllables at its disposal. It closed less than two months later, having learned that the last syllable was sort of crucial.</p>
        <p>By then the first chef associated with the restaurant had already left, and certain patterns had been established. Chefs would come; chefs would go. The E.U. would spring forward; the E.U. would fall back. This instability persisted even after it got a license for wine and beer last September. So did the setbacks, including a burst pipe in its building that flooded the place during dinner service on a weekend night.</p>
        <p>It toweled itself off. Picked itself up. Got yet another head chef, Akhtar Nawab, a Craftbar alumnus who began in late January.</p>
        <p>And then, at last, its fortunes changed. From the kitchen came a very fine appetizer of grilled octopus, served with chickpeas and preserved lemon, and an even better entree of baked monkfish, the mild, meaty fish less a cynosure than a backdrop for the cockles, mussels, tomato, green peppers and saucisson sec, a French salami, around it.</p>
        <p>In the door came the revelers, enough on many nights to fill all 110 seats and make this restaurant feel like one of the hottest tickets in town. And the E.U., such a tortured comer, showed signs of being a real keeper.</p>
        <p>It still has problems. E.U. stands for European Union, and the putatively pan-European menu that Mr. Nawab has put together is eclectic not only in terms of its national influences but also in the quality of different dishes. The desserts could stand some inspiration and improvement.</p>
        <p>And depending on where you sit and how crowded the E.U. is, its atmosphere can be infectiously lively or insufferably chaotic. In a way that perhaps befits the restaurant's herky-jerky beginnings, you're taking a chance every time you walk in.</p>
        <p>But there are reliable virtues, starting with the restaurant's looks. Before the owners, Bob Giraldi and Jason Hennings, could have predicted their costly catalog of woes, they splurged on the design wizards at AvroKo -- a wise investment.</p>
        <p>Those conjurers of urban cool have used bricks that look centuries old, wood beams that don't look much newer, exposed wine storage areas and strategically placed rolls of butcher paper to give the E.U. a fashionably worn, disheveled look.</p>
        <p>They've carved a sizeable space into intimate neighborhoods: a raw bar up front, a main bar in back, some raised tables with high stools, other tables distributed throughout various passageways and nooks. And they've performed their usual magic with light, acing a dimness that never teeters into gloominess.</p>
        <p>The E.U. strikes a casual tone, evident in the form taken by its menu, which is made of butcher paper and doubles as your place mat. The various boxes and sections of type within this brown rectangle seem to advise a cobbled-together meal rather than a conventional progression of appetizer, entree and dessert, though that progression is an option as well.</p>
        <p>You can do oysters. Or cheeses, with varieties from Italy, France and Spain. Or a charcuterie plate, including prosciutto, which was terrific, and mortadella, disappointingly presented as thin slices rather than fat chunks. Or tapas: mushrooms, beets, olives and raw scallops with hearts of palm, olive oil, lemon and sea salt.</p>
        <p>Most of this fare is less labor-intensive than purchasing-intensive. The E.U. provides a case study of how a restaurant can stretch out its menu without taxing its kitchen.</p>
        <p>Not that the kitchen doesn't make an effort, and an often impressive one at that. Like the monkfish, wild striped bass was impeccably cooked, and it came with an enticing pistachio vinaigrette that reflected Mr. Nawab's frequently clever touches.</p>
        <p>By seasoning pork meatballs with cumin and fennel seed, frying them until their outsides are crunchy and saucing them with yogurt, he comes up with an appetizer plate that could almost be mistaken for unusually substantial, oddly juicy falafel. And seems, in the process, to look beyond Europe's boundaries.</p>
        <p>He also taps into America, bringing it and Europe together in a plump but otherwise unremarkable burger, which you can order in a style identified as Italian (pecorino on top) or English (Cheddar).</p>
        <p>Following the leads of such recent restaurants as Sascha (now closed) and the Waverly Inn (not yet, um, open), he concocts a chicken pot pie, which in this case is really a mash of chicken, root vegetables and béchamel under a clumsy, fragile multi-tiered lid of puff pastry that shatters and scatters at the touch of a fork.</p>
        <p>He's doing the in-vogue comfort foods of the urban gourmand: braised veal cheeks with a horseradish-spiked crème fraîche; roasted chicken and ''dumplings,'' which turn out to be ricotta and spinach malfatti good enough to be stars of their own; a big fat sweetbread with a Marsala sauce and, for a pubby touch, a bruschetta-style piece of toast below it.</p>
        <p>These dishes worked in solid, unspectacular fashions, but others proved disappointing. While I was delighted by bright green fava beans with lamb loin and shoulder, I would have sacrificed them for more tender meat. A sirloin special one night and a pork special on another were also unusually tough.</p>
        <p>A version of a linzer torte was drier than it should have been, and an inevitable clutch of beignets had a somewhat deflated look and taste.</p>
        <p>You'd be better off skipping sweets and sipping more wine, from a smart list that touches down in all the major winemaking countries of Europe, does a quick survey of regions and grapes and keeps the trip relatively affordable. There's not a bottle over $70. Most are under $50. And Italy, Czechoslovakia, Belgium, Ireland, Denmark and Sweden all contribute to an impressive range of beers.</p>
        <p>As a watering hole, the E.U. actually feels charmed, though I articulate that with my fingers crossed (a tough trick when you're typing), and in spite of my parting glance at the restaurant around midnight one busy, noisy night. I walked out as three grim-faced police officers walked in.</p>
        <p>Uh-oh.</p>
        <p>The E.U.  * [Rating: One Star]  235 East Fourth Street, East Village; (212) 254-2900. theeunyc.com</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Rathskeller meets gastropub in a smartly sectioned room whose brick walls, concrete floor and lighting fixtures make something new look chicly old.  SOUND LEVEL -- Extremely loud when crowded.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Raw scallops with heart of palm; artichoke and spinach salad; grilled octopus; meat balls with yogurt; baked monkfish; poached striped bass; chicken and dumplings; brussels sprouts with mortadella; hazelnut meringue with chocolate ganache.  WINE LIST -- A medium-length, relatively affordable jaunt through many of Europe's main wine-producing regions. The beers are equally pan-Continental.  PRICE RANGE -- Dinner tapas and appetizers, $4 to $13. Entrees, $13 to $24. Desserts, $8. Brunch dishes, $7 to $16.  HOURS -- Dinner from 6 to 11:15 p.m. Sunday through Thursday and to 12:15 a.m. Friday and Saturday. Brunch from 11 a.m to 4 p.m. on Saturday and Sundays.  RESERVATIONS -- For prime dinner times, call at least three days ahead.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Entrance and entire restaurant on street level; accessible restroom.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN -- Ratings range from zero to four stars and reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.  PAST REVIEWS from The Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics:</p>
        <p>nytimes.com/dining</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 18, 2007, Wednesday  A restaurant review last Wednesday of E.U., in the East Village, referred incorrectly to the beers served there. No beer from Denmark is available. The restaurant serves beer from the Czech Republic, not Czechoslovakia, which divided in 1993 to create the Czech Republic and Slovakia.</p>
        <p>The review also referred incorrectly to the main ingredient in a potpie. It is vegetables, not chicken.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 18, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A restaurant review last Wednesday of E.U., in the East Village, referred incorrectly to the beers served there. No beer from Denmark is available. The restaurant serves beer from the Czech Republic, not Czechoslovakia, which divided in 1993 to create the Czech Republic and Slovakia.</p>
        <p>The review also referred incorrectly to the main ingredient in a potpie. It is vegetables, not chicken.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
