<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Usual Flourish, Sharpe James Pulls Curtain on a Career and an Era in Newark</title>
    <meta content="11james" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/nyregion/11james.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">James, Sharpe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E2D6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1089" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Usual Flourish, Sharpe James Pulls Curtain on a Career and an Era in Newark</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Usual Flourish, Sharpe James Pulls Curtain on a Career and an Era in Newark</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''You notice that no one ever calls me Mr. Mayor,'' Sharpe James said with a sly smile on Tuesday, the day after he announced that he would not seek re-election to the State Senate and signaled an end to his 37 years in the contact sport known as politics. ''Everybody calls me Sharpe. If I was a political boss and ran a political machine like so many say I do, then they would all call me Mr. Mayor.''</p>
        <p>There, said the 71-year-old Mr. James, lies one of the secrets to his political longevity. It was his personality, his ebullience, that allowed him to serve a record five terms as mayor here. The other was that he, like so many of his supporters, grew up poor in Newark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sharpe James, a master of political longevity, is getting out of the game after 37 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''You notice that no one ever calls me Mr. Mayor,'' Sharpe James said with a sly smile on Tuesday, the day after he announced that he would not seek re-election to the State Senate and signaled an end to his 37 years in the contact sport known as politics. ''Everybody calls me Sharpe. If I was a political boss and ran a political machine like so many say I do, then they would all call me Mr. Mayor.''</p>
        <p>There, said the 71-year-old Mr. James, lies one of the secrets to his political longevity. It was his personality, his ebullience, that allowed him to serve a record five terms as mayor here. The other was that he, like so many of his supporters, grew up poor in Newark.</p>
        <p>Yes, political contributors paid homage, and coughed up donations, at his birthday bash every February. But, Mr. James said, he always gave them quite a show in return, arriving on skis over a bed of fake snow one year and in a rented Rolls-Royce another.</p>
        <p>''I know some of them were saluting the uniform and not the person,'' he said in an interview on Tuesday at Essex County Community College, where Mr. James was a physical education teacher and track coach before going into politics and where he is now director of the Urban Issues Institute. ''But they all knew that they would have fun. It would be a party.''</p>
        <p>Mr. James's announcement that he would relinquish the Senate seat that he has held since 1999 is arguably the end of an era in Newark politics.</p>
        <p>His many critics say Mr. James held onto power by rewarding his friends and punishing his rivals. And the United States attorney's office is investigating allegations that Mr. James's administration sold city land to a friend for cut-rate prices.</p>
        <p>Despite his denials that he sat at the head of a Democratic political machine, there are those who know about such things who disagree. Steve Adubato, the Democratic leader of the vote-rich North Ward for the past 40 years, called Mr. James a wheeling and dealing political boss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adubato said that Mr. James also was a cheerleader for Newark when the city had little to cheer about, but that he stayed in office too long.</p>
        <p>''In the end it became about him and his friends,'' Mr. Adubato said. ''He did a great service for the city in the beginning, but he should have left elected office more than two terms ago.''</p>
        <p>Mr. James's decision was hardly a surprise here. His real political power evaporated last year when he decided not to seek a sixth term as mayor and left the field to Cory Booker, who had pursued the job since 2002. Mr. James had held on to the Senate seat in a kind of political rear-guard action, still wielding the senatorial courtesy that gives legislators a veto over crucial state appointments in their areas.</p>
        <p>In recent months, however, the United States attorney for New Jersey, Christopher J. Christie, has been investigating city land sales during Mr. James's tenure and his use of city funds to pay for trips for himself, his bodyguards and his aides to Puerto Rico, Brazil, Martha's Vineyard and Detroit in his waning days as mayor. Since last fall, Mr. Christie's office also has been examining real estate transactions between the city and Tamika Riley, a friend of Mr. James's. From 2002 to 2005, Ms. Riley bought nine lots owned by the city for a total of $46,000 and resold them for $700,000.</p>
        <p>It is not the first time that federal prosecutors have investigated Mr. James, although he has never been charged with a crime. In 1995, the United States attorney's office looked into how Mr. James used donations to his charitable fund, the Sharpe James Civic Association. After a separate federal investigation in 1997, his chief of staff was convicted of taking kickbacks from insurance companies that were seeking business with the city.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Christie would not comment on any investigations that the federal prosecutor may have begun, but Mr. James conceded that records involving the trips and real estate sales have been subpoenaed.</p>
        <p>''I have nothing to hide,'' Mr. James said. ''They have every right to investigate me, because when you are in political office you live in a fishbowl. But I will say that many of the things they are looking at, such as the land sales and the travel, were the purview of the City Council and not the mayor.''</p>
        <p>Kenneth Gibson, who became the city's first black mayor in 1970 and who introduced Mr. James to Newark politics -- only to be challenged and displaced by him in 1986 -- said he did not think the most recent federal investigations had prompted Mr. James to leave politics.</p>
        <p>''I think Sharpe is feeling the changing of the guard, and it's something he can't stop,'' he said. Mr. Gibson also noted that Mayor Booker, Mr. Adubato and others had joined forces to support Teresa Ruiz, 32, who is challenging Mr. James this year in the 29th Legislative District, which takes in parts of Newark and all of neighboring Hillside.</p>
        <p>In the interview Mr. James, looking fit in jeans and a sweatshirt, insisted that he wanted to play tennis, spend time with his family and travel on his boat.</p>
        <p>He also said he had learned a lesson from the way his rival, Donald Tucker, a former Newark councilman at large and assemblyman who died in 2005 after a debilitating illness, ended his public life. Mr. James said that in 2004, when local Democratic officials gathered at a hotel here for a rally with the vice presidential nominee, John Edwards, Mr. Tucker showed up in a wheelchair and asked them to hoist him onstage to await the candidate's arrival.</p>
        <p>''We wound up waiting three hours, and Donald fell asleep in his wheelchair, and you knew he was in a lot of pain,'' Mr. James said. And there was a hint of bitterness as Mr. James recalled what he said was his casting by many as ''the old degenerate politician'' in the challenge he faced from Mr. Booker, a former Rhodes Scholar and a child of the integrated suburbs. But there was also some satisfaction as he recalled how he defeated Mr. Booker in 2002.</p>
        <p>It was all grist, he said, for an autobiography for which he is seeking a writer and publisher.</p>
        <p>''I touched so many lives,'' said Mr. James. ''I think a lot of people underestimated me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
