<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Look Out, Below! The High, Dry Intrepid</title>
    <meta content="11intrepid" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/nyregion/11intrepid.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aircraft Carriers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Intrepid Sea-Air-Space Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Look Out, Below! The High, Dry Intrepid</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Look Out, Below! Intrepid Plots a Course High and Dry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The aircraft carrier Intrepid came close yesterday to displaying more of its normally submerged bottom than had been glimpsed in a generation. But for the full picture, observers will have to wait a little longer.</p>
        <p>As a prelude to its first stay out of water in 30 years, the Intrepid, which has served as a military museum at the edge of Manhattan, nestled into a dry dock in Bayonne, N.J., late in the morning. Before sunset, much of the water the ship floated in on had been drained away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The aircraft carrier Intrepid, which is set for renovations, was taken to a dry dock in New Jersey on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The aircraft carrier Intrepid came close yesterday to displaying more of its normally submerged bottom than had been glimpsed in a generation. But for the full picture, observers will have to wait a little longer.</p>
        <p>As a prelude to its first stay out of water in 30 years, the Intrepid, which has served as a military museum at the edge of Manhattan, nestled into a dry dock in Bayonne, N.J., late in the morning. Before sunset, much of the water the ship floated in on had been drained away.</p>
        <p>By this afternoon, the 64-year-old warship is expected to be high and dry, resting upon 212 wood-capped concrete blocks with its entire hull exposed for the first time since 1977. After that, repair crews will get to work power-washing the deck, patching the hull and coating the ship with 6,500 gallons of gray paint.</p>
        <p>The overhaul is expected to last about 10 weeks and cost about $5 million. It is one stage of a project with a total price of about $60 million in federal, state and city funds.</p>
        <p>After the ship leaves the dry dock, it will be towed to Staten Island for renovation of its interior spaces and the installation of new exhibits. It is scheduled to return to the West Side of Midtown in the fall of 2008 and reopen as the Intrepid Sea, Air and Space Museum. While it is away from its longtime home at Pier 86, the pier will be replaced.</p>
        <p>A team of tugboats dragged the Intrepid away from Pier 86 in early December, a month after the first try to move the ship ended when its propellers stuck in the Hudson River mud. Since then, it has been moored at a cruise-ship dock in Bayonne.</p>
        <p>The same team of tugs that hauled the Intrepid to Bayonne pulled and pushed it to dry dock yesterday -- this time with no interruptions.</p>
        <p>''As of now, everything's gone perfectly,'' Matt Woods, the Intrepid's vice president for operations, said in the afternoon. ''The difficult part is still yet to come.''</p>
        <p>He was referring to the painstaking process of bringing the 41,000-ton ship to rest on the blocks arrayed on the floor of the dock. As he spoke, the blocks, about seven feet high, were still submerged in the dock, which is like a concrete bathtub that can hold 13 million gallons.</p>
        <p>After the tugs delivered the Intrepid to the front of the dock, four handlers operating a 20-ton electric winch pulled the ship slowly in with a four-inch-thick rope. About two dozen other handlers guided the bow with three lines along each side.</p>
        <p>When all 912 feet of the Intrepid were inside, two tugs pushed a floating steel gate to the open end of the dock. The gate was filled with water and sunk to seal off the dock. Electric pumps then began sucking the water back into New York Harbor, bringing the Intrepid to the brink of revealing its hull to prying eyes for the first time in a generation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
