<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don Imus, Suspended, Still Talking</title>
    <meta content="11watc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE TV WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1D7153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don Imus, Suspended, Still Talking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Don Imus was suspended. But it looked as though NBC had suspended the suspension. This scandal-harried radio host and MSNBC star was free to appear on ''Today'' yesterday and explain himself again and again: His interview with Matt Lauer and his debate with the Rev. Al Sharpton, their second, were shown simultaneously on the MSNBC show ''Imus in the Morning.''</p>
        <p>The Rutgers University basketball players, fresh from a Rocky-like rise to the N.C.A.A. women's championship game, held a news conference to explain that the slur-heard-round-the-world robbed them of their ''moment.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Don Imus was suspended. But it looked as though NBC had suspended the suspension. This scandal-harried radio host and MSNBC star was free to appear on ''Today'' yesterday and explain himself again and again: His interview with Matt Lauer and his debate with the Rev. Al Sharpton, their second, were shown simultaneously on the MSNBC show ''Imus in the Morning.''</p>
        <p>The Rutgers University basketball players, fresh from a Rocky-like rise to the N.C.A.A. women's championship game, held a news conference to explain that the slur-heard-round-the-world robbed them of their ''moment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Imus's moment keeps going into overtime.</p>
        <p>NBC said Mr. Imus's two-week timeout would begin next Monday to allow Mr. Imus to hold a call-in pledge drive for several of his charities for sick children. The radiothon begins on Thursday, leaving Mr. Imus more time to lobby to keep his job -- and receive testimonials from longtime guests like the Newsweek columnist Howard Fineman and comrades in political incorrectitude like the comedian Bill Maher.</p>
        <p>The network had time to showcase its disgraced star and wring every last drop of attention from the latest ado about verbal insensitivity.</p>
        <p>Hypocrisy aside, the network's decision to delay Mr. Imus's punishment was useful. There are no laws to adjudicate racial harmony; morning television is the forum in which grievances are aired and sympathies are marshaled. Politicians weighed in (Rudolph W. Giuliani supports Mr. Imus; Senator Barack Obama does not), but television, or more specifically advertising, is the arbiter.) The hosts of ''Today'' in particular serve as America's test family, one that reflects many of the veiled tensions about race that exist throughout American society.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lauer, reclaiming the role of father figure after Katie Couric left for CBS, was at the top of his game as he even-handedly quizzed both Mr. Imus and Mr. Sharpton about their positions. Meredith Vieira, who positions herself as a stay-in-the-studio mom, was assigned the task of interviewing the Rev. Jesse Jackson, and was not nearly so agile or forceful as her co-host. She gingerly raised Mr. Jackson's infamous description of New York City as ''Hymietown,'' in the 1984 presidential race but avoided following up on Mr. Jackson's evasive answer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson said the Imus incident should be used to desegregate the media, complaining that MSNBC and CNBC have no African-American anchors. Ms. Vieira was silent, apparently forgetting that the parent network's stars include Lester Holt and Al Roker, the weatherman on ''Today.'' Mr. Roker, who is usually cast as the fun uncle, all sunshine and cooking demonstrations, was not part of the discussion on the air about Mr. Imus. But he is the only African-American host on ''Today,'' and he made his feelings known on the ''Today'' show blog.</p>
        <p>''What he said was vile and disgusting,'' Mr. Roker wrote about Mr. Imus, whom he urged to resign. ''A two-week suspension doesn't cut it. It is, at best, a slap on the wrist. A vacation. Nothing.''</p>
        <p>In this polite but sometimes strained community, Mr. Imus is the cranky, aging neighbor who can be relied upon to shovel snow off the sidewalk but occasionally blurts out words so offensive and insensitive that it makes everyone regret inviting him to the block party.</p>
        <p>He tried to explain his remark as a momentary slip, describing himself as a ''good person who said a bad thing.'' But there is a deeper dichotomy behind his disgrace: Mr. Imus wants to be both a shock jock and Charlie Rose, and the two roles inevitably collide. He is a radio star whose early popularity rested on sophomoric and outrageous humor. But Mr. Imus also staked his claim to gravitas, inviting journalists and politicians on his show and discussing --with considerable skill -- news and political affairs.</p>
        <p>He told Mr. Lauer that his racist remark about the Rutgers players came out in a comic context. ''I'm not a newsman,'' he said rather testily from his radio talk-show desk. ''This is not 'Meet the Press.' '' Actually, it is: ''Imus in the Morning'' is the place where fans who don't watch Tim Russert's talk show get a chance to hobnob with writers for The New York Times, NBC correspondents and Newsweek columnists.</p>
        <p>Shock jocks are aptly named: They fulfill the fans' expectation of verbal transgression first by saying the kinds of disgusting things that are forbidden almost anywhere else and then by laughing off critics and scolds. Mr. Imus's many acts of contrition are both not enough and too much: by admitting he was wrong, he surrenders any claim to the shock jock's dispensation. And the penalty for ordinary public figures is usually stiffer than a two-week suspension.</p>
        <p>THE TV WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
