<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Today in the N.H.L., Nothing Rolls Off the Ducks' Backs</title>
    <meta content="11ducks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/sports/hockey/11ducks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Anaheim Ducks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Minnesota Wild</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Anaheim Mighty Ducks</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Today in the N.H.L., Nothing Rolls Off the Ducks' Backs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anaheim Has Gone From Warm and Fuzzy to Fiery and Nasty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jenkins, Lee</byline>
      <dateline>ANAHEIM, Calif., April 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Anaheim Ducks used to have an animated Tinkerbell that fluttered across the scoreboard and sprinkled pixie dust onto pictures of players' heads.</p>
        <p>Tinkerbell cannot possibly recognize her team anymore. The Ducks have essentially traded pixie dust on the head for punches to the face.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ducks won the Pacific Division this season for the first time, and as they prepare to open the playoffs Wednesday night against Minnesota, they are giving most of the credit to their knuckles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Anaheim Ducks used to have an animated Tinkerbell that fluttered across the scoreboard and sprinkled pixie dust onto pictures of players' heads.</p>
        <p>Tinkerbell cannot possibly recognize her team anymore. The Ducks have essentially traded pixie dust on the head for punches to the face.</p>
        <p>''We fight,'' Anaheim General Manager Brian Burke said. ''It's what we do. We put a premium on it.''</p>
        <p>Burke may not sound politically correct, but he is refreshingly honest. While the National Hockey League has restricted contact and condemned violence, the Ducks have proved that fighting still works -- both as a promotional tool and a strategic technique.</p>
        <p>The Ducks won the Pacific Division this season for the first time, and as they prepare to open the Stanley Cup playoffs Wednesday night against Minnesota, they are giving most of the credit to their knuckles.</p>
        <p>They do not apologize for their 1,457 penalty minutes, which led the N.H.L. Nor do they apologize for their 71 fighting majors, 24 more than any other team. As usual, they defend themselves with both fists raised.</p>
        <p>''The night before you play our team, it's a little nerve-racking,'' Anaheim forward Brad May said. ''You sleep with the lights on.''</p>
        <p>It is still hard to be intimidated by a franchise called the Ducks, especially since they were named after a fuzzy Disney movie. But look around the Honda Center -- formerly known as the Pond -- and you may find a few scattered teeth.</p>
        <p>The Ducks were founded in 1993, not as a fight club, but as a marketing arm for the Walt Disney Company and a source of family entertainment in Orange County. If they happened to win a few hockey games along the way, it was almost a bonus.</p>
        <p>Then Disney sold the team two years ago to Henry and Susan Samueli, an Orange County couple. With input from fans, the Ducks junked their purple-and-teal uniforms for black and gold. They traded their duck-billed logo for a bold script.</p>
        <p>After spending a decade as the butt of jokes, the Ducks started to retaliate. Hockey in Orange County became as serious as a stiff-arm.</p>
        <p>''Other players come in now and look at our lineup and you know what they're thinking,'' forward Shawn Thornton said. ''Let's keep it quiet and get out of here.''</p>
        <p>The team is no longer named the Mighty Ducks, perhaps because they do not need to convince anyone of their might. Anaheim demonstrates its muscle the old-fashioned way.</p>
        <p>By dropping their gloves at the drop of a helmet, enforcers explain that they are protecting star players, allowing them to skate without fear. The Ducks' top scorers, Teemu Selanne and Andy McDonald, responded this season with a combined 75 goals.</p>
        <p>The last time Anaheim made the Stanley Cup finals, in 2003, McDonald had to sit out because of post-concussion syndrome and the Ducks lost to the Devils. When the Chicago Blackhawks hammered McDonald during a game this season, three Anaheim players took turns rushing to his defense.</p>
        <p>''This way, you don't get abused on the ice,'' McDonald said. ''You know that you've got 22 guys waiting to stand up for you. It's a good set-up for someone like me.''</p>
        <p>McDonald is sometimes overshadowed by his bodyguards. Anaheim forward George Parros racked up 18 fighting majors this season, the most in the N.H.L., and he grew a bushy black mustache, the envy of enforcers everywhere.</p>
        <p>The 'stache, as Parros calls it, has become so fashionable in Orange County that fans tape black whiskers to their upper lips before games. Parros, who graduated from Princeton with a major in economics, can only imagine the marketing possibilities.</p>
        <p>''People are always calling me a meathead, a dummy, telling me I'm too stupid to be a real player,'' Parros said. ''I guess they don't know where I went to college.''</p>
        <p>Parros seems as unlikely a fighter as Burke does a fighting advocate. Burke, a graduate of Harvard Law School, used to be the N.H.L.'s dean of discipline. But he was also general manager of Vancouver when Todd Bertuzzi played for the Canucks and punched Colorado's Steven Moore from behind and slammed him to the ice in 2004.</p>
        <p>Moore fractured three vertebrae in his neck, but Burke stood by his player. Since then, many executives have tried to distance themselves from fighting. Burke has cast himself as the voice of the pugilist. He stands out only in his candor.</p>
        <p>''The people who are in the game -- the players, coaches, fans -- they all want fighting,'' Burke said. ''The debate is always started by outsiders. I'm sick of it.''</p>
        <p>Burke has done his best to keep tough guys employed. While many teams in the salary-cap era play without a heavyweight, opting for skill over strength, the Ducks have four legitimate enforcers on their roster.</p>
        <p>Those four bruisers -- May, Parros, Thornton and Travis Moen -- are not exactly Philadelphia's Broad Street Bullies of the 1970s. But in the modern N.H.L., where fighting has been on the decline, they are about as rugged as it gets.</p>
        <p>''Every rose has thorns,'' May said. ''We're the thorns.''</p>
        <p>Sitting in their dressing room, the Ducks are as likely to be talking about right hooks as wrist shots. They monitor the Web site hockeyfights.com, which features penalty statistics that the N.H.L. does not always publish. Parros and Thornton take boxing lessons in the summer to hone their craft.</p>
        <p>''If I didn't learn how to do this, I probably would have been sent home a long time ago,'' Thornton said. ''Even now, if I were on another team, I don't know that I'd be in the N.H.L.''</p>
        <p>The Ducks insist that they are not trying to reverse the trend against fighting. They are only trying to win their first Stanley Cup, regardless of the collateral damage.</p>
        <p>In the playoffs, fights are rare. Teams are careful not to commit penalties and give up unnecessary power plays. One of Anaheim's greatest strengths could be neutralized.</p>
        <p>Then again, the Ducks went all the way to the Western Conference finals last season, and they did not exactly leave peacefully.</p>
        <p>''We fought in the first round, the second round and the third round,'' Burke said. ''And if we got to the finals, we would have fought there, too.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
