<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strange Racetrack Critters And the Horses They Watch</title>
    <meta content="11grim" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/books/11grim.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Churchill Downs Incorporated</org>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Not by a Long Shot: A Season at a Hard-Luck Horse Track (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEED8153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strange Racetrack Critters And the Horses They Watch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Strange Racetrack Critters and the Horses They Watch</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not by a Long Shot  A Season at a Hard-Luck Horse Track  By T. D. Thornton  356 pages. Public Affairs. $26.</p>
        <p>In a few short weeks the best 3-year-old horses in the United States will line up at the starting gate for the Kentucky Derby. Elsewhere, on that same day, thousands of horses at tracks across the country will also race, a lot more slowly and for a lot less money. Their drama is the subject of ''Not by a Long Shot,'' T. D. Thornton's chronicle of a sad season at Suffolk Downs, better known to its patrons as ''Sufferin' Downs.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>T. D. Thornton manages to communicate the weird allure of horse racing, even at a track like “Sufferin’ Downs,” which is a long way from Churchill Downs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not by a Long Shot  A Season at a Hard-Luck Horse Track  By T. D. Thornton  356 pages. Public Affairs. $26.</p>
        <p>In a few short weeks the best 3-year-old horses in the United States will line up at the starting gate for the Kentucky Derby. Elsewhere, on that same day, thousands of horses at tracks across the country will also race, a lot more slowly and for a lot less money. Their drama is the subject of ''Not by a Long Shot,'' T. D. Thornton's chronicle of a sad season at Suffolk Downs, better known to its patrons as ''Sufferin' Downs.''</p>
        <p>At Suffolk, in East Boston, many of the horses race on sore, crooked legs. Some are older has-beens, grinding out a few more victories at the end of long careers. Others are young but talentless. In winter jockeys brave swirling snow, biting wind and temperatures so cold that their frozen fingers cannot even feel the reins. Flailing hooves throw up frozen clods of earth. Jokingly referred to as ''death cookies,'' they hit riders in the face, splitting their lips and leaving their foreheads maps of contusions.</p>
        <p>The purse money is pitiful. Mr. Thornton, a former publicity director for Suffolk Downs, once saw a strangely familiar figure sorting through piles of discarded betting slips on the floor of the grandstand in the hope of finding a winning ticket. It was Ramiro Herrera, a jockey. When Mr. Herrera wins two races one afternoon, thereby doubling his season tally, it brings his total earnings to $20,000.</p>
        <p>Such is the sport of kings at the track that Mr. Thornton, a onetime racing writer, calls, variously, ''the East Boston oval,'' ''the gritty East Boston oval,'' ''the embattled East Boston oval'' or, for short, ''the Eastie oval.'' It is not a pretty sight, yet Mr. Thornton, in his rueful account of the 2000 racing season, manages to communicate the weird allure of horse racing, even at the lower levels. Struggling trainers, low-paid backstretch workers, degenerate gamblers and deluded owners all belong to the same mysterious cult, kept alive by the faintest glimmerings of sickly hope.</p>
        <p>It was not always thus. In 1935, when Suffolk Downs opened, horse racing was hugely popular. Before casino gambling and state lotteries undermined racing, crowds of 30,000 or 40,000 routinely turned out on the weekends, eager to place bets. Their dollars supported high-quality racing, and in its heyday Suffolk attracted marquee names, like Seabiscuit and Whirlaway.</p>
        <p>That was a long time ago. Today only a few thousand die-hard gamblers show up on an average day at Suffolk. The grandstand and clubhouse, nearly empty, have deteriorated. In an annual ritual, bettors steal the spring floral displays as soon as they are planted. The ambience, to put it mildly, is less than appealing, the clientele dodgy.</p>
        <p>Legends, a bar on the track's second floor, attracts two classes of customers, Mr. Thornton writes, ''scary-looking regulars who are, in fact, totally harmless, and another subset of souls who are, without a doubt, truly troubled.'' Security guards steer clear of the men's room, crowded with reefer-smoking Rastafarians.</p>
        <p>''Passing through during late-night simulcast hours,'' Mr. Thornton writes, ''one is as likely to encounter some skanky couple making out in a lonely, darkened corner of the bar as a paunchy drunk passed out over a table of losing tickets.'' So much for the sport of kings.</p>
        <p>There are dozens of Suffolks all over the country, and ''Not by a Long Shot'' gives a painfully accurate view of their struggles to stay afloat. At the same time Suffolk has its own idiosyncrasies, some charming, many not. Over the years it has been embroiled in race-fixing scandals, for example. This is no longer a problem. The betting pools are now so small that fixing a race is no longer worth the trouble, another sign of racing's decline.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thornton cannot quite decide whether he wants to present a diary made up of random observations or tell a story with fully developed characters. He tries to do both, with mixed results. A few personalities begin to emerge from the swirl of racetrack activity, notably Rudy Baez, a top jockey who suffers a paralyzing injury during a race; Michael Gill, a brash, Steinbrenneresque owner who hires and fires trainers at the drop of a hat; and Patty Meadow, a Harvard-educated doctor turned trainer who likes to give her horses esoteric names like Ybbs and Qom.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thornton never does enough with this promising human material, however, and he makes a bad mistake in devoting a hefty portion of the book to the planning and running of the Massachusetts Handicap. Yes, the Mass Cap is (or was, having since been dropped from the track's schedule) Suffolk Downs's premier race, but seven years after the event, it is a reheated soufflé.</p>
        <p>The grim pleasures of Mr. Thornton's book lie in the details of the daily racetrack routine, and the oddities of life at the gritty East Boston oval. When an unidentified carcass appears on the track, it inspires a furious round of betting in the press room. ''I'm offering 100 to 1 on it being a mink,'' an impromptu bookmaker says. ''You also get to keep the pelt if it is.'' The animal turns out to be a muskrat (10 to 1 odds).</p>
        <p>Best of all are the races. Although he has an unfortunate tendency to use the word ''steed,'' Mr. Thornton describes horse races with great flair, even when they involve no-hopers like Lonicut, an ancient 10-year-old looking for his second lifetime win after 34 races. This is racing too. They can't all make it to Churchill Downs in May.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
