<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Stella, No Stanley, but a Streetcar Named Desire Visits</title>
    <meta content="11desire" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/nyregion/11desire.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Tennessee Williams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Times Square and 42nd Street (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Stella, No Stanley, but a Streetcar Named Desire Visits</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Stella, No Stanley, but a Streetcar Named Desire Visits New York City</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yesterday, on a street in Times Square, there were no azaleas or Spanish moss, no hot and fetid air, no maligned wives in slips or coarse husbands in torn T-shirts, no New Orleans of the imagination at all.</p>
        <p>But there was, on windy West 44th Street, parked outside the television studios of ''Good Morning America,'' a streetcar named Desire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A streetcar parked in Times Square is part of a promotion by a tourist board to get more people to visit New Orleans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yesterday, on a street in Times Square, there were no azaleas or Spanish moss, no hot and fetid air, no maligned wives in slips or coarse husbands in torn T-shirts, no New Orleans of the imagination at all.</p>
        <p>But there was, on windy West 44th Street, parked outside the television studios of ''Good Morning America,'' a streetcar named Desire.</p>
        <p>Almost the length of a modern subway car, it was a green beauty of polished wooden benches and clanging bells, designed to look circa 1948, the period of the Tennessee Williams play. The front of the car reads, ''Desire.'' Inside, vintage advertisements span the car. ''Romance Never Starts From Scratch,'' reads a Burma Shave ad.</p>
        <p>The entire car, which arrived from New Jersey on Monday evening and will remain in place today, was a promotional ploy by a tourist board to get more people to visit New Orleans, where there are few streetcars running and few neighborhoods rebuilt since the levees broke during Hurricane Katrina in 2005.</p>
        <p>''It's almost a tale of two cities,'' said J. Stephen Perry, president of the New Orleans Metropolitan Convention and Visitors Bureau, as he sat in the streetcar. ''We have some outlying post-World War II neighborhoods that suffered damage that is incomprehensible. But the original city that the tourists come to -- the French Quarter, the Garden District and the Arts District -- are not only intact, but look better than they did before the storm.''</p>
        <p>Tourism is vital to New Orleans, Mr. Perry said. It is the city's largest business, he said, worth billions of dollars, supplying nearly a third of the city budget and employing some 85,000 residents.</p>
        <p>But the city's streetcar system is struggling. Before Katrina, some two million passengers a year hopped onto as many as 30 streetcars at rush hour, said Rosalind Blanco Cook, spokeswoman for the New Orleans Regional Transit Authority.</p>
        <p>Now, as few as six cars are running on a system that will not be fully restored until spring 2008. On a good day, Ms. Cook said, several hundred tourists take the streetcars on the riverfront line.</p>
        <p>As for the streetcar in Times Square yesterday, with its many parts and pieces added over the years, its provenance is as mixed as that of any old New Orleans family. Built in 1922, the 800 series car ran in New Orleans until 1964, when streetcar service was sharply reduced.</p>
        <p>Like other vintage streetcars donated to museums, the car was sent to the Shore Line Trolley Museum in East Haven, Conn., where it was mothballed for decades. Finally, it came out of storage in 1995 and was restored, off and on, over five years.</p>
        <p>Much of it is new. The restoration cost for materials alone was $100,000. The labor could have cost more than $500,000, but most of it was volunteer, according to Richard Slinsky, an electronics consultant and one of the Trolley Museum volunteers involved in the project.</p>
        <p>The reason it was restored to the 1948 era, rather than the 1922 era, was the scarcity of spare parts and documentation from the earlier period, Mr. Slinsky said.</p>
        <p>Is it really one of the streetcars named Desire on the French Quarter line that inspired Tennessee Williams's play title?</p>
        <p>Mr. Slinsky is careful. It's likely, he said. One of the original roll signs that arrived with the car includes the name Desire, as well as Bourbon, Esplanade, Decatur, Elysian Fields, Chartres, Tonti, France and Royal.</p>
        <p>As for the car in Times Square yesterday, visitors, many of them youngsters, seemed less fascinated by its history than by the smallness of the wooden benches.</p>
        <p>Shaquanna Squalls, 16, a high school student from the Bronx, said, ''How did they put their legs in? I guess people were a lot shorter back then.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
