<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DiPietro Starts Workouts, But Dubielewicz Will Start</title>
    <meta content="11islanders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/sports/hockey/11islanders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dipietro, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DiPietro Starts Workouts, But Dubielewicz Will Start</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">DiPietro Starts Workouts, but Dubielewicz Will Start</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>SYOSSET, N.Y., April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Islanders goaltender Rick DiPietro practiced Tuesday, but not with the team. He was signing autographs when his teammates took the ice to prepare for their first-round playoff series against the Buffalo Sabres.</p>
        <p>DiPietro was encouraged by his half-hour workout, saying he felt no symptoms from the concussion that has sidelined him since March 25. He said he did not know when he would play again, or if he would even accompany the team to Buffalo on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Goaltender Wade Dubielewicz has led the Islanders to four straight must-win victories in the final six days of the regular season while filling in for starter Rick DiPietro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Islanders goaltender Rick DiPietro practiced Tuesday, but not with the team. He was signing autographs when his teammates took the ice to prepare for their first-round playoff series against the Buffalo Sabres.</p>
        <p>DiPietro was encouraged by his half-hour workout, saying he felt no symptoms from the concussion that has sidelined him since March 25. He said he did not know when he would play again, or if he would even accompany the team to Buffalo on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Coach Ted Nolan sounded prepared to stick with Plan B: using Wade Dubielewicz, the stubby, self-deprecating goaltender who led the Islanders to four straight must-win victories in the final six days of the regular season.</p>
        <p>''Rick's not in our pattern right now,'' Nolan said.</p>
        <p>Nolan said it was more than likely that Dubielewicz would start the series opener Thursday. Dubielewicz spent most of the season with Bridgeport, the Islanders' American Hockey League affiliate, and he said he knew he was not the team's first choice.</p>
        <p>''He's a franchise player, a world-class goaltender,'' Dubielewicz said of DiPietro, ''and when he's in net, we have a better chance to win.''</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz's N.H.L. experience spans 17 games over three seasons. But he will be facing the speedy, swarming Sabres, who finished with the league's best record, 53-22-7.</p>
        <p>''Dubie's just got to make sure he stays Dubie,'' Nolan said.</p>
        <p>DiPietro said Tuesday that he had not recovered to the point of even devising a timetable for his return. He rode a stationary bicycle Thursday. On Tuesday, he faced shots from the injured forward Shawn Bates and the Islanders' goaltender coach, Gilles Lefebvre.</p>
        <p>''If you're a competitor, you want to get back,'' DiPietro said, ''but I don't want to do anything to jeopardize my health.''</p>
        <p>DiPietro said he would need to pass a neuropsychological test to resume practicing with the team. He said he had been symptom-free since Thursday and would need to be symptom-free for a full week before he could take the test.</p>
        <p>He said he was trying to be patient while he awaited word from Dr. Elliot Pellman, the Islanders' medical director. (Islanders General Manager Garth Snow would not comment.)</p>
        <p>''When they give me the go-ahead and say to take the test, I'll take it,'' DiPietro said.</p>
        <p>DiPietro sustained a concussion when Montreal forward Steve Bégin collided with him in the first period of a game March 13. He left the game, missed the next two, then returned for two games without any apparent symptoms.</p>
        <p>''I don't regret coming back at all,'' he said Tuesday. ''It was a decision we made that we felt comfortable with.''</p>
        <p>But on March 24 against the Philadelphia Flyers -- his third game back -- DiPietro said he was elbowed in the back of the head. The next day, he was jostled in a game against the Rangers at Nassau Coliseum, and he said he felt nauseous.</p>
        <p>The Islanders said March 27 that he would be out indefinitely, and they called up Dubielewicz to back up Mike Dunham. The Islanders lost their next two games; Dubielewicz replaced Dunham after the first period of the second loss.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz made his first start of the season March 31 against Ottawa, and the Islanders lost, 5-2. Nolan chastised his team after that loss.</p>
        <p>The Islanders have not lost since. Dubielewicz led them to the first of four straight victories, a 3-2 shootout victory over the Rangers, on April 3.</p>
        <p>Although his teammates have credited Dubielewicz with playing exceptionally well, he has attempted to pass all of the credit back to them, saying that they have been particularly attentive to playing tough defense.</p>
        <p>''We've got to play the same way against Buffalo,'' left wing Ryan Smyth said. ''Dubie's played well, and he's made some key saves at the right times. But we've got to play with confidence. We've got to make sure we do what we do best.''</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz has clearly been enjoying the moment. He admitted to being nervous before the Islanders played the Devils in their season finale Sunday -- a game that went to a shootout. But he has done well because he has tried to stay loose.</p>
        <p>''I don't know him very well,'' Islanders center Mike Sillinger said, ''but the kid says to himself, What do I have to lose?''</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz was asked Tuesday if any long-lost coaches, teammates or friends had contacted him in the past week. He said his sudden brush with fame had actually given him an excuse to get back in touch with them.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz faced Buffalo for two periods on March 30, facing 18 shots and allowing one goal after he replaced Dunham. He played in seven playoff games for Bridgeport last season and three in 2004.</p>
        <p>He grinned when he was asked if his experience in the earlier Buffalo game or in the American Hockey League's Calder Cup playoffs would help.</p>
        <p>''This is the Stanley Cup playoffs -- this is it,'' Dubielewicz said. ''Let's be realistic. It's not really the same. It's the N.H.L.''</p>
        <p>But he has taken an N.H.L. team to an unlikely playoff berth, becoming a known quantity in the process. As he said, ''Who doesn't like attention?''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
