<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Square Feet; Tied to a City, a Farmers' Market Proves Hardy</title>
    <meta content="11Real" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/realestate/11Real.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839491"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Farmers Markets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Portland (Me)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Market House (Portland, Me)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine/Portland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Portland (Me)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE4D6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1282" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Square Feet; Tied to a City, a Farmers' Market Proves Hardy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tied to a City, a Farmers’ Market Proves Hardy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>PORTLAND, Me.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Public Market House in Portland, Me, situated in square that has supported large outdoor seasonal farmers market for decades, has become latest example of how fresh local food and downtown markets can stimulate activity in American cities, big and small; market occupies basement and first floor of partly renovated four-story building at heart of downtown, which was last home to failing surplus store; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until last summer, the 136-year-old building at 28 Monument Square had been one of the most visible eyesores at the center of this energetic Atlantic Coast city. You would never know it now.</p>
        <p>Most days, a steady stream of customers follow their noses, thirst and appetites into the building, home of the new Public Market House, where in a narrow corridor flanked by vendors they can buy fresh-cut flowers, cheese from Maine farms, a sandwich on fresh-baked bread and beer from state microbreweries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until last summer, a 136-year-old building had been an eyesore at the center of Portland, Me. You would never know it now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until last summer, the 136-year-old building at 28 Monument Square had been one of the most visible eyesores at the center of this energetic Atlantic Coast city. You would never know it now.</p>
        <p>Most days, a steady stream of customers follow their noses, thirst and appetites into the building, home of the new Public Market House, where in a narrow corridor flanked by vendors they can buy fresh-cut flowers, cheese from Maine farms, a sandwich on fresh-baked bread and beer from state microbreweries.</p>
        <p>The seven-month-old market occupies the basement and first floor of the partly renovated four-story building at the heart of downtown, which was last home to a failing surplus store.</p>
        <p>Kris Horton, whose K. Horton Specialty Foods has become a local landmark, led an active public campaign last year to establish the new market after the Libra Foundation, a philanthropic organization in Maine, sold the last of its real estate holdings in Portland, including the larger indoor Portland Public Market, two blocks away. Ms. Horton and other food and farm-product vendors had worked in that market since 1998.</p>
        <p>The new Public Market House, situated in a square that has supported a large outdoor seasonal farmers market for decades, has become the latest example of how fresh local food and downtown markets can stimulate activity in American cities, big and small.</p>
        <p>Although the Public Market House is and will continue to be significantly smaller in size and sales than the old market it replaced, it will not be subsidized. Moreover, the Public Market House's proximity to the existing outdoor Wednesday farmers' market prompted the authors of a new economic study to propose promoting the indoor market as the centerpiece of a ''market district.''</p>
        <p>''Markets bring life to a city,'' said Nelle Hanig, a business development specialist in Portland's Economic Development Division, who helped accelerate the permit process to have the market built. ''This one is already a destination. The location of the Public Market House is important to its success. It's right in the middle of town. It's becoming a focus of activity, and that's always good in a city.''</p>
        <p>The study, completed last month for the Portland Downtown District, an economic development agency, said that the Public Market House is already attracting enough shoppers to generate $1.2 million annually in sales. The building's owner is planning to renovate the second floor to provide space for four or five more vendors, who could generate a further $1.2 million in sales.</p>
        <p>The market district, the study said, might also include a covered outdoor market with 25 vendors on nearby Lancaster Lane, as well as producers selling goods on ''day tables'' in Monument Square.</p>
        <p>The old market's sale last August and the steady departure of vendors until its formal closing in January stirred passions throughout the city. Downtown workers and weekend shoppers from the suburbs loved the old market's homegrown vendors and special events.</p>
        <p>But vendors paid less than $20 a square foot to rent space in a market that cost the foundation as much as $75 a square foot, said Morris Fischer, president of CB Richard Ellis-the Boulos Company, which represented Guggenheim Real Estate, the New York investment firm that bought the market last August.</p>
        <p>''Libra could not get it to a break-even point,'' Mr. Fischer said. ''Libra supported it for a long time hoping they could make sense of it. They came to the conclusion they couldn't do it any longer. Others who looked at it said the same thing.''</p>
        <p>It seems, however, that the old market may be put to a new public use. On March 19, the Portland City Council approved a measure to ask voters to allow the city to buy and convert the old market into the city's public library, replacing the current main library building, which is next door. A referendum to approve a $1 million bond is set for June 12. Most observers expect voters to approve the bond.</p>
        <p>Voters previously approved a $4 million bond to improve library services, and if the June referendum passes that money would also be used to renovate the market. The balance of the $9.5 million purchase and renovation project would be raised by the library.</p>
        <p>Last summer, Ms. Horton and her partners in Market Vendors -- A Country Bouquet, Maine Beer and Beverage and Big Sky Bread Company -- worked with the owner of 28 Monument Square, as well as a contractor, a banker, tradesmen and city officials to quickly renovate the derelict building, which had been closed for two years. The project took six weeks and cost the building's owner, H. Alan Mooney, $250,000. The Public Market House opened as scheduled on Sept. 1.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mooney, a prominent engineer, had paid $725,000 to buy 28 Monument Square after learning that Ms. Horton and her partners, all of whom he knew, were intent on establishing a new market. ''If I didn't have a tenant ready to get into the building immediately, I wouldn't have taken it on,'' Mr. Mooney said.</p>
        <p>He said that he is planning to spend $300,000 more this spring to renovate the market's second floor to make room for new vendors, prepare the third and fourth floors for professional offices and restore the 12,000-square-foot building's historic facade.</p>
        <p>The catalyst in this tale of civic renewal was the announcement by the Libra Foundation in February 2006 that it would sell the last of its holdings in downtown Portland, including the Portland Public Market, which the foundation built and opened in 1998.</p>
        <p>The $9.4 million, L-shaped expanse of glass and soaring timber beams had a huge fireplace at its center, and a parking deck attached by an overhead walkway. The market took in $6 million in sales in its first year, and sustained that sales level throughout most of its short life.</p>
        <p>The market was also a centerpiece of the Libra Foundation's novel strategy of using its considerable assets -- $220 million -- to buy and renovate downtown office buildings to jump-start Portland's reeling economy. Along with the Portland Public Market, the foundation -- started here in 1989 by Elizabeth Noyce, the former wife of Robert N. Noyce, a founder of Intel -- opened a downtown bank, bought and renovated seven office buildings and bought three large parking decks.</p>
        <p>When the foundation started its acquisition program in the early 1990s, office vacancy rates hovered at more than 60 percent and Portland's economy and reputation were stagnant.</p>
        <p>Portland, a city of 64,000, is now a place where housing values are stable, personal incomes are rising and historic neighborhoods overlooking Casco Bay and the Atlantic are so popular among young people, urban professionals and retirees from Boston and New York that the office and housing vacancy rates are under 3 percent.</p>
        <p>Four years ago, according to Owen Wells, the foundation's president, Libra changed course to take advantage of the economic conditions it had helped to foster. ''We wanted to capitalize on strong real estate markets in Portland,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In 2002 and 2003, Libra sold three buildings and a parking deck for $31 million. Three years later the foundation completed the sale of its other downtown real estate -- four office buildings, two parking decks and the Portland Public Market -- to Guggenheim Real Estate for more than $55 million, $20 million more than the original investment.</p>
        <p>Three months after its formal closing, the old market's windows are streaked and grimy. Two blocks away, though, on a bright winter afternoon, the new Public Market House swarms with customers.</p>
        <p>''I believe in the spirit of a public market being a community,'' said Ms. Horton, while attending to early afternoon customers. ''We found out that a lot of other people in Portland feel the same way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
