<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rapids' Spirits Are Higher Than the Mercury</title>
    <meta content="11soccer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/sports/soccer/11soccer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070412T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839527"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: EXTRA TIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sporting Goods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Colorado Rapids</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Soccer</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DF123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rapids' Spirits Are Higher Than the Mercury</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rapids’ Spirits Are Higher Than the Mercury</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a blue-ribbon day as the Colorado Rapids opened their Major League Soccer season and their new sold-out stadium, Dick's Sporting Goods Park.</p>
        <p>The 29-degree game-time temperature Saturday in Commerce City (elevation 5,112 feet) failed to chill the Rapids, who won their first game of the season for the first time. So after chasing D.C. United players across an enormous playing surface (80 by 120 yards, the maximum under FIFA rules) and winning, 2-1, the players were ready for their just reward: a hot shower.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 29-degree game-time temperature Saturday failed to chill the Colorado Rapids as they opened their Major League Soccer season and their new sold-out stadium with a victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a blue-ribbon day as the Colorado Rapids opened their Major League Soccer season and their new sold-out stadium, Dick's Sporting Goods Park.</p>
        <p>The 29-degree game-time temperature Saturday in Commerce City (elevation 5,112 feet) failed to chill the Rapids, who won their first game of the season for the first time. So after chasing D.C. United players across an enormous playing surface (80 by 120 yards, the maximum under FIFA rules) and winning, 2-1, the players were ready for their just reward: a hot shower.</p>
        <p>''We were playing in a $130 million complex in 29-degree weather and we had 35-degree water,'' Rapids defender Mike Petke said Monday during a telephone interview. ''It was freezing. But hey, nothing could have brought us down that day. We were pumped and had a bit of a laugh. We would have loved a hot shower. If something had to go wrong, I'd rather it have been the hot water.''</p>
        <p>This is Petke's 10th season in M.L.S., and the Rapids are his third team. He was drafted out of Southern Connecticut State in 1998 by the MetroStars and played two full seasons with D.C. United before he was traded to Colorado early in the 2005 season. Petke, who has played an average of 26 games over nine seasons, is the only starting defender back with Colorado, which yielded 49 goals last season (tied with Real Salt Lake for worst in the league) and had a minus-13 goal differential (the worst).</p>
        <p>''I blinked and realized that I was the only starter left,'' Petke said. ''Perhaps it's a compliment, perhaps there's other reasons. We did have one of the worst defenses, but I don't think it's a reflection on the players. We had the best goalkeeper, but I guess we just didn't click with the players we had.''</p>
        <p>Joe Cannon, the goalkeeper, was traded to Los Angeles. On the back line Saturday, Petke played with three newcomers: Brandon Prideaux (a former D.C. teammate), the veteran Greg Vanney and the 24-year-old Ugo Ihemelu.</p>
        <p>''It has been a big adjustment for me,'' Petke, 30, said. ''It's my 10th year in the league, my third team and my sixth different coach. I feel like I made an investment and now I'm watching it grow. I can't wait for next Sunday's game. It was a great stadium experience.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the 18,000-seat stadium and a surrounding complex of 24 fields on 360 acres, the Rapids have new colors (the maroon and blue worn by the N.H.L.'s Avalanche) and a new working agreement with Arsenal of the English Premier League. Stan Kroenke, who owns the Rapids and the Avalanche, bought a 9.9 percent stake in Arsenal for $128 million last week.</p>
        <p>Kroenke also owns the N.B.A.'s Denver Nuggets, an Arena League football team and a professional lacrosse club and is a co-owner of the N.F.L.'s St. Louis Rams.</p>
        <p>England</p>
        <p>The irascible and volatile Roy Keane could be back in the English Premier League next season, not as a player but as the manager of Sunderland.</p>
        <p>Keane, 35, took over foundering Sunderland last August after ending his playing career with Glasgow Celtic. The apex of his long career was as the midfield linchpin and fiery leader of Manchester United for more than 300 games from 1993 to 2005.</p>
        <p>Sunderland, a club from northeast England, was relegated after last season and lost its first four matches in the Championship, which is one level below the Premier League.</p>
        <p>The team's impressive turnaround continued Monday when the Black Cats defeated Southampton to take a 1-point lead over Derby County for first place. The top team in the Championship earns an automatic promotion to the Premier League; the next four teams compete in a playoff for two more spots.</p>
        <p>''Now is not the time to reflect on what has happened,'' Keane told Agence France-Presse. ''We cannot do that with four games still to go. I tell the players every day that we have achieved nothing.''</p>
        <p>During his often tumultuous playing career, Keane led Manchester United to seven Premier League titles and played a major role in helping Ireland qualify for two World Cups (although he did not play in the 2002 tournament because of a falling-out with Manager Mick McCARTHY).</p>
        <p>Keane overhauled Sunderland, bringing in 13 players, including striker Anthony Stokes, the veteran Dwight Yorke and wing Carlos Edwards. Keane also coaxed his old coach, Sir Alex Ferguson, into a loan deal for the Northern Ireland central defender Jonny Evans.</p>
        <p>Last month, Keane was named manager of the month in the Championship and told Reuters: ''I'm not bothered about it one bit. I'll stick it in the garage. I don't get sucked into that nonsense. The time to reflect on the season is at the end.''</p>
        <p>Notes</p>
        <p>The United States women's national team, No. 1 in the world in the latest FIFA rankings, will play Mexico on Saturday in Foxborough, Mass., in the opening game of a doubleheader. (New England and Toronto F.C. of M.L.S. will play the second game.) The women's match, at 5 p.m., will be streamed live at ussoccer.com, the site's first Webcast of a senior national team game, the federation said.</p>
        <p>Lauren Cheney, a 19-year-old striker from U.C.L.A., is the youngest player on the American roster. She has made one appearance for the national team. Defender Marian Dalmy, 22, also made Coach Greg Ryan's 18-player roster and could earn her first national team cap.</p>
        <p>The game against Mexico is the first of eight for the United States leading up to the Women's World Cup in China in September. Mexico did not qualify.</p>
        <p>Games in the United Soccer Leagues First Division, which is one level below M.L.S., will continue to be televised Friday nights on the Fox Soccer Channel through the 2009 season under terms of a new three-year deal. The contract also includes broadband and mobile rights, and broadcast of the W-League, U.S.L.-2 and Premier Development League championship games.  U.S.L., in a partnership with Turner Broadcasting, will go live on the Web with Friday's game between Rochester and Puerto Rico, the first of about 150 games on its subscription-based Internet channel, usllive.com.</p>
        <p>SOCCER: EXTRA TIME</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 12, 2007, Thursday  Because of an editing error, a report in the Extra Time soccer roundup yesterday, about the Sunderland club's turnaround in an effort to return to the English Premier League, referred incorrectly to the competition through which teams rise to that league from the next level, the Championship. The Championship's top two teams -- not just the top team -- receive automatic promotions; the next four compete for one more spot, not for two.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 12, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a report in the Extra Time soccer roundup yesterday, about the Sunderland club's turnaround in an effort to return to the English Premier League, referred incorrectly to the competition through which teams rise to that league from the next level, the Championship. The Championship's top two teams -- not just the top team -- receive automatic promotions; the next four compete for one more spot, not for two.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
