<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School Records on Special English Classes Are Called Works of Fiction by Critics</title>
    <meta content="11education" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/education/11education.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Education Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E5D6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1217" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School Records on Special English Classes Are Called Works of Fiction by Critics</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">School Records on Special English Classes Are Called Works of Fiction by Critics</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL G. FREEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freedman, Samuel G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under ordinary circumstances, few documents in a New York City high school serve as prosaic a purpose as the so-called bubble sheet. In homeroom and then in each class a teacher uses that sheet, a roster of names, to mark attendance, indicating whether students are present or absent by filling in the appropriate little circular bubble.</p>
        <p>At Sports Professions High School in the Bronx, however, a set of bubble sheets from last fall and winter tell a rather less-routine story. They reveal that, in apparent violation of state regulations, the school was not providing the required classes in English as a second language to immigrant children. The sheets also raise the question of whether the school was trying to cover up a failure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A high school in the Bronx is said to have failed to offer the required classes in English as a second language to immigrant children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Under ordinary circumstances, few documents in a New York City high school serve as prosaic a purpose as the so-called bubble sheet. In homeroom and then in each class a teacher uses that sheet, a roster of names, to mark attendance, indicating whether students are present or absent by filling in the appropriate little circular bubble.</p>
        <p>At Sports Professions High School in the Bronx, however, a set of bubble sheets from last fall and winter tell a rather less-routine story. They reveal that, in apparent violation of state regulations, the school was not providing the required classes in English as a second language to immigrant children. The sheets also raise the question of whether the school was trying to cover up a failure.</p>
        <p>According to official school documents, amplified by interviews with a teacher at the school and a union representative, the school tried at one point to create a paper trail to make it appear it was offering E.S.L. classes that were not actually being held.</p>
        <p>According to the documents and interviews, the school produced attendance records purporting to show that separate E.S.L. courses were being offered to eligible students, formally known as English language learners, when, in fact, those students were being lumped into regular English courses with fully fluent classmates.</p>
        <p>Janet Gallardo, the principal of the high school, did not respond to e-mail and telephone messages left at her office over the past week, when the city schools were not in session. The home phone number she has provided to the principals' union -- a number also listed as hers on various public-record databases -- has been disconnected, according to a recording. Melody Meyer, a deputy press secretary at the city Education Department, said she was not familiar with the class rosters at issue and so could not respond in detail to questions about them.</p>
        <p>But she pointed out that 93 percent of ninth-grade E.S.L. students at Sports Professions last year were promoted to the 10th grade for this year. That rate, she said, is ''well above the citywide average.'' She also said that the promotion rate ''is a good indicator of whether a student will graduate from high school.''</p>
        <p>While Sports Professions has corrected its practices over the past two months, the prior pattern ''is being investigated'' by the special commissioner of investigation for the city school system, said Laurel Wright-Hinckson, a spokeswoman for the commissioner.</p>
        <p>Advocates for immigrant rights see the situation at Sports Professions as consistent with what they say is the failure of the city Education Department to address the needs of immigrant children when large schools with many such pupils are broken apart and small ones like Sports Professions are hastily put together.</p>
        <p>''Why do we have this problem, and why is the current response so wrong?'' said Chung-Hwa Hong, the executive director of the New York Immigration Coalition, a group that follows educational issues, among others. ''The problem is too pervasive to be dismissed as a school-specific one. In every major reform initiative, like small schools, the English language learners come up only as an afterthought. The reforms that should be lifting the most vulnerable students make them into collateral damage.''</p>
        <p>Nina Chanpreet Singh, an E.S.L. teacher at Sports Professions, characterized the school's treatment of immigrant pupils more as a result of neglect, poor facilities and inadequate funds than of any deliberate bias. She said she considered the school to be ''friendly'' to E.S.L. students, about 30 of its 260 pupils. But she, too, drew broader conclusions from its performance.</p>
        <p>When English language learners' needs are not met and ''they do not receive the education they are mandated -- one of their most basic human rights -- it is a citywide and nationwide problem,'' she said. ''Entire generations of immigrant Americans are kept in a cycle of poverty. They do not have a means to move up in society, participate fully in society or fulfill their life's dreams.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Meyer said that Sports Professions has been able to promote more than 90 percent of its English Language Learners students from grade to grade each year ''and that's the bottom line.''</p>
        <p>Well, that is one bottom line. Another is what state regulations say.</p>
        <p>They stipulate a certain amount of E.S.L. instruction for eligible high school students -- three periods a day for those in the beginning level, two for intermediate and one for advanced. The city's Education Department, without being ironclad on the point, states in its manual for teaching immigrant pupils that most high schools should use separate E.S.L. classes for them rather than mixing them into regular English courses.</p>
        <p>The paper trail from Sports Professions shows something starkly at odds with those directives and recommendations. During second period last fall and winter, 14 immigrant children spread across the three levels of fluency were being put in a mainstream English class alongside 14 pupils who needed no extra instruction. During second period, 13 intermediate and advanced E.S.L. pupils were in class with the same number of non-E.S.L. classmates.</p>
        <p>The teacher of record in all of these classes was not a licensed E.S.L. instructor but one certified in English, Harriett Mahl. Ms. Mahl did not respond to an e-mail message requesting an interview.</p>
        <p>Ms. Singh, the E.S.L teacher, said she did ''push-ins'' for the eligible pupils in those classes, meaning that within one 45-minute period she had to try to explain unfamiliar vocabulary and cultural or historical references to more than a dozen teenagers at three varying levels of proficiency, even as Ms. Mahl's lesson proceeded.</p>
        <p>The physical and financial conditions at Sports Professions did not help. Opened in September 2004 in a former chocolate factory, the school, which offers some study of sports history in its college-prep curriculum, moved this academic year to five trailers set up on the playground of a middle school in the northeast Bronx.</p>
        <p>For the entire first semester, Ms. Singh said, the school did not buy her students either textbooks or the test-prep materials for the state exam that determines which pupils can be promoted out of E.S.L.. She received those materials only in the last month.</p>
        <p>For part of last fall, Ms. Singh also said, she was assigned by her principal to teach E.S.L. classes during an early morning period that, under the teachers' union contract, was specifically designated for individual or small-group tutoring. When the union discovered the practice and objected, high school administrators in early December produced bubble sheets purporting to show Ms. Singh teaching E.S.L. classes during another period, meaning the time before the normal school day. Ms. Singh said she considered those attendance records ''fraudulent,'' refused to sign them and reported them to Lynne Winderbaum, the United Federation of Teachers representative for Bronx high schools.</p>
        <p>After Ms. Winderbaum took up the issue with administrators in the Education Department's Region 2, which covers parts of the Bronx, the dubious bubble sheets did not reappear.</p>
        <p>The broader issue, however, remains: Are immigrant students the losers in the current school-reform movement?</p>
        <p>''What happened at Sports Professions sounds like something disconcertingly common,'' said Kathleen Bullock-McKoy, a parent representative from Region 2 on the Citywide Council of High Schools, an advisory group. ''It does not surprise me that in small schools the E.L.L. students don't have the right classes and don't have the support.''</p>
        <p>ON EDUCATION Samuel G. Freedman is a professor of journalism at Columbia University. His e-mail address is sgfreedman@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Samuel G. Freedman is a professor of journalism at Columbia University. His e-mail address is sgfreedman@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
