<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Closing Arguments Begin In Trial of Ex-Qwest Chief</title>
    <meta content="11qwest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/business/11qwest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insider Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Qwest Communications International Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nacchio, Joseph P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Conry, Colleen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Herbert (Lawyer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frosch, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insider Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Nacchio, Joseph P</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1D6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Closing Arguments Begin In Trial of Ex-Qwest Chief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Closing Arguments Begin in Trial of Ex-Qwest Chief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN FROSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frosch, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, April 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Closing arguments begin in fraud trial of former Qwest Communications chief executive Joseph P Nacchio; federal prosecutor Colleen Conry portrays Nacchio as man who knowingly and unlawfully concealed Qwest's growing money problems, while simultaneously cashing in on his stock options; Nacchio's lawyer Herbert Stern seeks to paint his client as ambitious and passionate executive who may have misjudged Qwest's financial prognostications, but believed deeply in his own numbers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal prosecutor, Colleen Conry, portrayed Joseph P. Nacchio, former chief executive of Qwest International, on Tuesday as a man who knowingly and unlawfully concealed Qwest's growing money troubles, while simultaneously cashing in on his stock options.</p>
        <p>''This is a case about choices,'' Ms. Conry said in closing arguments in the insider trading case against Mr. Nacchio. He ''made a choice,'' she said. ''He chose not to tell. And he also made a choice to sell.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joseph P. Nacchio faces 42 counts of insider trading related to his sale of more than $100 million in Qwest stock in 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal prosecutor, Colleen Conry, portrayed Joseph P. Nacchio, former chief executive of Qwest International, on Tuesday as a man who knowingly and unlawfully concealed Qwest's growing money troubles, while simultaneously cashing in on his stock options.</p>
        <p>''This is a case about choices,'' Ms. Conry said in closing arguments in the insider trading case against Mr. Nacchio. He ''made a choice,'' she said. ''He chose not to tell. And he also made a choice to sell.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nacchio faces 42 counts of insider trading related to his sale of more than $100 million in Qwest stock in 2001.</p>
        <p>In a lengthy summation peppered with financial reports and video clips, Ms. Conry told jurors that Mr. Nacchio had deceived analysts by exaggerating Qwest's internal financial projections, despite knowing that Qwest was facing a significant shortfall because of the company's failure to increase revenue.</p>
        <p>In his own closing remarks, Mr. Nacchio's lawyer, Herbert Stern, sought to paint his client as an ambitious and passionate executive who may have misjudged Qwest's financial prognostications, but believed deeply in his own numbers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern began his remarks before Judge Edward W. Nottingham of Federal District Court here adjourned the jury for the day, and will conclude his summation on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>In her remarks, Ms. Conry also pointed to a series of e-mail messages from other Qwest executives who assessed Mr. Nacchio's rosy projections as ''unrealistic'' and a ''huge stretch'' as evidence that Mr. Nacchio had been warned that Qwest was in trouble.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Nacchio was publicly talking about the company's good fortunes, Ms. Conry said, he was selling his stock options as fast as he could.</p>
        <p>''He puts his foot on the accelerator,'' she said. ''He dumps stock like he's never dumped before. He knew not only what he was doing was wrong, he knew it was unlawful. He is here because of his own choices.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern called the government's accusations ''false charges,'' saying that Mr. Nacchio might have miscalculated the company's financial threshold, but possessed no material inside information that led him to unload his stocks.</p>
        <p>''It's not true,'' Mr. Stern said. ''He knew no such thing. He believed no such thing.''</p>
        <p>On the contrary, Mr. Stern said that Mr. Nacchio had based his financial projections on recommendations reported by outside financial consultants hired to assess the merger between Qwest and US West in 1999.</p>
        <p>He added that Mr. Nacchio needed to get rid of the options because they were set to expire and Qwest's board had refused to extend them. Moreover, Mr. Stern said that Mr. Nacchio had cashed in only those options set to expire -- described by Mr. Nacchio as ''use them or lose them'' options in a video clip of a meeting with Qwest analysts played by the defense on Monday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern said that Mr. Nacchio had not sold other potentially more valuable options in 2001.</p>
        <p>''If the company was going to hell in a hand basket, don't you think it might have been smart to get rid of $28.50 options?'' Mr. Stern asked the jury. ''But he said no.''</p>
        <p>Speculation that Mr. Nacchio would take the stand in his own defense ended Monday when the defense wrapped up its case after calling only three witnesses.</p>
        <p>Before the trial, defense lawyers said that Mr. Nacchio, alone among company executives, knew about secret government contracts that Qwest could win, bolstering its revenue. The defense introduced none of that evidence, however, and it was mentioned only in passing by prosecution witnesses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nacchio's criminal case stems from a years-long government investigation into an accounting scandal at Qwest, a Denver-based primary telephone service provider in 14 mostly Western states.</p>
        <p>Federal regulators have said Qwest falsely reported fiber-optic capacity sales as recurring instead of one-time revenue between April 1999 and March 2002. The practice allowed Qwest to improperly report about $3 billion in revenue, regulators have alleged. Qwest later restated about $2.2 billion in revenue.</p>
        <p>Jury deliberation is likely to begin on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
