<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Retaining Wall at Ground Zero Will Get Its Own Wall</title>
    <meta content="11memorial" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/nyregion/11memorial.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Retaining Wall at Ground Zero Will Get Its Own Wall</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Retaining Wall at Ground Zero Will Get Its Own Wall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A section of the legendary slurry wall at ground zero -- the sturdy concrete ''bathtub'' that kept the waters of the Hudson River from inundating the World Trade Center site before and after the twin towers collapsed on Sept. 11, 2001 -- will be getting its own $10 million bathtub.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, construction managers for the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey offered new details about the measures that will be necessary to protect part of the slurry wall so it can be viewed -- and touched -- by visitors to the World Trade Center Memorial and its museum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A section of the legendary slurry wall at ground zero  the sturdy concrete “bathtub” that kept the waters of the Hudson River from inundating the World Trade Center site before and after the twin towers collapsed on Sept. 11, 2001  will be getting its own $10 million bathtub.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A section of the legendary slurry wall at ground zero -- the sturdy concrete ''bathtub'' that kept the waters of the Hudson River from inundating the World Trade Center site before and after the twin towers collapsed on Sept. 11, 2001 -- will be getting its own $10 million bathtub.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, construction managers for the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey offered new details about the measures that will be necessary to protect part of the slurry wall so it can be viewed -- and touched -- by visitors to the World Trade Center Memorial and its museum.</p>
        <p>''As an artifact, the slurry wall can no longer serve a structural purpose itself,'' said Anthony R. Coscia, the authority's chairman, as he walked through the 2.5-acre memorial site yesterday with officials from his agency and the World Trade Center Memorial Foundation for an update on construction progress. ''So the wall will need its own slurry wall.''</p>
        <p>Once the invisible 3,300-foot perimeter of the trade center, the utilitarian bathtub was a pebbly three-foot-thick slab that kept the twin towers' foundations dry so they could actually be constructed.</p>
        <p>But after it endured the equivalent of an earthquake of 2.3 magnitude on Sept. 11, the wall -- and the rusty steel tieback tendons that held it during construction of the trade center -- became a symbol of survival, viewed as sacred by some of the legions of tourists who photographed it. Daniel Libeskind, the ground zero master planner, termed the wall an emblem of ''the indomitable spirit of New York'' that stood as ''the trace of the actual attack, and the witness to it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Libeskind originally planned that a 300-foot stretch of the wall at West Street near Vesey Street would be preserved as the centerpiece of the memorial. Now it is viewed as an important, but less sizable, component of the memorial and museum experience, said Steven Plate, the director of trade center construction at the authority.</p>
        <p>He added that a 70-foot-high section measuring from 20 to 62 feet wide -- ''depending on budget,'' he said -- would be dramatically visible, from a north-facing platform, to visitors walking down ramps from ground level. When visitors reach the bottom of the wall, they may touch it.</p>
        <p>To stabilize the existing wall at West Street, a new concrete inner ''liner'' wall will be poured to cover the original bathtub. But in the section where the original wall is openly displayed, a new concrete bathtub -- from two and a half to four feet thick -- will be built on its outer, West Street side.</p>
        <p>The new wall will protect the original from brackish water seeping through the subterranean stones and dirt adjacent to the Hudson River, 150 feet to the west. Mr. Plate said that the preliminary cost estimate, $10 million, could change depending on how much of the original wall will be exposed.</p>
        <p>Despite delays involving the continuing search for human remains, the $510 million memorial ''is on budget and on time,'' said Anthony E. Shorris, the executive director of the authority, referring to its scheduled completion in 2010.</p>
        <p>Joseph C. Daniels, president of the World Trade Center Memorial Foundation, said that $253 million of the foundation's goal of $350 million had been raised, ''$120 million of it since last October,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Steel structure will begin rising from the ground at the memorial site in December, Mr. Plate said. Looking to the south, Mr. Plate said that managers hoped the dismantling of the shrouded former Deutsche Bank building at 130 Liberty Street would also be finished next December.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
