<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Miso: It's All About the Journey</title>
    <meta content="11miso" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/dining/11miso.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839465"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4D7153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Miso: It's All About the Journey</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Good Miso: It’s All About the Journey</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE BLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Black, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>CONWAY, MASS.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG before Nobu Matsuhisa's black cod became as familiar as crème brûlée, before Japanese restaurants popped up on every other corner and before most people had even heard of umami, a few mystical souls in western Massachusetts were making miso, the rich Japanese flavoring. Twenty-five years later those folks, here at South River Miso, are still at it.</p>
        <p>Visiting with the owner, Christian Elwell, is a bit of a trip back in time -- centuries ago, as well as perhaps 30 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At South River Miso in Conway, Mass., the rich Japanese flavoring of miso has been made with exquisite care for more than two decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LONG before Nobu Matsuhisa's black cod became as familiar as crème brûlée, before Japanese restaurants popped up on every other corner and before most people had even heard of umami, a few mystical souls in western Massachusetts were making miso, the rich Japanese flavoring. Twenty-five years later those folks, here at South River Miso, are still at it.</p>
        <p>Visiting with the owner, Christian Elwell, is a bit of a trip back in time -- centuries ago, as well as perhaps 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>The miso itself is the connection to the distant past. Like traditional Japanese artisans, Mr. Elwell ferments grain in a wooden crib tucked gently under a blanket to keep it warm. He cooks beans in a caldron for 20 hours over hand-fed wood fires. His workers blend the mixture by stamping it with their feet.</p>
        <p>''There are energies and thoughts and feelings that are worked into the product,'' he said as he sat in his office in green wool sweater, tan cords and flannel slippers. ''They stream out of our hands and feet.''</p>
        <p>And that's the echo of the more recent past, the '70s, when Mr. Elwell developed a worldview that has helped keep South River Miso going. Mr. Elwell still has a bit of the seeker about him, the young man who worked for the Peace Corps in Iran, then traveled the world to find himself.</p>
        <p>In India he grew interested in natural healing (to help take care of a case of hepatitis). At the Findhorn Garden commune in Scotland he learned about communicating with natural spirits (a process that he said helped the residents inspire cabbages to grow to 40 pounds). Then it was on to macrobiotics in Boston and organic gardening in northern California.</p>
        <p>But it was his next stop, studying how to make miso with Naboru Muramoto, a macrobiotic healer in Glen Ellen, Calif., that set Mr. Elwell on his path. He and his wife, Gaella, intended to stay for a week; instead they stayed three months. Two years later, back in Massachusetts, Mr. Elwell was approached by another of Mr. Muramoto's students who had begun to make miso commercially. For $10,000 the Elwells bought all the necessary equipment and 13 tons of miso.</p>
        <p>''The traditional way of making miso is a very aesthetically beautiful process,'' said Mr. Elwell, who had planned on starting a family farm. ''There's something very peaceful and meditative about it.''</p>
        <p>It also produces good miso.</p>
        <p>Mike Berard, chef de cuisine at Asia Nora, an organic restaurant in Washington, said South River miso's fresh ingredients and texture add a ''multidimensional flavor'' to miso soups and glazes for fish and chicken. ''It's not a bland, uniform paste,'' he said. ''You can still see the chunks of beans and grains. It's the best out there, hands down.''</p>
        <p>Like all miso makers, Mr. Elwell starts with grain, like rice or barley, and inoculates it with an aspergillus mold imported from Japan. This treated grain, called koji, is set to ferment inside a small room that looks like a miniature Scandinavian sauna. It is wood-paneled with a low ceiling to keep the room at 80 degrees, the ideal temperature for fermentation.</p>
        <p>Over two days the koji is stacked and restacked in trays, in special formations to cultivate slow, healthy growth. Mr. Elwell adds sea salt, which he imports from Baja California, and mixes in soaked and cooked beans.</p>
        <p>Workers pull on cotton socks and plastic booties and pound the mixture with their feet, like winemakers of long ago. It takes about an hour to tread 600 pounds of miso.</p>
        <p>''It's the difference between receiving a loving massage from a human being and one from a roll-back chair,'' he said in his office, which smelled pleasantly malty and sweet from the beans and grain fermenting -- for as long as three years -- in cypress vats downstairs. ''That energetic quality that goes into the food creates a different quality in the food itself.''</p>
        <p>While Japanese misos are traditionally made from just rice, barley or soybeans, South River now makes 11 kinds, including garbanzo bean, adzuki bean and a dandelion-leek brown rice miso that Mr. Elwell invented using wild greens he picked from the fields and woodlands around the farm. The greens are steamed with Maine sea vegetables and nettle greens, then pickled in the rich brown rice miso for one summer.</p>
        <p>South River produces 90,000 pounds of miso annually. Last year, for the first time, it continued production throughout the summer to keep up with demand. (Traditionally, miso is not made in summer when it is too hot to keep the fires burning.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Elwell, 60, and his wife of 28 years, Gaella, still maintain their spiritual pursuits. He is studying with the School of Spiritual Psychology, which is based in Benson, N.C., and she teaches conflict resolution and communication at the Conscious Communication Institute in nearby Greenfield, Mass., though she also offers free workshops, like one called Educating Our Hearts, to South River's 14 employees.</p>
        <p>It's all ''a positive affirmation of the path we've set out on,'' Mr. Elwell said. ''The ingredients and processes that go into making a medicinal food versus the ones you might use to elicit a certain taste or turn a profit.''</p>
        <p>South River Miso is available at many Whole Foods stores; Commodities East, 165 First Avenue (10th Street), East Village, (212) 260-2600; and Pumpkin's Organic Market, 1302 Eighth Avenue (13th Street), Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 499-8539. For mail order, (413) 369-4057 or southrivermiso.com. Minimum order: $20; because of warm weather, South River will stop shipping in the next few weeks until the fall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
