<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milledge May Be Sent To Minors for At-Bats</title>
    <meta content="11mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/sports/baseball/11mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Milledge, Lastings</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Willie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Alou, Moises</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Green, Shawn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5DE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milledge May Be Sent To Minors for At-Bats</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets’ Milledge May Go to Minors to Get More At-Bats</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph had a decision to make in the eighth inning of the Mets' 11-5 victory against Philadelphia on Monday afternoon: With Moises Alou on second and Shawn Green at first representing the go-ahead run, Randolph wanted to replace one of them with Endy Chávez, a faster runner and a superior defender. But which one?</p>
        <p>As hard as it might have been to believe two weeks ago, replacing either player would have removed one of the Mets' best hitters in the opening week of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The offensive consistency of Shawn Green and Moises Alou has made it difficult for manager Willie Randolph to incorporate Lastings Milledge into the starting lineup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph had a decision to make in the eighth inning of the Mets' 11-5 victory against Philadelphia on Monday afternoon: With Moises Alou on second and Shawn Green at first representing the go-ahead run, Randolph wanted to replace one of them with Endy Chávez, a faster runner and a superior defender. But which one?</p>
        <p>As hard as it might have been to believe two weeks ago, replacing either player would have removed one of the Mets' best hitters in the opening week of the season.</p>
        <p>During spring training, Green and Alou were rarely seen on the bases at all, let alone at the same time. Now they cannot stay off them. Green (.370) and Alou (.333) , the aging corner outfielders, trail only Paul Lo Duca for the highest batting average on the Mets, and their consistency has made it difficult for Randolph to incorporate other players, namely the young outfielder Lastings Milledge, into the starting lineup.</p>
        <p>The Mets were not overly concerned about Alou in spring training, even though he batted .161. He insisted throughout camp that, no matter how bad he might look, he always had a good April. His career trends back him up: he is a .330 hitter in the first month of the season. And sure enough, Alou has hit safely in six of the first seven games this season with three two-hit games, including Monday, when he went 2 for 4 and capped the Mets' seven-run eighth inning with a two-run single.</p>
        <p>''This team, with this offense, will have a lot of big innings,'' Alou said.</p>
        <p>But Green's case presented a different issue for the Mets, if only because the 22-year-old Milledge outplayed him by a wide margin in spring training. Green hit .149 and struck out 16 times in 74 at-bats in spring training and if his struggles had continued into the beginning of the season, Randolph might have given him a day or two off and let Milledge play. And who knows what might have happened if Milledge had a big game.</p>
        <p>But on opening night, Green had two hits against St. Louis, setting the tone for his dynamic first week. He went 3 for 5 in Saturday's game, although he committed a crucial error that helped Atlanta win, then hit a home run in his first at-bat on Sunday. Green had one hit Monday, and his 1-for-3 day actually lowered his average. Milledge, meanwhile, has stayed seated.</p>
        <p>Randolph proved particularly adept last season at knowing when to rest his regulars and how to use his bench. That is how Chávez morphed from being a late-inning defensive replacement into an important component of the Mets' success. As the season progresses, Randolph will almost certainly look to rotate Chávez and David Newhan into the outfield to keep Green and Alou fresh.</p>
        <p>Hampered by two stays on the disabled list with different ailments, Alou played in only 98 games last season, and Randolph will most likely use him as he did catcher Lo Duca last season, not starting him if the Mets play a day game after a night game. Lo Duca benefited, batting .318, and the Mets are hoping that a healthy Alou will do the same and provide protection for David Wright -- if Wright remains the No. 5 hitter.</p>
        <p>Because of Milledge's youth and potential, the Mets do not want to use him as a spare outfielder who plays sporadically, as Chávez and Newhan may do. If Milledge is going to be in the major leagues, the Mets want him to play more or less regularly, and as long as Green is hitting well, that does not seem like a realistic option.</p>
        <p>The Mets rewarded Milledge for an exceptional spring by including him on their opening day roster, but it appears as if he is holding a spot for the fifth starter Mike Pelfrey, who will probably be activated after Thursday's game so he can start Friday night against the Washington Nationals. After Pelfrey is activated, there is a good chance that Milledge will be sent to Class AAA New Orleans, where he can get some at-bats.</p>
        <p>General Manager Omar Minaya said last week that it was possible that someone would be demoted from the bullpen, which would go with six relievers instead of seven when Pelfrey arrives. But Ambiorix Burgos's inconsistency and Aaron Heilman's elbow tendinitis probably mandates that the bullpen remain at its size for now.</p>
        <p>So Milledge will probably get a tap on his shoulder. He will remain in the minors until an injury or a decline in production creates a chance for him to get substantial playing time in the majors. At this rate, it may not be any time soon.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The right-handed reliever Duaner Sánchez had successful surgery yesterday to repair a hairline fracture of a small bone in his right shoulder, the Mets said. Sánchez will need six to eight weeks to recover and another six to eight weeks of rehabilitation before he can be expected to return.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
