<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Full Federal Appellate Court Will Revisit Abortion Issue in South Dakota</title>
    <meta content="11abortion" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/us/11abortion.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Dakota</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saulny, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Long, Larry (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Dakota</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EED6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Full Federal Appellate Court Will Revisit Abortion Issue in South Dakota</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Full Federal Appellate Court Will Revisit Abortion Issue in South Dakota</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SAULNY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saulny, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal appeals court will revisit South Dakota law that would require doctors to tell women seeking abortion that procedure would 'terminate life of whole, separate, unique, living human being;' appeals court hearing is second opinion on 2006 decision that law should remain blocked because it includes value judgment; Planned Parenthood Federation of America, which brought suit, expresses surprise that court will rehear case; South Dakota Atty Gen Larry Long says appeal is largely based on one dissenting view on three-judge panel; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A South Dakota law that would require doctors to tell women seeking abortions that the procedure would ''terminate the life of a whole, separate, unique, living human being'' will be revisited today by the 11 judges of the federal appeals court in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>The statute is among many abortion laws around the country requiring counseling and consent. Such laws have been upheld in the Supreme Court and in federal appeals courts, but a federal judge has blocked South Dakota's law while she considers its constitutionality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A state law would require doctors to tell women seeking abortions that the procedure would “terminate the life of a whole, separate, unique, living human being.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A South Dakota law that would require doctors to tell women seeking abortions that the procedure would ''terminate the life of a whole, separate, unique, living human being'' will be revisited today by the 11 judges of the federal appeals court in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>The statute is among many abortion laws around the country requiring counseling and consent. Such laws have been upheld in the Supreme Court and in federal appeals courts, but a federal judge has blocked South Dakota's law while she considers its constitutionality.</p>
        <p>The appeals court hearing is a second take on an October decision by a three-judge panel of the same body, the United States Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit, that the law should remain blocked because it supplements factual information with a value judgment. The full Eighth Circuit court, acting on an appeal by the state, agreed to reconsider whether to allow the law to take effect.</p>
        <p>South Dakota's attorney general, Larry Long, said the appeal was largely based on the one dissenting view on the three-judge panel: that the required disclosure was an obvious fact. The State Legislature, Mr. Long said, had defined ''human being'' to mean a member of the species homo sapiens, and that phrase does not include a value judgment.</p>
        <p>''Human being is not a loaded phrase,'' he said. ''That definition everyone agreed was appropriate.''</p>
        <p>Mimi Liu, a lawyer for the Planned Parenthood Federation of America, which brought the suit, said the law violated the First Amendment.</p>
        <p>''We were surprised that the Eighth Circuit decided to rehear this case, but we believe that the law is one our side, as the panel already found,'' said Ms. Liu. Planned Parenthood is the only abortion provider in South Dakota.</p>
        <p>''What we are fighting is the imposition of a state mandated non-science-based script read by a doctor to a patient in an attempt to intimidate the patient,'' said Sarah Stoesz, the chief executive for Planned Parenthood in the three-state region of Minnesota, North Dakota and South Dakota.</p>
        <p>The Legislature said the measure, which was enacted in 2005, was merely meant to fully inform women. It required that the statement about the life that would be terminated be made in writing, along with a dozen other statements, including some about the legal relationship between the mother and the fetus, and others about the increased risk of depression and suicide after abortions.</p>
        <p>Patients would be required to sign each page of a written disclosure. Doctors would be required to certify whether they thought that the patient fully understood all the information.</p>
        <p>The preliminary injunction blocking the law before it could take effect was issued in June 2005 by Judge Karen E. Schreier in Rapid City, S.D.</p>
        <p>Judge Schreier wrote, ''The South Dakota statute requires abortion doctors to enunciate the state's viewpoint on an unsettled medical, philosophical, theological and scientific issue, that is, whether a fetus is a human being.''</p>
        <p>The decision on the law's constitutionality is still before Judge Schreier.</p>
        <p>The full Eighth Circuit court's decision on the injunction is not expected until late summer or early fall.</p>
        <p>The fate of a different abortion law was decided in the November midterm elections, when a majority of voters in South Dakota rejected a broad ban on abortion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
