<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Cutting in Line for Puget Sound Ferries, Under Penalty of Law</title>
    <meta content="11nice" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/us/11nice.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Puget Sound</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (State)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (State)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EED6153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Cutting in Line for Puget Sound Ferries, Under Penalty of Law</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Cutting in Line for Puget Sound Ferries, Under Penalty of Law</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, William</byline>
      <dateline>MUKILTEO, Wash., April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Washington State Legislature is close to approving bill that would make cutting in line to catch ferry illegal; penalty would be fine of at least $101 and place at end of queue; nation's largest ferry system has been lifeline for commuters, but it has also spurred growth; half of 24 million people who ride Puget Sound's ferry system are commuters; some longtime Washington residents suggest that Northwest 'politeness' has suffered as population has expanded; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Riding a ferry across Puget Sound amid evergreen islands and majestic mountain peaks might seem a pretty smooth way to commute. But first you have to get on the ferry.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the line is long. Sometimes people get edgy. Sometimes they forget to be their best selves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A bill that would impose a fine and a trip to the back of the queue on drivers who cut into ferry lines is one proposal intended to preserve Northwest nice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Riding a ferry across Puget Sound amid evergreen islands and majestic mountain peaks might seem a pretty smooth way to commute. But first you have to get on the ferry.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the line is long. Sometimes people get edgy. Sometimes they forget to be their best selves.</p>
        <p>''There are two kinds of line cutters,'' said Brad Collins, the supervisor of the car ferry terminal here, about 20 miles north of Seattle, ''the person who knows what they are doing and the person who doesn't know what they are doing.''</p>
        <p>Both kinds soon could face consequences. The Washington Legislature is close to approving a bill that would make cutting in line to catch a ferry illegal in most cases. The penalty would be a fine of at least $101 and, perhaps worse, a trip to the end of the queue.</p>
        <p>The ferry bill is among several proposals intended to preserve ''the politeness and the sensitivity that we've had'' in Washington, in the words of Judy Clibborn, chairwoman of the State House Transportation Committee, as the state accommodates more newcomers unfamiliar with Northwest nice.</p>
        <p>Simply merging lanes here can seem an exercise in excessive deference compared with the Darwinian driving inclinations that thrive elsewhere. But some longtime residents say the civility practiced with such reason and rigor in parts of the Pacific Northwest has not necessarily expanded with the population.</p>
        <p>''I think you're seeing people becoming much more me-centered,'' said State Senator Mary Margaret Haugen, a Democrat who sponsored the line-breaking bill. Her district includes Whidbey Island, where the port of Clinton is a 20-minute ferry ride to Mukilteo (pronounced muck-il-TEE-o) on the mainland.</p>
        <p>Ms. Haugen has tried to get the bill passed for several years. Yet if cutting in line to catch the ferry is not a new phenomenon, there is a sense that the problem is getting worse. The state does not track the offenses, but Ms. Haugen said she received support this year from newly elected representatives from districts with ferry terminals.</p>
        <p>The ferry system, the nation's largest, has long been a lifeline for islanders, but it has also sped growth.</p>
        <p>Ms. Haugen's grandparents came from Norway to Camano Island, just east of Whidbey, and worked as what she called ''poor stump farmers.'' Like other locals, she has seen farming and fishing villages transformed into Seattle exurbs and tourist destinations.</p>
        <p>Of her plan to make line jumping illegal, she said: ''This really was brought to me by the people on Whidbey. It's the locals who get most frustrated. They are gentle, and most of them follow the rules.''</p>
        <p>The bill, which is expected to gain final passage in the Senate after being amended by the House on Tuesday, would also prohibit blocking a residential driveway while lining up for the ferry.</p>
        <p>Drivers often have to line up in special lanes along the shoulder that pass in front of houses. The state has made a point of marking driveways and intersections as places where drivers may not idle, but some drivers cut in line in those places.</p>
        <p>Jim Welden, 89, was among the first in line on Friday to catch the 8:30 a.m. ferry out of Clinton. He had a special pass because he will spend the next several weeks traveling daily to the mainland for chemotherapy. Mr. Welden, who used to commute to the mainland to work, said he knew to plan ahead.</p>
        <p>He recalled the time when someone pulled in front of him in a long line in Clinton. The driver did not respond to initial courtesies.</p>
        <p>''So I just bumped him,'' Mr. Welden said, meaning he bumped the driver's car with his own. ''He didn't move, so I bumped him again. He finally figured out he'd better get out of there.''</p>
        <p>Force is not always necessary.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, on his way to a memorial service for former United States Representative Jack Metcalf, who lived on Whidbey Island and died last month, Representative Doc Hastings cut in line at the Mukilteo terminal. In an interview, an aide to Mr. Hastings noted that his district was in eastern Washington, where ferries are not a widespread means of travel, and he said the cut was ''an innocent mistake.''</p>
        <p>When confronted, he said, Mr. Hastings gladly went to the back of the line, even without a law requiring him to do so. The congressman still made the service for Mr. Metcalf, a fellow Republican known as Gentleman Jack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Collins, the Mukilteo terminal supervisor, said he brokered disputes over line breaking every day during the summer high season. Tourists are the usual suspects.</p>
        <p>''Some people like to say that because they didn't know what they were doing, it's O.K.,'' Mr. Collins said. ''That's just not logical to me.''</p>
        <p>A little more than half of the 24 million people who ride the ferry system's 10 routes and 28 boats are commuters, said Traci Brewer-Rogstad, director of operations for the system, which is part of the state Transportation Department.</p>
        <p>State financing for the ferries was cut in the late 1990s, and the system has since raised rates about 60 percent and reduced some service. The changes have not gone over well with regular riders, and Ms. Brewer-Rogstad said the ferry system supported the bill in part to ''show we actually listen to our customers.''</p>
        <p>While the bill is almost assured passage, other efforts to legislate motorists' conduct have failed. One unsuccessful proposal would have punished people who drive in the passing lane on Interstates if they are not passing someone, said Ms. Clibborn, the House transportation committee chairwoman. Another would have banned idling while waiting for a ferry.</p>
        <p>Some measures failed because they addressed what Ms. Clibborn said were simply ''pet peeves.'' Cutting in line at the ferry is another matter. ''It's just not fair,'' she said. ''Everybody has a sense of fairness.''</p>
        <p>Well, maybe not everybody. Ms. Clibborn recalled that on a trip to the East Coast she watched drivers race past her even after signs made it clear that a lane was about to close ahead.</p>
        <p>''That's one of the things that shocked me,'' she said, ''that everybody runs to the front and bottles things up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
