<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Chicago, Devotion Has Its Price</title>
    <meta content="11cubs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDE123FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Chicago, Devotion Has Its Price</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thomas Begel badly wants to buy the Cubs, and in his seat behind home plate at Wrigley Field on Monday, he offered a wealthy fan's sentiment sure to be repeated by other bidders.</p>
        <p>''How could you not want to own this team?'' he asked on a brisk and overcast opening day when the ivy on the ballpark's outfield wall was still weeks from blooming. ''You're buying a shrine, a team and a great place to watch baseball.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thomas Begel badly wants to buy the Cubs, and in his seat behind home plate at Wrigley Field on Monday, he offered a wealthy fan's sentiment sure to be repeated by other bidders.</p>
        <p>''How could you not want to own this team?'' he asked on a brisk and overcast opening day when the ivy on the ballpark's outfield wall was still weeks from blooming. ''You're buying a shrine, a team and a great place to watch baseball.''</p>
        <p>The Cubs are one of the most iconic teams in sports, with a legacy built on a famous amount of frustration rather than a long run of success. It is 99 years and counting since their last World Series title, but the Cubs remain immensely popular, as does Wrigley, a charming geezer of a ballpark that, at age 93, is as much an architectural treasure as it is a home to a baseball team.</p>
        <p>Last season, the Cubs won only 66 games -- the fewest in the National League -- yet drew 3.1 million fans. In the months leading into this season, the Cubs spent a fortune on free agents, but they are already under .500, with a 3-5 record that includes losses in Wrigley in Monday and Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Soon, the Cub critiques may start anew -- not enough pitching, not enough luck. But Begel, who cheered for the Cubs' minor league team in his hometown, Peoria, was already prepared with his own analysis Monday. ''You need someone to run it as a team to win the World Series,'' he said as the game progressed, ''not as part of a public corporation that must satisfy shareholders.''</p>
        <p>The public corporation he was referring to is the Tribune Company, which last week put the team up for sale as part of an $8.2 billion transaction in which it would go private in a deal engineered with the billionaire Samuel Zell.</p>
        <p>And already, at least four local bidders, including Begel, who runs a private equity group, and Thomas Mandler, a lawyer whose group lost out to Tribune in its attempt to acquire the Cubs in 1981, have declared their candidacies.</p>
        <p>Others are quietly assembling investors to buy a team that is virtually certain to sell for well over $500 million and almost certainly more than the $660 million that was paid in 2002 for the Boston Red Sox, the most ever for a major league team.</p>
        <p>Jerry Colangelo, the chairman of the Phoenix Suns and the onetime free-spending general partner of the Arizona Diamondbacks, is said to be interested. Mark Cuban, the rambunctious and idiosyncratic Internet billionaire who owns the Dallas Mavericks, said by e-mail that he might be interested in fulfilling the wishes of some Cubs fans for a real hands-on owner. ''Maybe,'' he wrote, ''they have seen me sing 'Take Me Out to the Ball Game' there,'' which he did in 2002.</p>
        <p>A local investment banker, John Canning, who is a limited partner in the Milwaukee Brewers, is also said to be considering a bid.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to work hard to sell the Cubs,'' said Sal Galatioto, an investment banker who said he was representing a group that had not publicly declared its intention to vie for the Cubs. ''You'll hear 50 names by the time this is over. If Tribune can't get a bidding war going, they shouldn't sell it.''</p>
        <p>Even though Tribune did not find a way to get the almost comically cursed Cubs a championship, or even a spot in the World Series, where they have not been since 1945, the company has provided the team with stability. Tribune paid $20.5 million to acquire the team in 1981, five months after a group led by Jerry Reinsdorf acquired the White Sox for $20 million. Since then, 27 teams have changed owners, with the Yankees, in their 35th season under George Steinbrenner, now enjoying the status of being the most continuously owned team in the majors.</p>
        <p>The roster of recent sales includes Arte Moreno's $182.5 million purchase of the Los Angeles Angels, Mark Attanasio's $223 million deal for the Milwaukee Brewers, Frank McCourt's $430 million acquisition of the Los Angeles Dodgers and Ted Lerner's $450 million deal for the Washington Nationals. The pending sale of the Atlanta Braves to Liberty Media by Time Warner, in a complex transaction that has yet to be approved, is worth $460 million to $470 million.</p>
        <p>''The last few years' sales of teams,'' said Bob DuPuy, the president of Major League Baseball, ''reflect a turnaround in industry cash flow and the facts that clubs are viewed as better investments than ever.''</p>
        <p>But the Cubs' sale is poised to tell an even richer story.</p>
        <p>Mandler's group, built from a core of the 100 investors who each pledged $250,000 apiece for the Cubs in a more modest era back in 1981, now requires a minimum personal ante of $1 million to join the bid.</p>
        <p>''Owning the team would be a lifelong dream,'' he said at Monday's game. ''And I want to see a winner in my lifetime.'' Like any Cubs fan, he has a reservoir of pain from the many losing years and from the particularly maddening ones, like 1969, when the Cubs squandered a sizable regular-season lead over the Mets; and 1984, when the Cubs blew a two-game lead in the best-of-five National League Championship Series; and 2003, when the Cubs were five outs from the World Series with a three-run lead and never got there.</p>
        <p>''It's been a good life lesson,'' he said. ''I got married in 1969. If our marriage could survive the collapse of '69, it could survive anything.''</p>
        <p>Just then, Richard Baehr, a management consultant who said he owns a tiny stake in the White Sox but is being ''noodged'' by Mandler to join him, said, ''I hear Steve Bartman just joined your group.''</p>
        <p>Baehr was referring to the Cubs fan who, in the 2003 N.L.C.S., interfered with a foul ball at Wrigley that Cubs left fielder Moises Alou could have caught. If the ball had ended up in Alou's glove, the Cubs would have been four outs from the World Series with a three-run lead. Instead, the roof fell in on the Cubs, and the team and its fans were left to contemplate one more miserable incident of black magic, along with the black cat at Shea Stadium that appeared to symbolize doom for Leo Durocher's Cubs in September 1969, and the hex bestowed in 1945 by the angry owner of a World Series-attending, malodorous goat.</p>
        <p>The collapses, curses and hexes are as much a part of the Cubs as Wrigley Field, where lights were not introduced until 1988; where the brilliance of Ernie Banks and Billy Williams still echoes; where home runs are caught in the street behind left field; where the singing of ''Take Me Out to the Ball Game'' is a major event; where the bleachers are packed; and where there are ushers who know your family and are as likely to take snapshots of fans as fans are likely to take pictures of Wrigley's ''friendly confines.''</p>
        <p>''It's nothing short of amazing, this social/sports experience,'' that helped lead the Cubs to one attendance record after another in the past quarter century, said John McDonough, the team's president and former lead marketer. ''Last year, I said, 'O.K., I got it, the ivy is beautiful, the scoreboard is hand-operated, but it's time to win,' '' he added.</p>
        <p>During the off-season, amid speculation that Tribune might sell the Cubs, team management turned uncharacteristically aggressive with a nearly $300 million spending spree to sign players like outfielder Alfonso Soriano and pitcher Ted Lilly.</p>
        <p>''Some of those contracts are back-loaded, which says they're not spending their money,'' said Mandler, a leading indicator to him that Tribune would sell. McDonough denied the spending was tied to any effort to enhance the team's value.</p>
        <p>Prospective owners like Mandler and Begel are, for now, in the dark about what they can do beyond solidifying their investment groups. Neither Tribune nor Zell has set a timetable to sell the team, which might not happen for seven or eight months, and it is not clear if Wrigley itself will be sold. Owning one without the other sounds like baseball sacrilege, but a long-term lease with generous terms might alleviate a new owner's anxiety about cash flow.</p>
        <p>Still, Begel said that a purchase of the team without the ballpark ''makes no sense.'' ''Without it, there'd have to be a big reduction in the price,'' Mandler said.</p>
        <p>Mandler and Begel have never met. But Mandler wondered aloud on Monday if Begel would like to merge for a joint bid. Later in the game, Begel thought for a moment, then said somewhat reluctantly, ''Give him my number.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
