<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Plays Portray a Couple Bound by Love and Conflict</title>
    <meta content="11tril" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/theater/reviews/11tril.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hutton, Arlene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Geis, Alexandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinbruner, Greg</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Nibroc Trilogy, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Seventy-Eighth Street Theater Lab</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hutton, Arlene</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Geis, Alexandra</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbruner, Greg</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Nibroc Trilogy, The (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D7153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Plays Portray a Couple Bound by Love and Conflict</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Three Plays Portray a Couple Bound by Love and Conflict</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ginia Bellafante reviews Arlene Hutton play The Nibroc Trilogy; Alexandra Geis and Greg Steinbruner star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first of the exquisitely quiet, gently reaching plays in Arlene Hutton's ''Nibroc Trilogy,'' in repertory at the 78th Street Theater Lab, begins with a young woman reading on a train bound from the West Coast at the end of 1940. It is a crowded train, spatially and psychically. The freight cars are carrying the bodies of F. Scott Fitzgerald and Nathanael West, who died within a day of each other, West in a car accident said to have been brought on by the wrecked condition in which his friend Fitzgerald's death had left him.</p>
        <p>The woman, May, is paying tribute to neither writer, appearing distinctly unreceptive to tales of the despoiled American dream. In the rigidity of her body language, in the way she darts her eyes in nervous judgment of anyone who might not possess her character's virtues, the actress Alexandra Geis immediately lets us know that we are in the presence of someone with an unwavering faith in her own rectitude and self-reliance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arlene Hutton’s “Nibroc Trilogy,” in repertory at the 78th Street Theater Lab, ought to be seen by anyone who doubts the capacity of front porch drama to tell a meaningful story beyond its own perimeters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first of the exquisitely quiet, gently reaching plays in Arlene Hutton's ''Nibroc Trilogy,'' in repertory at the 78th Street Theater Lab, begins with a young woman reading on a train bound from the West Coast at the end of 1940. It is a crowded train, spatially and psychically. The freight cars are carrying the bodies of F. Scott Fitzgerald and Nathanael West, who died within a day of each other, West in a car accident said to have been brought on by the wrecked condition in which his friend Fitzgerald's death had left him.</p>
        <p>The woman, May, is paying tribute to neither writer, appearing distinctly unreceptive to tales of the despoiled American dream. In the rigidity of her body language, in the way she darts her eyes in nervous judgment of anyone who might not possess her character's virtues, the actress Alexandra Geis immediately lets us know that we are in the presence of someone with an unwavering faith in her own rectitude and self-reliance.</p>
        <p>The book in May's hands, which a young man named Raleigh (Greg Steinbruner) fatefully comes by to tease her over, provides further clue: it is Lloyd C. Douglas's treacly inspirational, ''The Magnificent Obsession,'' the story of a rogue who applies himself to a life of noble purpose after causing the death of an admired surgeon.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hutton wrote ''Last Train to Nibroc,'' originally performed nearly a decade ago, with no immediate notion to follow the lives of May and Raleigh through the aftermath of World War II and beyond. But that is what she has done. And the reference to ''The Magnificent Obsession'' so early on has the effect, now, of seeming clairvoyant, foreshadowing as it does the themes that carry the trilogy without any of Mr. Douglas's bombast and agenda.</p>
        <p>In the simplest terms, ''Last Train to Nibroc'' and its companion plays, ''See Rock City'' and ''Gulf View Drive,'' which are both making their debuts in New York, examine the grace born of disruption. And they ought to be seen by anyone who doubts the capacity of front porch drama to tell a meaningful story beyond its own perimeters.</p>
        <p>Much of what happens between May and Raleigh literally transpires on benches and porches and patios. Soon after the two meet on the train, they discover that they are from the same small town in eastern Kentucky (Nibroc is the name of a local festival), each from religious if not equally prosperous lineage.</p>
        <p>May and Raleigh at once have everything in common and very little. She aspires to become a missionary; he, a writer in New York. The trilogy's first chapter sees their courtship interrupted by her sanctimony. But there is an essential goodness to her, a generosity of spirit, that emerges to eclipse her lapses into cruel expressions of self-certainty.</p>
        <p>In ''See Rock City,'' the strongest of the plays, and ''Gulf View Drive,'' May and Raleigh evoke the poignancy of two people who cannot easily see how similar their predicaments really are. They tend to understand their ambitions solely in conflict with each other. May, intent on a career and disinclined toward housework, becomes a school principal during the war but finds herself reluctantly having to return to the classroom when men return home to the jobs they left behind. And Raleigh, denied a chance at combat because of his medical history, discovers that missing this defining event of his time is the greatest hindrance to his evolving career as a writer.</p>
        <p>The Nibroc plays never become maudlin, and for this we should also thank Mr. Steinbruner, who denies Raleigh's disappointments any semblance of bitterness or failure. He plays Raleigh with such a natural sense of the character's supreme decency that you begin to think of him as someone who might volunteer to help you move a sofa even if you only met him twice. (And virtually the same could be said of Polly Adams, who does a wonderful job with May's kind, dignified mother, Mrs. Gill.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Hutton herself knows how to keep the forces of melodrama at bay, and she seems to posses the ability to weave the epic and the incidental with the lightest and least obtrusive thread. (In ''Gulf View Drive'' the controversial racial tolerance May displays in her Southern classroom is tested by the prospect of adopting a black child.)</p>
        <p>''The Nibroc Trilogy'' is a portrait of a marriage, a study in the readjusting of expectation. It is also a look at the mid-20th century's shifting cultural landscape. But Ms. Hutton never mistakes theater for social studies, and we are all the better for it.</p>
        <p>''The Nibroc Trilogy'' continues through April 29 at the 78th Street Theater Lab, 236 West 78th Street, Manhattan; 78thStreetTheatreLab.org or (212) 873-9050.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
