<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Bar Makes A Difference</title>
    <meta content="11choc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/11/dining/11choc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chocolate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chocolate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6D7153FF932A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Bar Makes A Difference</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Bar Makes a Difference</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabricant, Florence</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>UNSWEETENED chocolate for baking and cooking no longer needs to be dull-looking, gritty and inedibly bitter. Like bittersweet and semisweet chocolate, high-quality unsweetened chocolate is now widely available. It has a glossy sheen, a silky texture, a rich fragrance and a complex flavor. All this makes a big difference in the result.</p>
        <p>When a recipe calls for unsweetened chocolate, a cook should look for 99 or 100 percent on the label. This score does not represent perfection. It means the bar is pure chocolate, without sugar. These days it can also mean the chocolate has such finesse that it can perhaps be nibbled with an after-dinner black coffee or brandy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Melt it, chop it, whip it into frosting. For home bakers, the quality of chocolate has never been better.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>UNSWEETENED chocolate for baking and cooking no longer needs to be dull-looking, gritty and inedibly bitter. Like bittersweet and semisweet chocolate, high-quality unsweetened chocolate is now widely available. It has a glossy sheen, a silky texture, a rich fragrance and a complex flavor. All this makes a big difference in the result.</p>
        <p>When a recipe calls for unsweetened chocolate, a cook should look for 99 or 100 percent on the label. This score does not represent perfection. It means the bar is pure chocolate, without sugar. These days it can also mean the chocolate has such finesse that it can perhaps be nibbled with an after-dinner black coffee or brandy.</p>
        <p>Today, makers of fine chocolates, like Scharffen Berger, Lindt and Ghirardelli, also make unsweetened chocolate for baking. Break off a piece of one of these bars, or of a 100 percent bar from La Maison du Chocolat or Jacques Torres Chocolate Haven, and despite its unalloyed bitterness it is still full of flavor and aroma. It is velvety smooth as it melts on the palate. These attributes will come at a price, as much as $8 for a three-ounce bar.</p>
        <p>The percentage of chocolate listed on the label, which you will not see on a package of inferior chocolate, tells you something about quality, but not the whole story. Other factors, which vary from brand to brand, are the amount of cocoa butter, which affects viscosity; the type of beans and their source; and whether the manufacturer is offering a single origin chocolate, a single estate chocolate, or a blend.</p>
        <p>How well the cacao components are processed by refining, or grinding, then conching, a gentle cooking process that can last a few hours or several days, also makes a difference. These procedures improve chocolate's texture and viscosity and give the best brands their suave opulence.</p>
        <p>Unsweetened chocolate, which was the first baking chocolate sold in retail stores, is now mostly used in traditional American recipes like the one here for hot fudge sauce or for classic brownies.</p>
        <p>Today, more baking recipes call for bittersweet or semisweet chocolate because they were the first bars imported from Europe, some 20 years ago, to attract the attention of pastry chefs, chocolatiers and home cooks. High-quality bittersweet or semisweet chocolate is labeled 60 percent to 80 percent chocolate. Now, even mass-market brands like Nestlé and Hershey's have introduced high-end lines.</p>
        <p>Federal regulations make no distinction between bittersweet and semisweet chocolate. In fact, they are interchangeable in many recipes.</p>
        <p>Tasting and sniffing various bars are the only ways to determine which chocolate you prefer. But one thing is certain: in recipes that call for more than a smidgen of chocolate, the better the chocolate, the deeper the bow the cook will take.</p>
        <p>HOT FUDGE SAUCE  Adapted from ''Maida Heatter's Book of Great Desserts,'' by Maida Heatter (Alfred A. Knopf, 1974)  Time: 15 minutes</p>
        <p>2 ounces unsweetened chocolate, in pieces  1 tablespoon butter, preferably salted  2 tablespoons light corn syrup  1 cup sugar  1 teaspoon vanilla extract.</p>
        <p>1. Place chocolate, butter and 1/3 cup boiling water in a heavy 2-quart saucepan over very low heat. Stir until chocolate melts and mixture is smooth. Stir in corn syrup and sugar.  2. Increase heat to medium and stir occasionally until mixture comes to a full boil. Stop stirring and allow mixture to boil exactly 8 minutes. Meanwhile, half-fill a bowl that is larger than the saucepan with ice and water. After 8 minutes remove pan from heat and place in ice water to stop cooking. Stir in vanilla.  3. Serve while still warm, or allow to cool, then reheat over hot water or for about 30 seconds in a microwave oven. Sauce must be served warm.  Yield: 1 cup.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
