<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rapture</title>
    <meta content="Bell.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Bell.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Seizure (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E3DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rapture</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rapture</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MADISON SMARTT BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Madison Smartt</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEIZURE</p>
        <p>By Erica Wagner.</p>
        <p>214 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seizures are the least of the problems facing the protagonist of Erica Wagner’s first novel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEIZURE</p>
        <p>By Erica Wagner.</p>
        <p>214 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Janet is a young woman with a seizure disorder -- which partly explains the title of Erica Wagner's first novel. In the beginning, her seizures sound like anxiety attacks: ''A breath of cold metal, high in the back of her throat. The wrong end of a telescope. Was he watching her? She dug her nails into her wrist to hold herself in place, felt her chest rise and fall. She would not go over the edge of it. She would resist.'' But in fact her condition seems more dire, though never precisely diagnosed. A doctor in her childhood advised her: ''Don't tell anyone unless you have to.'' Janet's seizure syndrome becomes one of this novel's set of intricately guarded secrets -- not because she tells no one but because the experience can in no way be shared.</p>
        <p>She seems settled happily enough, in a city resembling London, with a violinist lover named Stephen, and a consuming, though weakly specified, public service job. Yet Wagner's dense, expert writing drenches Janet in neurasthenic sensitivity, spinning her affect all awry. She is most ill at ease in her comfortable world. In first person, Janet dreams of visiting her mother's grave: ''I can't see what is written on her gravestone because she is resting against it, as if it were the headboard of a bed.''</p>
        <p>''You found me,'' the mother says.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't looking,'' Janet replies.</p>
        <p>In her waking life, third-person Janet learns that her mother, whom she believes to have been killed in an accident very early in her own childhood, has only recently died, leaving her a seaside property in the north of England, a house with a name: ''The Shieling.'' For all its resonance, this title suggests no grand manor, according to the Oxford English Dictionary, but some rough shelter constructed on the edge of a pasture.</p>
        <p>Then there is Tom, who works as a mechanic in a remote northern area, welds beach-combed metal into rough sculptures by night and inhabits a small stone cottage with no electricity and a fireplace for heat, in the midst of sheep grazing at the edge of the sea. He is a natural solitary; his relationships with women don't last long and his boss at the garage suggests that others find him frightening, but Tom is at home in the world like an animal. Though not especially reflective, he has rich memories of his childhood, exclusively spent with his single mother, who wandered from place to place with him, binding him to herself with the darkest of folk tales: the selkie, the false knight on the road, a strikingly sinister variation on ''Beauty and the Beast.'' Scenes of his mother telling Tom these stories, in the most delicate, elaborate detail, form a counterpoint to Janet's recollections of her childhood spent alone with her father, who knew only one fairy tale, about how he had met and won her lost mother.</p>
        <p>Most readers won't have much trouble descrying, from a long way off, the point these four narrative arrows are destined to strike. But perhaps Wagner, the literary editor of The Times of London and the author of a previous book of stories, doesn't mean to disguise the target. Sometimes the most wracking suspense comes from knowing what is going to happen and watching it happen just that way.</p>
        <p>So of course Janet's inherited Shieling does turn out to be the cottage where Tom is already living, where his mother brought him, near the end of their gypsy wanderings. They converge into the narrow space as if competing for space in the same womb. ''Get out of my house,'' Janet orders him though she herself has barely arrived. ''This is private property. It is my property. I am not going to say it again. You will leave now.'' She tries to attack him, breaking a glass and cutting her palm on a shard of it. Tom, more stolid in his resistance, treats her wound. ''And I am telling you that I am not going. You don't know that this isn't my place as much as it is yours. I want to know why you came here. I'm asking you for a simple thing.''</p>
        <p>Janet does not call the law as she's threatened to do. She calls Stephen to tell him she's fine. ''Her phone, small and light with its green, glittering single eye, was still in her hand. She bent down and set it carefully on the stone floor, and then she lifted her foot and put her heel against it. Her weight transferred: one clean crack and then the thing came apart under her sole.'' With that, the world outside the space these two occupy disappears. When Tom and Janet make love the scene is so rendered that neither of them nor the reader can be certain if it is rape (though everyone does have reason enough to think it might be incest). Always cutting close to emotional nuance, here Wagner drives her scalpel through the outer layers of desire and attraction and into the deepest dark current of erotic need.</p>
        <p>''When I have a seizure, where am I?'' Janet asks herself. ''Do I become the seizure? I feel that I do, that I am vaporized metal, electricity, air, that I could be a bright hot gas flame with all of my senses burnt away by fear, burnt away by myself.'' Confronted by Janet's seizures, Stephen retreats behind a buffer of affectionate concern, becoming her caretaker, while Tom enters the seizure itself to become her lover. Seizure, rapture and possession become one and the same thing.</p>
        <p>One senses that it took a very witchy mother to prepare her two children for this encounter. ''Awful stories,'' Tom remembers, ''they weren't stories for a child.'' They are all about betrayal, abandonment and the most rending kinds of transformation. Tom to Janet: ''I guess you'd say they were about love.'' Janet, meanwhile, has her own notion of narrative. ''Your life was a structure. You built it yourself and then you climbed, building as you went, higher and higher, until you couldn't see the base anymore, couldn't even recall if you had used stone or brick or straw and mud.'' And sometimes the most exquisite rapture comes from burning that whole house down.</p>
        <p>Madison Smartt Bell's most recent books are ''Toussaint Louverture: A Biography'' and ''The Stone That the Builder Refused,'' a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Madison Smartt Bell's most recent books are ''Toussaint Louverture: A Biography'' and ''The Stone That the Builder Refused,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
