<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Selig and Baseball, It Was a Very Good Year</title>
    <meta content="08chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/baseball/08chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Selig, Bud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DC143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Selig and Baseball, It Was a Very Good Year</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Selig and Baseball, It Was a Very Good Year</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The story goes that when Babe Ruth demanded an $80,000 salary for the 1931 season, he was reminded that the sum was more than President Herbert Hoover made ($75,000). ''Yeah,'' Ruth supposedly responded, ''but I had a better year than he did.''</p>
        <p>Even though Alex Rodriguez won the American League Most Valuable Player award in 2005, Bud Selig had a better year than Rodriguez, so why shouldn't he have earned $14.5 million that year? Selig's stipend was slightly more than half A-Rod's $26 million salary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clubs sign mediocre free-agent pitchers to ridiculous contracts because they can afford to. Who needs to put a lid on salaries and payrolls when everyone is doing so well?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The story goes that when Babe Ruth demanded an $80,000 salary for the 1931 season, he was reminded that the sum was more than President Herbert Hoover made ($75,000). ''Yeah,'' Ruth supposedly responded, ''but I had a better year than he did.''</p>
        <p>Even though Alex Rodriguez won the American League Most Valuable Player award in 2005, Bud Selig had a better year than Rodriguez, so why shouldn't he have earned $14.5 million that year? Selig's stipend was slightly more than half A-Rod's $26 million salary.</p>
        <p>The Sports Business Journal quoted a sports compensation consultant as saying that the salaries of baseball executives were ''astonishingly high,'' when reporting last week on Selig's salary. It obtained the figure from Major League Baseball's tax return. But chief executives of major corporations earn far more than Selig, with their income based on their production.</p>
        <p>Selig's salary, too, is linked to his production, and the owners who determined his salary based it on criteria they created. They like the growth in attendance, which exceeded 76 million last season for a record, and they like the money that is pouring into baseball's bank account.</p>
        <p>In 1992, when Selig became acting commissioner, M.L.B.'s gross revenue was $1.2 billion. It was $5.2 billion last year, is projected to be at least $5.6 billion this year and is expected to reach $6 billion in 2008.</p>
        <p>Revenue from Major League Baseball Advanced Media has gone through the proverbial roof. In 2009, baseball will start its new cable television channel with 40 million subscribers committed from the start.</p>
        <p>Baseball is making so much money it has negotiated two consecutive labor agreements with the players union without a strike or lockout and without a demand for a payroll cap. Who needs to put a lid on salaries and payrolls when everyone is doing so well?</p>
        <p>Clubs may still sign mediocre free-agent pitchers to ridiculous contracts, but they do it because they can afford to.</p>
        <p>Selig, who would rather not have his salary discussed publicly (no, his wife knows what he earns; that's not the reason), declined to discuss it publicly.</p>
        <p>''I don't really have anything to say,'' he said. ''I have no comment.''</p>
        <p>For free-market advocates who believe that players should be able to make as much as they can, why shouldn't commissioners also make as much as they can? Just as Barry Zito didn't point a bazooka at the San Francisco Giants and demand $126 million from them, Selig didn't tell the owners what they had to give him.</p>
        <p>He did the job for $5 million a year, but like a player, he's not going to say no to $14.5 million. In fact, as long as he remains healthy and the owners want him to stay in office, Selig will most likely accept a contract extension to keep him on the job beyond the 2009 season, despite his pronouncement last year that he would retire then.</p>
        <p>The prospect of a healthy Selig retiring is as unlikely as a breathing George Steinbrenner turning over the Yankees to Steve Swindal, even when Swindal was a son-in-law in good standing.</p>
        <p>Red Sox Close the Gap</p>
        <p>On the subject of salaries, the Red Sox have narrowed their payroll gap with the Yankees. A year ago the teams began the season $74.7 million apart ($195.2 million to $120.5 million). They began this season $39.3 million apart ($182.4 million to $143.1 million).</p>
        <p>The Yankees' payroll includes only $15.6 million for Alex Rodriguez. The Texas Rangers will pay him $7.1 million in salary and a $1 million share of his signing bonus.</p>
        <p>Who's a Rookie?</p>
        <p>Daisuke Matsuzaka put his baseball pants on one leg at a time Thursday when he made his major league debut, but otherwise he was everything the Boston Red Sox hoped he would be for their $103.1 million. He stifled Kansas City on one run and six hits as he walked 1 and struck out 10 (74 strikes, 34 balls) in seven innings.</p>
        <p>His performance was so good that it raises the question that comes up every time a Japanese player performs well in his first year in the major leagues: Should he be his league's rookie of the year?</p>
        <p>The Baseball Writers' Association of America considers such players rookies even though they have played in the Japanese major leagues for years. Hideo Nomo won the award in 1995, Kazuhiro Sasaki in 2000 and Ichiro Suzuki in 2001. But Hideki Matsui did not win in 2003 because some voters ignored the established guidelines and decided on their own that Matsui, the Yankees' left fielder, wasn't a rookie.</p>
        <p>Before Matsuzaka suffers a similar experience, the association should decide to change the rule or make sure the writers it appoints as voters follow the existing rule and not reject Matsuzaka unilaterally.</p>
        <p>In his next step toward the rookie award as well as possible others, Matsuzaka is scheduled to pitch against Seattle at Fenway Park on Tuesday night. The first batter he will face: Suzuki.</p>
        <p>Pirates Off and Running</p>
        <p>In a spring training conversation about the team he manages, Jim Tracy expressed hope that the Pittsburgh Pirates could start this season the way they ended last season. The Pirates lost 60 of their first 90 games last season, then won 37 of their last 72. They also won 16 of their last 22 one-run games after losing 25 of their first 33.</p>
        <p>In starting this season, the Pirates swept a three-game series from the Houston Astros, winning the second and third games by a run each.</p>
        <p>Opening Day Tidbits</p>
        <p>Elias Sports Bureau uncovered some intriguing opening day developments worth noting:</p>
        <p>Elijah Dukes, Tampa Bay's rookie center fielder, was the 99th player to hit a home run in his first official major league at-bat, but the first to do it at Yankee Stadium on opening day.</p>
        <p>Tony Peña Jr., Kansas City's rookie shortstop and son of the Yankees coach Tony Peña, became the first player to hit two opening-day triples since Tommy Henrich did it for the Yankees in 1950.</p>
        <p>Marcus and Brian Giles of San Diego became the first brothers to bat first and second in a starting lineup since Matty and Jesús Alou of San Francisco in 1965.</p>
        <p>Félix Hernández of Seattle became only the fourth pitcher since 1900 to start and win an opener when he wasn't yet 21 years old. The last to do it? Fernando Valenzuela for Los Angeles in 1981.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
