<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Poet of Exile</title>
    <meta content="Logan.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Logan.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Walcott, Derek</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Selected Poems (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Poet of Exile</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Poet of Exile</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM LOGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Logan, William</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SELECTED POEMS By Derek Walcott. Edited by Edward Baugh. 307 pp. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For more than half a century Derek Walcott has remained a poet of divided loyalties and a double tongue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SELECTED POEMS By Derek Walcott. Edited by Edward Baugh. 307 pp. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $25.</p>
        <p>Poets behave like conquistadors wherever they roam, picking up a new verse form, a lover, some inventive cursing, a disease. Would Byron have been Byron without Italy and Greece? What would Eliot and Pound have become without the hostility of London? Can we imagine Hart Crane without the Caribbean or Elizabeth Bishop without Rio? Derek Walcott has crossed so many borders, his poems read like a much-thumbed Baedeker. To a boy born on St. Lucia, the rhythms and intonations of English verse were a passport to the elsewhere; but they came with a burden -- the language of the colonial masters was not the one caught in his ear at home. ''How choose,'' he wrote, ''Between this Africa and the English tongue I love? / Betray them both, or give back what they give?''</p>
        <p>Walcott's new ''Selected Poems'' begins with poems of disturbing self-confidence -- amused, self-mocking, mildly self-hating, his youthful work is filled with language that eases itself off the tongue (if some tongues are silver, his must be platinum). A powerful maker of phrases from the start, he adopted the English of an empire that, having once painted the map red, was slowly being dismantled: the ruins of a great house, ''Whose moth-like girls are mixed with candledust, / Remain to file the lizard's dragonish claws. / The mouths of those gate cherubs shriek with stain.''</p>
        <p>Walcott had barely been noticed before he became noted. By his mid 30s, he was composing a verse autobiography (an act of hubris akin to a pop star writing his life at 19). ''Another Life'' (1973) is a pretentious, pressure-cooker affair, a tour de force fatally uneasy with itself. (Surely you give a few hostages to describe yourself as a prodigy, even if a ''prodigy of the wrong age and colour.'') At times it reads like ''The Prelude'' by a writer far more elegant than Wordsworth, though almost every line about the poet himself sounds false:</p>
        <p>Afternoon light ripened the valley,</p>
        <p>rifling smoke climbed from small</p>
        <p>labourers' houses,</p>
        <p>and I dissolved into a trance.</p>
        <p>I was seized by a pity more profound</p>
        <p>than my young body could bear, I climbed</p>
        <p>with the labouring smoke,</p>
        <p>I drowned in labouring breakers of bright</p>
        <p>cloud,</p>
        <p>then uncontrollably I began to weep,</p>
        <p>inwardly, without tears, with a serene</p>
        <p>extinction</p>
        <p>of all sense; I felt compelled to kneel,</p>
        <p>I wept for nothing and for everything.</p>
        <p>This idea of compassion requires a lot of scenery-chewing. (One hopes the houses were small, not the laborers.)</p>
        <p>Most poets compromise between the diction of the poems they love, often centuries old, and the language they hear in the streets (the tin-eared poems in island patois have been among Walcott's least successful); but, for the exile, language is a daily form of betrayal. Walcott has remained a figure of divided loyalties and a double tongue -- his grandmothers were descended from slaves, his grandfathers white. Though he ''prayed / nightly for his flesh to change, / his dun flesh peeled white,'' like any young man of parts he was somewhat enamored of himself. Even the late verse can seem shallow and narcissistic, beauty seized in his own beautiful eye -- he treats women (''O Beauty, you are the light of the world!'') in a manner closer to lechery than to old-style courtesy. Caught between two races and two worlds, he has sometimes succumbed to pride or self-pity, or to that pride indistinguishable from self-pity.</p>
        <p>Although his taste for the sententious remark has never quite abated (''To change your language you must change your life,'' ''There is no harder prison than writing verse''), Walcott grew able to tame the rhetoric that, like a forest fire, occasionally roared out of control. He became the most striking poet of seascapes since Coleridge (between them lie only a few lines in ''The Waste Land''), rivaling the older poet's sense of the uncanny.</p>
        <p>I saw men with rusty eyeholes like</p>
        <p>cannons,</p>
        <p>and whenever their half-naked crews</p>
        <p>cross the sun,</p>
        <p>right through their tissue, you traced</p>
        <p>their bones</p>
        <p>like leaves against the sunlight; frigates,</p>
        <p>barquentines,</p>
        <p>the backward-moving current swept them</p>
        <p>on,</p>
        <p>and high on their decks I saw great</p>
        <p>admirals,</p>
        <p>Rodney, Nelson, de Grasse.</p>
        <p>This is no mere practiced and prettified version of ''The Rime of the Ancient Mariner'' -- later poets learn their craft from earlier; but they must provide the originality themselves, in resistance to what they learn.</p>
        <p>Walcott's most fluid and achieved work lies in the books from ''Sea Grapes'' (1976) through ''The Arkansas Testament'' (1987), where a mature intelligence no longer wrestles with language like an Antaeus, but subdues it by being subdued. ''Midsummer'' (1984) long seemed to me the exception, a laggard book of hours by an author too often at his desk. Reading the selection here, I realize I missed something. Without the shape of the lyric subject, Walcott's poetry becomes the registration of sensibility -- and in texture and sensibility he has been a master, even if the redolently patterned verse has sometimes been laid down like linoleum. Overstuffed with images, his languid, occasionally lackadaisical style is more in love with words than with what they represent. He's a better poet when just mulling things over, in a louche beachcomber-ish way -- when he talks politics, the taste seems bitter in his mouth.</p>
        <p>The colonized, decolonized islands, victims of what Walcott calls ''the leprosy of empire,'' have been taken up by scholars in subaltern studies, postcolonial studies and studies whose very names are subject to rancorous argument. The poet too often borrows the academic's gassy editorials (''the politicians plod / without imagination'') and self-service sentiments (''poetry is still treason / because it is truth''). If he had not invented himself, academia would have had to invent him. In condensed form, Walcott believes that the British Empire was bad, except where it was good, and English literature good, except where it was bad. His islands are ravishing but painterly, observed with a detachment that leaves him more a tourist than a fortunate traveler, not a man who got away but one who was never quite there.</p>
        <p>Many critics see Walcott's major achievement as ''Omeros'' (1990), a version of the Homeric epics translated to the Caribbean, the Trojan War reimagined as a struggle between two fishermen, Achille and Hector, over a woman named Helen. Despite imperious passages of broken terza rima, this epic of nearly 8,000 lines is spoiled by its clumsy narration (Walcott can never tell a story without losing his way in lovely detail), the black characters bloated with the poet's ambition, the white no more than ludicrous caricatures. Whether describing a man's scar ''puckered like the corolla / of a sea-urchin'' or an egret that ''stabs and stabs the mud with one lifting foot,'' Walcott never met a metaphor he didn't like -- or, indeed, that a reader wouldn't love. But a tale can't eat only rubies.</p>
        <p>Walcott's most frequently announced emotion is joy, a joy that rarely seems joyous -- his eye lacks nothing but a touch of sympathy (he could turn cancer into a bauble from Tiffany's). He has become a man for whom introspection never seems natural, though perhaps we've had too many poets confessing every sin under the sun (Walcott has none of Lowell's ravaging candor or unsettling mildness). He started as a painter, his failure likely the making of him as a poet; but the words sometimes seem mere daubs, skillfully pushed around the canvas while the pictures remain dead at the center.</p>
        <p>In the years since his Nobel Prize, Walcott's work has been haunted by the dissolutions of mortality -- ''The Prodigal'' (2004), his most recent book, sounds exhausted in its exits. He seems almost unmoved when taking the roll call of the dead, even when writing of the death of his twin brother; but when that reserve almost breaks down, as in his elegy for Joseph Brodsky, it produces some of his finest poems:</p>
        <p>+</p>
        <p>The last leaves fell like notes from a</p>
        <p>piano</p>
        <p>and left their ovals echoing in the ear;</p>
        <p>with gawky music stands, the winter</p>
        <p>forest</p>
        <p>looks like an empty orchestra, its</p>
        <p>lines</p>
        <p>ruled on these scattered manuscripts</p>
        <p>of snow.</p>
        <p>These self-devouring figures, turning the toolkit of poetry into metaphor (the cane fields are ''set in stanzas,'' his ''ocean kept turning blank pages''), speak to something almost unsaid -- writing was Walcott's escape from the islands. The metaphors whisper their quiet acknowledgment of guilt.</p>
        <p>Edward Baugh, the Jamaican poet who has edited this modest selection, has slapped on a slightly embarrassing fan's introduction, gushing about poems that are a ''distillation from the harvest'' and claiming that ''reading Walcott is also an adventure in poetic form and style.'' These are the metaphors of a vodka salesman and an army recruiter. Few poets have been lavished with greater gifts than Walcott; but much of his later work has been unadventurous (and undistilled), full of stock passages and stale opinions. He arrived at a few views when young and has trotted them out ever since. There are always marvelous passages, passages most poets would sell their souls for; but there are too many pages whose marvels have become all too routine.</p>
        <p>The poetry of exile begins in sorrow. No matter how awful Rome, the Black Sea will never seem like home (when you have to go home, the landscape is what has to take you in). Walcott has captured his islands with a lushness and richness rare in our poetry -- the outposts of empire once seemed as strange as Kipling's India or Bishop's Brazil. If air travel has brought them closer, it has brought their tragedies closer as well. No living poet has written verse more delicately rendered or distinguished than Walcott, though few individual poems seem destined to be remembered. For more than half a century he has served as our poet of exile -- a man almost without a country, unless the country lies wherever he has landed, in flight from himself.h</p>
        <p>William Logan is a poet and critic whose most recent books are ''The Whispering Gallery'' and ''The Undiscovered Country.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William Logan is a poet and critic whose most recent books are ''The Whispering Gallery'' and ''The Undiscovered Country.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
