<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bricks, Mortar And Priorities</title>
    <meta content="l08herbert" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Works</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DF143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bricks, Mortar And Priorities</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Our Crumbling Foundation,'' by Bob Herbert (column, April 5):</p>
        <p>Our federal, state and local governments seem still to be guided by the outdated principles of ''planned obsolescence.'' If a school, levee, highway or bridge is crumbling, build a new one. Finance it with bonds for our children to pay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Our Crumbling Foundation,'' by Bob Herbert (column, April 5):</p>
        <p>Our federal, state and local governments seem still to be guided by the outdated principles of ''planned obsolescence.'' If a school, levee, highway or bridge is crumbling, build a new one. Finance it with bonds for our children to pay.</p>
        <p>Over 50 years ago, I went to the oldest public high school in New Orleans. The brick building still stands there on Canal Street needing repairs, but it is stronger than many of the newer structures passing for schools today.</p>
        <p>Our crumbling foundations are also a dangerous symbol that we have lost whatever sense of history and continuity we might have once had and will now accept a disposable society.</p>
        <p>Disposable buildings, levees, roads, cities and even people. Our foundation is crumbling, and it's more than just bricks and mortar that we are losing.</p>
        <p>Theodore S. Voelker  Copake, N.Y., April 5, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The bill for the last generation's planning mistakes is now coming due. Spread-out housing and scattered jobs require more driving and longer pipes. With suburbs already in place, we find that widening heavily traveled roads and laying utilities beneath them is much more expensive than building on empty farmland.</p>
        <p>Closing the gap between infrastructure costs and revenues requires a push from both sides. New revenues are badly needed, but they have to be spent more wisely than in past decades.</p>
        <p>The focus should be on improving old and new urban centers with better mass transit, underground electric and phone wires, and new services like community-wide Wi-Fi access.</p>
        <p>Buyers of new tract houses and office parks should pay for the longer highways, pipes and wires that spread-out development demands; they should no longer be subsidized by taxpayers and utility ratepayers who live in denser communities that are more economically and environmentally efficient.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Ross  Bethesda, Md., April 5, 2007</p>
        <p>The writer is vice president of Action Committee for Transit, a Maryland citizen advocacy group.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Bob Herbert says Americans ''may have to wait for another New Orleans'' before taking seriously the problem of our nation's crumbling infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Our leaders haven't raised federal taxes to help New Orleans and the Gulf Coast recover from Katrina, to fight the war in Iraq or to help New York City recover from 9/11. The effects of underfinancing are well documented in Iraq and New Orleans.</p>
        <p>New York, with its wealth created as a central node in the global economy, managed to recover by combining federal aid with significantly raised local taxes.</p>
        <p>Our tax-cutting national leaders have sacrificed the long-term health of America's infrastructure for short-term political gains. Instead of waiting for another disaster to roll out underfinanced recovery programs in front of the cameras, they should begin the unsexy work of consensus-building and demanding shared sacrifice from all taxpayers for the monumental infrastructure costs we all should pay.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Carey  Astoria, Queens, April 5, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
