<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Farmar Does Double Duty For Lakers and D-Fenders</title>
    <meta content="08glass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/basketball/08glass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFF THE GLASS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EEDC143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Farmar Does Double Duty For Lakers and D-Fenders</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Farmar Does Double Duty for Lakers and D-Fenders</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most eventful day of Jordan Farmar's professional basketball career started at 7:45 in the morning and ended at 9:45 at night.</p>
        <p>It included trips to basketball facilities in two cities, a morning shoot-around, a short nap, two pregame warm-up sessions, an afternoon shower, a wardrobe change and more than 48 minutes of game action. And it ended with a blithe request from Mitch Kupchak, the general manager of the Los Angeles Lakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last Sunday, Jordan Farmar, a 21-year-old rookie point guard for the Lakers, became the first to play in the Development League and the N.B.A. on the same day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most eventful day of Jordan Farmar's professional basketball career started at 7:45 in the morning and ended at 9:45 at night.</p>
        <p>It included trips to basketball facilities in two cities, a morning shoot-around, a short nap, two pregame warm-up sessions, an afternoon shower, a wardrobe change and more than 48 minutes of game action. And it ended with a blithe request from Mitch Kupchak, the general manager of the Los Angeles Lakers.</p>
        <p>''I kidded him and said, 'Seven o'clock meeting in the morning,' '' Kupchak said. ''And he kind of looked at me like, 'Huh?' ''</p>
        <p>Last Sunday, Farmar, a 21-year-old rookie point guard for the Lakers, became the first to play in the Development League and the N.B.A. on the same day.</p>
        <p>After scoring 18 points in nearly 41 minutes for the Lakers' D-League affiliate, the D-Fenders, Farmar scored 4 points in seven and a half minutes during the Lakers' victory over the Sacramento Kings. Both games were in the Staples Center in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>For Farmar, who fell out of the Lakers' rotation, the feat was business as usual -- almost.</p>
        <p>''It reminds you of growing up, playing traveling team basketball,'' he said in a recent telephone interview. ''You play two, three games in a day.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't too tired. It started catching up with me three, four days down the road.''</p>
        <p>The unique double duty was an idea that started with the Lakers' basketball operations staff, which was looking for a way to bolster Farmar's confidence and get him back into a playing rhythm. By playing with the D-Fenders, he had more shots and an opportunity for more playing time.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a chance for him to let it all hang out,'' D-Fenders Coach Dan Panaggio said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The jury is still out on whether Farmar has benefited from this experience. (He repeated the feat Tuesday, playing 33 minutes in a D-Fenders game, then 12 minutes for the Lakers against Denver.) If nothing else, Lakers Coach Phil Jackson seems to have shown more confidence in Farmar by increasing his minutes.</p>
        <p>Playing for the D-Fenders and the Lakers on the same day is as much a physical strain as it is a mental one. Farmar said he had to adjust to being a star for the D-Fenders, then a role player for the Lakers. For many young players, being sent to the D-League might be an ominous first step out of the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>But Farmar said it felt good to know ''I wasn't getting sent down because I wasn't good enough, and wasn't going to miss any time with the Lakers.''</p>
        <p>The Lakers are the only N.B.A. team to own and operate their D-League franchise. They bought the D-Fenders to groom players in their triangle offense, develop coaches and gain an upper hand on scouting the D-League.</p>
        <p>Little could they have known that they would also make history.</p>
        <p>OFF THE GLASS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
