<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING IN/Milford Center, Conn.; There's a History to All This History</title>
    <meta content="08livi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/realestate/08livi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Living In | Milford Center, Conn."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Milford Center (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE7DE173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING IN/Milford Center, Conn.; There's a History to All This History</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">There’s a History to All This History</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. HUGHES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hughes, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Living In article on Milford Center, Conn; maps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS suburbs stretch farther and farther out, the beachy Long Island Sound city of Milford, an hour and a half from New York City and an easy trip to places like New Haven and Stamford, finds itself changing in character -- shifting, for many, from second-home destination to home sweet home.</p>
        <p>Nowhere has this shift been more noticeable than in the historic neighborhood at the heart of the city, Milford Center -- where, in recent years, making changes to facades and outdoor spaces has gotten a lot more procedure-bound.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As suburbs stretch farther and farther out, the beachy Long Island Sound city of Milford finds itself changing in character.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS suburbs stretch farther and farther out, the beachy Long Island Sound city of Milford, an hour and a half from New York City and an easy trip to places like New Haven and Stamford, finds itself changing in character -- shifting, for many, from second-home destination to home sweet home.</p>
        <p>Nowhere has this shift been more noticeable than in the historic neighborhood at the heart of the city, Milford Center -- where, in recent years, making changes to facades and outdoor spaces has gotten a lot more procedure-bound.</p>
        <p>With its population of 10,000 making up 18 percent of Milford's total 55,000, Milford Center has several microneighborhoods of historical interest: one in its northern reaches that received historic designation in 1977; a second, in the southeast, on Gulf Street, that some preservationists see as the next worthwhile project; and a third, in the south, given historic designation only last month, with Lafayette, Pond and High Streets as its rough boundaries.</p>
        <p>Last month, residents within that area voted by three to one to set rules governing the look of the district's 125 buildings -- in effect, to give zoning laws more teeth. Their motivation: Seeing condos and high-end rentals springing up in some parts of the neighborhood, and wondering whether some of its pre-Revolution-era homes could fall to developers.</p>
        <p>Given that concern, said Thomas Wade, who moved to Milford Center six months ago from Devon, in western Milford, any potential hassles from the new rules are negligible. ''At least now we know that they're not going to tear down the homes across the street,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wade and his wife, Melissa, paid $460,000 for their Colonial Revival home, a two-story wood-sided house built around 1900, he said. It has four bedrooms, two baths, and a quarter-acre lot. It needs a new kitchen but, at 1,700 square feet, is 60 percent larger than their old house.</p>
        <p>And just as important as extra room is a smoother commute for Mr. Wade, who works in an investment bank in Stamford. Now, instead of driving to the train station and scrambling for a rare no-pay spot, he can walk across the city green to the station in five minutes.</p>
        <p>''I won't touch my car in a week,'' he said. ''I have to fire the engine on weekends to keep it in good shape.''</p>
        <p>The new rules, which have yet to be formalized, will ban certain changes unless they conform to existing styles. Although modern materials like vinyl siding were prohibited in the 1977 district, they may be allowed in this one, because the district is close enough to the water to be a threat to wooden siding.</p>
        <p>Not everyone likes the idea of these rules. Thomas Thorndike, for one, says he is opposed to historic districts on principle but also because he lives on Gulf Street, where Milford Center's third such district might someday exist.</p>
        <p>''I want to live in the most luxurious home I can without anybody bothering it,'' said Mr. Thorndike, who last month paid $1.85 million for an 1890s three-story Queen Anne, with five bedrooms, five and a half baths, and 4,500 square feet.</p>
        <p>In fact, he's now building a 2,400-square-foot garage, which almost certainly would be in violation, should a historic district be instituted, said Mr. Thorndike, who works as a financial adviser in Woodbury. ''I don't want to live in a museum.''</p>
        <p>Nancy Bodick, a lifelong resident, remembers when the neighborhood was anything but, having lived through the decline in the 1960s. Ms. Bodickowns one of five local marinas, the Milford Boat Works, a 200-slip site that her grandfather founded on a former coal yard in 1946.</p>
        <p>Her house, an 1840 Greek Revival with two bedrooms, one and a half baths and 2,000 square feet, cost $50,000 in 1986 -- though at that point, ''you couldn't walk inside without a respirator,'' she said. After a $150,000 renovation, which removed everything but the exterior walls and the staircases, the home could sell for $600,000 today, Ms. Bodick said.</p>
        <p>''I like the old trees and the setbacks here,'' she said. ''But maybe I'm just a creature of habit.''</p>
        <p>What You'll Find</p>
        <p>Milford Center's boundaries roughly follow the stockade that fortified it in the 17th century, stretching from the harbor to Boston Post Road, and cut into two sections by train tracks across its middle.</p>
        <p>The northern historic district, clustered along North Street, has saltboxes and Italianates facing a necklace of parks with a pair of ponds fed by the Wepawaug River. Its homes, with roomy porches and deep lots, tend to stay in families for generations, though the Capes on West Town Street and colonials along Founders Way change hands more frequently, according to brokers.</p>
        <p>To the south is the recently designated historic district -- and east of that, along Gulf Street, is the third area appealing to preservationists. There, homes marked with plaques detailing original residents are found alongside newer ranch-style houses.</p>
        <p>New construction is spread throughout Milford Center, especially downtown, on the sites of former warehouses and factories.</p>
        <p>As for rentals, six of the eight apartment buildings that the Smith Craft Real Estate Corporation owns in the city are in Milford Center. There are 218 one- and two-bedrooms, some with expensive finishes, and most under three years old.</p>
        <p>Their vacancy rate is below 1 percent, said Milly Beyer, a leasing agent with Spinnaker Property Management, and units are planned for Railroad and Noble Avenues.</p>
        <p>But the city has so far rejected Smith Craft's plan to build apartments on Prospect Street in Milford Center, a plan that residents and brokers say galvanized the creation of the recent historic district.</p>
        <p>What You'll Pay</p>
        <p>Milford lays claim to having the longest shoreline in Connecticut, but Milford Center itself doesn't have much waterfront property -- and the lack acts as a price curb.</p>
        <p>Single-family homes typically cost $275,000 to $1 million, with an average of $475,000, according to Stephanie Ellison, a broker associate with Re/Max Right Choice, who has been selling area homes for 22 years.</p>
        <p>For that amount, she said, a buyer gets a mid-1800s home with three bedrooms, one and a half baths and 1,800 square feet. Though lots are small, the typical buyer usually doesn't mind. ''These aren't people who hang around in the yard,'' Ms. Ellison said. ''A lot of these buyers own boats, which they use a lot.''</p>
        <p>In September, the Attolino Development Group opened the sales office for the Anchorage at Shipyard Lane, a clutch of luxury condos with harbor views, rising above a baseball field on New Haven Avenue.</p>
        <p>There are 16 units in the development, ranging from 1,700-square-foot one-bedrooms to 2,200-square-foot two-bedrooms, and priced from $469,900 to $824,900, said Kristen Attolino, a sales associate with Coldwell Banker Moves. None have sold yet, though Ms. Attolino is betting that as spring progresses, ''people are going to like the in-town location and love that they're near trains, restaurants and the beach.''</p>
        <p>Renters pay about $1,200 for an 800-square-foot one-bedroom -- a bargain compared with prices in places like Fairfield, with similar commuting distances to New York.</p>
        <p>What to Do</p>
        <p>After a 20-year lull, Milford's main downtown in Milford Center is pulsing with activity, chockablock with boutiques selling hand-made jewelry, rare books, and bicycles.</p>
        <p>In just the last two years, the Downtown Milford Business Association's dues-paying membership has more than doubled, to 86 from 42. Most are mom-and-pop shops, offering a contrast to nearby Westport, where high commercial rents have forced outmany independent retailers, according to Susan Shaw, the association's president.</p>
        <p>The streets really bustle after dark. It is not uncommon to find three restaurants within the same two blocks, each providing live music. One, Daniel Street, which opened in 2005, has either a band or a comedian five nights a week.</p>
        <p>The neighborhood also has a Center for the Arts, a 100-seat auditorium and gallery space that since 1995 has operated out of a former train station building. According to William Meddick, executive director of the Milford Fine Arts Council, its plays and jazz offerings are popular enough that it recently began offering subscriptions.</p>
        <p>The Schools</p>
        <p>The neighborhood has three public elementary schools for kindergarten through Grade 5: Meadowside, Orange Avenue and Mathewson.</p>
        <p>Harborside is the only public middle school, but there are two public high schools -- Joseph A. Foran and Jonathan Law, each with roughly the same enrollment, about 1,050.</p>
        <p>Similarly, both offer about a dozen Advanced Placement classes a year, depending on interest, including economics, European history and Latin. Tennis, football and gymnastics are some of the 14 varsity sports, and after-school clubs focus on dance, foreign language and politics.</p>
        <p>SAT scores are slightly higher at Foran, which averaged 512 on math and 521 on verbal in 2005, compared with state averages of 512 math and 510 verbal. At Law, students scored 504 on math and 510 on verbal.</p>
        <p>In 2005, 83 percent of Foran graduates and 81.5 percent of Law graduates attended four- or two-year colleges, said Larry Schaefer, the city's acting superintendent.</p>
        <p>The History</p>
        <p>Tucked between New Haven and Fairfield Counties, though somewhat removed in spirit from both, Milford has had an independent streak since the earliest days, existing for a few years as its own colony, after being settled by Boston transplants in 1639.</p>
        <p>When the earliest settlers died, they were buried without headstones, though the city later memorialized them by carving their names into the pink granite bridge, built in 1889, that arches dramatically through downtown, said Richard N. Platt Jr., the city historian. His ancestors Richard and Mary Platt earned spots.</p>
        <p>The Commute</p>
        <p>Westbound rush-hour trains take about 40 minutes to get to Stamford, and a monthly round-trip pass costs $87.22 online, slightly more at the station. Monthlies to New York, meanwhile, cost $345.94 online.</p>
        <p>Because Milford is far enough from most commuter destinations, passengers can usually get a seat in the morning, although that's not always true coming the other way. A recent state proposal to do away with one afternoon train was rejected after a public outcry.</p>
        <p>Going Forward</p>
        <p>There is no real place to buy groceries in Milford Center, though there has been talk of starting a farmers' market.</p>
        <p>Also, Milford Lisman Landing Marina, a 40-slip facility that opened on the site of a sewage-treatment plant in 2003, packs in the summer boaters. The flood of tourists can turn certain bars rowdy, residents say.</p>
        <p>Living In | Milford Center, Conn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
