<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A West Side Story With a Promising Ending</title>
    <meta content="08nati" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/yourmoney/08natreal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070415T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NATIONAL PERSPECTIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Annapolis (Md)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carlyle Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parks, Jerome J, Companies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland/Annapolis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Annapolis (Md)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6DE173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A West Side Story With a Promising Ending</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A West Side Story With a Promising Ending</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>West side of Annapolis, Md, is in midst of neighborhood revival that is transforming it into chic, upscale living area; latest development in revival is Park Place, 11-acre mixed-used project, joint effort from Carlyle Group and Jerome J Parks Companies; $250 million European-style complex will offer 208 luxury condominiums along with commercial and retail offerings; drawing; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWO decades after deciding to resuscitate its economically troubled west side, Annapolis, Md., is now placing its hopes for a continued neighborhood revival on a new mixed-use development called Park Place.</p>
        <p>The $250 million complex -- with its European-style plaza, fountains and narrow, winding streets -- will include 208 luxury condominiums, a 225-room Westin Hotel, 200,000 square feet of office space and plenty of room for boutiques and restaurants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two decades after deciding to resuscitate its economically troubled west side, Annapolis, Md., hopes a mixed-use development will continue its revival.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWO decades after deciding to resuscitate its economically troubled west side, Annapolis, Md., is now placing its hopes for a continued neighborhood revival on a new mixed-use development called Park Place.</p>
        <p>The $250 million complex -- with its European-style plaza, fountains and narrow, winding streets -- will include 208 luxury condominiums, a 225-room Westin Hotel, 200,000 square feet of office space and plenty of room for boutiques and restaurants.</p>
        <p>City officials say that the project is already attracting other upscale developments to the area, and they are hoping for even more after the first part of Park Place opens this spring.</p>
        <p>Developers are finding a neighborhood steeped in history. Gen. George Washington arrived on the west side -- once the gateway to this city on the Potomac River -- in the 1780s. Under the Articles of Confederation, Annapolis, which is Maryland's capital, was once also the nation's capital.</p>
        <p>But two centuries or so later, the grand thoroughfare on which he traveled, now called the Inner West Street corridor, had become what Ellen O. Moyer, the city's mayor, described as ''a scary section of road lined with abandoned lots and failed businesses.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, Annapolis's historic east side continued to hum with activity. That part of the 6.5-square-mile metropolis -- the city's population is 35,900, according to 2000 census figures -- consists of mostly upscale single-family homes, an area of small shops and pubs catering to the tourist trade, and historic sites like the United States Naval Academy.</p>
        <p>Since 1985, Annapolis has spent around $13 million on the west side to revamp outdated zoning laws, build a new traffic circle, bury utility lines and install tree-lined brick sidewalks. It has also created a special tax district for the ongoing construction of a $25 million, three-story underground parking garage for 1,200 cars.</p>
        <p>Restaurants and shops have since opened in restored turn-of-the-20th-century homes near Park Place, and now home buyers, particularly those looking for luxury apartments, have rediscovered the area.</p>
        <p>''Our west side is finally becoming the uptown here that we've all been waiting for,'' said Kurt A. Hornig, 37, a real estate salesman who works in Baltimore. ''The west side is becoming very chic, like South Beach in Miami or D.C.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hornig is selling his three-bedroom house on the city's east side, where many homes go for $1 million and more, and moving into a one-bedroom condo in Park Place.</p>
        <p>He is being joined there by Bill and Shirley Vining, who were eager to downsize but unwilling to move to a larger metropolis like Washington to the west or Baltimore to the northwest, each about 25 miles away. They bought a two-bedroom condo.</p>
        <p>Park Place prices range from $525,000 for a one-bedroom to $1.99 million for a duplex penthouse with two terraces.</p>
        <p>The changes on the west side had been a long time in coming. Despite broad community support, the city's revitalization plans were delayed by economic downturns, explained Tom Smith, the city's planning commissioner.</p>
        <p>''Not a whole lot was happening in the way of development during the recession in 1990-92,'' Mr. Smith said. Then, after the city's zoning laws were rewritten in the late 1990s to encourage more development, he said, the 9/11 terrorist attacks took another toll on the local economy.</p>
        <p>The 11-acre Park Place is being developed jointly by the Carlyle Group, an investment company based in Washington, and the Jerome J. Parks Companies, a local family business that has constructed some 30 projects in the Baltimore-Washington area over the last 50 years.</p>
        <p>About 70 percent of the condominiums have already been sold, according to Jerome J. Parks, who is the company's chief executive.</p>
        <p>The condos will enable buyers like the Vinings to downsize from their five-bedroom colonial on the east side yet still remain in the city.</p>
        <p>''We're at that stage of life when we don't want a big house anymore, but we also don't want to leave friends and family who live around here,'' said Mr. Vining, 71, a semiretired management consultant. ''Up until now, though, there were no alternatives in Annapolis.''</p>
        <p>Mike and Joyce Gering, who live part-time in Tucson, where Mr. Gering runs a solar energy company, also bought a two-bedroom condo at Park Place. With strong family ties in Annapolis and the surrounding area -- they raised their family of nine children in nearby Dunkirk -- they had wanted a home base in Maryland.</p>
        <p>''We set out to find a penthouse-level condo in D.C. or Baltimore,'' Mr. Gering said. ''But Washington is too big a city for our tastes and Baltimore is a little out of the way, so when we heard about what was going on in Annapolis, we jumped.''</p>
        <p>The couple say they like the west side's easy access along major highways to Washington and Baltimore and its proximity to the Baltimore-Washington International Airport.</p>
        <p>Douglas Carter, the architect in charge of Park Place's design, said he was instructed by the developers to ''tap into history.''</p>
        <p>After a recent visit to Paris, Mr. Parks returned with photos of Old World architectural details that he wanted incorporated into the new construction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carter explained that his firm, Davis Carter Scott Architects, which has offices in McLean and Middleburg in Virginia, planned ''a development that would fit into the community rather than look like it was inserted into it.''</p>
        <p>Annapolis is renowned for buildings at the United States Naval Academy, which has three Beaux Arts-style structures designed in 1899 by Ernest Flagg.</p>
        <p>Park Place's buildings include European-style Beaux Arts architectural details, small plazas and landscaped courtyards, according to Mr. Carter. The grand plaza and one of the roads can be closed off for street festivals and special events.</p>
        <p>Four commercial tenants, including Merrill Lynch and the Building Owners and Managers Institute International, have so far leased 125,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>The retailers include the Papery, Varuna Aveda Salon &amp; Dayspa, Starbucks Coffee and the Carpaccio Italian Bistro. Morton's, the Steakhouse, a dining chain with seven other restaurants in the Washington-Baltimore area, also plans to open a 130-seat restaurant at Park Place, according to Roger J. Drake, a spokesman for Morton's.</p>
        <p>While pleased with the progress made so far on the west side, Ms. Moyer, the mayor of Annapolis, conceded that ''there is still a lot of work to do.''</p>
        <p>Aging strip shopping centers still line the corridor. ''It's not a very impressive introduction to the city,'' Ms. Moyer said. ''In time we plan to make more improvements to turn it into a true gateway and bring back some of the grandeur that it had when Washington used to come to Annapolis.''</p>
        <p>NATIONAL PERSPECTIVES</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 15, 2007, Sunday  The National Perspectives article last Sunday, about a new mixed-used development on the west side of Annapolis, Md., misidentified the river that touches this part of the city. It is the Severn River, not the Potomac.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 15, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>The National Perspectives article last Sunday, about a new mixed-used development on the west side of Annapolis, Md., misidentified the river that touches this part of the city. It is the Severn River, not the Potomac.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
