<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Clearing His Head In Spring Training, Yankee Is in Good Place</title>
    <meta content="08rodriguez" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/baseball/08rodriguez.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Clearing His Head In Spring Training, Yankee Is in Good Place</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Clearing Air in Spring Training Puts A-Rod in a ‘Good Place’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez said he figured the ninth inning would come down to his at-bat yesterday because, with the Yankees, almost everything seems to revolve around him. Rodriguez cannot avoid being a story, even when he is not a story and even when he is desperately trying to avoid being a story.</p>
        <p>There is always another wrinkle with Rodriguez, a player who is both fascinating and frustrating. Is Rodriguez friends with Derek Jeter? Will he opt out of the last three years of his contract after the season? Can he hit in the clutch? Will the fans embrace him? The Rodriguez chronicles operate on a 24-7 cycle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez, whose own manager said he worried too much about pleasing everyone, had one of those you-had-to-see-it-to-believe-it moments on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alex Rodriguez said he figured the ninth inning would come down to his at-bat yesterday because, with the Yankees, almost everything seems to revolve around him. Rodriguez cannot avoid being a story, even when he is not a story and even when he is desperately trying to avoid being a story.</p>
        <p>There is always another wrinkle with Rodriguez, a player who is both fascinating and frustrating. Is Rodriguez friends with Derek Jeter? Will he opt out of the last three years of his contract after the season? Can he hit in the clutch? Will the fans embrace him? The Rodriguez chronicles operate on a 24-7 cycle.</p>
        <p>But for one glorious day at Yankee Stadium, Rodriguez was the only story, and he was thrilled to be in that position. He hammered a two-out, two-strike grand slam in the bottom of the ninth into the black bleacher seats behind center field to catapult the Yankees past the Baltimore Orioles, 10-7.</p>
        <p>So Rodriguez, whose own manager said he worried too much about pleasing everyone, had one of those you-had-to-see-it-to-believe-it moments. He did not make the last out or leave runners on base. Rodriguez was a story because of his abilities, nothing else.</p>
        <p>''I'm just tickled for him,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''It was great to have that situation present itself. And the way it did. Two out and, really, there was no way out. I mean, there it is. You either produce or you're going to read about yourself again.''</p>
        <p>This time, Rodriguez will devour the attention. Rodriguez is a different man these days, he repeated several times after the game, a man at peace. It might have a lot to do with what Rodriguez said on the first day of spring training about his relationship with Jeter.</p>
        <p>''When your mind is right and your body is right, you feel like you're going to do it,'' he said yesterday. ''I'm just in a real calm place.''</p>
        <p>While Rodriguez explained how he has felt relaxed since spring training, he did not mention that that is when he acknowledged that he and Jeter do not share beers and chicken wings anymore. The players are closer to being co-workers than buddies.</p>
        <p>When Rodriguez was asked yesterday if his honesty about Jeter has helped him relax, he agreed that it had. Rodriguez does not have to behave as if he and Jeter were as friendly as they were more than a decade ago, and to Rodriguez the removal of that emotional burden is important.</p>
        <p>''I'm doing the best I can to enjoy the game,'' he said. ''I'm in a good place.''</p>
        <p>Will that good place last all season? Will Rodriguez be booed soon, as he was on Thursday for popping out with the bases loaded in the eighth inning of a game the Yankees lost, and as he was on opening day for missing a wind-blown pop-up?</p>
        <p>''I have no idea,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Torre said it was impossible for Rodriguez, a two-time Most Valuable Player award winner, to satisfy the expectations that surround him. But Torre also said he felt that Rodriguez, who flung his helmet before being mobbed by teammates after the grand slam, inched across another threshold.</p>
        <p>''I just think this game has helped him,'' Torre said. ''It wasn't a game where the home run didn't mean anything. It was a huge lift for everybody. That's sort of a plateau. People said: 'Men on base. He can't do this. He can't do that.' There it is. That shut the book on that one.''</p>
        <p>With a .389 average, three home runs and nine runs batted in this season, Rodriguez has easily been the most productive Yankee. Since Rodriguez can opt out of his 10-year, $252 million deal after the season, he is, in a way, proving himself to any potential suitors who want one of the premier players in the game.</p>
        <p>Why did Rodriguez, who was the sixth batter in the ninth, ever think he would decide the inning? Even after there were two outs and no one on base, he said, he felt that way.</p>
        <p>So Rodriguez, with his bat in his hands, leaned on the dugout steps and waited for a chance. After Robinson Canó singled, Jeter walked and Bobby Abreu was hit by a pitch, the chance came. Eventually, Rodriguez went deep on a 1-2 fastball from Chris Ray. Jeter pushed Rodriguez out of the dugout for a curtain call.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez, who also had a two-run homer in the first inning, mentioned how he noticed the ''fans kind of rocking'' when he rounded third and said that was ''kind of cool.'' As much as Rodriguez wants to avoid discussing how he is treated at Yankee Stadium, it was unavoidable this time.</p>
        <p>''I'm enjoying the game so much that I'm not caught up in the reaction either way,'' he said. ''But when it's that loud, it certainly makes you feel good.''</p>
        <p>The grand slam ball rested on a shelf in Rodriguez's locker. A silver crucifix was to the left of it and a picture of Rodriguez's wife and daughter was to the right. The crucifix and picture are fixtures. Perhaps the ball and the peacefulness it helps represent to Rodriguez will stay, too.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
