<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Mozart Tops the Charts</title>
    <meta content="08fran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/thecity/08fran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070415T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="URBAN STUDIES / SURVIVING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Frank Music Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rogers, Heidi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bleyer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED9173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Mozart Tops the Charts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Mozart Tops the Charts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER BLEYER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bleyer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Frank Music Co on West 54th Street near Broadway, where owner Heidi Rogers sells sheet music; city once had nearly 100 places to buy sheet music, but only half dozen remain; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AN oboist from the New York Philharmonic telephoned looking for some Astor Piazzolla tango etudes. Then an amateur cellist called to ask what was in stock by Scott Joplin.</p>
        <p>The telephone shrills constantly at Frank Music Company, where the sheet music for thousands of duets, quintets and concertos is wrapped in brown folders, piled high on metal shelves and sold out of spartan 10th-floor quarters on West 54th Street near Broadway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>These are trying times for the sheet music business, which has been increasingly chipped away at by illegal photocopying and online file sharing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AN oboist from the New York Philharmonic telephoned looking for some Astor Piazzolla tango etudes. Then an amateur cellist called to ask what was in stock by Scott Joplin.</p>
        <p>The telephone shrills constantly at Frank Music Company, where the sheet music for thousands of duets, quintets and concertos is wrapped in brown folders, piled high on metal shelves and sold out of spartan 10th-floor quarters on West 54th Street near Broadway.</p>
        <p>''You're the second unlucky parent to call me in a row,'' Heidi Rogers, the store's owner, told one caller. ''I don't sell band music. I'm in the heavy longhair business. You know: Beethoven, Stravinsky.''</p>
        <p>These are trying times for the sheet music business, which has been increasingly chipped away at by illegal photocopying and online file sharing. The loss is especially noticeable in New York. The 1947 telephone directory listed nearly 100 places in Manhattan to buy sheet music. Now, only a half dozen are listed, among them Patelson Music House on West 56th Street and the Juilliard Bookstore.</p>
        <p>Although her store is safe for now, Ms. Rogers worries that she may have to shutter its doors if the building is sold. ''It's like many other things in this economy,'' she said sadly. ''If it isn't big, it doesn't exist.''</p>
        <p>Business persists at Frank Music in large part because of Ms. Rogers, a feisty, black-haired 55-year-old who putters around her shop with her thick plastic glasses perched near the tip of her nose. She is the store's heartbeat, her encyclopedic knowledge drawing customers back again and again.</p>
        <p>The stock is vast and organized by composer, from Alexander Arutunian (folk music-inspired Armenian) to Alexander Zemlinsky (Austrian composer and conductor). An avowed Luddite, Ms. Rogers does not keep a computer inventory. She uses pencils until they are sharpened to two-inch stubs, and gives customers handwritten receipts on scraps of paper.</p>
        <p>She also sells fresh eggs, $4 a dozen, from the 68 chickens she keeps at her weekend home in Delaware County. As she put it, ''Why be in one dying profession when you can be in two: music dealer and farmer?''</p>
        <p>The business was started in 1937 by Frank Marx, a former floor sweeper at G. Lipskin &amp; Son, a music store on East 86th Street. Ms. Rogers's father, a composer named Milton Rogers, bought the store in 1978 and handed over its daily operation to his daughter, then just 26.</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon, a steady stream of musicians made their way in. Ms. Rogers commiserated with a gangly young trumpet player about his teacher, a well-known taskmaster, and advised a concert pianist with a Southern drawl who was looking for new material.</p>
        <p>Dimitri Moderbacher, a music teacher at the Dwight School, on the Upper West Side, came in seeking flute music for a student who favored Mozart. After trading pleasantries with him, Ms. Rogers padded over to the flute section.</p>
        <p>JENNIFER BLEYER</p>
        <p>URBAN STUDIES / SURVIVING</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 15, 2007, Sunday  An article last Sunday about Frank Music Company, a sheet music store, misstated the circumstances in which the owner, Heidi Rogers, acquired the store. She bought it on her own in 1978; her father, the composer Milton Rogers, never owned it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 15, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about Frank Music Company, a sheet music store, misstated the circumstances in which the owner, Heidi Rogers, acquired the store. She bought it on her own in 1978; her father, the composer Milton Rogers, never owned it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
