<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smithtown Loses Interest in Deal to Rent Pre-Revolutionary House</title>
    <meta content="08litopicLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08litopic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838665"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRESERVATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arthur House (Smithtown, NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcohol Abuse</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Smithtown (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotroneo, Nicole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcohol Abuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDC163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smithtown Loses Interest in Deal to Rent Pre-Revolutionary House</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Smithtown Loses Interest in Deal to Rent Pre-Revolutionary House</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLE COTRONEO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotroneo, Nicole</byline>
      <dateline>SMITHTOWN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Arthur House, pre-Revolutionary War house on Main Street in Smithtown, NY, which town officials have decided not to rent from local school district and refurbish for drug and alcohol education program</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE future of a pre-Revolutionary War house on Main Street looks as drab as its chipped white shingles now that the town has halted negotiations on renting it from the Smithtown Central School District.</p>
        <p>The 255-year-old structure, known as the Arthur House, was bought by the school district in 1924. It stands across an asphalt parking lot from the district's administration building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>SMITHTOWN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE future of a pre-Revolutionary War house on Main Street looks as drab as its chipped white shingles now that the town has halted negotiations on renting it from the Smithtown Central School District.</p>
        <p>The 255-year-old structure, known as the Arthur House, was bought by the school district in 1924. It stands across an asphalt parking lot from the district's administration building.</p>
        <p>The district used the house for years for home economics classes and as a processing center for books, said Dr. Meryl Ain, the assistant superintendent for general administration and planning. Most recently, the district used the house for its alternative school and adult education.</p>
        <p>But the district could not keep up with the maintenance, and about three years ago it declared the structure unsafe, Dr. Ain said.</p>
        <p>Last May the town offered to rent and refurbish the Arthur House for a drug and alcohol education program, said Patrick R. Vecchio, the town supervisor.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Vecchio said the square-footage rate in the proposed lease was excessive -- on par with more contemporary Main Street space.</p>
        <p>Now the program intended for the space has outgrown it, Mr. Vecchio said, and the town is no longer interested in the building.</p>
        <p>That was surprising news to the district late last month, according to Dr. Ain, who said that the school board and administration had thought the town's reservation was strictly financial.</p>
        <p>''The district fully expected Mr. Vecchio to come up with a counteroffer,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vecchio said the town had planned to invest $80,000 to paint the house, replace some windows and interior doors and install a new boiler and roof.</p>
        <p>''It was in the most dastardly shape you've ever seen,'' he said, recalling an inspection he made last year.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ain said that maintaining the Arthur House had not been a priority for the district, which was on a contingency budget last year and made cuts to get the budget passed the year before.</p>
        <p>''We cut 100 staff members to get out of contingency,'' she said. ''We cut and delayed some capital projects. We had to put priority on the ones that directly affect the children.''</p>
        <p>In recent weeks the school board and administration have discussed seeking help from community groups like the Chamber of Commerce, Dr. Ain said.</p>
        <p>Community cooperation has worked for other historic properties in Smithtown, most notably Deepwells Farm, an elegant Greek Revival house built about 1845 on 13.2 acres in St. James, three miles from the Arthur House.</p>
        <p>In the late 1980s a developer was prepared to knock down the Deepwells Farm house, according to Richard Martin, the Suffolk County director of historic services.</p>
        <p>''The community actively proposed that the county purchase it and did a petition drive,'' Mr. Martin said.</p>
        <p>The county bought Deepwells Farm in 1989 and refurbished it at a cost of more than $1 million with the help of a state grant. Deepwells was opened to the public as a county park in 1995. A newly formed volunteer group, the Deepwells Historical Society, runs the park for the county, Mr. Martin said.</p>
        <p>Deepwells had an advantage over the Arthur House. It is on the National Register of Historic Places, as part of the St. James District, and that helped the county obtain a grant for refurbishing. Deepwells was in dire shape as well, Mr. Martin said.</p>
        <p>It also has county landmark status, enabling it to receive county maintenance money. Only structures on county property can receive the landmark status, Mr. Martin said, and Arthur House does not qualify.</p>
        <p>PRESERVATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
