<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Attorney Inquiry Touches A Pillar of New Mexico</title>
    <meta content="08domenici" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/washington/08domenici.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulse, Carl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Domenici, Pete V (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Iglesias, David C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzales, Alberto R (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Mexico</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Domenici, Pete V</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DE143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Attorney Inquiry Touches A Pillar of New Mexico</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Attorney Inquiry Touches a Pillar of New Mexico</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dismissed federal prosecutor David C Iglesias tells Congress he felt pressured by phone call from New Mexico Sen Pete V Domenici to inquire about status of indictments in politically charged case; House and Senate committees are exploring whether Iglesias and seven other United States attorneys were ousted for strictly partisan reasons; inquiry has marred long-serving Domenici's almost spotless record; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The seat of federal justice in Albuquerque is named for Senator Pete V. Domenici, a former mayor and native son who has showered New Mexico with federal money during his decades in Washington and was rewarded by having his name adorn the United States courthouse.</p>
        <p>''He does extraordinary things for this state,'' said Kate Nelson, managing editor of The Albuquerque Tribune and a political commentator, who dubbed Mr. Domenici, a Republican, ''St. Pete'' in recognition of the federal benefits he shipped west, leavened with a bit of sass for the outsized reverence in which he is held at home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A brief telephone call from Senator Pete V. Domenici to a federal prosecutor has become a central element of an inquiry into the dismissal of eight U.S. attorneys.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The seat of federal justice in Albuquerque is named for Senator Pete V. Domenici, a former mayor and native son who has showered New Mexico with federal money during his decades in Washington and was rewarded by having his name adorn the United States courthouse.</p>
        <p>''He does extraordinary things for this state,'' said Kate Nelson, managing editor of The Albuquerque Tribune and a political commentator, who dubbed Mr. Domenici, a Republican, ''St. Pete'' in recognition of the federal benefits he shipped west, leavened with a bit of sass for the outsized reverence in which he is held at home.</p>
        <p>But a brief telephone call last year from Mr. Domenici to a federal prosecutor, David C. Iglesias, has become a central element of a Congressional inquiry into the dismissal of Mr. Iglesias and seven other United States attorneys.</p>
        <p>Mr. Iglesias told Congress that he felt pressured by the call from Mr. Domenici, once his political mentor, who days before the November elections telephoned to inquire about the status of indictments in a politically charged case.</p>
        <p>Committees in the House and Senate are exploring whether Mr. Iglesias and other federal prosecutors were ousted for strictly partisan reasons and whether Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales and senior Justice Department officials initially misled Congress in explaining the personnel moves.</p>
        <p>A complaint that Mr. Domenici broke Senate rules by interfering in a criminal matter has prompted an ethics committee inquiry. But it is unclear how that will play out because Mr. Domenici is not talking, and neither is the committee.</p>
        <p>The scrutiny has marred the almost spotless reputation of Mr. Domenici, 74, the second-longest-serving Republican in the Senate -- he was first elected in 1972 -- as he prepares to seek a seventh term. The personal toll appeared to be weighing on him as he made his way around the Capitol in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>''I think it has certainly been a distraction and a cause for stress,'' said Senator Jeff Bingaman, a New Mexico Democrat who replaced Mr. Domenici as chairman of the Energy and Natural Resources Committee.</p>
        <p>Steve Bell, Mr. Domenici's chief of staff and an aide throughout most of his Senate career, which began in 1973, said: ''I think he is really, really embarrassed, and it is so different from any reaction he has ever experienced before in his political life. The truth is he is absolutely stunned that this has been made into a huge political item.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bell, Ms. Nelson and others in both parties believe the fallout from the dismissals of the prosecutors is not enough to derail the re-election of Mr. Domenici, an immensely popular figure in New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Mr. Domenici, who issued a statement apologizing for the call, has retained a lawyer. His allies say that while the call turned out to be ill-advised, it is being exploited by Democrats and was simply an effort by Mr. Domenici to find out what was happening with a series of widely anticipated indictments.</p>
        <p>Charges were eventually returned at the end of March against leading Democratic figures in a case related to accusations of corruption surrounding the construction of a county courthouse.</p>
        <p>''He didn't threaten him, he didn't instruct him to do anything,'' said Bob Stevenson, a Republican consultant who is a former top aide to Mr. Domenici. ''This is a state where Pete Domenici has always been concerned about the responsiveness of government both at the federal and state level.''</p>
        <p>Democrats and some watchdog groups say the call appeared intended to spur Mr. Iglesias to file indictments in the hope of helping Representative Heather A. Wilson, a Republican congresswoman from the state. The suggestion is that a criminal case against prominent Democrats might have benefited Ms. Wilson, who ultimately won a tough re-election fight and had called Mr. Iglesias a week or so earlier.</p>
        <p>''If nothing else, it highlights his willingness to abuse his power,'' Matt Farrauto, executive director of the Democratic Party of New Mexico, said of Mr. Domenici. ''That is all fine and good in some people's eyes if he is bringing home the bacon, but when he is using his influence to save the failing campaign of Heather Wilson, that is another issue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Farrauto and others say there are signs that the furor over the federal prosecutors has cut into Mr. Domenici's standing in the state, which has become a national battleground because of the narrow divide between the two parties.</p>
        <p>But the Democrats do not have a candidate with the stature to mount a serious threat to Mr. Domenici, who typically coasts to re-election. Some of the state's leading Democrats have already indicated they are not interested in challenging Mr. Domenici, though any new revelations in the prosecutors' case or a serious rebuke from the ethics panel could change their perspective.</p>
        <p>Mr. Domenici already faced skepticism over whether he would run again. He has had serious health issues in recent years, including severe arthritis. But his Republican colleagues and members of his inner circle say that he is committed to running again and that they expect him to prevail.</p>
        <p>Some close colleagues said too much was being made of the fact that Mr. Domenici abruptly ended the call when Mr. Iglesias told him the indictments would not be forthcoming. On Capitol Hill, the senator is known for calling to express his displeasure and hanging up without notice.</p>
        <p>''It has only been happening to me for 35 years,'' said Mr. Bell, the chief of staff who said he now reminded Mr. Domenici to say goodbye.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
