<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeing the Beauty in Imperfect Floors</title>
    <meta content="08RHomeLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08RHome.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOME WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floors and Flooring</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kindall, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DC163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeing the Beauty in Imperfect Floors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seeing the Beauty in Imperfect Floors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES KINDALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kindall, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Kindall Home Work column on admiration he has for flaws in old wood floors that he has reinstalled and refinished in his home; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY morning, as I climb the stairs and trudge down the hall to my office, I pass over a section of floor that gives a noticeable groan. In former years, I made a mental note to one day pry up the offending plank and pad it with another layer of butcher paper. I also conceded this probably would come after about 200 other pressing chores.</p>
        <p>The beauty of this task deferred is that I've grown accustomed to the sound. In fact, I now regard it as a greeting from an old friend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There’s something to admire in the dings, warps and squeaks of old wood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY morning, as I climb the stairs and trudge down the hall to my office, I pass over a section of floor that gives a noticeable groan. In former years, I made a mental note to one day pry up the offending plank and pad it with another layer of butcher paper. I also conceded this probably would come after about 200 other pressing chores.</p>
        <p>The beauty of this task deferred is that I've grown accustomed to the sound. In fact, I now regard it as a greeting from an old friend.</p>
        <p>''Hello,'' says my wood floor. ''Shh,'' I say and keep walking.</p>
        <p>My wood floors talk to me.</p>
        <p>They speak of success and failure, death and rebirth, bizarre behavior and startling epiphanies.</p>
        <p>I first began listening during my house renovation nine years ago when I pulled up a filthy carpet in the living room, fully expecting to find yet another rotting disaster. Instead, I discovered a mottled but salvageable oak floor. What to do with it?</p>
        <p>Wood floors had never been in the upper tier of my consciousness, primarily because of my parents. They had a ready floor covering solution for all our homes: wall-to-wall carpeting. Having lived in this cocoon during my formative years, I had also seen the downside, that is, carpet smoky with dirt, worn as a forest path. Here was something more natural and enduring. All it needed was a little T.L.C.</p>
        <p>I decided to do the refinishing myself. The quest for supplies led me to a nondescript shop crammed with so many odd contraptions that I thought I had stumbled into Harry Potter's Diagon Alley. Instead of wizards, large-bellied men flowed in and out while exchanging ritualistic grunts of what I assumed was the Royal Order of Floormen.</p>
        <p>The people behind the counter were friendly enough, but there was no magic wand. Instead, I was shown how to use a drum sander, a bulbous contrivance that looks like a futuristic machine designed in the 1930s and that, if poorly handled, can create a floor that looks like a bad acid trip. My education included the difference between water-based and oil-based polyurethane (the oil one turns amber with age) as well as grades of sandpaper, how to use a lamb's wool applicator and how to buff things up with steel wool.</p>
        <p>The part I liked best was what I termed the Laying On of the Poly. It occurred when I put on the three coats of polyurethane, a miraculous period during which the formerly scarred and pockmarked wood was converted to a smooth foundation glowing with lustrous warmth. My jaw dropped every time. It was like watching Ugly Betty turn into Halle Berry.</p>
        <p>I often regaled (bored) visitors with these anecdotes, but some of my floors came with tales attached to them already, having been ripped from their previous homes. Destined for recycling in my house, for a while they were piles of lumber stored in my garage. One of the floors had belonged to a burly sound engineer with acute hearing and an explosive temper, a combination that made him so volatile that he chased workmen away from neighbors' houses for making too much noise. The other came from the dilapidated home of a once-beautiful woman who, according to the house's new owner, had devoted herself to a doomed affair. These floors have a lingering romance for me primarily because I never found out what happened to either of the former owners. But I still wonder.</p>
        <p>Both affected me in unexpected ways, mainly by teaching me a valuable lesson. I began learning when I installed the engineer's floor with Pat Smith, an exacting contractor who lives not far from me in Northport, N.Y., and who does not like dallying. I had already helped him build a stair landing in red oak, a variety I admired for its heft and color. The recycled floor didn't look nearly so promising. Its age-blackened patina was depressing enough. The boards were slightly warped and, when laid side by side, left as much as a quarter-inch gap in places. I was shocked when Pat blithely began nailing them down, his fast-moving hammer leaving rude indentations in the wood. He grinned at my horror. ''Learn to love the flaws,'' he said.</p>
        <p>This sounded suspiciously like a rationalization. But days later, as I sanded off the dark scum of time and once more laid on the poly, I saw the floor transformed into a glorious swath of yellow pine with a distinct shabby-chic charm. The aged affect was accented by, yes, the occasional nick from a heavy hammer.</p>
        <p>Still, this was hard to accept, considering the time and effort it had taken to create the refined look of my other floors. Of course, this had to be a freakish result. You couldn't simply bang something down and expect it to turn out all right. Surely, the attempt to civilize my floors was the moral thing to do.</p>
        <p>The final assault on my conservativism came a few years later during the remodeling of an upstairs bedroom. At this point, I was down to the remnants of the two ripped-up floors. I wasn't even sure if the blemished planks were usable. To me, their appearance was a canvas of sloppiness: boards that were grayed by age, blackened by stains of unknown origin. My plan was to sand away all these offenses and expose the richness once more.</p>
        <p>After putting down the flooring in its rough-hewn state, I left on a weeklong trip. Meanwhile, my wife planned to surprise me by finishing the job. Seeing the floor's raw potential, she decided to skip the difficult sanding step and apply the poly directly. If I had been home, I would have firmly put my foot down. (This wouldn't have done me any good, but I like to go through the motions.)</p>
        <p>On my return I was greeted with a glorious patchwork of coloration that, accented by the sheen of the polyurethane, revealed the wood's true splendor. All the pocks and dings I had frowned at before were now presented as painterly flourishes on a satiny canvas.</p>
        <p>At last, I realized what my contractor, my wife and my floors had been trying to tell me. Beauty must be appreciated on its own terms.</p>
        <p>My, I thought, gazing down, what lovely flaws.</p>
        <p>HOME WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
