<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Touch of Artistic License</title>
    <meta content="08sketch" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/realestate/08sketch.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SKETCH PAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennon, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EFDF173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Touch of Artistic License</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Touch of Artistic License</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sketch Pad column on architect Kevin Kennon's vision for redesign of former lawyers' offices at 325 East 57th Street into private gallery and living space; drawing; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DO you remember that smart, funny guy in high school who was so nice he danced with the girl nobody else would dance with? Kevin Kennon, now a high-powered architect with an office in Lower Manhattan, is that guy.</p>
        <p>While some architects bring an assistant to measure, the collegial Mr. Kennon, who was the principal designer for the amazing Rodin Museum in Seoul when he was a partner at Kohn Pedersen Fox, brought in his whole crew of mainly young professionals to check out an apartment for sale in Midtown Manhattan. It was such a crowd that the building's doorman thought the real estate broker was having an open house. (''There are no open houses allowed at 325 East 57th Street,'' the broker, Anthony vanEyck Miller of Bellmarc Realty, explained to the architects piling into the apartment, after hastening to disabuse the doorman, who still looked skeptical.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kevin Kennon reimagines an apartment, which had been used as lawyers’ offices, as a combined living and gallery space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DO you remember that smart, funny guy in high school who was so nice he danced with the girl nobody else would dance with? Kevin Kennon, now a high-powered architect with an office in Lower Manhattan, is that guy.</p>
        <p>While some architects bring an assistant to measure, the collegial Mr. Kennon, who was the principal designer for the amazing Rodin Museum in Seoul when he was a partner at Kohn Pedersen Fox, brought in his whole crew of mainly young professionals to check out an apartment for sale in Midtown Manhattan. It was such a crowd that the building's doorman thought the real estate broker was having an open house. (''There are no open houses allowed at 325 East 57th Street,'' the broker, Anthony vanEyck Miller of Bellmarc Realty, explained to the architects piling into the apartment, after hastening to disabuse the doorman, who still looked skeptical.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennon, who now has his own practice, had been asked to imagine who would buy this apartment, which had been used as lawyers' offices, and to design how the space might be converted for living.</p>
        <p>For this warren on the first floor of a prewar building, the co-op board had other rules as well: no door to the street can be broken through the red brick facade and no more than 20 people a day can visit.</p>
        <p>But here's the good news: whoever buys this 1,200-square-foot co-op, currently for sale for $705,000, can turn it into a private residence. Or a place to live and work. The space is now broken up into four rooms, with one and a half newly tiled baths and a rather dreary 16-foot-by-15-foot courtyard.</p>
        <p>''We are a research-based firm,'' Mr. Kennon said. ''We dig deep, into the possibilities of the site, the local information, and then a lot comes from the clients: how they live, how they work. Any renovation is like a short story.''</p>
        <p>A story, yes, but one based on the technical. Mr. Kennon walked around the space, making his way around members of his team who were stretching out tape measures and jotting down notes. He talked about the space as a diseased body that needed to be scanned to see what ailed it. ''We like to use highly technical means to end up with something simple,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The person who would live here, he said, chatting with the broker, would have something to do with the East 57th Street art scene, perhaps a gallery owner but one with a very special type of gallery that cannot be open to the public because of the co-op restrictions.</p>
        <p>Instead of breaking up the space into precise working and living areas, Mr. Kennon said that some of it could perform double duty, allowing for bigger rooms. ''The kitchen island could become the desk could become the conference table,'' he said. ''One of the fundamental problems in what is now a dark space is how the existing natural light is eaten up by partitions.''</p>
        <p>A week later, Mr. Kennon and his team produced a slide show that ''scanned'' the space with medical precision. In fact, some of the drawings showed a series of closely spaced vertical lines, or slices, sweeping across the page.</p>
        <p>To promote the idea of a secret space, there is no visible door from the lobby to the apartment. Instead, a bookcase swings open, like one in a haunted house (although this one, presumably, wouldn't creak). The door, Mr. Kennon said, ''is hidden in a whimsical way -- the only thing that obviously comes in from the outside is light.''</p>
        <p>And a few clients.</p>
        <p>Describing the imaginary gallery owner who would inhabit the apartment, Mr. Kennon said that ''she works on consignment.'' To further that conceit, there are some real sculptures shown in the proposal, including a miraculous stainless-steel tree in the courtyard. There are also large transparencies hanging from the ceiling through which sunlight passes all the way to the back wall, creating a second, more subtle image.</p>
        <p>Using transparencies also allows the gallery owner to save on insurance because the real artwork can be safely stored somewhere else.</p>
        <p>The real or photographed artwork can be displayed on a series of vertical panels that pull out from a digitized rack at one end of an expanded 34-foot living room/gallery space that runs across the street side of the apartment.</p>
        <p>The kitchen has been moved, and rather than being expanded, it has probably shrunk. ''The efficient kitchen runs along the wall here, behind translucent glass panels,'' the architect said.</p>
        <p>Toward the back, where there had been a jumble of rooms -- a back hall, a reception area and a room for the central air-conditioning condenser -- is now the bedroom, with a sliding door and light pulled in from the courtyard.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Kennon's plan, the open courtyard, which he called a prosaic space at the bottom of a light well formed by surrounding brick buildings, becomes a central feature, a glassed-in parlor more than 11 feet high where clients and friends can sit and speak about Kandinsky or Kant -- or the in-laws.</p>
        <p>The courtyard also becomes a prism of sorts, allowing what there is of its light to illuminate both the living room and the bedroom, forming a winter garden that in summer becomes an air-conditioned retreat. Very precise views of the stainless steel tree similar to one designed by Roxy Paine for the Whitney Biennial are proposed.</p>
        <p>The mechanical equipment, including the air-conditioning, is stored in its own space, created in a corner of the courtyard.</p>
        <p>Inside the apartment there are bleached floors and white walls. ''It doesn't feel dark and dreary -- it feels like downtown,'' said Mr. Kennon, who should know: his office is on Varick Street. There are a few very slightly curving walls. ''We only did it a little bit,'' he said. ''A surface wrapping the inside, it's meant to envelop you. It's very subtle. We don't like extreme gestures in small spaces.''</p>
        <p>The price for all the renovations, like the apartment itself, seems relatively modest -- $180,000 -- at least for a gallery owner. The glassed-in cube that becomes the winter garden would cost at least $45,000, bringing the total for the project to $930,000, assuming one paid the $705,000 asking price for the apartment.</p>
        <p>To the architect, the result would emote warmth and even seclusion in a spot right near the entrance to the Queensboro Bridge.</p>
        <p>''We live such public lives as New Yorkers that in a way the most valuable commodity is privacy,'' he said. ''How can you live in a relatively private world, living at the bottom of a light well that no longer feels like a dungeon? Our solution is about maximizing space and light.''</p>
        <p>THE SPECS  Sketch Pad focuses on an apartment, house, loft or shack now for sale that has unrealized potential. Each month, a different architect or designer is asked to create a vision of what the place might look like.</p>
        <p>There are no guarantees that the plans would be approved by co-op boards, municipal building departments or planning boards. But they can help real estate shoppers learn to see past ugly paint, too-small kitchens and a warren of rooms.</p>
        <p>ARCHITECTS  Kevin Kennon, Craig Bahney, Johnny Chiu, Katharine Ives, Donat Kirschner, Benjamin Kroll and Philip Vriend Kevin Kennon Architects  (212) 219-1171</p>
        <p>PROPERTY  Former lawyers' offices on the first floor of a prewar co-op at 325 East 57th Street. Price: $705,000.</p>
        <p>RENOVATION COST  To remodel the apartment, turning a maze of offices into a gallery space and living quarters: $180,000. To construct a glassy winter garden in the existing 16-by-15-foot rear courtyard: at least $45,000. Total: $225,000.</p>
        <p>REAL ESTATE BROKER  Anthony vanEyck Miller  Bellmarc Realty  (212) 517-9100, ext. 220</p>
        <p>SKETCH PAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
