<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Utah Dynasty Is Divided Over a Presidential Preference</title>
    <meta content="08utah" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/us/politics/08utah.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STATEHOUSE JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mormons (Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romney, Mitt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huntsman, Jon M Sr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huntsman, Jon M Jr (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mormons (Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Utah</location>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Romney, Mitt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E5DE143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Utah Dynasty Is Divided Over a Presidential Preference</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Utah Dynasty Is Divided Over a Presidential Preference</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>SALT LAKE CITY, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Self-made billionaire, philanthropist and patriarch of one of Utah's most powerful families, Jon M Huntsman Sr, supports Republican presidential candidate and fellow Mormon Mitt Romney; Huntsman's son, Jon M Huntsman Jr, is popular governor of Utah and supports Romney's rival, John McCain; some residents say their opinion of Gov Huntsman has risen for showing such independence in Mormon-dominated state; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jon M. Huntsman Sr., a self-made billionaire, philanthropist, and patriarch of one of Utah's most powerful families, waxes philosophic in the letters he has written urging people to support former Gov. Mitt Romney of Massachusetts as the Republican nominee for president. ''A defining moment for the future of our great country,'' Mr. Huntsman calls the 2008 election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huntsman's son, Jon M. Huntsman Jr., Utah's wildly popular governor, with a 77 percent approval rating in one recent poll, uses strikingly similar language in supporting Senator John McCain of Arizona.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The governor of Utah is supporting John McCain for president, while his father favors Mitt Romney.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jon M. Huntsman Sr., a self-made billionaire, philanthropist, and patriarch of one of Utah's most powerful families, waxes philosophic in the letters he has written urging people to support former Gov. Mitt Romney of Massachusetts as the Republican nominee for president. ''A defining moment for the future of our great country,'' Mr. Huntsman calls the 2008 election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huntsman's son, Jon M. Huntsman Jr., Utah's wildly popular governor, with a 77 percent approval rating in one recent poll, uses strikingly similar language in supporting Senator John McCain of Arizona.</p>
        <p>''John McCain is a remarkable American hero who has experienced war, and in the post-9/11 period, what better kind of leader could we have than that?'' Governor Huntsman, a Republican, said in an interview. ''If ever there was a time in our history when you need someone with his background, it would be now.''</p>
        <p>Elections? They come and go. But fathers and sons and dynasties are the stuff real dramas are made of, and in Utah the split between Mr. Huntsman Sr. and Mr. Huntsman Jr. has become the simmering back story of the campaign season.</p>
        <p>''It does have a lot of people scratching their heads,'' said LaVarr Webb, a Republican political consultant in Salt Lake.</p>
        <p>By most measures, Governor Huntsman, who is 47 and two years into his first term, is the odd man out in cheering for Mr. McCain, at least in this state. Mr. Romney's father, George, the automobile industry executive and governor of Michigan, partly grew up here. Mitt Romney, many people here say, saved the scandal-plagued 2002 Winter Olympics in Salt Lake. The Romneys, like the Huntsmans, are Mormon in a state where membership in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints dominates the political culture.</p>
        <p>''I refer to him as Utah's adopted son,'' said Lt. Gov. Gary R. Herbert, a Romney supporter whose receptionist's desk is emblazoned with a commonly seen bumper sticker here that says, ''I'm Smitten,'' with a line under the letters, ''Mitt.''</p>
        <p>A poll last November by Dan Jones &amp; Associates, a local polling firm, said Mr. Romney was supported by 44 percent of the state's residents, compared with 15 percent for Mr. McCain, who came in second. The poll of 416 registered voters had a margin of error of 5 percent.</p>
        <p>Some residents, however they feel about the presidential race, said their opinion of the governor had gone up if only because he was tacking against such strong prevailing winds.</p>
        <p>''I think he's shown some real independence,'' said Beth Whitsett, a 60-year-old lawyer and self-described ''card-carrying Democrat.'' Ms. Whitsett said she favored Senator Barack Obama of Illinois in his bid for the Democratic nomination but liked her governor more than ever. ''I was proud of his backbone.''</p>
        <p>Others said the McCain endorsement seemed calculated if not quite Oedipal, a continuation of the younger Mr. Huntsman's disengagement from the shadow of his family, an effort that began during the race for governor in 2004, when the father began to recede from public view as the son stepped forward.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huntsman senior, who is 69, is still running the giant specialty chemical company he founded, the Huntsman Corporation, and still very involved in philanthropy, especially the Huntsman Cancer Institute, a research and treatment center at the University of Utah. But he rarely makes news these days, political experts here say, and he declined to be interviewed for this article. A spokesman for Mr. Romney, Kevin Madden, also declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Governor Huntsman, who gave an interview over a lunch of spicy pork tacos from a downtown street vendor where he eats several times a week, said that he and his father had disagreed in ''polite respect,'' and that they rarely talked about politics anyway.</p>
        <p>But he said that while his support for Mr. McCain was heartfelt and personal, Utah's larger, longer-term interest affected his endorsement decision.</p>
        <p>The West, he said, is an emerging political force that is rising in economic and demographic clout and expressing a unique view that he thinks both parties will have to respond to. He praised moderate politicians of both parties, especially Gov. Brian Schweitzer in Montana and Gov. Bill Richardson in New Mexico, both Democrats, as leaders who have caught the new Western spirit. Mr. Richardson is seeking his party's nomination for president.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, Governor Huntsman said, also plans to make Utah a regional hub for the campaign -- covering eight or nine states in the interior West -- something he said had never happened to Utah in a presidential election.</p>
        <p>Western money is flowing, too. Of the $20 million raised by the Romney campaign since January, a significant part came from Utah, at least partly through the efforts of the elder Mr. Huntsman.</p>
        <p>According to the Huntsman Cancer Institute 2006 annual report and public campaign records, the list of givers to Huntsman causes and Romney supporters overlaps extensively. It includes sports stars like the former Utah Jazz great Karl Malone -- who, along with his wife, Kay, donated at least $100,000 to the Huntsman Institute; the Malones also gave $5,000 last year to Mr. Romney through his Commonwealth Political Action Committee. And the family of J. Willard Marriott Jr., the wealthy hotelier and fellow Mormon, has given substantially to the Huntsman institute and to Mr. Romney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marriott said in a telephone interview that his involvement with Huntsman causes and his backing of Mr. Romney were coincidental.</p>
        <p>''I've known Mitt all his life,'' he said. ''He is one of the most capable people I've ever run across.''</p>
        <p>Governor Huntsman said that because so many eyes were on his state now because of Mr. Romney, part of his message of endorsement was that Utah is more politically diverse than outsiders might think. He also said it is never wise to put all of one's eggs in a single basket.</p>
        <p>''Either man will have friends in Utah,'' he said. ''My position is that McCain is the best. But if an outgrowth of that is the fact that we're able to hedge our bets in protecting the state's interests longer term, that would be an additional benefit.''</p>
        <p>Sue Odette, for one, remains unimpressed. Ms. Odette, 39, who works in advertising sales for a Salt Lake City television station, said she thought Mr. Romney ''says what he's told to say,'' and that Governor Huntsman was just another politician too.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking for sincerity,'' said Ms. Odette, who described herself as a political independent.</p>
        <p>She said she was leaning toward Rudolph W. Giuliani, the former mayor of New York who is also seeking the Republican nomination.</p>
        <p>''I like people who can hold it together under pressure,'' she said, ''and I've seen Giuliani under pressure after 9/11.''</p>
        <p>STATEHOUSE JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
