<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How the West Was Accumulated, Back East</title>
    <meta content="08land" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/us/08land.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THIS LAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Memorabilia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Harrisburg (Pa)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Western States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Civil War Museum (Harrisburg, Pa)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania Fire Museum (Harrisburg, Pa)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, Stephen R (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/This Land</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memorabilia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pennsylvania</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E6DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How the West Was Accumulated, Back East</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How the West Was Accumulated, Back East</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>HARRISBURG, Pa.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dan Barry This Land column visits Harrisburg, Pa, where Mayor Stephen R Reed has quietly assembled many thousands of Old West artifacts with about $7.8 million of public money for museum he hopes to establish; has already established Pennsylvania Fire Museum and National Civil War Museum in effort to cement Harrisburg's position in regional tourism; map; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You may know Harrisburg as the capital of Pennsylvania. You may not know it as the gateway to the gateway to the gateway to the Old West.</p>
        <p>The supporting evidence for this distinction is found in a dusty warehouse, beside the city incinerator, that smells faintly of solid waste: thousands and thousands of Old West artifacts, many quite valuable. The gates to the OK Corral. A wanted poster for Jesse James. A painting shot through by Calamity Jane. Saddles and tintypes, hats and moccasins, knives and horse buggies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mayor of Harrisburg, Pa., spent $7.8 million of public funds on items for an Old West museum he hoped to open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You may know Harrisburg as the capital of Pennsylvania. You may not know it as the gateway to the gateway to the gateway to the Old West.</p>
        <p>The supporting evidence for this distinction is found in a dusty warehouse, beside the city incinerator, that smells faintly of solid waste: thousands and thousands of Old West artifacts, many quite valuable. The gates to the OK Corral. A wanted poster for Jesse James. A painting shot through by Calamity Jane. Saddles and tintypes, hats and moccasins, knives and horse buggies.</p>
        <p>A stuffed buffalo.</p>
        <p>So many artifacts are spread about that the eye struggles to rest on any particular item. Maybe this does not matter, since almost no one in Harrisburg has ever seen these relics, which the mayor bought with several million dollars of public money while on quiet, cross-country shopping trips -- all for an Old West museum he hoped to establish one day.</p>
        <p>If you consider this to be a curious approach to governance, if you think it odd that a mayor of an Eastern city of 50,000 would plan an Old West museum and, unbeknownst to almost anyone, select and buy the items, then by all means say it: Whoa.</p>
        <p>Last week the mayor, Stephen R. Reed, delivered a State of the City address so detailed that by the end of the long hour his listeners could be forgiven for not remembering whether it was 1.1 million pounds of leaves collected and 4,178 vehicles towed, or 4,178 pounds of leaves collected and 1.1 million vehicles towed.</p>
        <p>In a way, this form of oratory as inventory reflects the mayor's undisputed role in transforming once-sorrowful Harrisburg into a destination city with a booming downtown. Behind the recitation of the square footage being developed, of the number of hotel rooms being planned, stands this impressive number: 25 years in office.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Reed failed to include in his tally the thousands of Old West artifacts he had acquired over the years, such as a card table from Wyatt Earp's saloon that he keeps in his sanctum of an office, which, at least, reeks only of cigarette smoke.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reed sat in this office the other night and slowly explained, yet again, why he bought these items. He is 57, with gray hair, a pencil-thin moustache and an air of impatience with any questioning of his stewardship this deep in his administration. Once the savior of Harrisburg, it seems, he now is Harrisburg, forever reminding everyone how he eats, sleeps and breathes this city.</p>
        <p>Nearly 20 years ago, he said, he resolved to establish five museums that he hoped would cement Harrisburg's position in regional tourism. First came the Pennsylvania National Fire Museum, then the National Civil War Museum, which was chock-full of items personally selected by the mayor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reed then went shopping for Old West stuff, emboldened by his considerable knowledge of the period -- he calls himself a buff -- and by the belief that Harrisburg was a ''supply point and river-crossing point'' for those bound for the western territories. ''The West started here,'' he said, explaining why, for example, he planned to recreate a Tombstone street in the Keystone State.</p>
        <p>He was reimbursed through a ''special projects reserve fund'' maintained by the Harrisburg Authority, a bond-issuing agency packed with mayoral allies that oversees, among other projects, the city's profoundly flawed incinerator.</p>
        <p>A 400-page inventory of artifacts indicates that he spent $7.8 million from this fund since 1999, almost all of it on Old West items ranging from the distinctive (Virgil Earp's watch and badge) to the sundry (bottle with cracked neck). There were a few miscellaneous entries, though, including this: ''Vampire Hunter's Set'' ($6,500).</p>
        <p>The Harrisburg mayor would take trips of breathtaking acquisition, gladdening the hearts of antiquities dealers everywhere, and then dispatch a loyalist and a city police officer to collect the items in a rented truck. ''We found it to be 90 percent cheaper,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The breadth of spending and the casual accounting involved are reflected in a $32,928 reimbursement request he submitted in 2003. It included receipts for a Seventh Cavalry telescope and bugle bought in 1995, a collection of antique guns in 1994 and some ''early pottery'' from a New Jersey store in 1991.</p>
        <p>''There's no particular reason,'' Mr. Reed said in explaining the 12-year lapse between expense and submission. ''They accumulated to a point, and I submitted them.''</p>
        <p>The authority cut him a check the next day.</p>
        <p>Four years ago the local newspaper, The Patriot-News, revealed the mayor's acquisitions and plan for a National Museum of the Old West. Then a local businessman, Jason N. Smith, essentially shamed him into postponing the project and initiating a tourism study to assess its potential. But the mayor only paused from shopping.</p>
        <p>The artifacts were stored in the warehouse. Except for the Conestoga wagon and the stagecoach, which couldn't fit in the building and so were sent elsewhere. Oh, and the artifacts kept in the mayor's office, including a coat owned by Doc Holliday.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' Mr. Reed said, gazing at the coat, ''virtually all these items are going to auction.''</p>
        <p>Here is why. The mayor announced late last year that Harrisburg was in the red, in part because of the flawed incinerator plant overseen by the authority that financed his Old West vision. He proposed various deficit-reducing options, but a City Council member, Linda D. Thompson, resurrected a personal peeve.</p>
        <p>''I said: 'Sell the artifacts, sell the artifacts, sell the artifacts,' '' Ms. Thompson recalled.</p>
        <p>Under growing pressure from the council, Mr. Reed announced in October that he was dropping his plan for an Old West museum and would be selling most of the artifacts. Two months later, the council passed a resolution that laid out the terms, including a requirement that the city provide reports of the sale's progress.</p>
        <p>In recounting the last few months, Mr. Reed played down the council's power, mentioned that one council member's spouse had been arrested on drug charges, and insisted that he, and not the council, was behind the move to sell the artifacts. When asked whether he was disappointed with how things turned out, the mayor said, ''I'm well past that point.''</p>
        <p>Soon an auction house in Dallas will box and ship the artifacts in preparation for their eventual sale. Wyatt Earp's shaving kit. Annie Oakley's traveling case. Buffalo Bill's megaphone. All these wondrous items to spur the imagination, never seen, never appreciated, never home in the city of Harrisburg.</p>
        <p>THIS LAND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
