<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>300 Strikeouts? Not When Starters Don't Finish</title>
    <meta content="08score" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/baseball/08score.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="KEEPING SCORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Schilling, Curt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Randy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Martinez, Pedro</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DE143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>300 Strikeouts? Not When Starters Don't Finish</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">300 Strikeouts? Not When Starters Don’t Finish</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Benjamin</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While it may not have the resonance of a 50-home-run season, or the aura of a no-hitter, the benchmark for a power pitcher is a 300-strikeout season. Accomplished only 33 times since 1901, it is a feat that does not happen by chance.</p>
        <p>But with 11 of those seasons occurring between 1993 and 2002, and none since, the question can be raised whether an era has passed without anyone noticing it had even started.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The success of the modern bullpen is a prime contributor to the diminishing number of innings for starting pitchers and the ensuing reduction of high-strikeout seasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While it may not have the resonance of a 50-home-run season, or the aura of a no-hitter, the benchmark for a power pitcher is a 300-strikeout season. Accomplished only 33 times since 1901, it is a feat that does not happen by chance.</p>
        <p>But with 11 of those seasons occurring between 1993 and 2002, and none since, the question can be raised whether an era has passed without anyone noticing it had even started.</p>
        <p>In 2002, the Diamondbacks teammates Curt Schilling and Randy Johnson each had more than 300 strikeouts, the third year in that period that two pitchers reached 300 strikeouts in the same season. Since then the number has not been approached, and it appears there is no one on the horizon that is likely to change that.</p>
        <p>''The key issue when we're looking at 300-strikeout pitchers is not so much of skill, because there are quite a few pitchers who have the skill to do it,'' said Ron Shandler, author of ''Baseball Forecaster 2007.'' ''I think it's a product of opportunities, of getting innings.''</p>
        <p>The success of the modern bullpen is a prime contributor to the diminishing number of innings for starting pitchers and the ensuing reduction of high-strikeout seasons. The majority of 300-strikeout seasons were recorded by pitchers throwing more than 275 innings. In an era where even top pitchers are allowed only 34 starts and about 240 innings, a pitcher must not only throw a large number of innings, but must have a strikeout rate much higher than in previous generations.</p>
        <p>''From a standpoint of winning a game, it makes sense to bring a pitcher with a 2.5 E.R.A. to replace the pitcher with a 3.5 or 4 E.R.A. who has thrown 120 pitches,'' said Rob Neyer, a co-author of ''Baseball Prospectus 2007.'' ''There is a lot of criticism of the way bullpens are used, and I will criticize them as well, but there are many times when even if you have a good pitcher on the mound who is doing well, statistically it makes more sense to bring in the relief pitcher.''</p>
        <p>The reduction of innings, along with monitored pitch counts, has led some to believe that putting the ball in play is a better strategy for a starting pitcher than trying to strike out batters. Two recent examples of this are Jake Peavy of the San Diego Padres and Justin Verlander of the Detroit Tigers. Both have the velocity and skills to be dominant strikeout pitchers, with Peavy already owning one National League strikeout title, but both have been encouraged to try and get batters out in only a few pitches rather than the four to five it often takes to strike a batter out.</p>
        <p>''The more batters you strike out, the more pitches you have to throw,'' Shandler said. ''A pitcher who allows the ball to be put into play, especially those who put the ball into play on the ground, can be very successful.''</p>
        <p>Neyer agreed to a point, but said: ''In this current environment, maybe that's a good tradeoff, to trade a couple strikeouts for balls in play, with the side benefit that you get to stay in the game longer. I don't know if anybody has the answer. I happen to know that most of the greatest pitchers in baseball history were strikeout pitchers, whether it's Roger Clemens or Pedro Martínez or even Greg Maddux.''</p>
        <p>Kerry Wood was once considered to be next in a long line of great strikeout pitchers, an heir apparent to Johnson, Schilling and Clemens. He struck out 266 batters in 2003 and seemed primed to become the next pitcher with a 300-strikeout season. Since then he has started only 36 games and is again battling injuries.</p>
        <p>With strikeout rates still one of the prime indicators of future success for a pitcher, Neyer does not think the failures of Wood and his teammate Mark Prior, another young strikeout pitcher beset by injuries, will lead to changes in what teams are looking for in young talent.</p>
        <p>''If you ask any scouting director if he'd like to have an 18-year-old Kerry Wood, he'd say, 'Absolutely,' '' Neyer said. ''But what they might ask them to do is dial it back a little bit.''</p>
        <p>Since the reduced workload of starters is probably here to stay, the only hope for 300-strikeout seasons may be for a pitcher to go on a run similar to the one Martínez went on from 1997 to 2002. The 5-foot-11 Martínez does not match the size of a Schilling or a Nolan Ryan, and never threw more than 2411/3 innings in a season, but he struck out 305 batters in 1997 and 313 in 1999.</p>
        <p>It may be a long wait for the next Martínez.</p>
        <p>''To be able to do what he did, with his body type, it could be argued that he's been as good as any pitcher ever at his peak,'' Neyer said.</p>
        <p>KEEPING SCORE E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: keepingscore@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
