<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chain Reaction</title>
    <meta content="Overbye.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Overbye.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Changing Light (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chain Reaction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chain Reaction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS OVERBYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Overbye, Dennis</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHANGING LIGHT</p>
        <p>By Nora Gallagher.</p>
        <p>223 pp. Pantheon Books. $22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this novel, set in New Mexico in the 1940s, a nuclear accident leads to love.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHANGING LIGHT</p>
        <p>By Nora Gallagher.</p>
        <p>223 pp. Pantheon Books. $22.</p>
        <p>If, like me, you are of a scientific bent -- or even if you're not -- New Mexico in the 1940s is one of those legendary places where the destinies of colorful and disparate strangers intertwined to cast long shadows on history. Atomic scientists, artists, soldiers and spies, cowboys and Indians all wandered through the winding canyons.</p>
        <p>You can almost smell the piÃ$(1$)on smoke and the tortillas frying in Nora Gallagher's evocative first novel, which imagines a glancing love affair between an artist very much like Georgia O'Keeffe and a scientist very much like Leo Szilard, the Hungarian physicist and buddy of Einstein. Gallagher, best known for a pair of spiritual memoirs, ''Things Seen and Unseen'' and ''Practicing Resurrection,'' effortlessly conjures the real and the imagined in language as clear as the Southwestern landscape.</p>
        <p>''Changing Light'' is also a love letter to the Southwest, where the author grew up. My first reaction, once the book set its hook in me -- which took about two pages -- was regret that I haven't spent more time in Santa Fe. I wanted to live in a little adobe house with a hand-woven rug on a blood-red dirt floor and sit at a rough desk under a window looking down an arroyo at the Sangre de Cristo mountains.</p>
        <p>That's how Eleanor Garrigue, a young painter from New York, fleeing her domineering husband for the solitude and the light, has come to live. And up on the mesa beyond her arroyo, other newcomers, many of them refugees of a different sort, have been busy with their own new thing. But ''the gadget,'' as they refer to it, is never going to be theirs. The military already has plans for the cold war, and the surrender of Japan is only the opening act. ''If the project I was working on succeeds, Japan will be destroyed,'' a guilt-stricken Leo Kavan, the Szilard stand-in, reluctantly admits.</p>
        <p>After a radiation mishap kills his best friend and leaves him seriously ill, Leo stumbles down the mesa into Eleanor's arroyo. She takes this handsome stranger, mumbling German or Czech, home to her cottage and nurses him, even though he might be a criminal or worse. Why, she wonders, does she suddenly feel lonely ''when, for the first time in months, there was someone else in the house''?</p>
        <p>Eleanor confides in the local Episcopal priest, who in turn confides in his chess partner, a machinist up on the mesa. Unfortunately, this machinist, David Stein, is a spy -- a character inspired by David Greenglass, Ethel Rosenberg's brother, who machined molds for high explosives by day and by night smuggled drawings to the Soviet Union. The least well realized of the four characters at the center of this story, David is spoiled with melodrama. Rebuffed when he asks a supervising scientist when ''the gadget'' will be tested, he sulks in cardboard-socialist rage: ''There can be no friendships between classes. He doesn't trust me because I am a mere machinist. He will be surprised when he discovers who I am.''</p>
        <p>The novel's inevitable chase unfolds sumptuously, over red chile, blue-corn enchiladas and sudden desert snowstorms, flashing back and forth in space and time from Chicago to Europe, from the Manhattan art scene to the dusty heights of Los Alamos and Eleanor's cozy cabin. Gallagher has mined the scientific and historic record scrupulously, but she doesn't lard her narrative with science lessons, or art lectures either. Her description of the manufacture of bomb molds has the spare precision of a lab notebook -- and so does the scene in which an accident kills Kavan's friend, a version of a real-life accident in 1946. During an experiment that went wrong, Louis Slotin stopped a bomb core from running away in a nuclear chain reaction by knocking it apart with his bare hands, knowing that in doing so he had absorbed a deadly dose of radiation.</p>
        <p>Given this verisimilitude I found it annoying that Gallagher has made Leo Kavan a Czech. In real life, Szilard was one of a group of brilliant, influential Hungarian scientists, nicknamed the Martians, who came to this country. Gallagher recycles the Martian moniker, but it goes over like fingernails on a blackboard.</p>
        <p>The real-life Szilard instigated (and perhaps wrote) Einstein's letter to President Roosevelt that eventually led to the atomic bomb. Szilard didn't desert the project, as Gallagher's Leo does, but he wrote another letter to the president as the war was winding down, urging him not to use the bomb on Japan. Roosevelt died before reading it.</p>
        <p>We can argue about what might have happened if Roosevelt had lived to receive this second letter. History's final verdict on the atomic dawn has yet to be written, but Gallagher has come up with a convincing vision of what it was like to be in old New Mexico more than 60 years ago, when the light changed forever.</p>
        <p>Dennis Overbye is a science correspondent for The Times. His most recent book is ''Einstein in Love: A Scientific Romance.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dennis Overbye is a science correspondent for The Times. His most recent book is ''Einstein in Love: A Scientific Romance.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
