<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Delivers a Spring Break Punch to Get Back in the Fight</title>
    <meta content="08memo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/washington/08memo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LETTER FROM CRAWFORD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Crawford (Tex)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E5DE143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Delivers a Spring Break Punch to Get Back in the Fight</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">White House Delivers a Spring Break Punch to Get Back in the Fight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>CRAWFORD, Tex., April 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush's decision to use Congressional recess to fill three administrative posts with appointees Senate Democrats have vowed to block puts his administration in robust fight that even Bush's most dispirited backers can get excited about; high stakes strategy will culminate in fight over war financing; administration hopes to paint Democrats as causing delay by pushing bill they know Bush will not sign (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On its face, President Bush's decision to use the Congressional recess to fill three administration posts with appointees Senate Democrats had vowed to block -- including a man who helped finance attacks against John Kerry's war record in the 2004 presidential race -- was a puzzler.</p>
        <p>With Democrats in Congress pressuring him to fire Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales and scale back in Iraq, and polls registering continued low approval ratings, Mr. Bush seemed to be poking a sharp stick at Congressional Democrats from weak ground -- in the middle of a major clash over war financing, no less.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three recess appointments have helped put the White House back where it likes to be: in a robust fight with the Democrats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On its face, President Bush's decision to use the Congressional recess to fill three administration posts with appointees Senate Democrats had vowed to block -- including a man who helped finance attacks against John Kerry's war record in the 2004 presidential race -- was a puzzler.</p>
        <p>With Democrats in Congress pressuring him to fire Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales and scale back in Iraq, and polls registering continued low approval ratings, Mr. Bush seemed to be poking a sharp stick at Congressional Democrats from weak ground -- in the middle of a major clash over war financing, no less.</p>
        <p>But the calculation behind the moves, White House officials said, was as plain as the logo on the coffee mugs for sale down the country road from Mr. Bush's ranch here that read, ''W: Still Our President.''</p>
        <p>The recess appointments helped put the White House where it likes to be: in a robust fight with the Democrats that even the president's most dispirited backers can get excited about. As one administration official put it, ''It allows us to get our footing back, at least, on issues that resonate with the public.''</p>
        <p>It is a high-stakes strategy that will culminate in the fight over war financing on Capitol Hill. The fight will start anew next week, when Congress returns from its break. But as the president has vacationed here, his administration has been pressing against the Democrats on all fronts.</p>
        <p>There was Vice President Dick Cheney on Thursday, saying on Rush Limbaugh's radio program that the Democrats were ''prepared to pack it in and come home in defeat'' in Iraq; administration officials giving reporters a running count of days that have passed without the release of $100 billion in war financing the president has requested; and the president chiming in on his radio address, saying, ''Sixty-one days have passed since I sent Congress an emergency war spending bill.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has rarely lost a fight over support for the troops, but things are different now. Administration officials said they were confident they could paint the Democrats as causing the delay, arguing that they knowingly pushed war-financing bills that the president would not sign because they included timelines for withdrawal from Iraq.</p>
        <p>''The American people want Congress to fund the troops, not micromanage the generals from Washington,'' said Gordon D. Johndroe, an administration spokesman. But the dynamic in the debate over the war has evolved over the last year, as public support has eroded.</p>
        <p>''Normally, the president wins on something like this, but now it's not so clear,'' said Frank Luntz, a Republican pollster. ''The problem for him right now is that his popularity is so low that it undermines his credibility right where he needs it the most.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Luntz said the Democrats had their own risks. They undercut their claim to the moral high ground, he said, by securing passage of the withdrawal provisions through the appropriation of billions in pork spending to the states of politically endangered Democrats for items like shrimp farming and peanut storage.</p>
        <p>Yet Democrats see an opportunity to turn Mr. Bush's formerly strong suit against him -- placing him in a position where, whatever his argument, he will have to ultimately veto a bill that finances the troops.</p>
        <p>''Democrats are comfortable that they are where the American people are, and that this administration is isolated from the will of the people,'' said Jim Manley, a spokesman for Senator Harry Reid, Democrat of Nevada, the majority leader.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manley said the Democrats would continue to defend against the White House's attacks by highlighting delays in war financing when Congress was held by Republicans, which did not prompt similar accusations that lawmakers were harming the troops. Now, Democrats are complaining that Mr. Bush's recess appointments only made it harder to cooperate.</p>
        <p>Democrats were most angered by the appointment of Sam Fox to the ambassadorship of Belgium. Mr. Fox gave $50,000 to Swift Boat Veterans for Truth, the group that attacked Mr. Kerry's war record. The Senate had made it clear last month it would not confirm him.</p>
        <p>''When they do the Sam Fox appointment and all this other stuff, it's to communicate to their base, 'We're here; we're fighting,' '' said Representative Rahm Emanuel, Democrat of Illinois. ''They can't afford to look like they're throwing in the towel.'' Though White House officials say lawmakers forced the president's hand to make appointments in their absence, they did not entirely disagree with Mr. Emanuel.</p>
        <p>Last month, the White House came under criticism from its own supporters for not charging hard enough at the Democrats, with Fred Barnes of The Weekly Standard writing that Mr. Bush was having a ''crisis of presidential leadership.''</p>
        <p>''He's responsible for leading -- and defending -- his administration and the Republican Party,'' Mr. Barnes wrote. ''He's failing in both of these duties.''</p>
        <p>The fighting spirit of Mr. Bush's core supporters was on full display here Friday when Cindy Sheehan, the war protester, marched near Mr. Bush's ranch. A clerk at a local gift shop told a story of the protesters flashing a peace sign at two elderly women who support Mr. Bush and had driven out to get a look at his ranch. The women responded, the clerk said, by flashing ''half a peace sign.''</p>
        <p>LETTER FROM CRAWFORD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
