<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Added Attraction: A Charming Bistro</title>
    <meta content="08LIDineLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08LIDine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/MALVERNE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blue Sky Bistro (Malverne, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E2DC163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Added Attraction: A Charming Bistro</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Added Attraction: A Charming Bistro</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Blue Sky Bistro in Malverne, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BLUE SKY BISTRO does Malverne proud. In contrast to its neighbors in a tiny strip mall -- a Chinese takeout and a nondescript pizza parlor -- Blue Sky Bistro has a polished stone front and a brave little topiary tree in a pot by the door.</p>
        <p>The interior of the restaurant, which opened in October, also goes beyond run-of-the-mill. Tables boast white cloths and napkins, nosegays of fresh flowers and votive candles. More candles flicker on a wrought-iron wall decoration. The walls are painted a pale sage green and, yes, the ceiling is sky blue. There is an abstract painting on one wall, but the most arresting decoration is the collection of black-and-white photographs of everyday objects: a street sign, a park bench, a water fountain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Blue Sky Bistro, with it satisfying food and interior, does Malverne proud.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BLUE SKY BISTRO does Malverne proud. In contrast to its neighbors in a tiny strip mall -- a Chinese takeout and a nondescript pizza parlor -- Blue Sky Bistro has a polished stone front and a brave little topiary tree in a pot by the door.</p>
        <p>The interior of the restaurant, which opened in October, also goes beyond run-of-the-mill. Tables boast white cloths and napkins, nosegays of fresh flowers and votive candles. More candles flicker on a wrought-iron wall decoration. The walls are painted a pale sage green and, yes, the ceiling is sky blue. There is an abstract painting on one wall, but the most arresting decoration is the collection of black-and-white photographs of everyday objects: a street sign, a park bench, a water fountain.</p>
        <p>As we left the restaurant one evening, Richard Reilly, the chef and owner, was in the small bar near the door saying goodbye to diners. He pointed out that the striking photographs were all of Malverne sites.</p>
        <p>''I love Malverne,'' he said. ''I live here, and my kids go to the local schools.''</p>
        <p>The food at Blue Sky Bistro -- the chef de cuisine is Jeffrey Scala -- is also worth crowing about. It was eminently satisfying, as much for the accompaniments as for the main attraction on the plate. Take the loin of pork. It was juicy and delicious but eclipsed by its plate mates: a mélange of toasted nutty spaetzle, quartered brussels sprouts, roasted shallots and lardons of crispy bacon.</p>
        <p>Every entree was a well thought out combination of exciting ingredients. The pan-seared salmon, with its crusty skin, rested on a mix of Swiss chard, tomato, pickled pearl onions and lightly toasted gnocchi, all sparked by a black olive vinaigrette. Seared scallops shared the limelight with a B.L.T. risotto bursting with flavor from pancetta, arugula and a tomato confit. How often do you see rabbit on a Long Island menu? Here, the treat is a succulent leg stuffed with a bull's-eye of loin meat, accompanied by mashed potatoes and a lively fricassee of Swiss chard and wild mushroom.</p>
        <p>Appetizers were equally exciting. Even the house salad transcended cliché, with a paper-thin slice of soppresatta as crisp as bacon, a dab of creamy Gorgonzola and a tomato confit. My favorite opener was a pairing of seared shrimp and fat spears of asparagus with a puddle of hollandaise and a few citrus segments on the plate. Other appetizers not to be missed were the meltingly tender duck leg confit with crispy cubes of potato and braised Napa cabbage, a lush Tuscan white bean soup and crunchy smoked trout fritters enhanced by a bit of avocado mousse and red onion marmalade.</p>
        <p>The best dessert was the virtuous-sounding citrus salad, which was wickedly good. It featured cubes of tangy lemon poundcake, citrus segments, a delicate mint sauce and a dollop of whipped cream. The coconut-flavored crème brûlée was everything it should be: firm, satiny custard with an appropriately crunchy lid. The espresso semifreddo turned out to be tiramisù and a very good one. Mr. Reilly, in his farewells at the door, confided that the dessert didn't sell when it was called tiramisù on the menu, but it was a big hit under its new name.</p>
        <p>Blue Sky Bistro is a sweet little restaurant with wonderfully satisfying food, but it isn't perfect. Tight quarters and a bare tile floor make the place noisy on busy nights. Additionally, even though service is small-town friendly, there were a few minor slip-ups. For example, when we ran out of butter, the ramekin sat empty and was refilled only when we requested more.</p>
        <p>Dining companions from nearby towns said that they had thought of Malverne only as a place to go to the movies. (The nearby Malverne Cinema shows alternatives to Hollywood blockbusters.) Now, the Blue Sky Bistro is another major draw.</p>
        <p>Blue Sky Bistro</p>
        <p>366 Hempstead Avenue  Malverne  (516) 599-9002</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE PLACE -- Small, charming storefront with upscale touches. Wheelchair accessibility.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Noisy and casual, with many local people: small groups, couples and a few families.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- A small bar with a half-dozen stools near the entrance. The restaurant was awaiting its liquor license at the time of my visits. Diners were encouraged to bring their own wine.</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Lunch (called tea) entrees, $6 to $12. Sunday brunch, $24. Dinner entrees, $16 to $38.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Tuscan white bean soup, house salad, smoked trout fritters; duck leg confit, shrimp-asparagus pairing, leg of rabbit, loin of pork, salmon, scallops with risotto; all desserts.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Lunch (tea): Tuesday to Friday, noon to 3 p.m. Brunch: Sunday, noon to 4 p.m. Dinner: Tuesday to Saturday, 5 to 10:30 p.m. Closed all day Monday and Sunday dinner. Reservations are a must.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 8, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/MALVERNE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
