<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Country' Living and Quiet Neighbors</title>
    <meta content="08post" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/realestate/08post.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Green-Wood Cemetery (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Fred A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6DE173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Country' Living and Quiet Neighbors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">‘Country’ Living and Quiet Neighbors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED A. BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Fred A</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Number of luxury apartment buildings going up along perimeter of Green-Wood Cemetery in Greenwood Heights section of Brookyn is rising as Brooklyn's residential building boom continues; promoters of some buildings, like Greenwood Hills Condos complex, tout manicured grounds of 478-acre cemetery in marketing material while others, like developers of neighboring Simone building, make no mention of it; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the Greenwood Hill Condos, a pair of new buildings in the Greenwood Heights section of Brooklyn, the north-facing apartments have views of the Statue of Liberty and the Manhattan skyline. But the south-facing apartments face the headstone-studded hills of Green-Wood Cemetery across the street.</p>
        <p>Some people prefer the apartments with the city views, said Joseph Fuer, a senior associate at the Corcoran Group, which is representing the condominium. And others, he said, want to look across the street. ''You'll have the quietest neighbors in town,'' he tells potential buyers. The apartments facing the cemetery, with prices starting at $355,000, cost as much per square foot as the ones facing Manhattan, Mr. Fuer said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Brooklyn’s residential building boom continues, more luxury buildings are going up along the edge of Green-Wood Cemetery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the Greenwood Hill Condos, a pair of new buildings in the Greenwood Heights section of Brooklyn, the north-facing apartments have views of the Statue of Liberty and the Manhattan skyline. But the south-facing apartments face the headstone-studded hills of Green-Wood Cemetery across the street.</p>
        <p>Some people prefer the apartments with the city views, said Joseph Fuer, a senior associate at the Corcoran Group, which is representing the condominium. And others, he said, want to look across the street. ''You'll have the quietest neighbors in town,'' he tells potential buyers. The apartments facing the cemetery, with prices starting at $355,000, cost as much per square foot as the ones facing Manhattan, Mr. Fuer said.</p>
        <p>As Brooklyn's residential building boom continues, more and more luxury buildings are going up along the three-mile perimeter of Green-Wood, which, at 478 acres, is almost as large as nearby Prospect Park. And while there have always been houses along the cemetery's edge, the new apartments, in some cases, are high-priced condominiums, complete with glass-tiled showers, stainless-steel kitchens and equally lustrous marketing materials.</p>
        <p>Promoters of some buildings use the cemetery as a selling point, though none has gone so far as to trumpet the chance to live near dead celebrities (Leonard Bernstein, Edward R. Murrow and Jean-Michel Basquiat, for instance). Others pretend Green-Wood doesn't exist, perhaps fearing that the cemetery will deter potential buyers.</p>
        <p>At the Greenwood Hill Condos, marketing materials mention ''the impeccably manicured grounds of historic Green-Wood Cemetery.''</p>
        <p>But only a few blocks away, a new building called the Simone, at 35 McDonald Avenue, seems to avoid association with the cemetery -- despite the fact that the building was designed with setbacks so that many units have large terraces facing the memorial park (with the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge, Coney Island's Parachute Jump, and even bits of New Jersey in the distance).</p>
        <p>The Simone Web site and brochure never mention the cemetery, though they tout Brooklyn attractions much farther away. A map fails to name the swath of green directly across from the building.</p>
        <p>Andrew Booth, a vice president at Corcoran, the exclusive agent for the building, said a marketing company had presented the materials that way, and Corcoran had approved them. ''We didn't make a conscious decision not to mention the cemetery,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At a recent open house, several buyers said the cemetery wasn't a deterrent; a bigger issue, one said, is the lack of transportation options, with the F train a third of a mile away.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Booth said that 70 percent of the units in the building had sold, at prices topping out at well over $1 million.</p>
        <p>Gus Chiarello, who will soon be closing on a two-bedroom apartment with sweeping views, said that seeing the cemetery through his floor-to-ceiling windows was anything but a problem. He has lived his entire life in a house facing Green-Wood (on Minna Street, in the Kensington section, about a mile away). When he was growing up in the 1970s, he said, the cemetery was the place he went sledding in the winter. ''My friends and I climbed over the fence,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Having it outside ''is like living in the country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chiarello's new condo, which has a huge terrace facing the cemetery, was listed at $675,000. It is so beautifully appointed, he said, that living there ''will be like staying in the W Hotel every night.''</p>
        <p>But none of the W Hotels, at least in New York, has cemetery views.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chiarello said that both his mother and his father are buried in Green-Wood, and nearer to his new apartment than to the house he grew up in. ''By buying at the Simone,'' he said, ''I'm actually getting closer to my parents.''</p>
        <p>POSTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
