<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Winning Choreographer Gives the Campus a Whirl</title>
    <meta content="08LIdanceLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08LIdance.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hofstra University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarke, Martha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipson, Karin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hofstra University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clarke, Martha</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DC163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Winning Choreographer Gives the Campus a Whirl</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Winning Choreographer Gives the Campus a Whirl</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARIN LIPSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipson, Karin</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with choreographer and director Martha Clarke, who is special visiting professor for semester at Hofstra University in Hempstead, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''WELCOME to the madness,'' Martha Clarke said genially, ushering a recent guest into a Hofstra University dance studio where her two fluff ball Pomeranians, Sofie and Pie, were alternately dozing and mixing it up with the class.</p>
        <p>The choreographer and director -- known for theater pieces that interweave text, dance, music and visual art -- was guiding young dancers through their paces at the campus, where she is a special visiting professor for the semester.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The choreographer and director Martha Clarke is working with students on Hofstra University's spring dance program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''WELCOME to the madness,'' Martha Clarke said genially, ushering a recent guest into a Hofstra University dance studio where her two fluff ball Pomeranians, Sofie and Pie, were alternately dozing and mixing it up with the class.</p>
        <p>The choreographer and director -- known for theater pieces that interweave text, dance, music and visual art -- was guiding young dancers through their paces at the campus, where she is a special visiting professor for the semester.</p>
        <p>Despite her cheerily dire warning, there was no apparent madness (except for the occasional dash by the fluff balls) as Ms. Clarke moved from a sophomore choreography class to a rehearsal with 13 handpicked students working with her on a piece for Hofstra's spring dance concert April 19 to 22.</p>
        <p>The work, called ''Studies With Mask,'' has been a collaboration between teacher -- she prefers the term ''provocateur'' -- and students ranging from freshmen to seniors.</p>
        <p>That afternoon, though, rehearsal was not starting off as Ms. Clarke had hoped. ''We're never going to have time to chisel this out -- you O.K. with that?'' she asked the dancers, sounding at once solicitous and a bit alarmed.</p>
        <p>This has been a challenging undertaking for the 62-year-old artist, who gained fame with her seminal 1984 production, ''The Garden of Earthly Delights'' (based on the fantastical Hieronymus Bosch altarpiece), which sent performers flying, tumbling and spinning through the air. She has won multiple awards, including an Obie (for ''Vienna: Lusthaus'' in 1986) and a 1990 MacArthur Foundation ''genius'' grant.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Clarke had never worked with liberal arts undergraduates before this semester. ''For the first few weeks, I kind of sat in a state of terror,'' she told an audience last month at a Hofstra symposium. Accustomed to lengthy gestations for her work, ''I was quite frightened by a lack of time.''</p>
        <p>Still, she did not impose a ready-made piece on her concert students, whose improvisations helped create ''Studies With Mask.''</p>
        <p>Improv is risky, but ''I believe in spontaneity and instinct and in following things you don't understand,'' Ms. Clarke said. ''If I can give them anything, it's a sense of play and playfulness.''</p>
        <p>The playful provocateur, who lives in western Connecticut, was invited to Hofstra by the university's director of dance, Lance Westergard. ''I've known Martha since we were kids at Juilliard,'' he said. ''She was two years ahead of me. She's a maverick -- out in the field by herself most of the time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Westergard diplomatically stayed away from most of the rehearsals, but he ventured that ''Studies With Mask'' would offer ''a different way of looking at the stage, and of movement in space.'' Ms. Clarke's contribution will be one of five works on the program by as many choreographers, including a guest artist, Rosalind Newman, who said that her ''very conceptual'' piece would explore notions of time and distance.</p>
        <p>Ms. Clarke's own self-described theatrical bent emerged as her recent rehearsal wore on. One dancer donned a black mask; others, party hats retrieved from Ms. Clarke's closet at home. Clutches of students gamboled to haunting, percussive sounds played by Arthur Solari, the dance program's music director, or walked together, laughing. Two young women approached and half-embraced, lending the scene a charged sensuality.</p>
        <p>''It's a slightly decadent ball, in sweat pants,'' said Ms. Clarke, who said she had conceived the setting while reading a biography of Marie Antoinette. What the piece needed now, she told the students, was ''a little bit more whoosh.''</p>
        <p>Some days later, she reported an improved ''whoosh'' factor. And the students, she noted, have been ''very generous and very brave'' in following her lead.</p>
        <p>''I kind of feel like they're visiting Disneyland with me,'' she said. ''It's kind of a ride.''</p>
        <p>The Hofstra University Spring Dance Concert, with works by Martha Clarke, Rosalind Newman and several choreographers from the Hofstra faculty, will take place April 19 to 22 at the John Cranford Adams Playhouse, Hofstra University, South Campus. Tickets and information: (516) 463-6644, weekdays 11 a.m. to 3:45 p.m.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
