<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Slain F.B.I. Agent Is Recalled As Watchful, Loyal Neighbor</title>
    <meta content="08agent" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/08agent.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bank Robberies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Readington Township (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Easton (Pa)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pnc Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Barry Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schweber, Nate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEEDC143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Slain F.B.I. Agent Is Recalled As Watchful, Loyal Neighbor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Slain F.B.I. Agent Is Recalled as Watchful, Loyal Neighbor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE SCHWEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schweber, Nate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barry Lee Bush, FBI agent killed after being hit by bullet, apparently fired accidentally by another agent, during confrontation with bank robbery suspects in Readington Township, NJ, is remembered by friends, family and neighbors in Easton, Pa; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though Barry Lee Bush knew well the dangers that went with being an F.B.I. agent, he liked to joke that the most perilous part of his day was the hourlong commute to his office in Newark from his home in Easton, Pa., a friend and neighbor of Mr. Bush said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's assignments took him overseas and around the country, but when he was home the neighborhood slept better, said the friend, Joe Douress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though Barry Lee Bush knew the dangers that went with his job, he liked to joke that the most perilous part of his day was the hourlong commute to his office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Though Barry Lee Bush knew well the dangers that went with being an F.B.I. agent, he liked to joke that the most perilous part of his day was the hourlong commute to his office in Newark from his home in Easton, Pa., a friend and neighbor of Mr. Bush said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's assignments took him overseas and around the country, but when he was home the neighborhood slept better, said the friend, Joe Douress.</p>
        <p>''I always felt secure in knowing that Barry lived across the street because I knew he would keep a good, close eye on my house and my family,'' Mr. Douress, 47, said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, 52, died Thursday after being hit by a bullet, apparently fired accidentally by another agent, during the arrest of two bank robbery suspects outside a bank in Readington Township, N.J.</p>
        <p>Those men, and two suspects arrested later, will be arraigned on robbery and weapons charges tomorrow afternoon at the federal courthouse in Newark, said Michael Drewniak, a spokesman for the United States attorney in New Jersey. At least two other men believed to be part of a bank robbery gang that Mr. Bush and the other agents were pursuing are being sought in connection with a string of holdups in South Brunswick, East Brunswick, Ocean Township and Piscataway, he said.</p>
        <p>In Easton, which is near the New Jersey border, Mr. Bush's family remained in their two-story home in a neighborhood that was once farmland. The family, including Mr. Bush's wife of 25 years, Karen, their daughter, Jennifer, 23, who works in the mortgage business locally, and their son, Steven, 20, a student at the University of Delaware, were grieving but ''remaining very strong,'' according to Mr. Douress, who said he had known the family for 15 years. He said a funeral was planned for Thursday in Pottstown, Pa., where Mr. Bush was raised.</p>
        <p>Around the neighborhood Mr. Bush was known for spending hours working on his yard. Mr. Douress said Mr. Bush decorated his home with Civil War artifacts bought on many expeditions to antique shops in Gettysburg, Pa., and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>A fitness enthusiast, Mr. Bush often rode his bike, played tennis with neighbors and on warm evenings took long walks with his wife, who was his high school sweetheart, Mr. Douress said. Each Memorial Day weekend for the past 15 years Mr. Bush played in and helped organize a charity golf tournament held in honor of Mr. Douress's nephew, who died of leukemia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush spent the early part of his career as a correction officer and a police officer, and ''felt he reached the pinnacle'' when he joined the bureau in 1987, Mr. Douress said.</p>
        <p>On occasion, Mr. Douress would hear something about his neighbor's work -- from pursuing narcotics cases in South America to investigating the 1998 United States Embassy bombing in Nairobi, Kenya, to helping track down the sniper who killed a Buffalo-area obstetrician, Dr. Barnett A. Slepian, the same year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Douress last saw Mr. Bush two weeks ago, he said, when Mr. Bush knocked on his door and offered to help put together registration packets for this year's golf tournament.</p>
        <p>''He knelt down and stuffed envelopes and licked stamps for half an hour,'' Mr. Douress said. ''It's poignant that he helped me prepare for this year's tournament. Barry will be with us in spirit forever.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
