<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Form, Function and Controversy</title>
    <meta content="08goods" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/yourmoney/08goods.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OPENERS: THE GOODS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Goods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crosses and Crucifixes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crosses and Crucifixes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Form, Function and Controversy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Form, Function and Controversy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENDAN I. KOERNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Koerner, Brendan I</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CLEANLINESS, as the saying goes, is next to godliness. But combine these two virtues into a single product and some consumers may take offense.</p>
        <p>That is the lesson Ian Stallard, a partner in the London design firm FredriksonStallard, has learned from creating the Cross brushes, a set of cleaning tools shaped like Christianity's most sacred symbol. ''Some people have become very upset about it,'' said Mr. Stallard, recalling a number of vitriolic e-mail messages his company has received. The negative feedback doesn't really bother Mr. Stallard and his collaborator, Patrik Fredrikson. The Cross brushes were meant to provoke controversy, although the designers say that blasphemy was never their goal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cleanliness, as the saying goes, is next to godliness. But combine these two virtues into a single product and some consumers may take offense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CLEANLINESS, as the saying goes, is next to godliness. But combine these two virtues into a single product and some consumers may take offense.</p>
        <p>That is the lesson Ian Stallard, a partner in the London design firm FredriksonStallard, has learned from creating the Cross brushes, a set of cleaning tools shaped like Christianity's most sacred symbol. ''Some people have become very upset about it,'' said Mr. Stallard, recalling a number of vitriolic e-mail messages his company has received. The negative feedback doesn't really bother Mr. Stallard and his collaborator, Patrik Fredrikson. The Cross brushes were meant to provoke controversy, although the designers say that blasphemy was never their goal.</p>
        <p>''We're not trying to be nasty or arrogant,'' said Mr. Stallard, who characterizes himself and Mr. Fredrikson as ''nonreligious.'' ''We're saying, 'Here is a symbol with a story. Read into it whatever you want.' ''</p>
        <p>The brushes were inspired by the 9/11 terrorist attacks. ''There was all this religious hysteria at the time,'' Mr. Stallard said. In response, he and Mr. Fredrikson planned a series of seven to nine brushes, shaped like the world's best-known symbols of faith, including the Islamic crescent and Judaism's Star of David. But the designers ultimately decided to make only the cross, in part because of its simplicity, but also because it seemed like the symbol least likely to cause an uproar.</p>
        <p>''I find that Christianity is the most accepting and forgiving religion, generally,'' said Mr. Stallard. ''I think Christianity may be a little bit more open to criticism.''</p>
        <p>FredriksonStallard commissioned a brush maker in rural England to make two one-of-a-kind versions of their designs: an oak brush with pig bristles and a cast-iron brush with steel bristles.</p>
        <p>In 2003, the firm exhibited these products at 100 Percent Design, a trade show in London. A representative from Citizen:Citizen, a San Francisco distributor of imaginative products, loved the brushes and worked out a deal with Mr. Fredrikson and Mr. Stallard to produce them in the United States.</p>
        <p>FredriksonStallard sent its technical drawings to a brush maker in Maine. Prototypes were shipped back across the Atlantic, but the earliest ones did not measure up to the standards of Mr. Fredrikson and Mr. Stallard. They were concerned, for example, when they held the prototypes up to a lighter and the bristles melted into a viscous pool. They insisted that the wood grain on the handles be free of knots. And they rejected models in which the bristles were not aligned in perfect rows.</p>
        <p>Citizen:Citizen wound up producing and selling two versions of the Cross brushes. One is intended for scouring tiles and tubs; it went on sale in May 2005. The other is meant for removing lint and hair from clothes; it was introduced a year later. (The cast-iron version, initially envisioned as a boot cleaner, never went into production.) Both brushes are available through Citizen-Citizen.com -- the scouring brush for $128 and the lint remover for $95.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stallard said that he didn't know how many brushes had been sold, but that he was surprised by the products' popularity among religious consumers.</p>
        <p>''People have told us that they've bought it because they like having a Christian artifact,'' he said. Other consumers -- perhaps the more traditional clientele for FredriksonStallard's avant-garde vases and coffee tables -- have been attracted to the brushes as wry takes on faith.</p>
        <p>Several people have challenged Mr. Fredrikson and Mr. Stallard to follow through on their original idea and design a brush shaped like the Islamic crescent. But Mr. Stallard doubts that they will: ''We don't,'' he said, ''want to get into a big religious debate.''</p>
        <p>OPENERS: THE GOODS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
