<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chained to His Desk</title>
    <meta content="08POSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/fashion/08POSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSSESSED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Dunham, Carroll</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E0D9173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chained to His Desk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chained to His Desk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID COLMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Colman, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS Jonathan Lethem made clear so cleverly in his purposely plagiarized article, ''The Ecstasy of Influence,'' in the February Harper's, no canvas is ever really blank. And artists are cut from the same cloth, the tapestry of art history.</p>
        <p>Even so, to many artists this cloth is somewhat itchy. Why else do so many of them scoff at tradition and march off in rebel wear: soiled T-shirts, leather jackets and rebel hair?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cornerstone of the painter Carroll Dunham’s studio is a desk that belonged to his grandfather.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS Jonathan Lethem made clear so cleverly in his purposely plagiarized article, ''The Ecstasy of Influence,'' in the February Harper's, no canvas is ever really blank. And artists are cut from the same cloth, the tapestry of art history.</p>
        <p>Even so, to many artists this cloth is somewhat itchy. Why else do so many of them scoff at tradition and march off in rebel wear: soiled T-shirts, leather jackets and rebel hair?</p>
        <p>This specific affectation never managed to infect the painter Carroll Dunham. Given his raucously colored, cartoonish burlesques of bodily protuberances and orifices, a show of which is now up at the Gladstone Gallery in Chelsea, you would expect at least some token of revolt.</p>
        <p>''I get this all the time,'' said Mr. Dunham, who dresses as he speaks -- quietly and well. ''People think I am supposed to have safety pins and purple hair.''</p>
        <p>This twofold path of self-expression is encapsulated in his new show. One room is all proper geometry and good tailoring: yellows and blacks, lapels and pocket squares. The other is topsy-turvy, to say the least: half-naked bodies and spectacularly rude gestures in pink and gray. Just as striking as the difference between these two modes is how rationally levelheaded Mr. Dunham is about his paintings, which despite their raw physicality seem to have been concocted through a scientific formula, a fact borne out by his neatly arrayed studio in the Red Hook area of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>The cornerstone of this studio is a desk that belonged to his grandfather, who was in the import-export business. Once the property of a New York customs inspector, so the legend goes, the desk remained for decades with an uncle of Mr. Dunham's, then ended up in his father's basement, where Mr. Dunham saw it, admired it and, about 1994, found it his.</p>
        <p>It's a good-looking piece: square, straightforward, of the school that might be called 19th-century practical. But beside the fact that it's the right height -- just to the bottom of Mr. Dunham's rib cage -- for him to use from a standing position, which he likes, it is not quite what it seems.</p>
        <p>''It's barely holding together,'' he said. ''It's all very rickety. There are a lot of nail holes and nailheads sticking out.'' Not to mention the slanted top, which at some point was made level with some homegrown carpentry, making it impossible to use while sitting down.</p>
        <p>Nor does the desk remind him of happy times with Grandfather, who died in 1948, a year before the artist was born.</p>
        <p>In spite of all this, the desk exerts a strong pull. ''I find it weirdly comforting to be around,'' he said. ''It's like a center of gravity. I've moved my studio a lot over the last several years, and it helped me get located quickly whenever I found the right place for it, usually by a window. It brings a kind of continuity to my choppy existence.''</p>
        <p>And continuity beats a file drawer. ''I am not into family genealogy or anything,'' he said, ''but I am interested in the idea of operating with an awareness of tradition. The fact that I know this was in the personal space of someone I have some familiar connection to makes me feel connected to something bigger than me. That's how I think about working as a painter. It's being part of the chain of things.''</p>
        <p>So while other artists may find tradition stifling, Mr. Dunham sees nothing but permission to tinker. If the history -- of art or your family -- is discouraging, you may be looking at it all wrong. One man's prison is another's playground.</p>
        <p>POSSESSED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
