<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Converting a Co-op To a Condominium</title>
    <meta content="08home" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/realestate/08home.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6DE173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Converting a Co-op To a Condominium</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Converting a Co-op to a Condominium</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your Home column on pros and cons of converting co-op building to condominium; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE question often asked is whether it makes sense for a co-op to convert to a condominium. And most lawyers say that completing such a conversion is almost always more trouble -- and more costly -- than it's worth.</p>
        <p>''At least a dozen times a year I'm asked by boards about converting from a co-op to a condominium,'' said Stuart M. Saft, the chairman of the Council of New York Cooperatives and Condominiums. ''And in virtually every instance the complexity of the procedure or the tax consequences make the conversion not worth doing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most lawyers say that converting a co-op to a condominium is almost always more trouble than it’s worth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE question often asked is whether it makes sense for a co-op to convert to a condominium. And most lawyers say that completing such a conversion is almost always more trouble -- and more costly -- than it's worth.</p>
        <p>''At least a dozen times a year I'm asked by boards about converting from a co-op to a condominium,'' said Stuart M. Saft, the chairman of the Council of New York Cooperatives and Condominiums. ''And in virtually every instance the complexity of the procedure or the tax consequences make the conversion not worth doing.''</p>
        <p>Most proprietary leases require a ''super-majority'' of shareholders, as many as 80 percent, to make this sort of change, and persuading that many residents to vote in favor is the first hurdle. Next, the shareholders would have to agree on new governing documents, and the co-op would have to hire an architect to prepare and certify a new set of plans for the building ''as built.''</p>
        <p>Then there are the nuts and bolts issues of getting every owner with a share loan to pay it off or obtain consent from the lender to convert it to a mortgage. The co-op corporation would also have to pay off any mortgage on the building itself.</p>
        <p>There are also potential tax implications for both individual shareholders and the co-op corporation. Joel E. Miller, a Queens tax lawyer, said that converting an apartment from a co-op to a condo is considered a sale for tax purposes because shareholders exchange their co-op shares and proprietary leases for deeds to their apartments as condominium units. Since the transactions are considered sales, shareholders have to calculate their taxable gains based on the current market value of their apartments. So if shareholders originally paid, say, $100,000 for a co-op apartment, and that same apartment is now worth $700,000, they would have a $600,000 gain, even though they still remain the owners of the apartment.</p>
        <p>Under current tax law, Mr. Miller said, a taxpayer can exclude up to $250,000 in gains ($500,000 for married taxpayers filing jointly) on the sale of a principal residence.</p>
        <p>There are also tax consequences for the co-op corporation. Marc Shernicoff, a certified public accountant in Manhattan, said that when the co-op corporation gives a shareholder a deed in exchange for shares and the proprietary lease, that also is considered a taxable event for the co-op. Since the deed is valued at the current market value of the apartment, any increase in value over the years, from the very inception of the co-op, is considered taxable.</p>
        <p>And while the tax laws specifically exempt from taxation any gain associated with an apartment used as a principal residence by the shareholder, that exemption does not apply to apartments owned by investors and those not used as principal residences.</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Shernicoff said, even if there are only a few apartments that are not exempt from taxes as far as the co-op corporation is concerned, those few can cost the co-op hundreds of thousands of dollars in taxes.</p>
        <p>Kenneth Jacobs, a co-op and condo lawyer in Yonkers who has done such conversions, says that it is easier to make the change from a co-op to a condo than most lawyers believe. And with regard to taxes at the corporate level, Mr. Jacobs said he believes that since the proprietary lease itself has value, the I.R.S. can be persuaded to treat the transfer in such a way that will substantially reduce the tax exposure of the corporation.</p>
        <p>For those who want more information, The Cooperator, a monthly magazine about co-op and condo issues published by Yale Robbins, is conducting a panel discussion on converting from co-op to condo at its annual expo on April 25 at the New York Hilton. More information is available by calling (212) 683-5700 or online at coopexpo.com.</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
