<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amy Knapp and Myron Walden</title>
    <meta content="08vows" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/fashion/weddings/08vows.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knapp, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walden, Myron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DB173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amy Knapp and Myron Walden</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amy Knapp and Myron Walden</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER TUNG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OVER the last few decades, Amy Knapp's genius with numbers and her fierce business acumen have propelled her up the corporate ladder, landing her most recently in the position of chief executive of UnitedHealthcare for the Southeast. But her biggest passion is emotional, unfettered and far from corporate: jazz.</p>
        <p>''The hook that pulls me in is instrumental jazz,'' said Ms. Knapp, 51, who discovered the genre in the 1970s at Pomona College, in Claremont, Calif. ''Nobody's telling the story to you. You're free to hear the music and let it move you, inspire you and set you free.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A jazz lover and a saxophone player were immediately drawn to one another, despite their differences in age, race and profession.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OVER the last few decades, Amy Knapp's genius with numbers and her fierce business acumen have propelled her up the corporate ladder, landing her most recently in the position of chief executive of UnitedHealthcare for the Southeast. But her biggest passion is emotional, unfettered and far from corporate: jazz.</p>
        <p>''The hook that pulls me in is instrumental jazz,'' said Ms. Knapp, 51, who discovered the genre in the 1970s at Pomona College, in Claremont, Calif. ''Nobody's telling the story to you. You're free to hear the music and let it move you, inspire you and set you free.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Knapp's closest college friend, Pam Mays McDonald, recalled: ''At 18, Amy was fresh-scrubbed, perky, blond and blue-eyed and a genius at economics. I'm African-American and wore an Afro and was very free-spirited. I had a radio show and played records 24/7, so I guess I turned her on to jazz music. I taught her to be funky, and she taught me how to take notes and alphabetize things.''</p>
        <p>In 1998, Ms. Knapp, who earned her M.B.A. at the University of Southern California and was married briefly in her 20s, was named chief executive for UnitedHealthcare for the Northeast, and she moved to New York. ''For a jazz fan, New York City is like Disneyland,'' Ms. Walden said.</p>
        <p>In January 2005, she moved to Miami for her current position but kept her New York apartment and flew back on weekends. On the night of April 1 that year, she persuaded two friends to accompany her to a show at the Kitano Hotel, where they caught the last song of the last set. Ms. Knapp was struck by the saxophone player, Myron Walden, and realized she owned one of his recordings. ''He has an exuberance that draws you in,'' she said. ''He plays with great passion. I just felt compelled to say thank you.'' So she did.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walden, a 34-year-old graduate of the Manhattan School of Music, was equally struck by the petite wide-eyed woman before him. ''After a performance, I'm exhausted,'' he said. ''But Amy had so many positive vibrations. When she walked away, I felt the energy go down, and I thought: 'Oh, my goodness. I have to say something.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Walden asked Ms. Knapp to visit his Web site, and several days later, she sent him an e-mail message, and gradually they opened up to each other. They candidly discussed their differences in age (17 years), race and profession. ''It wasn't clear to either of us whether this was going to be a friendship or something else,'' Ms. Knapp said. ''So we let it flow in its own meter.''</p>
        <p>Soon, though, the e-mail messages became flirtatious.</p>
        <p>In June, Mr. Walden e-mailed Ms. Knapp the itinerary for his coming European tour with the group Brian Blade Fellowship. ''In my mind, I was saying to her, 'Wherever I am, you're more than welcome to be,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>That translation was lost on Ms. Knapp, who recalled, ''This e-mail had to be parsed by all my girlfriends.'' Ultimately, she booked a trip to Rome, coinciding with the three days Mr. Walden would be there, but she did not tell him that she was there expressly to see him.</p>
        <p>On July 14, they walked all over Rome. At one point, Ms. Knapp spotted a pair of red and magenta shoes in a shop window and went in to buy them. For some reason, Ms. Knapp's credit card was declined. Without hesitation, Mr. Walden took out his card and paid for the shoes.</p>
        <p>''The emotional, not financial, extravagance of that gesture helped me understand that he was prepared to give to me and take care of me,'' Ms. Knapp said. ''I was enjoying my life, my work, my friends and my hobbies. But something about Myron took my breath away.''</p>
        <p>They now refer to that day as their first date.</p>
        <p>Last Sunday evening, exactly two years from the day they met, the couple, who will split time between Miami and New York, married in front of about 150 family members and friends in the Allen Room at Frederick P. Rose Hall, Home of Jazz at Lincoln Center. Under her body-skimming lace-accented white dress, Ms. Knapp wore the very shoes that sealed her fate; her bouquet of deep red roses (and Mr. Walden's boutonniere) matched them perfectly. After a gospel choir sang, they exchanged vows in front of vast floor-to-ceiling windows overlooking Columbus Circle and Central Park. Titia de Lange, a Universal Life minister and a friend of Ms. Knapp's, officiated.</p>
        <p>Mrs. McDonald, who introduced Ms. Knapp to jazz 30 years ago and wrote the couple's wedding vows, said: ''She's a C.E.O., he's creative. She works with numbers, he works with notes. But I've seen their deep soul connection. He practices eight hours a day getting his technique down so his soul can flow through the performance, and Amy is organized mentally, but she improvises and lets her soul come through in her work. They're both stars.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
