<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bibliophiles Not Baby Sitters</title>
    <meta content="08WEborchert" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borchert, Don</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0D6163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bibliophiles Not Baby Sitters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Don Borchert</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borchert, Don</byline>
      <dateline>TORRANCE, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by librarian Don Borchert offers suggestions for dealing with bored and unruly teens during after-school hours (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EARLIER this year, the Maplewood Memorial Library in New Jersey became the center of controversy over what is a growing problem throughout the region and across the country.</p>
        <p>Faced with unruly middle school students who were flocking to the library after school, library officials announced plans to close on weekdays from 2:45 to 5 p.m. The resulting uproar was so intense that the town's mayor stepped in to keep the doors open. And in addition to the town's providing security guards at the library's two buildings, community groups decided to extend the hours of after-school programs and expand their offerings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EARLIER this year, the Maplewood Memorial Library in New Jersey became the center of controversy over what is a growing problem throughout the region and across the country.</p>
        <p>Faced with unruly middle school students who were flocking to the library after school, library officials announced plans to close on weekdays from 2:45 to 5 p.m. The resulting uproar was so intense that the town's mayor stepped in to keep the doors open. And in addition to the town's providing security guards at the library's two buildings, community groups decided to extend the hours of after-school programs and expand their offerings.</p>
        <p>This was good news all around. After all, librarians like people coming into their libraries. But that librarians were even considering such drastic action highlights what a serious issue this has become.</p>
        <p>And it's not just Maplewood. Nearby Irvington struggled with similar problems several years ago as have libraries in Connecticut and Westchester and on Long Island.</p>
        <p>I have worked in a library for more than 10 years. It is across the street from a junior high school and a few blocks away from an elementary school. At 2 p.m., the library is a place of intellectual curiosity, civilized calm and innate civility. The regular patrons are uniformly aware of the witching hour. They know that they have to be checked out and in their cars with the windows rolled up by 3:15 p.m. -- tops!</p>
        <p>The teenagers and preteenagers are like a storm surge. They've been sitting all day; they've been good and relatively quiet. But now school's out. By 3:25 p.m., the library is packed, every seat is taken, the noise level ramps up and even the homeless lose their nerve and bolt for the door. There are, at most, four full-time library employees braced for this assault. They have gone to graduate school and know how to recommend a good adventure novel and how to put together a bibliography, but none have been trained for anything like this.</p>
        <p>Facing us may be 100 to 125 middle school students. Some will open a book; others will take out pencil and paper and start doing their homework. But we're not homework monitors, and so many of them don't bother. They are there because that's where their parents told them to be until they get picked up -- usually around 6 p.m., sometimes as late as 7:30, and in a few odious situations, well past 8 p.m., when we are officially closed.</p>
        <p>Three to four hours a day in the library for a teenager is punishment, pure and simple. We are paid to be there. They are not. Even the ones who bear down and do their homework are bored with the whole affair in an hour or two. Their options are limited. So they go wild.</p>
        <p>The four library employees don't have a chance. It's like trying to take four conscientious adults and put them in charge of crowd control for the French Revolution. While one employee is calming down a small group of radicals by the science project books, another group is erecting a guillotine in the juvenile biographies.</p>
        <p>What's the solution? We have had some success with asking the wilder youngsters to leave -- and not allowing them back until they are accompanied by a parent or guardian. It may not be fair, but it gives us a chance to meet the folks and make a pitch for solidarity. Usually they understand.</p>
        <p>We've been known to call the police in certain circumstances, but we'd better have a really good reason. Renting a security guard or hiring more librarians is neither in the cards nor the current budget.</p>
        <p>Still there are some creative solutions. A library in Norwalk, Conn., offers training to staff members in dealing with adolescents. The library has created a teenage advisory board and blocks computer access of anyone caught misbehaving.</p>
        <p>In an attempt to deal with rowdy teenagers, the New Rochelle Public Library recently got a grant to install more computers. Indeed, several libraries in Westchester and Nassau Counties are using computer technology in educational and recreational ways to work with teenagers during after-school hours. In our library, we've gotten good mileage out of cheap plastic chess sets. It's a war game of sorts, and they're mesmerized.</p>
        <p>But dealing with disruptive teenagers is not something that can be fixed simply with a parade of innovative ideas. In many parts of the country, there's a baby boom going on -- and those babies are going to grow up fast. With more and more parents choosing or having to work outside the home, public libraries need to stand up and admit they have problems.</p>
        <p>City officials should see to it that those libraries with a significant number of teenage users have at least one librarian who is trained to provide programs for adolescents. Depending on the number of teenagers pouring into the library, they might also consider dedicating specific space in the library just for them.</p>
        <p>And if a library finds that a security guard is necessary, it would be sweet synchronicity between the libraries and the schools to set up a program where teachers and principals chaperone for a few hours each week.</p>
        <p>In many ways, the Maplewood Memorial Library forced the issue to the forefront, and the community is responding in all the right ways. I hope they succeed. Libraries around the region and across the country will be watching and taking notes.</p>
        <p>Don Borchert, a librarian, is the author of the forthcoming ''Free-for-All: Oddballs, Geeks and Gangstas in the Public Library.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Don Borchert, a librarian, is the author of the forthcoming ''Free-for-All: Oddballs, Geeks and Gangstas in the Public Library.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
