<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Colt, With Big Victory, Shows Growth</title>
    <meta content="08racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/othersports/08racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kentucky Derby</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E6DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Colt, With Big Victory, Shows Growth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Colt, With Big Victory, Shows Growth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barclay Tagg took Nobiz Like Shobiz into the Wood Memorial looking for a growth spurt, a mental one that would match the colt's imposing physique. Tagg, the colt's trainer, believed he had a horse with more ability than Funny Cide, the gelding he trained to victories in the Kentucky Derby and the Preakness Stakes in 2003.</p>
        <p>Nobiz Like Shobiz, however, was an immature colt that had the tendency to look around and dilly-dally down the stretch of important races. Yesterday, Tagg took no chances. Not only did he fit Nobiz Like Shobiz with blinkers to block his peripheral vision, but he also packed his ears with cotton to blot out crowd noise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nobiz Like Shobiz withstood a late charge from Sightseeing on Saturday in the 83rd running of the Wood, one of the most important Kentucky Derby prep races.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barclay Tagg took Nobiz Like Shobiz into the Wood Memorial looking for a growth spurt, a mental one that would match the colt's imposing physique. Tagg, the colt's trainer, believed he had a horse with more ability than Funny Cide, the gelding he trained to victories in the Kentucky Derby and the Preakness Stakes in 2003.</p>
        <p>Nobiz Like Shobiz, however, was an immature colt that had the tendency to look around and dilly-dally down the stretch of important races. Yesterday, Tagg took no chances. Not only did he fit Nobiz Like Shobiz with blinkers to block his peripheral vision, but he also packed his ears with cotton to blot out crowd noise.</p>
        <p>Tagg gave the jockey, Cornelio Velasquez, a leg up and prayed that his colt was growing up. Tagg got his answer 1 minute 49.46 seconds later. Nobiz Like Shobiz first repelled the highly regarded Any Given Saturday at the stretch and then withstood a late charge from Sightseeing for a half-length victory in the 83rd running of the Wood, one of the most important Derby prep races.</p>
        <p>It means Nobiz Like Shobiz, his owner, Elizabeth Jones Valando, and Tagg are bound for Kentucky for America's greatest race as one of the favorites on the first Saturday in May.</p>
        <p>''He didn't gallop away by 10, but he had a pretty well-bred horse chasing him,'' a relieved and satisfied Tagg said. ''He'll be fine now. There were some immaturity things happening to him, but he'll get better each time.''</p>
        <p>At Hawthorne Park in Chicago yesterday and at Santa Anita Park in Arcadia, Calif., two other colts punched their tickets to the Kentucky Derby. Cowtown Cat captured the Illinois Derby, and the 29-1 long shot Tiago won the Santa Anita Derby in come-from-behind fashion much like his half-brother Giacomo, the long-shot winner of the 2005 Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>In fact, Tiago will return Giacomo's owner, Jerry Moss; trainer, John Shirreffs; and rider, Mike Smith to Kentucky.</p>
        <p>It has been a white-knuckle ride to the Derby for Tagg even though Nobiz Like Shobiz, a son of Albert the Great, had shown extraordinary talent in winning four of his six races. Last month in the Grade II Fountain of Youth Stakes at Gulfstream Park, he endured a rough trip early in the race, but still looked like the winner in the stretch.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, however, he started looking into the stands, lost his concentration and finished third, beaten by a half a length.</p>
        <p>In the opening half-mile of the mile-and-an-eighth race at Aqueduct yesterday, Nobiz Like Shobiz fought Velasquez as well.</p>
        <p>''He really wanted to go,'' Velasquez said. ''Breaking inside, I tried to get him to relax. He was just pulling me the whole time.''</p>
        <p>Velasquez finally gave the colt his head going into the far turn, and Nobiz Like Shobiz took off with Any Given Saturday in close pursuit. As they hit the stretch, however, Any Given Saturday appeared to hit the wall. Just three weeks ago, he lost a stretch duel by a nose to last year's 2-year-old champion, Street Sense.</p>
        <p>''I was disappointed in the last sixteenth of a mile,'' said Any Given Sunday's trainer, Todd Pletcher. ''He didn't really polish it off. I thought Nobiz ran a very good race. He had to rush into the first turn a little bit and get position on the inside. We got to him and we had a chance to beat him.''</p>
        <p>Barreling down the lane behind Any Given Saturday was Sightseeing. He passed him and took aim at Nobiz Like Shobiz.</p>
        <p>''It looked like he was a winner,'' said Sightseeing's trainer, Shug McGaughey. ''He drifted out a little bit. I'm tickled to death with the effort.''</p>
        <p>This time, Nobiz Like Shobiz did not get distracted. Velasquez gave him mild urging with his left hand, the blinkers kept him staring straight ahead and the cotton in his ears apparently worked. He crossed the line first to pay his backers $3.40 for a $2 bet to win. He collected a $450,000 check to push his career earnings past $850,000.</p>
        <p>''I liked that he really finished good,'' Velasquez said. ''He really ran straight today.''</p>
        <p>Nobiz Like Shobiz ran straight into the Derby.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
