<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women's Health, in Focus</title>
    <meta content="08boss" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/yourmoney/08boss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Boss</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women's Health, in Focus</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Women’s Health, in Focus</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DR. PAULA JOHNSON; As told to Patricia R. Olsen.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olsen, Patricia R; Johnson, Paula (Dr)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I GREW up in Brooklyn during the height of the civil rights movement. It was a time of change and hope. My parents reinforced that feeling and made me think I was the most privileged person alive. I've made the most of opportunities.</p>
        <p>After my residency at Brigham and Women's Hospital in Boston, I was supposed to leave for a cardiology fellowship in Philadelphia. But I had recently met my husband-to-be and I didn't want to leave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“You can achieve great things only if you understand how the environment you are in operates,” said Dr. Paula Johnson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I GREW up in Brooklyn during the height of the civil rights movement. It was a time of change and hope. My parents reinforced that feeling and made me think I was the most privileged person alive. I've made the most of opportunities.</p>
        <p>After my residency at Brigham and Women's Hospital in Boston, I was supposed to leave for a cardiology fellowship in Philadelphia. But I had recently met my husband-to-be and I didn't want to leave.</p>
        <p>I asked the chief of cardiology to release me from my commitment, saying that if he could not, I'd probably return to Boston in a year. I gave up that fellowship not knowing what the future would bring. With the help of a mentor I was offered a fellowship in Boston. It wasn't like me to change plans like that.</p>
        <p>As a third-year medical student, I had to learn the language of medicine and understand the values and currency. For instance, in presenting cases before teams of other physicians, you have to communicate in a certain way. There's an expectation about how you summarize the facts and tell the story. It's a learned skill. You can achieve great things only if you understand how the environment you are in operates.</p>
        <p>When the executive director position was first offered nine years ago, I didn't get it. It was a tremendous disappointment. I thought I was a perfect fit. But I realized I needed more leadership experience within the institution. I led the department that was charged with improving quality of care, while staying passionate about women's health.</p>
        <p>I needed stronger academic credentials, too, which I got by being promoted over the years. When the second opportunity arose five years ago, I was selected. The institution was clearer in what they needed in a leader, too.</p>
        <p>The Connors Center is similar to an entrepreneurial division that does cutting-edge work in the corporate world. It works across all traditional areas of medicine but is a separate discipline.</p>
        <p>I'm also chief of the division of women's health at the hospital. People think of women's health as mammograms and Pap smears besides general health care, but it's much more. It's understanding the science of sex differences and how that science influences the way we deliver care, both in the office and by means of highly technical procedures. That can then affect health policy as well as the next generation of scientists and leaders.</p>
        <p>Take women and heart disease. Recently a woman with a history of heart disease came to see me complaining of chest pain with exercise. Another doctor had told her that an invasive test showed nothing unusual and nothing else could be done for her. She wanted a second opinion. Women's conditions can be harder to diagnose than men's. Their heart disease is frequently more diffuse than men's, and more can suffer from small vessel disease.</p>
        <p>I was working with our invasive-cardiology group on a protocol using new technology that is more sensitive to women's coronary disease. It wasn't quite ready, so I told her to go home and I'd call her.</p>
        <p>One month later, I did. In addition to injecting dye into an artery to look for a blockage -- the traditional method -- we used intravascular ultrasound. We actually looked at the artery wall and found an abnormal area not obvious on traditional angiography. We also used a flow wire to measure blood flow across the artery. We used a stent to open the blockage and gave her medication.</p>
        <p>She's now symptom-free. That patient shows the promise of the women's health field. Not every woman with heart problems will need that procedure, but the options are there, and they're expanding.</p>
        <p>I have a 12-year-old son and a 6-year-old daughter. When I got my first BlackBerry, she was 2. I took it out one night when I was reading to her. She looked at it and said, ''Mommy, put that away.'' I'm more aware of the impact of taking it out now. Evenings are my children's time, and I try not to cheat.</p>
        <p>DR. PAULA JOHNSON  Executive director, Connors Center for Women's Health and Gender Biology, Brigham and Women's Hospital</p>
        <p>BIRTH DATE  Sept. 24, 1959</p>
        <p>PHOTO ON OFFICE WALL  U.S. Representative Barbara Jordan (1936-1996)</p>
        <p>ALWAYS WEARS  Pins for awareness of women's heart disease</p>
        <p>BOOK RECENTLY READ  'A Peace to End All Peace,' by David Fromkin</p>
        <p>OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
