<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flexing Big Muscles For a Little Library</title>
    <meta content="08doma" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/thecity/08doma.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENSONHURST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eminent Domain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Public Library</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mooney, Jake</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eminent Domain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flexing Big Muscles For a Little Library</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Flexing Big Muscles for a Little Library</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAKE MOONEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mooney, Jake</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dispute between Parisi family, which owns Ulmer Park Branch Library building in Bensonhurst, and Brooklyn Public Library described; library wants to use eminent domain to acquire building; Parisis want to raise rent and say building is not for sale; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ulmer Park Branch Library, a squat, one-story brick building on Bath Avenue in Bensonhurst, Brooklyn, would seem to have little in common with the skyscrapers and the wavy metal arena proposed for the 22-acre site to the north where the developer Bruce Ratner seeks to build the Atlantic Yards.</p>
        <p>But like Mr. Ratner, officials of the Brooklyn Public Library are wrangling with local landowners over property they want -- in this case, the library building. And like Mr. Ratner, the library's representatives have raised the possibility of using eminent domain, which is the government's power to acquire private property without the owner's consent for the public good.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ulmer Park Branch Library, a squat, one-story brick building on Bath Avenue in Bensonhurst, Brooklyn, would seem to have little in common with the skyscrapers and the wavy metal arena proposed for the 22-acre site to the north where the developer Bruce Ratner seeks to build the Atlantic Yards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ulmer Park Branch Library, a squat, one-story brick building on Bath Avenue in Bensonhurst, Brooklyn, would seem to have little in common with the skyscrapers and the wavy metal arena proposed for the 22-acre site to the north where the developer Bruce Ratner seeks to build the Atlantic Yards.</p>
        <p>But like Mr. Ratner, officials of the Brooklyn Public Library are wrangling with local landowners over property they want -- in this case, the library building. And like Mr. Ratner, the library's representatives have raised the possibility of using eminent domain, which is the government's power to acquire private property without the owner's consent for the public good.</p>
        <p>Officials say the chances that the library, in the end, will acquire the property by eminent domain are remote. Still, even the possibility has electrified the dispute between the Parisi family, which owns the building and is seeking a rent increase, and the library, which says it cannot afford such an increase and in any case would rather buy than rent. The dispute was reported in Bay News, a local weekly.</p>
        <p>The issue arose in 2005, when the families of William and Joseph Parisi, brothers who bought the library building in 1963, asked for rent of $25 a square foot, compared with about $12 a square foot under the lease that expired that year.</p>
        <p>The library balked, and in a letter on Oct. 4, 2005, it informed the Parisi family that the city intended to acquire the property by eminent domain but wished to negotiate an interim lease.</p>
        <p>The family reduced its asking price to an initial $19 a square foot, but library officials nevertheless sought the city's permission and financing to buy the building -- which the owners say is not for sale.</p>
        <p>According to Josephine Margiotta, daughter of William Parisi, now 92, the family wants to keep renting the 8,400-square-foot building, with five parking spaces, to the library but believes that it has charged too little rent for too long.</p>
        <p>''Since 1963, my uncle and my dad never once negotiated with them with a lawyer, which is a thing they should have done from the first time they signed a lease,'' Ms. Margiotta said.</p>
        <p>John Vitali, the Brooklyn Public Library's chief financial officer, said his institution would be better off buying the building and spending its money on upkeep rather than on rent. Nine of its 59 branches are in privately owned buildings, and the library hopes to buy all of them, he said.</p>
        <p>Community Board 13, which represents the area, voted 11 days ago to support the library's plan to buy the Bath Avenue building. The proposal must still pass through the city's land use review process before negotiations over a sale could begin, but Mr. Vitali portrayed the vote as a victory.</p>
        <p>''The people who live in that neighborhood have endorsed the library remaining there,'' he said, ''and they have endorsed the city's acquisition of the property for the library to stay there and get better.''</p>
        <p>Chuck Reichenthal, the board's district manager, said that using eminent domain to force the sale, should the Parisis and the library fail to reach a deal, is a last resort.</p>
        <p>And if they can't agree?</p>
        <p>''Let's say that they will,'' he said.</p>
        <p>JAKE MOONEY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENSONHURST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
