<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rites of Spring; Befriending God</title>
    <meta content="08RwecatholicWC-4" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Segunda Iglesia Pentacostal Church (Port Chester, NY)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Port Chester (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aspan, Maria</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E4DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rites of Spring; Befriending God</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIA ASPAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Aspan, Maria</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at Segunda Iglesia Pentacostal church in Port Chester, NY, described during Palm Sunday service; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a season of renewal for Christians and Jews as they commemorate momentous events in their histories: for Christians, the resurrection of Jesus; for Jews, the liberation of the ancient Hebrews from slavery in Egypt. As Jews began celebrating the eight days of Passover at sundown last Monday, Christians observed the final, most solemn days of Lent in preparation for Easter services this weekend. Here are a handful of stories about different faith communities around the region.</p>
        <p>Sunday school was under way at the Segunda Iglesia Pentecostal Juan 3:16, a squat, unassuming group of buildings that make up one of the oldest Spanish churches in Port Chester, N.Y. In one of the small, interlocking rooms, Eva Manani led her class through the week's lesson. ''Jesús es bueno, sí?'' she asked. The 22 boys and girls, all 5 to 7 years old, called back, ''Sí!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a season of renewal for Christians and Jews as they commemorate momentous events in their histories: for Christians, the resurrection of Jesus; for Jews, the liberation of the ancient Hebrews from slavery in Egypt. As Jews began celebrating the eight days of Passover at sundown last Monday, Christians observed the final, most solemn days of Lent in preparation for Easter services this weekend. Here are a handful of stories about different faith communities around the region.</p>
        <p>Sunday school was under way at the Segunda Iglesia Pentecostal Juan 3:16, a squat, unassuming group of buildings that make up one of the oldest Spanish churches in Port Chester, N.Y. In one of the small, interlocking rooms, Eva Manani led her class through the week's lesson. ''Jesús es bueno, sí?'' she asked. The 22 boys and girls, all 5 to 7 years old, called back, ''Sí!''</p>
        <p>Then, as Ms. Manani told her students to take out their study guides, the children started laughing and clapping. Now they could color.</p>
        <p>It was Palm Sunday at the church, which was founded in 1962 and has about 175 members, according to Efrain Roman, a police officer and church deacon who is also the pastor's son-in-law. The services and the Sunday school are entirely in Spanish, and the church attracts many immigrants, as well as Hispanics who, like Mr. Roman, have grown up nearby.</p>
        <p>As their Sunday school classes ended, children and teenagers made their way to the main church.</p>
        <p>Inside, the service was in full swing, led by Cynthia Quintana, 34, the pastor's daughter-in-law. In heels, a stylish black skirt and a blouse covered in a bright pink print, Ms. Quintana led the congregation in a musical performance worthy of a pop concert. Backed by a full band, microphone in hand, she sang, first in Spanish, then in English, to the standing, swaying crowd.</p>
        <p>''I am a friend of God, he calls me friend,'' she sang, as the congregation clapped and sang along, some reading the lyrics on the large projector screen behind her.</p>
        <p>The crowd was young, with many parents hustling their infants in and out of the main room, a comfortable square space with air-conditioners and cushioned folding chairs.</p>
        <p>In between songs and sermons, the congregation surged forward to welcome new members to the church with embraces and handshakes. According to Mr. Roman, the church sends out small groups to preach and find new members on Wednesday evenings. ''They accepted the Lord,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The church's longtime pastor, the Rev. Ramón Quintana, preached about Jesus' last days, his voice rising fiercely as he described the crown of thorns, the nailed hands and the lancing after death. His listeners responded with murmurs that rose to cries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quintana, who is 63 and recovering from heart and back surgeries, preached while sitting, then stood, inviting those who were sick or suffering to crowd around the altar and accept Jesus Christ as Lord and Savior. The pastor welcomed the newest members, laying his hands on them and praying fervently.</p>
        <p>In the audience, Kevin Santacruz, 16, stood and swayed with his arm around his mother's shoulders; both had their eyes closed, and his mother's face wore tracks of tears.</p>
        <p>Earlier that morning, as he walked into the main service from Sunday school, Kevin said he planned to hold onto his faith when he goes to college. ''It's definitely not something that I would want to lose,'' he said. ''We can be separated from the building, but not what's going on here, not the knowledge.''</p>
        <p>MARIA ASPAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
