<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knowing the Score</title>
    <meta content="08age" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/fashion/08age.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE AGE OF DISSONANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Emotions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emotions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFDB173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knowing the Score</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Knowing the Score</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morris, Bob</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The other day I was sitting across from my accountant. He was calculating what I earned, spent and deducted. My head was racing. Did I earn more than last year? Did I deduct too little? Then there was a new chunk of money to consider, recently left by my father. Did that bequest really equal more than all my savings? I'm doing well compared with most, but I still wondered why I make less than many I know.</p>
        <p>His fingers were tapping on his adding machine. But I felt as if he were tapping into my soul.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It’s tax season and money has become something we are being encouraged to study and inspect with messianic zeal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The other day I was sitting across from my accountant. He was calculating what I earned, spent and deducted. My head was racing. Did I earn more than last year? Did I deduct too little? Then there was a new chunk of money to consider, recently left by my father. Did that bequest really equal more than all my savings? I'm doing well compared with most, but I still wondered why I make less than many I know.</p>
        <p>His fingers were tapping on his adding machine. But I felt as if he were tapping into my soul.</p>
        <p>Ah, tax season. It's always emotionally taxing, isn't it?</p>
        <p>Ask any accountant and you'll hear about couples fighting and individuals crying. One friend of mine is crestfallen because his accountant didn't remark on how much he gave to charity this year. Another, a liberal conflicted about the financial aid she receives from her conservative parents, gets upset because her accountant reminds her of her mother. Wayne Koestenbaum, a prolific author and tenured professor, worries his accountant will fire him for not earning as much as other clients.</p>
        <p>''It's a moment of judgment,'' he said. ''It's as if he's assessing not just my financial worth, but my cultural and social worth.''</p>
        <p>Typical these days? Absolutely, but also a little delusional.</p>
        <p>''I don't judge any of my clients,'' said Mark Kornspan, an accountant in Manhattan. ''They judge themselves.'' So when they ask him, ''How am I doing?'' his response is always, ''How do you think you're doing?'' Sometimes he holds their hands. Other times he consoles them by softly saying, ''It's just money'' as if it were a lullaby.</p>
        <p>''People need help at both financial and emotional levels,'' said Paige Paulsen, a ''holistic accountant'' from Utah, who likes to consider the entire personality of clients when dealing with their money. Her clients include some with what she calls ''financial blockage'' who avoid taxes. One wouldn't file for a refund because she associated getting money from the I.R.S. with getting money from her father. Others with self-esteem issues think they don't deserve deductions they are legally allowed to claim.</p>
        <p>''It's never about money or taxes,'' Ms. Paulsen said. ''It's always about other issues.''</p>
        <p>Yes, because, as the saying goes, money is never about money. And to make matters more upsetting for those who would rather keep discussions of it at bay, it has become something we are being encouraged to study and inspect with messianic zeal.</p>
        <p>Why else would money pundits like James Cramer (who recently gloated about manipulating the stock market) and Suze Orman (who suggests that women have issues of shame around handling money but who was unashamed to announce she spends $500,000 a year on private jets) be so influential? And Maria Bartiromo, the CNBC financial reporter known as the Money Honey, is treated as if she were a head of state or a supermodel.</p>
        <p>More than half the advice books on the best-seller lists are about getting rich. Many suggest it is as much a spiritual as a financial quest, and a healthy form of self-expression. No wonder even Andrew Weil, a well-regarded doctor and author of books about healthy living, is now hawking an expensive line of cookware.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in current Charles Schwab television commercials, unhappy clients who aren't wealthy whine that their financial advisers don't respect them enough.</p>
        <p>Maybe the reason we're all having mini-meltdowns and anxiety attacks around our accountants is because we're being shamed into thinking we have to obsess about the life of our money in ways that used to be only for the wealthy or obnoxious.</p>
        <p>''Money talks,'' said Olivia Mellan, an author and a columnist for Investment Advisor magazine. ''But what is it talking about? What is it saying?''</p>
        <p>It's hard to know exactly. In my case, it may be telling me that my father, who I always dismissed as relatively unsuccessful, had a lot more on the ball (along with my parsimonious librarian mother) than I thought. Or maybe my money is trying to tell me that it isn't shameful to be happy with modest, rather than stunning, success.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, my accountant agrees. But then, he cares about values other than stock values. ''You're doing fine just as you are,'' he told me the other day, as he was finishing my taxes. ''It's the rest of society that worries me.''</p>
        <p>Now that's the kind of reckoning I like hearing at tax time.</p>
        <p>THE AGE OF DISSONANCE E-mail: Bobmorris@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Bobmorris@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
