<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/Long Island; A Village Is Thinking Beyond Cabanas</title>
    <meta content="08lizo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/realestate/08lizo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boardwalks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic Beach (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotsalas, Valerie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Etrog, Nat</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DE173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1154" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/Long Island; A Village Is Thinking Beyond Cabanas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Village Is Thinking Beyond Cabanas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE COTSALAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotsalas, Valerie</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC BEACH</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Atlantic Beach, LI, two-block-wide village on barrier island, have been approached by owners of town's beach clubs with proposals to change zoning on club properties and allow residential development; residents considered proposals but balked completely at plans to tear down village-owned boardwalk; long-time resident Nat Etrog says rejection is short-sighted and village may eventually end up with only abandoned and unsightly beach clubs; photo (In the Region/Long Island) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a recent afternoon when light flashed off the ocean waves and the white sandy shore of Atlantic Beach, what was striking was that no one was on the beach to appreciate it.</p>
        <p>Not that it is easy to get there. ''Residents Only'' is a mantra in this two-block-wide village on a barrier island between the Atlantic and Reynolds Channel in Nassau County.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even though the clubs in Atlantic Beach are full in the summer, their owners say that rising taxes and maintenance costs are driving them out of business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a recent afternoon when light flashed off the ocean waves and the white sandy shore of Atlantic Beach, what was striking was that no one was on the beach to appreciate it.</p>
        <p>Not that it is easy to get there. ''Residents Only'' is a mantra in this two-block-wide village on a barrier island between the Atlantic and Reynolds Channel in Nassau County.</p>
        <p>The only way to enter the village's stretch of beach, which is enclosed by chain-link fencing below a boardwalk, is to have a resident beach pass or belong to one of the eight operating beach clubs that line the boardwalk on Ocean Boulevard.</p>
        <p>The clubs are full in the summer with thousands who reserve shares in the hundreds of rough-hewn cabanas in horseshoe-shaped complexes facing the ocean. But the club owners say that rising taxes and maintenance costs are driving them out of business.</p>
        <p>''The beach clubs are obsolete -- dinosaurs,'' said Michael Calandrillo, the largest of seven shareholders in the Clearwater Beach Club, who lives nearby in Long Beach but winters in Florida. He also said he was losing money and would sell the land right now if he could find a buyer.</p>
        <p>But under the clubs' current zoning, which prohibits most development, Mr. Calandrillo said, ''who's going to buy it?''</p>
        <p>The owner of the New Plaza Beach Club, perhaps thinking along the same lines, has closed up a second, smaller club called the Plaza West. Its untended cabanas are crumbling, and lockers near the boardwalk have caved in.</p>
        <p>Nearby, an empty lot owned by the Town of Hempstead, which never built the town beach club it had proposed, is a vacant eyesore with a strip of portable toilets.</p>
        <p>Yet just across the street, multimillion-dollar homes are under construction.</p>
        <p>The homes ''overlook a parking lot and my club's Dumpster, which gets emptied on Saturday and Sunday mornings,'' said Stuart Berman, owner of the Westbury and Westbury III beach clubs (there is no Westbury II). ''There you have wealthy people with big houses on double lots, and here you have all these old, deteriorating clubs.''</p>
        <p>But in March, when a local weekly newspaper reported that according to some club owners, big-time developers like Toll Brothers and Donald Trump wanted to develop the oceanfront, the village was in an uproar.</p>
        <p>''When people hear a name like Trump,'' said Stephen Mahler, the village mayor, ''they think some giant is going to come in and bowl over the village and the mayor and get what they want.''</p>
        <p>(Mr. Berman said that a recent caller claiming to represent the Trump Organization had inquired about the property, but he never verified the caller's identity. Mr. Calandrillo, who is also a developer, said he met two years ago with representatives of Toll Brothers and Pulte Homes to discuss working with the village to create a master plan for oceanfront development.)</p>
        <p>The claims came three months after a meeting that the club owners had held to present renderings and blueprints of their own vision for the waterfront. They had sought to win over residents and persuade the village to change the zoning on the club lots, from a restrictive marine and recreation designation to one that permits residential development.</p>
        <p>The plan included turning the land under seven contiguous clubs into lots for up to 130 units of a mixture of single-family homes, attached town houses and a three-story, eight-unit condominium. One two-acre lot would be given to the village, and a village-owned block with tennis courts would be renovated.</p>
        <p>All of which might have been palatable, some residents say, except that the club owners also proposed razing the village-owned boardwalk and replacing it with a meandering ground-level promenade that would connect the eight village beaches interspersed between the clubs.</p>
        <p>''The reaction to taking away the boardwalk was, if they could run them out of town on a rail, they would have,'' Nat Etrog, a longtime resident who has served as lifeguard, parks commissioner and a village trustee, said of the club owners.</p>
        <p>They now say they have scaled back their proposal, but it may be too late. ''The club owners have become the bad guys -- greedy guys interested only in money,'' Mr. Etrog said. ''That's the perception of the community.''</p>
        <p>The beach clubs -- known farther afield because they have been used as the setting for movies like ''The Flamingo Kid'' and ''Goodfellas'' and series like ''The Sopranos'' -- still look much as they did 50 years ago. At the Westbury club, for example, there is faded blue wallpaper with scenes of surfers in the office, wood paneling in the dining room and, inside each painted wooden cabana, storage shelves, a shower and a refrigerator. Most clubs have large swimming pools, and owners own the beach out front, to the high-tide line.</p>
        <p>When members arrive starting on Memorial Day, cabana boys carry their chairs and umbrellas onto the beach and take them food and drinks from the restaurant, and valets park their cars. For the few who reserve the cabanas and lockers, and for local residents, Atlantic Beach is a summer paradise.</p>
        <p>But for anyone else, visiting the village is discouraged. The most direct route to the village requires crossing a toll bridge that charges $2 in each direction -- the only toll bridge on Long Island -- and residents have bridge passes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Etrog says it is time for the village to consider the club owners' scaled-back plan. They would build single-family homes only, while still giving the two-acre lot to the village and beautifying the eight local village beaches, he said.</p>
        <p>''It's shortsighted to think that the beach club owners will run the clubs forever,'' Mr. Etrog said. ''It's not going to happen. I'm afraid we'll end up having abandoned clubs like the Plaza all over the place.''</p>
        <p>Public beaches and some development have proven lucrative on other parts of the barrier island. East of Atlantic Beach, developers have recently built million-dollar condos along the public beach and boardwalk in Long Beach, one of two small cities on Long Island, along with Glen Cove. ''Now their beach-block sales have passed ours,'' said Annett Ellis, a real estate agent in Atlantic Beach.</p>
        <p>If the beach clubs could find support for a zoning change to permit single-family homes on the ocean, she estimated, the homes would start at $4 million or so.</p>
        <p>But as they are, the clubs are ''tired looking,'' she said, adding, ''Long Beach has just come up with new construction and development on the ocean that makes our oceanfront look worn out.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Mahler, for one, says he can envision ''a lot of upsides'' to developing the oceanfront. ''It would beautify Ocean Boulevard,'' he said. ''It would make it more upscale.''</p>
        <p>But as far as any new development on the oceanfront is concerned, many residents feel like Marie Pellegrino, who lives a block from ocean. ''Personally,'' she said, ''I think it's fine the way it is now.''</p>
        <p>In the Region | Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
