<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Change, Ball Bounces Wrong Way For the Mets</title>
    <meta content="08mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/baseball/08mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070411T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Glavine, Tom</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Smoltz, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Change, Ball Bounces Wrong Way For the Mets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Poor Defense Brings the Mets’ Fast Start to a Halt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The overlooked story line in the Mets' sizzling start, Manager Willie Randolph said before Saturday's game, was their crisp defense. As the Cardinals bumbled all over the outfield and the Braves booted grounders, the Mets, in going 4-0, seemed immune from such mishaps.</p>
        <p>But in the time it took for the ball to fall out of Shawn Green's glove in the sixth inning Saturday, the Mets' visions of remaining unbeaten evaporated. They committed two costly errors in the game, leading to their first loss, 5-3, to the Braves at Turner Field.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Braves scored three unearned runs off Tom Glavine  one in the first and two in the sixth  to prevent him from ascending the all-time victory list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The overlooked story line in the Mets' sizzling start, Manager Willie Randolph said before Saturday's game, was their crisp defense. As the Cardinals bumbled all over the outfield and the Braves booted grounders, the Mets, in going 4-0, seemed immune from such mishaps.</p>
        <p>But in the time it took for the ball to fall out of Shawn Green's glove in the sixth inning Saturday, the Mets' visions of remaining unbeaten evaporated. They committed two costly errors in the game, leading to their first loss, 5-3, to the Braves at Turner Field.</p>
        <p>The Braves scored three unearned runs off Tom Glavine -- one in the first and two in the sixth -- to deny him his 292nd career victory. The Mets' offense, which had scored 21 runs in the previous two games, stranded 13 base runners.</p>
        <p>''I guess 162-0 wasn't in the cards for us this year,'' David Wright said.</p>
        <p>Green's error was the Mets' second drop of the day, but it was the more damaging. With one out, the bases loaded and the score tied, 2-2, Matt Diaz, who had homered earlier, ripped a fly ball to right field. Green, expecting the ball to slice toward the line, backpedaled in that direction. The wind, which gusted to 21 miles an hour, pushed the ball farther back than Green expected.</p>
        <p>Thinking it would go over his head, he spun around, tried to get his bearings and then, he said, ''everything happened at once.'' He stuck out his glove. The ball popped in, then it popped out. The go-ahead run would have scored anyway on a sacrifice fly, but the error extended the inning and the Braves tacked on two more runs.</p>
        <p>''I just got turned around,'' Green said.</p>
        <p>Green was not the only player bothered by the conditions. In addition to the cold, which made pitching a challenge, the late-afternoon start, to accommodate a national television broadcast, meant that most of the game was played in shadows. Carlos Delgado had trouble with a few balls at first base, and Wright had similar problems at third.</p>
        <p>''I'm not a big fan of 3:55 start times -- the shadows are killers,'' Wright said. ''Especially against John Smoltz.''</p>
        <p>Glavine spoke with Smoltz late Monday night from St. Louis. Smoltz had finished pitching the first game of the season in Philadelphia. They realized that they were set to pitch against each other Saturday for the second time in their careers. (The first was July 15, 2005, at Shea Stadium.) But the matchup between the best friends, golf buddies and future Hall of Famers did not materialize the way they had hoped. Both struggled to adjust to the weather.</p>
        <p>Each consistently ran deep counts, and they combined to walk seven batters. At the start of the game, the thermometer read 45 degrees. The wind made it seem colder, so some players, including Atlanta center fielder Andruw Jones, wore ski masks beneath their caps.</p>
        <p>For Glavine, who allowed five runs -- two earned -- and four hits in five and one-third innings, the most notable aspect of his outing was his pitch count. Of his 113 pitches, 57 were balls, marking the first time that he had thrown more balls than strikes since Sept. 18, 2004, in Pittsburgh. That day, 50 of his 98 pitches were called balls, according to the Elias Sports Bureau.</p>
        <p>''That was a pretty good indication of the tough conditions,'' Glavine said.</p>
        <p>For Glavine, who relies on changing speeds and on breaking pitches rather than on an overpowering fastball, the colder weather made it difficult for him to feel the seams on the ball. To get a better grip, he tried keeping his fingers moist, but they dried up almost immediately.</p>
        <p>Spotted a 1-0 lead on Paul Lo Duca's home run in the first inning, Glavine got off to an inauspicious start. The Braves' leadoff hitter, Kelly Johnson, reached base when Delgado dropped José Valentín's throw after a grounder.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to make a big deal of it,'' Delgado said. ''I just dropped it, and that's it.''</p>
        <p>Glavine then walked two of the next three hitters before Jeff Francoeur tied the score with a groundout. When the inning finally ended, Glavine had thrown 30 pitches. After that, however, he gradually discovered his command. Diaz hit a solo homer in the second, putting the Mets behind for the first time this season, but Glavine allowed only one other hit until the pivotal sixth. When Glavine left with one out, the fans showered him with a seemingly sincere ovation.</p>
        <p>''I guess I did notice that there weren't as many boos as there used to be,'' Glavine said.</p>
        <p>The Mets drew to 5-3 in the seventh on Green's run-scoring single. Green came up in the ninth with a chance at redemption. With two outs, runners on second and third and closer Bob Wickman on the mound, Green belted a line drive to the right of first baseman Craig Wilson, who leaped and grabbed the ball for the final out.</p>
        <p>''I thought I had it,'' Green said. ''I missed by a couple of inches.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Mike Pelfrey allowed two earned runs and five hits over six innings Saturday for Class A Port St. Lucie in his final tuneup before making his season debut Friday against the Washington Nationals.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 11, 2007, Wednesday  A sports article in some copies on Sunday about the Mets' first loss of the season, to the Braves in Atlanta on Saturday, referred incorrectly to pitcher Tom Glavine's pursuit of 300 career victories. He had been seeking his 292nd victory, not his 293rd.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 11, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A sports article in some copies on Sunday about the Mets' first loss of the season, to the Braves in Atlanta on Saturday, referred incorrectly to pitcher Tom Glavine's pursuit of 300 career victories. He had been seeking his 292nd victory, not his 293rd.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
