<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senators Offer New Plan to Pay for Rail Cars</title>
    <meta content="08ctweekCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08ctweek.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stevenson Dam (Conn)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pollen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Allergies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Housatonic River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Zoar (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metro-North Commuter Railroad</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">First Light Power Resources</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdonald, Andrew (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nickerson, William H (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rell, M Jodi (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holtz, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Allergies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0D6163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senators Offer New Plan to Pay for Rail Cars</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Week in Connecticut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF HOLTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holtz, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Week column; Connecticut Senators Andrew McDonald and William Nickerson, responding to Gov M Jodi Rell's request, propose raising Metro-North fares by 1 percent a year for seven years beginning in 2010 and issuing state bonds in order to pay $140 million for 342 new Metro-North railroad cars; First Light Power Resources plans to build lift for Stevenson Dam at Lake Zoar to help eels migrate up Housatonic River; American Academy of Allergy, Asthma and Immunology says mild start to winter could mean high pollen counts in state in next few months (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rather than charge $1 more per ride on Metro-North starting in 2008, Gov. M. Jodi Rell asked legislators last month to come up with another way to pay $140 million for 342 new cars.</p>
        <p>Two state senators said last week that they had found one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rather than charge $1 more per ride on Metro-North starting in 2008, Gov. M. Jodi Rell asked legislators last month to come up with another way to pay $140 million for 342 new cars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rather than charge $1 more per ride on Metro-North starting in 2008, Gov. M. Jodi Rell asked legislators last month to come up with another way to pay $140 million for 342 new cars.</p>
        <p>Two state senators said last week that they had found one.</p>
        <p>The senators, Andrew J. McDonald, of Stamford, and William H. Nickerson, of Greenwich, proposed raising Metro-North fares by 1 percent a year for seven years beginning in 2010. At the same time, the state would borrow $20 million a year through 20-year bonds.</p>
        <p>Mr. McDonald and Mr. Nickerson said that if ridership on Metro-North stayed the same, the fare increases would cover the $1.73 million needed to pay the principal and interest on the debt from the bonds.</p>
        <p>They said the plan charged all riders fairly and did not force them to pay for the cars before most are put into service in 2010.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nickerson conceded that the $1 surcharge, which would bring in $150 million over 7.5 years, according to the State Department of Transportation, would completely pay for the new cars. But he said it amounted to a fare hike that was too high.</p>
        <p>''We want to keep down increases to the minimum to encourage people to get off the roads and onto the rails,'' Mr. Nickerson said.</p>
        <p>Jim Cameron, chairman of the Connecticut Rail Commuter Council, a riders' advocacy group, said he liked the new plan, but warned that it still amounted to a fare increase.</p>
        <p>''It would be secondary to anything the D.O.T. comes up with, in terms of another fare increase,'' he said. ''You're still making mass transit less attractive over those seven years.''</p>
        <p>Adam Liegeot, a spokesman for Mrs. Rell, said the governor's budget office would analyze the plan to see if there were any other costs that taxpayers would have to absorb.</p>
        <p>The plan must be voted on by the General Assembly before its current session ends on June 30. Unless a plan is voted into legislation by that time, the previous $1 surcharge goes into effect.</p>
        <p>Power Company Builds Aid for Migrating Eels</p>
        <p>While some who use the Housatonic River may be happy that they have not encountered any eels lately, others are trying to bring them back.</p>
        <p>First Light Power Resources, which owns five dams on the Housatonic, said last Tuesday that it was building a lift for the Stevenson Dam at Lake Zoar, on the borders of Monroe and Oxford, to help eels migrate up the river.</p>
        <p>The company's license with the federal Energy Regulatory Commission requires it to build the lift. It must also eventually build lifts farther up the river at the Shepaug Dam in Southbury and the Bulls Bridge Dam in New Milford.</p>
        <p>The requirements came from recommendations by the State Department of Environmental Protection. Steve Gephard, a biologist with the department's Inland Fisheries Division, said the normally six- to eight-inch American eel had just about disappeared from the upper part of the river. ''The Stevenson and Shepaug are very tall,'' he said. ''They're smooth concrete, and most of the water goes through the turbines. Therefore, it is impossible for the eel to get over them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephard said the eels were important because they preyed on certain fish and were food for others.</p>
        <p>''Eel is a prominent component of all East Coast ecosystems,'' he said. ''Any portion of a watershed that is devoid of eel is flawed.''</p>
        <p>The eels will be lured by running water into a barrel-like trap at the base of the dam. After a significant number are collected, workers at the dam will release them into the water on the other side.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Gates, station manager for Connecticut Hydro, a division of First Light Power Resources, said he was studying where the eels were congregating before deciding where to put the lift. ''Then we'll be counting them to make sure it's the proper location,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said the lift would cost less than $20,000. He said he hoped to have it in place by May 15.</p>
        <p>The main migration period for eels in the Housatonic is from July through September, Mr. Gephard said.</p>
        <p>Monitoring Group Predicts Long Allergy Season</p>
        <p>It could be a long season of coughing, sneezing and headaches for allergy sufferers in the state.</p>
        <p>The American Academy of Allergy, Asthma and Immunology, which has 78 monitoring stations in the country, including one on the roof of Waterbury Hospital, said last week that the mild start to the recent winter could mean high pollen counts in the state in the next few months.</p>
        <p>''You'd anticipate high pollen counts and mold counts because everything that grows is going to be proliferated, and for longer periods,'' Dr. Christopher C. Randolph, an allergist who runs the Waterbury station, said last Tuesday.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Randolph said the weather could still make a difference. ''Rain will keep the mold count high, but the pollen count will plummet because you're clearing the air,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Most of the airborne allergens in the state are either mold or pollen, Dr. Randolph said. ''Mid-May is the worst time for allergies in the East,'' he said. ''You've got people with sore eyes, ears, noses and throats that are often mistaken for being infected.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Randolph said those suffering from severe allergies should stay in air-conditioned rooms as much as possible, use proper medications and see an allergist.</p>
        <p>He said anyone who believed they might have an allergy should have a skin prick test by a board-certified allergist. ''It's the gold standard internationally,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The latest pollen count at the Waterbury station is available from April through October by calling the Waterbury Hospital: (203) 573-6116.</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
