<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Longer an Outsider Looking In</title>
    <meta content="08hunt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/realestate/08hunt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE HUNT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trenta, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holloway, Rosa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Hunt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEEDF173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Longer an Outsider Looking In</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Longer an Outsider Looking In</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Hunt column on search by Bob Trenta and Rosa Holloway for New York City apartment to use as summer home and possibly retirement residence, for up to $500,000; found fourth-floor walk-up studio on West 106th Street in Manhattan for $340,000; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>UNLIKE those people who move to the South when nearing retirement, Bob Trenta headed to the warmth of Florida early in his career. Now, decades later, he wanted to return North -- back to his not-quite-home turf.</p>
        <p>''New York is the cultural capital of the world, and I am lucky enough to be able to participate in that,'' Mr. Trenta said. ''At my age, I don't want to downsize. Florida is great, but it is not amped-up enough.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bob Trenta grew up in New Jersey and moved to Florida, but yearned for Manhattan. He and his girlfriend, Rosa Holloway, even came in under budget, at $340,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>UNLIKE those people who move to the South when nearing retirement, Bob Trenta headed to the warmth of Florida early in his career. Now, decades later, he wanted to return North -- back to his not-quite-home turf.</p>
        <p>''New York is the cultural capital of the world, and I am lucky enough to be able to participate in that,'' Mr. Trenta said. ''At my age, I don't want to downsize. Florida is great, but it is not amped-up enough.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trenta grew up in northern New Jersey, always gazing longingly toward the city. While attending Canisius College in Buffalo, he spent summers in New Jersey working at the old Lever Brothers plant, taking the overnight shift so he could watch the sun rise over Manhattan. After graduation in 1970, he moved to northern Florida, working as a high school guidance counselor in several cities there, primarily St. Augustine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trenta, who is divorced, lived in what he called ''cold Florida,'' in the northern part of the state. After his daughter, Chandler, entered Florida State University, he decided to try ''warm Florida.'' He landed as far south as he could. He is currently a guidance counselor at Key West High School and an assistant basketball coach there for the Fighting Conchs. He rides his bicycle to school, much preferring it to driving.</p>
        <p>''If you are going to live without a car in America there are only a few cities where you can pull it off,'' he said. ''Key West is one and New York is another.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trenta has regularly visited New York over the years -- for plays, movies, museums and annual gatherings with friends at the Big East Basketball Tournament at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>In recent years, he and his girlfriend, Rosa Holloway, a native of Germany whose former husband was American, would visit open houses. ''We would look at high-end places and fantasize,'' she said. ''Three million dollars -- we were dreaming.''</p>
        <p>A friend suggested that they visit apartments they could actually afford. ''That's when it clicked,'' Mr. Trenta said. ''I said, he's right. Let's stop the fantasy world and get real and make this a workable thing. I am soon to be 59 years old, and life expectancy is 76 for me. As you can see, I am very quantitative. Life expectancy is a very real thing.''</p>
        <p>He and Ms. Holloway, who owns M &amp; N Holloway Realty in St. Cloud, Fla., decided to hunt seriously for a one-bedroom in New York. They would use it first as a summer home, perhaps eventually retiring here.</p>
        <p>They could pay up to $500,000 with a monthly maintenance of up to $1,000. They initially thought Brooklyn would be more affordable than Manhattan, and seriously considered a one-bedroom co-op for $375,000 in Park Slope, but they weren't ready to buy. What's more, Brooklyn still felt a bit removed. ''You are looking over to the city, which is what I did as a kid,'' Mr. Trenta said.</p>
        <p>They decided to focus on Manhattan's West Side, preferably near the Hudson River, so they could watch the sun set over New Jersey, and easily ride their bicycles over the George Washington Bridge to Mr. Trenta's old neighborhood.</p>
        <p>They flew up occasionally for long weekends, lining up open houses. There was little they liked. ''It wasn't sticker shock,'' said Mr. Trenta, who rents a studio apartment in Key West for $1,600 a month, which is typical for that area. ''What surprised us was the inadequate or inferior quality for the money that was asked.'' If the apartment wasn't small and dark, it was in terrible condition.</p>
        <p>On a visit to a fourth-floor walk-up on West 89th Street, they met Regina Wierbowski, an independent broker. The one-bedroom was lovely, but they feared the maintenance would rise because of a high underlying mortgage on the building. ''That is like buying two times,'' Mr. Trenta said. ''Every month you are paying off the building's debt.''</p>
        <p>IN the ensuing weeks, Ms. Wierbowski said she taught them all about buying a co-op in the city. ''Rosa had a lot of the first questions I had when I moved to New York, like, why do they need so much information?'' she said.</p>
        <p>She offered to drive them from apartment to apartment, but they declined. ''I enjoy going on the subway,'' Mr. Trenta said. ''I didn't want to go in a car with a real estate agent. Half the fun of the hunt is running around New York.''</p>
        <p>One weekend last fall, the couple found themselves with a list of places from Ms. Wierbowski. They were disappointed that a two-bedroom turned out to be a one-bedroom with a dining room.</p>
        <p>They had a near hit with a sun-filled one-bedroom on Riverside Drive. ''We looked at each other and thought, 'This is the place,' '' Ms. Holloway said. Then they walked to the window and saw construction below, guaranteed to block the sun.</p>
        <p>They normally skipped places advertised as studios, but Ms. Wierbowski sent them to one, a fourth-floor walk-up on West 106th Street. The owner was marrying a man who lived on the same block. With the addition of a wall, the 400-square-foot main room could be divided into a real bedroom and living room. The small kitchen, though, fit just a two-burner stove and a half-refrigerator. The listing price was $342,000 with monthly maintenance in the mid-$600s.</p>
        <p>They headed to the next place on the list. ''You never know,'' Ms. Holloway said. ''There may be one out there that you like even more. There is no telling -- maybe you will love it.''</p>
        <p>That, however, was the worst of all, with a back terrace hemmed in by high-rise buildings. It was so dark inside that Mr. Trenta banged into the coffee table, cutting his shin.</p>
        <p>The two returned to West 106th Street, where their offer of $340,000 was accepted. During the walk-through last winter, they left an inflatable mattress and a coffee maker. After the closing, they returned and set up the bed.</p>
        <p>Since then, they have visited their new home several times, most recently to paint walls and buy furniture, in preparation for summering in the city. ''It was so beautiful to come up to our own apartment'' instead of a hotel, Mr. Trenta said. ''Now, I am right smack in the middle of things.''</p>
        <p>From the Juliet balcony they can watch the sun set over New Jersey.</p>
        <p>As for the many flights of steps? Lugging luggage and groceries is more of a challenge than they thought. ''We have either lied to ourselves or convinced ourselves that we are using it as a workout regimen,'' Mr. Trenta said.</p>
        <p>THE HUNT E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
