<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 34, Devils' Linchpin Is Stingier Than Ever</title>
    <meta content="08brodeur" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/hockey/08brodeur.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brodeur, Martin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 34, Devils' Linchpin Is Stingier Than Ever</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stingiest Devil of Them All</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From his spot at the bar, Dr. Coyle Connolly, a dermatologist and rabid Flyers fan, had an open look at Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur. It was late summer 1995 in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., and Connolly's heart was on the mend after Brodeur and the Devils broke it with their defeat of Philadelphia in that year's Eastern Conference finals.</p>
        <p>Connolly, who had booed Brodeur from his season seat, swooped in like a skater to congratulate Brodeur for having gone on to win his first Stanley Cup. He half expected his introduction to end in rejection, but Brodeur did not turn him away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 34, Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur is playing better than ever, getting his 48th victory of the season Thursday night to break Bernie Parent’s 33-year-old record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From his spot at the bar, Dr. Coyle Connolly, a dermatologist and rabid Flyers fan, had an open look at Devils goaltender Martin Brodeur. It was late summer 1995 in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., and Connolly's heart was on the mend after Brodeur and the Devils broke it with their defeat of Philadelphia in that year's Eastern Conference finals.</p>
        <p>Connolly, who had booed Brodeur from his season seat, swooped in like a skater to congratulate Brodeur for having gone on to win his first Stanley Cup. He half expected his introduction to end in rejection, but Brodeur did not turn him away.</p>
        <p>Accepting Connolly's offer of a beer, Brodeur ended up inviting him to join him and a friend for dinner so they could continue their hockey conversation. Nearly a dozen years later they are still talking about hockey and a whole lot more.</p>
        <p>Brodeur is the godfather to Connolly's 3-year-old son, and Connolly, who lives at the Jersey Shore, is now -- against all odds -- a Devils fan. He became one upon discovering that the Devils' last line of defense on the ice is the first to let people in off it.</p>
        <p>''As fans, we want our sports figures to be just normal people and, you know, a lot of the time we're let down,'' Connolly said in a recent telephone interview. ''Marty is really refreshing that way. His accessibility is always something I marvel at.''</p>
        <p>On the ice, Brodeur inspires awe, bringing out the artistry in a job that is akin to being a traffic cop. This season, his 13th in the N.H.L., Brodeur has excelled despite a spate of injuries last month to Devils skaters and the death of the teenage daughter of his longtime lawyer in a car accident this year, which Brodeur said shook him to his core.</p>
        <p>At 34, he is playing better than ever, getting his 48th victory of the season Thursday night to break Bernie Parent's 33-year-old record -- and leading the league in shutouts with 12. After the regular-season finale today against the Islanders, the Devils will prepare for a run at a fourth Stanley Cup in the last dozen seasons, and a possible first-round matchup with the Rangers. Brodeur is the player his teammates look to and the one whom opponents truly fear.</p>
        <p>His physical nimbleness is surpassed only by his mental agility. The son of artistic parents -- his father, Denis, is a photographer and his mother, Mireille, a painter -- Brodeur appears to have inherited his father's aptitude for picturing a shot a split-second before it develops and his mother's gift for working by feel and not just by sight.</p>
        <p>Brodeur, who grew up in Montreal, regards goaltending as the most creative position on the ice. And the way he plays, wielding his stick like a paint brush, that does not sound silly at all. Before a game last month at Tampa Bay, Glenn Resch, the color commentator on the Devils' television broadcasts and a former N.H.L. goaltender and goaltending coach, grew animated as he described a few of the more spectacular saves Brodeur had made this season.</p>
        <p>Resch, who is known as Chico, lowered into a crouch, kicked one leg out, motioned as if he were twirling a baton and shook his head in wonderment over and over. ''He is the envy of anybody who has ever put the pads on,'' Resch said. ''Marty might be the Einstein of goalies.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur's style is a mosaic of bits and pieces that he has picked up from scrutinizing tape of other goaltenders, from Gump Worsley and Terry Sawchuk to the Detroit Red Wings' Dominik Hasek.</p>
        <p>He was watching Hasek recently and was struck by how, for all his lobster-in-a-net flailing, his eyes never moved off the puck.</p>
        <p>''I watch a lot of tapes, a lot of games, all the replays,'' Brodeur said. ''You watch the highlights on TV, those are all about goals getting scored or big saves. So you just look and see what guys do and how they're successful, and sometimes I see something and I go, Wow, that could work for me.''</p>
        <p>Memories Off the Ice</p>
        <p>Brodeur is the Devils' rock -- their Hope Diamond, really. He is worth his weight in carats most games, as he was on the road against the Carolina Hurricanes on March 15 when he made 22 saves in the third period and the Devils, playing without four key skaters, held on for a 3-2 victory.</p>
        <p>Asked to assess Brodeur's value, Devils center Scott Gomez said, ''Time only stops in Jersey when you hit Marty in the head with a shot.''</p>
        <p>This is the ninth consecutive season in which Brodeur has appeared in at least 70 games and his sixth career 40-victory season. ''To play 70 games year after year is unfathomable to me,'' said Ron Hextall, a former N.H.L. goaltender who is an assistant general manager with the Los Angeles Kings.</p>
        <p>Brodeur grew up idolizing Hextall because he played the puck as if he were a third defenseman on the ice. Now, Hextall is the admirer.</p>
        <p>''He's as strong mentally as any goaltender who has played the game,'' Hextall said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>Brodeur's deft puck-handling abilities allow him to block a shot and start his team's rush. He is a cross between two Patricks -- Roy and Ewing.</p>
        <p>''He throws the puck where they can go back on offense,'' Tampa Bay right wing Martin St. Louis said. ''He's not just concentrating on making the save.''</p>
        <p>On a rare day off between games in Florida last month, Brodeur turned his attention to real estate. He spent the morning on a house-hunting expedition in Palm Beach County with his girlfriend of five years, Geneviève Nault.</p>
        <p>The 150 golf courses in the county were a big lure for Brodeur, an avid golfer who is no stranger to the area. He spent many vacations as a child there hanging out with his father, who served as the official photographer for the Montreal Expos when the team's spring training base was West Palm Beach.</p>
        <p>Brodeur's childhood memories of South Florida are bathed in warmth, and he hopes the mental albums of his four children will be filled with the same sunny snapshots. Anthony, 11; the 10-year-old twins, William and Jeremy; and Anabelle, 5, spend the bulk of their summers with Brodeur, who shares custody with his ex-wife, Melanie.</p>
        <p>The couple separated in December 2002, and Melanie filed for divorce during the 2003 playoffs after discovering that Brodeur was involved with Nault, who was briefly married to Melanie's half-brother.</p>
        <p>In his autobiography, ''Brodeur: Beyond the Crease,'' which he wrote last year with the sports columnist Damien Cox of The Toronto Star, Brodeur said of that period of his life, ''I had made mistakes, and at times had acted like a model idiot.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur will spend the rest of his life making amends. ''You act in different ways for your own personal well-being, and you don't think about the people you hurt along the way,'' he said in an interview last month. ''I wish I would have thought about it.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''It's not something I'm proud of, that's for sure.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur negotiated his own six-year, no-trade contract with the Devils in January 2006 for $5.2 million a year. His salary is under his market value, but his main motivation was his desire to remain close to his children. Between bites of fried calamari during lunch at a Fort Lauderdale-area hotel, Brodeur spoke of their lives -- they all play multiple sports -- in the rueful tones of a parent who wishes he could pass on the simpler rhythms of his youth.</p>
        <p>''I don't know where sports in general will go,'' he said. ''But when I grew up, you just played the sport. Parents just wanted to make sure that you were happy doing something. Now they're pushing them to be the best.''</p>
        <p>Relaxing on a Harley</p>
        <p>A few Christmases ago, Brodeur was taken aback when Anthony unwrapped a hockey stick that was endorsed by Sidney Crosby, who had signed a five-year deal with a stick manufacturer before playing a game in juniors.</p>
        <p>As a teenager, Brodeur was neither a wunderkind nor particularly worldly. ''I didn't even know how much my idols were making,'' he said. ''I didn't even know they were getting paid. I thought they were doing it for free. Now it's so different. It's all about the bottom line.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur's passion for the game is boundless, but it seemed as if the N.H.L. was trying to rein him in last year with its new rule prohibiting goaltenders from playing the puck anywhere outside the crease except in a designated trapezoid behind the net.</p>
        <p>To avoid feeling boxed in, Brodeur had to figure out how to adjust.</p>
        <p>It was the same way with fame. As Brodeur's profile grew because of his three Stanley Cup rings and two Vézina Trophys, his world grew suffocatingly small.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, Brodeur bought a Harley-Davidson Fat Boy and found, on the open road, the freedom of movement and anonymity that he gradually lost as he became one of hockey's brightest lights.</p>
        <p>''You know what I like?'' Brodeur said. ''When you ride a bike, you really can't allow yourself to think too much. You just go out there, and it's you and the road and the bugs. It's fun. It's a laid-back time.''</p>
        <p>After Pittsburgh Steelers quarterback Ben Roethlisberger was injured in a motorcycle accident last summer, Brodeur's in-box was inundated with cautionary messages from friends.</p>
        <p>''I understand all the concerns,'' Brodeur said. ''But at the end of the day, I go out and I try to be as safe as possible.'' Which means always wearing a helmet, steering clear of city traffic, monitoring his speed and staying off his bike during the hockey season ''just in case anything happens,'' Brodeur said.</p>
        <p>Lou Lamoriello, the president, general manager and coach of the Devils, drafted Brodeur in the first round in 1990, with the 20th overall pick, and their relationship has evolved over the years to the point where some things do not need to be said.</p>
        <p>''Marty knows my feelings,'' Lamoriello said. ''I don't ask because I know he has control of what he's doing.''</p>
        <p>In 2005, when the N.H.L. was dark because of a labor dispute, Brodeur and some friends attended a bike rally in Myrtle Beach, S.C. Aside from winning another Stanley Cup, Brodeur's long-term goals include attending the Sturgis bike rally in South Dakota.</p>
        <p>He loves bike rallies for the same reason other people enjoy costume parties. ''You put your boots on, your leather jacket, it's so out of character,'' Brodeur said, laughing. ''Nobody notices who I am. That's why it's kind of fun. I can step out of who I am.''</p>
        <p>Martin Woo, a resident of Essex County, N.J., stepped into Brodeur's character for a game last month against the Pittsburgh Penguins at Continental Arena. He wore a No. 30 Devils jersey and full goaltender regalia, minus the skates.</p>
        <p>Brodeur did not see Woo that night, but he has made his acquaintance. Woo showed up at one of Brodeur's book signings last fall dressed the same way. ''When he was in line,'' he said, ''he was doing all my little rituals -- stretching, tapping his pads. It was unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>In another time and place, Brodeur might have invited Woo to join him and a buddy for dinner, as he did the night he met Connolly at the Baha Beach Club. His web of friends, which includes people from all walks of life, was weaved from such chance encounters.</p>
        <p>''Now it's always in the back of my mind, Why do they want to know me?'' he said.</p>
        <p>So Brodeur is more careful, if no less friendly. He posed for photographs with Woo, then they went their separate ways.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
