<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rough Ride Ends Where It Started</title>
    <meta content="08lede" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/mutfund/08lede.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1202" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rough Ride Ends Where It Started</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Rough Ride Ends Where It Started</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIKAS BAJAJ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INVESTORS' smooth and profitable stock market ride hit a nasty speed bump in February and finished the first quarter just about where it started.</p>
        <p>The choppiness was caused by a familiar group of concerns: a slowing American economy, rising problems with risky mortgages and signs that fast-growing emerging markets like China and India might be due for a correction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The choppiness in the stock market was caused by a familiar group of concerns: a slowing American economy, rising problems with risky mortgages and signs that fast-growing emerging markets might be due for a correction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INVESTORS' smooth and profitable stock market ride hit a nasty speed bump in February and finished the first quarter just about where it started.</p>
        <p>The choppiness was caused by a familiar group of concerns: a slowing American economy, rising problems with risky mortgages and signs that fast-growing emerging markets like China and India might be due for a correction.</p>
        <p>Major American stock indexes and indexes for many Asian markets -- though not the Shanghai stock exchange that led February's global sell-off -- were either flat or down for the quarter. European stocks fared better, but their returns for the quarter were lower than the gains they put up in the second half of last year.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, up 6.2 percent in the fourth quarter of 2006, was up just 0.2 percent in the first quarter this year. The Dow Jones industrial average, up 6.7 percent in the fourth quarter, lost 0.9 percent in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Investors, for their part, were left wondering whether this was the beginning of the end of the four-year bull market that started in October 2002, or simply a pause.</p>
        <p>After all, the market overcame a wrenching period of soul-searching in May and June of last year when the Federal Reserve was at the end of a two-year campaign to raise interest rates and the housing boom had started to fade. The concerns that dominated the minds of investors then, however, did not linger, and the market had a solid second half.</p>
        <p>Many market specialists assert that the current concerns will play out similarly. Weaknesses like those in the market for subprime mortgages issued to borrowers with weak credit will not threaten the broader financial markets, these experts say, because the world economy is growing, corporate profits are rising and consumers with good credit are not defaulting at high rates.</p>
        <p>''Even a soft landing has some bumps,'' said Jerry Webman, the senior investment officer and chief economist at OppenheimerFunds. ''The market is trying to figure out just how deep those bumps and potholes are going to be.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Webman is generally upbeat about the prospects for stocks and the global economy, but he has advised investors to protect themselves from a sell-off in riskier investments by buying higher-quality bonds.</p>
        <p>Mutual fund investors may have had it better than the lackluster results of the major stock indexes would suggest. Over all, funds that invest in domestic stocks were up 2.2 percent, international stock funds were up 3.4 percent and taxable bond funds were up 1.7 percent, according to Morningstar. The markets got off to a strong start last week, with a gain in the Dow of 1.7 percent.</p>
        <p>Some strategists, however, say they believe that there are reasons for greater caution. In this view, the problems that have emerged in the housing market could crop up elsewhere, including commodities and stock markets in emerging-market countries, which have been bid up by much speculation.</p>
        <p>Marc D. Stern, the chief investment officer at Bessemer Trust, has been more skeptical than most strategists on Wall Street. He believes that investors should avoid risky assets like emerging-market stocks and shares of energy companies, as well as those of smaller companies in general.</p>
        <p>He prefers larger companies, and stocks in the developed world that are profiting from the growth in fast-growing developing countries. He also likes certain commodities -- coffee, cotton and cocoa, for example -- that he says remain good bargains relative to oil and natural gas.</p>
        <p>''We are in for some meaningful volatility for the next several years, and none of us should be surprised by that,'' Mr. Stern said. ''There are lots of uncertainties to ponder.''</p>
        <p>The Chicago Board of Trade's VIX index, which measures volatility based on investors' use of options on the S.&amp; P. 500-stock index, spiked in early March from historically low levels, though it has fallen back somewhat since then.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, investors have turned to more defensive sectors of the market to cushion the bumpier ride they are now encountering.</p>
        <p>Mutual funds that specialize in utilities were up 8 percent in the first quarter, on average, driven partly by the private equity buyout of TXU, the Texas utility. Funds specializing in natural resources were up 5.7 percent and communications funds were up 3.9 percent, on average, according to Morningstar.</p>
        <p>''When you look at the higher-quality names, they have tended to do well,'' said Robert C. Doll, vice chairman at BlackRock, the asset management company.</p>
        <p>That is not to say that investors have become entirely risk averse.</p>
        <p>The VIX index, for example, even at its recent heights, is below its level during the bull market of the late 1990s and 2000.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, medium- and small-capitalization companies again outperformed larger-cap stocks in the first quarter, even as many market specialists were warning investors to stick with large caps because big companies tend to weather tougher economic times better.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is saying it, but nobody must be doing it, because it hasn't happened,'' Mr. Webman of Oppenheimer said about shifting focus to large-cap stocks.</p>
        <p>THE Russell 2000 index, which tracks the performance of 2000 smaller and mid-cap stocks, ended the quarter up 1.7 percent. That compares with a 0.8 percent gain for the Russell 1000 index, which tracks the 1,000 biggest companies in the stock market.</p>
        <p>The Hennessey Focus 30 fund, which has $233 million under management, uses a formula to pick 30 mid-cap companies with market capitalizations of $1 billion to $10 billion. It chalked up a 9.7 percent return in the quarter. The fund's second-biggest stock holding, the Albemarle Corporation, a chemical maker, closed the quarter up 15.15 percent.</p>
        <p>''The market is in great shape,'' said Neil J. Hennessy, who manages the fund and is president of Hennessy Funds. He said stocks were much cheaper, per dollar of earnings and sales, than they were during the late 1990s.</p>
        <p>Yet strong earnings and sales growth did little to help financial stocks that were exposed to the troubled housing market. Funds specializing in financial stocks closed down 1.8 percent during the quarter.</p>
        <p>The Muhlenkamp fund, which has $2.3 billion under management, ended the first quarter down 3.9 percent. It was hurt by its large positions in Countrywide Financial, Merrill Lynch and Citigroup. The shares of Countrywide, the nation's largest mortgage lender, fell 20.8 percent in the first quarter because investors were concerned that the problems in subprime mortgages would spread to the higher-quality loans that make up the bulk of the company's business.</p>
        <p>Ronald H. Muhlenkamp, who manages the fund and is president of the investment management firm Muhlenkamp &amp; Company, said he still had faith in Countrywide and the other financial stocks he owned, but he acknowledged that it was hard to know precisely how bad things would become in the mortgage market.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muhlenkamp said he stood by a prediction he made late last year that the odds of a soft landing for the economy were 50 percent and becoming better. He said the challenge for investors was to invest for the long term and not to be swayed by short-term market swings.</p>
        <p>''It takes a little patience and a little guts,'' he said, ''but we think you will get paid for it.''</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
