<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On France's Far Right, Tweaking an Image</title>
    <meta content="08france" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/world/europe/08france.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernard, Ariane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarkozy, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Le Pen, Jean-Marie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Le Pen, Jean-Marie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DE143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On France's Far Right, Tweaking an Image</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On France’s Far Right, Tweaking an Image</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO and ARIANE BERNARD; Elaine Sciolino reported from Paris, and Ariane Bernard from Argenteuil.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernard, Ariane; Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Far-right French presidential candidate Jean-Marie Le Pen stops in troubled, multiethnic Paris suburb of Argenteuil; tells thin crowd they are not outsiders but part of French nation; leading conservative candidate Nicolas Sarkozy is still suffering politically from 2005 visit to same spot to chastise young troublemakers; Le Pen hopes to shed his image as anti-immigrant, anti-Europe racist; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jean-Marie Le Pen, the far-right presidential candidate, ventured into potentially hostile terrain on Friday, making a surprise visit to a troubled, multiethnic suburb of Paris.</p>
        <p>The visit was remarkable for its symbolic value: Mr. Le Pen stopped at the same spot where Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative presidential candidate who is leading in the polls, called young troublemakers ''scum'' during a visit in 2005 when he was the interior minister.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jean-Marie Le Pen, the far-right presidential candidate, made a surprise visit to a troubled, multiethnic suburb of Paris on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jean-Marie Le Pen, the far-right presidential candidate, ventured into potentially hostile terrain on Friday, making a surprise visit to a troubled, multiethnic suburb of Paris.</p>
        <p>The visit was remarkable for its symbolic value: Mr. Le Pen stopped at the same spot where Nicolas Sarkozy, the conservative presidential candidate who is leading in the polls, called young troublemakers ''scum'' during a visit in 2005 when he was the interior minister.</p>
        <p>Trailed by scores of journalists, Mr. Le Pen, 78, the leader of the National Front, stopped for 40 minutes at a concourse in the town, Argenteuil, telling a thin crowd of passersby that they were not outsiders, but part of the French nation. ''You are the branches of the tree that is France,'' he said. ''You are full-fledged Frenchmen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarkozy is still suffering politically from the 2005 incident and from telling residents of another grimy Paris suburb a few months earlier that he would use a Kärcher -- the brand name of a high-powered hose used to clean graffiti -- to rid them of criminal gangs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Le Pen, who is running in his fifth presidential race, this time has tried to shed his image as an anti-immigrant, anti-Europe racist in an effort to lure right-wing voters from the Sarkozy camp. To that end, he is portraying himself as a conciliatory figure and the true protector of all French citizens, regardless of their race or ethnic origin.</p>
        <p>''If some want to 'Kärcherize' you, to exclude you,'' he said Friday, ''we want to help you get out of these ghettos of the suburbs where French politicians have parked you, to call you 'scum' later on.'' He added, ''I want to thank all of you for allowing me to speak in this place, where even our former interior minister does not dare go.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarkozy has promised to return to Argenteuil, but a planned campaign trip this year was canceled after the police found gasoline bombs in an apartment complex.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Mr. Sarkozy abruptly canceled a stop in a neighborhood of Lyon where more than 100 demonstrators had gathered to protest his visit. He blamed the late arrival of his plane for the cancellation, but on Friday, Xavier Bertrand, his spokesman, said the actual motivation had been to avoid ''training the spotlight on the left and the extreme left.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Le Pen consistently places fourth in French opinion polls among the 12 candidates in the first round of the presidential election, set for April 22, but he says he is hoping to stage a repeat of his stunning upset victory over the Socialist candidate in the first round in 2002. He placed second in that contest, winning nearly 17 percent of the vote and making it into the second round of balloting, after no candidate won a majority of the votes in the first round.</p>
        <p>According to a survey by the CSA polling institute published Friday, Mr. Le Pen support now stands at 16 percent. He is trailing Mr. Sarkozy, at 26 percent; the Socialist candidate, Ségolène Royal, at 23.5 percent; and the centrist, François Bayrou, at 21 percent. (The telephone survey had a sample of 881 registered voters.)</p>
        <p>He is so confident that he will make the runoff that he has ordered 350,000 campaign posters to be distributed the day after the first round.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly to many here, he is making inroads among some older, more established ethnic Arab and African voters in the suburbs, who say they want to improve security in their neighborhoods and keep out new immigrants.</p>
        <p>Although no one stepped forward as a firm Le Pen supporter in Argenteuil on Friday, some residents were not hostile to his message.</p>
        <p>''If I had no other choice, I would vote for Le Pen before Sarkozy,'' said a 27-year-old mechanic who would identify himself only by his first name, Mehdi. ''Le Pen, he's been in politics for 40 years. We know more or less what he wants, and what he thinks.'' As for Mr. Sarkozy, he added, ''He's a newcomer and a fox.''</p>
        <p>A group of mothers who live in the neighborhood were less friendly to Mr. Le Pen. ''We don't need you here!'' shouted one woman. ''Go home. We don't need you here!''</p>
        <p>A young man shouted, ''What do you think this is, a zoo?'' Another yelled, ''Mr. Le Pen, son of Hitler.''</p>
        <p>But Aicha Beggatt, 45, a homemaker of Algerian origin, urged a group of young people hurling insults at Mr. Le Pen to let him speak.</p>
        <p>''Oh, be good, you kids,'' she said. ''For the image of Argenteuil, we're not scum. We are reasonable people. We can talk.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Le Pen, a former Foreign Legionnaire who was an intelligence officer in Algeria and a paratrooper in Indochina, has campaigned on an anti-immigrant platform. His movement favors a reduction in income taxes, the elimination of some subsidies to businesses, a shrinking of France's bloated government bureaucracy and the elimination of benefits to illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>This time, though, he has tried to woo ethnic Arab and black voters by criticizing what he characterizes as the failed integration policies of the political establishment.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has promised you the moon, and look at where they have led you,'' he said Friday. ''I, I will keep my promises because I am a man of honor.''</p>
        <p>But some of Mr. Le Pen's views continue to be widely criticized. In an interview with Le Monde this week, he said that not all races were equal.</p>
        <p>''You can't dispute the inequality of the races, which I have shown when I say that it is obvious that blacks are much better than whites at running, but whites are better at swimming,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Last year, he joked that his first trip abroad as the next president would be to the suburbs of France.</p>
        <p>In February, he dismissed the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, as ''an incident.'' In 1987, he called the Nazi gas chambers a ''detail'' in the history of World War II, and he was convicted of Holocaust denial. Ten years later, he repeated his remarks and was condemned again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
