<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>San Francisco, N.Y.</title>
    <meta content="08boite" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/fashion/08boite.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOÎTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D9173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>San Francisco, N.Y.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">San Francisco, N.Y.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SCHOENEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schoeneman, Deborah</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST social networking Web sites emerged from San Francisco's first dot-com boom. Now the people behind some of those sites, their pockets lined with venture capital, are taking the socializing offline, hoping to give the San Francisco singles scene some flesh-and-blood sex appeal.</p>
        <p>Vessel, just opened in February, is the latest incarnation of that. The small club has big ambitions: to bring a slice of New York nightlife to the corporatized Union Square neighborhood. Vessel, in the basement of a Niketown store, is owned by Philippe Rieser of Cielo, a popular dance spot in Manhattan's meatpacking district, and Sunwoo Hwang, a D.J. who worked in technology venture capital and now owns a nightlife consulting firm. ''A lot of the people you see here are the ones running Web 2.0,'' Mr. Hwang said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vessel aims to bring a slice of New York nightlife to San Francisco’s corporatized Union Square neighborhood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST social networking Web sites emerged from San Francisco's first dot-com boom. Now the people behind some of those sites, their pockets lined with venture capital, are taking the socializing offline, hoping to give the San Francisco singles scene some flesh-and-blood sex appeal.</p>
        <p>Vessel, just opened in February, is the latest incarnation of that. The small club has big ambitions: to bring a slice of New York nightlife to the corporatized Union Square neighborhood. Vessel, in the basement of a Niketown store, is owned by Philippe Rieser of Cielo, a popular dance spot in Manhattan's meatpacking district, and Sunwoo Hwang, a D.J. who worked in technology venture capital and now owns a nightlife consulting firm. ''A lot of the people you see here are the ones running Web 2.0,'' Mr. Hwang said.</p>
        <p>On a recent Saturday night, those entrepreneurs included the founder of Friendster, Jonathan Abrams, also an investor in another new club nearby, Slide. (Guess how you get from the door to the subterranean dance floor at that place.)</p>
        <p>Alexander Lloyd, another technology venture capitalist, was the host of his own birthday party at Vessel with about 100 friends. ''I like it here and I think my friends like it here,'' said Mr. Lloyd, a gregarious blond wearing a John Varvatos blazer. He's also an investor in Socializr, a new Evite rival that he used to invite people to the party. ''I think having a party is kind of like making a beautiful piece of sand art,'' he said. ''Once it's finished you wipe it away, but you can have this moment of beauty and this place speaks to me in that way.''</p>
        <p>The beauty he referred to could have been the petrified Hollywood juniper tree in the middle of the raised V.I.P. area or the photograph of a topless Marilyn Monroe, and the maritime theme seemed limited to the ice buckets built into the tables.</p>
        <p>In the smoking room, Joy Sian, who works for a new social networking site called HeyLetsGo, enjoyed an American Spirit cigarette. ''I don't think exclusive bars work in San Francisco,'' she said, referring to the club's attempt at imitating Manhattan door policies by keeping a list and charging $250 and up to reserve a table. ''People here don't really respond well to lists. They think it's a joke.'' Upstairs, a restless crowd of 20-something men each insisted they were on said list, but no one was laughing.</p>
        <p>Vessel  85 Campton Place, San Francisco; (415) 433-8585</p>
        <p>GETTING IN -- Open door, open seating during the week, but on the weekends after 9 p.m. you must have reservations, be on the house list or win over the doorman with a mention of part ownership in a social-networking Web site.  DRESS CODE -- Fleece or puffy vests for men, stilettos and skinny jeans for women. Handheld devices for everyone.  SIGHTINGS -- Leonardo DiCaprio, Salma Hayek, Orlando Bloom, Gael García Bernal, Mayor Gavin Newsom.  SIGNATURE DRINK -- Vessellini (passion fruit foam infused with vanilla bean and vanilla vodka and topped with Champagne), $12.</p>
        <p>BOÎTE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
