<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tara Smith, Thomas Struth</title>
    <meta content="08smith" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/fashion/weddings/08smith.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Tara Bray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Struth, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0DB173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tara Smith, Thomas Struth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tara Smith, Thomas Struth</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tara Bray Smith, a writer, and Thomas Struth, the photographer, were married yesterday by the Rev. Vernon Nichols, a Unitarian Universalist minister, at the Church Center for the United Nations in New York.</p>
        <p>Ms. Smith, 36, graduated from Dartmouth and received a Master of Fine Arts in nonfiction writing from Columbia. She is the author of ''West of Then: A Mother, a Daughter and a Journey Past Paradise'' (Simon &amp; Schuster, 2004), both a memoir and a history of Hawaii.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tara Bray Smith, a writer, and Thomas Struth, the photographer, were married yesterday by the Rev. Vernon Nichols, a Unitarian Universalist minister, at the Church Center for the United Nations in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tara Bray Smith, a writer, and Thomas Struth, the photographer, were married yesterday by the Rev. Vernon Nichols, a Unitarian Universalist minister, at the Church Center for the United Nations in New York.</p>
        <p>Ms. Smith, 36, graduated from Dartmouth and received a Master of Fine Arts in nonfiction writing from Columbia. She is the author of ''West of Then: A Mother, a Daughter and a Journey Past Paradise'' (Simon &amp; Schuster, 2004), both a memoir and a history of Hawaii.</p>
        <p>She is the daughter of Karen Morgan of Honolulu and the late Kirk Smith and the stepdaughter of Deborah Baker of Kona, Hawaii. Her stepmother is an owner of Current Events, a public relations agency in Kona. Her father was the vice president for advertising and marketing at Hawaiian Airlines in Honolulu.</p>
        <p>Mr. Struth, 52, is known for his large-scale prints of streetscapes, cultural institutions and family portraits. He was the subject of a career retrospective in 2003 at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York. He now has exhibitions at the Museo del Prado in Madrid, the Galerie Max Hetzler in Berlin and the Marian Goodman Gallery in New York. He graduated from the Düsseldorf Art Academy, in Germany.</p>
        <p>He is a son of Gisela Struth of Königsdorf, Germany, and the late Heinrich Struth. His mother is a ceramic potter. His father was a bank director at SEB Bank in Cologne.</p>
        <p>The couple met in 2005 at the Marian Goodman Gallery in Manhattan, when Ms. Smith attended the opening of one of Mr. Struth's shows.</p>
        <p>She recalled that as she entered the showroom she noticed that ''this tall, very distinguished-looking man lit up.'' They were briefly introduced by a mutual friend before Mr. Struth was obligated to mingle with his other guests.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Struth said he kept an eye on Ms. Smith. ''Friends of mine were flirting with her, and I got a bit jealous,'' he said.</p>
        <p>They later shared a moment and a cigarette overlooking Central Park on the rooftop terrace of Marian Goodman's apartment building.</p>
        <p>He asked for her phone number, and Ms. Smith, who was dating someone else at the time, surprised herself by giving it to him. ''This is crazy,'' she remembered thinking. ''This is a guy who lives in Germany. He's older than me.''</p>
        <p>Yet two days later she agreed to have dinner with him, and Mr. Struth nervously showed up an hour early. Ms. Smith said she found him compelling. ''When he concentrates on you his eyes are very big,'' she elaborated. ''When he was talking to me he was talking to me. He was focused on me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Struth was equally taken. ''When you meet somebody you don't reveal yourself so easily, or at least that's how I am,'' he said. ''But with Tara, after an hour or so, I just let go completely. ''</p>
        <p>He invited her to his next opening, in Oslo, and they've been together since then.</p>
        <p>But marriage was not an implicit outcome. ''For most of my life I thought I was never going to get married because it felt too closed in and too pressured,'' said Mr. Struth, whose art has been described as a response to the stress of growing up in a very traditional, postwar-German household.</p>
        <p>''That's why he does these family portraits,'' Ms. Smith explained, referring to his acclaimed series of photographs. ''He observes what pulls these people together and what pulls them apart. Who stands in front and who hides in the shadows.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Smith comes from a completely different background, growing up in Hawaii with ''hippy parents'' and a ''surfer dad.'' Mr. Struth believes she carries the spirit of the islands with her.</p>
        <p>''There are 3,000 miles of water around Hawaii, and now I know what it feels like to be floating in water,'' he said. ''Air and space, that's what I feel with her.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
