<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Late Scoring Spree Gives Spartans a Championship</title>
    <meta content="08frozen" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/hockey/08frozen.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070622T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Michigan State University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E0DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Late Scoring Spree Gives Spartans a Championship</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Late Scoring Spree Hands Spartans Championship</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAT BORZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borzi, Pat</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Justin Abdelkader's dance after his game-deciding goal for Michigan State might have been niftier than the score itself. After burying a Tim Kennedy feed with 18.9 seconds to play, Abdelkader jumped, spun and skipped away in celebration while his teammates on the bench mobbed one another and Coach Rick Comley.</p>
        <p>Chris Mueller added an empty-net goal with 1.7 seconds left to finish off Michigan State's 3-1 victory against Boston College for the N.C.A.A. men's championship. The Eagles, who saw their 13-game winning streak end, lost the Frozen Four title game for the second year in a row.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a tight-checking, physical game the patient Spartans prevailed by scoring three goals in the final 10 minutes 7 seconds before a Frozen Four-record crowd of 19,432 at the Scottrade Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Justin Abdelkader's dance after his game-deciding goal for Michigan State might have been niftier than the score itself. After burying a Tim Kennedy feed with 18.9 seconds to play, Abdelkader jumped, spun and skipped away in celebration while his teammates on the bench mobbed one another and Coach Rick Comley.</p>
        <p>Chris Mueller added an empty-net goal with 1.7 seconds left to finish off Michigan State's 3-1 victory against Boston College for the N.C.A.A. men's championship. The Eagles, who saw their 13-game winning streak end, lost the Frozen Four title game for the second year in a row.</p>
        <p>Abdelkader's goal was the latest game winner in regulation time in an N.C.A.A. final.</p>
        <p>In a physical game, the Spartans prevailed by scoring three goals in the final 10 minutes 7 seconds. Abdelkader won the tournament's most outstanding player award, but the diminutive goalie Jeff Lerg proved at least as valuable.</p>
        <p>The 5-foot-6 Lerg, who has asthma and uses a breathing machine before games, made 29 saves. With Boston College leading, 1-0, five minutes into the third, his spectacular, belly-flopping glove stop on Brian Boyle foiled a short-handed two-on-one and energized the Spartans, who tied the score about five minutes later.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of what I've been waiting my whole life to do, proving everyone wrong on a national level,'' said Lerg, a sophomore. ''I've been too small at so many levels. Some coaches didn't want to talk to me. Coach Comley gave me a great opportunity.''</p>
        <p>Before a Frozen Four-record crowd of 19,432 at the Scottrade Center, the game appeared headed for overtime when Boston College (29-12-1) turned over the puck with less than 30 seconds to play. The Spartans (26-13-3) broke in three-on-one, and Abdelkader's shot hit the right post and richoceted to the corner.</p>
        <p>Pressure prevented the Eagles from clearing the zone. Kennedy gained control from Boston College's Dan Bertram behind the net and threw the puck in front for Abdelkader, whose quick shot beat goalie Cory Schneider.</p>
        <p>''I was just in the right place at the right time,'' Abdelkader said. After Mueller's empty-netter, the Spartans jumped on the ice to celebrate. Boston College Coach Jerry York asked the officials to wave off the final seconds.</p>
        <p>Comley became the third coach to win an N.C.A.A. men's hockey championship at two schools, adding to his 1991 title at Northern Michigan.</p>
        <p>In their streak, the Eagles converted 35 percent of their power-play chances. Michigan State's penalty killers had gone 14 for 14 in the tournament until Boston College broke through for the first goal on an extended power play in the second. When Michigan State could not clear the puck in the left faceoff, Brock Bradford pounced and swept a forehand off Lerg's glove.</p>
        <p>Kennedy missed the net on an attempt early in the third, but made up for it later. Michigan State had gone 0 for 5 on the power play when Boston College's Tim Filangieri hooked Mueller with 10:13 left. On the faceoff, Kennedy took the puck, sped past Boyle into the zone alone and beat Schneider with a forehand for the tying goal. Elapsed time: six seconds.</p>
        <p>''It's been so hard for us to score this year that after we score, it skyrockets,'' Comley said.</p>
        <p>The victory finished an emotional few weeks for the undrafted captain, Chris Lawrence. Before postseason practices Lawrence did 21 pushups, signifying the 21 years since Michigan State's last national title, in 1986.</p>
        <p>Saturday, realizing he was about to play his final game, Lawrence cried in the dressing room. Forward Brian Lerg, Jeff's cousin, had to remind Lawrence to tape his stick.</p>
        <p>Teammates were asking, '' 'What are you doing?' '' Lawrence said. ''But what a way to go out.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 22, 2007, Friday  A sports article on April 8 about Michigan State's 3-1 victory over Boston College to capture the N.C.A.A. men's ice hockey championship misidentified the player who scored the only goal for the Eagles. It was Brian Boyle -- not Brock Bradford, who had the assist. The reporter pointed out the error this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 22, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>A sports article on April 8 about Michigan State's 3-1 victory over Boston College to capture the N.C.A.A. men's ice hockey championship misidentified the player who scored the only goal for the Eagles. It was Brian Boyle -- not Brock Bradford, who had the assist. The reporter pointed out the error this week.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
