<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Industry's Critics Turn to Washington</title>
    <meta content="08gove" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/mutfund/08gove.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E3D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1276" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Industry's Critics Turn to Washington</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Industry’s Critics Turn to Washington</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. HOLSTEIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER the Enron and WorldCom meltdowns, many American investors were outraged. They demanded change -- and they got it, in the form of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act of 2002 and new directives issued by the major stock exchanges.</p>
        <p>Henceforth, publicly traded companies would have to impose new internal financial controls to guard against fraud. Chief executives and chief financial officers would personally sign off on the truthfulness of their companies' financial results, at the risk of criminal penalties. And boards would have to include many more directors who were independent of management.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A movement to impose more checks and balances -- to protect the interests of investors -- has been testing its strength in the mutual fund industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER the Enron and WorldCom meltdowns, many American investors were outraged. They demanded change -- and they got it, in the form of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act of 2002 and new directives issued by the major stock exchanges.</p>
        <p>Henceforth, publicly traded companies would have to impose new internal financial controls to guard against fraud. Chief executives and chief financial officers would personally sign off on the truthfulness of their companies' financial results, at the risk of criminal penalties. And boards would have to include many more directors who were independent of management.</p>
        <p>A similar movement for change has been testing its strength in the mutual fund industry, which, critics say, would benefit from more checks and balances to protect the interests of investors.</p>
        <p>A fundamental problem for mutual funds has been conflicts of interest at the top, in this view. One issue is whether funds' boards should have chairmen who are independent of the management, or advisory, firms that actually manage investors' money. In some cases the chairman of a mutual fund board owns the management and subadviser firms or has deep connections with them.</p>
        <p>At Fidelity, for example, Edward C. Johnson III, known as Ned, heads the Fidelity Management and Research Company, the investment adviser to approximately 300 Fidelity mutual funds, at the same time that he is chairman of the board that oversees the funds. Similar arrangements exist at other fund companies.</p>
        <p>The concern among critics about nonindependent chairmen is that their jobs on a mutual fund board center on hiring and firing management firms and deciding how much investor money to spend to compensate those firms. Investors may be denied a higher rate of return if boards spend too much on advisers.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure he knows his business very well, but there are inherent conflicts between Ned Johnson running the fund board and the management company,'' said Laura Pavlenko Lutton, senior mutual fund analyst at Morningstar, the mutual fund rating company based in Chicago. ''He's not going to fire the management company that he and his family owns.''</p>
        <p>Fidelity declined to make Mr. Johnson available for comment, but a spokesman said that the proportion of Fidelity board members who are independent exceeds 75 percent -- the minimum percentage that critics are demanding.</p>
        <p>What prompted the latest round in the war of words between the mutual fund industry and its critics -- spearheaded by Morningstar, the A.F.L.-C.I.O. and consumer rights groups -- was the Securities and Exchange Commission's call in December for comments by March 2 on the issue of independent chairmen. Some supporters of an independent-chairman rule sense that there may be an opening on the issue because of Democratic gains in Congress.</p>
        <p>''Having Barney Frank as chairman of the House Financial Services Committee will give shareholders more support,'' said Richard L. Trumka, secretary-treasurer of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. in Washington. ''With the changing Congress, there was a change in dynamic toward the shareholder and away from the established people at the mutual funds.''</p>
        <p>Representative Frank, a Massachusetts Democrat, has oversight responsibilities for the S.E.C., which is headed by Christopher Cox, a former Republican colleague in the House.</p>
        <p>Whether the S.E.C. will next hold hearings or will propose a new rule is not known. ''The staff is reviewing the comments received,'' said John D. Heine, an agency spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trumka says he believes that the S.E.C. will take some type of action. ''They're not in the business of wasting everyone's time,'' he said. ''If they were not interested in issuing a rule, they wouldn't have gone through all this.''</p>
        <p>The A.F.L.-C.I.O. says it has a huge stake in how mutual funds are managed: its own pension funds hold $400 billion in assets, and union members as a whole participate in pension plans with $5 trillion in assets. Tens of millions of other Americans also own mutual funds, either directly or through their 401(k) plans or individual retirement accounts.</p>
        <p>The mutual fund industry, represented by the Investment Company Institute, also based in Washington, argues that 80 percent of mutual funds have boards on which at least 75 percent of members are independent. It says significant progress has been made in cleaning up the industry, and that any further edicts from the S.E.C. would raise the cost of managing the boards and thus hurt investors' returns.</p>
        <p>''We don't think an independent chairman is necessarily a bad idea,'' said Paul Schott Stevens, president of the Investment Company Institute. ''What we think is that it should be left up to the people on those boards, the vast majority of whom are independent, to make that choice.''</p>
        <p>William H. Donaldson, Mr. Cox's immediate predecessor as S.E.C. chairman, sought twice to require that mutual funds have independent chairmen; each time the United States Chamber of Commerce brought legal action to block the move. Then a federal appeals court decided that the S.E.C. had not properly considered the economic impact of such a ruling.</p>
        <p>That court, the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit, in effect told the S.E.C. to study the matter more seriously. That resulted in the release last December of two S.E.C. studies, which the warring parties interpret differently.</p>
        <p>Industry critics say the studies support the view that the benefits would outweigh the increased costs of having more independent directors and chairmen -- more of whom would have travel expenses than insiders who presumably live closer to a company's headquarters. Critics say that more independent chairmen and boards would be tougher on the fee structure for management companies, meaning that investors would win.</p>
        <p>BUT defenders say the studies do not support the view that investors would gain. ''The S.E.C.'s own Office of Economic Analysis studies do not support the need for the rules,'' said Mr. Stevens of the mutual fund association. ''We believe they should conclude this without any further action.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Stevens argues that investors do not care whether the chairmen of their mutual funds are independent. The mutual fund group paid an independent research firm in 2006 to interview 737 randomly selected fund investors and found that just 15 percent of them cared about ''information about the fund's board of directors.'' The greatest percentage, 74 percent, cared about ''the fund's fees and expenses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trumka of the A.F.L.-C.I.O., however, disputes the notion that investors do not worry whether board chairmen are independent. ''This is one of the best-kept secrets,'' he said. ''When we tell people about the facts, they are universally concerned.''</p>
        <p>Whether the S.E.C. will be concerned enough to act may ultimately depend on Mr. Cox. He has displayed some grass-roots fervor -- for example, in seeking to make it easier for investors to obtain company financial information via computer. If he supports the concept of independent chairmen, he would have to broker a deal with fellow commissioners.</p>
        <p>One of them, Paul S. Atkins, a Republican like Mr. Cox, recently gave a speech stressing the economic costs of imposing a requirement for an independent chairman; he is considered solidly against the idea. Another Republican commissioner, Kathleen L. Casey, is relatively new; her views on the subject are not known. Two Democratic commissioners, Roel C. Campos and Annette L. Nazareth, are considered likely to back an independent-chairman rule.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Cox has tried to avoid divisive 3-to-2 votes, he would have to devise a solution that Ms. Casey would find palatable. That might set the stage for a vote of 4 to 1, leaving only Mr. Atkins in opposition. But because the industry and its critics have turned up the volume of their debate, it may take every bit of Mr. Cox's deal-making savvy to avoid a political backlash from one camp or the other.</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
