<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rites of Spring; Rebuilding on a Foundation</title>
    <meta content="08RcatholicLI-2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Barry Avenue African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mamaroneck (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rites of Spring; Rebuilding on a Foundation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at Barry Avenue African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church in Mamaroneck, NY, described as congregation worships during Lenten season; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a season of renewal for Christians and Jews as they commemorate momentous events in their histories: for Christians, the resurrection of Jesus; for Jews, the liberation of the ancient Hebrews from slavery in Egypt. As Jews began celebrating the eight days of Passover at sundown last Monday, Christians observed the final, most solemn days of Lent in preparation for Easter services this weekend. Here are a handful of stories about different faith communities around the region.</p>
        <p>When the Rev. Yasmin D. Harris McMillian arrived at Barry Avenue African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church in Mamaroneck, N.Y., almost four years ago, the youngest member of her new congregation was 65.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a season of renewal for Christians and Jews as they commemorate momentous events in their histories: for Christians, the resurrection of Jesus; for Jews, the liberation of the ancient Hebrews from slavery in Egypt. As Jews began celebrating the eight days of Passover at sundown last Monday, Christians observed the final, most solemn days of Lent in preparation for Easter services this weekend. Here are a handful of stories about different faith communities around the region.</p>
        <p>When the Rev. Yasmin D. Harris McMillian arrived at Barry Avenue African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church in Mamaroneck, N.Y., almost four years ago, the youngest member of her new congregation was 65.</p>
        <p>''There were no youths, no young adults,'' said Pastor Harris McMillian, 49, who had previously served as a minister at Greater Centennial A.M.E. Zion Church in nearby Mount Vernon.</p>
        <p>Mary Young, 72, of Port Chester, a great-granddaughter of Robert Purdy, a runaway slave who helped found the church in 1852, said, ''We were going down.''</p>
        <p>But with a rich 155-year history to build upon, Pastor Harris McMillian set out to help revitalize the congregation, and signs of success were evident this Lenten season.</p>
        <p>In the early days, the families worshiped in homes, including Mr. Purdy's on Saxon Wood Road in Scarsdale. In 1903, the congregation built the current church, a modest white wood-frame structure with a steeple in a mostly residential neighborhood just north of the town's train station.</p>
        <p>Shortly after her arrival, Pastor Harris McMillian focused her efforts on updating the worship service. The traditional gospel music is now accompanied by electric guitars and drums. The pastor also reached out to former members and asked them to return -- with family and friends.</p>
        <p>Although the congregation remains small and some of the younger members are not regular churchgoers, the church is expected to be packed for Easter services as the children put on a special program -- a presentation of the 23rd Psalm in sign language.</p>
        <p>Over the last two months, the church took part in ecumenical services held every Tuesday during Lent at a different Mamaroneck church. Each service followed the host denomination's practices, but a guest minister gave the sermon.</p>
        <p>Pastor Harris McMillian was the homilist at the Mamaroneck United Methodist Church, which is headed by the Rev. Richard E. Allen Jr.</p>
        <p>''It was fun for people in my congregation to have someone with a different preaching style -- and in this case a different race -- preach,'' Pastor Allen said.</p>
        <p>Beyond the challenge of revitalizing a dwindling congregation, Pastor Harris McMillian has faced the objections of some church members to having a woman in the pulpit.</p>
        <p>''I still don't like it,'' said William Peterson, 89, who is Mary Young's brother and a great-grandson of Mr. Purdy. ''However, I learned from the age of 7 to keep quiet and observe.''</p>
        <p>Pastor Harris McMillian has taken such feelings in stride. ''Over time, people in the congregation began to respect a woman in the position as pastor, and now people and pastor have come together,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Among the people she has drawn back to the church is Nseya Hutt, who stopped attending the church about 10 years ago while in her early 20s. She and her husband were the first young adults who joined the ministry after Pastor Harris McMillian's arrival. Now Ms. Hutt is the pastor's administrative assistant.</p>
        <p>''I started with another church because there were no young adults here,'' said Ms. Hutt, who has five children, ages 9 months to 14.</p>
        <p>But Pastor Harris McMillian's sermons -- a mix of teaching the gospel and riffing on the day-to-day life of her congregants, a practice that she has called Yasminology -- helped lure Ms. Hutt back.</p>
        <p>''It was nice to come back home,'' Ms. Hutt said.</p>
        <p>BARBARA WHITAKER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
