<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Walk, Don't Run, Is Rule For Two Champion Racers</title>
    <meta content="08LIpeopleLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08LIpeople.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="RACE WALKING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monahan, Jenna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buletti, Leah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EFDC163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Walk, Don't Run, Is Rule For Two Champion Racers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Walk, Don’t Run, Is Rule for Two Champion Racers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <dateline>HAUPPAUGE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Jenna Monahan, 17, and Leah Buletti, 15, champion race walkers who were top seeds going into New York State Federation Indoor Track and Field Championships at Cornell University; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROCKING their hips and pumping their arms, Jenna Monahan and Leah Buletti practiced race walking around the parking lot of the H. Lee Dennison building here. Striding side by side, they kept their heads high and their posture perfect.</p>
        <p>Jenna, a 17-year-old from Holbrook, and Leah, 15, of East Moriches, are champions in this fast-paced sport, practicing together on Tuesdays and Thursdays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hauppauge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROCKING their hips and pumping their arms, Jenna Monahan and Leah Buletti practiced race walking around the parking lot of the H. Lee Dennison building here. Striding side by side, they kept their heads high and their posture perfect.</p>
        <p>Jenna, a 17-year-old from Holbrook, and Leah, 15, of East Moriches, are champions in this fast-paced sport, practicing together on Tuesdays and Thursdays.</p>
        <p>''We are very friendly with each other more than competitive,'' said Leah, who, like Jenna, works out with her high school track team for more than an hour after school before heading to Hauppauge for additional training with WalkUSA, a national race walking club.</p>
        <p>But during a track meet, the two athletes are rivals. The girls were the top seeds going into the New York State Federation Indoor Track and Field Championships at Cornell University on March 3.</p>
        <p>Leah, a sophomore at Westhampton Beach High School, won the 1,500-meter race walking event. Her 6:46.66 time set the national indoor record for sophomores. She is No. 1 in the nation in the event. Jenna, a senior at Sachem High School East, clocked 7:05.96.</p>
        <p>''I had a stomach virus that day,'' Jenna said. While she was upset that she didn't win, she said, ''at least it went to someone from Long Island.''</p>
        <p>Gary Westerfield, a coach with WalkUSA, race official and president of Long Island Track and Field, said Leah's victory was unexpected. ''Jenna was the person to beat all season,'' Mr. Westerfield said.</p>
        <p>The race walkers were part of a track team representing Suffolk County high school girls. The team won the overall team state championship for the second straight year.</p>
        <p>Not to be outdone, Jenna cinched the gold in a one-mile race, striding to the finish line in 7:38.16 at the National Scholastic Indoor Championships at the Armory in New York on March 11.</p>
        <p>Leah's bid for victory in the mile race at the Nike Indoor Nationals, a competition in Landover, Md., on March 10, was cut short when she was disqualified for improper form.</p>
        <p>Unlike in running, according to the sport's rules, one foot must remain in contact with the ground in race walking. In addition, when the advancing leg touches the ground it has to straighten and remain straight until it passes under the walker's body.</p>
        <p>Jenna started race walking in the ninth grade, at the urging of her high school track coach, Pete McNeill, who ''makes everyone try it in the beginning of the year,'' she recalled. Leah took up race walking last year, inspired by her older sister. Heather, now 19 and a freshman at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, N.Y., captured the one-mile national record -- 6:49.63 -- for high school girls at the Eastern States Championship in Bellmore last June.</p>
        <p>John Broich, the Buletti sisters' track coach at Westhampton Beach, said Leah was a tough competitor and ''should be able to beat her sister's record'' someday.</p>
        <p>He said he didn't believe in pushing his high school track star, however. ''The opportunity is there for her,'' Mr. Broich said. ''She has to either take it and run with it, or let's say walk with it, or do something else.'' Jenna, meanwhile, is hoping to compete on a higher level.</p>
        <p>''I would be disappointed if I didn't go any further with it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Recently Jenna finished in fourth place in the trials for the Pan American Games in Miami, just missing a chance to compete. She hopes to make the World Cup in Russia next year and eventually land a spot on the Olympic race walking team, where women compete in a 20-kilometer race.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, when Jenna walks to class at school, her friends tell her to ''slow down,'' she said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>RACE WALKING E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
