<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Has the Exit Sign Ever Looked So Good?</title>
    <meta content="08axe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/yourmoney/08axe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070415T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EXECUTIVE PAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E1D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Has the Exit Sign Ever Looked So Good?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Has the Exit Sign Ever Looked So Good?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT was the price of failure in corporate America in 2006?</p>
        <p>More than $1 billion, with shareholders left holding the bag. At America's biggest companies, it was possible for chief executives to fumble, fudge or fail to deliver results -- and yet still walk away with more money than most people earn in a lifetime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shareholders are paying for performance, almost any kind of performance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT was the price of failure in corporate America in 2006?</p>
        <p>More than $1 billion, with shareholders left holding the bag. At America's biggest companies, it was possible for chief executives to fumble, fudge or fail to deliver results -- and yet still walk away with more money than most people earn in a lifetime.</p>
        <p>Consider:</p>
        <p>In late January last year, Mary L. Forte was ousted as the chief executive of the Zale Corporation after her plans to transform the discount jeweler into a more upscale chain fizzled. Lackluster holiday sales pulled down profits two years in a row. Yet Ms. Forte left with a $7.2 million golden goodbye -- including $4.9 million in severance.</p>
        <p>A few weeks later, David J. Edmondson resigned as RadioShack's chief executive, a week after admitting to lying on his résumé about his college credentials. The board still chose to give him more than $1 million in severance, including unused vacation.</p>
        <p>And in October, Jay S. Sidhu, citing health concerns, resigned as chief executive of Sovereign Bancorp amid mounting criticism from investors. Despite the bank's poor performance, Mr. Sidhu left with a $73.56 million platinum parachute lined with $24.4 million in cash and stock options, five years of free health care, and a three-year, $40,000-a-month consulting contract.</p>
        <p>Investors have long complained that too many top executives are taking home enormous paychecks for average performance. Even more galling to shareholders are the staggering amounts the executives are paid when they fail. It is tantamount to winning the lottery by losing their jobs.</p>
        <p>''Classically, severance awards were to help people as a transition between jobs,'' said Richard C. Breeden, who was chairman of the Securities and Exchange during the early 1990s and is now an activist investor. ''The notion that some of these 'severance' awards are turning themselves into lifetime lifestyle maintenance awards,'' he added, ''is particularly outrageous.''</p>
        <p>A confluence of forces has increased the jackpot over the last two decades or so. A wave of buyouts and mergers has bid up the price of experienced managers. Boards are fond of luring superstar chief executives from other companies rather than promoting from inside. As a result, they often must extend a "golden hello" to compensate them for the pay package they left behind. At the same time, investor pressure and regulatory scrutiny have caused a surge in the number of ousted executives.</p>
        <p>Chief executives, meanwhile, have negotiated employment contracts that provided upfront guarantees and sweetheart severance deals. Aided by compensation consultants, compensation surveys and hired legal guns, they wove lucrative stock options awards and retirement plans into their exit packages. And in yet another example of the law of unintended consequences, a tax that Congress enacted in the early 1980s to curb excessive payouts actually encouraged boards to approve bigger parachutes.</p>
        <p>As the years wore on, most corporate compensation committees never bothered to tally the various components of increasingly complex severance packages, leaving boards with little understanding of what an ousted chief executive would receive. Now, the S.E.C.'s new disclosure rules require companies to disclose how much they will pay top managers if they are forced out.</p>
        <p>In 2006, the 35 chief executives who were ousted were handed more than $799 million on their way out the door, according to an analysis of exit packages by James F. Reda &amp; Associates, an independent compensation consulting firm in New York.</p>
        <p>Add in the $210 million platinum parachute for Robert L. Nardelli, the former Home Depot chief executive who was officially dismissed on the first workday of 2007, and the total comes to more than $1 billion for the year.</p>
        <p>''What you are seeing is an early indicator of other things to come,'' said Mr. Reda, the head of the consulting firm that bears his name. ''The system has drifted and wasted corporate assets.''</p>
        <p>As large as the failure payouts are, something is still missing: the roughly $750 million in payouts that at least 27 chief executives received last year for selling their companies, according to estimates from Mr. Reda's firm. Yet many of those companies were on the block precisely because they had underperformed.</p>
        <p>The failure payouts from last year also don't include exit packages awarded in the midst of scandal but frozen in litigation. For example, after Dr. William W. McGuire of the UnitedHealth Group and Bruce E. Karatz of KB Home were dismissed in the wake of option backdating investigations, Dr. McGuire walked away with about $1.1 billion (largely in stock options), while Mr. Karatz left with about $114 million. Both awards are now tied up by the courts.</p>
        <p>Analysts say that enormous exit packages underscore a central problem with pay-for-failure: employment or severance contracts, not typically offered to the rank and file, create a ''heads I win, tails you lose'' proposition for executives.</p>
        <p>While companies boast about their pay-for-performance programs, boards typically guarantee senior executives big salaries, stock options, future legal fees, severance packages and retirement plans when they are hired -- long before their on-the-job performance can be assessed. Companies argue that this is necessary to attract and motivate top talent, and is the price they pay to induce executives to sign noncompete agreements.</p>
        <p>If everything works out, investors, directors and executives are happy. If it doesn't, shareholders are still on the hook -- and then obligated to dole out even more in exit pay. Of the $799 million that departing executives received last year, 37 percent, or $296 million, was severance.</p>
        <p>Consider Douglas A. Pertz, who resigned in August as the C.E.O. of Harman International Industries, an electronics company. Mr. Pertz, an experienced manager, had never overseen an electronics company when Harman recruited him. As soon as he took over, Harman shares began to plummet. Four months later, Mr. Pertz was ousted -- taking $3.8 million in severance with him. That was almost $32,000 for each day he was a Harman employee.</p>
        <p>''When it is apparent that it doesn't work, you take your medicine and move on,'' said Robert Ryan, a Harman spokesman, noting that the company needed to honor its contractual agreements. ''Harman's board could have swept it under the carpet and not admitted to the mistake.''</p>
        <p>Corporate spokesmen at RadioShack, Zale and Sovereign declined to comment about the severance packages of their former executives.</p>
        <p>Being a former executive usually means receiving a cushier exit package than the one snared by simply retiring. And given how narrowly many contract terms are usually defined, pay advisers joke that it usually takes murder, embezzlement or outright fraud for an executive to be fired for cause.</p>
        <p>''You can certainly 'fire' a C.E.O.,'' said Stewart J. Schwab, the dean of Cornell Law School. ''The real question is: Can you fire them without these very large severance payments being triggered?''</p>
        <p>Most often, the answer is no. Corporate boards are often eager to avoid long legal battles and critical press reports, Mr. Schwab said. For a multibillion-dollar enterprise, others argue, paying a top executive even tens of millions of dollars might be economically rational if it lets the company quickly put problems behind it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reda's firm examined roughly 150 companies where the chief executives stepped down. Just two -- Atmel and KLA-Tencor -- were found to have terminated their chief executives without making payments.</p>
        <p>Losing your job was not always solucrative. But just as the gap has grown between C.E.O. pay and what average workers bring home, so has the difference in their severance payments. The average worker is lucky to get about two weeks' salary for every year worked. The average chief without a contract can expect the equivalent of about 18 weeks of salary for each year worked, according to Mr. Reda's firm.</p>
        <p>And in 2006, the average chief who was ousted could expect a $9 million in severance, the equivalent of about 170 weeks of salary for each week at the helm.</p>
        <p>''There is less economic justification to provide a soft landing for executives who are fired than for the rank and file,'' said Lucian A. Bebchuck, a professor at Harvard Law School and a compensation expert. ''In the real world, you see the reverse.''</p>
        <p>Corporate media officers and industry groups say severance pay is, by and large, not out of line -- especially given the risk that chief executives from outside take by wading into unfamiliar waters. ''It is dictated by the marketplace, not unlike an entertainer or athlete,'' said Thomas J. Lehner, a policy director at the Business Roundtable, a corporate lobbying group. Besides, others say, the news media and critics tend to focus on a few choice examples.</p>
        <p>But 2006 offered a bounty of choices. Executives in at least a dozen different industries -- from auto repair (The Pep Boys -- Manny, Moe &amp; Jack) and banking (Mellon Financial) to fast food (Wendy's International) and fashion (Phillips-Van Heusen) -- were awarded large exit packages when they left. So did managers in other businesses like education (Apollo), insurance (Conseco), pest control (ServiceMaster) and subprime lending (New Century).</p>
        <p>In July, Hank McKinnell, Pfizer's chairman and chief executive, resigned with an exit package worth nearly $200 million -- although the company lost more than $137 billion in market value during the six years he was on watch. Mr. Nardelli, Home Depot's ousted chief, received a $210 million exit package for six years of work and a sagging stock price -- which quickly made him the standard-bearer for failure-based pay. Analysts say Mr. Nardelli was assured a lush payout because Home Depot's board guaranteed him roughly $180 million when he was hired.</p>
        <p>Some boards are starting to take notice. Those at the Hartford Financial Services Group and Prudential Financial Services, for example, are tightening their contracts; others are inserting claw-back clauses to recover any improper gains. .</p>
        <p>But most compensation lawyers and consultants say that it will take at least another generation of new leaders to bring the golden era of the golden parachute to an end. Sitting chief executives are reluctant to renegotiate. And it is investors -- not board members -- who foot the severance bill, giving directors little incentive to rein in the payouts.</p>
        <p>''It would be interesting if the guys who were on the compensation committee were writing the checks,'' said Michael S. Kesner, a consultant at Deloitte &amp; Touche.</p>
        <p>EXECUTIVE PAY</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 15, 2007, Sunday  An article in the pay report about exit packages for ousted chief executives misstated a salary equivalent of the average severance in 2006. That average, $9 million, was equivalent to about 170 weeks of salary for each year, not each week, at the helm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 15, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in the pay report about exit packages for ousted chief executives misstated a salary equivalent of the average severance in 2006. That average, $9 million, was equivalent to about 170 weeks of salary for each year, not each week, at the helm.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
