<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Rockslide, Merchants Are Still Struggling</title>
    <meta content="08weupdateWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08weupdate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="UPDATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Landslides and Mudslides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pelham (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malone, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landslides and Mudslides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DF173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Rockslide, Merchants Are Still Struggling</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Rockslide, Merchants Are Still Struggling</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL MALONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Malone, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Update on impact on local merchants from December 2005 rockslide in Pelham, NY; insurance companies have labeled it earth movement and refused to pay claims; displaced proprietors hired lawyers, so far to no avail; some merchants have retired, some have reopened and others have relocated; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALMOST 16 months after a landslide damaged several shops on Fifth Avenue in Pelham, the owners of those businesses are painfully aware of the difference between ''an earth movement'' and ''a rock topple.''</p>
        <p>Had their insurance companies deemed the slide a topple, the owners might have received a substantial amount of money by now. But since it was labeled an act of God (or earth movement, in insurance parlance), they have received nothing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALMOST 16 months after a landslide damaged several shops on Fifth Avenue in Pelham, the owners of those businesses are painfully aware of the difference between “an earth movement” and “a rock topple.”.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALMOST 16 months after a landslide damaged several shops on Fifth Avenue in Pelham, the owners of those businesses are painfully aware of the difference between ''an earth movement'' and ''a rock topple.''</p>
        <p>Had their insurance companies deemed the slide a topple, the owners might have received a substantial amount of money by now. But since it was labeled an act of God (or earth movement, in insurance parlance), they have received nothing.</p>
        <p>And that has left merchants frustrated, to say the least.</p>
        <p>''I was very, very surprised to hear we weren't covered, since we had every kind of insurance,'' said Chris Hickey, a partner in the restaurant Rangoli, who said the business lost about $100,000. ''I said, 'You've got to help us out, even a little bit!' ''</p>
        <p>While the displaced proprietors hired lawyers to prod the insurance companies, their efforts have so far been fruitless. The same goes for Lordae Property Management, which was forced to demolish one extensively damaged building and finally reopened three others last August. ''We haven't gotten a dime,'' Chris Santomero, the owner, said. ''My children might be able to recoup the loss, but I can't.''</p>
        <p>Lordae's insurance company, Crum &amp; Forster, and Mr. Hickey's, Tower Insurance, did not return calls for comment.</p>
        <p>In December 2005, a huge piece of the cliff behind Fifth Avenue, the village's main commercial street, gave way, sending boulders and tons of debris tumbling onto the street below. One bank and two businesses were destroyed, and a dozen stores were forced to evacuate.</p>
        <p>Some merchants have retired, some have reopened, and others have set up shop elsewhere on Fifth Avenue or in the county.</p>
        <p>Hector Vera, who ran the Pelham Cafe at 112 Fifth Avenue for a decade, is reopening at 138 Fifth Avenue in a few months. Mr. Vera, who has been working at his brother's diner in White Plains since the rockslide, said he was not about to leave his adopted hometown. ''I've been there 10 years,'' he said. ''They know me, and I know them.''</p>
        <p>Those plying their trades in neighboring towns said they hoped that enough old customers would find them to help pay off their loans. But the new places don't always feel like home.</p>
        <p>''I live in Pelham, I have four kids in Pelham,'' said Linda Collins, who was a partner in Village Optician in Pelham and now works out of Raymond Opticians in New Rochelle. ''It's nice, but it's not your community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hickey has also moved, to New Rochelle. He said that putting his son through college with no income and giant loans was particularly challenging, but that he was guardedly optimistic about Rangoli's new site.</p>
        <p>''It's an up-and-coming town and we've got a beautiful restaurant,'' he said. ''But we have to prove ourselves all over again.''</p>
        <p>UPDATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
