<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First You Cry, Of Course, but Illness Also Has an Upside</title>
    <meta content="08wcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/yourmoney/08wcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="OFFICE SPACE: LIFE'S WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Life's Work</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First You Cry, Of Course, but Illness Also Has an Upside</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">First You Cry, of Course, but Illness Also Has an Upside</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA BELKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belkin, Lisa</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BETTY ROLLIN, a best-selling author and a former NBC News correspondent, woke up one morning and realized that she was happy. Not an unusual realization for a woman with a good marriage, a good job and good health.</p>
        <p>What was unusual, as she tells it, was the root of her happiness: two bouts with breast cancer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How coping with adversity can lead to happiness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BETTY ROLLIN, a best-selling author and a former NBC News correspondent, woke up one morning and realized that she was happy. Not an unusual realization for a woman with a good marriage, a good job and good health.</p>
        <p>What was unusual, as she tells it, was the root of her happiness: two bouts with breast cancer.</p>
        <p>''Cancer was the cause of all the good things in my life,'' she says. ''It was the reason why everything else -- really, everything else -- was so good.''</p>
        <p>It was, for instance, the reason she ended her first marriage and fell for her second husband, a man whose quiet kindness she says she never would have appreciated in her B.C. (before cancer) days.</p>
        <p>''Cancer improved my taste in men,'' she writes in her new book ''Here's the Bright Side  Of Failure, Fear, Cancer, Divorce and Other Bum Raps'' (Random House) to be in stores on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The hard-won happiness that Ms. Rollin writes about comes not only after cancer, but after battles with all kinds of adversity. And adversity changes your outlook not only on love, but also on work.</p>
        <p>Scientists call it ''paradoxical growth.'' They found it while looking for its opposite: depression and downward spirals in women who have been treated for breast cancer. What their data showed instead was that a striking percentage of the subjects stressed the good that had come from their disease.</p>
        <p>Studies of other unfortunate people -- those who have lost spouses, who lived through natural disasters, who have suffered job loss -- found the same effect.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rollin sums up the phenomenon this way: ''Having coped, you now know, as you didn't before, that you can Do It.'' And as thrilled as she is by the changes in her love life, she is equally giddy about what she says cancer did to her professional life.</p>
        <p>For starters, it gave her the courage to take chances. She was a correspondent at NBC when she had the first of two mastectomies. (The first was 30 years ago, the second nine years later.) What she really wanted to do, though, was write, and her first book, ''First, You Cry'' was groundbreaking in that it talked openly about a disease that was not commonly discussed in 1975.</p>
        <p>A subsequent book, ''Last Wish,'' in 1985, about her reaction to her ill and elderly mother's wish to commit suicide, would also never have come to be had her own illness not emboldened her, she says.</p>
        <p>''I knew that if I wrote a book about it, I could be letting myself and my husband in for a heap of trouble,'' she writes in her new book, given the legal implications of suicide. But she decided to go ahead, she writes, because she ''was still afraid of the cancer.'' (No legal trouble ensued.)</p>
        <p>She adds: ''I remember thinking: What if it's not done with me? What if I have another recurrence and die soon? I'll be mad at myself for not writing this book.''</p>
        <p>A corollary of taking chances, she says, is a reordering of priorities, a determination to act on what most of us merely say: that there are more important things in life than work. It was that realization, she says, that made it easy for her to leave her job at NBC a few years ago and join ''Religion &amp; Ethics Newsweekly'' on PBS even though it was, she says, a step off the fast track.</p>
        <p>''I have an nth of the audience at PBS that I had at NBC, and I couldn't be happier because I love every minute of what I do,'' she says. ''Cancer taught me that.''</p>
        <p>SHE says that it also taught her to have fun. Even at -- especially at -- work. It is a word that peppers her conversation: ''I look at my producer all the time and say, 'Isn't this fun!' and she says, 'Well, yes, I guess it is.' She doesn't get it the way I do. I didn't used to get it. I don't remember, before cancer, ever thinking, 'Is this fun?' when making choices about work. I remember asking 'Where will this get me?' or 'What do my bosses think?' but now I want it to be fun.''</p>
        <p>It is fear, she says, that drives the fun, as surely as it drove her decision to write ''Last Wish.'' A fear that life is short and that there might not be time to fit the postponed plans.</p>
        <p>It is a fear underlined recently by the news about Elizabeth Edwards and Tony Snow, both of whom have described earlier fights with cancer as enriching their lives, and both of whom are now being treated for a recurrence.</p>
        <p>''This thing could come back,'' Ms. Rollin says.</p>
        <p>''If it does come back I don't want it to find me slogging away to climb a work ladder. I want it to find me having a good time.''</p>
        <p>OFFICE SPACE: LIFE'S WORK This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. E-mail: Belkin@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. E-mail: Belkin@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
