<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A NIGHT OUT WITH -- Cara Buono; Mrs. Wiseguy</title>
    <meta content="08nite" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/fashion/08nite.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="A Night Out With Cara Bruono"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/A Night Out With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFDB173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A NIGHT OUT WITH -- Cara Buono; Mrs. Wiseguy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mrs. Wiseguy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS VINCIGUERRA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vinciguerra, Thomas</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CARA BUONO, a k a Kelli Moltisanti in ''The Sopranos,'' has yet to get whacked. But landing the part did entail a bloodbath of sorts.</p>
        <p>''It was not a good time in my life,'' Ms. Buono said over dinner at A Voce, just off Madison Square Park. ''I had a long-term relationship end. I was coming home from the audition on the train, and a bunch of kids came by and stepped on these ketchup packets on the platform, and they squirted all over me. I said, 'Something's got to give.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The actress plays the wife of the wiseguy Christopher Moltisanti on “The Sopranos,” which is in its last season on HBO.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CARA BUONO, a k a Kelli Moltisanti in ''The Sopranos,'' has yet to get whacked. But landing the part did entail a bloodbath of sorts.</p>
        <p>''It was not a good time in my life,'' Ms. Buono said over dinner at A Voce, just off Madison Square Park. ''I had a long-term relationship end. I was coming home from the audition on the train, and a bunch of kids came by and stepped on these ketchup packets on the platform, and they squirted all over me. I said, 'Something's got to give.' ''</p>
        <p>On the long-running HBO series, whose last season begins tonight, Ms. Buono plays the wife of the wiseguy Christopher Moltisanti. Fictionally, at least, cozying up to Christopher is a perilous prospect. A previous inamorata, Adriana La Cerva, was bumped off for ratting to the feds.</p>
        <p>Surrounded by Italian dishes and old friends -- Jessica Queller, a television writer; Gillian Zoe Segal, a photographer; and Jonathan Marc Sherman, a playwright -- Ms. Buono recounted that she was more concerned with her pronunciation than with being shot.</p>
        <p>''I used this heavy Jersey accent,'' she said, sampling shrimp ravioli, veal tortellini and grilled pork tenderloin. ''But the producers wanted me to moderate between 'CHRIS-tuh-fuh' and 'Christopher.' That was the note I got.''</p>
        <p>She laughed and added, ''I want to do a character in a one-woman show who's a yoga teacher from the Bronx. I could do the best accent: 'Raise yaw ahms up! Reach faw da sky!' ''</p>
        <p>The dark-eyed Ms. Buono, who calls to mind a young Isabella Rossellini, is a Bronx native herself. Her career began at age 12, when she appeared in Harvey Fierstein's play ''Spookhouse,'' and she worked her way through Columbia in three years with a double major in English and political science. When a registrar's mix-up forced one of her professors to teach a class in a hallway, she complained to her adviser, who happened to be the provost.</p>
        <p>''I said to myself: 'This class is costing me $275 an hour. I want a classroom.' The next day I had one.''</p>
        <p>''You didn't even have to call in the goombahs,'' Ms. Segal said.</p>
        <p>''The Sopranos'' offers a happy intersection between two of Ms. Buono's passions, acting and food. When she made her debut as a recurring character in the series in May, she had a screening party for about 15 friends. The fare was homemade lasagna and angel-hair pasta with walnut sauce. The pasta dish was not, she insisted, a homage to Paulie Walnuts, played by Tony Sirico.</p>
        <p>''I love to cook,'' she said. ''I'd hoped by now I'd have a big loft. I have this fantasy that between 12 and 4, if you're in New York, it's known that I'll be serving a meal and you can just show up. You can watch TV, hang out, nap. Once a month. Wouldn't that be nice?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Buono addressed the last of fennel-glazed duck with spicy chard, Vidalia onion and grape mostarda. ''I make the best eggplant parmigiana,'' she declared. ''Except maybe my mother. The way she makes it is delicious.'' Leaning forward, she intoned, ''If I told you how, I'd have to kill you.''</p>
        <p>Bada bing!</p>
        <p>Dessert was procured at Veniero's, the landmark East Village Italian bakery. Amid the crush of a Lenten Friday crowd, Ms. Buono indicated her selections from the glass display case, and a counterman quickly filled a box with éclairs, zeppole, fruit-topped custard tarts and other miniature pastries.</p>
        <p>''They have the best cheesecake in the city,'' Ms. Buono said. ''And they ship everywhere.''</p>
        <p>''Cara, did you get chocolate-chip cannolis?'' Ms. Queller asked.</p>
        <p>Ms. Buono was reassuring. ''I got what you need,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A Night Out With Cara Bruono</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
