<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Get Out. No, Wait, Come Back!</title>
    <meta content="08books" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/fashion/08books.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838775"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF STYLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0D9173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Get Out. No, Wait, Come Back!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Get Out. No, Wait, Come Back!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIESL SCHILLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schillinger, Liesl</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walking on Eggshells  Navigating the Delicate Relationship Between Adult Children and Parents.  By Jane Isay.  256 pp., Flying Dolphin Press.  $23.95.</p>
        <p>The Empty Nest  31 Parents Tell the Truth About Relationships, Love, and Freedom After the Kids Fly the Coop.  Edited by Karen Stabiner.  320 pp., Voice (a Hyperion imprint).  $23.95.</p>
        <p>WE could perhaps learn something from the female leatherback turtle. She lays her clutch of eggs then departs forever, never to discover how her progeny fared for the rest of her long life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>WALKING ON EGGSHELLS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Walking on Eggshells  Navigating the Delicate Relationship Between Adult Children and Parents.  By Jane Isay.  256 pp., Flying Dolphin Press.  $23.95.</p>
        <p>The Empty Nest  31 Parents Tell the Truth About Relationships, Love, and Freedom After the Kids Fly the Coop.  Edited by Karen Stabiner.  320 pp., Voice (a Hyperion imprint).  $23.95.</p>
        <p>WE could perhaps learn something from the female leatherback turtle. She lays her clutch of eggs then departs forever, never to discover how her progeny fared for the rest of her long life.</p>
        <p>Would the hatchlings have led happier lives with her interference? She will never know.</p>
        <p>Human parents, of course, lack the detachment of the turtle, these days more than ever it seems, while adult children find it difficult, sometimes impossible, to emotionally separate from their parents. That means you could easily find yourself coaching your 40-year-old daughter through her first pregnancy while fending off unsolicited baby-shower ideas from your 85-year-old mother.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is a mercy that, unlike the leatherback turtle, humans don't live to be 150.</p>
        <p>For ''Walking on Eggshells,'' a quietly groundbreaking exploration of the ties between adult children and their parents, Jane Isay, the editor and writer, spoke with scores of Americans about complicated generational dynamics. ''I wanted to get a fix on those decades between the time the kids leave home and the time when we really need their help,'' she says.</p>
        <p>Ms. Isay finds a boundary-bashing mother-in-law who called her son's wife ''fatty'' during her pregnancy; a nonagenarian who would phone her daughter (herself a grandmother) to nag her about her hairstyle; and a controlling mother who told her grown son what to wear: ''But Mom, I'm 60 years old,'' he protests. ''You're still my son,'' she retorts.</p>
        <p>Ms. Isay lays down a long overdue 11th commandment: ''Thou shalt not give your grown children advice.'' And yet, she doesn't pretend that adult children are all right on their own. They often seek substantial economic support and emotional guidance from their parents well into their 30s (and beyond), she points out.</p>
        <p>''Today, many members of the baby-boom generation are better off than their children, and acts of generosity are common,'' Ms. Isay writes.</p>
        <p>With generosity comes strings. Parents can become resentful of repeated demands for cash; children can bite the hand that feeds.</p>
        <p>One mother, a free spirit at 67 who lives with her second husband on a houseboat, decided early on that adult children should not be dependent on their parents. She explained: ''They are 20, 30, 40, and they're adults, and they need to stand on their own. In the old days, you would probably be dead. You wouldn't be there for them to count on you. I think that's how it should be.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Isay's portraits have nuance and pathos, and there is much to learn from them, including the good news that, ''Since adulthood lasts for decades, we have plenty of time to adjust and to get it right.''</p>
        <p>THAT unromanticized wisdom should console the authors of ''The Empty Nest,'' a book of essays by parents who (mostly) mourn the departure of their young, even as they take guilty pleasure in being able (at last) to buy a red sports car, or walk around the living room naked.</p>
        <p>Harvey Molotch, whose wife died when his children were 2 and 5, remembers the family's glory days when as an exhausted but fulfilled single father he would plan the weekly family grocery-shopping expedition. ''I used to tell people that if my life were a soap opera, it would be 'Search for a Nap,' '' he recalls.</p>
        <p>Recently, with his son at college and his daughter married, he automatically headed toward the children's food aisle before stopping himself.</p>
        <p>''The grocery-shopping cart was where my rubber hit the road, the place where I realized that life had changed,'' he writes. ''Which aisles do I now walk? What jars do I check out?'' It occurred to him, he writes, that ''I didn't even have to be there. I felt the luxury of ennui.''</p>
        <p>In the first chapter, ''Proof of Love,'' Karen Stabiner, the book's editor, anticipates the day next fall when she will load up a suitcase and take her daughter to college. ''How can you pack an entire life into a finite space?'' she wonders.</p>
        <p>Ms. Isay's book shows that you can't and that you don't have to, and so do the personal stories Ms. Stabiner has assembled in what probably is an exercise in creative catharsis.</p>
        <p>In one chapter, an eerily far-seeing 7-year-old boy asks his mother, ''Why do you take such good care of me when you know I am going to leave you someday?'' The day he left for college, the boy's mother tearfully told a group of women that she was thinking of writing a book about ''the end of motherhood.'' An older woman reassured her, ''Motherhood never ends.''</p>
        <p>And as Ellen Goodman, a Pulitzer-winning columnist, notes in another chapter, neither does grandmotherhood. Ms. Goodman, the mother of a daughter and a stepdaughter, and grandmother of two, writes, ''If there were any more proof needed that care giving does not end, that family continues, it is grandchildren.''</p>
        <p>She jokes, ''What empty nest?''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF STYLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
