<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newcomers Put Ryder Experience To Good Use</title>
    <meta content="08augusta" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/golf/08augusta.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Henry, J J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newcomers Put Ryder Experience To Good Use</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Newcomers Put Ryder Experience to Good Use</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the days before the United States Ryder Cup team went to Ireland last September, Tiger Woods took the team's four rookies to a steakhouse for dinner. The four -- Brett Wetterich, Vaughn Taylor, Zach Johnson and J. J. Henry -- had an audience with Woods, the top player in golf.</p>
        <p>The same four players also made it to the weekend at the 71st Masters at Augusta National Golf Club, and two of them -- Taylor and Johnson -- are in contention to win a green jacket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though the United States Ryder Cup team played poorly in Ireland, the experience on foreign soil for four rookies might aid one of the players in the pursuit of a green jacket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the days before the United States Ryder Cup team went to Ireland last September, Tiger Woods took the team's four rookies to a steakhouse for dinner. The four -- Brett Wetterich, Vaughn Taylor, Zach Johnson and J. J. Henry -- had an audience with Woods, the top player in golf.</p>
        <p>The same four players also made it to the weekend at the 71st Masters at Augusta National Golf Club, and two of them -- Taylor and Johnson -- are in contention to win a green jacket.</p>
        <p>''I was thinking about that,'' said Taylor, an Augusta native who trailed the lead of Stuart Appleby by two strokes through 54 holes. ''I think we kind of got a bit of a hard rap for having four no-name rookies on the team. I feel like we all have something to prove somewhat. It's pretty neat to see our names up there.''</p>
        <p>Taylor shot a five-over-par 77 on Saturday and Johnson carded a four-over-par 76 to also trail Appleby by two shots.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying not to get emotional,'' Johnson said. ''You just have to be patient.''</p>
        <p>Though the United States Ryder Cup team played poorly in Ireland, losing, 181/2 to 91/2, the four rookies did not cost the Americans the trophy. (Of the four, only Wetterich went without at least half a point during the matches.)</p>
        <p>In the end, the experience on foreign soil against a strong opponent might aid one of the players in the pursuit of a green jacket.</p>
        <p>''The Ryder Cup was big-time pressure,'' Taylor said Friday. ''We all felt it and we all dealt with it. It's helped us. It's helped me every week I tee it up. It especially helps here in a major where the pressure is big time.''</p>
        <p>Wetterich said: ''There's definitely a lot more people at the Ryder Cup. You had 40,000 or 50,000 people on four holes. I think it's a different kind of pressure as opposed to a major.''</p>
        <p>Of the four players, Wetterich held up the strongest through two rounds at Augusta before ballooning to an 83 in the cold, windy conditions of the third round. Still, he is becoming a familiar name on PGA Tour leader boards.</p>
        <p>All but unknown last year, Wetterich won the Byron Nelson Championship in what has been a long road in golf that included mini-tours and a stop at Wallace State Community College in Alabama.</p>
        <p>''Took me a while to progress,'' he said. ''Every year I got a little better and better. Here I am now.''</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Wetterich nearly caught Woods in the final round of the CA Championship before falling two strokes short.</p>
        <p>Taylor has appeared comfortable in contention in front of fans in his hometown. Twenty years ago, another Augusta native, Larry Mize, shocked Greg Norman in a playoff by holing a 140-foot chip for birdie on the 11th hole to win the Masters in a playoff.</p>
        <p>Taylor was in the gallery, an 11-year-old just beginning to dream about a life in golf.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, I can pull something off special,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Though he was paired in the first two rounds with the 71-year-old Gary Player -- a chatty and amiable golfer -- Taylor said he mostly kept to himself during the competition.</p>
        <p>But on the 18th hole Friday, after Taylor finished with a bogey, Player pulled him aside and placed a hand on his back.</p>
        <p>''He said that I was a great player and that I could win this thing this week,'' Taylor said. ''He said, 'Just go out there and play to win and be tough and stay focused.' Those are very kind words. It puts a smile on my face to hear him say those things.''</p>
        <p>With Player and Woods, who have 21 major championships between them, the four Ryder Cup rookies have heard plenty of advice in recent months.</p>
        <p>At the Masters, they are trying to learn how to use it.</p>
        <p>ROUND FOR THE RECORD BOOKS -- The third-round scoring average of 77.35 was the fifth-highest in the history of the tournament. It was the third-highest average in the third round.</p>
        <p>The highest scoring average ever recorded at the Masters was 78.596, set in 1936.</p>
        <p>Many players called the speedy course conditions difficult but fair.</p>
        <p>''The course setup, I don't think you can really argue with where they put the flags,'' said Justin Rose, who trailed Appleby by a shot in his bid to win his first major. ''I wasn't out there on the course thinking, 'That's ridiculous.' It was just tough.''</p>
        <p>Phil Mickelson, four shots back, added: ''Tough as I've seen. It wasn't as hard as it could have been because they put water on the greens. As tough as it is, I didn't think it was unfair by any means. You have to fight on every hole to make par here.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
