<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOUSING SLUMP PINCHES STATES IN POCKETBOOK</title>
    <meta content="08housing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/us/08housing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070411T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Equity Loans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arizona</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nevada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DC143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOUSING SLUMP PINCHES STATES IN POCKETBOOK</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Housing Slump Pinches States in Pocketbook</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH; Terry Aguayo contributed reporting from Miami, and David Leonhardt from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, April 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State tax revenues around country are growing more slowly this year because of housing market slowdown; Florida, New Jersey and California all face revenue shortfalls; new home sales nationally fell in February to their lowest rate in seven years; homeowners who recently tapped into plentiful home equity are cutting back on borrowing and purchases of big-ticket items; Arizona, California, Nevada and Florida are expected to suffer disproportionately; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State tax revenues around the country are growing far more slowly this year and in some cases falling below projections, a result of the housing market slowdown that has curbed voracious spending on real estate, building materials, furniture and other items.</p>
        <p>Nowhere is the downturn more apparent than in Florida, where tax revenue is projected to drop this year for the first time since the energy crisis of the 1970s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>State tax revenues are growing more slowly this year and in some cases falling below projections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State tax revenues around the country are growing far more slowly this year and in some cases falling below projections, a result of the housing market slowdown that has curbed voracious spending on real estate, building materials, furniture and other items.</p>
        <p>Nowhere is the downturn more apparent than in Florida, where tax revenue is projected to drop this year for the first time since the energy crisis of the 1970s.</p>
        <p>But other states, especially those where housing prices soared in recent years, are also seeing their collections slow, especially in the sales and real estate transfer tax categories. While the economy remains generally strong and it is too early to predict whether the housing slump will have long-term effects, some states will have to adjust their wish lists.</p>
        <p>For example, New Jersey could face a $2.5 billion shortfall by mid-2008, Gov. Jon S. Corzine has said, and may lease its turnpike or its lottery to a private company to raise money. In California, where income tax receipts in January were $1 billion less than forecast, a nonpartisan legislative analyst has urged budget cuts and warned that the state could have about $2 billion less in revenue this year and next than Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger has projected.</p>
        <p>''It's the year of the housing hangover,'' said Sean M. Snaith, director of the Institute for Economic Competitiveness at the University of Central Florida.</p>
        <p>New home sales nationally fell in February to the lowest rate in seven years, and homeowners who tapped into plentiful home equity and spent extravagantly during the real estate boom have started to cut back.</p>
        <p>Those events not only threaten revenue streams for things like building materials and labor, but also affect spending on big-ticket items like cars and furniture, which many homeowners financed with home equity lines of credit.</p>
        <p>Chris McCarty, survey research director at the Bureau of Economic and Business Research at the University of Florida, said it would be foolish to ''underestimate the effect that the inability to extract equity from homes is going to have.''</p>
        <p>In one hint of how much Floridians were relying on property wealth during the real estate boom, 16 percent of new car purchases here were being made with home equity loans in 2006, compared with 7 percent nationally, according to CNW Marketing Research, an automotive research firm in Bandon, Ore. In California, the percentage was even higher -- about 30 percent, said Art Spinella, the firm's president.</p>
        <p>During the last few years, families in much of the country have relied on the cash from mortgage refinancing, made possible by rising house values, low interest rates and a bevy of creative new loans, to make up for stagnant wages. From 2001 to 2005, even as the economy was growing at a healthy clip over all, the pay of most workers failed to keep pace with inflation. Now the housing slowdown is making it more difficult to take equity out of a house, and an improved job market is finally causing wages to rise.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. McCarty said consumer confidence in Florida dropped markedly last month, especially willingness to buy expensive items.</p>
        <p>Some budget watchers say that Florida, whose housing boom was prolonged and intensified by the rebuilding frenzy after a series of hurricanes, could be a warning beacon for other states anticipating housing-related economic woes. Last spring, 9 of the 20 metropolitan areas that saw the sharpest home price appreciation were in Florida, according to the Office of Federal Housing Enterprise Oversight. Many areas of the state now have plummeting home values.</p>
        <p>Arizona, California, Florida and Nevada, the chief beneficiaries of the housing rush, are also expected to suffer disproportionately from the slump. From late 2005 to late 2006, existing home sales fell by 21 percent in California, 27 percent in Arizona, 31 percent in Florida and 36 percent in Nevada, the steepest drop in the nation.</p>
        <p>Maryland's real estate transfer tax revenue has tumbled by 22 percent this fiscal year, suggesting that fewer homes are being sold, prices have fallen or both. Connecticut's real estate transfer tax revenue, which state budget analysts predicted would fall by 3.6 percent, is down by 13.3 percent so far.</p>
        <p>Some states have defied the trend, chiefly among them New York, where the housing market has been bolstered by sales in Manhattan. The prices and number of apartments selling in Manhattan rose in the first three months of this year, according to data released last week by several of New York City's largest real estate brokerages.</p>
        <p>Healthy reserves built up over the last few years and stable economic conditions outside the housing sector could cushion the blow for many states, at least for now.</p>
        <p>''The tendency is for people to say, 'Wow, things look pretty good, except for housing,' '' said Richard Nathan, co-director of the Nelson A. Rockefeller Institute of Government in Albany. ''But that is a very big exception, because it has a large impact on people's perceptions of what they feel their asset capability is.''</p>
        <p>Some economists fear the situation will worsen as credit standards tighten and more recipients of subprime loans -- typically people with bad credit, who obtained such loans easily during the housing boom -- default on their payments.</p>
        <p>But others expect the revenue lag to last two years at most, because with the exception of industrial Midwestern states like Michigan and Ohio, the economy remains relatively healthy.</p>
        <p>''Real estate is going to be a drag on the rest of the economy,'' said Ryan Ratcliff, an economist for the Anderson Forecast at the University of California, Los Angeles, referring to California's situation. ''But previous recessions have always had construction plus something else combining to create job loss. Without a second source of weakness, we're predicting sluggishness, but not a recession.''</p>
        <p>Alan Greenspan, the former Federal Reserve chairman who has expressed worries about the housing market, has said he believes there is a one-in-three chance the economy will slip into recession in 2007.</p>
        <p>Even without a recession, a growing national movement to reduce local property taxes could leave local governments short of the amount they need to provide services at a time when home values are falling, some economists said.</p>
        <p>Property tax relief is the Florida Legislature's top priority this spring. And a new package of bills in New Jersey, if approved, would give a tax credit of up to 20 percent to homeowners and cap annual local tax increases at 4 percent -- despite the predicted deficit.</p>
        <p>''People are reacting to the large increases in assessments that took place over the past few years and looking to cut property taxes,'' wrote Iris J. Lav, deputy director of the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, a liberal research and advocacy organization. ''If assessments stagnate or decline, however, the cuts could seriously overreach.''</p>
        <p>Gov. Charlie Crist of Florida is among officials across the country who dismiss that notion, saying that reducing property taxes would fatten consumers' wallets and dissuade them from leaving the state.</p>
        <p>Census data show that fewer people than usual moved into Florida last year. And an abrupt halt in the growth of public school enrollment this year suggests that families are leaving. Despite dropping prices, communities like Naples, Miami and Sarasota still have some of the most overvalued real estate in the nation, according to Global Insight, a research firm in Waltham, Mass.</p>
        <p>''People are packing up the equity and moving to North Carolina and Tennessee,'' Mr. Snaith said.</p>
        <p>Georganna Meyer, chief economist for the Arizona Department of Revenue, said both sales and income tax receipts had slowed there, in part because so many people who jumped into the real estate business during the boom are now earning less. ''I've heard stories about real estate broker income going up 50 percent year after year,'' she said. ''So a large part of why the income tax is not what it used to be is related to the real estate market tightening, no doubt.''</p>
        <p>It is still too early to know how most states' fiscal years will end -- this month's income tax filings will be crucial. But Florida, which does not have an income tax, has $303 million less than anticipated for its $70 billion budget, thanks to slowing sales tax and real estate transfer tax collections. Florida also expects to have $653 million less than anticipated in 2007-08, but Amy Baker, coordinator of the Office of Economic and Demographic Research at the State Legislature, said that was not a sign of long-term trouble.</p>
        <p>''We saw double-digit price appreciation for several years in a row, so the atmosphere here was very charged,'' Ms. Baker said, adding that the state's housing market should bottom out by summer and pick up again by January.</p>
        <p>''We are just returning to normal levels of growth,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 11, 2007, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, a front-page article on Sunday about the housing slump's effect on state tax revenues misstated the status of a tax credit and local tax cap in New Jersey in some copies. The legislation has been signed into law, it is not awaiting approval.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 11, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a front-page article on Sunday about the housing slump's effect on state tax revenues misstated the status of a tax credit and local tax cap in New Jersey in some copies. The legislation has been signed into law, it is not awaiting approval.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
