<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Instant Messages</title>
    <meta content="Heller.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/Heller.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="VISUALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Instant Messages</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Instant Messages</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Steven Heller</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heller, Steven</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the best-kept secrets of American visual culture are those plastic-lettered, brightly illuminated religious message boards that beseech all to ''Repent Now,'' ''Be Saved'' or ''Make Us Instruments of Your Peace and Love.'' Though in plain sight, they are virtually invisible, and like those ubiquitous convenience store displays announcing gas or egg prices, the average religious signboard offers the essentials -- usually times and dates for worship or a spiritual bromide. But in CHURCH SIGNS ACROSS AMERICA (Overlook, $19.95), the photographers Steve Paulson and Pam Paulson have found and documented the uncommon poetry and sly wit used to rouse the flock, and the book is curiously inspirational.</p>
        <p>Although their photographs are not especially heavenly -- each page features a bland view of a church or chapel on top and its respective sign below -- the sheer act of amassing these images (more than 300) is impressive. Seen together they reveal how evocations of faith are communicated at a grass-roots level, and the result is not always pretty. A majority of church logos in these photos resemble strip-mall store signs, suggesting that sophisticated typography and design are less important to spreading the Gospel than the unadorned Word itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Billboards are designed to be eye-catching spectacles, not works of street art; subtlety is a bad idea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among the best-kept secrets of American visual culture are those plastic-lettered, brightly illuminated religious message boards that beseech all to ''Repent Now,'' ''Be Saved'' or ''Make Us Instruments of Your Peace and Love.'' Though in plain sight, they are virtually invisible, and like those ubiquitous convenience store displays announcing gas or egg prices, the average religious signboard offers the essentials -- usually times and dates for worship or a spiritual bromide. But in CHURCH SIGNS ACROSS AMERICA (Overlook, $19.95), the photographers Steve Paulson and Pam Paulson have found and documented the uncommon poetry and sly wit used to rouse the flock, and the book is curiously inspirational.</p>
        <p>Although their photographs are not especially heavenly -- each page features a bland view of a church or chapel on top and its respective sign below -- the sheer act of amassing these images (more than 300) is impressive. Seen together they reveal how evocations of faith are communicated at a grass-roots level, and the result is not always pretty. A majority of church logos in these photos resemble strip-mall store signs, suggesting that sophisticated typography and design are less important to spreading the Gospel than the unadorned Word itself.</p>
        <p>Speaking of words, so taken were the photographers with what they found that they did not include even a brief contextual introduction, relying on the worship schedules and religious slogans (and a caption indicating where the photos were taken) for the only text. Most of the slogans are decidedly clever -- ''Free Trip to Heaven, Details Inside,'' at the Ascension Lutheran Church in Kansas City, Mo., appears on the cover, though that's not even the best. Here's a sampling: ''Rapture, the Only Way to Fly,'' at the Venice Baptist Church in Los Angeles; ''You've Seen the Movie, Now Come Read the Book,'' at the Central Parkway Baptist Church in Orlando, Fla.; ''The Easter Bunny Didn't Rise From the Dead,'' at the Cypress Lake Baptist Church in Fort Myers, Fla.; and ''Swallow Your Pride. It Contains No Calories,'' at the Bridgeton Bible Church in Bridgeton, Mo. But the hippest, at the Montgomery Place Church of God in Albuquerque, is ''Jesus Is the Rock That Doesn't Roll.''</p>
        <p>Not all are this witty, but even the somber ones, like ''Exposure to the Son May Prevent Burning,'' ''We Are Too Blessed to Be Depressed'' and ''Pray Until Something Happens,'' provoke a smile. Nor must one be a true believer to savor them. The agnostic who merely appreciates the art of snappy advertising copy will know exactly how difficult it is to write something as effective as the motto for the Christian Assembly Ministries in Stewartsville, N.J.: ''Give Your Troubles to God. He's Up All Night Anyway.''</p>
        <p>Most commercial billboards aspire to the same heights -- when it comes to sloganeering, anyway -- attained by these religious signs. Yet they differ in one significant way: while church signs have no discernible design style (or guile), advertising billboards are overloaded with it. In the last 100 years this singularly American outdoor advertising genre -- attacked by beautification and environmental advocates -- has evolved from innocent pictorialism, built on idealized tableaus and famous trade characters, to an aggressive mélange of word and image strategically situated to pique desire and stimulate consumption. In GREAT AMERICAN BILLBOARDS: 100 Years of History by the Side of the Road (Ten Speed, paper, $19.95), Fred E. Basten, who has worked in advertising, surveys a century of sublime, subliminal, though mostly ham-handed billboards, with an emphasis on commercial ostentation rather than aesthetic quality.</p>
        <p>Many of the examples are inventive but visually inelegant -- like one advertising the 1976 film ''Ode to Billy Joe,'' with a huge 3-D version of the Tallahatchie Bridge, over which Billy Joe McAllister threw his mysterious bundle in the Bobbie Gentry song. A 1959 billboard for Wil Wright's ice-cream parlor also relies on monumental 3-D, with a reproduction of the shop jutting impressively from the sign like a diorama. It doesn't have a hint of nuance, but it succeeds.</p>
        <p>Billboards are designed not as works of street art but as eye-catching spectacles (the kinetic, illuminated ones in Times Square are known in the trade as ''spectaculars''). Since they are meant to grab attention in as much time as it takes passengers in a car or pedestrians on the street to glimpse the message, subtlety would be counterproductive. So designers trust bold styles to get their point across -- from the dynamic simplicity of the 1963 billboard ''The Birds Is Coming,'' for Alfred Hitchcock's classic film, showing Hitch bemusedly pointing at a huge dive-bombing crow, to the vibrant and complex psychedelic board for the Jimi Hendrix album ''Axis: Bold as Love,'' which hung over the Sunset Strip in 1968.</p>
        <p>This is not the first chronicle of American billboards. A similarly titled book -- ''The American Billboard: 100 Years,'' written by James Howard Fraser and published in 1991 -- was much better designed and annotated. But Basten's horizontal paperback has some fine additions. Unfortunately, he credits few of the designers, copywriters or art directors for their accomplishments. It's a shame, for instance, that Otis Shepard, famous for his 1930s Wrigley's gum billboards and subway car posters, goes unacknowledged for the example reproduced here. Basten does give credit for a 1939 New York World's Fair poster, but it's incorrect: attributed here to Nembhard N. Culin (who designed a different poster for the same fair), it was actually created by Joseph Binder. Such is the ephemeral nature of commercial art that it is often considered too insignificant for its makers to receive just recognition.</p>
        <p>There is no question who deserves the credit for all the images published in the newspaper The Black Panther during the late 1960s and early 70s. He is Emory Douglas, not a household name today, though his militant graphic art influenced many polemical illustrators and cartoonists working at the time for left-wing underground newspapers. But since the Black Panthers were vilified and their movement came to a dispiriting end, with many of its leaders imprisoned or killed, the newspaper to which Douglas gave a distinct visual identity has been all but forgotten. In BLACK PANTHER: The Revolutionary Art of Emory Douglas (Rizzoli, cloth, $50; paper, $35) -- edited and with an introduction by Sam Durant, a Los Angeles artist, and including essays by Danny Glover, Bobby Seale, Amiri Baraka, Kathleen Cleaver and others -- these lost visual artifacts are faithfully preserved and contextualized. Douglas finally gets his due.</p>
        <p>A majority of '60s underground newspapers were founded as clarions of sex, drugs and rock 'n' roll -- and most were run by white middle-class kids -- but The Black Panther, founded by Bobby Seale, was a radical alternative at a time when the mainstream media virtually ignored the black community unless they were reporting on riots and crime. The publication also propagated a real and symbolic revolution, visualized by Douglas (as minister of culture for the Black Panther Party) through emblematic graphics. He designed the layouts for the paper and built its graphic imprimatur through stark black-and-white line drawings and woodcuts. Reminiscent of turn-of-the-century political art in such oppositional satiric magazines as Simplicissimus in Germany and L'Assiette au Beurre in France, his art made armed revolutionaries into heroes even as the police (mostly depicted as pigs) and national leaders, especially President Nixon and Attorney General John Mitchell (shown as rats), were turned into demons. As with Chinese Cultural Revolution posters from the same era, Douglas also appended strident slogans to the images, like ''We will not hesitate to either kill or die for our freedom'' and ''You can murder a revolutionary but you can't murder revolution.''</p>
        <p>Handsomely designed by Lorraine Wild and Stuart Smith, the book is printed on an uncoated paper stock that underscores the yellowing patina of newsprint and the immediacy of the original newspapers. Douglas's work, alternately angry and jubilant, yet always defiant, recalls a period before gangsta rap (which was influenced by the Panther aesthetic) became an acceptable and profitable commercial style. But Douglas's art was never brought into mainstream commerce the way hip-hop art and design were, so today it is as powerful as similar expressions by Goya, Daumier, George Grosz and other great political artists.</p>
        <p>One of England's foremost graphic designers, typographers and art directors, and co-founder of the international design firm Pentagram, Alan Fletcher, who died last September, took respites from corporate work by designing a few political posters but also painting, sculpturing and doodling for the pure fun of it. He made vibrant watercolor impressions of ideal sunsets and black-and-white sketches of intricate building facades and walls, as well as collages from common graphic art detritus. One of these, an acerbic series called ''Confrontations,'' featured directional arrows printed on shipping boxes cut out and recomposed to look as though they were attacking one another. Fletcher also took more than a dozen souvenir postcards with New York City vistas and burned or tore out the twin towers as a memorial. These and more than a score of other curious thematic groupings are collected in PICTURING AND POETING (Phaidon, $39.95), a scrap- and sketchbook of idiosyncratic visual ideas, punctuated by quotations and short passages about image making by Fletcher and others, ranging from Henri Matisse to Richard Dawkins.</p>
        <p>These days, publishing artists' and designers' sketchbooks is fairly common. Some are exact facsimiles of the real objects, like Leonardo's journals, simulating the effects of wear and age. Others, like this, are collections of artistic inspirations and insights organized according to an overarching editorial principle. While beginning work on this sequel to ''The Art of Looking Sideways'' (2001), a brick-size miscellany devoted to design thinking, and ''Beware Wet Paint'' (1996), a monograph covering more than 30 years of his career as a graphic designer, Fletcher learned he was dying of cancer. He suspected the book might be posthumously released, which indeed it was, and conceived it not as a last will and testament of his formal work but as a means for readers (mostly artists and designers, although his sense of visual humor will appeal to anyone) to see the commonplace as a wellspring of invention -- his prescription for triggering the creative process. One of the wittier sections, called ''Billet Doux'' -- ''a pseudo-scientific line of inquiry into the realm of graphic absurdity,'' he wrote -- consists of eight small scraps of notepaper on which he analyzes what his handwriting looks like when, among other things, (1) his eyes are closed; (2) he walks over a pavement of badly laid cement; and (3) the wheels of an airplane he is on hit the tarmac at Heathrow Airport.</p>
        <p>Sprinkled throughout are other mini-lessons in how to build on what one sees: a section called ''Streetscapes'' shows three pages of schematic abstract-looking lines that, in fact, are impressionistic maps of real streets and road signs in London, Locarno and Basel. He invites the viewer to decipher hieroglyphs that ''aren't vague marks but significant symbols ... a vocabulary which few comprehend except the bureaucrats who invented them.'' Fletcher had a knack for finding the poetry in pictures, and the pictures in poetry.</p>
        <p>VISUALS Steven Heller is the former art director of the Book Review. This is his first column on visual culture.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Steven Heller is the former art director of the Book Review. This is his first column on visual culture.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
