<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Chicken and the Egg Both Come First Here</title>
    <meta content="08wedineWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08wedine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eggs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pound Ridge (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">John Boy's Farm Market (Pound Ridge, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ubaldo, John L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Denitto, Emily</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Eggs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7D8163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Chicken and the Egg Both Come First Here</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Chicken and the Egg Both Come First Here</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EMILY DeNITTO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Denitto, Emily</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on John Boy's Farm Market in Pound Ridge, NY, which sells fresh eggs, and its owner, John Ubaldo; list; of other places to buy fresh eggs in Westchester County; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are lovely pale green eggs available at John Boy's Farm Market these days, but they have nothing to do with Easter. Instead, these eggs come naturally from the farm's Araucana chickens, one of four types that provide this Pound Ridge farm with its daily quota of fresh bounty.</p>
        <p>You probably bought a 99-cent carton of supermarket whites to dye for the holiday. But when it comes to eating, just-laid eggs from all-natural free-range local chickens are dramatically richer, lighter and more satisfying.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to eating, just-laid eggs from all-natural free-range local chickens are dramatically richer, lighter and more satisfying.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are lovely pale green eggs available at John Boy's Farm Market these days, but they have nothing to do with Easter. Instead, these eggs come naturally from the farm's Araucana chickens, one of four types that provide this Pound Ridge farm with its daily quota of fresh bounty.</p>
        <p>You probably bought a 99-cent carton of supermarket whites to dye for the holiday. But when it comes to eating, just-laid eggs from all-natural free-range local chickens are dramatically richer, lighter and more satisfying.</p>
        <p>They aren't easy to find. As recently as 15 years ago, Westchester still had an array of farms providing fresh eggs. Today, John Boy's -- a small operation discreetly housed in a residential area -- is the rare exception.</p>
        <p>Blue Hill at Stone Barns in Pocantico Hills sells about 4,000 eggs a week, harvested from their 800 chickens, for $3.50 a dozen, and the long line to buy them attests to their deliciousness.</p>
        <p>Others occasionally sell eggs as the byproduct of other activities. Teatown Lake Reservation in Ossining intermittently sells eggs for about $3 a dozen, but the main purpose of the chickens at its Cliffdale Farm is to provide educational programs for area elementary schools.</p>
        <p>Hemlock Hill Farm in Cortlandt Manor sells eggs periodically from the chickens it raises for slaughter -- also for $3 a dozen -- but most of their eggs come from a Pennsylvania farm.</p>
        <p>''It's just too much work,'' said Laura De Maria, co-owner of Hemlock. ''The collecting, washing and boxing is really time consuming, and it just doesn't make sense for us.''</p>
        <p>Thankfully, John L. Ubaldo, owner of John Boy's, is willing to take that time. In addition to the Araucanas, Mr. Ubaldo coaxes eggs from New Hampshire Reds, Rhode Island Reds and Black Australorps -- about 150 birds in all. A gaggle of honking geese and 20 sweet fluffy ducks provide eggs as well. Chicken eggs are $3.50 a dozen; duck, $5.50 a dozen; and goose eggs are $2 each.</p>
        <p>Farm fresh eggs look different from the supermarket variety. They won't all be the same size or shape and most will be brown (though the color is simply a result of the breed involved and doesn't affect taste, which mainly comes from the feed used and the way the chickens are raised).</p>
        <p>Because farm fresh eggs are higher in protein, the shells are thicker and sturdier -- if you're careful you can even peel the shell away while keeping the membrane intact. Crack them open and the contrast to mass-produced supermarket eggs is dramatic. The yolks are a rich and profound yellow that almost verges on orange, and the whites will have a hint of color as well.</p>
        <p>The taste is extraordinary: fuller, deeper, more eggy somehow. ''There's no comparison,'' said Scott Eckenrod, head chef at Cava restaurant in New Canaan, Conn., which uses John Boy's eggs exclusively. ''They're almost buttery. Everybody says how good breakfast tastes in Vermont. It isn't just the maple syrup. They mainly use farm fresh eggs up there.''</p>
        <p>A simple sign announcing ''Fresh Eggs'' is the only hint you'll have of the treasures waiting at John Boy's, which also offers smoked salmon, sturgeon and trout ($22, $26 and $9 a pound); Canadian and slab bacon ($6.50 and $5.50 a pound); a variety of sausages and more -- all made on the premises.</p>
        <p>The business is based in Mr. Ubaldo's home. But behind it, a four-acre spread unfolds with a large pond, an icehouse and the henhouses. Geese will honk and gather around Mr. Ubaldo, who gently swats at them good-naturedly in response. (Call ahead to order and to schedule pickups.)</p>
        <p>For Mr. Ubaldo, 41, the work is both the fulfillment of a childhood dream and a refuge from a nightmare. He grew up in the Pound Ridge house, attached to the geese his family kept for their own enjoyment. Indeed, he almost chose his college based on which one would allow the geese to come with him (he ended up at Skidmore, without the geese, even though Bennington would have accepted them). After school, he worked on Wall Street as a broker for 12 years, until Sept. 11, 2001.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't so much the day,'' he said, ''which was profoundly weird and horrifying, but the months afterward. I lost my brother-in-law, half the people I knew. We used to depend on the e-mail banter back and forth early in the morning to get us through the day. After 9/11, there was no e-mail because so many of those people were gone.''</p>
        <p>In early 2002, he moved back to the Pound Ridge house and started buying chickens. The work is methodical -- he rises to the sound of roosters and tends to the birds all day, feeding them and hand-washing their eggs in an organic solution. The cleansing, as well as keeping the henhouses immaculate, is to prevent salmonella or other bacteria from contaminating the eggs, Mr. Ubaldo said. ''Salmonella is born out of the conditions at many commercial factories,'' he added. ''So then they need to irradiate and pasteurize to keep the eggs safe.''</p>
        <p>His work is also healing. ''I feel like I'm just now coming out of a kind of fog,'' Mr. Ubaldo said. ''For years, I have relied on this work to keep me going.''</p>
        <p>In the process, he has been able to focus on what he finds meaningful. It has something to do with nurturing and the way pure, simple, unprocessed foods can satisfy the soul as well as the stomach.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ubaldo never uses medications, vaccinations or artificial feed ingredients for his birds. ''We just keep them really clean, let them run around,'' he said. ''I know it sounds funny, but they're happy. That's why the eggs taste so good.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Eckenrod of Cava said: ''I have so much respect for John. He could sell his land for real estate development and make a nice chunk of money. But instead he wants to be a farmer. It's hard and unforgiving work and you don't make much. But if you like what you do, you're blessed. John is one of those people.''</p>
        <p>Where to Buy Fresh Eggs</p>
        <p>JOHN BOY'S FARM MARKET  9 Pheasant Road  Pound Ridge  (914) 764-9208</p>
        <p>BLUE HILL AT STONE BARNS</p>
        <p>630 Bedford Road  Pocantico Hills  (914) 366-9600</p>
        <p>TEATOWN LAKE RESERVATION</p>
        <p>(limited quantities)  1600 Spring Valley Road  Ossining  (914) 762-2912</p>
        <p>HEMLOCK HILL FARM</p>
        <p>(limited quantities; others from a Pennsylvania farm)  Croton and Maple Avenues  Cortlandt Manor  (914) 737-2810</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
