<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In N.H.L., Fists Don't Lie In Fuss on Fighting</title>
    <meta content="08hockey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/hockey/08hockey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Campbell, Colin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E0DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In N.H.L., Fists Don't Lie In Fuss on Fighting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In N.H.L., Fists Don’t Lie in Fuss on Fighting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF Z. KLEIN and KARL-ERIC REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Jeff Z; Reif, Karl-Eric</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Colin Campbell merely suggested that a question be asked. But it sent a shock wave through hockey, igniting consternation, debate and outrage among fans and commentators.</p>
        <p>Campbell -- a former tough-guy defenseman, a former coach of the Rangers and now the N.H.L.'s director of hockey operations and chief of discipline -- was commenting on two recent fighting incidents that resulted in concussions when he said on March 22, ''It's probably time that the general managers ask the question, 'Where are we at with this?' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Colin Campbell’s suggestions that fighting might have outlived its usefulness, and the issues that inspired them, have stirred as much talk as the league’s intensely exciting playoff race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Colin Campbell merely suggested that a question be asked. But it sent a shock wave through hockey, igniting consternation, debate and outrage among fans and commentators.</p>
        <p>Campbell -- a former tough-guy defenseman, a former coach of the Rangers and now the N.H.L.'s director of hockey operations and chief of discipline -- was commenting on two recent fighting incidents that resulted in concussions when he said on March 22, ''It's probably time that the general managers ask the question, 'Where are we at with this?' ''</p>
        <p>The implication was that it had finally dawned on those in the upper echelons of hockey that fighting might have outlived its usefulness, if it ever had any, and that it had become more of a detriment to the game than an asset.</p>
        <p>Campbell's remarks, and the issues that inspired them, have stirred as much talk as the league's intensely exciting playoff race.</p>
        <p>''At no time did I say I was in favor of removing fighting from the game,'' Campbell said last week by telephone from Toronto. ''I'm only in favor of asking the question to players, coaches, managers, even fans: Where are we when it comes to fighting. Is it a necessary part of our game?''</p>
        <p>The same week that Campbell first asked the question about fighting, Serge Savard spoke out against the practice in an interview in The Hockey News. Savard, a Hall of Fame defenseman mainly for Montreal and also the Canadiens' general manager for 12 years, went on at length in opposition to fighting, a position he emphatically reiterated last week.</p>
        <p>''I've always been against it,'' he said by telephone from Hilton Head, S.C. ''I fought when I was a player, but only because I had to. I never wanted to fight. That's not the way I was brought up.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there's a need for it in hockey. We're the only sport that allows it. What does that say? The Triple A youth league I founded, from the start, we never allowed fighting.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''A spontaneous fight can happen. But the planned stuff, the frontier justice, the guys who are there to start fights, that's not sport. To say we need to allow more of that, to bring back more fighting, that's taking the game backward 30 years. I thought with the new rules we were moving forward.''</p>
        <p>Campbell dismissed two prevalent arguments from the pro-fighting faction. ''If we have to depend on fights to sell tickets, then we're in trouble,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also said: ''I don't agree with that keeps-the-game-safe argument because -- what drives me nuts about fighting now is that players are allowed to say no. If you were challenged to fight in the '70s and '80s, into someplace in the '90s -- the majority of players had to say yes even though they didn't want to. Now you're allowed to turn down the invitation. So that whole culture has changed.''</p>
        <p>Pat LaFONTAINE, the former Islander, Sabre and Ranger and a member of the Hall of Fame, had his career ended by a series of concussions. He endorsed Savard's viewpoint over the telephone from Buffalo last week.</p>
        <p>''When you start to see as many guys being carted off on stretchers, whether it be concussions from a fight or from a hit, you've got to ask yourself some serious questions as a league,'' LaFontaine said. ''What is it going to take? God forbid something even more severe happens, to really wake up to the fact that it's out of control or it's crossed the line.</p>
        <p>LaFontaine cited the March 8 game in which Ryan Hollweg of the Rangers drove Chris Simon of the Islanders into the boards from behind, and Simon retaliated by swinging his stick into Hollweg's face. ''The irony of the whole Simon situation is that in the hockey world, he was wrong, he swung his stick,'' LaFontaine said. ''It was totally inappropriate and he knows that, but it was two stitches, and he's suspended.</p>
        <p>''But he could have dropped his gloves and beat Hollweg to a pulp, put him in the hospital for a month, and the irony is he'd have been back playing the next night, and we'd have condoned it.''</p>
        <p>LaFontaine added: ''It's interesting Colie Campbell made the comments he made, and I'm glad he did. He has a son playing this game, and who's to say it couldn't happen to him? I'm sure he's thinking that way. Shouldn't we all be?''</p>
        <p>Penguins Partial to OT</p>
        <p>Maxime Talbot's goal with 9.8 seconds left in regulation Thursday not only gave Pittsburgh a 3-2 win over Ottawa, it also saved the Penguins from playing their 28th overtime period this season. Only four teams in N.H.L. history have been tied at the end of regulation more than this season's Penguins -- all of them in the last three seasons.</p>
        <p>Bernie and Brodeur</p>
        <p>Martin Brodeur's 3-2 victory for the Devils over Philadelphia on Thursday was his 48th of the season, one more than Flyers goalie Bernie Parent had in 1973-74, and counts as an N.H.L. record. But 10 of Brodeur's wins came in shootouts, a luxury Parent did not have in his day. ''I understand that shootouts are on the goalie's side now,'' Brodeur said after the game. ''I wish that anyone that ever looks at the record has to mention Bernie Parent and his effort, with a shorter season and no shootouts, still having 47 wins.''</p>
        <p>The Second Season</p>
        <p>In the playoffs, there is no such thing as a shootout or a four-on-four overtime session that gives the loser a bonus point anyway.</p>
        <p>That is why trying to gauge a team's playoff strength by looking at its regular-season record is so misleading: its record can be distorted by having done well or poorly in the postgame contests that exist only in the regular schedule.</p>
        <p>But looking at a team's record during the 60 minutes of regulation time, which is played under the same rules as the playoffs, provides a more accurate gauge.</p>
        <p>Below are the records of the playoff-bound teams and contenders for 60 minutes of play only. Compare them with the current league standings, and you will see that teams like Buffalo and Vancouver are not as strong as they seem to be in the official standings. That is because they do well in the shootouts and four-on-four overtimes.</p>
        <p>Other teams are revealed as secret powerhouses -- namely Ottawa and San Jose.</p>
        <p>And in the West, Colorado would still be in the race, while in the East, Tampa Bay would be out, and the Rangers, the Canadiens, the Islanders and the Hurricanes would be battling for the final two berths.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY: SUNDAY SHOOTOUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
