<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rites of Spring; Accommodating a Growing Flock</title>
    <meta content="08RcatholicLI-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">St Mary of the Pines Roman Catholic Church (NJ)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Stafford Township (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coyne, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rites of Spring; Accommodating a Growing Flock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN COYNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Coyne, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>One of four articles about springtime religious traditions around New York City metropolitan area; describes scene at St Mary of the Pines Roman Catholic Church in Stafford Township, NJ, as priests and parishioners celebrate Mass on Palm Sunday in new church; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a season of renewal for Christians and Jews as they commemorate momentous events in their histories: for Christians, the resurrection of Jesus; for Jews, the liberation of the ancient Hebrews from slavery in Egypt. As Jews began celebrating the eight days of Passover at sundown last Monday, Christians observed the final, most solemn days of Lent in preparation for Easter services this weekend. Here are a handful of stories about different faith communities around the region.</p>
        <p>Of all the blessings of the new church -- the airy sanctuary under the white-pine planked dome, the bronze statuary, the 400 parking spots -- perhaps the most welcome were the green-cushioned kneelers in each pew.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a season of renewal for Christians and Jews as they commemorate momentous events in their histories: for Christians, the resurrection of Jesus; for Jews, the liberation of the ancient Hebrews from slavery in Egypt. As Jews began celebrating the eight days of Passover at sundown last Monday, Christians observed the final, most solemn days of Lent in preparation for Easter services this weekend. Here are a handful of stories about different faith communities around the region.</p>
        <p>Of all the blessings of the new church -- the airy sanctuary under the white-pine planked dome, the bronze statuary, the 400 parking spots -- perhaps the most welcome were the green-cushioned kneelers in each pew.</p>
        <p>On the first Palm Sunday at St. Mary of the Pines Roman Catholic Church in Stafford Township, N.J., as the ushers squeezed in the last arrivals just before Mass started, many of the parishioners seemed to be lingering on their knees, folding their green fronds into crosses or gazing up toward the huge crucifix as they prayed from a position that had been hard for them to get into for the last 30 years.</p>
        <p>''Most of the time people just stood,'' the Rev. Kenard J. Tuzeneu said about the Masses at the gym where half of his parish had worshiped until three weeks earlier, with its 500 folding chairs, a portable altar under the basketball backboards and a hard tile floor that made kneeling difficult. ''It's nice to be in a church.''</p>
        <p>When Father Tuzeneu, 53, first came to the parish in Stafford as pastor in 1992, he had a church in Barnegat, the gym at the parish center in neighboring Stafford, and 2,500 families spread across more than 100 square miles. But new arrivals kept streaming down the Garden State Parkway, leaving the old stone parishes that the first wave of Roman Catholic immigrants had built, trading the denser northern cities for the new houses and retirement villages that keep gnawing away at the pine groves here in southern Ocean County.</p>
        <p>He has 5,500 families now, one of the five largest parishes among the 118 in the Diocese of Trenton, and nine Masses each weekend. The church in Barnegat is routinely packed to its capacity of 500, and a closed-circuit TV broadcasts Mass into the basement for the overflow. ''Some parishes are doing some consolidating, but fortunately we're at the other end of the spectrum,'' Father Tuzeneu said.</p>
        <p>He started imagining a proper church to replace the gym not long after he arrived, and began working on it four years ago. St. Mary of the Pines, which cost $5.2 million, was dedicated by Bishop John M. Smith on March 10, the newest church in the diocese. It has enough seats for 1,100 people, and every one looked filled for Palm Sunday.</p>
        <p>''Father, into your hands I commend my spirit,'' the Rev. John T. Jakub, one of Father Tuzeneu's two assistants, said at the altar, reading from the Gospel of Luke, reaching the moment when Jesus dies.</p>
        <p>''And when he had said this he breathed his last,'' the lector read, and in the silent, heavy moment that followed, the whole congregation, which had been standing to hear the Passion, knelt as one.</p>
        <p>When Mass ended, many of the parishioners were slow to leave, mingling among the semicircle of blond-wood pews.</p>
        <p>''With all those curved benches, it feels gathered when you're in here,'' said Pat Voelker, 68, who will celebrate her 50th anniversary with her husband, Bob, in September in the parish they joined 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>''It's a big church, but we wanted to keep the closeness of it,'' said Father Jakub, before heading over to the Barnegat church for noon Mass.</p>
        <p>Beyond the pines that fringe the parking lot sprawled a raw landscape in the process of becoming a town, with new strip malls still stocking their shelves, treeless retirement villages, acres of soccer and baseball fields for the armies of children, backhoes waiting to dig foundations for new houses and ''Coming Soon'' signs on staked lots. As the parishioners left the new church, many of them drove the mile to the old parish center, where Father Tuzeneu was holding court in the gym. Some of the folding chairs had been set up there again, but for a purpose the room was much better suited for than Mass: a pancake breakfast.</p>
        <p>KEVIN COYNE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
