<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Meetings Are Part Revival, Part Rally, but All Sharpton</title>
    <meta content="08sharpton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/08sharpton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Action Network</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wlib (NYC Radio Station)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharpton, Al (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Imus, Don</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fernandez, Manny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Action Network</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharpton, Al</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Meetings Are Part Revival, Part Rally, but All Sharpton</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Meetings Are Part Revival, Part Rally, but All Sharpton</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fernandez, Manny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rev Al Sharpton holds rallies every Saturday at his National Action Network's headquarters in Harlem, and they are part radio show, church service, comedy revue, civil rights demonstration, town hall meeting and fund-raising drive; are broadcast live on WLIB-AM, city's first black-owned radio station; Sharpton called during recent meeting for firing of Don Imus over his remarks about Rutgers University women's basketball team; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a rather small, anonymous stage in Harlem, in an old building a few doors down from a Laundromat and a Dunkin' Donuts, something unexpected happens to the Rev. Al Sharpton's sizable and nationally known persona. It shrinks accordingly.</p>
        <p>Every Saturday morning, Mr. Sharpton opens the doors of his National Action Network's headquarters in Harlem for an ''action rally.'' The meetings are something more than a rally -- part radio show, church service, comedy revue, civil rights demonstration, town hall meeting and fund-raising drive. The rallies are broadcast live on WLIB-AM, the city's first black-owned radio station.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Rev. Al Sharpton opens the doors of his National Action Network’s headquarters, sometimes he raises money, and sometimes he makes national news.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a rather small, anonymous stage in Harlem, in an old building a few doors down from a Laundromat and a Dunkin' Donuts, something unexpected happens to the Rev. Al Sharpton's sizable and nationally known persona. It shrinks accordingly.</p>
        <p>Every Saturday morning, Mr. Sharpton opens the doors of his National Action Network's headquarters in Harlem for an ''action rally.'' The meetings are something more than a rally -- part radio show, church service, comedy revue, civil rights demonstration, town hall meeting and fund-raising drive. The rallies are broadcast live on WLIB-AM, the city's first black-owned radio station.</p>
        <p>On most Saturdays, the so-called House of Justice on West 145th Street can feel as casual as the International House of Pancakes 10 blocks south. Anyone can walk in and take a seat. The words etched onto the large tinted window at the entrance, facing 145th Street, read not House of Justice or National Action Network but Diamond Gym, the storefront's former occupant, which explains why the walls are lined with mirrors.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, in a fast-paced 90 minutes before a crowd of fewer than 100 people, Mr. Sharpton led a drummer and a pianist through a gospel song (''Sing it like you mean it,'' he sang into the microphone), criticized the federal government's slow pace of rebuilding in New Orleans after Hurricane Katrina and paid tribute to the sacrifices of both Jesus Christ and the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.</p>
        <p>He happened also to make national news, which sometimes happens at his rallies, too. He called for the firing of Don Imus, the syndicated radio host, after Mr. Imus referred on Wednesday to the students who play for the Rutgers University women's basketball team as ''nappy-headed ho's.''</p>
        <p>After the television cameras had left, Mr. Sharpton refocused on the nuts and bolts of his civil rights organization, signing up seven new members to the National Action Network. Then he taught an introductory class for new members.</p>
        <p>''It gives him an energy that helps him and keeps him propelling along,'' said Michael A. Hardy, a lawyer, longtime friend of Mr. Sharpton's and the host of the radio show and rally. ''It is the tent that holds everyone in the movement, whether you're high profile and a celebrity, or a no-profile but important.''</p>
        <p>It is here on Saturdays that Mr. Sharpton pleads for donations for his network (''I need some more hundreds,'' he told the audience recently) and wades through unglamorous organizational housekeeping.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharpton has been holding Saturday rallies broadcast on the radio since 1991, when he founded the National Action Network. Some of those in the audience are network members who have been going to the rallies for years. They remember the auditorium of Public School 175, where the rallies were first held. They remember the speech the Rev. Jesse Jackson gave years ago, when he dubbed the network's headquarters the House of Justice. And they remember the Saturday, in July 2002, when Michael Jackson depicted Thomas D. Mottola, a record company executive, as the devil.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, in two hard-backed chairs near the aisle, sat James and Sylvia Snead, a couple from Queens who have attended the Saturday rallies regularly since the early 1990s. When Mr. Snead was hospitalized months ago, he had a friend send him recordings of the rallies he missed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Snead, 68, said people keep going to the rallies because they seek inspiration in overcoming the economic and social problems that African-Americans face. ''It gives them another week to go again, because it ain't easy in this world,'' said Mr. Snead, a retired union leader. ''I would say they need a mental cleansing after a week of struggling.''</p>
        <p>A couple rows back was James Lee Frazier Jr., a man from Queens who calls himself a ''celestial education consultant'' and who is writing a series of poems based on the acorn (he carries some in his pocket). Over there was a rally regular, Yosef A. A. ben-Jochannan, a renowned historian known as Dr. Ben who sits in a special chair with a red bow on top.</p>
        <p>In January 2003, a fire gutted the old headquarters at 125th Street and Madison Avenue, and after that the gatherings were at two other churches. The current headquarters has seen a flurry of activity since December, when the organization moved in. The current space has been a backdrop for news conferences in the aftermath of the Sean Bell shooting. Nicole Paultre Bell, Mr. Bell's fiancée, is a frequent guest; on Christmas Day, she served food to the needy.</p>
        <p>''I don't care how many national TV shows I do, or how many big speeches I do, coming home on Saturday, you know you can't get up and sell hogwash to them,'' Mr. Sharpton said in an interview. ''You got to be real.''</p>
        <p>He sometimes gets corrected by the audience. Yesterday, he said in error that Mr. Imus had made his remark about the University of Tennessee players. He jokes with longtime supporters from the stage, gets people on their feet, talks frankly about his past. ''He comes across as the brother in the barber shop,'' said Owen Rogers, 53, a Harlem literary researcher often in the audience.</p>
        <p>Yesterday morning, after a number of guests stood at the lectern, including Charlie King, acting executive director, who gave an update on the group's annual convention starting April 18, Mr. Hardy introduced Mr. Sharpton, ''the soul-seeker, the liberation-reacher, the people's preacher.''</p>
        <p>''No justice,'' Mr. Sharpton called out.</p>
        <p>''No peace,'' came the response.</p>
        <p>There was no mistaking that this was the House of Sharpton. Seated in the audience, people's eyes are often drawn not to Mr. Sharpton, dressed yesterday in a matching, beige pin-striped shirt and pants, but to stage right, where a framed, close-up portrait of Mr. Sharpton hangs on the wall. One of the stage lights on the ceiling is aimed directly at it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharpton's address was at once humorous and serious, part of his strategy to infuse the rally with what he calls ''information, destination, inspiration.''</p>
        <p>On Mr. Imus, Mr. Sharpton said: ''Don Imus should be fired and taken off the airwaves. This is not about insensitivity, this is about the abusive, racist, sexist use of our federally regulated airwaves.''</p>
        <p>He spoke about the mother, whom he did not want to name, who came up to him at a march one day and told him she could not stand him.</p>
        <p>''She said, 'Every time you come on TV, I turn the channel. Loud-mouth Sharpton,' '' he told the audience. ''She said, 'But the night they called me from the hospital and told me the police had killed my son, all I could think of was how can I find Al Sharpton.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
