<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An F for W.</title>
    <meta content="Heilbrunn2.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Heilbrunn2.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Brzezinski, Zbigniew</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Second Chance: Three Presidents and the Crisis of American Superpower (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E2DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An F for W.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An F for W.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACOB HEILBRUNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heilbrunn, Jacob</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SECOND CHANCE</p>
        <p>Three Presidents and the Crisis</p>
        <p>of American Superpower.</p>
        <p>By Zbigniew Brzezinski.</p>
        <p>234 pp. Basic Books. $26.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a provocative assessment, Zbigniew Brzezinski sharply reprimands the last three presidents for squandering American power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SECOND CHANCE</p>
        <p>Three Presidents and the Crisis</p>
        <p>of American Superpower.</p>
        <p>By Zbigniew Brzezinski.</p>
        <p>234 pp. Basic Books. $26.95.</p>
        <p>ZBIGNIEW BRZEZINSKI, who was national security adviser to Jimmy Carter, has steadily warned that American arrogance might well lead to catastrophe abroad. And unlike his ingratiating Republican counterpart, Henry Kissinger, he was an early and vociferous opponent of the Iraq war.</p>
        <p>Now, in his brilliantly provocative ''Second Chance,'' Brzezinski appraises American foreign policy over the past three presidential administrations. Shunning the sonorous language that pervades most books by former high-ranking officials, he sharply reprimands George H. W. Bush, Bill Clinton and George W. Bush for squandering American power. By the end, he even issues presidential report cards, with marks of ''B'' for the elder Bush, ''C'' for Clinton and a dismal ''F'' for you know who.</p>
        <p>As Brzezinski sees it, the first Bush administration did not capitalize on America's victory in the cold war. George H. W. Bush helped ensure that the Soviet Union expired peacefully, that Germany was reunified and that an international coalition expelled Saddam Hussein from Kuwait. But, Brzezinski believes, much more could, and should, have been done: ''America's unique political influence and moral legitimacy were not strategically applied to either transform Russia or pacify the Middle East.'' Bush, he says, should have pushed Israel far more forcefully to reach a permanent accommodation with the Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat.</p>
        <p>If Bush senior lacked the vision and boldness to reinvent American foreign policy after the cold war, Clinton was bedazzled by the notion that globalization would bring an end to world conflict. Brzezinski awards Clinton good marks for successfully enlarging NATO. But he argues that Clinton badly erred in failing to achieve an accord between the Israelis and Palestinians. At his marathon sessions with Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Barak and Arafat at Camp David in July 2000, Clinton may have striven for peace, but there was too much ''emphasis on immediately assigning blame for the parties' failure to emerge from the meeting with an agreement in hand.'' Overall, Brzezinski says, Clinton ''did not leave a historically grand imprint on the world.''</p>
        <p>So disdainful is Brzezinski of George W. Bush that he barely even pauses to discuss him. Instead, the neoconservatives surrounding Bush trigger his ire. According to Brzezinski, the Iraq war's ''only saving grace is that it made Iraq the cemetery of neocon dreams. Had the war been more successful, America by now might be at war with Syria and Iran, pursuing a policy driven more by Manichaean notions and dubious motivations than by any sober definition of its national interest.''</p>
        <p>Brzezinski covers a great deal of ground with dispatch and verve. On page after page, acerbic observations vie for attention with apodictic verdicts. Despite his contempt for George W. Bush, however, Brzezinski has something in common with him: abundant self-confidence. While his predilection for sweeping pronouncements ensures that his book is never less than exciting, it can also lead him astray.</p>
        <p>For one thing, he doesn't adequately take into account the fact that American global pre-eminence after the cold war was not only historically anomalous, but probably also bound to produce a new coalition of adversaries, most notably China and Russia. Clinton's personal popularity abroad temporarily masked this development, and the second Bush's ham-handed policies have greatly accelerated it. But neither president created the shift against the United States.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Brzezinski tends to exaggerate the ability of American presidents to guide world politics, particularly in the Middle East. The first President Bush suspended loan guarantees to Israel to force it to halt settlement activity on the West Bank, bringing a storm of obloquy upon him from Israel's American supporters. What more would Brzezinski have had him do? In 2000, no matter how much Clinton pleaded, Arafat was simply unwilling to bargain seriously. Is it any wonder that Clinton came to view him as untrustworthy? Brzezinski's apparent conviction that the Israeli-Palestinian conflict could be quickly and tidily ended if Washington only had the willpower seems almost as utopian as the belief that democracy can be implanted everywhere in the Middle East. A grand strategist like Brzezinski bridles at a policy of small steps, but such a policy is more likely to yield results.</p>
        <p>Nor does Brzezinski adequately acknowledge that the source of the current mess in the Middle East antedates the past three presidencies. In many ways, it can be traced to the administration Brzezinski himself served in. Jimmy Carter may have brokered peace between Israel and Egypt at Camp David, but his hapless response to the fall of the shah of Iran and the rise of Islamic theocracy in 1979 has bedeviled American foreign policy ever since. In addition, Carter, at Brzezinski's urging, began secretly arming the Afghan mujahedeen, who eventually morphed into the Taliban and Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>Carter's great accomplishment was to put human rights at the center of American foreign policy, and it is here that Brzezinski is at his best. In his last chapter, he boldly seeks to restore America's moral authority by redeeming the idea of democratization and regime change from the battering it has received at the hands of the Bush administration. He sees a ''global political awakening'' centered on a drive for ''universal human dignity,'' which, he says, is rendering Bush's martial fervor both anachronistic and self-defeating. Retreating into a fearful garrison state will only compound America's problems. The ''nearly universal access to radio, television and the Internet,'' Brzezinski writes, ''is creating a community of shared resentments and envy that ... poses a challenge to both existing states and the global hierarchy, on top of which America still perches.'' Brzezinski's final warning, then, is that America must address those shared resentments or risk signing its death warrant as a superpower.</p>
        <p>Jacob Heilbrunn is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jacob Heilbrunn is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
