<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Curry's Unexpected Shot Gives Knicks Some Hope</title>
    <meta content="08knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/basketball/08knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Milwaukee Bucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Milwaukee Bucks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Curry, Eddy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE0DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Curry's Unexpected Shot Gives Knicks Some Hope</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Curry’s Unexpected Shot Gives Knicks Some Hope</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>MILWAUKEE, April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eddy Curry was left alone Saturday night, his high-scoring teammates having all abandoned him for the training room. As the hour grew late, he was alone again, standing 23 feet from the basket with the game -- and the Knicks' season -- on the line.</p>
        <p>There was no more unlikely place for Curry to be. Coach Isiah Thomas asked him to hit shoot a 3-pointer with nine-tenths of a second left in regulation. Curry hit it. And the Knicks' playoff hopes, however faint, are alive because of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eddy Curry hit a 3-pointer with nine-tenths of a second left in regulation to send the game to overtime and finished with a career-high 43 points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eddy Curry was left alone Saturday night, his high-scoring teammates having all abandoned him for the training room. As the hour grew late, he was alone again, standing 23 feet from the basket with the game -- and the Knicks' season -- on the line.</p>
        <p>There was no more unlikely place for Curry to be. Coach Isiah Thomas asked him to hit shoot a 3-pointer with nine-tenths of a second left in regulation. Curry hit it. And the Knicks' playoff hopes, however faint, are alive because of it.</p>
        <p>The Knicks defeated the Milwaukee Bucks, 118-113, in overtime, with Curry scoring a career-high 43 points, leaving everyone unusually giddy as they left the Bradley Center court.</p>
        <p>''I just had confidence,'' Curry said. ''I felt like things have been going so bad for this team, that the shot had to go in.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks had lost four straight games and 10 of their last 12, all but killing their once-bright playoff hopes. Curry's memorable night probably only stalled their elimination. The eighth-place Orlando Magic also won Saturday, leaving the Knicks three games out with six games to play.</p>
        <p>Curry was dominant inside all night, making 17 of 20 field goals and 8 of 12 free throws. He also grabbed 13 rebounds. But it was his rare appearance on the perimeter, the very deep perimeter, that made his performance noteworthy.</p>
        <p>Milwaukee's Ruben Patterson had just given the Bucks what appeared to be the clinching basket, an equally unlikely bank-shot 3-pointer with nine-tenths of a second left. Patterson, a poor shooter, had hit just two 3-pointers all season.</p>
        <p>Then again, the burly Curry had converted just one 3-pointer in his career. But these are desperate times for the Knicks, so it seems Coach Isiah Thomas felt free to gamble a bit. Stephon Marbury missed Saturday's game with a bad case of turf toe, leaving the Knicks without their top four guards and four of their top six scorers.</p>
        <p>The Knicks were down to just two guards, the rookie Mardy Collins and the second-year pro Nate Robinson. Collins had 19 points, 12 rebounds, 8 assists and 5 steals. Robinson scored 34 points, including a clinching 3-pointer in overtime.</p>
        <p>Curry trumped them all. Although Robinson had hit five 3-pointers, Thomas said he designed the final play of regulation for Curry. From the sideline near the Knicks' bench, Collins threw the inbounds pass to Curry, who was standing several feet to his right, just behind the arc. At the last moment, Dan Gadzuric lurched toward Curry, but it was too late.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think that they would guard him,'' Thomas said. ''I've been telling him the whole season that at some point in time I was going to design a play for him to shoot a 3 and win the game for us.''</p>
        <p>Thomas said the Knicks had practiced the play and that Curry made 3-pointers in practice. Players chuckled at that assertion.</p>
        <p>''That was just something he drew up,'' Curry said. ''Me and Nate kind of kid around after practice now and then, shooting 3's and stuff. It's not something I really practice. I will now though.''</p>
        <p>The night began with bad news, as Marbury limped in wearing a protective boot on his right foot. The turf toe forced him to miss just his second game of the season and it was not clear whether he would be able to play Monday against Detroit.</p>
        <p>Only a month ago the Knicks appeared playoff-bound. But injuries to Jamal Crawford, Quentin Richardson, Steve Francis, David Lee and now Marbury have ruined the season.</p>
        <p>''It's tough to deal with, because we saw a light at the end of the tunnel,'' Marbury said. ''And now, basically the door is closing. I think for us, we hate to be looking forward to next year, but at the same time, injuries do happen. And that's just part of the game.''</p>
        <p>Marbury said he hoped to return for Monday's game against Detroit, but he did not sound confident. He originally jammed the toe just before the All-Star Game break and said the pain was worse this time. He aggravated the injury in the first quarter Friday, when he tripped over Mike James's foot and slammed the toe into the court. It did not respond to a novocaine shot, and Marbury needed pain medication just to sleep Friday night.</p>
        <p>It was striking to consider what the Knicks were missing. Marbury, Francis, Crawford and Richardson, their top four guards, make a combined $46 million this season. Together, they were averaging 57.5 points and 16.1 assists a game.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>David Lee has vowed to play the rest of the season, but the stress reaction in his lower right leg might not permit it. Lee, who played 20 minutes Friday, was in obvious pain for the two minutes he played Saturday. He did not play after the first quarter and his status for Monday's game against Detroit is uncertain. ''Every step I took was just absolutely killing me,'' Lee said.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
