<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Ways to Shine In a Foggy Market</title>
    <meta content="08topp" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/mutfund/08topp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Heebner, G Kenneth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Ways to Shine In a Foggy Market</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Three Ways to Shine in a Foggy Market</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was a lackluster quarter for the overall market, but some mutual funds made money from eclectic stock portfolios. Here, managers of three of the top-performing funds talk about their stocks, their strategies and what they see ahead in the market.</p>
        <p>A Quantitative Approach</p>
        <p>The $233 million Hennessy Focus 30 fund rose 9.7 percent in the first quarter, riding the strong domestic electronics and retail sectors. The manager, Neil J. Hennessy, 51, uses a quantitative approach to pick the fund's 30 stocks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Managers of three of the top-performing funds talk about their stocks, their strategies and what they see ahead in the market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was a lackluster quarter for the overall market, but some mutual funds made money from eclectic stock portfolios. Here, managers of three of the top-performing funds talk about their stocks, their strategies and what they see ahead in the market.</p>
        <p>A Quantitative Approach</p>
        <p>The $233 million Hennessy Focus 30 fund rose 9.7 percent in the first quarter, riding the strong domestic electronics and retail sectors. The manager, Neil J. Hennessy, 51, uses a quantitative approach to pick the fund's 30 stocks.</p>
        <p>He starts by screening 9,700 United States companies with market capitalizations of $1 billion to $10 billion, but excludes American depository receipts and stocks priced at less than $5 a share.</p>
        <p>Next, he looks for companies with price-to-sales ratios of 1.5 or less, and current earnings that exceed the previous year's, as well as for share prices that have increased over the most recent three and six months. He selects 30 companies and buys equal amounts of their shares, holding them for a year, then repeats the procedure. Currently, 30 percent of the fund's assets are invested in retail companies.</p>
        <p>One winner was Big Lots, the discount chain based in Columbus, Ohio, that sells product overruns, discontinued items and other closeout merchandise. Shares rose 36 percent in the quarter, partly because of the overall strength of retail stocks, Mr. Hennessy said. The strong performance also reflected the current interest of private equity firms in buying retailers, he added.</p>
        <p>Another winner was CommScope, a company based in Hickory, N.C., that makes cable used in communications networks. Its price-to-sales ratio was 1.29 when he bought the shares; it is now 1.58, as the company's operations have become more efficient and sales have increased. CommScope's shares rose 41 percent in the quarter.</p>
        <p>The fund also made money in Belden CDT of St. Louis, which produces high-speed electronics cables. Mr. Hennessy says the company is undervalued, adding that ''a lot of these types of companies are overlooked because their businesses are boring.'' Belden's stock rose 37 percent in the quarter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hennessy says he thinks that the overall stock market is still very strong. ''Fundamentally, the economy is in great shape,'' he said. ''Corporate earnings are growing, albeit slowly.''</p>
        <p>Bullish Overseas</p>
        <p>''I'm bullish on the global economy,'' said G. Kenneth Heebner, 66, manager of the $2.5 billion CGM Focus fund, up 9.4 percent. It holds just 19 stocks. Like Hennessy Focus, its concentrated holdings make it potentially more volatile than more diversified portfolios.</p>
        <p>About two-thirds of the fund's assets are tied directly to overseas activity, Mr. Heebner said. Over all, 30 percent is invested in companies that mine iron ore, copper, nickel and coal. ''Huge demand from all over the world is keeping metal prices higher than they would be normally at this point in the business cycle,'' Mr. Heebner said.</p>
        <p>The fund made money in Companhia Vale do Rio Doce, a Brazilian miner of nickel and iron ore. The company bought Inco in an all-cash transaction that closed in January, Mr. Heebner said, making it one of the biggest nickel producers in the world. The fund owns the company's American depository receipts, which rose 24 percent in the quarter.</p>
        <p>Another winner was Allegheny Technologies of Pittsburgh, a leading provider of titanium to the aerospace industry. The company also profited from strong demand for its nickel alloys, used in airplane engines, Mr. Heebner said. The stock rose 18 percent in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>The fund has also done well with Vimpel Communications, a Russian wireless telecommunications company, which ''is experiencing a profit surge related to the overall strength of business in Russia,'' he said. The fund holds A.D.R.'s traded on the New York Stock Exchange; for the quarter, they rose 20 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heebner is not very bullish on the American economy. He expects a broadening of the decline in housing and a slowdown in economic growth.</p>
        <p>Small-Company Bargains</p>
        <p>The $38 million Westwood Mighty Mites fund, up 7 percent in the quarter, buys very small companies with market capitalizations of no more than $300 million. The fund, which holds 200 stocks, is managed by Mario J. Gabelli, 64; Walter K. Walsh, 64; and Laura Linehan, 39.</p>
        <p>''We look for companies that are trading at significant discounts to what we consider to be their private market value,'' Ms. Linehan said. The fund is highly diversified across a variety of industries.</p>
        <p>One winner was the Epoch Holding Corporation, a money management firm in New York City with a market capitalization of about $260 million. Its shares rose 33 percent.</p>
        <p>The fund also made money in Sonic Innovations, based in Salt Lake City, a maker of digital hearing aids and auditory testing equipment. ''The aging of the American population is one of our investment themes,'' Ms. Linehan said. ''This company is one of the few pure plays in that area.'' Its stock rose 62 percent in the quarter.</p>
        <p>Another winner was Edgewater Technology, an information technology management consultant in Wakefield, Mass., with a market capitalization of less than $100 million; its shares rose 38 percent. ''It's a niche consulting company that gets a lot of clients that bigger consultants wouldn't bother with,'' Ms. Linehan said. ''Its service revenues have been increasing at a nice pace.''</p>
        <p>While Ms. Linehan would not comment on the overall market, she said that she expects smaller companies to ''continue benefiting from a robust mergers-and-acquisitions environment.''</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
