<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Dual Triple-Doubles, Carter and Kidd Join Elite</title>
    <meta content="08nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Washington Wizards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFDB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Dual Triple-Doubles, Carter and Kidd Join Elite</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With just over a minute and a half remaining in the Nets' game Saturday night, point guard Jason Kidd missed a 3-pointer from the wing, caught his own rebound as it sailed over the baseline and threw the ball off the back of Wizards forward Jarvis Hayes to keep possession for the Nets.</p>
        <p>The sequence pretty much summed up what the Nets have become: a gritty bunch who make things difficult for themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With just over a minute and a half remaining in the Nets' game Saturday night, point guard Jason Kidd missed a 3-pointer from the wing, caught his own rebound as it sailed over the baseline and threw the ball off the back of Wizards forward Jarvis Hayes to keep possession for the Nets.</p>
        <p>The sequence pretty much summed up what the Nets have become: a gritty bunch who make things difficult for themselves.</p>
        <p>With the stakes high -- trying to secure a playoff spot and move up in the standings -- the Nets needed overtime to defeat the depleted Washington Wizards, 120-114, at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>The Nets (36-40) moved within three games of the Wizards (39-37) for sixth place in the Eastern Conference as Vince Carter and Kidd became the first teammates to record a triple-double in the same game since Michael Jordan and Scottie Pippen did it for the Chicago Bulls in 1989.</p>
        <p>Carter had 46 points, 16 rebounds and 10 assists, and Kidd had 10 points, 16 rebounds and 18 assists. Several of Kidd's teammates joked that, with nine turnovers, he nearly had a quadruple double.</p>
        <p>It was the third triple-double of Carter's career and the 86th for Kidd, who has 11 this season.</p>
        <p>''I've been trying for a long time,'' Carter said. ''It's a special night.''</p>
        <p>Richard Jefferson added a season-high 27 points for the Nest, who made a franchise-record 17 3-pointers. Carter hit seven 3-pointers and Jefferson made six.</p>
        <p>Even though the Wizards are without their two All-Stars -- Gilbert Arenas and Caron Butler -- they got star-caliber performances Hayes and forward Antawn Jamison. Jamison scored a season-high 37 points and Hayes a career-high 29 points.</p>
        <p>With his team trailing by 3 points and 4.4 seconds remaining in regulation, Jamison hit a 3-pointer from the top of the arc to tie the score at 104-104 and send the game into overtime.</p>
        <p>But the Nets scored the first 8 points of overtime.</p>
        <p>''We do tend to make things difficult,'' said Kidd, who tied his career high in rebounds and had his 11th triple-double of the season. ''That's just the way we've been. We never quit. We keep fighting. That's the makeup of this team.''</p>
        <p>Carter, who had a career high in rebounds and tied his season high in scoring, said: ''We're playing for wins. It doesn't matter how the game looked. Of course we want to go out there and play a perfect game and a complete game, but if it doesn't happen we have to find a way to get a win.''</p>
        <p>The Nets had plenty of motivation to play well, not the least of which was to get the bad taste out of their mouths from a night earlier when they lost to the Chicago Bulls by 31 points.</p>
        <p>The Nets also were looking to creeping toward the sixth spot in the East. The Nets, who lead the season series by 3-0, will have an opportunity to get even closer to the Wizards when the teams play again in Washington on Tuesday night. Each team has six games remaining.</p>
        <p>The Nets' chances of catching the Wizards became much better last Wednesday when Washington lost Arenas for the season with a knee injury. Butler is out with a broken bone in his right hand.</p>
        <p>But the Nets seemed to know better than to underestimate the Wizards.</p>
        <p>''I think you have to give Washington a lot of credit, playing without two of their All-Stars and yet they're using it as motivation that everyone is counting them out,'' Nets Coach Lawrence Frank said. ''And as you see, they have more than enough.''</p>
        <p>The game started as a one-man explosion for the Nets with Carter, who took 11 of their first 13 shots, scoring their first 17 points. Cliff Robinson became the first Net other than Carter to score when he hit a 3-pointer with 54.2 seconds remaining in the quarter.</p>
        <p>Jefferson helped to pick up the offensive load in the second quarter by scoring 16 points. Jefferson, who took only one shot in the first quarter, made all four of his 3-pointers in the quarter and 6 of 8 for the game.</p>
        <p>MAGIC 116, GRIZZLIES 89 -- Dwight Howard had 31 points and 11 rebounds, and host Orlando remained in eighth place in the Eastern Conference, a game ahead of Indiana.</p>
        <p>PACERS 105, CELTICS 98 -- Mike Dunleavy scored 22 points, and Jermaine O'Neal added 14 points and 14 rebounds to lead host Indiana.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
