<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yes, It's a 7-Year Streak, but No, They're Not Bragging</title>
    <meta content="08worst" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/mutfund/08worst.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yes, It's a 7-Year Streak, but No, They're Not Bragging</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yes, It’s a 7-Year Streak, but No, They’re Not Bragging</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM GRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LANCE ARMSTRONG'S winning streak -- seven consecutive Tour de France victories from 1999 through 2005 -- helped to make him the pitchman for American Century Investments' target-date retirement funds.</p>
        <p>But two of the 95 mutual funds sold by American Century, based in Kansas City, Mo., have seven-year streaks that the company isn't bragging about: its Ultra Investor and Growth Investor funds have underperformed the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index in every calendar year since 2000, according to Morningstar, the fund tracker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock-pricing runs in cycles, and times have not been good for growth investing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LANCE ARMSTRONG'S winning streak -- seven consecutive Tour de France victories from 1999 through 2005 -- helped to make him the pitchman for American Century Investments' target-date retirement funds.</p>
        <p>But two of the 95 mutual funds sold by American Century, based in Kansas City, Mo., have seven-year streaks that the company isn't bragging about: its Ultra Investor and Growth Investor funds have underperformed the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index in every calendar year since 2000, according to Morningstar, the fund tracker.</p>
        <p>The American Century Ultra Investor and Growth Investor funds share that distinction with 28 other mutual funds. And two other funds -- Pioneer Growth Shares A and Fifth Third Dividend Growth -- have had an even longer streak, failing to beat the index since 1999.</p>
        <p>Among the group that has lagged the S.&amp; P. since 2000 are tiny funds like Frontier Microcap, with assets of only $200,000. But some underperformers are from some of the biggest names in the asset management business. In addition to American Century Ultra Investor and Growth Investor, the list includes Fidelity Blue Chip Growth, JPMorgan Large Cap Growth Fund Select and  GMO U.S. Growth III. (GMO is also a manager for such giant funds as Vanguard Explorer, which isn't on the list.)</p>
        <p>Of course, many of the companies with funds on the list are also home to some of the strongest performers of recent years. American Century Value Investor and American Century Real Estate Investor, for example, have beaten the S.&amp; P. 500 for seven years in a row.</p>
        <p>Most funds on the underperformance list share this trait: their managers focus on buying large-capitalization growth stocks -- shares in big companies whose earnings they expect to grow at above-average rates.</p>
        <p>The market moves in cycles, favoring one style of stock-picking at any given time. Since 2000, growth investing has slumped, said Kevin M. Lewis, client portfolio manager for American Century Ultra. ''Only 11 percent of large-cap growth managers in our Morningstar peer group have outperformed the S.&amp; P. index in that period,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His argument, that the market has frowned on the large-cap growth philosophy in recent years, predominated among the investment companies that responded to requests for comment on their funds' losing streaks. In fact, a leading large growth index, the Russell 200, has failed to beat the S.&amp; P. since 2000.</p>
        <p>Large-cap stocks have been down long enough that, by at least one measure, they may be due for a rebound. A recent analysis by Ford Equity Research in San Diego found the price-to-earnings ratio of large caps was a third of its level in March 2000. The P/E ratio of small-cap stocks, meanwhile, has soared. Of course, the fact that large-cap stocks are relatively inexpensive doesn't mean they can't become even cheaper.</p>
        <p>Representatives for a few funds on the list argued that peers who did beat the S.&amp; P. might have moved away from their stated mission -- buying large-cap growth stocks -- to pump up returns. ''You could've gone down to midcap stocks,'' said Bruce T. Herring, group chief investment officer overseeing Fidelity Blue Chip Growth, the largest fund on the list. ''You could've gone to more value stocks, or you could've gone abroad.''</p>
        <p>John B. McDowell, manager of Blue Chip Growth for most of the time since 2000, stuck strictly with his mandate and managed to beat the Russell 200 index for five of the last seven years, Mr. Herring said. ''This fund did exactly what it was supposed to do,'' he said, ''and it beat a very appropriate benchmark.'' Last year, Jennifer S. Uhrig replaced Mr. McDowell as the manager of the fund, which in late March had about $20 billion in assets.</p>
        <p>Fund analysts differ on whether investors should bolt from funds just because they fail to match the S.&amp; P. over long periods. Christine Benz, director of mutual fund analysis at Morningstar, urged caution, agreeing that the market's tilt away from large-cap growth stocks could have hurt otherwise competent managers. Morningstar, as a rule, applauds managers who hew to a philosophy rather than jumping around in hopes of bolstering returns when the market moves against them.</p>
        <p>''Warren Buffett underperformed during the tech bull market,'' she said, ''and I think we'd all have to agree that he was right to stick to his strategy.''</p>
        <p>But Jeff Tjornehoj, a senior research analyst at Lipper, said he would be less patient, tolerating only a couple of years of poor performance before going elsewhere. ''I don't mind a manager who sticks with his conviction,'' he said. ''But I can't retire on conviction. I have to retire on his performance.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Benz also said a comparison with calendar year returns of the S.&amp; P. 500 might not accurately gauge the quality of some funds on the list. Long-term, continuous returns -- known as trailing returns -- calculated over, say, five years, are a better indicator, she said. ''You might have a fund that's underperformed its category peers on a calendar year basis, but over a five-year period, it might land in the top half.''</p>
        <p>For Alan J. Marcus, a finance professor at Boston College, the inability of a group of professional money managers to beat the S.&amp; P. in any calendar year in nearly a decade points to a reason to prefer indexed mutual funds over actively managed ones. An index fund will generally underperform its index by a few tenths of a percentage point because of costs. But actively managed funds have higher costs, on average. So even if they beat an index fund on an absolute basis, they can still fall short once they have subtracted their fees. And when they fail to beat an index on an absolute basis, their higher costs magnify the shortfall.</p>
        <p>''With only a few exceptions, paying an active fund manager 1 percent-plus to manage a fund has usually been a bad bet, whether the fund focuses on value or growth,'' Professor Marcus said.</p>
        <p>HOW do some poorly performing funds survive in an industry as competitive as mutual funds, where investors have thousands of choices and can switch among funds easily?</p>
        <p>One possibility is that employers' retirement plans limited some investors' choices, said Roy Weitz, publisher of FundAlarm.com. Retirement plans often offer a handful of options and, because of legal and administrative requirements, participants have more difficulty than retail investors in swapping funds.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Tjornehoj of Lipper chalked up the endurance of the funds on this list to the unpredictability of consumer behavior. ''Every industry has products that just don't seem to be worth the money, but people keep buying them,'' he said. ''People drove Ford Pintos for years.''</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
