<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Light at the End of the Trail</title>
    <meta content="08njtopicNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08njtopic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HIKING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sourland Mountains (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">D&amp;r Greenway</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nussbaum, Debra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rawlyk, William C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E6DE173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Light at the End of the Trail</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Light at the End of the Trail</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA NUSSBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nussbaum, Debra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on 20-mile trail in Sourland Mountains of Central New Jersey; nonprofit D&amp;R Greenway Land Trust land preservation director William Rawlyk says about 90 percent of land for trail has been bought by state, municipalities and preservation groups in last two decades and only about a dozen small parcels are needed to fill gaps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 20-MILE trail through the largest remaining tract of contiguous forest in Central New Jersey could finally be reality in the next five years.</p>
        <p>About 90 percent of the land for the trail in the Sourland Mountains has been bought by the state, municipalities and preservation groups in the last two decades, and only about a dozen small parcels of land are needed to fill in the gaps, said William C. Rawlyk, the director of land preservation for the D &amp; R Greenway Land Trust, a nonprofit group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 20-mile trail through the largest remaining tract of contiguous forest in Central New Jersey could finally be reality in the next five years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 20-MILE trail through the largest remaining tract of contiguous forest in Central New Jersey could finally be reality in the next five years.</p>
        <p>About 90 percent of the land for the trail in the Sourland Mountains has been bought by the state, municipalities and preservation groups in the last two decades, and only about a dozen small parcels of land are needed to fill in the gaps, said William C. Rawlyk, the director of land preservation for the D &amp; R Greenway Land Trust, a nonprofit group.</p>
        <p>Since 1992, D &amp; R Greenway (formerly the Delaware &amp; Raritan Greenway) has completed 86 land transactions in the Sourlands and bought 4,313 acres with $41 million in public and private money, said Linda J. Mead, the group's executive director. The trail will run between Lambertville on the Delaware River in Hunterdon County and Belle Mead in Somerset County, and go through Mercer County.</p>
        <p>''I was absolutely amazed when I first drove to the Sourlands,'' Ms. Mead said. ''It's like being in another world. It's another culture and environment.''</p>
        <p>John Flynn, the administrator for the State Department of Environmental Protection's Green Acres Program, called the Sourlands ''close-to-home wilderness.'' He said $26 million from the Garden State Preservation Trust Fund had been spent on Sourlands property in the last six years because its preservation is so important.</p>
        <p>Only 20 minutes from Princeton and the hectic Route 1 corridor, the Sourlands is 90 square miles of forest with 10 streams. It is the breeding ground for more than 65 neotropical migratory birds and threatened species of frogs and home to animals like barred owls, black bears and bobcats, Mr. Rawlyk said.</p>
        <p>The land is also steeped in history. George Washington and his troops marched through the Sourlands, and John Hart, a signer of the Declaration of Independence, hid there while fleeing the British in the Revolutionary War. The Lindbergh estate is also in the Sourlands area.</p>
        <p>D &amp; R Greenway began its efforts to buy and preserve land in the Sourlands in 1989, using state grants, county and township funds and private money. ''Our purpose was to preserve the natural landscape,'' Mr. Rawlyk said.</p>
        <p>Some deals were done with partners. The Nature Conservancy and the 3M Company (which donated $1.5 million) teamed with county officials and helped buy some of the land.</p>
        <p>The Sourlands Planning Council, a nonprofit group, has done much of the environmental planning and public education about the importance of the region and worked to gather support for the area, Mr. Rawlyk said.</p>
        <p>About six years ago, D &amp; R Greenway began plans for connecting trails to create one trail. ''It was natural we would want to connect it as a trail,'' Mr. Rawlyk said. There have been no court battles for the land. ''We only deal with willing sellers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still, it will probably be at least 10 years before the trail is fully cleared in such dense forest with volunteer help, Ms. Mead and Mr. Rawlyk said. There are trails now that hikers can use, but they are not connected. (Information on completed trails can be found at www.njtrails.org.)</p>
        <p>There is ''overwhelming support'' for preserving the Sourlands and for a trail, said C. Larry Tatsch, the mayor of East Amwell Township, about a third of which is in the Sourlands. ''We are very much into the program,'' he said. ''It's a great idea.''</p>
        <p>Though the Highlands and Pinelands are larger, the Sourlands still has great significance, said John G. Trontis, the director of the Hunterdon County parks department.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't mean that you throw out a smaller diamond,'' he said. ''It's a diamond in the rough and an important preservation area.''</p>
        <p>HIKING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
