<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEST SELLERS: April 08, 2007</title>
    <meta content="Besthard.nonfiction" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838986"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEST SELLERS: April 08, 2007</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 24, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>NANCY CUNARD: Heiress, Muse, Political Idealist, by Lois Gordon. (Columbia University, $32.50.) A biography of Cunard (1896-1965), a poet, publisher, journalist and tireless supporter of the disenfranchised.</p>
        <p>THE SECOND CHILD: Poems, by Deborah Garrison. (Random House, $19.95.) A former New Yorker editor celebrates motherhood and domestic life.</p>
        <p>GHOSTS OF SPAIN, by Giles Tremlett. (Walker, $26.95.) The legacy of Francoism: part modern social history, part travelogue.</p>
        <p>CHANCE AND CIRCUMSTANCE, by Carolyn Brown. (Knopf, $37.50) Twenty years of dancing with Merce Cunningham and John Cage.</p>
        <p>CRAZY '08, by Cait Murphy. (Smithsonian/Collins, $24.95.) An argument that 1908 -- the last time the Chicago Cubs won the World Series -- was the greatest year in baseball history.</p>
        <p>ONCE UPON A COUNTRY, by Sari Nusseibeh with Anthony David. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $27.50.) A nuanced assessment of his country's national life from a Palestinan scholar.</p>
        <p>COLLECTED PLAYS &amp; WRITINGS ON THEATER, by Thornton Wilder. (Library of America, $40.) An anthology of theatrical writing by a great and misunderstood playwright.</p>
        <p>ASTRID &amp; VERONIKA, by Linda Olsson. (Penguin, paper, $14.) A writer from New Zealand moves to a remote Swedish village.</p>
        <p>IN THE FOOTSTEPS OF THE PROPHET, by Tariq Ramadan. (Oxford University, $23.) A biography of Muhammad by a Muslim scholar who has been barred from the United States argues that Islam and Western democracy are compatible.</p>
        <p>WHY THE FRENCH DON'T LIKE HEADSCARVES, by John R. Bowen. (Princeton University, $27.95.) An account of the controversy that culminated in a 2004 law forbidding conspicuous religious apparel in French schools.</p>
        <p>RIPPLE EFFECT: New and Selected Poems, by Elaine Equi. (Coffee House, $18.) A thoughtful, curious poet explores the link between heart and mind.The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ended March 24, at many thousands of venues where a wide range of general interest books are sold nationwide. These include hundreds of independent book retailers (statistically weighted to represent all such outlets); national, regional and local chains; online and multimedia entertainment retailers; university, gift, supermarket, discount, department stores and newsstands. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger () indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>NANCY CUNARD: Heiress, Muse, Political Idealist, by Lois Gordon. (Columbia University, $32.50.) A biography of Cunard (1896-1965), a poet, publisher, journalist and tireless supporter of the disenfranchised.</p>
        <p>THE SECOND CHILD: Poems, by Deborah Garrison. (Random House, $19.95.) A former New Yorker editor celebrates motherhood and domestic life.</p>
        <p>GHOSTS OF SPAIN, by Giles Tremlett. (Walker, $26.95.) The legacy of Francoism: part modern social history, part travelogue.</p>
        <p>CHANCE AND CIRCUMSTANCE, by Carolyn Brown. (Knopf, $37.50) Twenty years of dancing with Merce Cunningham and John Cage.</p>
        <p>CRAZY '08, by Cait Murphy. (Smithsonian/Collins, $24.95.) An argument that 1908 -- the last time the Chicago Cubs won the World Series -- was the greatest year in baseball history.</p>
        <p>ONCE UPON A COUNTRY, by Sari Nusseibeh with Anthony David. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $27.50.) A nuanced assessment of his country's national life from a Palestinan scholar.</p>
        <p>COLLECTED PLAYS &amp; WRITINGS ON THEATER, by Thornton Wilder. (Library of America, $40.) An anthology of theatrical writing by a great and misunderstood playwright.</p>
        <p>ASTRID &amp; VERONIKA, by Linda Olsson. (Penguin, paper, $14.) A writer from New Zealand moves to a remote Swedish village.</p>
        <p>IN THE FOOTSTEPS OF THE PROPHET, by Tariq Ramadan. (Oxford University, $23.) A biography of Muhammad by a Muslim scholar who has been barred from the United States argues that Islam and Western democracy are compatible.</p>
        <p>WHY THE FRENCH DON'T LIKE HEADSCARVES, by John R. Bowen. (Princeton University, $27.95.) An account of the controversy that culminated in a 2004 law forbidding conspicuous religious apparel in French schools.</p>
        <p>RIPPLE EFFECT: New and Selected Poems, by Elaine Equi. (Coffee House, $18.) A thoughtful, curious poet explores the link between heart and mind.The full reviews of these and other recent books are on the Web: nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>FICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>34</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>NINETEEN MINUTES, by Jodi Picoult. (Atria, $26.95.) The aftermath of a high school shooting reveals the fault lines in a small New Hampshire town.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>SHOPAHOLIC &amp; BABY, by Sophie Kinsella. (Dial, $24.) Becky is pregnant, and the obstetrician turns out to be her husband's ex-girlfriend.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>DADDY'S GIRL, by Lisa Scottoline. (HarperCollins, $25.95.) A law professor caught in a prison riot must defend herself when she is unjustly accused of murder.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>WHITETHORN WOODS, by Maeve Binchy. (Knopf, $25.95.) A proposed highway threatens the existence of a religious shrine in a rural Irish village.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>FOR A FEW DEMONS MORE, by Kim Harrison. (Eos/HarperCollins, $21.95.) A witch owns an ancient artifact that may stop a serial killer or ignite a gang war; the fifth book in the Hollows series.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>STEP ON A CRACK, by James Patterson and Michael Ledwidge. (Little, Brown, $27.99.) A detective raising 10 children alone must rescue 34 high-level hostages.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>SISTERS, by Danielle Steel. (Delacorte, $27.) After a family tragedy, four sisters with very different lives decide to share a Manhattan brownstone.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>HEART-SHAPED BOX, by Joe Hill. (Morrow, $24.95.) An aging rock star who buys what's advertised online as a ghost to add to his collection of macabre objects is stunned when it turns out to be the real thing.</p>
        <p>9*</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>THE DOUBLE BIND, by Chris Bohjalian. (Shaye Areheart, $25.) A young woman who works at a homeless shelter struggles to understand the mysterious photographs taken by a recently deceased resident.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>WHAT THE DEAD KNOW, by Laura Lippman. (Morrow, $24.95.) A woman claims to be one of two sisters who disappeared mysteriously 30 years earlier.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>THE WATCHMAN, by Robert Crais. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.95.) A former Los Angeles police officer becomes the bodyguard of a troubled heiress marked for death.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>BURNING BRIGHT, by Tracy Chevalier. (Dutton, $24.95.) In Georgian London, the poet William Blake befriends two neighborhood chldren.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>INNOCENT IN DEATH, by J. D. Robb. (Putnam, $25.95) Lt. Eve Dallas investigates the murder of an apparently inoffensive private-school history teacher; by Nora Roberts, writing pseudonymously.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>FOR ONE MORE DAY, by Mitch Albom. (Hyperion, $21.95.) A troubled man gets a last chance to reconnect and restore his relationship with his dead mother.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE POST-BIRTHDAY WORLD, by Lionel Shriver. (HarperCollins, $25.95.) In parallel narratives, a London woman stays with her boyfriend and leaves him for another.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>NONFICTION</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>IN AN INSTANT, by Lee and Bob Woodruff. (Random House, $25.95.) The aftermath of the ABC co-anchor's traumatic brain injury in Iraq in 2006.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>GRACE (EVENTUALLY), by Anne Lamott. (Riverhead/Penguin, $24.95.) Essays about faith and forgiveness.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>HOW DOCTORS THINK, by Jerome Groopman. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) A doctor and New Yorker staff writer describes how doctors arrive at diagnoses and what patients can do to make sure they don't err.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>A LONG WAY GONE, by Ishmael Beah. (Sarah Crichton/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) A former child soldier from Sierra Leone describes his drug-crazed killing spree and his return to humanity.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>THE AUDACITY OF HOPE, by Barack Obama. (Crown, $25.) The Illinois junior senator proposes that Americans move beyond their political divisions.</p>
        <p>6*</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>34</p>
        <p>I FEEL BAD ABOUT MY NECK, by Nora Ephron. (Knopf, $19.95.) A witty look at aging from a novelist and screenwriter (''When Harry Met Sally'').</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>INFIDEL, by Ayaan Hirsi Ali. (Free Press, $26.) A memoir by the Somali-born advocate for Muslim immigrant women, once a member of the Dutch Parliament, who has been threatened with death.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>THE HARDCORE DIARIES, by Mick Foley. (World Wrestling Entertainment/Pocket, $24.) The former professional wrestling champion discusses his fame and his life at World Wrestling Entertainment.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>BLACKWATER, by Jeremy Scahill. (Nation/Avalon, $26.95.) An account of the private army that has been deployed by the government in Afghanistan and Iraq.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>SOMEBODY'S GOTTA SAY IT, by Neal Boortz (HC/HarperCollins, $25.95.) A radio talk-show host discusses government, poverty, prayer in the schools, race relations, gun control and other topics.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>SECOND CHANCE, by Zbigniew Brzezinski. (Basic, $26.95.) The former National Security adviser discusses how America can regain the global power and prestige squandered by its three post-cold-war presidents.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>98</p>
        <p>FREAKONOMICS, by Steven D. Levitt and Stephen J. Dubner. (Morrow, $27.95.) A maverick scholar and a journalist apply economic theory to nearly everything.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>THE GOD DELUSION, by Richard Dawkins. (Houghton Mifflin, $27.) An Oxford scientist asserts that belief in God is irrational.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>RELIGIOUS LITERACY, by Stephen Prothero. (HarperSanFrancisco, $24.95.) What Americans need to know about the world's religions and their own.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>THE INNOCENT MAN, by John Grisham. (Doubleday, $28.95.) Grisham's first nonfiction book concerns a man sentenced to death for a crime he did not commit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
