<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Isles Beat Flyers, Then Wait for Help to Arrive</title>
    <meta content="08isles" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/hockey/08isles.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Smyth, Ryan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Isles Beat Flyers, Then Wait for Help to Arrive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Isles Beat Flyers, Then Wait for Help to Arrive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Islanders left wing Ryan Smyth, his hair still wet from a shower, strode out of Wachovia Center shortly after 4 p.m. Saturday and stepped onto a white bus with a leprechaun painted on the side.</p>
        <p>The Islanders seem to be catching a break on every leg of a strange journey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Islanders can clinch the final Eastern Conference playoff berth if they defeat the Devils on Sunday in the final game of the regular season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Islanders left wing Ryan Smyth, his hair still wet from a shower, strode out of Wachovia Center shortly after 4 p.m. Saturday and stepped onto a white bus with a leprechaun painted on the side.</p>
        <p>The Islanders seem to be catching a break on every leg of a strange journey.</p>
        <p>They defeated the Philadelphia Flyers, 4-2, to stay in contention for a playoff berth that did not even seem possible a week ago. The Islanders then gathered at a Manhattan restaurant later Saturday to watch Toronto beat Montreal, 6-5.</p>
        <p>That combination of results meant the Islanders (39-30-12) can clinch the final Eastern Conference playoff berth if they defeat the Devils on Sunday in the final game of the regular season. If Montreal had won Saturday, the Islanders would have been eliminated. If the Islanders lose Sunday, Toronto gets the playoff spot.</p>
        <p>Smyth was asked if he was enjoying being in a playoff race decided at virtually the last minute.</p>
        <p>''How could it not be?'' Smyth said. ''No question, this is fun.''</p>
        <p>It certainly beats the alternative of having no shot to make the playoffs. Smyth was acquired Feb. 27 from the Edmonton Oilers, who will finish the season nearly 30 points out of a playoff spot.</p>
        <p>''We seem to open doors,'' Smyth said of the Islanders. ''We seem to find ways to create opportunities.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders seem most pleased that their push for a playoff berth -- which seemed to be all but over after losses to Buffalo and Ottawa on March 30 and 31 -- has led them to rediscover their resourcefulness.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we've been playing desperate hockey these last three games; we've been playing controlled hockey,'' said Ted Nolan, the Islanders' first-year coach.</p>
        <p>With Wade Dubielewicz again replacing the injured Rick DiPietro in goal, the Islanders won their third game in five days. The Flyers tested them, scoring a short-handed goal with 62 seconds left to close to 3-2.</p>
        <p>But Islanders defenseman Tom Poti took a pass from Smyth with 29 seconds remaining and scored an empty-net goal. With that, the Islanders had earned at least a six-hour reprieve from playoff elimination, and they planned to enjoy every minute of it.</p>
        <p>''It's exciting, it's nerve-wracking, it's just great to be in the fight,'' Islanders defenseman Sean Hill said. ''That's all you can ask for.''</p>
        <p>The Flyers (21-48-12) gave the Islanders a chance simply by starting goaltender Antero Niittymaki, who has not won a game since Feb. 17. Philadelphia will end the worst season in the franchise's 40-year history at home Sunday against Buffalo. The Sabres clinched the Presidents' Trophy for the best overall record by beating Washington on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia gave the Islanders nine power-play opportunities Saturday, the first less than two minutes into the game. Flyers defenseman Randy Jones was called for hooking, and Miroslav Satan gave the Islanders a 1-0 lead 3 minutes 36 seconds into the period by firing a shot over Niittymaki's right shoulder.</p>
        <p>Alexei Yashin scored another power-play goal 70 seconds into the second period with a hard shot from the face-off circle that sailed over Niittymaki's glove. Yashin, who has missed 22 games because of injuries, has four goals in the past seven games.</p>
        <p>Richard Park, the center on the Islanders' fourth line, shoveled a rebound past Niittymaki 9:58 into the second period to stretch the lead to 3-0. Four of his eight goals this season have come against the Flyers.</p>
        <p>With Philadelphia on a power play late in the second period, Simon Gagné scored his 40th goal. The Flyers cut the Islanders' lead to 3-2 with 1:02 left in the game when Mike Richards swerved around Hill to beat Dubielewicz.</p>
        <p>But with two Flyers in the penalty box, Poti sealed the victory. Dubielewicz, who stopped 28 shots for his third straight victory, said the Islanders had buckled down defensively in the past week.</p>
        <p>''Whether it's the fact that I'm in net or not, that's what we have to do to be successful,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dubielewicz said he would use a voodoo doll against Montreal, if he had one. Poti joked that he would stop by the hotel gift shop to buy a rabbit's foot. Smyth said he planned to watch the Toronto-Montreal game wearing a Leafs hat.</p>
        <p>''Root for them for a couple of hours,'' he said, ''then take it right back off.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
