<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Clinches Victory; Will Meet Sweden in Semis</title>
    <meta content="08tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/tennis/08tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Davis Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Sweden</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bryan, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2DC143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Clinches Victory; Will Meet Sweden in Semis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Clinches Victory; Will Meet Sweden in Semis</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
      <dateline>WINSTON-SALEM, N.C., April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andy Roddick, James Blake, and Bob and Mike Bryan took turns circling the tennis court inside Lawrence Joel Veterans Memorial Coliseum on Saturday, waving the American flag in front of a roaring capacity crowd. It was a victory parade for the United States Davis Cup team, which clinched its quarterfinal against Spain with a doubles victory by the Bryan twins.</p>
        <p>Their victory gave the United States a decisive 3-0 lead in the best-of-five match. But it was not easy for the Bryans, the top-ranked doubles team in the world. They labored to beat Feliciano López and Fernando Verdasco, 7-5, 6-3, 3-6, 7-6 (5).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Davis Cup team clinched its quarterfinal against Spain with a doubles victory by tBob and Mike Bryan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andy Roddick, James Blake, and Bob and Mike Bryan took turns circling the tennis court inside Lawrence Joel Veterans Memorial Coliseum on Saturday, waving the American flag in front of a roaring capacity crowd. It was a victory parade for the United States Davis Cup team, which clinched its quarterfinal against Spain with a doubles victory by the Bryan twins.</p>
        <p>Their victory gave the United States a decisive 3-0 lead in the best-of-five match. But it was not easy for the Bryans, the top-ranked doubles team in the world. They labored to beat Feliciano López and Fernando Verdasco, 7-5, 6-3, 3-6, 7-6 (5).</p>
        <p>At one point, Roddick got up from his seat on the sideline and pumped his fists, leading chants of ''U-S-A, U-S-A'' that rolled through the crowd of 14,453. The United States players credited the raucous fans with carrying the team after the Bryans faltered in the third set and struggled in the fourth.</p>
        <p>''I was so nervous there,'' Roddick said to the fans after the doubles match. ''We're all going out tonight, so come along and join us. What do you think?''</p>
        <p>Roddick will rest Sunday, when the teams play two meaningless singles matches to close out the quarterfinal.</p>
        <p>The United States will next meet Sweden in the semifinals, which will be played Sept. 21-23 in Sweden. The Swedes clinched their quarterfinal against Argentina earlier Saturday with a victory in the doubles for a 3-0 lead.</p>
        <p>Confidence is growing that the United States finally has the team to win it all for the first time since 1995.</p>
        <p>''This is certainly one of our best shots in at least the last 10 years, absolutely,'' said Arlen Kantarian, the chief executive of professional tennis for the United States Tennis Association.</p>
        <p>The United States overcame some concerns heading into the quarterfinal and surprisingly dominated Spain. Roddick, ranked No. 3 in the world, arrived with a strained hamstring but played through it to defeat Verdasco in singles on Friday. Blake arrived in Winston-Salem ranked No. 9 but in a slump. Still, he put away No. 6 Tommy Robredo in straight sets. Spain's top player, Rafael Nadal, skipped the quarterfinal because of an injured foot.</p>
        <p>The Bryans came into the match with a 10-1 career record in Davis Cup play and took care of the first two sets. But the Spaniards started to take control in the third.</p>
        <p>''I think we were more aggressive,'' Verdasco said. ''We was playing so much better than the beginning of the match.''</p>
        <p>The Spaniards broke Bob Bryan's serve in the sixth game of the third set and held from there to extend the match to a fourth set. The Bryans went ahead, 6-4, in a tie breaker in the fourth on a winner off the net cord by Mike Bryan. They closed out the match with Bob Bryan's winning volley on the 12th point.</p>
        <p>''It was a scary match,'' Mike Bryan said. ''They were playing with no pressure after we got up two sets to love.</p>
        <p>''It felt so good to finish off that last tie breaker. Anything can happen in the fifth.''</p>
        <p>SWEDEN AND GERMANY ADVANCE -- Sweden and Germany secured spots in the Davis Cup semifinals by building 3-0 leads in their matchups Saturday. Russia won its doubles match to take a 2-1 lead against France.</p>
        <p>At Goteborg, Sweden, Jonas Bjorkman and Thomas Johansson rallied to beat Guillermo Cañas and David Nalbandian of Argentina, 4-6, 7-6 (4), 6-2, 6-3.</p>
        <p>At Ostend, Belgium, Alexander Waske and Michael Kohlmann beat Olivier and Christophe Rochus of Belgium, 4-6, 6-2, 6-3, 6-1, to lead Germany to its first Davis Cup semifinal since 1995. (AP)</p>
        <p>HIP HAMPERS HINGIS -- Martina Hingis said Saturday that she would not compete in the Family Circle Cup next week in Charleston, S.C., because of a hip injury. (AP)</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
