<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Captain Of the Low Seas</title>
    <meta content="08sail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/thecity/08sail.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CITY PEOPLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Peking (Sailing Ship)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wavertree (Sailing Ship)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">South Street Seaport Museum (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansen, Lars</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giddens, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">South Street Seaport Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E7D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Captain Of the Low Seas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Captain of the Low Seas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH GIDDENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Giddens, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elizabeth Giddens City People essay on Lars Hansen, 83, who reigned for three decades as king of New York City's South Street Seaport and master rigger of seaport's historic vessels, Peking and Wavertree; Hansen is recovering from stroke in Queens nursing home; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BETWEEN the recent migration of the Fulton Fish Market and the impending arrival of Santiago Calatrava's stack of ultra-luxurious condos, the South Street Seaport is somewhat short on true grit these days. It is shorter still with the recent and possibly permanent departure of Lars Hansen.</p>
        <p>Though currently laid up in a Queens nursing home after a stroke, stranded among landlubbers, linoleum and Muzak, Mr. Hansen reigned for 30 years as king of the still-gritty side of the seaport. He was the master rigger of the seaport's historic vessels, and he remains a sailors' sailor. In the collective imagination of the seaport's salts, Mr. Hansen is a Paul Bunyan of the sea. They speak of his strength in terms like ''gentle giant,'' and of his kindness in phrases typically reserved for the canonization process.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though berthed after a 30-year run, he still reigns as king of the Seaport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BETWEEN the recent migration of the Fulton Fish Market and the impending arrival of Santiago Calatrava's stack of ultra-luxurious condos, the South Street Seaport is somewhat short on true grit these days. It is shorter still with the recent and possibly permanent departure of Lars Hansen.</p>
        <p>Though currently laid up in a Queens nursing home after a stroke, stranded among landlubbers, linoleum and Muzak, Mr. Hansen reigned for 30 years as king of the still-gritty side of the seaport. He was the master rigger of the seaport's historic vessels, and he remains a sailors' sailor. In the collective imagination of the seaport's salts, Mr. Hansen is a Paul Bunyan of the sea. They speak of his strength in terms like ''gentle giant,'' and of his kindness in phrases typically reserved for the canonization process.</p>
        <p>But when he is confronted with the charge that he is a living legend, his modesty is offended.</p>
        <p>''Bah,'' he growls, and proceeds to dismiss such praise in unprintable terms.</p>
        <p>Like any seaman worthy of the name, Mr. Hansen is capable of some salty language. But he surely qualifies as a romantic figure. A strikingly handsome Dane with twinkling hazel eyes and a silver mustache, he spent his teenage years resisting the Nazis, took to the sea for the heyday of the merchant marine, and settled in New York to become both an embodiment of the nautical virtues and an éminence grise of the city's jazz scene.</p>
        <p>Every hero deserves a dramatic stage, and for the past three decades, Mr. Hansen has made his home in the master cabin of the Peking, the enormous turn-of the-century square-rigger that has become a familiar part of the Lower Manhattan skyline. He was invited aboard by the South Street Seaport Museum when it hired him to restore the then-derelict ship and the Wavertree, its nearly as shoddy sister, as part of the museum's efforts to revive the seaport.</p>
        <p>And so Mr. Hansen took up the Herculean task of rigging the 300-foot, four-masted monsters with eight miles of rope and wire, two acres of canvas and 34 spars, or beams that support the sails. The spars weigh as much as six tons.</p>
        <p>His days thus had much in common with those of an 18th-century tar: he swabbed the deck, hoisted the spars, spliced massive cables with a four-foot marlinespike, tarred everything in sight, and generally performed tasks so archaic and arcane that their very names have fallen out of the language -- worming, parceling, serving -- all with the hulking modernity of Downtown Manhattan as an inspiring and incongruous backdrop.</p>
        <p>Square-riggers like the Peking and the Wavertree are akin to preposterously tall jungle gyms for adults, and Mr. Hansen was always happy to be aloft. ''You couldn't keep him on the ground,'' said Jim Clements, a ship's carpenter who once worked for the seaport.</p>
        <p>The Peking was indisputably his lair, and he could navigate its crazy maze more quickly than anyone else, climbing many times a day the equivalent of a 17-story building via skinny rope ladders, with no harness and no net.</p>
        <p>The other day, as he sat in his wheelchair in the Whitestone nursing home, where he has been since last fall, wearing a T-shirt that reads, ''Wavertree: hard work, long hours, no pay,'' Mr. Hansen recalled his labors with a laugh and a sigh.</p>
        <p>''I do miss it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hansen also misses jazz. He retired from the merchant marine to settle in the city because his passion for the music trumped his love of the sea.</p>
        <p>Once here, he set about introducing his fellow seamen to jazz, and serving as host to his countless musician friends at the seaport. His Peking cabin, an exquisitely appointed stateroom with a sweeping 12-porthole view, may have been the finest private jazz venue south of Canal.</p>
        <p>''Everybody knew him,'' said Johnnie Williams, baritone saxophonist in Count Basie's band, ''and everybody loved him.''</p>
        <p>But music did not hamper his labors. ''He did a phenomenal amount of work on those ships,'' said Charlie Deroko, the museum's former waterfront director. ''He was unstoppable. He'd be up at first light, work 12 hours, bathe with the fire hose, go out until 3, and be right back up the rigging the next morning.''</p>
        <p>According to Jack Putnam, who bunked in a nearby cabin, Mr. Hansen's much younger drinking partners used to stumble in to work hours later, ''looking like they'd been passed through a knothole the wrong way twice.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hansen's beneficent sway over the Peking and its environs extended to just last year, a few months before his 83rd birthday. In the final years of tending his fief, he managed to put his personal stamp on the pursuits of old age.</p>
        <p>INSTEAD of getting about on a senior scooter, for example, Mr. Hansen used a forklift, and he was famous for driving it places forklifts have no business going, including but not limited to a busted section of pier that promptly collapsed, sending him and the forklift into the water with such violence that both had to be sent off for repairs.</p>
        <p>The huge floating pier between the Wavertree and the Peking, off limits to lubbers, was known as Lars's Rust Garden, and he puttered there daily with his forklift, tending his massive, exotic metal specimens.</p>
        <p>Every so often he took out a skiff to pick up the garbage that collects around the piers, using one oar with the grace of a gondolier. And well into his 70s, Mr. Hansen was capable of sliding hand over hand down a 90-foot cable at a 15-degree pitch.</p>
        <p>But now, for the first time in his life, Mr. Hansen is landlocked. And though he persists in calling his shared room in the nursing home his ''cabin,'' his real cabin remains untouched -- a testament to the esteem in which he is held by his countless admirers.</p>
        <p>One of their number is Pilar Montero, doyenne of Montero's in Brooklyn Heights, an old sailors' bar a block from the harbor on Atlantic Avenue, who said Mr. Hansen used to bring her flowers every year for her birthday.</p>
        <p>''Such a lovely man,'' Ms. Montero said, sighing. ''He never forgot.''</p>
        <p>CITY PEOPLE Elizabeth Giddens is a former senior editor of Harper's Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Giddens is a former senior editor of Harper's Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
