<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>STREETSCAPES/West 56 th Street; One Dances the Cancan, The Other the Minuet</title>
    <meta content="08scap" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/realestate/08scap.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Streetscapes | West 56th Street"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Landmarks Preservation Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edey, Frederick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollings, Henry B (1854-1938)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDF173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>STREETSCAPES/West 56 th Street; One Dances the Cancan, The Other the Minuet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Dances the Cancan, the Other the Minuet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gray, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Streetscapes column on history of town houses on West 56th Street, built side by side in late 1800s and early 1900s by business partners Frederick Edey and Henry B Hollings; 12 West 56th Street was designated by Landmarks Preservation Commission in 1984 and No 10 is under consideration; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE town houses at 10 and 12 West 56th Street could not be more different. One is a sumptuously French essay built entirely in limestone, the other a subdued Georgian-style brick residence. But they are inextricably linked, constructed almost at the same time by two business partners, Frederick Edey and Henry B. Hollins, who was sometimes known as Harry. Now, a circle of sorts is closing as the Landmarks Preservation Commission, which designated 12 West 56th Street in 1984, is aiming to do the same for its neighbor.</p>
        <p>The men were partners in H. B. Hollins &amp; Company, a Wall Street banking house established by Mr. Hollins in 1878. They commuted to their offices from Islip, on Long Island, and the firm was favored by the Morgan banking interests. In 1899 Mr. Hollins bought three lots on the south side of 56th Street, just off Fifth Avenue, an area nearly full with mansions and town houses. He immediately began work on his own double-lot house at No. 12, and sold the third parcel, No. 10, to his partner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The town houses at 10 and 12 West 56th Street could not be more different, but they are inextricably linked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE town houses at 10 and 12 West 56th Street could not be more different. One is a sumptuously French essay built entirely in limestone, the other a subdued Georgian-style brick residence. But they are inextricably linked, constructed almost at the same time by two business partners, Frederick Edey and Henry B. Hollins, who was sometimes known as Harry. Now, a circle of sorts is closing as the Landmarks Preservation Commission, which designated 12 West 56th Street in 1984, is aiming to do the same for its neighbor.</p>
        <p>The men were partners in H. B. Hollins &amp; Company, a Wall Street banking house established by Mr. Hollins in 1878. They commuted to their offices from Islip, on Long Island, and the firm was favored by the Morgan banking interests. In 1899 Mr. Hollins bought three lots on the south side of 56th Street, just off Fifth Avenue, an area nearly full with mansions and town houses. He immediately began work on his own double-lot house at No. 12, and sold the third parcel, No. 10, to his partner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edey had to wait to begin construction until 1901, when a setback requirement expired, but Mr. Hollins's property was unencumbered by this restriction, and he was able to start right away. The architect Stanford White produced an utterly correct Georgian-style house of uncharacteristic sobriety. While not severe or even plain, the red brick and marble facade had everything perfectly in place. It might have been a Boston women's club.</p>
        <p>White anticipated the Edey town house with a small court on the left side of the Hollins house. He gave it a setback wing, and repeated on the sidewall the decorative details of the main facade.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Edey was ready to begin, he hired the new firm of Warren &amp; Wetmore, which had become famous for its extravagant galleon-front New York Yacht Club on 44th Street. It provided the dash that might otherwise have come from White, producing a facade that could have been picked up from the streets of Paris. All in limestone, the house is dominated by a lush Palladian window on the second floor, with an intricate medallion in the center of the arch; on the ground floor a central doorway was flanked by two bull's-eye windows. The two houses are paired in an uneasy dance, one doing the cancan, the other a minuet.</p>
        <p>Indeed, although White had offered a friendly deference in his design, Warren &amp; Wetmore treated the Hollins property as a stranger. It gave the limestone house no cornice return, balcony, large window or other evidence of architectural friendship.</p>
        <p>In 1903 the Edeys were able to move in. Although Mr. Edey and Mr. Hollins had several club memberships in common, they do not appear to have been related by blood or marriage, and although both were named frequently in the society columns, it appears that they never gave a joint party, ball, charity benefit, dinner or other event. Indeed, in a decade of articles in The Brooklyn Daily Eagle and The New York Times, there is none suggesting they were in any way connected, and certainly not with the intimacy that a joint house construction project would suggest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hollins seems to have declared Islip his official residence, and responded to the census taker there. But the Edeys were in occupancy at 10 West 56th when the enumerator for the 1905 New York State census arrived. The census form lists Frederick Edey, along with his wife, Birdsall; their daughter, Julia; and 10 servants.</p>
        <p>West 56th off Fifth was one of the power blocks: The leather merchant Lewis Lapham built a house at No. 15; Arthur Lehman, a member of the Lehman Brothers banking family, built at No. 31; and Henry Seligman, another investment banker, built his grand house at No. 30.</p>
        <p>By 1910 Mr. Edey had left the Hollins firm, which had been bailed out of several scrapes by J. P. Morgan. He died in March 1913, seven months before the Hollins firm collapsed. In 1914 Mr. Hollins sold the 56th Street house to the Calumet Club, a social organization.</p>
        <p>Change was sweeping Midtown, as shops and even garment factories took over areas thought to be immune to commercial invasion for decades, and in 1916 the Edeys sold No. 10 to Frances Spingold, who operated there as Mme. Frances, a dressmaker.</p>
        <p>In 1924 the Calumet Club had the architect J. E. R. Carpenter rather neatly alter the Hollins house, converting the central entrance into a window and pushing the entryway off to the side. Both houses went through further changes of ownership: In 1943 the Hollins house was a Salvation Army club for servicemen, and in 1947 it was bought by the government of Argentina; it is now the Argentine Consulate.</p>
        <p>In 1990 the Japanese firm Felissimo took over the Edey house -- whose ground floor had been widened -- but there were few major changes to the town houses on the block until last year, when four similar houses, Nos. 31 through 37, were demolished for new construction.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the Landmarks Preservation Commission proposed the Edey house for designation. Haruko Smith, director of Felissimo, said she was not upset by the prospect. ''We happen to be very much in love with this building,'' she said.</p>
        <p>So the Edey-Hollins odd couple could well survive indefinitely.</p>
        <p>Streetscapes | West 56th Street E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: streetscapes@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
