<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Grip of Octopus At a Greek Taverna</title>
    <meta content="08NJdineNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08NJdine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/HIGHLAND PARK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pithari Taverna (Highland Park, NJ, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Karla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EED6163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Grip of Octopus At a Greek Taverna</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Grip of Octopus at a Greek Taverna</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARLA COOK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cook, Karla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karla Cook reviews Pithari Taverna restaurant in Highland Park, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF one dish can represent a restaurant, at Pithari Taverna it would be the octopus. It was one fat tentacle on a blue plate, in a clear pool of oil and vinegar specked with oregano. Fresh from the grill, it was fragrant, almost fork tender and luscious.</p>
        <p>The octopus that night was just as delicious as it had been a month earlier, so it is likely to be the same next month, when the weather may be warm enough that you can sit on the patio and pretend that the sound of nearby traffic is the Aegean, lapping at the shore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If one dish can represent a restaurant, at Pithari Taverna in Highland Park it would be the octopus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF one dish can represent a restaurant, at Pithari Taverna it would be the octopus. It was one fat tentacle on a blue plate, in a clear pool of oil and vinegar specked with oregano. Fresh from the grill, it was fragrant, almost fork tender and luscious.</p>
        <p>The octopus that night was just as delicious as it had been a month earlier, so it is likely to be the same next month, when the weather may be warm enough that you can sit on the patio and pretend that the sound of nearby traffic is the Aegean, lapping at the shore.</p>
        <p>Until then, the 60-seat indoor dining room works fine, despite its popularity and sometimes longish waits, even with reservations. An open kitchen tucked into a corner provides constant movement. A flat screen opposite the minuscule vestibule displays footage of Greek attractions.</p>
        <p>Tassos and Chrisanthe Stefanopoulos opened their restaurant last September after developing a clientele, expertise and passion for the idea through their Greek foods shop next door.</p>
        <p>The menu is spiral-bound and laminated, a tidy two-pager with a page of daily specials tucked into it.</p>
        <p>Appetizers make up almost a page, with many hits among them. Saganaki was a gooey, salty slab of hot kefalograviera cheese (though we opted out of the tableside flaming because the server was concerned for her eyebrows). Bakalao skordalia was a combination of cod fried to salty succulence with a mild version of the potato-based classic skordalia, which contained garlic, lemon, olive oil and glykadi vinegar; the beets on the plate were a tasty surprise.</p>
        <p>Lamb sausage, with pork, allspice and orange peel, was particularly satisfying tucked into a hot pita. An epilogi plate was a generous sampler: two roasted gyro meats -- mixtures of lamb with beef and pork -- along with spreads of tzatziki (cucumber-yogurt), eggplant and caviar, as well as feta, dolmades (stuffed grape leaves), roasted red peppers and olives.</p>
        <p>Melitzanes salata was a delicious dip of wood-broiled eggplant peeled and mashed with feta, olive oil, oregano, parsley, roasted red peppers, nuts and vinegar. A heap of horta, with the deep green tendrils of sautéed dandelions twining around one another, held only a hint of bitterness.</p>
        <p>Did I mention the octopus?</p>
        <p>Avgolemono was a fine version of the richly flavored egg and lemon soup. It was slightly slippery, which was not a problem. Greek salad was adequate but should be addictive when made with vine-ripe tomatoes this summer and served al fresco.</p>
        <p>Several main dishes stood out. The fagri, a Mediterranean white snapper, was well flavored from its marinade of olive oil and oregano and its grilling over a wood fire. One night the lemon-roasted potatoes served on the side were humdrum; another time they were nearly magical, a lemony crust yielding to creamy flesh within.</p>
        <p>The fried mullet, a special, was a simple plate of three peachy-tinged head-on fish lined up in a row, with lemon slices placed precisely alongside; a saucer of horta came separately. The tsipoura, also called porgy, or sea bream, got the same treatment as the fagri; it, too, was delicious.</p>
        <p>Three typical specialties were excellent examples of classics: moussaka, spanakopita and giouvetsi sti gastra, a casserole of tender lamb chunks, tomato sauce and orzo, sealed with grated kefalograviera (an aged cheese of sheep and goat's milk).</p>
        <p>Not everything was perfect. The arni fricassee, a lamb shank with too much lemon artichoke sauce, wasn't much to look at and, accompanied only by a couple of artichoke hearts, was monotonous. Lamb wrapped in phyllo with béchamel and feta was a clash of flavors with no relief. Skewered marinated pork was tough, not tender.</p>
        <p>Desserts put the meal back on track: a nicely nutty baklava; a milk custard pie called galaktoboureko; a pastry of nuts, shredded wheat and syrup called kataifi. The simplest one, though, was the best: a swirl of Greek yogurt topped with chopped walnuts and Cretan honey. Have that with a demitasse of strong Greek coffee, and you may be thinking about booking a flight.</p>
        <p>Pithari Taverna  28 Woodbridge Avenue  Highland Park  (732) 572-0616  www.pitharitaverna.com</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE Smallish, bustling L-shaped dining room, with Mediterranean-blue accents and an open kitchen. Wheelchair accessibility.  THE CROWD Noisy and casual; friendly, slightly distracted servers; child-friendly atmosphere.  THE BAR Bring your own.  THE BILL Appetizers, soups and salads, $4.75 to $12; souvlaki and gyro platters, $10 to $12; main dishes, mostly $9 to $20, though the occasional special ( like fagri) can reach $33. All major cards accepted.  WHAT WE LIKE Octopus, Greek spreads with grilled pita, stuffed grape leaves, dandelions; all fish, lamb in tomato with orzo and cheese, moussaka; yogurt with walnuts and honey, Greek coffee.  IF YOU GO Lunch: Monday to Friday, 11:30 a.m. to 3 p.m. Dinner: Monday to Thursday, 3 to 10 p.m., and Friday, Saturday and Sunday, 3 p.m. to midnight. Reservations recommended on weekends. Limited parking next to the building; free street parking.  Reviewed April 8, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/HIGHLAND PARK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
