<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Scores Climb Ever Higher at Augusta, So Does Woods</title>
    <meta content="08golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/golf/08golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Appleby, Stuart</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rose, Justin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Scores Climb Ever Higher at Augusta, So Does Woods</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Scores Climb Ever Higher at Augusta, So Does Woods</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, Ga., April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last red number at Augusta National Golf Club fell at 6:34 p.m., sending the Masters to a place it has never been.</p>
        <p>As a frigid day crossed into chilly night, white scoreboards highlighted an Australian named Stuart Appleby chasing a country's first Masters title and the imposing figure of Tiger Woods chasing him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a third consecutive day of taxing conditions, Stuart Appleby shot a one-over-par 73 on Saturday to take a one-shot lead over Tiger Woods and Justin Rose at two-over 218.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last red number at Augusta National Golf Club fell at 6:34 p.m., sending the Masters to a place it has never been.</p>
        <p>As a frigid day crossed into chilly night, white scoreboards highlighted an Australian named Stuart Appleby chasing a country's first Masters title and the imposing figure of Tiger Woods chasing him.</p>
        <p>After a third consecutive day of taxing conditions, Appleby shot a one-over-par 73 on Saturday to take a one-shot lead over Woods and Justin Rose at two-over 218. Appleby's total was the highest to lead a third round in the history of the Masters. The previous high was even-par 216, set in 1966.</p>
        <p>Trailing Appleby by two shots were Padraig Harrington, with a 75, Zach Johnson, who shot 76, and the Augusta native Vaughn Taylor, with a 77. Bradley Dredge, who shot 76, stood three shots back. Phil Mickelson, with a 73, was four shots behind.</p>
        <p>Woods, seeking his fifth Masters title and third consecutive major championship, carded an even-par 72 -- the second-best score of the day -- despite bogeying the final two holes. Retief Goosen shot the best round of the day, a 70, in temperatures that never left the low 50s. The forecast calls for a high temperature of 59 on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Woods, despite his late errors, earned a spot in the final group, from which the winner has come in the past 16 Masters. In each of his 12 major victories, however, he has never come from behind to win. He will share the stage with Appleby, an occasional practice partner in Orlando, Fla., where they live, and frequent Presidents Cup opponent.</p>
        <p>''What do you want me to say, that I beat him on the driving range, drive it past him, that I've had my way with him?'' Appleby said, joking. ''No, no and no.''</p>
        <p>Asked what it will be like playing next to Woods with a major on the line, he said, ''He won't even know I'm there.''</p>
        <p>Woods was four shots out of the lead when he finished his round by missing a 15-footer for par on the last hole. He slammed his putter into his golf bag and stood rigid behind the green.</p>
        <p>But by nightfall he was firmly in contention, where he so often is among Augusta's loblolly pines.</p>
        <p>On the final day a year ago, trying to win the last major that his ailing father, Earl, would see, Woods went through an awful putting day and finished tied for third as Mickelson won.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking forward to having an opportunity to win the championship,'' Woods said. ''I've got a shot at it.''</p>
        <p>Many players could say the same thing, despite huge numbers on their scorecards. In past years, a three-round total of six over par would have meant a spot well back in the pack. This year, it put you on the leader board.</p>
        <p>''It's just different,'' Woods said. ''The way they set up the golf course, its length, dry conditions, that's what's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>When Appleby made a triple bogey on the par-4 17th hole -- with a drive pulled left, a bunker shot that clipped the top shelf of sand and dribbled into the rough and a three-putt -- the Masters had no golfers under par.</p>
        <p>Instead of taking a sizable lead into the final round, he held the kind of lead that can disappear in an instant.</p>
        <p>''Hanging on, manufacturing pars when bogeys could have been easily on the card, today was a real fight out there,'' said Appleby, seeking his first major title. ''There's no way to shoot three or four under. Those days seem to be a thing of history in this tournament.''</p>
        <p>Taylor held the lead by a stroke after a birdie on the 15th hole. He then bogeyed his last three holes. ''You know it's playing really tough and you just try to fight it out,'' he said. ''If you are going backward, you just try to hang in there, make pars and a birdie would be great.''</p>
        <p>The second-round leaders, Brett Wetterich and Tim Clark, struggled playing in the glare of Saturday's final group. Clark shot 80, Wetterich an 83.</p>
        <p>Amid a maze of bogeys in the field, Woods was able to surge near the front despite trailing by five shots going into the third round. He birdied No. 3 from 15 feet and added another 15-foot birdie putt at No. 8, where he raised his putter to the sky.</p>
        <p>On 17, Woods hit a drive left and tried to hit a cut shot over the trees that plugged into a greenside bunker. He blasted out to 25 feet, missed the par putt and settled for bogey.</p>
        <p>On the last hole, Woods split the fairway with his drive before a poor iron shot left him short and right of the green. He chipped 15 feet past the cup, missed the slippery par putt and dropped another stroke.</p>
        <p>Through it all, he remained on the leader board, close enough to look into Appleby's eyes and close enough to fit into another green jacket.</p>
        <p>''Emotionally and mentally, he's always strong,'' Appleby said. ''He knows how to tackle a golf course. He's not worried about anyone else there.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
