<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Fine Mess, Born of Excess</title>
    <meta content="08essa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/mutfund/08essa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT: ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Fine Mess, Born of Excess</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Another Fine Mess, Born of Excess</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SCHWARTZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HELLO, everybody, and welcome back to the humor column of the Mutual Funds Report, where we wrestle chuckles out of the world of investing and finance. This time, we're taking on the impending financial apocalypse prompted by the collapsing subprime mortgage market.</p>
        <p>You're laughing already! Or maybe not. We at the column love a challenge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the world of mortgages, excess is exemplified by the wacky financial structures that companies came up with to get people into homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HELLO, everybody, and welcome back to the humor column of the Mutual Funds Report, where we wrestle chuckles out of the world of investing and finance. This time, we're taking on the impending financial apocalypse prompted by the collapsing subprime mortgage market.</p>
        <p>You're laughing already! Or maybe not. We at the column love a challenge.</p>
        <p>Surely you are familiar with this whole apocalypse notion, which registers way past mere ''corrections'' and ''bursting bubbles'' on the financial Bad-O-Meter. Apocalypse means things like fire and brimstone, dogs lying down with cats, and, of course, the Beast (who currently offers an A.P.R. of 6.66 percent).</p>
        <p>Is the end really nigh? Probably not. But the Four Horsemen of this particular apocalypse are plenty scary, as described in the news coverage of the mortgage market: the first is rising mortgage interest rates, followed by default by risky borrowers. Then comes failure of at least some of the lenders. And, if the crisis keeps escalating, you could end up with the collapse of all stocks linked to the housing and financial markets -- which is, let's face it, a huge chunk of the overall stock market. This would not be pretty.</p>
        <p>So here we are with the fret du jour, and wondering how we got into such a mess -- just as we wondered about the excesses that led to the housing market bubble, the tech stock bubble and, back in the '80s, the savings-and-loan bubble. You might get the feeling that we, as a culture, move from excess to excess, with somebody always willing to push the market a little further and consumers always willing to come along for the ride. And you would not be wrong.</p>
        <p>In the world of mortgages, that excess is exemplified by the wacky financial structures that companies came up with to get people into homes, like so-called liar loans, which require little or no documentation. The industry calls them that. The companies sound as wild-and-crazy-guy-ish as some credit card hawkers whose standards have been about as low as a drunk's at closing time.</p>
        <p>That is where Hellfire Schwartz comes in. Some years ago, we bought a computer game called Hellfire for my older son. Some weeks after buying the game, we started getting junk mail for a Hellfire Schwartz. I assume that we filled out the online registration form incorrectly, but who knows how a bug enters the system?</p>
        <p>All I know is that for years now, Hellfire Schwartz has gotten come-ons from credit card companies that are so desperate for new customers that they are willing to extend credit to a glitch. And when we moved to another state, the Hellfire mail followed us.</p>
        <p>As a family, we try not to carry a lot of plastic. (After our longtime credit card company jacked up our annual interest rate to 29 percent over a late payment, we limited ourselves to a debit card and one revolving card from our credit union.) But my wife, who works as a checker at a department store, sees the rest of America come through on a daily basis, pulling out wallets bulging with 15 or more cards and, embarrassingly, having more than one of them turn up over their credit limits. Why do we let ourselves sail out so far over the line? And who keeps moving the line out further?</p>
        <p>I make no argument for abdicating personal responsibility, but I do wonder what kind of company thinks that a guy named Hellfire Schwartz looks like a good credit risk. They love Hellfire.</p>
        <p>Which brings us back to the apocalypse. Things look pretty grim at the moment, and it doesn't take a Nostradamus to predict pain ahead. The excesses will be curbed, and financial opportunities will be lost. (Google ''baby'' and ''bathwater.'') The Democrats will call for tighter regulation of industry, while the Republicans will call for greater protections for companies against the excesses of irresponsible consumers.</p>
        <p>And then, after the shouting, we will be left to muddle through, perhaps to hum along with the Alan Greenspans of bluegrass, the Austin Lounge Lizards, whose analysis of the current situation is incisive:</p>
        <p>Though we hear reassurances that everything is fine</p>
        <p>It's been a while since we've heard a canary in this mine</p>
        <p>It's when we think it's really bad it gets a little worse</p>
        <p>But keep on looking forward though we're going in reverse</p>
        <p>We've been through tough times before. We pick up, we move on. The wild and crazy guys do, too. And, somewhere out there, the next bubble is already forming.</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT: ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
