<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 9 Killings in 3 Months, Tension Grows in Trenton</title>
    <meta content="08trenton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/08trenton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gangs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Witnesses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Trenton (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fahim, Kareem</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Trenton (NJ)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DC143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 9 Killings in 3 Months, Tension Grows in Trenton</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trenton Is Tense After 9 Killings in 3 Months</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREEM FAHIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fahim, Kareem</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rash of nine murders in first three months of 2007 shakes city of Trenton and strains resources of Police Dept's eight homicide detectives; authorities variously attribute violence to availability of guns, to gang members disrespecting one another or simply to kind of bloodletting that often follows drug trade; say investigations are hindered by history of witness intimidation and retaliation, especially in certain neighborhoods; photos: chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The homicide rate in this city is soaring, and the police know retaliation can only make things worse.</p>
        <p>That means detectives need to find the man who shot and killed Matthew Brunson, in a grassy lot behind Dee Dee's Lounge and Liquor Store, before Mr. Brunson's buddies do. ''They said, 'Don't worry about it, Mama, we're going to get them,' '' Mr. Brunson's mother, Maria DeLeon, recalled her son's friends telling her after he was killed on March 20. ''I told them, 'No, I don't want to see no more violence.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A rash of killings has shaken the city and strained the resources of the Police Department’s eight homicide detectives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The homicide rate in this city is soaring, and the police know retaliation can only make things worse.</p>
        <p>That means detectives need to find the man who shot and killed Matthew Brunson, in a grassy lot behind Dee Dee's Lounge and Liquor Store, before Mr. Brunson's buddies do. ''They said, 'Don't worry about it, Mama, we're going to get them,' '' Mr. Brunson's mother, Maria DeLeon, recalled her son's friends telling her after he was killed on March 20. ''I told them, 'No, I don't want to see no more violence.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brunson, 27, was the eighth of nine people killed in the first three months of the year, up from two homicides in the same period last year.</p>
        <p>The rash of killings has shaken this city of 85,000 people and strained the resources of the Police Department's eight homicide detectives, some of whom are working 18- or 20-hour shifts. With arrests in only two of the nine cases, the authorities have variously attributed the violence to the availability of guns, to gang members disrespecting one another or simply to the kind of bloodshed that often follows the drug trade.</p>
        <p>In March alone, seven people were killed, a monthly total higher than anyone here can remember; at this pace, the annual homicide rate would top the 31 recorded in 2005, the most reported in four decades. Already, the nine homicides are more than the full year's total recorded in 1999, 1994 and 1985.</p>
        <p>The authorities have tried to calm residents by saying the violence seems confined to conflicts within a small circle of men.</p>
        <p>Investigators say they have been hindered by a lack of cooperation from a public frozen by a history of witness intimidation and retaliation, especially in neighborhoods like the West Ward, where the latest killing, of an 18-year-old man on March 26, caused a few residents to say it was time to move. ''The fear is real,'' Trenton's mayor, Douglas H. Palmer, acknowledged. ''But what we need is for the citizens to give us anonymous tips, and not to tolerate this kind of behavior.''</p>
        <p>Capt. Joseph Juniak, who oversees 67 detectives as chief of the Trenton police force's Criminal Investigative Bureau, offered little detail about the open homicide investigations, saying there were many theories about the motives, ranging from simple street robberies to the meting out of violent discipline within gangs.</p>
        <p>''I remember a time similar to this, when crack was introduced to the streets,'' he said. ''Unfortunately, in urban areas, it's a way of life.''</p>
        <p>Other cities in the region have also been seized by rising violence. In Philadelphia this year, there were 104 homicides through April 2, a significant increase over the same period last year. Newark's homicide rate is also up slightly this year, despite an overall drop in crime.</p>
        <p>''I hope this is just one of those streaks,'' said Captain Juniak, who took over the department's detective bureau two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Joseph J. Santiago, the department's director, called the spate of homicides in March ''extraordinary,'' particularly because of what he described as a ''highly unusual victim profile.''</p>
        <p>Several of the victims lived outside Trenton, and they included men ages 50, 43 and 27 -- beyond the 18- to 24-year-old range detectives are most used to seeing. In many of the cases, investigators say, the killings seem less like gang warfare, and more like violence stemming from narcotics sales.</p>
        <p>Also puzzling is the accompanying drop in most of the city's other crime categories, including sexual assaults, auto theft and robbery, which are all lower than in the same period last year. But the homicides are enough: In part to prevent violent retaliations, the police have established a large presence in some parts of the city in recent weeks, especially near the housing projects.</p>
        <p>Around the Wilson-Haverstick project, where Naquan Archie, 18, was shot and killed on March 26, the police ''stop and challenge'' groups of young men, asking what they are doing and where they are headed. In the evenings, the police footprint grows, giving the neighborhood the appearance of a crime scene. A truck parked near the housing project is a mobile base for officers in the area, and inside on a recent day, an officer peered at maps of the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Capt. Paul Messina, the department's head of patrol, said the Wilson-Haverstick operation was one of five such special patrols now operating throughout the city.</p>
        <p>There are some who say it is not enough. Tony Mack, a Freeholder who ran for mayor, called the police response ''reactive,'' saying a larger, permanent police presence was needed in more than a dozen trouble spots in the city.</p>
        <p>Mr. Santiago said the police were paying attention to areas with a history of crime, adding that the attention to some neighborhoods after violence prevented further outbreaks.</p>
        <p>The Federal Bureau of Investigation offered the police its help, including software to help manage cases and track leads, Mr. Santiago said. But some of the investigators said they did not have time to learn how to use the software.</p>
        <p>''Yes, you do,'' Mr. Santiago said he had replied.</p>
        <p>The rising violence in Trenton is part of a nationwide pattern, said Chuck Wexler, the executive director of the Police Executive Research Forum. His organization released a report last month that showed large increases in violent crime in spots across the country since late 2005, especially in midsize and larger communities like Trenton, and Prince George's County, Md., which has seen a similar surge in its homicide rate this year, with 11 killings in as many days in March.</p>
        <p>''We don't see this in smaller cities, and we didn't see this five years ago,'' Mr. Wexler said.</p>
        <p>For Tamala Whittington, 40, who lives in the Wilson-Haverstick houses, the violence does not so much surge and recede as simply lurk. Last year, she sent her 11-year-old son to live with his aunt a short drive away from the projects after a stray bullet hit a 7-year-old girl in the face as she rode her bicycle. The girl survived. After the shooting of Mr. Archie last month, Ms. Whittington said, she, too, has decided to move, perhaps to nearby Lawrenceville.</p>
        <p>''I try not to stay outside,'' Ms. Whittington said. ''I'm always looking. I'm in my car, and I'm gone.''</p>
        <p>The first day of 2007 brought Trenton's first homicide, of Steven D. Mason, 43. Less than a week later, Antonio Green, 23, was shot and killed in an apparent robbery. Two people have been arrested in connection with Mr. Green's death.</p>
        <p>February was quiet. Then the violence exploded.</p>
        <p>On March 5, 20-year-old Rajeem Denson -- who made the newspapers at age 11 after his near-drowning during a swimming class led to a state law governing swimming instructors in public schools -- was shot and killed outside his home.</p>
        <p>The next day, there were two more: Jarrett James, 18, and Sidibrima Joseph Massaquoi Jr., 23, who was fatally shot in the basement of the house where he lived with his girlfriend, said his father, Sidibrima Joseph Massaquoi Sr.</p>
        <p>''The death certificate said there were multiple shots,'' Mr. Massaquoi said. ''One to his heart. The other perforated his lungs.'' He said that he did not know why his son was killed, but that his son and his girlfriend had fought about another man recently.</p>
        <p>''I think it's somebody that both of them knew,'' Mr. Massaquoi said of his son's killer.</p>
        <p>Robert Fiorello, who leads an antigang program for a nonprofit group called PEI Kids, said Mr. James, the other March 6 victim, worked for him for two summers as a peer mentor and was not in a gang.</p>
        <p>''He was like a son to me,'' Mr. Fiorello said. ''He was a good kid with a few frailties.''</p>
        <p>Edgar Rios, a homicide detective and a 26-year veteran of the department, is investigating three of this year's killings, including those of Mr. James and Mr. Brunson. His work gets harder by the year.</p>
        <p>''Years ago, they would tell us basically anything we want to know,'' he said of residents. ''Now they're scared for their life. All you can do is keep going back at them, and treat them nice. Let them know you need their help.</p>
        <p>''But it takes time,'' he added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
