<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CALENDAR</title>
    <meta content="08njlistingsNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD6163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2305" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CALENDAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Englewood Joy Behar. April 14 at 8 p.m. $45 to $80. Bergen Performing Arts Center, 30 North Van Brunt Street. (201) 227-1030.  Red Bank Colin Mochrie and Brad Sherwood, improv. Friday at 8 p.m. $25 to $65. Count Basie Theater, 99 Monmouth Street. (732) 842-9000.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>New Brunswick The New Jersey Film Festival, Spring 2007. Schedule and information: njfilmfest.com. Through April 15. $4 to $10. New Jersey Media Arts Center, 72 Lipman Drive. (732) 932-8482.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>New Brunswick ''Sesame Street Live,'' children's musical. Through Monday. $10 to $26. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.  South Orange ''Double V: Victory Abroad and Victory at Home,'' family musical presented by Flying Ship Productions, followed by a discussion with the audience. Wednesday at 7 p.m. $6 and $12. ''Ralph's World,'' one-man children's musical by Ralph Covert. Ages 2 to 8. April 15 at 11 a.m. and 3 p.m. $15. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Boonton ''When You Wish Upon a Song: A Magical Musical Revue,'' presented by Boonton Parks and Recreation Theater Company. Friday through April 15. $9 to $12. Boonton High School, 306 Lanthrop Avenue. (973) 335-9700.  Camden Multimedia remix of ''Birth of a Nation,'' D. W. Griffith's silent film, by DJ Spooky, following a free roundtable discussion with the composer at 6 p.m. Friday at 8 p.m. $22 to $26. Walter K. Gordon Theater, Camden Center for the Arts, Rutgers University, Third and Pearl Streets. (856) 225-2700.  Chatham ''The Best of Jersey,'' benefit concert with Pat DiNizio, Rio Clemente, Red Molly and Harmonytryx. April 14 at 8 p.m. Suggested donation: $20. Sanctuary Concerts at Presbyterian Church of Chatham, 240 Southern Boulevard. (973) 376-4946.  Englewood ''1964: The Tribute,'' Beatles tribute show. Friday at 8 p.m. $20 to $50. Itzhak Perlman, violinist. April 15 at 3 p.m. $35 to $125. Bergen Performing Arts Center, 30 North Van Brunt Street. (201) 227-1030.  Morris Township Wyeth Jazz Showcase: Jeff Barnhart, jazz and ragtime pianist; tribute to Scott Joplin. Monday at 8 p.m. $13 and $15. Bickford Theater, 6 Normandy Heights Road. (973) 971-3706.  Morristown ''A Gala Evening of Grand Ballet,'' by the Moscow Festival Ballet. Thursday at 8 p.m. $32 to $47. ''Glory to Gospel!'' with the Dixie Hummingbirds and Harlem Gospel Choir. April 14 at 8 p.m. $32 to $42. The Warren Vaché Group, jazz. April 15 at 3 p.m. $15. The Community Theater, 100 South Street. (973) 539-8008.  New Brunswick Rutgers Brass; Renaissance to contemporary music. April 15 at 6:30 p.m. Free. Christ Church Episcopal, 5 Paterson Street. (732) 545-6262.  New Brunswick Handel's ''Athalia,'' performed by Opera at Rutgers and Musica Raritana. April 14 and 15. Free. Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, Douglass Campus, Rutgers University, 85 George Street. (732) 932-7511.  New Brunswick Rutgers Jazz Ensemble with Frank Sinatra, Jr. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $15 to $40. Rutgers Symphony Orchestra; Kynan Johns, conductor. Friday at 8 p.m. $15 to $25. Nicholas Music Center, Rutgers University, 85 George Street. (732) 932-7511.  New Brunswick Richard Nader's ''Magic Moments to Remember Concert.'' Friday at 8 p.m. $25 to $55. ''Giselle,'' by the Moscow Festival Ballet. April 14 at 8 p.m. $20 to $55. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.  Newark ''I Can't Stop Loving You: The Music of Ray Charles,'' musical revue. Through April 8. $20 to $58. Discovery Concerts: ''Discover Gershwin,'' with the Discovery Orchestra; George Marriner Maull, conductor. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $42. Sonny Rollins, jazz saxophonist. Friday at 8 p.m. $20 to $78. The New Jersey Symphony Orchestra. April 14 at 2 and 8 p.m. $22 to $77. New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street. (888) 466-5722.  Princeton Mary Chapin Carpenter. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $15 to $48. Kalichstein-Laredo-Robinson, piano trio. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $40 to $53. Tchaikovsky's ''Sleeping Beauty,'' with choreography by Marius Petipa, performed by the Moscow Festival Ballet. April 15 at 3 p.m. $15 to $50. McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place. (609) 258-2787.  Rahway Bob DeVos, jazz guitarist, and his trio. Friday at 8 p.m. $14 and $16. Arts Guild of Rahway, 1670 Irving Street. (732) 381-7511.  Red Bank The Isley Brothers, classic soul and rock. Thursday at 8 p.m. $20 to $100. The Parsons Dance Company. April 14 at 8 p.m. $19.50 to $39.50. Pat Metheny and Brad Mehldau, with Larry Grendier and Jeff Ballard, jazz. April 15 at 7:30 p.m. $30 to $75. Count Basie Theater, 99 Monmouth Street. (732) 842-9000.  South Orange Kalichstein-Laredo-Robinson, piano trio. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $8 to $20. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.  Teaneck LiquidBody Dance and World Music of Nana, multimedia modern dance and music. April 14 at 8 p.m. Donation: $10. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 1 to 5 p.m. Puffin Cultural Forum, 20 East Oakdene Avenue. (201) 836-8923.  West Long Branch Lura, Portuguese-Creole music and dance. Friday at 8 p.m. $30. Pollak Theater, Monmouth University, 400 Cedar Avenue. (732) 571-3400.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Branchburg ''Awakening Galatia,'' comedy by John (J. D.) Newman. Wednesday through April 14 at 8 p.m. $5 and $8. Raritan Valley Community College, Route 28 and Lamington Road. (908) 725-3420.  Hackettstown Women Playwrights Series: ''Daphne Does Dim Sum,'' staged reading of the play by Eugenie Chan. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Centenary Little Theater, Centenary College, 400 Jefferson Street. (908) 852-1400.  Hoboken ''The Miracle Worker,'' drama by William Gibson, presented by the Hudson Theater Ensemble. Through April 15. $8 to $15. Hudson School, 601 Park Avenue. (201) 377-7014.  Lawrenceville ''The Heidi Chronicles,'' drama by Wendy Wasserstein, presented by Rider University student actors. Thursday through April 21. $4 to $10. Rider University, Yvonne Theater, 2083 Lawrenceville Road. (609) 896-5303.  Long Branch ''Love and Murder,'' drama by Arthur Giron; world premiere. Thursday through May 6. $25 to $40. New Jersey Repertory Company, 179 Broadway. (732) 229-3166.  New Brunswick ''Falsettos,'' musical by William Finn and James Lapine. Tuesday through May 6. $28 to $64. George Street Playhouse, 9 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7717.  Nutley ''I Hate Hamlet,'' comedy by Paul Rudnick. Friday through April 28. $12. Nutley Little Theater, 47 Erie Place (off Brookfield Avenue). (973) 667-0374.  Oaklyn ''Much Ado About Nothing,'' William Shakespeare's comedy; directed by Denise George. Through April 15. $17 to $30. Ritz Theater, 915 White Horse Pike. (856) 858-5230.  Oradell ''Angels in America: Millennium Approaches,'' drama by Tony Kushner, presented by the Bergen County Players. Through April 21. $15 and $18. Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road. (201) 261-4200.  Princeton ''Radio Golf,'' drama by August Wilson. Through April 8. $40 to $53. ''Boris Godunov,'' drama by Alexander Pushkin. Thursday through April 14 at 8 p.m. $15. ''Completely Hollywood (Abridged),'' comedy by the Reduced Shakespeare Company. April 14 at 8 p.m. $25 to $35. McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place. (609) 258-2787.  Wayne ''Seussical,'' musical by Stephen Flaherty and Lynn Ahrens, adapted from the books by Dr. Seuss; presented by the William Paterson University Pioneer Players. Thursday through April 22. $3 to $7. YM-YWHA of North Jersey, 1 Pike Drive. (973) 595-0100.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Maplewood C. K. Williams, poet. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. $10. Columbia High School, 17 Parker Avenue. (973) 378-7620.  Newark ''Hip Hop: Out, Loud and Proud,'' spoken-word performance and discussion with Pandora Scooter, host. April 14 at 8 p.m. $16. New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street. (888) 466-5722.  South Orange ''Simpsons Mania: Inside America's Favorite Family,'' discussion and video clips with Mike Reiss, producer of ''The Simpsons.'' Thursday at 8 p.m. $25. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Cape May ''Small Towns, Black Lives: African American Communities in New Jersey,'' photography by Wendel A. White. Through May 13. $1 and $2. Mid-Atlantic Center for the Arts, 1048 Washington Street. (609) 884-5404.  Clinton ''Barbara Klein: New Marks,'' abstract paintings, and ''How American Women Artists Invented Post Modernism,'' group show presented by the Feminist Art Project. April 8 through June 3. Reception: April 15, 2 to 4 p.m. Donation: $3. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Hunterdon Museum of Art, 7 Lower Center Street. (908) 735-8415.  Cranford ''Memories and Mountains,'' mixed-media by Carole Wong Chesak. Through April 20. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m. Additional hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 6 to 9 p.m. Tomasulo Gallery, Union County College, 1033 Springfield Avenue. (908) 709-7155.  Hamilton ''New Jersey Perspective,'' photography by Owen Kanzler and sculpture by Kate Graves. Through April 8. $1 to $12; members free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m., April through October; 10 a.m. to 6 p.m., November through March. Grounds for Sculpture, 18 Fairgrounds Road. (609) 586-0616.  Hopewell ''The Intimacy of Flowers,'' photography by Tasha O'Neill. Through April 15. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Gallery 14, 14 Mercer Street. (609) 333-8511.  Lambertville ''Constructions and Reconstructions,'' mixed media and photography by Nancy Shill and John Treichler. Through April 29. Reception: April 14, 6 to 9 p.m. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m., or by appointment. Artists' Gallery, 32 Coryell Street. (609) 397-4588.  Lincroft Photographs from the collection of Brookdale Community College, includes works from prominent 20th-century documentary and fine art photographers. Through April 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Monmouth Museum, Brookdale Community College, Newman Springs Road. (732) 747-2266.  Maplewood ''Lisa Pressman: Mixed Media, Transitions and Processes.'' Through April 28. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, noon to 8 p.m. Classic Design Framing, 168 Maplewood Avenue. (973) 762-5588.  Montclair ''Dreaming of a Speech Without Words: The Painting and Early Objects of H. C. Westermann.'' Through May 27. $6 to $8; free for members and children 12 and under; free for everyone on Fridays from 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Montclair Art Museum, 3 South Mountain Avenue. (973) 746-5555.  Morristown ''Oil on Linen,'' paintings by David Moore. Through April 21. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Simon Gallery, 48 Bank Street. (973) 538-5456.  Newark ''Mi Puerto Rico: Master Painters of the Island,'' paintings by José Campeche, Francisco Oller and Miguel Pou. Through April 15. $3 and $7. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., October through June; noon to 5 p.m., July through September. The Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street. (973) 596-6493.  Oceanville ''Spinning Worlds: Emerging Artists,'' works by Paul Santoleri and Carla Falb. ''Surface Rhythms,'' works by Bennett Bean and Barbara Bullock. Both through April 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Noyes Museum of Art, 733 Lily Lake Road. (609) 652-8848.  Princeton ''History, Identity or None of the Above: Regarding African-American Art,'' mixed-media exhibition. Through May 13. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Princeton University Art Museum, Nassau and Witherspoon Streets. (609) 258-3788.  Princeton ''Radiant Evocations,'' paintings by Sam Feinstein. Through April 14. The Jewish Center of Princeton, 453 Nassau Street. (609) 921-0100.  Rahway ''High Fiber Content,'' mixed-media group show. Through April 20. Hours: Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 1 to 3 p.m. and 5 to 7 p.m. Arts Guild of Rahway, 1670 Irving Street. (732) 381-7511.  Rahway The Way of the Cross: ''Passion of Christ,'' paintings by Jean Charlot. Through April 14. Hours: Thursdays through Saturdays, noon to 7 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Edge Art Gallery, 1575 Irving Street. (732) 669-0112.  Skillman Group show by the A-Team Artists of Trenton. Through May 6. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Montgomery Center for the Arts, 124 Montgomery Road. (609) 921-3272.  South Orange ''Cathexis: Art of Obsession,'' mixed-media group show. Through May 6. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Pierro Gallery, 5 Mead Street. (973) 378-7755.  Springfield ''Structures,'' photographs by Sue Zwick. Through April 26. Hours: Mondays, Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Tuesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 3:30 p.m. Donald B. Palmer Museum, 66 Mountain Avenue. (973) 376-4930.  Summit ''Repose,'' works by Lindsay Walt. Through Wednesday. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Domo Gallery, 447 Springfield Avenue. (908) 608-0079.  Trenton ''Friends for the Marsh 2007,'' photography exhibition. Through April 21. Free. Wood-fired ceramics and handmade paper and printmaking by Peter Callas and Margaret Kennard Johnson. Through April 22. Suggested admission: $2 to $5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. The Trenton City Museum, Cadwalader Park. (609) 989-3632.  Union ''As I See It,'' photography by Jane H. Rapp. Through June 13. Les Malamut Art Gallery, 1800 Morris Avenue. (908) 851-5450.  Upper Montclair  ''Narcissus,'' mixed-media group show. Through April 29. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m. Gallery of Modern Symbolism, 594 Valley Road.  Washington Township ''In the Shadows of Manhattan,'' mixed-media group show. Through April 22. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 6 a.m. to 10 p.m.; Fridays, 6 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 8 a.m. to 5 p.m. Atrium Gallery, Bergen County Y, 605 Pascack Road. (201) 666-6610, Extension 222.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>COMEDY</p>
        <p>Englewood Joy Behar. April 14 at 8 p.m. $45 to $80. Bergen Performing Arts Center, 30 North Van Brunt Street. (201) 227-1030.  Red Bank Colin Mochrie and Brad Sherwood, improv. Friday at 8 p.m. $25 to $65. Count Basie Theater, 99 Monmouth Street. (732) 842-9000.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>New Brunswick The New Jersey Film Festival, Spring 2007. Schedule and information: njfilmfest.com. Through April 15. $4 to $10. New Jersey Media Arts Center, 72 Lipman Drive. (732) 932-8482.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>New Brunswick ''Sesame Street Live,'' children's musical. Through Monday. $10 to $26. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.  South Orange ''Double V: Victory Abroad and Victory at Home,'' family musical presented by Flying Ship Productions, followed by a discussion with the audience. Wednesday at 7 p.m. $6 and $12. ''Ralph's World,'' one-man children's musical by Ralph Covert. Ages 2 to 8. April 15 at 11 a.m. and 3 p.m. $15. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.</p>
        <p>MUSIC AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Boonton ''When You Wish Upon a Song: A Magical Musical Revue,'' presented by Boonton Parks and Recreation Theater Company. Friday through April 15. $9 to $12. Boonton High School, 306 Lanthrop Avenue. (973) 335-9700.  Camden Multimedia remix of ''Birth of a Nation,'' D. W. Griffith's silent film, by DJ Spooky, following a free roundtable discussion with the composer at 6 p.m. Friday at 8 p.m. $22 to $26. Walter K. Gordon Theater, Camden Center for the Arts, Rutgers University, Third and Pearl Streets. (856) 225-2700.  Chatham ''The Best of Jersey,'' benefit concert with Pat DiNizio, Rio Clemente, Red Molly and Harmonytryx. April 14 at 8 p.m. Suggested donation: $20. Sanctuary Concerts at Presbyterian Church of Chatham, 240 Southern Boulevard. (973) 376-4946.  Englewood ''1964: The Tribute,'' Beatles tribute show. Friday at 8 p.m. $20 to $50. Itzhak Perlman, violinist. April 15 at 3 p.m. $35 to $125. Bergen Performing Arts Center, 30 North Van Brunt Street. (201) 227-1030.  Morris Township Wyeth Jazz Showcase: Jeff Barnhart, jazz and ragtime pianist; tribute to Scott Joplin. Monday at 8 p.m. $13 and $15. Bickford Theater, 6 Normandy Heights Road. (973) 971-3706.  Morristown ''A Gala Evening of Grand Ballet,'' by the Moscow Festival Ballet. Thursday at 8 p.m. $32 to $47. ''Glory to Gospel!'' with the Dixie Hummingbirds and Harlem Gospel Choir. April 14 at 8 p.m. $32 to $42. The Warren Vaché Group, jazz. April 15 at 3 p.m. $15. The Community Theater, 100 South Street. (973) 539-8008.  New Brunswick Rutgers Brass; Renaissance to contemporary music. April 15 at 6:30 p.m. Free. Christ Church Episcopal, 5 Paterson Street. (732) 545-6262.  New Brunswick Handel's ''Athalia,'' performed by Opera at Rutgers and Musica Raritana. April 14 and 15. Free. Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, Douglass Campus, Rutgers University, 85 George Street. (732) 932-7511.  New Brunswick Rutgers Jazz Ensemble with Frank Sinatra, Jr. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $15 to $40. Rutgers Symphony Orchestra; Kynan Johns, conductor. Friday at 8 p.m. $15 to $25. Nicholas Music Center, Rutgers University, 85 George Street. (732) 932-7511.  New Brunswick Richard Nader's ''Magic Moments to Remember Concert.'' Friday at 8 p.m. $25 to $55. ''Giselle,'' by the Moscow Festival Ballet. April 14 at 8 p.m. $20 to $55. State Theater, 15 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7469.  Newark ''I Can't Stop Loving You: The Music of Ray Charles,'' musical revue. Through April 8. $20 to $58. Discovery Concerts: ''Discover Gershwin,'' with the Discovery Orchestra; George Marriner Maull, conductor. Thursday at 7:30 p.m. $42. Sonny Rollins, jazz saxophonist. Friday at 8 p.m. $20 to $78. The New Jersey Symphony Orchestra. April 14 at 2 and 8 p.m. $22 to $77. New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street. (888) 466-5722.  Princeton Mary Chapin Carpenter. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $15 to $48. Kalichstein-Laredo-Robinson, piano trio. Wednesday at 8 p.m. $40 to $53. Tchaikovsky's ''Sleeping Beauty,'' with choreography by Marius Petipa, performed by the Moscow Festival Ballet. April 15 at 3 p.m. $15 to $50. McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place. (609) 258-2787.  Rahway Bob DeVos, jazz guitarist, and his trio. Friday at 8 p.m. $14 and $16. Arts Guild of Rahway, 1670 Irving Street. (732) 381-7511.  Red Bank The Isley Brothers, classic soul and rock. Thursday at 8 p.m. $20 to $100. The Parsons Dance Company. April 14 at 8 p.m. $19.50 to $39.50. Pat Metheny and Brad Mehldau, with Larry Grendier and Jeff Ballard, jazz. April 15 at 7:30 p.m. $30 to $75. Count Basie Theater, 99 Monmouth Street. (732) 842-9000.  South Orange Kalichstein-Laredo-Robinson, piano trio. Tuesday at 8 p.m. $8 to $20. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.  Teaneck LiquidBody Dance and World Music of Nana, multimedia modern dance and music. April 14 at 8 p.m. Donation: $10. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 1 to 5 p.m. Puffin Cultural Forum, 20 East Oakdene Avenue. (201) 836-8923.  West Long Branch Lura, Portuguese-Creole music and dance. Friday at 8 p.m. $30. Pollak Theater, Monmouth University, 400 Cedar Avenue. (732) 571-3400.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>Branchburg ''Awakening Galatia,'' comedy by John (J. D.) Newman. Wednesday through April 14 at 8 p.m. $5 and $8. Raritan Valley Community College, Route 28 and Lamington Road. (908) 725-3420.  Hackettstown Women Playwrights Series: ''Daphne Does Dim Sum,'' staged reading of the play by Eugenie Chan. Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Centenary Little Theater, Centenary College, 400 Jefferson Street. (908) 852-1400.  Hoboken ''The Miracle Worker,'' drama by William Gibson, presented by the Hudson Theater Ensemble. Through April 15. $8 to $15. Hudson School, 601 Park Avenue. (201) 377-7014.  Lawrenceville ''The Heidi Chronicles,'' drama by Wendy Wasserstein, presented by Rider University student actors. Thursday through April 21. $4 to $10. Rider University, Yvonne Theater, 2083 Lawrenceville Road. (609) 896-5303.  Long Branch ''Love and Murder,'' drama by Arthur Giron; world premiere. Thursday through May 6. $25 to $40. New Jersey Repertory Company, 179 Broadway. (732) 229-3166.  New Brunswick ''Falsettos,'' musical by William Finn and James Lapine. Tuesday through May 6. $28 to $64. George Street Playhouse, 9 Livingston Avenue. (732) 246-7717.  Nutley ''I Hate Hamlet,'' comedy by Paul Rudnick. Friday through April 28. $12. Nutley Little Theater, 47 Erie Place (off Brookfield Avenue). (973) 667-0374.  Oaklyn ''Much Ado About Nothing,'' William Shakespeare's comedy; directed by Denise George. Through April 15. $17 to $30. Ritz Theater, 915 White Horse Pike. (856) 858-5230.  Oradell ''Angels in America: Millennium Approaches,'' drama by Tony Kushner, presented by the Bergen County Players. Through April 21. $15 and $18. Little Firehouse Theater, 298 Kinderkamack Road. (201) 261-4200.  Princeton ''Radio Golf,'' drama by August Wilson. Through April 8. $40 to $53. ''Boris Godunov,'' drama by Alexander Pushkin. Thursday through April 14 at 8 p.m. $15. ''Completely Hollywood (Abridged),'' comedy by the Reduced Shakespeare Company. April 14 at 8 p.m. $25 to $35. McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place. (609) 258-2787.  Wayne ''Seussical,'' musical by Stephen Flaherty and Lynn Ahrens, adapted from the books by Dr. Seuss; presented by the William Paterson University Pioneer Players. Thursday through April 22. $3 to $7. YM-YWHA of North Jersey, 1 Pike Drive. (973) 595-0100.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>Maplewood C. K. Williams, poet. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. $10. Columbia High School, 17 Parker Avenue. (973) 378-7620.  Newark ''Hip Hop: Out, Loud and Proud,'' spoken-word performance and discussion with Pandora Scooter, host. April 14 at 8 p.m. $16. New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street. (888) 466-5722.  South Orange ''Simpsons Mania: Inside America's Favorite Family,'' discussion and video clips with Mike Reiss, producer of ''The Simpsons.'' Thursday at 8 p.m. $25. South Orange Performing Arts Center, 1 Sopac Way. (973) 313-2787.</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>Cape May ''Small Towns, Black Lives: African American Communities in New Jersey,'' photography by Wendel A. White. Through May 13. $1 and $2. Mid-Atlantic Center for the Arts, 1048 Washington Street. (609) 884-5404.  Clinton ''Barbara Klein: New Marks,'' abstract paintings, and ''How American Women Artists Invented Post Modernism,'' group show presented by the Feminist Art Project. April 8 through June 3. Reception: April 15, 2 to 4 p.m. Donation: $3. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Hunterdon Museum of Art, 7 Lower Center Street. (908) 735-8415.  Cranford ''Memories and Mountains,'' mixed-media by Carole Wong Chesak. Through April 20. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m. Additional hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 6 to 9 p.m. Tomasulo Gallery, Union County College, 1033 Springfield Avenue. (908) 709-7155.  Hamilton ''New Jersey Perspective,'' photography by Owen Kanzler and sculpture by Kate Graves. Through April 8. $1 to $12; members free. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m., April through October; 10 a.m. to 6 p.m., November through March. Grounds for Sculpture, 18 Fairgrounds Road. (609) 586-0616.  Hopewell ''The Intimacy of Flowers,'' photography by Tasha O'Neill. Through April 15. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Gallery 14, 14 Mercer Street. (609) 333-8511.  Lambertville ''Constructions and Reconstructions,'' mixed media and photography by Nancy Shill and John Treichler. Through April 29. Reception: April 14, 6 to 9 p.m. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m., or by appointment. Artists' Gallery, 32 Coryell Street. (609) 397-4588.  Lincroft Photographs from the collection of Brookdale Community College, includes works from prominent 20th-century documentary and fine art photographers. Through April 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Monmouth Museum, Brookdale Community College, Newman Springs Road. (732) 747-2266.  Maplewood ''Lisa Pressman: Mixed Media, Transitions and Processes.'' Through April 28. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, noon to 8 p.m. Classic Design Framing, 168 Maplewood Avenue. (973) 762-5588.  Montclair ''Dreaming of a Speech Without Words: The Painting and Early Objects of H. C. Westermann.'' Through May 27. $6 to $8; free for members and children 12 and under; free for everyone on Fridays from 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Montclair Art Museum, 3 South Mountain Avenue. (973) 746-5555.  Morristown ''Oil on Linen,'' paintings by David Moore. Through April 21. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Simon Gallery, 48 Bank Street. (973) 538-5456.  Newark ''Mi Puerto Rico: Master Painters of the Island,'' paintings by José Campeche, Francisco Oller and Miguel Pou. Through April 15. $3 and $7. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., October through June; noon to 5 p.m., July through September. The Newark Museum, 49 Washington Street. (973) 596-6493.  Oceanville ''Spinning Worlds: Emerging Artists,'' works by Paul Santoleri and Carla Falb. ''Surface Rhythms,'' works by Bennett Bean and Barbara Bullock. Both through April 22. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Noyes Museum of Art, 733 Lily Lake Road. (609) 652-8848.  Princeton ''History, Identity or None of the Above: Regarding African-American Art,'' mixed-media exhibition. Through May 13. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Princeton University Art Museum, Nassau and Witherspoon Streets. (609) 258-3788.  Princeton ''Radiant Evocations,'' paintings by Sam Feinstein. Through April 14. The Jewish Center of Princeton, 453 Nassau Street. (609) 921-0100.  Rahway ''High Fiber Content,'' mixed-media group show. Through April 20. Hours: Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 1 to 4 p.m.; Thursdays, 1 to 3 p.m. and 5 to 7 p.m. Arts Guild of Rahway, 1670 Irving Street. (732) 381-7511.  Rahway The Way of the Cross: ''Passion of Christ,'' paintings by Jean Charlot. Through April 14. Hours: Thursdays through Saturdays, noon to 7 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Edge Art Gallery, 1575 Irving Street. (732) 669-0112.  Skillman Group show by the A-Team Artists of Trenton. Through May 6. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Montgomery Center for the Arts, 124 Montgomery Road. (609) 921-3272.  South Orange ''Cathexis: Art of Obsession,'' mixed-media group show. Through May 6. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. Pierro Gallery, 5 Mead Street. (973) 378-7755.  Springfield ''Structures,'' photographs by Sue Zwick. Through April 26. Hours: Mondays, Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 8:30 p.m.; Tuesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, to 4:30 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 3:30 p.m. Donald B. Palmer Museum, 66 Mountain Avenue. (973) 376-4930.  Summit ''Repose,'' works by Lindsay Walt. Through Wednesday. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m. Domo Gallery, 447 Springfield Avenue. (908) 608-0079.  Trenton ''Friends for the Marsh 2007,'' photography exhibition. Through April 21. Free. Wood-fired ceramics and handmade paper and printmaking by Peter Callas and Margaret Kennard Johnson. Through April 22. Suggested admission: $2 to $5. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 1 to 4 p.m. The Trenton City Museum, Cadwalader Park. (609) 989-3632.  Union ''As I See It,'' photography by Jane H. Rapp. Through June 13. Les Malamut Art Gallery, 1800 Morris Avenue. (908) 851-5450.  Upper Montclair  ''Narcissus,'' mixed-media group show. Through April 29. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m. Gallery of Modern Symbolism, 594 Valley Road.  Washington Township ''In the Shadows of Manhattan,'' mixed-media group show. Through April 22. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 6 a.m. to 10 p.m.; Fridays, 6 a.m. to 3 p.m.; Sundays, 8 a.m. to 5 p.m. Atrium Gallery, Bergen County Y, 605 Pascack Road. (201) 666-6610, Extension 222.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
