<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Anarchist Casebook</title>
    <meta content="Crime.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Crime.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CRIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Rankin, Ian</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bruen, Ken</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Naming of the Dead, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Anarchist Casebook</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Anarchist Casebook</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marilyn Stasio</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anyone who turns to genre fiction for escapist reading is well advised to stay clear of Ian Rankin's hard-boiled procedurals featuring Inspector John Rebus of the Edinburgh police force. Like George Pelecanos, the American crime novelist he most resembles, Rankin is a flinty realist with little use for the romantic heroics that allow series detectives to operate above the fray of real life lived in real time. Events that shape the course of history in Scotland are just as likely to determine the plots of his novels. But while that factual fidelity lends authenticity to his books, it also accounts for their unwieldy structure and overburdened narratives.</p>
        <p>The eyes of the world are on Scotland in THE NAMING OF THE DEAD (Little, Brown, $24.99), which opens shortly before the G-8 summit conference that will bring top international leaders to a secluded golf resort on the outskirts of the Perthshire town of Auchterarder in the early summer of 2005. With everyone from Scotland Yard's Special Branch to a contingent of United States marines involved in the massive security effort, the local constabulary is hard-pressed to maintain order in the streets of nearby Edinburgh, teeming with a quarter of a million peaceful protesters and high-profile celebrities, along with political agitators and grassroots hooligans bent on making mischief.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ian Rankin’s latest novel opens as protesters and celebrities converge on Edinburgh for the G-8 summit conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anyone who turns to genre fiction for escapist reading is well advised to stay clear of Ian Rankin's hard-boiled procedurals featuring Inspector John Rebus of the Edinburgh police force. Like George Pelecanos, the American crime novelist he most resembles, Rankin is a flinty realist with little use for the romantic heroics that allow series detectives to operate above the fray of real life lived in real time. Events that shape the course of history in Scotland are just as likely to determine the plots of his novels. But while that factual fidelity lends authenticity to his books, it also accounts for their unwieldy structure and overburdened narratives.</p>
        <p>The eyes of the world are on Scotland in THE NAMING OF THE DEAD (Little, Brown, $24.99), which opens shortly before the G-8 summit conference that will bring top international leaders to a secluded golf resort on the outskirts of the Perthshire town of Auchterarder in the early summer of 2005. With everyone from Scotland Yard's Special Branch to a contingent of United States marines involved in the massive security effort, the local constabulary is hard-pressed to maintain order in the streets of nearby Edinburgh, teeming with a quarter of a million peaceful protesters and high-profile celebrities, along with political agitators and grassroots hooligans bent on making mischief.</p>
        <p>Rankin vividly captures the bizarre pageantry of this political circus and gives Rebus's partner, the warmhearted Sergeant Siobhan Clarke, a good reason for being in the thick of things when her hippie parents, camped out among some anarchists, are swept up in the rioting that gives Edinburgh a black eye for police brutality. But for all the forced connections linking the riots and the suspicious death of an influental member of Parliament to a multiple homicide case that Rebus is working, the maverick detective is largely out of the loop on this one.</p>
        <p>''Rebus knew his place in the food chain,'' Rankin tells us in the sardonic voice that gives his books their abrasive edge: ''somewhere down among the plankton, the price for years of insubordination and reckless conduct.'' The more Rebus is cut off from the main action, the more we hang on his brooding thoughts about his own strange investigation -- a series of murders of sexual predators by a killer who leaves ritual fetishes at a ''clootie well'' in the woods outside Auchterarder. In investigating the origin of the site, said to be a place where offerings are made and ''all sorts of witchy goings-on'' are conducted in memory of the dead, Rebus delves into some of the peculiar superstitions that persist in modern-day Scotland. But it's hard to keep focused on the implications of this fascinating mystery when the Rebel Clown Army, wearing red and purple wigs and waving feather dusters, is marching on Edinburgh.</p>
        <p>Unlike Rebus, who has rarely left his native turf in the 30 years he's been on the job, the protagonists in three Irish crime novels are returning home to cities they scarcely recognize. And while Rebus's sense of disaffection comes from an ingrained rebellious streak (''I do my best work on the margins''), the alienation felt by these sleuths is literal as well as psychological.</p>
        <p>Jack Taylor, the violent, guilt-driven, alcoholic ex-cop who suffers exquisite agonies in Ken Bruen's black-bordered narratives, has been away from Galway for only five months when PRIEST (St. Martin's Minotaur, $23.95) opens. But he spent those months in a hospital (''the madhouse ... the loony bin ... the home for the bewildered''), traumatized at having caused the death of a child. Back in his old haunts but still extremely disoriented, Jack is reluctantly drawn into the investigation of the murder of a pedophile priest whose disembodied head was found in the confessional, a crime that has put the fear of God into any man of the cloth, guilty or not, accused of sexual abuse. You can't expect much in the way of conventional sleuthing from this tormented hero, but there's music in his lament for the corruption of innocence and the loss of faith -- in the government and the clergy -- in ''the new Ireland,'' even as he does battle with the demons that have claimed his own soul.</p>
        <p>Ed Loy had been living in Los Angeles for 20 years when he went home to Dublin to bury his mother in Declan Hughes's first novel, ''The Wrong Kind of Blood.'' Having stuck around to set up a private-eye practice in the hard-boiled American style, Loy resurfaces in THE COLOR OF BLOOD (Morrow, $24.95) to take on a nasty case of pornography, extortion and murder that blackens the reputation of a revered family of physicians. Hughes, a founder of the Irish theater company Rough Magic, racks up a body count to rival that in the last scene of ''Hamlet'' in order to expose the hypocrisies of a certain privileged class of Dublin society. But the overheated theatrics are a proper fit for his tough-guy hero, whose stern moral code and haunted personal history lend credibility to Hughes's recurring theme of ''the sins of the fathers'' and the ''legacy of tainted blood'' they pass on to their children.</p>
        <p>After 12 years on the run in Mexico, the United States and Peru, the Irish mercenary Michael Forsythe battles and bluffs his way home to Belfast in THE BLOOMSDAY DEAD (Scribner, $24), the explosive final installment in a trilogy of kinetic thrillers by Adrian McKinty. After making a surreal stopover in Dublin, where he eludes hit men by mingling with the mobs of James Joyce enthusiasts observing Bloomsday, Forsythe settles an old debt with the New York Irish mob boss Bridget Callaghan by agreeing to recover her kidnapped 11-year-old daughter. Bullets fly and Joycean literary references ricochet everywhere as Forsythe tries to get his bearings in a Belfast so politically stable and yet so redolent of the evil in its violent past that he can't wait to get out of town.h</p>
        <p>CRIME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
