<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Passover Sermon, a Play, and a Century of the Melting Pot</title>
    <meta content="08melting" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/08melting.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schulman, Samuel (Rabbi)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zangwill, Israel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Sam</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Melting Pot, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Passover</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EEDC143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Passover Sermon, a Play, and a Century of the Melting Pot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Passover Sermon, a Play, and a Century of the Melting Pot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sam Roberts article on Jewish origins of phrase 'melting pot' to describe America; notes that Rabbi Samuel Schulman claimed to have coined term during Passover sermon in New York City 100 years ago; says phrase was popularized for eternity by The Melting Pot, 1908 play by Israel Zangwill, London-born son of Russian Jewish immigrants, who was Zionist and believed in assimilation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The melting pot metaphor, touchstone of America's debate over immigration, was claimed by the rabbi of a New York City synagogue, who said he coined it in a Passover sermon he gave exactly 100 years ago.</p>
        <p>The image has been traced to a naturalized New Yorker in 1782, and also to DeWitt Clinton and Ralph Waldo Emerson. Later in 1907, a book by the English writer Ford Madox Ford included a chapter titled ''The Melting Pot,'' which said Britain had been revitalized by the influx of foreigners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stage play “The Melting Pot,” which popularized the phrase and preached the gospel of assimilation, is about to celebrate its centennial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The melting pot metaphor, touchstone of America's debate over immigration, was claimed by the rabbi of a New York City synagogue, who said he coined it in a Passover sermon he gave exactly 100 years ago.</p>
        <p>The image has been traced to a naturalized New Yorker in 1782, and also to DeWitt Clinton and Ralph Waldo Emerson. Later in 1907, a book by the English writer Ford Madox Ford included a chapter titled ''The Melting Pot,'' which said Britain had been revitalized by the influx of foreigners.</p>
        <p>And finally, the following year, the phrase was popularized for eternity in ''The Melting Pot,'' a stage play by Israel Zangwill that preached the gospel of assimilation.</p>
        <p>''I coined the term,'' Rabbi Samuel Schulman said years after his 1907 sermon. ''But I used it in a much different sense than Zangwill subsequently did. American democracy, in my mind, is a vast 'single melting pot,' in that it absorbs all races, brings out the common humanity in each, separates the gold from the dross and preserves only the gold.''</p>
        <p>The play by Zangwill, a London-born son of Russian Jewish immigrants who was a Zionist, made its debut in Washington in 1908 and played in New York for four months the next year. The protagonist is David Quixano, a Jewish immigrant, orphaned by a pogrom, who lives with his uncle on Staten Island and becomes smitten with the daughter of a Russian nobleman.</p>
        <p>In the end, love triumphs, inspiring David to declare from the rooftop of a Lower East Side settlement house that ''America is God's crucible'' and to declaim: ''What is the glory of Rome and Jerusalem where all nations and races come to worship and look back, compared with the glory of America, where all races and nations come to labor and look forward!''</p>
        <p>Prof. Edna Nahshon, of the Jewish Theological Seminary in Manhattan, wrote in the introduction to a new collection of Zangwill's plays that ''unlike its major competitors -- salad bowl, stew, mosaic and symphony -- the melting pot image focuses on process, not on outcome, and presents a prophetic vision that is entirely futuristic.''</p>
        <p>She said: ''The figurative term is an intrinsic element of American discourse and functions as a key image in the country's self-definition.''</p>
        <p>The play's title, wrote Nathan Glazer and Daniel Patrick Moynihan a half century after its premiere, ''was seized upon as a concise evocation of a profoundly significant American fact.'' At least in New York City, though, Moynihan argued in their influential book ''Beyond the Melting Pot,'' ethnicity would eventually be subsumed, yet would never be entirely submerged.</p>
        <p>Zangwill originally titled the play ''The Mills of God,'' then ''The Crucible,'' before settling on ''The Melting Pot.'' The phrase has many fathers, including J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur, a French writer who lived for many years in New York. He wrote 225 years ago that in America, ''individuals of all nations are melted into a new race.'' In his famous sermon, Rabbi Schulman of Temple Beth-El and later of Temple Emanu-El, both on Fifth Avenue, described America as ''the melting pot of nationalities'' (but went on to caution his congregation against too much assimilation).</p>
        <p>By that time, the phrase had appeared in various writings about assimilation, including at least two articles in The New York Times in the fall of 1889 that referred to the ''American melting pot'' as a ''mysterious force which blends all foreign elements in one homogeneous mass.''</p>
        <p>Zangwill's play debuted in New York at the Shuberts' Comedy Theater on Sept. 6, 1909, to criticism from Jewish religious leaders because it tacitly sanctioned intermarriage. (Zangwill himself had married a non-Jew.) The New York Times unambiguously pronounced it a ''very bad play''; another review said the play ''has nothing in it to interest man, woman or child, Jew, Heathen or Christian.''</p>
        <p>After it opened, Zangwill altered the text because President Theodore Roosevelt complained that a line seemed to imply that Americans didn't take marriage seriously enough. (Roosevelt later said the play ''shall always count among the very strong and real influences upon my thought and my life.'') Starring Walker Whiteside, an accomplished Indiana-born actor who later appeared in a silent film version, ''The Melting Pot'' endured a four-month run on Broadway. It was published and occasionally revived, but, as a play, was largely forgotten.</p>
        <p>Zangwill, who also wrote ''Children of the Ghetto'' and ''The King of Schnorrers,'' first visited the United States in 1898 (he likened New York to ''little toy houses built by children of giants'') and maintained an abiding fascination with America.</p>
        <p>In 1923, on his fifth visit, he urged fellow Jews to unite politically to deliver a ''Jewish vote'' on vital issues. He berated New York audiences with a jeremiad against hypocrisy over Prohibition, slow restaurant service, Sunday newspapers, the dirtiness of Central Park, too many towels in hotel rooms, ''Southern slackness in New York'' and postwar restrictions on immigration.</p>
        <p>''You shut out immigrants instead of holding out hospitable hands,'' he said. ''And how did you get your country? You took it by force from the Indians, and your duty is to hold it in trust for humanity. You call it 'God's own country.' For God's sake, make it so.''</p>
        <p>Before returning to Britain, he said: ''I do not dislike America; I love her. When I wrote 'The Melting Pot' I believed her the hope of humanity. How much more terribly true that is today!''</p>
        <p>Zangwill added, however: ''I must confess that at one time I had thought of becoming an American citizen, but I have the desire no longer. I thought I could help America, even though I would be debarred from becoming the president.''</p>
        <p>He died in Britain in 1926 at age 62.</p>
        <p>Since then, the metaphor of the melting pot has evolved. ''If it means that cultures have mixed and impacted each other, he'd have no problem with it,'' said Professor Nahshon, whose book ''From the Ghetto to the Melting Pot'' was published last year. ''If it meant uniformity, he'd totally reject the meaning.''</p>
        <p>The Zangwills had three children: Margaret, who was committed to a sanatorium; Oliver, who became a professor of experimental psychology at the University of Cambridge; and Ayrton, a metallurgical engineer who was about to marry a Welsh woman when he was prodded by his mother to pursue his career instead. He left Britain for a job in Mexico with a company owned by friends of the family, the Guggenheims.</p>
        <p>Ayrton changed his first name to Jorge and married Sara Terrazas Olivares, the granddaughter of a cattle baron. The couple moved to El Paso, where their three daughters were raised as Catholics.</p>
        <p>''From that day forward, Ayrton never missed voting in an election,'' a granddaughter, Patricia Z. Holland-Branch, who runs an interior design company in El Paso, said the other day. He also became a Yankee fan.</p>
        <p>Today, Israel Zangwill's descendants in the United States are a mixture of Irish, Scottish, German, Pennsylvania Dutch, Italian, Swedish, Austrian and Filipino.</p>
        <p>''Israel Zangwill would have been proud to know,'' Ms. Holland-Branch said, ''that the family he helped create has become a tapestry of diverse cultures and ethnic backgrounds, which personify the 'melting pot' he wrote about.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
