<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Island Aid Comes at Westchester's Expense</title>
    <meta content="08limainLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08limain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070415T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION FINANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fessenden, Ford</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFDC163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Island Aid Comes at Westchester's Expense</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Long Island Aid Comes at Westchester’s Expense</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FORD FESSENDEN; Kate Stone Lombardi and Linda Saslow contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fessenden, Ford</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on outrage among Westchester County politicians over last-minute school budget formula worked out between New York Gov Spitzer and state Senate Republican lawmakers; new formula will send much higher amounts of funding to Long Island schools at expense of Westchester County; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR school districts in the suburbs of New York City, there was much to celebrate in the new state budget: lots of new money, for rich districts and poor alike, much more than Gov. Eliot Spitzer had originally proposed.</p>
        <p>But the deal that legislative leaders struck with Mr. Spitzer, allowing the budget to be pushed through at the last minute, contained a new formula for what is called high-tax aid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR school districts in the suburbs of New York City, there was much to celebrate in the new state budget: lots of new money, for rich districts and poor alike, much more than Gov. Eliot Spitzer had originally proposed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR school districts in the suburbs of New York City, there was much to celebrate in the new state budget: lots of new money, for rich districts and poor alike, much more than Gov. Eliot Spitzer had originally proposed.</p>
        <p>But the deal that legislative leaders struck with Mr. Spitzer, allowing the budget to be pushed through at the last minute, contained a new formula for what is called high-tax aid.</p>
        <p>And this new formula sends shovels full of dollars to Long Island but only spoonfuls to Westchester. It was so carefully worded, and its impact is so lopsided, that Democrats are calling it retribution for the defeat last year of a Republican state senator from Westchester, Nicholas A. Spano.</p>
        <p>Republicans, who control the Senate, did not work very hard to dispel that idea last week.</p>
        <p>''This would never have happened if Senator Nick Spano was still there,'' said Senator Dean G. Skelos, the deputy majority leader from Long Island, during a radio interview in New York City last week.</p>
        <p>In a later interview, he insisted that Republicans had not sought retribution but that Westchester's new senator, Andrea Stewart-Cousins, and her Democratic colleagues ''fell asleep at the switch.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Stewart-Cousins replied that the deal was made behind closed doors. ''When you have Dean Skelos even pretending that somehow I sat in the chamber and said nothing -- as if this were some discussion that was open and aboveboard -- it is absolutely ridiculous,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Westchester schools still got lots of money, but in the sibling psychology that prevails in debates over education aid in Albany, there was an outcry over why the county did not get what Nassau and Suffolk got. The Westchester County's Assembly delegation voted against the budget package, although the county senators did not, and last week vowed to undo the new formula.</p>
        <p>''This is a gun that's being pointed at Westchester today,'' said Assemblyman Richard L. Brodsky, a Westchester Democrat. ''If you legitimize this, it could be pointed at New York City or Nassau or Syracuse tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's budget director, Paul E. Francis, scolded Mr. Brodsky in a letter last week for his criticism of the package, saying that Westchester made out very well in the new budget. Not only will state aid increase, but the county will also benefit from School Tax Relief, or STAR, rebate increases, he said.</p>
        <p>The governor's communications director, Darren Dopp, also criticized Mr. Brodsky and defended Ms. Stewart-Cousins. ''He was not talking about Westchester community issues in budget negotiations, but Andrea was,'' Mr. Dopp said.</p>
        <p>Overall state aid to Westchester schools will increase by 9.4 percent next year, slightly less than the 10.1 percent overall increase that Long Island will get. Many districts that would have received a little new money under Governor Spitzer's original proposal, which would have increased school aid 5 percent on Long Island and 6 percent in Westchester, will get substantially more.</p>
        <p>''What we did, what the Republican senators did, was to drive aid to suburban school districts throughout the state,'' Mr. Skelos said.</p>
        <p>Casual readers of the budget bill could be forgiven for missing the big Westchester repudiation. The piece of the aid formula that drove more money to Long Island was based on a ratio of the total property tax revenue generated from a county's residents. This was then divided by the total amount of income all residents reported on tax returns.</p>
        <p>Here's how the formula was written: All school districts in counties in which tax levies were more than 4.2 percent of income would get $147.29 in high-tax aid for every student enrolled. In counties that fell below the cutoff, only certain school districts would get aid, $30 per student.</p>
        <p>Westchester has high taxes, but it also has the highest incomes in the state by far -- about $300,000 per student in the schools, compared with about $160,000 on Long Island and it fell below that cutoff because of its high average income.</p>
        <p>In spite of its many affluent enclaves, Nassau and Suffolk Counties are more diverse than Westchester, and their ratios are above the cutoff. The result is that all Long Island districts will get the higher aid amount, a total of more than $70 million of the $100 million in high-tax aid.</p>
        <p>Only some Westchester districts get aid, and it amounts to a total of $1.2 million.</p>
        <p>''The goal was giving money to Long Island,'' said Assemblywoman Amy Paulin, a Democrat from Scarsdale. ''What they did was figure out a way to manipulate the numbers to make a formula to do that.''</p>
        <p>Westchester state lawmakers also saw large amounts of school aid dollars get distributed to neighboring counties: Orange, Ulster and Putnam. Under the budget agreement, they will all get more than Westchester does.</p>
        <p>On Long Island, where Republicans hold eight of the nine Senate seats, school officials were happy with their state money.</p>
        <p>''We haven't seen the final numbers yet, but we are very grateful that after many years when Long Island didn't get its fair share of funding, our legislators worked so hard to get us more,'' said Carole G. Hankin, the superintendent of the Syosset Central School District.</p>
        <p>But Westchester school officials joined in the outrage. ''It certainly does seem like there were some last-minute political deals, which is unfortunate because there was talk about having a formula and sticking to it,'' said Lisa P. Davis, the president of the Westchester-Putnam School Boards Association.</p>
        <p>Both school officials and Westchester Democrats said they would try to undo the high-tax-aid formula.</p>
        <p>''The door did not close on this,'' Mr. Brodsky said.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION FINANCE</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 15, 2007, Sunday  A photograph with an article last Sunday on the Around Long Island page, about the formula for financing schools in the new state budget, was published in error. It showed Anita F. Hill, a professor at Brandeis University, not State Senator Andrea Stewart-Cousins, a Democrat from Westchester.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 15, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>A photograph with an article last Sunday on the Around Long Island page, about the formula for financing schools in the new state budget, was published in error. It showed Anita F. Hill, a professor at Brandeis University, not State Senator Andrea Stewart-Cousins, a Democrat from Westchester.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
