<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Booming Enrollment, the Odd District Out</title>
    <meta content="08ctmainCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08ctmain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Enrollment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maker, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5D8163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Booming Enrollment, the Odd District Out</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amid Booming Enrollment, the Odd District Out</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH MAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maker, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Region 1 School District in northwestern Connecticut, bucking trend of above-capacity enrollment in public schools, is considering combining grades, laying off teachers and canceling sports programs after sharp decline in enrollment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT a time when enrollment is so far above capacity that some of the state's public schools hold classes in closets, one six-town region in northwestern Connecticut has the opposite problem: Enrollment has declined so sharply that officials are considering combining grades, laying off teachers and canceling sports programs.</p>
        <p>The Region 1 School district -- which has seven schools in Canaan, Cornwall, Kent, North Canaan, Salisbury and Sharon -- has the lowest enrollment of any system in the state. At the Lee H. Kellogg School in the Falls Village section of Canaan, there are seven pupils in the fourth grade, and only five children are expected for kindergarten in September. Enrollment has dropped to 101 from 150 a decade ago, and it is projected to fall to 83 by 2012.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT a time when enrollment is so far above capacity that some of the state’s public schools hold classes in closets, one six-town region in northwestern Connecticut has the opposite problem: Enrollment has declined so sharply that officials are considering combining grades, laying off teachers and canceling sports programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT a time when enrollment is so far above capacity that some of the state's public schools hold classes in closets, one six-town region in northwestern Connecticut has the opposite problem: Enrollment has declined so sharply that officials are considering combining grades, laying off teachers and canceling sports programs.</p>
        <p>The Region 1 School district -- which has seven schools in Canaan, Cornwall, Kent, North Canaan, Salisbury and Sharon -- has the lowest enrollment of any system in the state. At the Lee H. Kellogg School in the Falls Village section of Canaan, there are seven pupils in the fourth grade, and only five children are expected for kindergarten in September. Enrollment has dropped to 101 from 150 a decade ago, and it is projected to fall to 83 by 2012.</p>
        <p>Over all, enrollment at the seven schools has dropped to 1,973 from 2,300 in 1997, and is expected to shrink to 1,646 in the next five years.</p>
        <p>''It's surprising to hear of a district with such low enrollment, when there's a population explosion going on in many schools around Connecticut,'' said Alison Zhou, a State Education Department consultant.</p>
        <p>Connecticut recently received a $2.9 million grant from the federal Department of Education, under the No Child Left Behind program, to help the most crowded school systems build facilities and hire staff members to reduce class sizes.</p>
        <p>''The middle school and high school population is at its highest ever in Connecticut right now,'' said Thomas Murphy, a spokesman for the State Education Department. ''It's expected to decline, but we have quite a number of schools that are filled beyond capacity.''</p>
        <p>New Britain High School, for example, has a capacity of 2,999 but an enrollment of 3,163. ''We've had to convert storage spaces into classrooms, and we have study hall in the cafeteria, which is not good,'' said the principal, Michael J. Foran. The school's average class size is 27, compared with the state average of 20, and many classes have 31 or more students, he said.</p>
        <p>Even wealthy communities like Greenwich and Fairfield have overcrowded schools. Greenwich High School has a capacity of 2,250 but an enrollment of 2,692, and Fairfield Warde High School, with a capacity of 1,400 students, has 1,445, according to the state.</p>
        <p>The reason for Region 1's declining enrollment, educators agree, is that property values have doubled in the last decade, and the residential makeup is now mostly weekenders from New York who educate their children in the city. ''There are 15 houses on my street in Salisbury, and 11 of them are owned by New Yorkers,'' said Paul Sales, principal of the Salisbury Central School.</p>
        <p>But Region 1 is reveling in its tiny class sizes, despite concerns about economics or what happens when there are not enough students to make up a baseball team.</p>
        <p>''I like that no one can steal your lunch money because we don't have a cafeteria and everyone brings their own lunch,'' said Karl Grannan, one of eight third graders at the Lee H. Kellogg School.</p>
        <p>''I like how our teacher knows us so well, and we know her,'' said a classmate, Riley Simmons, also 8, as his teacher, Eileen Rogers, smiled. ''Like, we know she has a fluffy dog named Daisy, and we know where she lives, and we know what she does every weekend. Pretty much everything.''</p>
        <p>But Kellogg's principal, Maria Bulson, questioned whether the students were acquiring the socialization skills they would get at a larger school. ''Going from kindergarten through eighth grade with the same few kids is tough,'' she said.</p>
        <p>So next year, the school will group together kindergarten through second grades, and third through fifth grades, a move that could result in eliminating several teaching positions, Ms. Bulson said.</p>
        <p>''The low-enrollment situation has enormous pros and cons,'' said Patricia Chamberlain, the region's schools superintendent. ''On the one hand, you have small, intimate classes, where the children are showered with attention. It's like a family, everyone knows each other and feels very comfortable.</p>
        <p>''On the other, there's economics; can we afford to keep running all of these schools with so few students in them?''</p>
        <p>Region 1's annual per-child education cost is about $16,000, while the state average is about $10,000. ''Our per-pupil cost is the highest in the state, and it's just going to go up as our enrollment goes down,'' said Mr. Sales, the Salisbury principal.</p>
        <p>The region comprises six kindergarten-to-eighth-grade schools in each town, and one regional high school in Canaan. The school in Salisbury has two buildings, elementary and intermediate. With enrollment there dropping to 312 from 404 in 1997, and projected to slide to 254 by 2012, Mr. Sales and other educators believe the intermediate building will have to be closed in two years, and all grades will be consolidated into one building.</p>
        <p>''You've got certain fixed costs in keeping these buildings running, regardless of how many students are in them,'' he said. ''It's just not cost-effective.''</p>
        <p>Salisbury is also grappling with the prospect of canceling sports programs as enrollment dwindles. ''We're already making exceptions and letting sixth graders join teams that are supposed to be for the older kids,'' Mr. Sales said. ''But we may soon be at the point where we just can't come up with the numbers you need for team sports.''</p>
        <p>Susan Kennedy, director of the No Child Left Behind program in Connecticut, said that Region 1's situation might have its drawbacks but that its strengths were enviable. ''The goal is to create smaller school environments, where teachers can really get to know the kids, and the kids want to be there because they feel loved and important,'' she said. ''Like they do in Region 1.''</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
