<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Where Family Died Is Now Safe Haven</title>
    <meta content="08baltimore" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/us/08baltimore.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baltimore (Md)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dawson Safe Haven Community Center (Baltimore, Md)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simmons, Melody</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dawson, Angela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dawson, Carnell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland/Baltimore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Baltimore (Md)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3DE143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Where Family Died Is Now Safe Haven</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Home Where Family Died Is Now Safe Haven</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELODY SIMMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simmons, Melody</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, April 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Baltimore house where fire started by drug dealer killed neighborhood crusader Angela Dawson, her husband Carnell and their five children in 2002 has been renovated as Dawson Safe Haven Community Center; financing for $1.5 million project came from city, state, federal and private sources; building houses computer lab and arts and crafts center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For most of the last five years, the charred corner house in a blighted East Baltimore neighborhood stood vacant, a symbol of all that could go wrong in an urban war on drugs.</p>
        <p>Last week, though, that changed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A community center has opened in a Baltimore row house that made headlines when a drug dealer set it ablaze, killing a neighborhood crusader and her family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For most of the last five years, the charred corner house in a blighted East Baltimore neighborhood stood vacant, a symbol of all that could go wrong in an urban war on drugs.</p>
        <p>Last week, though, that changed.</p>
        <p>The sound of children's laughter once again fills the row house, which made headlines in 2002 when a drug dealer kicked open the front door in the middle of the night and set it ablaze, killing Angela Dawson, a neighborhood crusader; her husband, Carnell; and their five children, ages 9 to 14.</p>
        <p>The house has been renovated as the Dawson Safe Haven Community Center, and officially opened last week.</p>
        <p>''We will not let them be forgotten,'' said Pamela V. Carter, 53, director of the center. ''The tragedy put a great cloud over us. People were heartbroken and hoped to see something done about this tragedy.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Dawson, 36, was known as a fierce opponent of the drug dealing that routinely took place outside her door. The fire occurred on Oct. 16, 2002, after Ms. Dawson had filed a string of complaints with the police against drug dealers.</p>
        <p>Days after the fire, the police arrested Darrell Brooks, 21, who lived near the Dawson home. Mr. Brooks pleaded guilty and is serving a life sentence without parole.</p>
        <p>Each year on the anniversary of the fire, a vigil has been held on the street outside the home. A memorial garden was planted on an adjacent corner, filled by a small grove of trees and mosaic plaques bearing the name of each victim.</p>
        <p>Plans for the center have been in the works for years, Ms. Carter said, with financing for the $1.5 million project coming from city, state, federal and private sources.</p>
        <p>Construction began a year ago and inspired a mixture of hope and horror among the neighbors. Many said they wanted the house to be renovated but feared stirring up memories of the fire.</p>
        <p>''It's very important for the kids to come here, but I think a bit eerie sometimes'' said Taneisha Sanders, a coordinator at the center. ''They say, I wonder where this or that was, or where the kids were'' at the time of the fire.</p>
        <p>The third floor, where the family's bedrooms had been, today holds a busy computer lab. An arts and crafts center sits one floor below. Outside, a bright blue light flashes 24 hours a day, notification that a police camera is trained on the corner.</p>
        <p>Ms. Carter said drug dealers still did business in the neighborhood, but she is not deterred. ''You'll see them, hanging around and standing on different corners and things,'' she said, ''but it's not like I'm afraid. I have a job to do. I walk in God's blessings and so far, they're very respectful. They know we mean business and that we're here to stay.''</p>
        <p>Baltimore ranks among the nation's most violent cities. As of Friday, the city had recorded 71 homicides this year, higher than last year's count at the same date. The police say most of the killings are drug related.</p>
        <p>Visitors to the center one busy afternoon this week said they came at first out of curiosity. Taylor Street, 12, a sixth grader, is working on a biography of the Baltimore jazz musician Cab Calloway. ''Everybody was scared to come in here,'' she said. ''They said the spirits were going to come back,'' Taylor said. ''But once I was here, it was fine.''</p>
        <p>Aaron Anderson, 15, who lives nearby and knew the Dawson children, added: ''It's sad. I'd rather not be here and them still alive, but the center will play a big role in keeping kids off the streets.</p>
        <p>''The streets are terrible,'' Aaron added. ''Anything can happen on any given day. You can get shot, killed, everything. Maybe it might save somebody's life and make them realize they should come in here and do their homework. It's easier.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
