<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nuova Cucina Newcomer On Restaurant Row</title>
    <meta content="08ctdineCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08ctdine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/STAMFORD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ferrante (Stamford, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6D8163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nuova Cucina Newcomer On Restaurant Row</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nuova Cucina Newcomer on Restaurant Row</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews Ferrante restaurant in Stamford, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''DO you only review Italian restaurants?'' a reader once asked. Of course not. But sometimes it seems that the only restaurants to open with regularity are Italian.</p>
        <p>That's what took me recently to restaurant row in Stamford -- Summer Street between Broad Street and West Park Place -- to visit Ferrante. This Italian newcomer is situated in a much-reconfigured space that once housed Zanghi and, before that, Amadeus. I like what the new owners have done with what used to be a rather awkward layout; the principal dining room is now in front, and the atmosphere is clubby and congenial. On warm days the entire front wall opens to the sidewalk, adding an extra dimension to the dining experience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While the décor is traditional at Ferrante in Stamford, some of the food is different for an Italian restaurant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''DO you only review Italian restaurants?'' a reader once asked. Of course not. But sometimes it seems that the only restaurants to open with regularity are Italian.</p>
        <p>That's what took me recently to restaurant row in Stamford -- Summer Street between Broad Street and West Park Place -- to visit Ferrante. This Italian newcomer is situated in a much-reconfigured space that once housed Zanghi and, before that, Amadeus. I like what the new owners have done with what used to be a rather awkward layout; the principal dining room is now in front, and the atmosphere is clubby and congenial. On warm days the entire front wall opens to the sidewalk, adding an extra dimension to the dining experience.</p>
        <p>While the décor is traditional, some of the food is different for an Italian restaurant: many entree portions are medium-small, not overwhelming, and the plates have eye appeal (in nuova cucina style). Instead of a gargantuan amount of chicken smothered in sauce, pollo alla Ferrante contained a few segments of breast wrapped around prosciutto and fresh asparagus in a soupçon of Champagne sauce. (While I applaud the concept of smaller portions, I found this one a bit stingy, but my guest considered it just right.)</p>
        <p>Another entree in nuova cucina mode was cannelloni di funghi -- four short pasta tubes filled with ricotta and wild mushrooms. Instead of the menu's cherry tomato marinara, my friend requested a white sauce and the kitchen accommodated with a delicious cream sauce.</p>
        <p>My chief complaint is that dishes in relatively spartan portions deserve a little garnishing -- a veggie perhaps, or a starch -- to justify the prices and appease the palate. Saltimbocca alla Romana consisted of veal escalope with prosciutto, wild mushrooms and baby artichokes, but a scoop of mashed potatoes or rice would have absorbed some of the tantalizing sauce. Another entree, grilled tuna steak, with sautéed radicchio over-doused in a sharp-edged aged balsamic vinegar, also needed a touch of rice or potato.</p>
        <p>My osso buco alla Bosco, though, was just right: a healthy hunk of veal shank, with a huge bone and fatty ''shawl.'' The meat was succulent and fork-tender, surrounded by whole chanterelles, oyster and shiitake mushrooms, with a small side dish of soft polenta.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, small portions worked well in many appetizers. At too many restaurants the starters are so large that an entree is almost unnecessary. Carpaccio malatesta -- filet mignon sliced tissue-paper-thin, with equally thin shavings of Parmesan, an abundance of arugula and a julienne of vegetables -- piqued the appetite perfectly. The same was true of calamaretti fritti (baby squid pan-fried crisp, with a tangy red sauce) and vitello tonnato (veal pounded paper-thin and covered with a delicate tuna sauce).</p>
        <p>There were just two menu mishaps. The anchovies were missing from an otherwise tasty Caesar salad and the croutons, of all things, were missing in panzanella, a Tuscan bread salad, which consisted of an appealing medley of fresh tomato, cucumber, onion and basil spilling prettily from a radicchio leaf.</p>
        <p>Desserts were impeccable, from crème brûlée with a melt-in-mouth crust, to a super-smooth panna cotta and housemade cheesecake. Our table's favorite was a warm chocolate cake (torta cioccolato) stippled with almond bits.</p>
        <p>Ferrante is still feeling its way. But it already does so many things right, fine-tuning should come easily. It can be a winner for years to come.</p>
        <p>Ferrante</p>
        <p>191 Summer Street  Stamford  (203) 323-2000</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Stately wooden columns, cream-colored walls with wood wainscoting, a few banquettes and glass wall sconces with subdued lighting characterize this large space, with a bar along one wall and a second room in the rear for private parties. Wheelchair accessibility.</p>
        <p>THE CROWD -- Mostly couples, a few families and some business groups. Large staff is cordial and helpful, but some have limited English skills.</p>
        <p>THE BAR -- Full bar. Wine list is varied and comprehensive. Italian vintages dominate, with interesting choices from all major wine-producing countries. By the glass $9 to $12; bottles range from $35 to the rare reservas ($300 to $2,000).</p>
        <p>THE BILL -- Same menu for lunch and dinner. Appetizers $7 to $14; entrees $14 to $36; desserts $9 to $12. Most credit cards accepted.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE LIKE -- Vitello tonnato, calamaretti fritti, carpaccio malatesta, capesante alla griglia; cannelloni funghi, pollo alla Ferrante, tonno alla griglia, osso buco alla Bosco; panna cotta, torta cioccolato, crème brûlée, cheesecake.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO -- Open Sunday to Thursday, 11:30 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 11:30 a.m. to midnight. Reservations recommended on weekends. Limited street parking, but there are several pay lots farther down Summer Street.</p>
        <p>Reviewed April 8, 2007</p>
        <p>DINING/STAMFORD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
