<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Magic Words</title>
    <meta content="Fairbanks.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Fairbanks.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Framing the Debate: Famous Presidential Speeches and How Progressives Can Use Them to Change the Conversation (and Win Elections) (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E2DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Magic Words</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Magic Words</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVE FAIRBANKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fairbanks, Eve</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FRAMING THE DEBATE</p>
        <p>Famous Presidential Speeches and</p>
        <p>How Progressives Can Use Them to Change</p>
        <p>the Conversation (and Win Elections).</p>
        <p>By Jeffrey Feldman.</p>
        <p>201 pp. Ig Publishing. Paper, $14.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How Democrats can win by using terms that resonate with voters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FRAMING THE DEBATE</p>
        <p>Famous Presidential Speeches and</p>
        <p>How Progressives Can Use Them to Change</p>
        <p>the Conversation (and Win Elections).</p>
        <p>By Jeffrey Feldman.</p>
        <p>201 pp. Ig Publishing. Paper, $14.95.</p>
        <p>Back in 1990, Newt Gingrich sent his Republican colleagues a list of words to use to describe their Democratic opponents: ''sick,'' ''pathetic,'' ''bizarre,'' ''traitors'' and ''corrupt'' were some of the choicest. Getting the party on message helped the Republicans win in 1994, but Gingrich's memo was a disaster for our political culture: it enshrined as demonstrated truth the idea that winning elections in America is all a game of spin and wordplay -- a game Republicans happened to be better at than Democrats. Weirdly, even after last November's Democratic rout, we're still living in Newt's world. ''Those Republican 'magic words' '' that blind voters, according to the blogger Jeffrey Feldman, are still the big threat to Democrats' electoral success -- and, to help the left, he offers a rhetoric handbook, ''Framing the Debate,'' based on the Democratic strategist George Lakoff's ideas about politics and language. In it he parses the language of great speeches to give progressives some words of their own -- ''keywords'' and ''metaphors,'' as he describes them -- that will help create persuasive ''frames'' for their policies, like ''us against them'' or ''happiness is achievement.''</p>
        <p>Writing a blog is different from writing a book, and Feldman is best on the kind of smaller-bore observations that might fare well online; for example, he recognizes that the humble mood of George Washington's first inaugural speech could prove a powerful affect for a rising star like, say, Barack Obama. But his grand theory of how ''the frame'' works in politics is a shockingly simplistic, almost childlike application of Gingrich's axiom: in short, turning voters from conservative evil to liberal good doesn't depend on a rich mix of language, leaders, circumstances and actual accomplishments, but boils down to hitting the right keywords to put us in a happy mood about progressive proposals.</p>
        <p>Armed with this interpretation of why politicians succeed, Feldman makes bizarrely grandiose claims about what the proper word can accomplish: it would be ''virtually impossible,'' he says, ''for even an expert in presidential rhetoric to not be persuaded'' by Harry Truman's arguments against Communism -- because of the way Truman deployed the word ''enemy.'' Nowadays, if we talk about health insurance in terms of ''promise of opportunity'' instead of cost, ''new health care possibilities can flourish without being stomped out by the fear of costs.'' Solutions are easy. Selling them is the hard part.</p>
        <p>First off, it ain't true. When the Republican Party's image went south in 1995, George Stephanopoulos likened Gingrich to a poker player whose masterly bluffs were finally starting to fail: ''Newt's very good. He has his word list. But he has a very bad hand.'' To make his claims about the power of framing hold, Feldman tries to credit rhetorical efforts, like calling veteran candidates ''Fighting Dems,'' for last year's Democratic victories. But it seems forced. Republicans had botched Iraq, Katrina and ethics, and once again had a very bad hand.</p>
        <p>Feldman's theory also promotes unjust misinterpretations of the great presidential speeches he's chosen, because by ascribing their success to framing, it severs their words from the ideas behind them. He determines that the power of the Gettysburg Address derives from its frame of the ''principle of equality,'' which Lincoln sets up by invoking the keywords ''of the people, by the people.'' The Gettysburg Address does have a particularly beautifully rendered frame, one that compares the Civil War to Jesus' Passion: ''Our fathers brought forth'' the nation, ''dedicated'' it, as in baptism, and, after a bloody trial, it will have a ''new birth.'' But when Lincoln said, ''We are ... testing whether that nation'' conceived in liberty ''can long endure,'' he wasn't ''framing'' the war ''as a conversation about preserving the people's democracy.'' He was saying something much bolder: that the war was a struggle for democracy. Equality is not Lincoln's frame. It is his message.</p>
        <p>And this message wasn't common-sensical then, or merely in need of some semantic freshening up -- it was radical. Why would Lincoln have spent six years before he was elected in 1860 on a single-minded crusade to convince people that ''all men are created equal'' was the foundation, the ''ancient faith,'' of American government, if all it took was the right framing to get them in a mood to abolish slavery?</p>
        <p>But Feldman's Americans are not the kind who stand for hours at a Lincoln-Douglas debate, who ever ask their politicians to substantively persuade them of the rightness of ideas or weigh arguments in the voting booth. They -- we -- are more Pavlovian. Our brains are like vast blinking switchboards; the successful politician is the one who presses just the right buttons (''equality,'' ''enemy'') to light up the sequence of neurons that makes our hands shoot out and pull the lever marked ''D.''</p>
        <p>This approach radiates cynicism. That's the most amazing -- and insidious -- thing about this book: Feldman presents himself as a bulwark of democracy, dedicated to promoting ''a healthy American political culture filled with more voices and more points of view.'' But his vision of politics is profoundly undemocratic. To believe that the ''enemy'' frame is impossible for us to resist -- that our behavior as citizens flows, robotlike, from the way we are manipulated by buzzwords -- is to see us as Shakespeare saw those laughably malleable Romans in ''Julius Caesar'': they are inspired first to hate Caesar by Brutus' speech and then to love him by Antony's, in the space of minutes. This scene is terrifying because it reveals that even though Caesar has just been assassinated to preserve the Republic, the Republic is already dead. Its people are unfit for it. So, too, with us, if our minds are governed by keywords.</p>
        <p>Eve Fairbanks is an assistant editor at The New Republic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eve Fairbanks is an assistant editor at The New Republic.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
