<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Concierge Loves Bouncing Around the N.B.A. Store</title>
    <meta content="08cheer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHEERING SECTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DE143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Concierge Loves Bouncing Around the N.B.A. Store</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallozzi, Vincent M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three of the N.B.A.'s leading scorers got an assist from Steve Candeloro last month.</p>
        <p>''LeBron James was throwing a party for his son, and he asked me to send him 500 basketball-shaped mugs,'' said Candeloro, the concierge manager at the N.B.A. Store in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three of the N.B.A.'s leading scorers got an assist from Steve Candeloro last month.</p>
        <p>''LeBron James was throwing a party for his son, and he asked me to send him 500 basketball-shaped mugs,'' said Candeloro, the concierge manager at the N.B.A. Store in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''Gilbert Arenas, my best customer, stopped by the store and I helped him find some new jerseys we have in stock,'' Candeloro said. ''Vince Carter left a message on my machine about an item he was looking for, and I got back to him right away.''</p>
        <p>Candeloro, 45, who lives in Astoria, Queens, has worked at the N.B.A. Store since it opened in 1998, earning the promotion from sales associate in September 2000. Sports fans and celebrity hounds would pay to have his job, which involves meeting and greeting shoppers, some of whom are professional athletes, movie stars and politicians. He offers tours of the store, rattling off prices and other information about the merchandise along the way.</p>
        <p>Often perched behind a lectern a few feet from the front door on Fifth Avenue, Candeloro also spends a good deal of time handling telephone orders. He has shipped bandannas, backpacks, bobbleheads and basketballs to Brooklyn and to Beijing.</p>
        <p>He once sent a 3-foot-high bobblehead of the Spurs' Tony Parker to San Antonio, at Parker's request. But he has also helped hundreds of parents pick out goody-bag fillers for birthday parties and other celebrations at the store.</p>
        <p>''It's an interesting job, an opportunity to meet all kinds of fans,'' said Candeloro, who previously worked on television talk shows and soap operas. He is comfortable in the company of celebrities, who allow their inner fan to surface in the store.</p>
        <p>''Here,'' he said during a recent fashion show, ''the sports gods walk among the normal people.''</p>
        <p>Working to the beat of the buzz spilling from his walkie-talkie, Candeloro showed Nets Coach Lawrence Frank a 3-foot-tall bobblehead of Carter, one of his star players. He handed Frank a business card, then wheeled to deal with the Knicks' Channing Frye and Jared Jeffries, who were staring at a huge framed lithograph of the 50 greatest N.B.A. players.</p>
        <p>''Hello, gentlemen,'' Candeloro said in a voice that was equal parts casino greeter, salesman and priest. ''My name is Steve Candeloro. I'm your concierge, and I'll be glad to help you with any questions you might have this evening.''</p>
        <p>''The top-50 lithograph is one of our most precious items,'' he told Frye and Jeffries. ''It's signed by everyone except Pete Maravich,'' who died in 1988. ''If either of you are interested, it costs $75,000.'' They raised their eyebrows.</p>
        <p>When someone asked when and where the Denver Nuggets were playing next, Candeloro scurried to the nearest computer. He looked up from the keyboard to see the former Knick Walt Frazier, who said he was interested in ''old-school jerseys.''</p>
        <p>Seconds later, Frazier was staring at racks of classic jerseys stitched with names like Chamberlain, Erving and Gervin. Hanging among them was a 1970s-style Frazier jersey, which Candeloro, an astute sports fan, had placed next to Earl Monroe's.</p>
        <p>''These older jerseys are 100 percent polyester,'' Candeloro told Frazier. ''As you know, players perspired a lot more in these than they do in the microfiber-type jerseys they wear today.''</p>
        <p>Frazier smiled as he ran his fingers over his old No. 10.</p>
        <p>''No doubt, these were a lot warmer,'' Frazier said. ''But the arenas we played in back then were so much colder, so we needed it.''</p>
        <p>Candeloro dashed into a back room to look for an autographed Michael Jordan jersey. Rummaging through stacks of boxes, he came across a Yao Ming jersey and recalled that Yao, the 7-6 Houston Rockets center, once ducked into the store and was startled by a life-size bobblehead of Shaquille O'Neal. Candeloro also remembered the night Jason Williams, then with the Sacramento Kings, showed up with several teammates long after the store had closed.</p>
        <p>''They were just standing out there, their faces pressed against the window,'' Candeloro said. ''So I let them in.''</p>
        <p>W.N.B.A. stars like Sue Bird, Diana Taurasi and Tamika Catchings have also been drawn to the store.</p>
        <p>But the famous clientele includes people outside the basketball world. The N.H.L. greats Wayne Gretzky and Mark Messier have stopped in, Candeloro said, as have dozens of baseball players past and present, including Don Sutton, Dontrelle Willis and Dave Winfield.</p>
        <p>''One night, Melky Cabrera and Robinson Canó popped in,'' Candeloro said, referring to two young Yankees.</p>
        <p>The soccer star David Beckham picked up gear for his sons. ''He bought a Knicks jersey for one son, and a Miami Heat jersey for the other,'' Candeloro said.</p>
        <p>Former President Bill Clinton shopped there, and as did Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger of California and his wife, Maria Shriver. Candeloro has also crossed paths with the actors Tom Hanks, Bill Murray and Julianne Moore.</p>
        <p>''One of the keys to this job,'' he said, ''is comfortable shoes.''</p>
        <p>CHEERING SECTION E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
