<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A (Relatively) Good Quarter for Foreign Stocks</title>
    <meta content="08intl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/mutfund/08intl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838800"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A (Relatively) Good Quarter for Foreign Stocks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A (Relatively) Good Quarter for Foreign Stocks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OWNERS of American blue chips found the first quarter eventful if unprofitable. Investors in overseas stock markets had more to show for their wandering spirit as those markets continued a long run of outperformance.</p>
        <p>The Morgan Stanley Capital International World Index, excluding the United States, ended the quarter up 3.5 percent, easily beating the 0.2 percent gain of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investors in overseas stock markets had more to show for their wandering spirit as those markets continued a long run of outperformance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OWNERS of American blue chips found the first quarter eventful if unprofitable. Investors in overseas stock markets had more to show for their wandering spirit as those markets continued a long run of outperformance.</p>
        <p>The Morgan Stanley Capital International World Index, excluding the United States, ended the quarter up 3.5 percent, easily beating the 0.2 percent gain of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index.</p>
        <p>The relative resilience may comfort investors in overseas markets. Even so, after four years of strong gains and several weeks of nervous trading in markets worldwide, managers of international portfolios counsel vigilance.</p>
        <p>Many are turning attention to companies that they expect to be relatively immune from further market turbulence. They are gravitating toward industries where earnings stability is virtually assured, like health care, food and drink, retailing and tobacco, because they provide products that consumers need or want enough to keep buying regardless of the economic climate.</p>
        <p>Other selections are companies in any industry that have financial strength their rivals lack or that are taking aggressive steps to improve profitability. The picks tend to share one feature: they have been overlooked or even avoided by investors, often for several years.</p>
        <p>Gilman Gunn, manager of the Evergreen International Equity fund, has long admired ''big consumer-staples companies that have global reach.'' These companies were not the most lucrative path to profit as the global economy and stock markets were moving ahead without interruption, but their stocks have been paying off lately.</p>
        <p>During the market decline in late February and part of March, consumer staples stocks ''outperformed by a considerable margin,'' he noted.</p>
        <p>William Fries, co-manager of Thornburg International Value, is another who prefers ''consistent earners'' in an iffy climate. His favorites include Teva Pharmaceutical Industries, the Israeli manufacturer of generic drugs; Next, the British clothing retailer; and Rogers Communications, the Canadian cable television company -- all of which, he said, are reasonably well insulated from problems in the broader economy. Even when the economy is on less-than-firm footing, he said, ''people are not going to stop paying their cable bill.''</p>
        <p>They are not going to stop eating and drinking, either, an attraction of many businesses that Mr. Gunn prefers, including Unilever, the British-Dutch maker of food and household products; Cadbury Schweppes,  the British food and drink company; and Carrefour, the French retailer.</p>
        <p>Also in their favor, he said, is their willingness to take steps to reinvent themselves after years of disappointing investors. He applauds the efforts of these companies and others in different sectors, like  Siemens of Germany and Michelin of France, to revamp operations. The shares stand a good chance of advancing if restructuring efforts succeed, Mr. Gunn said.</p>
        <p>And maybe even if they do not. The companies' low valuations leave them ripe for takeover bids, another factor that should put a floor under their stocks, he said. ''Time is short for these guys,'' he remarked. ''It's really close to the point where if they don't do it, others will.''</p>
        <p>AS far as Christopher Semenuk, manager of the TIAA-CREF International Equity fund, is concerned, time has already run out for Unilever, Siemens and others that he dismisses as serial restructurers.</p>
        <p>''We almost never own those kinds of companies,'' he said. ''They are typical restructuring companies and are not performance-oriented.'' Instead of overhauling their operations to enhance growth, he said, they ''always try to acquire their way out of trouble, and they always seem to pay too much.''</p>
        <p>When discussing the companies he prefers, Mr. Semenuk sounds more like their shrink than their shareholder. ''We're focused on companies that are self-help-oriented,'' he said. When they take steps to ''uncover or realize value in their businesses, they're doing things that they're in control of and that the market is less in control of.''</p>
        <p>Examples include Reckitt Benckiser, the British maker of household products, which he credits with continually replenishing its repertoire of products and increasing sales at a faster clip than rivals, and Danone,  the French producer of yogurt and other foods. ''Danone is a perfect example of a management that does restructure,'' he said. ''They're always getting rid of businesses that they don't see a future in and plowing money back into businesses where they do see a future.''</p>
        <p>Referring to the company's fast earnings growth, he said, ''It's not a cheap stock, but you get more than what you pay for.''</p>
        <p>These companies happen to sell consumer staples, but Mr. Semenuk, unlike Mr. Gunn, has no special affection for the sector. What makes Danone and Reckitt safe, Mr. Semenuk said, is not so much what they make as how they make it.</p>
        <p>''There are good defensives and bad defensives,'' he said. ''People need to eat, but if companies never grow, how is that defensive?''</p>
        <p>Other safe choices that he highlighted include Bayer, the German health care and chemical business; Accor, the French hotel company; and Kao, a Japanese maker of household and personal care products.</p>
        <p>As in other facets of life, the best defense for an investor can be a good offense. For Mr. Fries at Thornburg, that means buying Western companies that do big business in emerging markets. Even if growth slows around the globe, his reasoning goes, it is still likely to be stronger in emerging markets than in the developed world. An example is PotashCorp, based in Saskatchewan, which is finding healthy demand for its fertilizer in emerging economies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fries cited China Mobile, that country's dominant provider of cellphone service, as a company that combines the safety of a utility with the growth prospects available in emerging markets. It has 300 million subscribers, he said, and is adding 3 million to 4 million a month.</p>
        <p>''China Mobile will have a growing inventory of subscribers at revenue rates that over time will expand,'' he predicted. As a national corporate champion in a country where free-market principles are not always applied rigorously, he added, it may also benefit from government assistance in acquiring radio frequencies and infrastructure for its network.</p>
        <p>Mark Headley, manager of Matthews Pacific Tiger and other Asia funds, advises investors in the region to ''look for quality assets that have gotten ahead of themselves.'' He says he has been finding them in markets like Thailand and South Korea that are reasonably valued yet have been buffeted lately, along with far more richly priced markets like China.</p>
        <p>If some of the cheaper stock markets ''take a 20 percent haircut,'' he said, ''they'll start to look very exciting.''</p>
        <p>When conditions are unsettled, Hugh Young, head of equities at Aberdeen Asset Management, says he finds the best havens to be companies with ''strong balance sheets and robust business models.''</p>
        <p>His choices include Oversea-Chinese Banking Corporation, known as OCBC Bank, of Singapore; Swire Pacific, a Hong Kong conglomerate; QBE, the Australian insurer; Femsa, the Mexican beverage company; Banco Santander of Chile and Petroleo Brasileiro, the giant Brazilian oil company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Young said he was having trouble finding safe investments in emerging markets because so many of his peers were looking for them. ''The trouble is that the shares prices of many of the classically defensive stocks have risen,''he said. ''Ultimate safety may lie only in cash.''</p>
        <p>Americans who choose to stay in stocks may start seeking safety closer to home, Mr. Semenuk said. Although foreign markets have shown resilience this year, he wonders how long investors will stick with them if conditions remain difficult.</p>
        <p>''When people are confident, they go to Europe, then when they feel really good they go to Asia,'' he said. ''Then in times of trouble they head back the other way. People always migrate westward in times of trouble.''</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
