<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rites of Spring; Honoring Through Song</title>
    <meta content="08RcatholicLI-5" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838951"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">St Paul's Episcopal Church (Fairfield, Conn)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Episcopal Church</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rites of Spring; Honoring Through Song</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA WOLFE BOYNTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boynton, Cynthia Wolfe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at St Paul's Episcopal Church in Fairfield, Conn, described as children's choir rehearses for Easter services; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a season of renewal for Christians and Jews as they commemorate momentous events in their histories: for Christians, the resurrection of Jesus; for Jews, the liberation of the ancient Hebrews from slavery in Egypt. As Jews began celebrating the eight days of Passover at sundown last Monday, Christians observed the final, most solemn days of Lent in preparation for Easter services this weekend. Here are a handful of stories about different faith communities around the region.</p>
        <p>Standing tall behind mahogany desks, their sheet music splayed before them, the members of the children's choir of St. Paul's Episcopal Church in Fairfield, Conn., looked as serious as the music they were about to sing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a season of renewal for Christians and Jews as they commemorate momentous events in their histories: for Christians, the resurrection of Jesus; for Jews, the liberation of the ancient Hebrews from slavery in Egypt. As Jews began celebrating the eight days of Passover at sundown last Monday, Christians observed the final, most solemn days of Lent in preparation for Easter services this weekend. Here are a handful of stories about different faith communities around the region.</p>
        <p>Standing tall behind mahogany desks, their sheet music splayed before them, the members of the children's choir of St. Paul's Episcopal Church in Fairfield, Conn., looked as serious as the music they were about to sing.</p>
        <p>For Easter, the group plans to perform familiar, upbeat hymns that need little practice. But for Good Friday services, the 9- to 13-year-olds needed to learn a new piece -- one that because of the solemnity of occasion, they would sing a cappella, in Latin.</p>
        <p>And many of the choir members at this rehearsal last Monday were seeing the song for the first time.</p>
        <p>''Come on, kids -- lots to do before chocolate bunnies this weekend,'' said John Abdenour, the director of music at St. Paul's, as he stood at a worn baby grand piano. Established at the church in the early 1900s, the choir is modeled after those that have sung in Anglican cathedrals in England for centuries. Affiliated with the Royal School of Church Music founded in 1927 at London's Westminster Abbey, the choir performs in Europe every four years. Its next trip, scheduled for June, will take the choir to St. Mary's Episcopal Cathedral in Edinburgh and Durham Cathedral in England, where the group will sing at services each day.</p>
        <p>''We have an elite choir with a grand tradition to uphold, which most of the kids take pretty seriously,'' Mr. Abdenour said. ''But right now we've got four days to get ready for Good Friday and are a little behind.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Abdenour, or Mr. A to the children, doesn't hold auditions. All parish youths are welcome to give the choir a try. To help accommodate busy schedules, he holds four rehearsals each week. Each choir member is required to attend at last two.</p>
        <p>''The schedule can be tough, but my daughter never balks,'' Robin Jerrild said of her 9-year-old, Meghan. ''Getting her to go to soccer practice can sometimes be a challenge, but never to choir.''</p>
        <p>Hannah Nemiah, 10, said she considered the choir good training. ''Singing harder pieces, and with older kids, forces me to challenge myself,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Challenging'' might well describe the choir's first few tries Monday at ''Miserere'' -- the newly introduced Good Friday piece. Several times, Mr. Abdenour used his pencil to tap out the rhythm on the piano lid.</p>
        <p>''Forget it, you're all fired,'' he said, as several youngsters stumbled over the word ''righteousness.''</p>
        <p>''No, no,'' he quickly added. ''You're doing a great job learning this from scratch. Keep going.''</p>
        <p>A Baroque hymn composed in the 1600s, ''Miserere'' is based on the 51st Psalm. It is a prayer for forgiveness and mercy that asks God to ''open thou my lips'' so ''my mouth shall shew forth thy praise.''</p>
        <p>While the psalm itself is dark and full of lamentations, one line of ''Miserere'' seems to describe what the Rev. Bennett A. Brockman, the rector of St. Paul, said he sees the choir do each week.</p>
        <p>''Words can be inadequate -- especially during the Easter season, which celebrates the most triumphant moment in Christianity,'' he said. ''They spread the word of God with a kind of exuberance that you can't help but get caught up in.''</p>
        <p>CYNTHIA WOLFE BOYNTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
