<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Show Goes On, Just Don't Drink to It</title>
    <meta content="08NJcolNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08NJcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pitman (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coyne, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1DF173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Show Goes On, Just Don't Drink to It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Show Goes On, Just Don’t Drink to It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kevin Coyne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Coyne, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>Pitman</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kevin Coyne Jersey column on debate over whether to allow liquor sales in Pitman, one of only 39 dry towns left in New Jersey; voter referendum, prompted by success of newly refurbished Broadway Theater, has been scheduled for November; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the evening sky dimmed, the neon marquee seemed to glow ever brighter and redder against the soft spring dusk, beckoning toward the beloved old theater a line of patrons that kept lengthening down the block.</p>
        <p>''This is what you did,'' said Peter Slack, taking in with a sweep of his arm the Broadway Theater, the ornate movie palace where he and just about everyone else who grew up in this shady, front-porch town once spent their matinee afternoons, and where he became the new owner last year. ''We brought it back to what it was like when I was a kid.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the success of a reopened theater, a dry town asks if it should offer visitors a place to drink.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the evening sky dimmed, the neon marquee seemed to glow ever brighter and redder against the soft spring dusk, beckoning toward the beloved old theater a line of patrons that kept lengthening down the block.</p>
        <p>''This is what you did,'' said Peter Slack, taking in with a sweep of his arm the Broadway Theater, the ornate movie palace where he and just about everyone else who grew up in this shady, front-porch town once spent their matinee afternoons, and where he became the new owner last year. ''We brought it back to what it was like when I was a kid.''</p>
        <p>And it's what you do again now, ever since the thousand-seat theater reopened in September and turned out to be exactly the kind of magnet that old downtowns are always seeking in their battles against the outlying malls that have lured away their shoppers. Movies are $5, and 5,700 people bought the season subscription for live performances: $65 to see ''Gypsy,'' ''The Odd Couple'' and four other regional-theater staples. George Carlin sold out two shows in one night recently, drawing 2,000 people to a town with a population of 9,600.</p>
        <p>But what those 2,000 people discovered that night was that the only places to eat near the theater were a couple of pizza parlors, and the only places to drink were the bars and restaurants that wait to catch the outbound traffic at the borders of this dry Gloucester County town, one of just 39 left in New Jersey. (Most of the others are sparsely populated rural townships in the southernmost counties.)</p>
        <p>''It's coming to a head now,'' said Mayor Alice Polocz, talking about the debate over liquor licenses as she walked near the barnlike tabernacle at the center of Pitman Grove, the defunct Methodist camp meeting ground where the town was born, a short block away from the theater. Twelve lanes, echoing the number of the apostles, radiate out from the tabernacle like the spokes of a wheel, lined by small, closely set cottages.</p>
        <p>And so at its most recent meeting, on March 26, spurred by the theater's success and the grumblings of some downtown merchants, the Borough Council finally discussed in public a question that previously had been posed only in private: Should Pitman remain dry?</p>
        <p>''The council decided, considering how the town was formed, that the people also need to have a say,'' said Ms. Polocz, 66, who owns Bob's Hobbies and Crafts a few doors down from the theater, and who is running for her second term in November. She expects to share the ballot with a referendum question that will ask voters whether a town founded by temperate Methodists should issue liquor licenses for the first time in its history.</p>
        <p>Across from the mayor's store, Alan Forte was already planning his strategy. ''Big, big signs -- 'Vote for liquor here,' '' said Mr. Forte, 27, who owns a fitness center that would benefit from the increased foot traffic he believes a restaurant or two would bring to the downtown. ''It's ridiculous. This is 2007. That we have that law now is absurd.''</p>
        <p>Pitman's population would entitle it to issue three licenses for restaurants or bars and an additional one to the theater, which has more than the thousand seats required under state law. ''Everyone's realized that Pitman has gone downhill, so everyone's thinking what are the ways we can help bring it back, and a liquor license is something that pops up, because there are bars on every corner outside of Pitman,'' said Mr. Slack, 50, who owns a medical publishing company and lives 10 blocks from the theater he bought for $303,000 at a bankruptcy auction. ''People in Pitman are frequenting these places, and the money's going outside of town.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Slack spent $700,000 to refurbish the theater where Frank Sinatra, Abbott and Costello, Bing Crosby and Bob Hope performed, and he plans to seek a license to serve beer and wine in the thickly carpeted upper lobby. Pitman may have outlived its dry years, he thinks, but not everyone agrees.</p>
        <p>''A liquor license would be great in a restaurant, if it could stay there,'' said Walt Madison, 57, a painting contractor who spent 21 years on the Borough Council, and 1,000 hours -- and 12 cases of Krylon gold spray paint -- making the cavernous gilt interior look the way it did when the Broadway opened in 1926. ''But the problem is that when the restaurant closes, it can go anywhere. I'm not in favor of it.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Polocz suspects that Mr. Madison's sentiments will prevail in the referendum. ''I think most of the people will go back to why the town was founded,'' she said. ''I also think people will look at it this way: 'Why do we want to be like everybody else when we've got something special the way we are?' ''</p>
        <p>As she circled back from Pitman Grove to her store, she passed an old stone horse trough that sits on the plaza across from the municipal building, a reminder of the town's past and of the hurdles facing the referendum. ''WCTU 1912'' is the inscription. The initials are a mystery to some people in town, but many others still remember what they stand for: the Woman's Christian Temperance Union.</p>
        <p>JERSEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
