<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spotlight N.B.A.; Valuable? McGrady Surely Ranks For Impact</title>
    <meta content="08hoops" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/basketball/08hoops.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Dallas Mavericks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Houston Rockets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Houston Rockets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Dallas Mavericks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Houston Rockets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McGrady, Tracy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nowitzki, Dirk</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Boozer, Carlos Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bosh, Chris</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1296" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spotlight N.B.A.; Valuable? McGrady Surely Ranks For Impact</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Most Valuable? McGrady Surely Ranks for Impact</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tracy McGrady wanted in on the debate. But first he wanted a definition.</p>
        <p>''What is our M.V.P.?'' he said Thursday during a spirited telephone interview from Houston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Houston’s Tracy McGrady, Utah’s Carlos Boozer and Toronto’s Chris Bosh have worked behind the scenes to lift their teams out of last season’s disarray.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tracy McGrady wanted in on the debate. But first he wanted a definition.</p>
        <p>''What is our M.V.P.?'' he said Thursday during a spirited telephone interview from Houston.</p>
        <p>One man's treasure is another man's junk, the saying goes, and McGrady, the Rockets' star, was trying to determine value in terms of the subjective season-ending award given to the N.B.A.'s most valuable player.</p>
        <p>Most times it is awarded to the complete player who led his team to the best record in the league (like Dirk Nowitzki of Dallas this season). Or it is given to the player who has led his team to the second-best record (like Steve Nash of Phoenix). Sometimes even the player who scores in hypnotic, extraterrestrial flashes (like Kobe Bryant of the Lakers) elbows himself into the argument.</p>
        <p>When asked last week to choose between Nowitzki and Nash for M.V.P., Suns forward Amare Stoudemire, the beneficiary of Nash's nifty passes, sidestepped the obvious.</p>
        <p>''I think Kobe Bryant should be at the top of the list,'' Stoudemire said by telephone. ''His game is unstoppable.''</p>
        <p>McGrady, a two-time scoring champion, said that adding Bryant to the mix muddied the award's intent.</p>
        <p>''If you're going to put Kobe in there, it's not who's most valuable to their team,'' McGrady said. ''He is the best player in the league, no doubt. But to me, the M.V.P. is about the overall contributions to the team and what the team has done.''</p>
        <p>Reporters and broadcasters who cover the N.B.A. vote for the postseason awards; The New York Times does not participate. If McGrady had a ballot, he said: ''I'd vote for Dirk Nowitzki. What his team has done this year and how he's played, it's his time.''</p>
        <p>As Nowitzki and the Mavericks have captivated the league with their single-minded success, McGrady and other All-Stars -- Utah's Carlos Boozer and Toronto's Chris Bosh, especially -- have worked behind the scenes to lift their teams out of last season's disarray and into the playoff picture.</p>
        <p>Perhaps a new category should be created to honor the N.B.A.'s biggest impact player. Do we hear chants for B.I.P.?</p>
        <p>McGrady said the idea was right, if not the abbreviation. Still, he nominated himself for the B.I.P. shortlist.</p>
        <p>''I would put myself in that category because we have one of the best records in the league,'' McGrady said. ''What I did when Yao was out of the lineup, that speaks for itself.''</p>
        <p>Center Yao Ming broke his right leg in December and missed 32 games; McGrady carried the Rockets to a 20-12 record. He scored 30 or more points in 15 games, while averaging 7.1 assists.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people had written us off, and I took that as a challenge,'' McGrady said.</p>
        <p>Nobody had been writing much about the Raptors until Bosh, a fourth-year forward, gave his worldly teammates a reason to believe. His 22.8 points and 10.7 rebounds a game have led Toronto to the top of the Atlantic junk pile and their first division title. The Raptors (43-33) have won 16 more games than they did last season, the biggest improvement in the N.B.A. this season.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Washington's Gilbert Arenas was the East's most legitimate M.V.P. contender for his all-around numbers. Even before Arenas's season-ending knee injury last week, his enormous game and personality did not give the Wizards a double-digit boost.</p>
        <p>Arenas's and Bosh's accomplishments could be considered relative. The disparity between the conferences has been a season-long theme, so why not rub it in? On Friday, the team with the fourth-best record in the West, Utah, had the same number of victories as the East's best, Detroit.</p>
        <p>It is in the middle of the West, where Houston and Utah -- destined to meet in the first round -- present a compelling study of the impact of stars and coaches.</p>
        <p>Coach Jerry Sloan is not exactly enjoying Utah's impending playoff berth, its first since the John Stockton-Karl Malone era. His team has been too inconsistent, he said, too young, and the home-court advantage against Houston not yet secure.</p>
        <p>''It's been my toughest year with this team,'' said Sloan, in his 19th season. He knew his team would be deeper and healthier than last season, starting with Boozer, who was injured for 56 games of Utah's 41-41 campaign.</p>
        <p>Why was this season so tough? ''Because of what I put myself through,'' Sloan said. ''I have to be the blame for it, for the expectations of wanting to do well and expecting more.''</p>
        <p>Sloan's relentless drive for perfection, demanding style and knack for finding the right combinations to fit his system unites him and his Houston counterpart, Jeff Van Gundy, in misery.</p>
        <p>''That's the beauty of how good a coach Jerry Sloan is: He gets whoever's available to play as hard as he can, every time,'' Van Gundy said last week, crediting Sloan's toughness and tenacity. ''He's never won the coach of the year award, and that speaks more to who votes. If the coaches had a chance, he might win the award every year.''</p>
        <p>Sloan would not indulge that notion, although he agreed to discuss Boozer's impact. Utah is 34-13 when Boozer registers a double-double, his versatility, strength and his quickness often overwhelming opponents.</p>
        <p>''He's been a hard worker, something which was probably overlooked by people when he got hurt,'' Sloan said. ''That example really helps our young players.''</p>
        <p>Boozer is a more accurate shooter (56.1 percent) and pulls down more rebounds (11.8 a game) than Nowitzki and Duncan. He complements Utah center Mehmet Okur while the second-year point guard Deron Williams is emerging as Stockton's heir apparent.</p>
        <p>Few Jazz players (except the backup Derek Fisher) have significant playoff experience, and the quest for a long postseason run continues to motivate McGrady.</p>
        <p>He is tired of hearing that he is the best player never to win a playoff series.</p>
        <p>Is this the year?</p>
        <p>''Oh man, I sure hope so,'' he said, laughing. Reflecting on his five previous series with Toronto, Orlando and Houston, he added: ''I know looking back, I was always the underdog. Each time the team that beat us was the better team. I think that this is the year I have the supporting cast. I've got a dominant big man.''</p>
        <p>Yao and McGrady have never fully realized their combined potential in their three seasons together. The Rockets were 6-15 last season when Yao had toe surgery, five of those losses coinciding with McGrady's absence because of back spasms. They are 11-38 without McGrady in his three seasons, including the past two games that he missed because of a stiff back.</p>
        <p>When Yao was hurt after an M.V.P.-worthy start, McGrady was inspired.</p>
        <p>Van Gundy said: ''There's not one guy in the league who, during the time Yao was out, could have taken his team and done what Tracy did. He played out of his mind and gave our team confidence.''</p>
        <p>McGrady is averaging a career-high 6.3 assists this season and gives another assist to Van Gundy for his coaching during Yao's absence.</p>
        <p>''Somehow he reached Dikembe Mutombo and rejuvenated him like he was 20 years old,'' McGrady said, referring to the Rockets' 40-year-old backup center. ''He put players in positions where their strengths are, like using Chuck Hayes as an undersized power forward to help Deke.''</p>
        <p>McGrady said Thursday that he felt clear of the serious back pain and that the recent stiffness was unrelated to his previous injury. For that, McGrady gives B.I.P. consideration to John Patterson, the rehabilitation specialist in Waco, Tex., who has worked wonders McGrady cannot explain.</p>
        <p>''I could barely walk when I got in there,'' he said of his initial visit in December. ''When I got back on the court, it was like perfect timing.''</p>
        <p>Now in sync with Yao, McGrady can only hope it is his time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
