<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Surge's Elusive Target: Fear Itself</title>
    <meta content="08wong" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/weekinreview/08wong.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838855"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD: DO OVER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Petraeus, David H</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6DF143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Surge's Elusive Target: Fear Itself</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iraq Plan’s Elusive Target: Fear Itself</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Americans call it a ''soft knock.''</p>
        <p>American soldiers on patrol pound on an Iraqi family's front door, then parade in, each with 70 pounds of body armor, ammunition and M-16 assault rifle. Sometimes they search the house room by room. Sometimes they sit and talk. Depending on the family's mood, sweet tea is served.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>G.I.’s are back to knocking on doors, seeking Iraqis’ trust. It isn’t quickly given  or easily kept.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Americans call it a ''soft knock.''</p>
        <p>American soldiers on patrol pound on an Iraqi family's front door, then parade in, each with 70 pounds of body armor, ammunition and M-16 assault rifle. Sometimes they search the house room by room. Sometimes they sit and talk. Depending on the family's mood, sweet tea is served.</p>
        <p>It is being done throughout Baghdad. As part of the new security plan, soldiers are trying to narrow the gap between Iraqis and Americans, in hopes that will leave the locals feeling safer -- a task that has always seemed beyond the Americans in the four years they have been here.</p>
        <p>On a recent night in western Baghdad, the conversation went like this.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to harass you or anything,'' Lt. Johnny Mulholland, 23, said to the father through his interpreter.</p>
        <p>The lieutenant had planted himself on the couch. His fellow soldiers hung about like linebackers waiting to block any trouble.</p>
        <p>''We just want to learn a little bit about the neighborhood,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The father, Abdul Hadi, stood across the room in a white robe.</p>
        <p>''I don't mix with the other people in this neighborhood,'' he said, his voice tense.</p>
        <p>''Do you know anything about the illegal checkpoints on Market Road?'' the lieutenant asked.</p>
        <p>''They put up illegal checkpoints sometimes,'' Abdul Hadi said.</p>
        <p>Who were ''they''? No one in the house knew. Or if they did, they would not say. The soldiers marched out. And with that, the look of anxiety on the faces of Abdul Hadi and his wife vanished.</p>
        <p>I felt like I had just watched one of those movie sequels in which the plot is a thinly disguised replay of the original, with different actors speaking the lines. I had accompanied soldiers on the same kinds of house visits and night patrols in 2003 and 2004, when the war seemed as young as the men and women sent to fight in it. I had seen similar families in similar homes along the same dark streets trying to figure out what these well-armed foreigners wanted -- and how to emerge unscathed from each encounter.</p>
        <p>The security plan that began on Feb. 14 is in many ways a return to the days of formal occupation. It involves raising the troop level to 173,000, the highest of the war. It involves soldiers living in neighborhoods across Baghdad, eating lamb with sheiks, doing foot patrols through streets littered with trash and stray dogs and rusted car hulks.</p>
        <p>It is Counterinsurgency 101 as espoused by Gen. David H. Petraeus, the top American commander in Iraq. The idea is to establish regular contact with Iraqi civilians and win their allegiance. Back in 2003, the commanders also had a name for it: ''hearts and minds.''</p>
        <p>''I have a job to do, and I ask, 'What do I need to do to make these people feel secure, and how long do I need to be out on the street?' '' said Capt. Benjamin Morales, 28, a barrel-chested Bronx native in charge of the same company of the 82nd Airborne Division to which Lieutenant Mulholland is assigned.</p>
        <p>But there are differences in the American approach now, products of a long, difficult learning curve as the nature of the war -- and the Iraqis' hearts and minds themselves -- have changed. For one thing, the soldiers and their commanders no longer talk about ''dead-enders,'' no longer insist to reporters that Iraqis do not think of themselves as Sunnis and Shiites. They recognize that they stand between two sides in a sectarian war.</p>
        <p>Commanders like Captain Morales point to neighborhoods on their satellite maps and say: Here is where the Shiite militias are driving out Sunni families. Here is where Sunni insurgents threaten Shiites. They can put their fingers on spots where bodies are found -- eyes blindfolded, hands tied, skin covered with the kinds of marks no one outside medical school should ever have to see.</p>
        <p>That kind of violence has actually been unfolding for two years, but during that period American generals were distancing themselves from the population, pulling their troops back into sprawling bases with movie theaters and a dozen flavors of ice cream in the dining halls. Fewer soldiers on the streets meant fewer Americans at risk, and it was comforting to hope that Iraqi security forces would increasingly take charge. That did not work out.</p>
        <p>Hence the surge, with the order to get back outside the wire: Talk to the locals. Stroll through markets. Step out of Humvees.</p>
        <p>''Driving through an area at 30 miles per hour and calling that a patrol is not effective,'' Captain Morales said. ''You're not going to get the information you need. You're never going to establish a rapport.''</p>
        <p>So the captain sends his men out on foot patrols almost every night. He meets with neighborhood councils as he did on his first tour here in 2003 and 2004.</p>
        <p>The captain's unit, Company B of the 1st Battalion, 325th Airborne Infantry, arrived in Baghdad at the start of February. It is stationed in one of 48 neighborhood garrisons that the Americans have set up in the capital. There are squat toilets and lukewarm showers and a mess hall with no lunch, just dinner cooked up by the soldiers.</p>
        <p>The base is in the Ali Salah neighborhood of western Baghdad. My first day there, Captain Morales walked me over to a map in the hallway of his command center. To the north of the base was Kadhimiya, a Shiite stronghold dating back centuries. To the south was Mansour, an upper-class Sunni Arab neighborhood that the Shiites want to take over, he said. In between were Salaam, Topchi and Ali Salah, where Shiite militias had driven out almost all Sunni Arab families.</p>
        <p>That recognition of Iraq's volatile sectarian dynamic was absent from American calculations in the first two years of the war.</p>
        <p>Now the officers say a central focus of the mission is to keep militias, Sunni or Shiite, from carrying out sectarian cleansing. To do that, they need to understand the population better.</p>
        <p>The captain said he felt he was developing a real rapport with the locals this time around. ''In 2003, we paid people for intelligence,'' said Captain Morales, who is on his third tour. ''Now, people are sick of the insurgents. They're sick of the violence, they're sick of bombs breaking their windows. They'll give the information for free. I haven't had to pay for information.''</p>
        <p>But the contact can be shattered by a single bullet. That happened with the death of a woman I had met in the captain's neighborhood, and whose murder I covered.</p>
        <p>Captain Morales had cultivated a relationship of trust with Suaada Saadoun, a widowed Sunni Arab who had complained to the Americans that she and her family were being harassed by Shiite militiamen.</p>
        <p>The captain had her number in his cellphone. She had come to the base to tell him about the bad elements in the neighborhood. He had visited her home.</p>
        <p>On March 28, Ms. Saadoun was shot dead while walking through the market -- just a day after American and Kurdish soldiers arrested two Shiite men who were trying to serve her with an eviction notice.</p>
        <p>When Captain Morales heard about Ms. Saadoun's murder, he sent Lieutenant Mulholland's platoon to her home. The lieutenant was to play detective. He walked past black-robed women wailing in the backyard and sat down with two men inside the home.</p>
        <p>One man, Abu Bariq, a resident of the house, said the handful of Sunni Arabs left in the neighborhood were all on a hit list compiled by a Shiite militant named Haider. But Haider was hard to find. He moved from place to place.</p>
        <p>There's no one we can go after right now, said one of the lieutenant's men, Sgt. Danny Medina, using an expletive.</p>
        <p>The Americans drove to the alleywaywhere Ms. Saadoun had been killed. Men in a nearby bakery said they had heard shots but seen nothing.</p>
        <p>In the early years of the war, Lieutenant Mulholland might have ordered his men to round up dozens of people from the market to bring back to the base for questioning. Then he might have gone and done the same in Haider's neighborhood.</p>
        <p>I had seen American soldiers back then drag groups of men from their homes, put green sacks over their heads or white blindfolds around their eyes, and march them into armored vehicles to drive them back to base for interrogation. The detainees were then corralled into dirt pits surrounded by concertina wire. Such tactics are now frowned upon by many commanders, lest they convert more Iraqis into insurgents.</p>
        <p>But that still left the question of how to quell the fears Ms. Saadoun's murderers had roused.</p>
        <p>On this afternoon, Lieutenant Mulholland returned to his base with only a photo of Haider that Abu Bariq had given him.</p>
        <p>He would carry it with him as he knocked on more doors.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD: DO OVER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
