<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Hamptons, No Hedging On Their Privacy</title>
    <meta content="08licolLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/08licol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hamptons (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sagaponack (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island/Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDC163FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Hamptons, No Hedging On Their Privacy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Hamptons, No Hedging on Their Privacy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Corey Kilgannon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <dateline>SAGAPONACK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Corey Kilgannon The Island column on tall privet hedges that surround luxury homes and estates in Hamptons, NY, and possibility that Sagaponack might curtail their use; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS Hamptons village has the highest home prices in the country, with the median selling price in 2005 topping $3 million. The biggest, most expensive home in the Hamptons, a $185 million, 29-bedroom oceanfront estate on 63 acres, is also here.</p>
        <p>One doesn't drop $185 million, or even $3 million, on a summer pad to be gawked at by day-trippers, and that's where that totemic Hamptons hedge known as privet comes in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the Hamptons, the hedge known as privet keeps day-trippers from gawking at high-priced estates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS Hamptons village has the highest home prices in the country, with the median selling price in 2005 topping $3 million. The biggest, most expensive home in the Hamptons, a $185 million, 29-bedroom oceanfront estate on 63 acres, is also here.</p>
        <p>One doesn't drop $185 million, or even $3 million, on a summer pad to be gawked at by day-trippers, and that's where that totemic Hamptons hedge known as privet comes in.</p>
        <p>This hardy shrub was brought to Southampton by English settlers in the 1600s and used as natural fencing. The tall, well-clipped hedgerows of privet have become ubiquitous along the luxurious lanes of Southampton and East Hampton Villages, shielding the summer homes of the rich and famous from onlookers.</p>
        <p>In those leafy labyrinths, open space means the distance to the next hedge, but Sagaponack still offers sweeping views of unencumbered expanses of old potato farms and fields that run down to ocean dunes.</p>
        <p>As more summer mansions, however, are thrown up on these open lots, and hedges are thrown up around them, locals are throwing up objections to the threat of these bushy barriers.</p>
        <p>''People still appreciate Sagaponack as a village because it still has open farmland views,'' said Patrick Guarino, chairman of Sagaponack's zoning commission. It is proposing a zoning code for the village, which incorporated in 2005.</p>
        <p>The commission has discussed whether owners of open space in Sagaponack should be allowed to plant tall hedges. Members decided that restricting size and placement of new privet hedges is not a zoning issue but one for the village code, and that it may be proposed to village trustees in coming weeks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Guarino said that tall hedges are problematic to Sagaponack's open character, but that it would also be problematic to make homeowners hold back their hedges. ''We don't think that's ever been done before,'' he said. Sagaponack falls within the Town of Southampton, which has never applied its fencing restrictions to privet hedges.</p>
        <p>The office of Dan's Papers is near the turnoff to Sagaponack. The weekly's publisher, Dan Rattiner, said that the lack of tall hedges had long set Sagaponack apart from the rest of the Hamptons, but that the hedges that sprang up in recent years had begun spoiling that.</p>
        <p>''Generations of families were able to look from one end to another, across the farm fields stretching down to the beach,'' Mr. Rattiner said. ''But in a lot of areas you really can't do that anymore because of the hedges. It's simple historical preservation to regulate them now.''</p>
        <p>Perry Guillot, a landscape architect and hedge connoisseur from Southampton, agreed. As he drove around Southampton Village on Monday, he pointed out the consequences of hyper-hedging in the Hamptons. The privet hedges on Meadow Lane and First Neck Lane and Gin Lane reveal as much as they conceal about their homeowners, he said.</p>
        <p>''These hedges give you an insight to extreme wealth,'' said Mr. Guillot, whose 2004 book, ''Privet Lives: An Imaginary Tale of Southampton's Iconic Shrub'' (Powerhouse Books), offers a spoof of the Hamptons hedge. ''The hedges seem to say, 'I have all this and I can afford to maintain it and I don't need people to see it.' ''</p>
        <p>He admires the way a simple shrub known as Ligustrum vulgare became a Hamptons symbol of wealth, power and privacy. He respects it as a dignified alternative to fencing and loves the way it signifies the Hamptons and lends the villages a visual unity. He loves the way a hedge can mirror its homeowner's personality, whether clipped high and tight into topiaries or let loose like a shaggy hippie haircut. From the settlement of the Hamptons by some of the earliest Americans to its settlement today by some of the richest Americans, the privet is the symbolic link, Mr. Guillot said.</p>
        <p>But he laments that the hedges have become a weapon of estrangement, used to block out one's fellow man and the larger natural world, as well as a metaphor for the lack of understanding of the rural roots of the land.</p>
        <p>''These hedges break down the sense of community and create not just a physical barrier but an emotional and psychological separation between people,'' Mr. Guillot said. ''Blocking off your house with a hedge is a selfish way to claim that what's yours is yours and no one else can see it.''</p>
        <p>He stopped at the Meadow Club, with hedges encircling grass tennis courts that exude a very specific message: Exclusivity. Privacy. Members only. ''The hedge is symbolic of all that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Guillot passed the turreted oceanfront estate of Calvin Klein and then the yellow mansion of the late music mogul Ahmet Ertegun. It was surrounded by unkempt hedges upward of 20 feet.</p>
        <p>Even owners of the few farms and open parcels left in Southampton have begun putting up hedges. The historic Fiore Farm on Wickapogue Road was sold to a developer who, while seeking building permits, has put up tall privet hedges.</p>
        <p>''You see?'' Mr. Guillot said. ''And farm owners are putting hedges around farmland, too. This is what Sagaponack is afraid of.''</p>
        <p>THE ISLAND E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: theisland@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
