<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Leader Board and Fans, Nature's Cold Shoulder</title>
    <meta content="08anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/sports/golf/08anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masters Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Appleby, Stuart</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mickelson, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Leader Board and Fans, Nature's Cold Shoulder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Leader Board and Fans, Nature’s Cold Shoulder</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA, GA.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Masters weather is usually warm and sunny, sometimes rainy and often windy. But it is hardly ever cold, and it was never cold and windy until the third round yesterday, when Mother Nature demanded to be Augusta National's first female member.</p>
        <p>With record cold frosting the azaleas and a stiff, swirling northwest wind swaying the towering pine trees, the world's best golfers wore cashmere sweaters or thick wind shirts as if they were trying to cope with the windy chill off the North Sea at St. Andrews in Scotland. Tiger Woods wore rain pants to keep warm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>No matter which golfer wins, if the Augusta National nabobs have a sense of humor or a sense of propriety, Mother Nature will deserve the green jacket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Masters weather is usually warm and sunny, sometimes rainy and often windy. But it is hardly ever cold, and it was never cold and windy until the third round yesterday, when Mother Nature demanded to be Augusta National's first female member.</p>
        <p>With record cold frosting the azaleas and a stiff, swirling northwest wind swaying the towering pine trees, the world's best golfers wore cashmere sweaters or thick wind shirts as if they were trying to cope with the windy chill off the North Sea at St. Andrews in Scotland. Tiger Woods wore rain pants to keep warm.</p>
        <p>Most of the Masters ''patrons,'' alias the peasants behind the green gallery ropes, were dressed for it. Ski caps and mittens suddenly were fashionable.</p>
        <p>At least it was sunny, which warmed the temperature from the low 40s in midmorning when the first twosomes teed off to a high of 52 around 2:15 in the afternoon. The wind chill rose from 36 degrees at noon to a high of 47 degrees at 4 p.m., but when the last twosome finished after 7:30 p.m., it had dropped to a not-so-warming 42 degrees.</p>
        <p>Golfers aren't accustomed to wind-chill weather. They follow the sun. Even a scorching sun, almost always a comfortable sun.</p>
        <p>And just when Woods was moving up the leader board, Mother Nature gave him a cold shoulder. Bogeys on the last two holes for a par 72 kept him at three over par for the tournament and four strokes off the lead at the time he finished. When Stuart Appleby of Australia toppled backward with a triple-bogey at No. 17 but still held the lead at two-over-par 218, Woods was only one stroke behind entering the final round today, when they will tee off in the final twosome.</p>
        <p>''It was tough day with the wind gusts,'' Woods said. ''You hit quality shots and just get absolutely hosed. Hopefully, you get committed to hit the proper shot and get lucky at the same time with the wind.''</p>
        <p>Woods always wears a red shirt on Sunday, but when asked if he had packed a red sweater or any warm red clothing for today's round, when the wind is expected to be not quite so fierce, he said, ''No and no.''</p>
        <p>Of the early leaders, Jerry Kelly had endured the most cold-weather golf. Born and raised in Madison, Wis., and still residing there when he's not on the PGA Tour, he was an all-city high school hockey player who went to the University of Hartford on a golf and hockey scholarship. So growing up, he knew how to play good golf in chilly weather.</p>
        <p>''I prepare for it,'' he said after a 69 on Friday. ''I know what gloves I'm going to wear. It's the same clothing I wear at home when I practice. I can't tell you how many times I've practiced when it's below freezing. That's a normal occurrence for me. A lot of times I'll have to hit from the inside of a trailer with heaters, but you always want to get out there on the grass.''</p>
        <p>Out there on the Augusta National grass yesterday, Kelly, his bare forearms protruding from a red shirt over a zippered black turtleneck, was cruising along in second place at one over par for the tournament until he bogeyed No. 12, double-bogeyed No. 14 and bogeyed both No. 15 and No. 18. He finished with a 78, but thanks to Mother Nature, he was only four strokes off the lead.</p>
        <p>The cold wind blew Brett Wetterich, an Ohioan who now lives in the warmth of Jupiter, Fla., off the leader board.</p>
        <p>''It's harder, the cold air,'' he said Friday when he shared the 36-hole lead with Tim Clark of South Africa. ''Obviously no one wants to play in 50 degrees out here. You've just got to take a little more club on holes. I grew up in it, so I'm kind of used to the cold weather.''</p>
        <p>But yesterday, Wetterich, bundled in a beige windshirt, had a bogey at No. 2, a triple-bogey at No. 3 and a bogey at No. 4, never to be seen again among the 10 names on the big leader boards. He shot an 83.</p>
        <p>Phil Mickelson, who moved to within four strokes of the lead with a 73, described the conditions ''as tough as I've seen,'' but because the greens had been watered, he said he didn't think ''it was unfair by any means.''</p>
        <p>For today, the forecast was for a freeze warning with record cold below 30 degrees from midnight to 9 o'clock in the morning when the weather is expected to be sunny but continued very cool with an eventual high of 59 degrees and a wind from the west-northwest at 8 to 12 m.p.h.</p>
        <p>No matter which golfer wins, if the Augusta National nabobs have a sense of humor or a sense of propriety, Mother Nature will deserve the green jacket.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
