<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lisa Ristow and Mark Polansky</title>
    <meta content="08unions" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/fashion/weddings/08unions.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STATE OF THE UNIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EEDB173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lisa Ristow and Mark Polansky</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lisa Ristow and Mark Polansky</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Jane</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR most of his life, Mark L. Polansky's heart was in outer space. Then one day, he agreed to give Lisa N. Ristow, a striking blonde and former high-school cheerleader, a ride to a work-related brunch. She appeared at his doorstep in Houston, and his heart came screeching back to planet Earth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Polansky, 50, an astronaut who piloted his first mission on the shuttle Atlantis in 2001, and Mrs. Polansky, 36, who worked for a NASA contractor in Houston, married a few months after Mr. Polansky arrived home from the Atlantis mission. Since then, they have traversed the Earth inside the atmosphere, to Italy, France and just recently, to the vineyards of the Napa Valley.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A follow-up on a couple featured in Vows on Oct. 14, 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR most of his life, Mark L. Polansky's heart was in outer space. Then one day, he agreed to give Lisa N. Ristow, a striking blonde and former high-school cheerleader, a ride to a work-related brunch. She appeared at his doorstep in Houston, and his heart came screeching back to planet Earth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Polansky, 50, an astronaut who piloted his first mission on the shuttle Atlantis in 2001, and Mrs. Polansky, 36, who worked for a NASA contractor in Houston, married a few months after Mr. Polansky arrived home from the Atlantis mission. Since then, they have traversed the Earth inside the atmosphere, to Italy, France and just recently, to the vineyards of the Napa Valley.</p>
        <p>But any travel has been curtailed severely, at least on Mrs. Polansky's part, by the birth of Caitlin, now 2, and the impending arrival of a baby boy in July.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Polansky, a native of San Antonio, left her job about six months ago, but plans to return after she has her second child. ''I left with mixed emotions; I really enjoyed my job,'' Mrs. Polansky said. ''But it was hard with having a child. I can always go back when I'm ready.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polansky, though, still managed to zip off into space in December. The native New Jerseyan commanded the shuttle Discovery, arriving home three nights before a better-known pilot fueled by fantasy and reindeer.</p>
        <p>''Once we had Caitlin,'' he said, ''I thought a lot more about family, about my wife and kids, and that I put them at some level of risk when I climb aboard that vehicle to carry out my profession.''</p>
        <p>Love keeps Mrs. Polansky looking the other way. ''He could go out in the street and get hit by a car today,'' she said. ''What comes comes. I have to accept it.''</p>
        <p>Her husband flew his first space mission two years before the space shuttle Columbia disintegrated upon re-entry over Texas in 2003, killing all aboard.</p>
        <p>''I know that we talked about it after Columbia, whether this was something we still wanted to do, and we did,'' Mr. Polansky said. ''But the perspective for Lisa, watching me go off to do my job in space, was going to be different than the first time, before Columbia. I have control. She comes into this as a passenger.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Polansky asserts herself in other ways. She moved into the four-bedroom house Mr. Polansky already owned in Houston, and, taking advantage of her husband's easy nature, decorated it in her style. ''Never did I feel that the house belonged only to Mark,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Once Caitlin was born, he for the most part gave up any thought of running out for an ice hockey game. She sacrificed afternoons of ice skating. But they haven't given up spending time with friends. They belong to a dinner club, where the children play, the adults drink and eat.</p>
        <p>''What I really like about my core group of friends is that they know me as Mark and not as an astronaut,'' he said. ''They'd kick me upside of the head if I got a big head, if Lisa hadn't kicked me upside of the head already.''</p>
        <p>Every now and then they still make a night of dinner out and the opera. But they stay home more often now, their feet planted firmly on the terra firma of Houston.</p>
        <p>''I think having my best friend around and being able to confide and talk to him, that is something I've gotten used to having,'' Mrs. Polansky said.</p>
        <p>He takes comfort in the fact that Mrs. Polansky was working as a support engineer for the astronaut office of the Johnson Space Center in Houston when she married him, so she was prepared for how the risks of his job might affect the family.</p>
        <p>''She's worked with astronauts, been to launches, eyes widen open, knew what this business was about,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But, there could be other perils as well. Those were made evident by a highly publicized love triangle involving the astronauts Cmdr. William Oefelein and Capt. Lisa Nowak, friends of Mr. Polansky's. Captain Nowak is charged with the attempted kidnapping with intent to commit bodily harm of a perceived rival, Capt. Colleen Shipman, for the affections of Commander Oefelein.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Polansky believes those perils exist in all of human nature, as unpredictable on ground as in space.</p>
        <p>''It's easy to sit there and say 'she has this special job and therefore that causes this,' '' he said. ''But we're talking about individual human beings who have their behavior patterns and their quirks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polansky's biggest flaw, his wife said, is his penchant for flinging his clothes on the floor. Mrs. Polansky is almost as easygoing as her husband, though, and she has forgiven him for allowing his clothes to surrender to gravity. Her kindly nature and her tendency not to sweat the small things has not gone unnoticed.</p>
        <p>''She's warm and loving and will curl up with me and make me melt, and I've always enjoyed that,'' he said. ''But as hard as I try, I'm never going to learn to pick those things up.''</p>
        <p>STATE OF THE UNIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
