<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thinking Big At a Time Others Are Thinking Small</title>
    <meta content="08stre" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/nyregion/thecity/08stre.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="STREET LEVEL / DUTCH KILLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dutch Kills (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vandam, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Queens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E6D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thinking Big At a Time Others Are Thinking Small</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Thinking Big at a Time Others Are Thinking Small</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF VANDAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vandam, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Street Level column on upzoning efforts in Dutch Kills neighborhood in northwest Queens, NYC; many local residents favor upzoning designation so that larger structures could be built on most streets, which may lead to economic boom; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT community meetings in veterans' halls, senior centers and junior high cafeterias throughout Queens, it's the rare debate that doesn't center on the thorny issue of zoning. From Maspeth to Douglaston, simmering anger over McMansions and overbuilding in general is bubbling over. The result is a boroughwide push to use zoning -- specifically downzoning -- to keep out the tall, bulky multifamily dwellings that seem to be popping up in more and more neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Yet in Dutch Kills, a small community in northwest Queens that is part of Long Island City, keeping out big buildings is the furthest thing from many minds. Few imposing mega-manors with terra cotta-style roofs have arrived; instead, the neighborhood has for decades been home to a mix of residential and industrial uses that is increasingly rare in the city. Two- and three-story houses sided in pale pink and firehouse red vinyl or aluminum, their backyards dominated by plaster shrines to the Virgin Mary, share blocks with brick garages and businesses like the Dewes-Gumbs Die Company, a fixture on 24th Street for half a century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Dutch Kills, a small community in northwest Queens that is part of Long Island City, keeping out big buildings is the furthest thing from many minds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT community meetings in veterans' halls, senior centers and junior high cafeterias throughout Queens, it's the rare debate that doesn't center on the thorny issue of zoning. From Maspeth to Douglaston, simmering anger over McMansions and overbuilding in general is bubbling over. The result is a boroughwide push to use zoning -- specifically downzoning -- to keep out the tall, bulky multifamily dwellings that seem to be popping up in more and more neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Yet in Dutch Kills, a small community in northwest Queens that is part of Long Island City, keeping out big buildings is the furthest thing from many minds. Few imposing mega-manors with terra cotta-style roofs have arrived; instead, the neighborhood has for decades been home to a mix of residential and industrial uses that is increasingly rare in the city. Two- and three-story houses sided in pale pink and firehouse red vinyl or aluminum, their backyards dominated by plaster shrines to the Virgin Mary, share blocks with brick garages and businesses like the Dewes-Gumbs Die Company, a fixture on 24th Street for half a century.</p>
        <p>The talk in Dutch Kills these days is not of downzoning, which would keep out bigger buildings. Instead, local residents want upzoning, a much less frequently requested designation, which would make possible larger structures, at least on certain specified streets.</p>
        <p>''It will bring a lot of change, and a lot of people don't like change,'' said George Stamatiades, second vice chairman of the local community board and vice president of a neighborhood funeral home, who discussed possible changes as he conducted an impromptu tour of the neighborhood in his black Cadillac. ''But they know that if they don't get change, the neighborhood will atrophy and die.''</p>
        <p>Dutch Kills is wedged between once-seedy Queens Plaza to the south and somewhat happening Astoria to the north. The ''kills'' in the name refers to streams that once ran through the area. What runs through the area now is the noise of hammering from Queens Plaza, where a 12-story condominium tower called View59 is rising quickly, its steel beams pointing skyward like an oversized cellular tower. View59, scheduled to open this fall, is the second such tower rising in the neighborhood. The first occupants of the other new building, the 10-story Queens Plaza condominium, have already moved in.</p>
        <p>Residents of Dutch Kills have also seen the new residential buildings sprouting along the Long Island City waterfront, and they want their share. Working with the City Planning Commission, they have developed a plan that would allow buildings of 5 to 7 stories on the widest local avenues and 8-to-12-story buildings on Northern Boulevard, the area's southern border. Buildings on the side streets would be restricted to three or four stories.</p>
        <p>Given the proximity of Dutch Kills to Manhattan -- Bloomingdale's is two stops away, on the N train -- many local residents believe that under the right conditions, a boom could occur.</p>
        <p>''The community is very obviously familiar with the fact that they have great transit access,'' said Amanda Burden, chairwoman of the City Planning Commission. ''I think there's a very broad consensus for this rezoning.''</p>
        <p>The changes, she added, which need to pass a gantlet of municipal reviewing boards, could go into effect by the summer of next year.</p>
        <p>Not everyone is over the moon about rezoning. One subject being discussed on the streets of Dutch Kills is including affordable housing in new buildings along Northern Boulevard.</p>
        <p>''When we were talking about affordable housing, they're telling you one-bedroom for $1,600,'' said Helen Hubbard, who works as a volunteer at Saint Patrick's Roman Catholic Church on 29th Street. ''That's not affordable.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stamatiades, whose black and white two-story house next to the elevated subway tracks on 31st Street turns 100 this year, has a related concern. ''I hate to use the word gentrification,'' he said. ''But that's the negative side of the upzoning, because the property becomes more valuable.''</p>
        <p>Yet even before a possible rezoning becomes law, gentrification may already be under way, and the prospect is not universally unwelcome. ''We're not looking to maintain anything,'' Mr. Stamatiades said. ''We're looking to change.''</p>
        <p>STREET LEVEL / DUTCH KILLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
