<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Lose Intensity, But Hold On to 6th Place</title>
    <meta content="08rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Lose Intensity, But Hold On to 6th Place</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time in more than a month, the Rangers exhaled.</p>
        <p>They skated off the ice Saturday after losing to the Pittsburgh Penguins, 2-1, not knowing who their first-round opponent in the postseason would be. Only when they stepped into the locker room did they learn that they had clinched sixth place in the Eastern Conference and would play the Atlanta Thrashers in the first round.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the first time in more than a month, the Rangers exhaled.</p>
        <p>They skated off the ice Saturday after losing to the Pittsburgh Penguins, 2-1, not knowing who their first-round opponent in the postseason would be. Only when they stepped into the locker room did they learn that they had clinched sixth place in the Eastern Conference and would play the Atlanta Thrashers in the first round.</p>
        <p>The Rangers (42-30-10) fought hard in the third period, trying to earn sixth place on their own, but instead they secured it by way of Atlanta's 3-2 shootout victory against the Tampa Bay Lightning. Tampa Bay will be the seventh seed and play the Devils in the first round.</p>
        <p>The Rangers had been hoping to avoid the Devils, who swept them in the first round last season.</p>
        <p>''Obviously we're happy to be in the playoffs,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said. ''The higher the seed, the bigger the accomplishment. We don't care who we play. We'll play anybody, but now that we've got that determined, away we go.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers finished with 94 points. They could be forgiven for a slight letup after clinching their playoff berth Thursday with a victory against the Montreal Canadiens which capped a march from 11th place in early February.</p>
        <p>But after an uninspired first period and a penalty-marred second on Saturday, the Rangers showed their resolve against Pittsburgh in the third. The Penguins (47-24-11) held a 2-0 lead after power-play goals by Gary Roberts and Mark Recchi in the second.</p>
        <p>The Rangers took four of their seven penalties in the second, but began fighting back. Petr Prucha scored 1 minute 50 seconds into the third period to slice the lead in half.</p>
        <p>The Rangers took 12 of their shots in the third period. Their best chance came on a power play, when forward Jaromir Jagr ripped a wrist shot from the slot that goalie Marc-André Fleury snared with his glove with 4:30 remaining.</p>
        <p>A few moments later, the Rangers' coaches learned of Tampa Bay's loss. The players found out after they left the ice.</p>
        <p>''I would say the last five weeks, six weeks, it was very stressful mentally,'' Jagr said. ''I would say physically also. All I would think about is hockey, how not to lose a hockey game. We couldn't afford to lose. Then the last game against Montreal, we clinch it and it's kind of like a huge relief.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to win it, for sure, but I would say it is the first hockey game in three or four months that it's not a big deal when you lose it.''</p>
        <p>None of the Rangers would admit that they wanted to avoid the Devils. Forward Sean Avery, who joined the team after a Feb. 5 trade, said he was actually rooting for a matchup against the Devils.</p>
        <p>''I thought it would have been great to play them in the first round,'' Avery said. ''It would have been less travel and Jersey-Rangers in the first round is always a good thing. But that's out of our control and now we're playing Atlanta.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers were 1-1-2 against the Thrashers this season.</p>
        <p>They insist that they are far better prepared for the playoffs than they were last season. A year ago, they lost the last five games of the regular season, lost the Atlantic Division title to the Devils on the final day, then were swept in the first round. And goalie Henrik Lundqvist was trying to shake a hip-pointer injury and struggled with migraines.</p>
        <p>''This year I feel healthy; that's a big difference,'' Lundqvist said after only his second loss in the Rangers' past 11 games. ''Last year, it was a little frustrating to go out there. You try to do your best at first and it doesn't work, for us as a team or for me. This year, we come better prepared and with a much better effort.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers are also determined not to waste the momentum they have built.</p>
        <p>''I never play the playoffs to just win the first round,'' Jagr said. ''I always go to win it. That's how I play. If you finish second or lose in the first round, it's the same. It's all about the championship.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Penguins center Sidney Crosby finished the regular season as the N.H.L. scoring leader with 120 points. He had two assists Saturday, giving him 84, to go with 36 goals.  The Penguins were playing for home-ice advantage in their first-round series with Ottawa, but the Senators won Saturday to lock that up.  The Rangers expect to have forward Marcel Hossa back for the playoffs after he missed the past 16 games with a ligament sprain in his left knee. Hossa's brother Marian is one of Atlanta's star forwards.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
