<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They're Playing Our Song?</title>
    <meta content="08lanin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/fashion/08lanin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E1DF143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They're Playing Our Song?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">They’re Playing Our Song?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE was no stopping Helena Thorne Marrin when the music started. ''Do you do the Charleston?'' she asked a just-arrived guest at the black-tie fund-raiser she had helped to organize.</p>
        <p>The guest said no. But Ms. Marrin, 25, demonstrated the steps, right there in the hallway outside the ballroom in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the two and a half years since Lester Lanin’s death, the Lester Lanin Orchestra has tried to find the balance between staying relevant and staying true to its roots.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE was no stopping Helena Thorne Marrin when the music started. ''Do you do the Charleston?'' she asked a just-arrived guest at the black-tie fund-raiser she had helped to organize.</p>
        <p>The guest said no. But Ms. Marrin, 25, demonstrated the steps, right there in the hallway outside the ballroom in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>She did not get that guest onto the dance floor. But a minute or two later, Ms. Marrin was swaying happily to the big-band staple ''In the Mood.'' She danced on as the band cycled through ''I Just Called to Say I Love You,'' ''YMCA'' and other hits from the '70s, '80s and '90s.</p>
        <p>But this was no soft-rock band, it was the venerable Lester Lanin Orchestra. In the two and a half years since Lanin's death at 97, his successors have tried to find the balance between staying relevant and staying true to their roots.</p>
        <p>So, while they talk about infusing their repertory with a somewhat more contemporary flavor, they also talk about how Lanin did that himself, years ago.</p>
        <p>Lanin was the quintessential society bandleader who played at big-name weddings (Grace Kelly and Prince Rainier, Christie Brinkley and Billy Joel), big-name birthday parties (Queen Elizabeth) and big-name balls on the charity circuit. And Ms. Marrin, the sales and marketing director for a bistro in Needham, Mass., is the type of guest Lanin catered to: well-connected and young, but traditional.</p>
        <p>''My parents and my grandparents danced to Lester Lanin,'' she said, adding that Lanin played at her debutante ball in 1999.</p>
        <p>She paused. She listened to Cole Porter's ''Anything Goes,'' which gave way to ''Cheek to Cheek,'' which gave way to ''The Lady Is a Tramp.'' She smiled. ''You can still hear him in the music,'' she said.</p>
        <p>And so the Lanin band plays on, even though the demographics of the music business and the society-party circuit have changed.</p>
        <p>Spencer Bruno, who took over as the musical director of the Lester Lanin organization, likes to talk about the Lanin ''continuum'' -- how Lanin played for the parents of people like Ms. Marrin, and maybe their grandparents. ''Young people do know about Lester Lanin,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Lanin was old enough to be Ms. Marrin's great-grandfather or, for that matter, the great-grandfather of the rapper Eminem, who is in his mid-30s. And Mr. Bruno does not sound like a fan of what record producers and radio stations have been playing for the last few years.</p>
        <p>That is not the only problem for a society band these days. D.J.'s playing recorded music have changed the expectations of partygoers -- they can dance to more than just arrangements of the songs they know.</p>
        <p>''That progression had started when Lester was still in front of the band,'' said John Burcin, who books the dates and hires the musicians. ''People associate you with his style of music and he was locked into that society two-beat; that's what his clientele wanted.'' But, Mr. Burcin said, ''as far back as the '60s, he started to incorporate'' current music into the sets. ''We continue the tradition, improving it.''</p>
        <p>And maybe the pendulum has swung the other way. ''The young people are still into the Sinatra, the Tony Bennett groove,'' Mr. Burcin said. ''We get just as many requests for that kind of music as the rock stuff, which makes us as versatile as the D.J., so it becomes a question of whether you want live music.''</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Bruno and Mr. Burcin, Lanin's musical heirs, played under him for years. Their combined ages make them only a bit older than Mr. Lanin's was.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno plays the saxophone, flute and clarinet. He was Lanin's principal leader before the bandleader died, and is also an arranger. ''After Lester's passing,'' he said, ''I worked very hard to write musical arrangements which would modernize and at the same time preserve the Lester Lanin style.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burcin -- who leads the second band on nights when there are two jobs at the same time in different places -- is lanky and more talkative and folds himself around his drums, something he has been doing for most of his life.</p>
        <p>He started taking drum lessons when he was 5, and when he was a teenager and his friends were in rock bands, he was doing what he does now. He played his first date with Lanin when he was 15 or 16. Another band member had to pick him up and drive him to the job.</p>
        <p>Alex Donner, who was a vocalist under Lanin and who is now a rival bandleader, says that what Lanin built was not just a band, it was a brand.</p>
        <p>''What I learned from Lester,'' he said, ''is, it's not about what you want to play, it's about what will make that crowd flow continuously onto the dance floor. And it's about handling requests. If anybody walked up and asked for something, he'd play it right away.''</p>
        <p>But what has happened to the music business has cut into the business of society bands. Lanin once sent a dozen bands out on a single night. Nowadays the Lanin organization rarely produces more than one band at a time.</p>
        <p>But there was a rare two-band evening on a Friday last month. A four-person combo played at the St. David's Society dance at the Yale Club. A five-person ensemble set up their music stands seven blocks away at the Union League Club for the Ticonderoga Ball. That event, for which Ms. Marrin was listed as the junior committee chairwoman, raised money for restoration work at the fort above Lake Champlain in upstate New York.</p>
        <p>The chairwoman, Alexandra Pell Kuhel, 41, said the band has changed, but so has the crowd that attends the $275-a-person event.</p>
        <p>''We realized people want to dance shorter sets,'' she said, ''but he's able to cater to anything.''</p>
        <p>Yes, even though Lanin has been dead since 2004, people still talk about Lanin as if he were still in front of the band. But it was Mr. Bruno who was calling the tunes and, late in the evening, tossing out the hats. Lanin always threw beanie-like hats into the crowd; now Mr. Bruno and Mr. Burcin carry on that tradition.</p>
        <p>On the dance floor were people in their 60s and 70s and people like Ms. Marrin, in their 20s. The Lanin band, Mrs. Pell Kuhel said, ''knows how to play an event: how to play during dinner, between courses, when it's time to get everybody up and dancing.''</p>
        <p>Dancing to what is the question. At the St. David's dance, one guest, Duncan Bruce, declared, ''The great thing about Lanin is his guys play waltzes and samba.''</p>
        <p>''Where else can you hear these things?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Bruce A. MacLeod, the author of ''Club Date Musician,'' a 1993 survey of who played what on the society- and wedding-music circuit, said Lanin managed to blend everything together smoothly. ''It sounded hip,'' he said. ''I grew up with rock 'n' roll. I knew what was good and what was not. It was very convincing.''</p>
        <p>Lanin -- who played at inaugural balls from Dwight D. Eisenhoweron (but not for Jimmy Carter and George W. Bush) and composed the ''Pink Petal Waltz,'' a staple of debutante balls -- took a drubbing from jazz critics who frowned on his two-beat ''businessman's bounce.'' But Lanin laughed all the way to the bank. Booking dates, hiring musicians and, in his heyday, recording albums made him rich. In 1987, Forbes estimated that he was earning $5 million a year.</p>
        <p>Lanin never said how much he charged, and Mr. Burcin says the price depends on where the job is and how much travel is involved and how many musicians go. ''There is no set price for any given job,'' he said. Lanin liked to say he was in ''the happiness business.'' And he had his regulars, like Susan Parker, the chairwoman of the annual Yorkville Community Association dinner-dance.</p>
        <p>The event, which raises money to send inner-city children to Y.M.C.A. camps, is always held on the third Friday in January. In 1989, Lanin called to say there was a little last-minute scheduling problem.</p>
        <p>''He said, would I mind if he went to the inaugural ball,'' Ms. Parker said. ''I couldn't believe my ears.'' (Even though he himself went to Washington, Lanin sent a band to her dance, and he was back in person the following year.)</p>
        <p>She says that hiring Lanin (or, now, Mr. Bruno and Mr. Burcin) means she gets predictability, familiarity. ''Some of our crowd is older,'' Ms. Parker said. ''Young people like all sorts of things that are loud. I say, 'Play Lester Lanin music.' They say, 'Mrs. Parker, everyone will leave.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno talks of ''bridging the gap,'' something he does mainly with his repertory. Mr. MacLeod said that Lanin himself ''was aware of current trends in music, even if he didn't like them particularly.''</p>
        <p>That explains what Mr. Bruno calls the ''rock band within the band.''</p>
        <p>''If you looked at his older jobs, he'd have 15 men and there would be 6 or 7 musicians within the band,'' Mr. Bruno said. But there are fewer and fewer nights of 15-person bands these days.</p>
        <p>''It's not like it was 15 to 20 years ago, where you had 10, 12 bands out every night,'' Mr. Burcin said. ''The whole music business has changed.''</p>
        <p>''Lester outlasted everybody,'' he said, ''even his original band.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
