<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Long-Delayed Security Deposit</title>
    <meta content="08qa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Q &amp; A"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFDF173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Long-Delayed Security Deposit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. When my 24-unit building changed owners a number of years ago, the former landlord returned the security deposit on my rent-stabilized apartment. The new landlord made no request for a deposit until recently. On my last lease renewal I was asked to send in a partial deposit, and this year the landlord is demanding the remainder for the full deposit. Since I have lived here now for over a decade without a deposit, can the new landlord demand one now?</p>
        <p>A. ''The Rent Stabilization Code permits an owner to hold one full month of rent as security,'' said Robert Sokolski, a Manhattan lawyer who represents tenants. ''And the rent-stabilized lease form contains a provision that the security deposit increases along with the rent.'' Normally, Mr. Sokolski said, security deposits are not given back to the tenants when the building is sold but are passed along to the new owner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. When my 24-unit building changed owners a number of years ago, the former landlord returned the security deposit on my rent-stabilized apartment. The new landlord made no request for a deposit until recently. On my last lease renewal I was asked to send in a partial deposit, and this year the landlord is demanding the remainder for the full deposit. Since I have lived here now for over a decade without a deposit, can the new landlord demand one now?</p>
        <p>A. ''The Rent Stabilization Code permits an owner to hold one full month of rent as security,'' said Robert Sokolski, a Manhattan lawyer who represents tenants. ''And the rent-stabilized lease form contains a provision that the security deposit increases along with the rent.'' Normally, Mr. Sokolski said, security deposits are not given back to the tenants when the building is sold but are passed along to the new owner.</p>
        <p>If the letter writer's lease contains a provision for a security deposit, as is likely, the tenant is subject to that provision, Mr. Sokolski said.</p>
        <p>In fact, he added, the lease probably contains a provision that if the landlord does not ask for a security deposit immediately, this will not bar him from demanding one later. ''The tenant's failure to remit the security deposit would be a breach of the lease,'' Mr. Sokolski said, ''and the housing courts will routinely enforce a security-deposit provision.''</p>
        <p>Can a Co-op Board Member Campaign for Candidates?</p>
        <p>Q. I am on a board of a Queens co-op that has split into two factions. The annual shareholder's meeting is scheduled for next month. Can I endorse, lobby and campaign for a slate of like-minded shareholders who are interested in joining the board?</p>
        <p>A. ''Just because a shareholder is a director of his co-op doesn't mean he loses his rights as a shareholder,'' said Aaron Shmulewitz, a Manhattan co-op lawyer. There is nothing in New York law that would bar a director from endorsing, lobbying or campaigning for other candidates for the board, he said, even if they are running in opposition to some of the current board members.</p>
        <p>''The writer would have the right to do so in any manner he chooses, including contacting other shareholders directly by telephone, e-mail or by regular mail,'' Mr. Shmulewitz said. ''He can also distribute fliers to shareholders entering or leaving the building and can even distribute fliers inside the building, unless the cooperative has a house rule prohibiting solicitation within the building.''</p>
        <p>JAY ROMANO</p>
        <p>Q &amp; A</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
