<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Technology Leaps Ahead, Concerns About Cheating Grow</title>
    <meta content="08chess" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/crosswords/chess/08chess.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070415T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cheating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Varshavsky, Eugene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smirin, Ilia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcclain, Dylan Loeb</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cheating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cheating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7DC143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Technology Leaps Ahead, Concerns About Cheating Grow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Technology Leaps Ahead, Concerns About Cheating Grow</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dylan Loeb McClain</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcclain, Dylan Loeb</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chess column says more attention is being paid to cheating at tournaments because of recent incidents and because of increasing sophistication of computers and communication devices; diagram of World Open game won by Eugene Varshavsky, low-ranked player suspected of using 25 consecutive moves suggested by computer program, over Ilia Smirin, a grandmaster (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Concerns about cheating, and ideas about how to stop it, have become a preoccupation of the chess world in recent months.</p>
        <p>While cheating is not new -- for years, some Soviet players were suspected of colluding at international tournaments -- more attention is being paid now because of recent incidents and because of the increasing sophistication of computers and communication devices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While cheating is not new, more attention is being paid now because of recent incidents and the increasing sophistication of computers and communication devices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Concerns about cheating, and ideas about how to stop it, have become a preoccupation of the chess world in recent months.</p>
        <p>While cheating is not new -- for years, some Soviet players were suspected of colluding at international tournaments -- more attention is being paid now because of recent incidents and because of the increasing sophistication of computers and communication devices.</p>
        <p>In July, two players at the World Open in Philadelphia fell under suspicion. One, Steve Rosenberg, who was winning his section, was found with a wireless receiver in his ear. He was expelled and subsequently banned from tournaments by the United States Chess Federation for three years.</p>
        <p>The other, Eugene Varshavsky, a low-ranked player, was searched thoroughly before each game after he beat a strong grandmaster by playing 25 consecutive moves that matched those suggested by a computer program. (Efforts to locate Varshavsky, or to find a phone number where he could be reached for comment, were unsuccessful; people in the chess world say they have not seen him recently.)</p>
        <p>At the world championship in October, Veselin Topalov of Bulgaria insinuated that Vladimir Kramnik of Russia might have consulted a computer during frequent bathroom trips. The bathrooms were locked and the match was suspended. Subsequently, the bathrooms were reopened and the match resumed, and no proof of wrongdoing was found.</p>
        <p>In January, a German newspaper article said Silvio Danailov, Topalov's manager, behaved strangely at the Corus tournament and might have been signaling Topalov during games. Danailov denied the accusation, and no investigation resulted.</p>
        <p>In December, Umakanth Sharma of India was caught with a receiver in his cap and was banned from playing in India for 10 years.</p>
        <p>Another Indian player, Diwakar Prasad Singh, who suddenly improved enormously last year and qualified for the international master title, was also accused of cheating. He was subsequently cleared by the All India Chess Federation after an investigation, but because of persistent concerns, he is now routinely searched before competitions.</p>
        <p>In light of these incidents, the Association of Chess Professionals wrote to the World Chess Federation in February proposing steps to address the problem. ''The situation has become unpleasant, to say the least,'' its letter said. ''Rumors can be very harmful. Recent allegations and articles published in the press create an unhealthy situation in the chess world.''</p>
        <p>The Continental Chess Association, which organizes the nation's largest tournaments, including the World Open, has instituted new policies at its biggest events. Players will no longer be allowed to use headphones, cellphones or hearing aids and may be searched at any time by a tournament director. Competitors who do not comply will be expelled.</p>
        <p>The first tournament to use the new rules is the Foxwoods Open in Connecticut, which ends today.</p>
        <p>Bill Goichberg, who runs the Continental Chess Association and is president of the United States Chess Federation, said that in the future, electronic detection devices may be used. ''Mainly we want to have the right to do things,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While it has never been proved that Varshavsky cheated, here is the game at last year's World Open between him and Ilia Smirin, an Israeli grandmaster, that raised suspicion.</p>
        <p>The opening was the open variation of the Ruy Lopez. It is well known and heavily analyzed, so it was not surprising that Varshavsky played the first moves accurately.</p>
        <p>With 11 h3, Smirin adopted a somewhat offbeat system. More usual is to retreat the bishop with 11 Bc2.</p>
        <p>After Varshavsky won, Larry Christiansen, a grandmaster, found that the last 25 moves matched those chosen by a commercially available computer program called Shredder.</p>
        <p>With no copy of Shredder, I compared Black's moves with those suggested by Fritz 9. From 14  a5 (the first move that varied from what had previously been played) to the end, Fritz agreed with 34 out of 44 moves.</p>
        <p>In addition to the high degree of correlation, two other things stood out. The moves 35  Re8 and 36  g5 were unusual and counterintuitive; most people playing Black would probably retreat the bishop rather than attack White's bishop.</p>
        <p>The other element was how easily Varshavsky outplayed Smirin in the endgame. Usually, grandmasters have a large advantage at that stage over low-ranked players.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Smirin said he felt he was ''playing against a machine.''</p>
        <p>CHESS</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 15, 2007, Sunday  The Chess column last Sunday, about the effect of technology on cheating, included incorrect information from the United States Chess Federation about Steve Rosenberg, a player who was expelled from the World Open last July after a tournament director said he found a wireless receiver in Mr. Rosenberg's ear. Although the federation's ethics committee has indeed ordered that he be suspended from playing in tournaments, that suspension is not in effect because Mr. Rosenberg is appealing. His case will be heard in August.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 15, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Chess column last Sunday, about the effect of technology on cheating, included incorrect information from the United States Chess Federation about Steve Rosenberg, a player who was expelled from the World Open last July after a tournament director said he found a wireless receiver in Mr. Rosenberg's ear. Although the federation's ethics committee has indeed ordered that he be suspended from playing in tournaments, that suspension is not in effect because Mr. Rosenberg is appealing. His case will be heard in August.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
