<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Religious Principles Take Root in Funds</title>
    <meta content="08relig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/business/mutfund/08relig.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3D8173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1195" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Religious Principles Take Root in Funds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Religious Principles Take Root in Funds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J. ALEX TARQUINIO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RELIGION has always been a central theme of American life, but until recently, there weren't too many options for those interested in investing based on religious principles. That has begun to change.</p>
        <p>More mutual funds that invest according to religious beliefs have been created, and the funds' assets have ballooned into the billions of dollars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Those whose faith guides their investing now have more choices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RELIGION has always been a central theme of American life, but until recently, there weren't too many options for those interested in investing based on religious principles. That has begun to change.</p>
        <p>More mutual funds that invest according to religious beliefs have been created, and the funds' assets have ballooned into the billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>In some ways, these funds are similar to those that are managed by companies like Domini Social Investments or Pax World Funds  and that are known collectively as ''socially responsible investing'' funds because they screen out stocks on ethical grounds. ''But most S.R.I. funds tend to have a more liberal bent, while some of the religious funds tend to be more conservative,'' said David Kathman, a fund analyst at Morningstar.</p>
        <p>The handful of widely available funds that make investment decisions based on religious doctrine are generally open to investors of any faith -- or, for that matter, to nonbelievers.</p>
        <p>One is the Amana Income fund, which screens stocks based on Shariah, or Islamic law. It started trading in 1986 and was followed in 1994 by the Amana Growth fund. Nick Kaiser, a portfolio manager at Saturna Capital, based in Bellingham, Wash., manages both funds. He is the only non-Muslim on the Amana funds' board of trustees.</p>
        <p>The Amana funds avoid holdings that earn interest, which is proscribed under Shariah codes; therefore they cannot invest in financial companies or own bonds. They also cannot invest in companies with a lot of debt; the cash in both funds must be kept in accounts that do not earn interest. The income fund focuses on stocks that earn dividends.</p>
        <p>Advisers to the Amana funds also avoid investing in companies that, for example, sell pork or alcohol. Less than 5 percent of a company's revenue can come from such products if it is to be considered for the fund, and such revenue must be incidental to the business.</p>
        <p>By way of example, Mr. Kaiser pointed to airlines, which usually sell alcohol on flights. But such sales generate a minuscule portion of their revenue and are incidental to their primary business of providing transportation, so investing in airlines would not violate the funds' investment philosophy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaiser said the screening process tends to keep the funds light on industries like restaurants, while overweighting technology. The Amana Income fund, with $170 million in assets, returned 15.1 percent in the 12 months through March, while the Amana Growth fund, with $330 million in assets, returned 8.1 percent. By comparison, the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index returned 11.9 percent. The growth fund charges 1.41 percent in annual expenses, and the income fund charges 1.49 percent.</p>
        <p>Two other fund families -- the Ave Maria funds and Timothy Plan funds -- may appeal to some Christian investors. The Ave Maria funds are focused on Catholics and the Timothy Plan funds on evangelical Christians.</p>
        <p>The Roman Catholic Church does not own or endorse the Ave Maria funds. But George P. Schwartz, who founded the funds, said he consults with an advisory board of Catholic parishioners, and with Cardinal Adam Joseph Maida of Detroit. Mr. Schwartz, the president of Schwartz Investment Counsel, based in Bloomfield Hills, Mich., is the co-manager of the Ave Maria Catholic Values fund and the Ave Maria Rising Dividend fund.</p>
        <p>The Timothy Plan funds are not affiliated with a religious denomination. But Arthur D. Ally, the president of the fund company, based in Winter Park, Fla., said that he and his staff select stocks based on biblical principles.</p>
        <p>''That is the only source of truth that exists,'' said Mr. Ally, who considers himself an evangelical Christian. He focuses on stock screening and hires other fund companies for day-to-day portfolio management.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwartz and Mr. Ally emphasize their anti-abortion stance. None of the Ave Maria or Timothy Plan funds own shares of hospital chains or insurance companies that perform or pay for elective abortions. The funds also do not invest in pharmaceutical companies that make certain drugs, like oral contraceptives or the abortion pill RU-486. And they will not invest in companies that donate to Planned Parenthood.</p>
        <p>The two fund families have another similarity: both try to avoid investing in companies that produce or distribute pornography.</p>
        <p>But the two fund groups do have some differences. For example, the Timothy Plan funds exclude stocks that make money from alcohol, tobacco or gambling, but the Ave Maria funds do not.</p>
        <p>The Ave Maria Catholic Values fund -- the largest of the Ave Maria funds, with about $270 million in assets -- returned 7.6 percent in the 12 months through March. It has an expense ratio of 1.5 percent. The Timothy Plan Large/Mid-Cap Value fund, with $110 million in assets, returned 15.4 percent and charges 1.55 percent in expenses.</p>
        <p>Schwartz Investment Counsel, the investment adviser to the Ave Maria Mutual Funds, purchased the Catholic Equity fund for an undisclosed price on March 30. It was combined with the Ave Maria Rising Dividend fund, which now has $88 million in assets.</p>
        <p>Two other fund families have direct church ties. The New Covenant funds are sponsored by the Presbyterian Foundation, which is an agency of the Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.) The foundation and the funds are based in Jeffersonville, Ind.</p>
        <p>The MMA Praxis funds, based in Goshen, Ind., are owned by the Mennonite Church U.S.A. These funds are rooted in the Anabaptist tradition -- which includes dozens of denominations like the Mennonites, Church of the Brethren and Old Order Amish.</p>
        <p>The MMA Praxis funds take a pacifist stance and will not invest in companies that make weapons. Mark A. Regier, the stewardship investing services manager of MMA Praxis Mutual Funds, said that the company liked environmental initiatives at General Electric, but that the funds cannot own G.E.'s stock because the company is also a military contractor.</p>
        <p>THE New Covenant funds do not exclude G.E.; in fact, the company is a top holding in the New Covenant Growth fund. ''We have to do some fine parsing with defense stocks,'' said Robert E. Leech, the president of the Presbyterian Foundation and the New Covenant funds. ''We are not opposed to reasonable defense of your homeland. But we screen out certain elements of defense where injury might occur to noncombatants,'' like companies that make land mines or hand grenades.</p>
        <p>The New Covenant and MMA Praxis funds also try to persuade companies in their portfolios to take measures like improving their environmental records and labor relations.</p>
        <p>To have more sway with large companies, they participate in some shareholder resolutions backed by the Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, an association of 275 church-based institutional investors.</p>
        <p>New Covenant Growth, which has $972 million in assets, returned 9.4 percent over the last 12 months. It charges annual expenses of 1.07 percent. The MMA Praxis Core Stock fund, with $336 million in assets, returned 8.6 percent and charges annual expenses of 1.99 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kathman at Morningstar says that investors who are considering any of these funds should not lose sight of their long-term goals. ''If they are looking at these funds, then the religious aspect is obviously important for them,'' he said, adding that investors should make sure that funds fit into their portfolio strategies.</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
