<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miracles and the Fast Track to Sainthood</title>
    <meta content="08basics" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/weekinreview/08basics.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="The Basics"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beatifications and Canonizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nuns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beatifications and Canonizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="online_producer">John Paul II</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Benedict XVI</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Teresa (Mother)</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E3D6173FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miracles and the Fast Track to Sainthood</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Miracles and the Fast Track to Sainthood</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To become a saint during the Roman Catholic Church's first thousand years, it was enough for a local church in Christendom's far reaches simply to declare someone holy. But inevitably, sticky issues of process and standards crept in: in the 12th century, Pope Alexander III scolded Swedes for venerating a monk killed in a drunken brawl.</p>
        <p>Now, even under the modern church's more complicated rules, a pope can -- in theory -- still declare a saint immediately. Two years ago this month, crowds in Rome urged the newly elected pope, Benedict XVI, to do exactly that after the death of his predecessor, John Paul II.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Easter, a look at what it takes to become a saint.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To become a saint during the Roman Catholic Church's first thousand years, it was enough for a local church in Christendom's far reaches simply to declare someone holy. But inevitably, sticky issues of process and standards crept in: in the 12th century, Pope Alexander III scolded Swedes for venerating a monk killed in a drunken brawl.</p>
        <p>Now, even under the modern church's more complicated rules, a pope can -- in theory -- still declare a saint immediately. Two years ago this month, crowds in Rome urged the newly elected pope, Benedict XVI, to do exactly that after the death of his predecessor, John Paul II.</p>
        <p>John Paul, an outsize figure in the church and beyond, was himself especially active in the cause of saints. In 1983, he eased the process of sainthood, and by the end of his 26 years as pope, he added more saints and ''blesseds'' -- those named to beatification -- than all other popes combined.</p>
        <p>But much as the rules for sainthood have shifted over the church's 2,000 years, Benedict has followed a more restrictive vision of the process. Yet on John Paul's behalf, Benedict has done something that has happened only once before under current rules: He waived the five-year waiting period after a person's death to begin the process for beatification, the first step toward sainthood. John Paul did the same for Mother Teresa, the nun who cared for India's poor.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, the pope seems set to let the case for John Paul's sainthood run its specified course. He has suggested that John Paul is already a saint. (Theologically, God makes saints in heaven; the church only makes it known on earth.)</p>
        <p>A milestone was reached last week, when John Paul's diocese in Poland presented its case for beatification. Technically, this recognizes that a person who died has entered heaven and can intercede on behalf of those who venerate him or her. One miracle is required, and a French nun has claimed that she was cured of Parkinson's disease, the illness that afflicted John Paul, after praying to him.</p>
        <p>A second miracle is required for canonization, or entrance into the canon of saints. (Before John Paul's changes, two more miracles were required). The definition of miracle is not just an unexplainable cure from disease, though most often it is.</p>
        <p>''The wonder of the miracle is due to the fact that its cause is hidden, and an effect is expected other than what actually takes place,'' the Catholic Encyclopedia explains. Some in the church, though, argue against the emphasis on miracles, saying that other, less dramatic, tests would better serve the modern church, which is ever more distant from the hierarchy.</p>
        <p>''Saints are examples rather than miracle workers or intercessors,'' says the Rev. Richard P. McBrien, author of ''Lives of the Saints'' (HarperCollins, 2001). ''They are signs of what it means to be human in the fullest and best sense of the word. Which is also why the church has been wrong to have canonized so many priests and nuns rather than married lay people who lived ordinary lives in extraordinary ways, rejoicing in their children and grandchildren and doing good for so many others.''</p>
        <p>IAN FISHER</p>
        <p>The Basics</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
