<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OFF THE DRIBBLE</title>
    <meta content="08nbarail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDC143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="412" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OFF THE DRIBBLE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED BIERMAN and BENJAMIN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Benjamin; Bierman, Fred</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'I just want to have a feeling that my team and my franchise are fully committed to win and are going to invest for that to happen.'</p>
        <p>PAU GASOL</p>
        <p>The Memphis forward, speaking about his Grizzlies (19-59), who will probably finish with the worst record in the league after three seasons of 45-plus wins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'I just want to have a feeling that my team and my franchise are fully committed to win and are going to invest for that to happen.'</p>
        <p>PAU GASOL</p>
        <p>The Memphis forward, speaking about his Grizzlies (19-59), who will probably finish with the worst record in the league after three seasons of 45-plus wins.</p>
        <p>WIN TO GET IN</p>
        <p>Looking like a battle of sub-.500 teams backing into the playoffs, the race for the eighth spot in the Western Conference has turned into a dogfight between the Clippers and the Warriors.</p>
        <p>The two franchises, known more for their failures than successes, are separated by one game with seven games left for the Clippers and six for the Warriors before yesterday's games. Over the past 12 games, the Warriors have won eight, moving to two games under .500, while the Clippers have won 8 of 10.</p>
        <p>If the Warriors were to make the playoffs it would end a drought of 12 seasons.</p>
        <p>WITHOUT WADE</p>
        <p>On Feb. 21, when DWYANE WADE, below, separated his shoulder and tore a labrum, the Heat was a game under .500 at 26-27. Although Wade seemed like the player Miami could least afford to lose, the Heat has enjoyed surprising success without him. It has gone 16-7 since Wade went down, including an Eastern Conference-best 11-4 in March.</p>
        <p>Center SHAQUILLE O'NEAL has also played much better since Wade's injury, increasing his scoring from 13.9 points a game to 17.2. Now Wade is practicing and traveling with the team and could return to the lineup by next week. This makes the Heat, which qualified for the playoffs with a 94-90 overtime victory over Cleveland on Thursday, a team that no one wants to see in the first round.</p>
        <p>NOTHING BUT NET</p>
        <p>Fans of basketball and comedy were certainly a little brokenhearted when Washington guard GILBERT ARENAS went down with a knee injury after colliding with Charlotte forward Gerald Wallace on Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Arenas, who had surgery the next day, is out for two to three months, effectively ending his season.</p>
        <p>After having the operation, Arenas immediately updated his blog on NBA.com and said that the worst part about his operation was that a spotty Internet connection interrupted his video-game playing.</p>
        <p>''So when you're injured and video games is your life and you can't play, it just makes the injury that much worse,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>FRED BIERMAN and BENJAMIN HOFFMAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
