<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unplanned Shutdown for Indian Pt. 3 Reactor</title>
    <meta content="08weweekWC-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070407T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1838936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sirens</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buchanan (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Entergy Nuclear Northeast</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charkes, Juli Steadman</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DB143FF93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unplanned Shutdown for Indian Pt. 3 Reactor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULI S. CHARKES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Charkes, Juli Steadman</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Entergy Nuclear Northeast shuts down Indian Point 3 nuclear reactor for nearly day after water-pump control device malfunctioned during scheduled refueling procedure; plant was also forced to retest new emergency system after problems arose with 123 of 150 new sirens; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Indian Point 3 nuclear reactor was shut down for nearly a day last week after a water-pump control device malfunctioned. The plant was also forced to retest its new emergency system after problems arose with 123 of 150 new sirens.</p>
        <p>Jim Steets, a spokesman for Entergy Nuclear Northeast, which owns and operates the plant, said the shutdown occurred at 4 a.m. Tuesday after operators noticed that the water level in the steam generators had dropped. The reactor was in the process of being brought back to full power after a scheduled 24-day refueling procedure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Indian Point 3 nuclear reactor was shut down for nearly a day last week after a water-pump control device malfunctioned. The plant was also forced to retest its new emergency system after problems arose with 123 of 150 new sirens.</p>
        <p>Jim Steets, a spokesman for Entergy Nuclear Northeast, which owns and operates the plant, said the shutdown occurred at 4 a.m. Tuesday after operators noticed that the water level in the steam generators had dropped. The reactor was in the process of being brought back to full power after a scheduled 24-day refueling procedure.</p>
        <p>''There were no safety implications or margins diminished in any way,'' Mr. Steets said.</p>
        <p>Service was returned by 1 a.m. Wednesday and was scheduled to reach full capacity by the end of the week, he said.</p>
        <p>David Novich, a spokesman for the Westchester County Department of Emergency Services, said he was satisfied with how the unplanned shutdown was handled. ''This is a complicated plant, and these sorts of incidents can occur when plants are brought back online,'' he said.</p>
        <p>On Monday, a test of the new siren system, scheduled to be ready by next week, ''indicated a need for additional work,'' Mr. Steets said. The problems do not jeopardize the existing system, which officials say has operated without incident for a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Novich said that additional testing performed last Thursday had better results, with 17 of 150 new sirens not performing as required.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, we want this to be 100 percent, but based on this second set of testing, we are clearly getting back on track,'' Mr. Novich said.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the plant were troubled by the incidents.</p>
        <p>''No other plant has these kinds of problems,'' said Alex Matthiessen, president of the environmental group Riverkeeper. ''How many times are they going to avert disaster before their -- and our -- luck runs out?''</p>
        <p>The Indian Point Reactors 2 and 3, in Buchanan, provide 10 percent of the state's electricity, and 25 percent for Westchester and New York City.</p>
        <p>Plant officials say they plan to apply for a renewal of their operating licenses with the Nuclear Regulatory Commission this month. The current licensing agreements expire in 2013 for Plant 2 and in 2015 for Plant 3.</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 7, 2007, Saturday  A brief article in the Westchester section this weekend about the shutdown of the Indian Point 3 reactor on Tuesday was printed before a fire yesterday forced the plant to close again. An article on B3 today reports on the latest developments.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 8, 2007, Sunday  A brief article in the Westchester section today about the shutdown of the Indian Point 3 reactor on Tuesday was printed before a fire on Friday forced the plant to close again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 7, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A brief article in the Westchester section this weekend about the shutdown of the Indian Point 3 reactor on Tuesday was printed before a fire yesterday forced the plant to close again. An article on B3 today reports on the latest developments.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: April 8, 2007, Sunday</p>
        <p>A brief article in the Westchester section today about the shutdown of the Indian Point 3 reactor on Tuesday was printed before a fire on Friday forced the plant to close again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
