<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Proceed to Checkout</title>
    <meta content="Paul.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/Paul.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Barber, Benjamin R</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Consumed: How Markets Corrupt Children, Infantalize Adults, and Swallow Citizens Whole (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Proceed to Checkout</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Proceed to Checkout</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAMELA PAUL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Paul, Pamela</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONSUMED</p>
        <p>How Markets Corrupt Children, Infantilize</p>
        <p>Adults, and Swallow Citizens Whole.</p>
        <p>By Benjamin R. Barber.</p>
        <p>406 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $26.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Benjamin Barber argues that consumer culture hurts America’s democracy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONSUMED</p>
        <p>How Markets Corrupt Children, Infantilize</p>
        <p>Adults, and Swallow Citizens Whole.</p>
        <p>By Benjamin R. Barber.</p>
        <p>406 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $26.95.</p>
        <p>In the aftermath of Sept. 11, when publishers scrambled to provide explanations for the attacks, Benjamin R. Barber's 1995 book, ''Jihad vs. McWorld,'' an examination of the tensions between consumer capitalism and religious fundamentalism, was dusted off, rushed back to press and propelled to best-sellerdom. Around that time, Barber also released a memoir of his stint as a freelance intellectual in the Clinton White House, a melancholy rumination on the failures of that administration as well as his own failure to be named chairman of the National Endowment for the Humanities. With his latest book, Barber, a political theorist at the University of Maryland, returns to familiar territory. But if ''Jihad'' provided an answer to the ubiquitous post-9/11 question ''Why do they hate us?,'' the question behind ''Consumed'' seems to be ''Who wouldn't?''</p>
        <p>Barber, for one, is put off by much of what global capitalism has wrought. Hollywood movies are cartoonish and trashy; kids reared on video games and fast food miss out on childhood's meaningful pleasures; life at the mall is soulless; much of popular culture is dreck. How all this came about takes up the bulk of his book.</p>
        <p>According to Barber, global inequality has left the planet with two kinds of potential customers: the poor of the undeveloped world, with vast and unserved needs but not the means to fulfill them, and the first-world rich, who have scads of disposable income but few real needs. While an earlier capitalist economy, backed by a Protestant ethos, was built around selling goods like timber and buckwheat that served people's needs, today's consumerist economy sustains profitability by creating needs, convincing us that Wiis and iPhones are necessary. It has done so by promoting what Barber calls an ethos of infantilization, a mind-set of ''induced childishness'' in which adults pursue adolescent lifestyles, as evidenced by their tastes and spending habits. In other words, in order to sell superfluous stuff, the market must foster a permanent mentality of ''Gimme'' and ''I want it now!''</p>
        <p>The resultant ''radical consumerist society'' has set capitalism and democracy against each other, undermining both. Capitalism, Barber writes, ''seems quite literally to be consuming itself, leaving democracy in peril and the fate of citizens uncertain.'' Children's lives are reduced to shopping excursions in which their identities are subsumed by brands -- they're the Nike generation, Abercrombie kids, iPod addicts. Meanwhile, the grown-ups have become so focused on the private ''me'' sphere, they've withdrawn from the public ''we.'' Our political culture compounds this by elevating the private sector over the public, encouraging Americans to believe that anything the government can do, private enterprise can do better (for example, prisons-for-profit are preferable to those run by the state, mercenaries trump the Marines, and so on). Left unchecked, Barber warns, ''infantilization will undo not only democracy but capitalism itself.''</p>
        <p>If this sounds like a bit of a stretch and a lot of muddle, it is. Yes, marketers target children. Yes, consumer capitalism infantilizes adults. Yes, the private sector is overvalued. All this is scary. But ultimately, Barber fails to tie the disparate strands into a coherent argument. Much of the book feels as if it were cobbled together by a series of grad students with a Nexis account. A chapter using mini-bios of Jakob Fugger (known as Jakob the Rich in 16th-century Germany), John D. Rockefeller and Bill Gates to illustrate the history of capitalism would read like a sophomore-year textbook, were the source material not so shallow (in the case of Rockefeller, Barber relies almost exclusively on Ron Chernow's ''Titan''). Marginally relevant filler -- like a chart of Google's top queries from 2001 to 2005, a list of Howard Hughes's lovers, and a rundown of reality TV shows and their earlier televised sources -- pads the text, seemingly to generate book-length proportions.</p>
        <p>Reading ''Consumed'' is like opening up and actually reading the contents of a direct-mail brochure sent by a politician whose campaign you support. You may agree with the guy, but must his message in written form -- overblown, repetitive, clichéd -- be so bad? One suspects that like most campaign advertisements, this book is not meant to be read at all; it's an example of what James Fallows has called the ''op-ed book'': an argument, even a valuable one, that could do in 900 words what it does in 400 pages.</p>
        <p>Then there are the careless errors. Quoted writers and thinkers are misidentified or not identified at all. At one point Barber refers to a Hollywood tabloid couple, ''Jennifer Lopez and Brad Pitt'' (hello?!). Later, he accuses Steven Soderbergh of directing ''Batman II.'' Barber might consider such pop drivel beneath him -- but then why write about it, let alone devote lengthy tangents to the Sims and Shaquille O'Neal?</p>
        <p>This is a shame, because the messages contained in ''Consumed'' are important. Barber makes points that need to be made -- about the excesses of consumer capitalism, the pernicious effects of creeping libertarianism and the cheapening consequences of omnipresent branding. Barber, who apparently aspires to the life of a public intellectual, with its talk show appearances and lecture circuits, could serve as the anti-Thomas L. Friedman, offering a decidedly less rosy view of life behind the Lexus wheel. If only he wrote a book half so well.</p>
        <p>Pamela Paul is a frequent contributor to the Book Review and the author, most recently, of ''Pornified.'' Her next book will be about the business behind child rearing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Pamela Paul is a frequent contributor to the Book Review and the author, most recently, of ''Pornified.'' Her next book will be about the business behind child rearing.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
