<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trail of Tears</title>
    <meta content="Royte.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Royte.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Eskimos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eskimos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Long Exile, The: A Tale of Inuit Betrayal and Survival in the High Arctic (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1238" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trail of Tears</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trail of Tears</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH ROYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Royte, Elizabeth</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LONG EXILE</p>
        <p>A Tale of Inuit Betrayal and Survival</p>
        <p>in the High Arctic.</p>
        <p>By Melanie McGrath.</p>
        <p>268 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three Inuit families were forcibly relocated to an extremely inhospitable island in Arctic Canada.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LONG EXILE</p>
        <p>A Tale of Inuit Betrayal and Survival</p>
        <p>in the High Arctic.</p>
        <p>By Melanie McGrath.</p>
        <p>268 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Throughout human history, seemingly simple turns of events have changed the fates of individuals and nations. In 1906, Thomas Watt Coslett invented a way to keep iron corset stays from rusting, and the bottom fell out of the whale-bone market. The whalers who remained on the eastern shore of Hudson Bay switched to trading for the creamy pelts of the Arctic fox, which local Inuit, on the Ungava Peninsula, began to trap in ever greater numbers. But when prices for skins fell in 1950, at a time when fox populations had also crashed, trappers -- formerly subsistence hunters -- moved to trading posts and begged rations from the Canadian police.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile the cold war raged, and the Canadian government became increasingly concerned about its sovereignty in the east Arctic archipelago. The United States and Canada jointly ran a weather station on Ellesmere Island, but Canadian officials wanted permanent residents there. The remedy to both the geopolitical and welfare problems was simple: uproot the Ungava Inuit and plant them 1,200 miles north, on Ellesmere. In ''The Long Exile,'' Melanie McGrath tells the story of this forced relocation -- a tale of almost unrelenting horror -- with so much moral vigor and descriptive verve that one quits reading only long enough to shake one's head in disbelief. And then, with a shiver, reads on.</p>
        <p>To succeed on Hudson Bay, the Inuit needed to know everything about their immediate surroundings: the landmarks, the animals' travel and migration routes, the location of fresh-water springs, berries, bird eggs and willow-worm cocoons to dip into seal fat for dinner. Describing the land's natural features with lyrical precision, McGrath emphasizes that the harsh physical realities of this place shaped not only how the Inuit lived but also their personalities, making a strong case that psychology is destiny. At one time, expressing rage, lust or ambition were considered so threatening to Inuit group survival that persistent offenders were banished. But while serenity and self-restraint were adaptive in the Inuit's ancestral environment, their unwillingness to speak out, on Ellesmere, would almost kill them.</p>
        <p>It was the late summer of 1953 when the Canadian government deposited three reluctant Inuit families, including a master carver named Paddy Aqiatusuk, on a narrow Ellesmere beach. They had been promised abundant game and a return ticket in one year's time if they were unhappy. They were, in fact, instantly miserable.</p>
        <p>At 81 degrees north latitude, Ellesmere is, McGrath notes, the harshest terrain that humans have ever continuously inhabited. A high arctic desert, its interior is ''an impenetrable mass of frozen crags and deep fjords.'' The Inuit soon learned that marine mammals were scarce, as were caribou, fox and fresh water. Their clothing wasn't warm enough, and their sleds and harnesses were all wrong for the rocky terrain. The rough waters made hunting by kayak impossible, and the dry wind made their dogs' lungs bleed. Sufficient snow for snow houses arrived late, leaving the settlers in flimsy canvas tents until late winter. There wasn't enough fuel for fires. The air was almost 30 degrees colder than back home, and the near constant wind made it feel more than 50 degrees worse. Four months of darkness ''made hunting an almost daily terror,'' McGrath writes. Ellesmere supported a small musk ox population, but the police detachment, 40 miles from the Inuit encampment, forbade killing them. The starving Inuit ate bird feathers, made broth from boot liners. ''The children leaked diarrhea then vomit which the women in the camp fed to the dogs rather than have it go to waste.''</p>
        <p>Too reticent to complain, even when to save her family from starvation, Aqiatusuk's 6-year-old granddaughter was forced onto the ice to hunt in total darkness, the Inuit persevered. When they finally screwed up their courage and asked to go home, the police refused. It was logistically complicated: the Inuit must cope. Government careers were on the line: the colony had to succeed. Its inhabitants were the equivalent of national flags fluttering in the wind.</p>
        <p>McGrath, wickedly talented, brings every bit of this to life (helped by her Inuit subjects' preternatural memory for details). We hear the gnash of the ice (''a terrible, raw, geologic sound''), feel the pangs of hunger and thirst. We feel, too, the Inuit's aching sense of abandonment and betrayal, their utter disorientation in a land where they knew nothing of the animal routes, the sea's eddies and currents or the habits of wind and ice. Such details are not a matter of comfort, they are a matter of survival. McGrath is a meticulous researcher -- she took the trouble to learn the names and colors of lichens that grow on rocks beneath bird colonies and fox lookouts -- and she writes as if she'd lived in the Arctic for years. The book moves quickly, to a drumbeat of doom. As the Inuit approach their new home, ''the frail summer had already begun to sicken and the sky pressed down on the land like a dead hand.''</p>
        <p>McGrath, who has written three previous books, is smart to focus on Aqiatusuk and his extended family. They humanize her tale, which includes a history of exploration in the eastern Canadian Arctic and of the relentless exploitation of Inuits by whites. Aqiatusuk was the adoptive father of a boy named Josephie, whose real father was the American Robert Flaherty, the director of ''Nanook of the North.'' Filmed on the Ungava Peninsula in the 1920s, the so-called documentary idealized the Inuit as innocents in an unblemished land. The movie colored the Western view of Inuit life in the Arctic for generations as it traveled the globe winning prizes, immortalizing a world that never existed. Actually, the Inuit way of life was already tainted by white fur traders by the time Flaherty arrived (he himself was financially backed by a trader), and the film's starring family was entirely contrived, just like the settlement on Ellesmere, a place with no history or purpose beyond politics. According to McGrath, Flaherty made Nanook out of admiration for the Inuit's ''raw unquestioning confidence,'' qualities shattered by the move to Ellesmere. As an adult, Josephie Flaherty, whose mother starred in ''Nanook'' (and cohabited with Flaherty), would follow Aqiatusuk to Ellesmere and die there, a broken man. But his daughter Martha, the child hunter and granddaughter of Robert Flaherty, eventually escaped and later forced the Canadian government to reckon with its crimes.</p>
        <p>As the years wore on, the Inuit gradually learned how to survive on Ellesmere. They constructed huts from scrap wood, revamped their sleds and dog harnesses.They learned the beluga's migration route and would eventually hunt over a range of 6,864 square miles each year. In 1962, the government sent a teacher to the island, but only two school books: one on how to run a bank, the other called ''The Roads of Texas.''</p>
        <p>Forty years after the first families left Ungava for Ellesmere, the Canadian government held hearings to investigate the relocation program. At its conclusion, the Royal Commission on Aboriginal Peoples called the relocation ''one of the worst human rights violations in the history of Canada.'' The country was shocked by the abuse and arrogance of its leaders, who eventually made financial reparations of 10 million Canadian dollars to the survivors and their families. But the government has yet to apologize.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Royte, whose ''Garbage Land: On the Secret Trail of Trash,'' has recently been published in paperback, is a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Royte, whose ''Garbage Land: On the Secret Trail of Trash,'' has recently been published in paperback, is a frequent contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
