<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>My Favorite Spy</title>
    <meta content="Taylor2.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Taylor2.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Eye of the Archangel: A Mallory and Morse Novel of Espionage (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E0DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>My Favorite Spy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">My Favorite Spy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES TAYLOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Taylor, Charles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EYE OF THE ARCHANGEL</p>
        <p>A Mallory and Morse Novel of Espionage.</p>
        <p>By Forrest DeVoe Jr.</p>
        <p>296 pp. HarperCollins Publishers. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A retro thriller pays homage to the 1960s secret agent Modesty Blaise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EYE OF THE ARCHANGEL</p>
        <p>A Mallory and Morse Novel of Espionage.</p>
        <p>By Forrest DeVoe Jr.</p>
        <p>296 pp. HarperCollins Publishers. $24.95.</p>
        <p>At the heart of ''Eye of the Archangel'' lies a sincere compliment. The author, Max Phillips, writing under the smoking-jacket pseudonym Forrest DeVoe Jr., has clearly modeled this tale of a cold war co-ed spy duo on Peter O'Donnell's Modesty Blaise novels, and nearly every page shows how Phillips has imbibed his source.</p>
        <p>His devotion isn't surprising. O'Donnell is one of those rare popular writers, like Josephine Tey or P. G. Wodehouse, who inspire not just fandom but love. To get a sense of what Phillips is trying to channel here, it's necessary to give a brief overview of the Modesty Blaise books. Written from the mid-1960s to the '80s (the material first appeared as a comic strip), the novels were about the young, beautiful, stylish and fabulously wealthy Modesty, retired as the head of an international organization of thieves, who, with her cockney partner, Willie Garvin, takes on a series of archvillains at the behest of the British secret service.</p>
        <p>The formula was the same in each book: a crazed supervillain poses a threat to world peace; Modesty and Willie are recruited to destroy him, but are captured and imprisoned in the bad guy's seemingly inescapable fortress before engineering an amazing escape during which the villain is defeated.</p>
        <p>Amid the spy craze of the '60s, publicists and lazy reviewers were all too happy to describe Modesty as a female James Bond. But O'Donnell's books have nothing in common with the cold, puritanical sadism of Ian Fleming's rather joyless novels, and only a little with the infinitely better sly and hedonistic movies made from them. The fantastic elements of the Modesty novels were tempered by O'Donnell's superb physical writing; his knack for describing the rudiments of mechanical action or the specifics of derring-do always advanced the narrative. At heart, the Modesty Blaise books were romantic adventure novels grounded by the story of a platonic friendship that had the ardor of a love affair. They were 19th-century romances amid the pop trappings of the 20th century. (The link to an earlier style of adventure writing was brought home in the historical romances O'Donnell wrote under the name Madeleine Brent.)</p>
        <p>Phillips obviously means his American pair, Jack Mallory and Laura Morse, to be a homage to Modesty and Willie. They too work as intelligence agents (for a supersecret group called the Consultancy). They too are proficient in all sorts of physical combat. They've even been trained, like Modesty and Willie, to regulate their sleep, allowing them catnaps during the lulls in danger.</p>
        <p>The plot of ''Eye of the Archangel,'' a workable travesty of superagent fiction, starts with one of Hitler's top scientists who, since the end of World War II, has been shunted from the Nazis to the Soviets to Arne Jespers, a black marketeer who wants this Teutonic Mr. Wizard to complete the fiendish thingamabob he was working on for the FÃ1/4hrer. Jack and Laura have to derail Jespers's scheme, and since he plans to hold bidding for the invention in Monte Carlo during the Grand Prix, Phillips can throw a little travel-brochure color into the proceedings. He needs it.</p>
        <p>Out of the most affectionate intentions, Phillips has landed himself in a pickle. He can't imitate the specifics of the characters to whom he's paying homage. But his aren't remotely as appealing. Willie Garvin's skeptical cockney bonhomie has been replaced by Jack Mallory's swaggering, drunken bluster, and Modesty Blaise's chic, sophisticated reserve has been jettisoned for Laura Morse's prudish patrician airs. (Why would any writer make the heroine of a sexy secret agent story a Boston Brahmin? That's like using Arthur Fiedler records as the soundtrack to a seduction.) And the unrequited love Laura feels for Jack never takes emotional hold. You're left thinking it's the story of an ice cube pining for a barroom braggart.</p>
        <p>The evil characters fare somewhat better. Jespers's mistress/henchwoman, an Amazonian number named Milena, has a suitable sexual grotesquerie, and his entourage includes a pair of teenage Danish twins (I swear) who work as nude masseuses. Phillips gets some laughs by having Jack alternately bed and fend off this depleting trio, but the book can't decide whether its guiding inspiration is Terry Southern or Hugh Hefner.</p>
        <p>It's the unhip side of the latter, unfortunately, that seems to predominate. ''Eye of the Archangel'' is an efficient piece of genre craftsmanship, and you certainly can't accuse Phillips of not being aware of how ridiculous the whole enterprise is -- he means that to be part of its appeal. But too often it reads like the second-rate movies that in the '60s tried to cash in on the Bond success, the Matt Helm and Derek Flint pictures in which 007's cool was reduced to swinging bachelor squaresville, a place where it was believed that all the right accouterments -- the right stereo system, the right booze, the right sex -- equaled style and wit.</p>
        <p>Max Phillips has previously tried his hand at hard-boiled fiction (he wrote ''Fade to Blonde'' for his own Hard Case Crime imprint). But it may be that genre writing isn't Phillips's best form: his debut novel, ''Snakebite Sonnet,'' was one of the loveliest coming-of-age stories of the last two decades. Not only did the book have a genuine, lyrical eroticism, his depiction of the thorniness of male-female relations was so accurate it could make you wince in recognition. I'm touched by the affection Phillips shows in ''Eye of the Archangel.'' But his own voice is more convincing than this pastiche.</p>
        <p>Charles Taylor is a columnist for The Star-Ledger of Newark.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Charles Taylor is a columnist for The Star-Ledger of Newark.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
