<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Lonely Seeks Solace In No Man's Land</title>
    <meta content="08waxm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/movies/08waxm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839062"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waxman, Sharon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kasdan, Jonathan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">In the Land of Women (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kasdan, Lawrence</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kasdan, Jake</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">In the Land of Women (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEFD81F30F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Lonely Seeks Solace In No Man's Land</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mr. Lonely Seeks Solace in No Man’s Land</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sharon Waxman interviews writer-director Jonathan Kasdan about his new film In The Land Of Women; life, career, origin of film and difficulty relating to women discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SLIGHT in stature and concave in shape, the writer-director Jonathan Kasdan has the frail intensity of a somewhat mad professor. Just 27, he is the creative force behind a new film starring Meg Ryan and Adam Brody, ''In the Land of Women.'' Mr. Brody, the television star from ''The O.C.,'' plays a Kasdan surrogate: a young man from Los Angeles, forging friendships with a host of women of different ages who are each coping with crisis.</p>
        <p>The film, Mr. Kasdan's first, signals a moment of triumph for the Kasdan family. Jon's older brother, Jake, has just finished his latest film, ''The TV Set'' -- about the making of a television show -- which came out Friday, just two weeks before Jon's April 20 release. Both men are the sons of Lawrence Kasdan, the director of such cultural touchstones as ''The Big Chill'' and ''Body Heat'' and the executive producer of ''In the Land of Women.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jonathan Kasdan, director of “In the Land of Women” and son of Lawrence Kasdan, discusses filmmaking as a family affair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SLIGHT in stature and concave in shape, the writer-director Jonathan Kasdan has the frail intensity of a somewhat mad professor. Just 27, he is the creative force behind a new film starring Meg Ryan and Adam Brody, ''In the Land of Women.'' Mr. Brody, the television star from ''The O.C.,'' plays a Kasdan surrogate: a young man from Los Angeles, forging friendships with a host of women of different ages who are each coping with crisis.</p>
        <p>The film, Mr. Kasdan's first, signals a moment of triumph for the Kasdan family. Jon's older brother, Jake, has just finished his latest film, ''The TV Set'' -- about the making of a television show -- which came out Friday, just two weeks before Jon's April 20 release. Both men are the sons of Lawrence Kasdan, the director of such cultural touchstones as ''The Big Chill'' and ''Body Heat'' and the executive producer of ''In the Land of Women.''</p>
        <p>Seated at a new, so-retro-it's-trendy cupcake shop in the Brentwood section of Los Angeles ($3 for a Red Velvet with cream cheese frosting) Mr. Kasdan opened up -- with trepidation -- to Sharon Waxman about his new film, life as the child of a Hollywood veteran, cancer and his terror of women.</p>
        <p>Q. When did you start writing movies?</p>
        <p>A. I've been writing screenplays pretty much since I was 16. To grow up in the household that I did, the idea of writing extremely personal movies seemed like an incredibly rewarding job, something to be a part of.</p>
        <p>Q. You dropped out of New York University film school and started writing for ''Freaks and Geeks,'' Judd Apatow's show. How did that happen?</p>
        <p>A. I'd finished my first year of film school, and I'd been planning to go back. Judd and Jake [Kasdan, who directed several episodes] decided there was a value to having someone fresh out of high school on the staff. So I lucked into this situation where they invited me to be part of this thing. I could not say no.</p>
        <p>Q. You weren't worried about missing film school?</p>
        <p>A. I came to film school at a funny time, '98, '99. You could feel the encroaching digital age, but all the stuff they're teaching was still about how to cut sound, traditional filmmaking.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you get along with your brother?</p>
        <p>A. He and I are very close. We talk constantly.</p>
        <p>Q. Are you similar?</p>
        <p>A. We are. He's more reserved, and more mature than I am. Jake is a storyteller in a way that I admire. He creates characters. I'm writing way more one-to-one, for myself.</p>
        <p>Q. So when did you start writing movie scripts?</p>
        <p>A. I was trying to write something that was inspired by my father's film ''Grand Canyon.'' Everything I was writing was personal, about growing up on the Westside of Los Angeles. I wrote a pilot for FX. They didn't do it. I wrote two more scripts in a row, one that I finished and never showed to anybody. I did not like it enough. Something about it just didn't feel like I wanted it to represent me. Then I went up to my parents' cabin in Telluride, and I started writing this script -- it's the only one I've ever done quickly -- in four weeks. But it had elements of things I'd been working on for a long time. This idea of an older woman in a moment of crisis in her life, meeting a young man at a different point of crisis in his life, was something I'd been trying to write for a long time.</p>
        <p>Q. Why? Was this based on your life?</p>
        <p>A. There was a friend of my parents who had briefly separated from her husband. One summer, while my parents were in Colorado, she and I ran into each other, and ended up making plans for a walk together. And we did. It was never romantic, never sexual, but it was something I liked. I felt I was connecting with an adult for the first time.</p>
        <p>Q. Were you in crisis at the time?</p>
        <p>A. I was in total crisis. When I was 16, I got Stage 2 Hodgkins disease. I needed six months of chemotherapy and radiation therapy. That was the basis for Meg's side of the story. But the real lasting effect of that was it left me with a lifetime of anxiety about my physical health. I was permanently nervous about my body. This kind of anxiety disorder started exactly a year after treatment. I'm medicated for it. It's a real thing. I'm very quick to descend back into mania. I'm a textbook hypochondriac. I was a neurotic guy to begin with, and when this happened, it gave me a profound reason to feel I'm right to be worried.</p>
        <p>Q. How did you come to cast Adam Brody in the part that, is, basically, you?</p>
        <p>A. I started to look for a guy to be at the center of a movie, and I met a ton of guys. They were different, unusual, great, but they didn't have this John Cusack thing I was looking for. This very relatable, winning, funny guy. In frustration we opened it up to television actors who were not available to us for eight months. This was August. The first person I met with was Adam. We immediately had a rapport, and we shut the project down. Adam doesn't have the unabashed neurotic quality that I do, that the character had in the script. He brought something more attractive. He has a confidence and an ease about him, that's a big part of his personality. I was so crazy about Adam that I wanted to take the chance. And we lucked out, it worked.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the movie about, to you?</p>
        <p>A. The messy business, I guess, of connection in the world.</p>
        <p>Q. And where does the title come from?</p>
        <p>A. It came from my photo thesis at N.Y.U. One of the things the movie is about is a guy who's completely preoccupied with his relationships with women. It's a central subject of his interest, but essentially he knows nothing about them. And he keeps learning that over and over again. [Pause to play with the baby at the next table.] I wanted to make a movie in that one of the things that makes the guy sexy is that he's a listener. I wish I was better at that. It's something I aspire to be, a great listener, and something I admire in people. I find it incredibly attractive.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you feel yourself a stranger in the land of women?</p>
        <p>A. I do. I certainly feel this inability to make the kind of connections the movie is about. That's always been a real struggle for me. To women, definitely. I would like to know how to be a better man to women.</p>
        <p>Q. But -- you're saying that you feel like it's hard to talk to women?</p>
        <p>A. I do. Absolutely. Even you. I don't feel I'm incapable, certainly. Honestly I think this anxiety thing plays into that a lot. I'm very guarded. I barely can go an entire conversation without saying something I'll deeply regret. Already I shudder to think ----.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you have a girlfriend?</p>
        <p>A. No. I'm desperately seeking Susan at this point, you have to say. I'm eager to be in a relationship. But for some reason it doesn't come naturally to me. It never has. I have almost no confidence. I don't know if it's possible for a guy to have less confidence in this department than I do. And women can see it. They can see it in your eyes.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
