<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Travels Abroad Lead to Journeys Within</title>
    <meta content="08fine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/arts/design/08fine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rubin Museum of Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fineman, Mia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Lynn (Photographer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rubin Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Davis, Lynn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0D81F30F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Travels Abroad Lead to Journeys Within</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Travels Abroad Lead to Journeys Within</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIA FINEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fineman, Mia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles photographer Lynn Davis, whose works are being shown at Rubin Museum of Art; although museum's mission is promotion of art and culture of Himalayas, it felt Davis's works, which evoke feeling of inner peace and contemplation, were in line with its values and energy; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a recent Thursday afternoon the photographer Lynn Davis sat nursing a cappuccino in the airy, ground-floor cafe of the Rubin Museum of Art in Chelsea. The Rubin, which opened in 2004, is primarily devoted to the Buddhist art of Himalayan Asia, and that afternoon Ms. Davis, a slender woman with translucent skin and a gleaming mane of white hair, seemed to radiate an air of inner tranquillity and relaxed contemplation.</p>
        <p>Or maybe it was jet lag. The day before, she returned from a trip to southern India, where she photographed the ruins of Hampi, the 14th-century capital of the Hindu kingdom Vijayanagara, now designated a Unesco World Heritage Site. ''If I closed my eyes,'' she confessed, ''I could fall asleep right now.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For 20 years, Lynn Davis has sought out and photographed “sites that evoke a feeling of inner peacefulness.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a recent Thursday afternoon the photographer Lynn Davis sat nursing a cappuccino in the airy, ground-floor cafe of the Rubin Museum of Art in Chelsea. The Rubin, which opened in 2004, is primarily devoted to the Buddhist art of Himalayan Asia, and that afternoon Ms. Davis, a slender woman with translucent skin and a gleaming mane of white hair, seemed to radiate an air of inner tranquillity and relaxed contemplation.</p>
        <p>Or maybe it was jet lag. The day before, she returned from a trip to southern India, where she photographed the ruins of Hampi, the 14th-century capital of the Hindu kingdom Vijayanagara, now designated a Unesco World Heritage Site. ''If I closed my eyes,'' she confessed, ''I could fall asleep right now.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Davis, 62, is a veteran traveler. For the last 20 years she has circled the globe with her camera, documenting mammoth structures like the Great Pyramids and natural wonders like Wave Rock in western Australia in an austere yet ravishing style. She has photographed icebergs in Greenland; ancient architectural ruins throughout Asia, Africa and the Middle East; and rock formations in the American West, following what she described as an ''internal logic'' from one continent to the next.</p>
        <p>''What I'm looking for,'' she said, ''are sites that evoke a feeling of inner peacefulness, some quality of contemplation. I don't always get it, and I don't always translate it, but I certainly know when the feeling comes over me, and that's what keeps me going.''</p>
        <p>''Illumination: Photographs by Lynn Davis,'' which opened at the Rubin on Friday, takes this feeling as its central theme, presenting the photographs as objects of spiritual as well as aesthetic contemplation. Installed in spacious galleries painted in subdued shades of tan and eggplant, it is the largest show the museum has devoted to a living artist.</p>
        <p>''We're taking Lynn out of the white box of the traditional gallery and placing her in a museum that feels more like a temple,'' said Charles Melcher, a member of the museum's photography committee and president of Melcher Media, an independent book packager and publisher in New York.</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Davis's photographs don't relate directly to the Rubin's mission of promoting the art and culture of the Himalayas, the committee felt that her work ''was in line with the values and energy of the place,'' said Mr. Melcher, who helped organize the exhibition and published the accompanying catalog.</p>
        <p>''It couldn't be more appropriate because Lynn has traveled a spiritual path,'' he said. ''She is a student of Buddhism, and it's an undercurrent in her work that people haven't looked at before.''</p>
        <p>Of the 30 photographs on view several depict important Buddhist sculptures and monuments in China, Japan and Thailand. In others the religious reference is more oblique. A tightly framed photograph of stone steps half-covered by desert sand in a cemetery in Dunhuang, China, powerfully evokes the Buddhist principle of impermanence. The relationship between form and emptiness, another fundamental concept in Buddhist philosophy, finds expression in a dramatic view of the sky through a hollow rock formation at Arches National Park in Utah.</p>
        <p>In order to integrate the show more fully with the Rubin's collection of more than 2,000 Himalayan paintings, sculptures, textiles and prints, the museum invited Ms. Davis to choose a group of artifacts to be displayed in the galleries alongside her pictures.</p>
        <p>At first glance the eight objects she selected -- all elaborately detailed, metalwork sculptures -- seem to have little in common with the spare, elemental forms in her photographs. But for Ms. Davis the objects and images have a deeper resonance.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to use the word spiritual,'' she said, ''but the spirit behind them is the same.''</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Davis has some familiarity with Eastern religious art from her travels in Asia, she chose the objects on the basis of their beauty or emotional appeal, not necessarily for their art-historical significance. (She replaced several of her initial selections with artifacts that the Rubin's curators considered more noteworthy.)</p>
        <p>Examining the works in the galleries before the show opened, Ms. Davis said she was particularly drawn to objects with some connection to architecture, like a fragment of a metalwork mandala featuring a torana, a type of gateway common at Buddhist and Hindu shrines. A 15th-century Tibetan statue of the Buddha's son Rahula with three rows of heads rising from his shoulders reminded her of the tiered eaves of a pagoda.</p>
        <p>An eighth-century statue of the bodhisattva Avalokiteshvara with 10 radiating arms had a somewhat more prosaic appeal. ''That's how I feel when I'm on the road with all my bags and cameras,'' she said. ''I often wish I had a few extra arms when I'm working.''</p>
        <p>WHILE Ms. Davis's photographs of ancient monuments are generally devoid of tourists, soft-drink vendors and other signs of human life, her early pictures focused almost exclusively on the human form. After graduating from the San Francisco Art Institute in 1970, she moved to New York and began shooting nudes in a sensual, classicizing style not unlike that of her close friend Robert Mapplethorpe.</p>
        <p>Her work changed dramatically in 1986, when she first traveled to the Arctic to photograph icebergs floating in Greenland's Disko Bay. At the time several of her friends, including Mapplethorpe and the photographer Peter Hujar, were dying of AIDS, and the mood in New York seemed dismal and bleak.</p>
        <p>''I was trying to find an outer manifestation of what I was feeling,'' she recalled. ''When I saw the ice, something clicked. It was like the beginning of another journey.''</p>
        <p>That journey kept her on the road, usually alone, for about six months of every year. Using an old Rolleiflex camera, she photographed from the backs of horses and camels, from boats and helicopters. Back in her studio, she rendered her negatives as exquisite, large-scale black-and-white prints, toned with gold and selenium to shift the neutral grays toward blue or sepia.</p>
        <p>Because of her far-flung subject matter and old-fashioned printing techniques, Ms. Davis is often seen as a successor to 19th-century photographers like Francis Frith, who recorded the pyramids of Egypt in the late 1850s, or William Bradford, who led a photographic expedition to the Arctic in 1869.</p>
        <p>But the real strength of her work, said Keith F. Davis (no relation), curator of photography at the Nelson-Atkins Museum of Art in Kansas City, Mo., resides in the sophistication of its ''dual perspective.''</p>
        <p>''There's a deliberate nod to 19th-century precursors and to the true kind of awe that sailing through Arctic waters or seeing the pyramids represented,'' Mr. Davis said by phone from Kansas City. ''At the same time there's a very contemporary mood of elegy in her work, a sense of the frailty of human life in the face of these giant objects and vast forces.''</p>
        <p>This underlying gravitas has earned Ms. Davis the admiration of an array of poets and writers. John Ashbery and Patti Smith have written forewords to books of her photographs; the essay in the Rubin's catalog is by the British-born travel writer Pico Iyer. In 1999 the scholar Henry Louis Gates Jr. included 66 of her photographs in his book ''Wonders of the African World.'' And in a recent cover story for Aperture magazine, the critic and philosopher Arthur Danto used her pictures of space stations as the starting point for a discussion of Kant's scientific metaphysics.</p>
        <p>Recently Ms. Davis has been traveling less and spendingmore time in her studio in Hudson, N.Y., where she lives with her husband, Rudy Wurlitzer, a novelist and screenwriter. ''I'm in a real completion stage now,'' she said. ''I feel like I'm at the end of a bell curve.''</p>
        <p>In her latest series, called ''Fata Morgana'' (after the Latin name for Morgan le Fay, King Arthur's legendary half-sister), she has used old negatives to create composites in which a subject -- like an iceberg or a mound of lava -- is transformed into a seamless mirror-image of itself. Printed in a wide horizontal format, the pictures, two of which are view at the Rubin, are as symmetrical as Rorschach blots and as unearthly and mysterious as mirages.</p>
        <p>Illumination: Photographs by Lynn Davis  Rubin Museum of Art  150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000.  Through July 16.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
