<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tween On The Screen</title>
    <meta content="08NICKELODEON.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFDF1F30F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="4864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tween On The Screen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Dee</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six or eight hip, pretty, very nervous-looking girls -- somewhere around 14 years of age, though it's possible they only look that old -- were perched on couches in the splashy lobby of Nickelodeon's New York production offices, high above Times Square. The girls were there to audition, but they weren't holding scripts, because they were not auditioning for anything in particular. ''We're seeing kids all the time,'' Paula Kaplan, senior vice president of talent at Nickelodeon, told me. ''Even when we don't have a show to cast. We're meeting kids on a regular basis, just bringing them in, just to see who they are.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Six or eight hip, pretty, very nervous-looking girls -- somewhere around 14 years of age, though it's possible they only look that old -- were perched on couches in the splashy lobby of Nickelodeon's New York production offices, high above Times Square. The girls were there to audition, but they weren't holding scripts, because they were not auditioning for anything in particular. ''We're seeing kids all the time,'' Paula Kaplan, senior vice president of talent at Nickelodeon, told me. ''Even when we don't have a show to cast. We're meeting kids on a regular basis, just bringing them in, just to see who they are.''</p>
        <p>It might not have blunted their nervousness to know that on that day last November there was in fact a new show in the early stages of development just beyond those lobby doors -- not an animated show either, but a live-action sitcom -- though ''early stages'' may be an overstatement. Nick's next big sitcom had only one or two actors cast, no writing staff, no title, no pilot episode -- not even a script for a pilot episode. Not even an outline of one. In spite of which, Nick's head of development and original programming, Marjorie Cohn, told me, the network had already committed not only to producing 13 episodes of this hypothetical show but also to begin broadcasting those episodes in the fall of 2007.</p>
        <p>At first I thought I must have heard this wrong. Thirteen episodes of a concept? Nickelodeon is part of Viacom, after all, and Viacom does not do business in this improvisatory fashion. Not to mention that the success of the Disney Channel was making Nick's demographic more of a battleground than ever. Where were the poll results, the Q ratings, the meetings full of midlevel executives? How was it possible that a network that has led its particular niche of the entertainment industry for the last 12 years -- the highest-rated network on cable TV, period -- could have already scheduled a season's worth of a show that no one there seemed to know the first thing about?</p>
        <p>When I put the question to Cohn, she turned to look at an associate, and together they shrugged, unperturbed. Then she looked back at me and said simply, ''It's Dan.''</p>
        <p>''Dan'' is Dan Schneider, creator of three of Nick's most successful series, ''Drake &amp; Josh,'' ''Zoey 101'' and ''The Amanda Show.'' He has kick-started the careers of adolescent stars like Amanda Bynes, Kenan Thompson, Drake Bell and now Miranda Cosgrove, known to legions of preteens for her roles in ''Drake &amp; Josh'' and the movie ''School of Rock'' and positioned to make her debut next fall as the star of Schneider's new show. His career as a kind of Aaron Sorkin of tween sitcoms is lent a certain psychological piquancy by the fact that he was once a famous teen actor himself; at 41, he is still recognizable to TV viewers of a certain age as Dennis Blunden, the wisecracking brainiac from the '80s sitcom ''Head of the Class.''</p>
        <p>The autonomy Schneider enjoys says a lot about TV for tweens, an economically fertile territory that manages for the most part to operate under the cultural radar. All kinds of science and pseudoscience attach themselves to discussions of TV shows for very young children -- its deleterious effects on the toddler brain and whatnot -- but by the time those kids reach 7 or 8, educators, TV programmers and to some extent parents themselves have stopped paying much attention to that stuff. Children go from being a kind of cultural protectorate to the Junior Auxiliary of the tube-watching nation at large, and programs are designed for them on the same principle as they're designed for grown-ups: as a way to sell eyeballs to advertisers. Nickelodeon made $800 million on that sale last year, and that doesn't even include the various merchandising streams -- the DVDs, the magazines, the toys, the theme hotel, etc. Even so, the fact that they are lately taking a ratings beating from Disney tween-coms like ''The Suite Life of Zack and Cody'' and ''Hannah Montana'' has to be setting off some internal alarms.</p>
        <p>The effort by Viacom and Disney and others to colonize youngsters' attention boils down to a bunch of adults trying to figure out what kids will like -- a question that stays refreshingly elusive, even when the adults have M.B.A.'s. There's an element of magic to it; and so when you find a grown-up like Schneider with the requisite mojo, you pretty much let him do whatever he wants.</p>
        <p>By mid-January, with the pilot scheduled to be taped in two weeks, Schneider's new show was starting to seem a little more real: it had acquired about three-quarters of a cast and a title -- ''iCarly,'' as in ''iPod'' or ''I, Claudius.'' He had yet to write a script for this half-hour of television, but it apparently marked me as a layman to be surprised by this. ''The dialogue is pretty easy for me,'' he said. ''Everybody knows what the show is. We just don't know the exact words that are going to be spoken by the actors.''</p>
        <p>In 1988, when ''Head of the Class'' was in its heyday, Schneider -- in his 20s by then, though still playing a high-school student -- was hired by a Nick development executive named Albie Hecht to be a co-host of Nick's second annual Kids' Choice Awards. He and Hecht stayed friends, and a couple of years later -- by which time ''Head of the Class'' had been canceled and Hecht had been made head of production for the network -- they got to talking about the idea of a sketch-comedy show. ''Basically it was 'Let's create our own ''Saturday Night Live'' for kids,' '' Schneider said. ''Or our own 'Laugh In,' or 'Your Show of Shows.' '' He wrote a pilot episode, and the series, titled ''All That,'' ran for 10 years -- an eternity in light of the havoc time wreaks on any show cast entirely with children.</p>
        <p>But the turning point in his relationship with the network came after Schneider added to the evolving cast of ''All That'' a girl named Amanda Bynes. Everyone recognized her as a nascent star, and so the network set about creating a show just for her -- without consulting Schneider. The pilot that was shot for this new Bynes vehicle, though, was so poor that the network shelved it and scrapped plans for the series entirely -- at which point Schneider felt he had to speak up. ''I went to the Nickelodeon executives, and I said: 'Look, you can't blame Amanda for that; it was just the wrong project for her. Amanda is such a rangy little actress -- she's like a little Dana Carvey or a little Carol Burnett. What I would have done, if you had come to me, is I would have created a show where she could have played a lot of different characters. More of a sketch-type show.' So I talked to them for a while and they said O.K., go ahead; and I created 'The Amanda Show,' which is one of the most successful shows Nickelodeon has ever had.''</p>
        <p>That sense of himself as an advocate for the child actors he hires has its roots in his own experience. ''By the time I was on TV, I was 19,'' he told me, ''but I played a kid, and they treated us like kids, so it's almost like I was a kid actor. Basically we were considered props who spoke.'' In practice, Schneider's desire to empower his young actors is more about emotional support than anything else, for total creative control is something he freely admits to requiring. ''Delegating,'' he said, ''is something that I don't do as much of as people wish I would.'' But his need to make the kids feel like stars is a key to not only how he runs his shows, but also to what those shows are about. It can be summed up in the simple mandate Nick executives gave him when he first started writing for them: ''Kids win.''</p>
        <p>''It made a lot of sense to me,'' he said, ''because when you're a kid, most of the time you're being told to shut up by adults. In school: be quiet. Your dad's watching a show: be quiet. Even the kids who seem to have a lot of freedom, their lives are pretty controlled. So what I try to do on my shows is to have kids come out on top. They're the smartest ones in the room. They're the ones in charge.''</p>
        <p>As an afternoon spent watching Nick or the Disney Channel will bear out, the ''kids win'' policy, if not exactly zero-sum, does tend to turn the fictional adults into something like losers. But ''iCarly'' is a particularly refined example: 13-year-old Carly Shay's father is in the military overseas, and her mother is . . . well, Schneider hadn't figured that out yet, but for now it was enough that the mother is out of the picture. Which leaves Carly in the care of her 26-year-old brother, Spencer, a struggling artist whose life skills are considerably less evolved than his baby sister's; as she would say to him in their very first scene together in the pilot, ''I can't believe you're in charge of me.'' Carly is living out two adolescent fantasies at once: she gets to elude her caregiver's restrictions and do whatever she wants, and she also gets to be the caregiver, for Spencer is an adult in dire need of looking after.</p>
        <p>The buffoonery of the authority figures is the No. 1 thing parents dislike about these shows, but that's also the beauty of them: your parents aren't watching anyway, so who cares what they think? When most of today's parents were young, there were three major networks to choose from, and those networks aspired to develop shows that whole families could watch together; the hour between 8 and 9 p.m., lest we forget, was once designated TV's ''family hour.'' It sounds like a nice idea, but it also made for a lot of sappy, moralistic programs. Now the efflorescence of cable channels has segmented the audience: even if parents approve of what their kids are watching on Nick or the Disney Channel, they almost never watch it with them, in large measure because these shows tend to come on between 4 and 8 p.m. And because the parents are out of the room, the shows themselves are no longer obliged to convey any tedious lessons about adult authority. They are -- just as much as adult programming is -- a reflection of their particular audience's fantasies. To the adults whose influence the tweens fantasize about scaling down, this may be an upsetting development, but it isn't really a bad or even a cynical one.</p>
        <p>At the same time, though, a sweet and unexpected nostalgia reigns over almost all of tween TV. (While Nickelodeon's demographic might be defined as anything south of age 14 and north of the maternity ward, the definition of a ''tween'' is fungible -- 8 to 12 seems like a reasonable range.) You might expect that today's youth, whether because of their devolved attention spans or their easy embrace of new technology, would represent some sort of vanguard in the evolution of new forms: shows that last 15 minutes instead of 30, shows that take place on a split screen, shows with multiple endings. But the actual creators of these shows are not young anymore; when it comes to the question of what kids like, in the end all the creators really have to call upon is the memory of what they liked when they were kids themselves. Thus Schneider's first big success was patterned in part on ''Your Show of Shows,'' which might as well be MoliÃ</p>
        <p>re for all anyone in the ''All That'' demographic could tell you. ''The Amanda Show'' is recognizable to any boomer as ''The Carol Burnett Show'' with a much shorter cast. ''I try to think,'' Schneider said of his writing process, ''when I was a kid, would I have wanted to watch this?''</p>
        <p>By no means is he the only one who practices this sort of nostalgia; Disney's ''Phil of the Future'' is like ''My Favorite Martian'' set in high school, and Nick's newest hit, ''The Naked Brothers Band,'' is essentially a cover version of ''The Partridge Family.'' For years Nick ran a game show indistinguishable from the ancient ''I've Got a Secret.'' Tween programming is so retro that the shows even have theme songs, something the quest for more commercial time drove out of prime-time television years ago.</p>
        <p>But it can't be mere coincidence that Schneider is so particularly successful at this minigenre. Schneider himself offered the less-than-searching explanation that he is ''a kid at heart,'' but it seems more interesting than that; the memory of having been undervalued, as a young person, on the set of a TV show seems to have given him access to a particular comedic language in which to redress the way he and his co-stars were viewed by adults. Even if in overtime, kids win.</p>
        <p>Just 12 days later, on the eve of taping, the newly acquainted cast and crew gathered at the Nick on Sunset studios for the run-through -- the last time the episode would be performed by the actors straight through from beginning to end. It was an odd sort of theater: the actors trotted from set to set between scenes as the assistant director read out stage directions from the script, and the assembled executives, parents and guests shuffled along a narrow corridor behind them, as if on a palace tour. Everything ran smoothly until they came to Scene R, in which Carly and her best friend, Sam, tape the first installment of their soon-to-be-popular Webcast, a kind of Stupid Human Tricks episode featuring acts deemed unsuitable for the school talent show. Schneider and company cast the extras for this scene by putting out a call to agents asking for kids with unusual talents: this call yielded a rapping contortionist, a girl who played the trumpet while hopping on a pogo stick and a boy who, according to the script, could inhale milk through his nose and make it come out of his eyes.</p>
        <p>Until then, this last phenomenon existed purely as a stage direction: only Schneider and a couple of others had seen it, and then only on a DVD. But the boy himself was present for the run-through. When Carly and Sam introduced him, he poured some milk from a glass into his cupped palm, bent over and stuck his nose in it, stood up with one hand pinching his nostrils shut and the other tautening the skin around his cheekbones, and a veritable jet of milk shot from underneath the boy's eyeball six feet through the air and onto the floor of the stage.</p>
        <p>Pandemonium ensued. The kids screamed and the adults screamed, and though the run-through was supposed to proceed in real time, it was a while before the A.D. could silence the audience and refocus the actors in order to finish the scene. It was perhaps the grossest thing anyone in the room had ever witnessed. For one euphoric minute, the on-set distinction between child and adult disappeared, and we were all in sixth grade.</p>
        <p>When Sam ''photo-docs'' the head of her and Carly's least favorite teacher onto the body of a rhinoceros and posts it all over the school, Carly takes the rap in order to spare Sam a suspension. But Carly's own punishment comes in an odd form: the teacher makes her give up a Saturday to monitor auditions for the school's talent show. Carly's lovestruck neighbor, Freddy, agrees to tape the auditions for them -- and then accidentally posts the outtakes online, including footage of Carly and Sam cutting up at the teacher's expense. But when the footage becomes an unexpected YouTube-like sensation -- and when the teacher rejects all their talent-show selections as ''inappropriate'' -- they are inspired to make their accidental Webcast a regular gig, and ''iCarly,'' the show within a show, is born.</p>
        <p>''I just hate it,'' Carly says in the pilot's key scene, ''when adults like her get to control what kids can do and see. It ticks me off!'' It is a line whose irony seemed beneath the notice of Schneider and the other off-camera intermediaries who were, in fact, in charge of what these kids would do and what millions of their peers would eventually see.</p>
        <p>The most conspicuous sound at the taping was that of Schneider's own boisterous laughter in the wake of every one of the script's dozens of jokes; it seemed downright immodest, considering that he had written all the jokes himself and was usually hearing them for the seventh or eighth take in a row, but it turned out that the laughter itself was done for practical reasons. ''The kids will forget to leave a beat after the jokes, for when we sweeten the show,'' he told me between takes -- ''sweeten'' being the euphemism for the addition of canned laughter. ''So I'm laughing to keep them from going too fast. If we're here until 9 o'clock tonight, you'll still hear me laughing at the same jokes the same way.''</p>
        <p>He was momentarily forgetting that there was no way they would be there until 9:00 that night, because they started at 9:30 in the morning, and there are strict rules -- laws, actually -- about how long the underage actors are permitted to work. No child may work for more than nine and a half hours (which, since Cosgrove was in every scene, pretty much dictated that the workday itself would run no longer than that); in addition, they must maintain a minimum of one, and an average of three, hours a day of on-set schooling. Parents or guardians must also be present on the set the entire time their children are there -- something some working parents don't fully understand when their kid gets cast. ''Which is why you see a lot of parents as their kids' manager,'' Kaplan said. ''It becomes their job.'' She also estimated, half-jokingly, that 99 percent of the child actors she has met are home-schooled.</p>
        <p>Certainly these kids' jobs required more patience and focus than the average junior-high-schooler possesses. Those with speaking parts tended to come to the set with one well-rehearsed reading for each line and would not move off of that reading for 20 takes unless Schneider asked them to. By contrast, a veteran like Mindy Sterling -- who played the nemesis teacher and who enjoyed great cachet among the kids by virtue of her role as Frau Farbissina in the Austin Powers movies -- delivered her lines differently every time, perhaps to give the director and editor more to work with or perhaps to keep herself from getting bored. Interestingly, some of the social dynamics of an actual junior high seemed to recreate themselves on the set of the fake one: the stars talked to one another, and the extras talked among themselves while watching the stars but did not actually approach them.</p>
        <p>I watched in vain for any hint of cynicism on the ''iCarly'' set, any trace of the corporate imperative to get these kids to simulate innocence no matter how miserable they were. Schneider's prime directive -- ''Kids win'' -- is an element not just of the fictional Nick universe but of the real one as well. Not once in three days of taping did I encounter a pushy stage mom; nowhere did anyone break out in tears for any reason at all. Even the extras exhibited none of the restlessness or aspirational smart-mouthing you might expect. The crew didn't grumble about the kids (they were busy passing around a Super Bowl betting sheet), and the kids were undemanding pros. A live goat was present in a house-party scene, and when, inevitably, it had an accident on the set, the kids cringed and screamed, but they did not leave their marks.</p>
        <p>After a few days, in fact, I became aware of a surprising seamlessness between the fiction and the real-world machinery of its portrayal: it was like the apex of a certain style of parenting. The adults were facilitators, in the background and out of the kids' light, more than content to stay there and play down their own contributions. The kids were told almost nothing but how great they were -- and with good reason, for it was almost impossible not to feel a kind of vicarious pride in what a good job they were doing. Of course, there on the set you saw only the children and parents whose choices had been justified; there is a much less visible culture, in Los Angeles and its environs, made up of those families who have reoriented their lives in expectation of a return on their child's greatness that never comes.</p>
        <p>Those teenage girls who auditioned in Nick's New York offices, back in November, were dreaming of a stardom that Miranda Cosgrove seems almost to have been born into. She was discovered as a toddler, dancing amid the tables at an L.A. restaurant where an agent happened to be dining as well; her first audition, at age 3, landed her a soft-drink commercial, and from there it has been success upon success, most notably her role as the grade-grubbing band manager in the Jack Black vehicle ''School of Rock.'' Having made her reputation playing second-banana, precocious-little-sister roles, sort of a preadolescent Eve Arden, Miranda seems poised to become a true, idiosyncratic beauty. She is, in the hermetic world of kids' entertainment, a big deal: on the marquee outside the Nick on Sunset studios the week of the ''iCarly'' taping was the single word: ''MIRANDA.''</p>
        <p>''She's a star,'' Schneider said. ''She is one of the classiest little girls that I've ever met. I don't believe I've ever heard her complain about anything, I don't think I've seen her in a bad mood once in my life, and I've done 61 episodes of television with her. I really avoid the overly trained Hollywood kid, the kids that are 10 years old and have had eight years of acting and dancing and singing lessons and they're so cute and precocious and perfect that you want to slit your wrists. Miranda's the real deal; there's nothing Hollywood about her.''</p>
        <p>''She loves vintage clothing,'' a publicist whispered to me on the set; she checked to see if I was writing it down. ''I don't know if she has any pets at this point.''</p>
        <p>A great deal of fuss surrounded the question of when and for how long I would be given access to her, and for once, I shared the flack army's concern, because she was, after all, not just a kid but a kid who was working a nine-and-a-half-hour day. Finally I was given 10 minutes in her dressing room during the lunch break, on the second day of taping.</p>
        <p>She was utterly delightful and charming and friendly and cooperative, and yet it was still a strange experience. I am used to getting spun by kids, but not to getting spun by kids in such a manifestly adult way: her performance would surely have earned her an A in Nick's Talent 101. Even her friendships seemed to have a preternaturally adult quality; they were, after all, office friendships. She had known most of her co-stars for only a couple of weeks; ''I've seen Jennette at auditions before,'' she said, ''because we're practically the same age, but I've only said hi to her. She's really fun, and so's Nathan [Kress, who plays Freddy]. This is actually my first time meeting both of them, and it's already like we're best friends.''</p>
        <p>After the pilot wrapped, production would be suspended for six weeks for focus-group testing -- a strange sort of interlude, presumably, for a home-schooled only child with no set to go to. ''Sometimes I get kind of bored if I go like a month or so and I'm not doing anything,'' she said. ''At first I'm like, 'Cool, I'll have a little time off and I'll get to hang out with friends,' but then after a little while goes by I'm like, 'Oh,' and I really wish that I could go back and start doing work again. It's just a blast to get to come in to the set and say hi to everyone and work with the people you know. After a few months it seems like everybody's like family.''</p>
        <p>Miranda lives an unusual life, but it would be pure sentimentality to feel sorry for her in the light of ''normal'' experiences she may have missed. Nobody seems to be exploiting her or living through her; her childhood has been bent to her gifts. There is nothing fake about her -- there doesn't have to be, for in the context of her life, she's good at everything she does. When our interview was over, she looked relieved, and also somewhat pleasantly surprised. ''That was easy,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The fully sweetened pilot episode of ''iCarly'' was shown to four groups of 8- to 11-year-olds, divided by sex, in the town of Teaneck, N.J. Technically, further work on the series was halted until after the results came in, but Schneider was regally unconcerned; in fact, somewhat against orders, he and his staff of four writers were writing new episodes of ''iCarly'' all during the six-week hiatus.</p>
        <p>Even as the testing was being conducted, Nick was pushing ''iCarly'' as its next big hit at last month's ''upfronts'' -- the annual pageant at which each TV network announces the coming year's sure-to-be-successful programming schedule in a theater full of advertisers and media buyers. From their description of ''iCarly,'' though, it became clear what Nickelodeon's executives were really hearing last fall when Schneider first sketched out his idea for a show about a girl who becomes famous by accident: the dulcet sounds of cross-platforming. No matter how old-fashioned it is in most of its sitcom aspects, ''iCarly'' is being held out to prospective advertisers as a bold embrace of the future. Not only will there be an ''iCarly'' Web site, but viewers will also be able to upload their own videos to the site -- and the best of them will actually be incorporated into the show, as part of Carly and Sam's fictional Webcast.</p>
        <p>The next wave in figuring out what kids want to watch, it seems, is to let the kids start supplying the content themselves. Schneider's ''iCarly'' comes in the wake of Nick's rechristening its 5-p.m.-to-7-p.m. programming block as Me:TV, a vertiginously meta exercise in which kids with Webcams can tune into the network in order to watch themselves watching the network. Viacom has been moving to outflank Disney and others on the Internet front for more than a year -- everything from buying the popular kids' site Neopets.com to suing the bejesus out of YouTube. It's old news, though, that kids these days spend lots of time online; what's more eye-catching -- indeed, almost counterintuitive -- is that they also manage to watch on average about two and a half hours more TV today than they did a decade ago.</p>
        <p>Still, why should tweens -- people without jobs, after all -- be such a desirable market for advertisers? True, they reportedly control $39 billion in purchasing power. It sometimes seems that they're the only ones who buy music anymore -- at one point last year the top three albums in the country were ''Kidz Bop 9,'' ''High School Musical'' and the soundtrack to ''Curious George.'' But the real reason is that these days, kids win at home too: Nick's own research reveals a truly astonishing number of families -- 70, 80, 90 percent, depending on the product -- in which buying decisions are effectively ceded to the kids, on the grounds that they know more about movies, vacation destinations, packaged foods, cellphones and so on than their parents do. There are about 25 million children in America between the ages of 9 and 14, and 77 percent of them, according to Nickelodeon, have television sets in their bedrooms.</p>
        <p>This is why an audience of 500 suits left their offices on a freezing March morning to sit in a Times Square theater and watch a montage of people belching, followed by a truly indulgent performance by the Naked Brothers Band -- two brothers, 12 and 9, with rudimentary musical skills and eight adult session musicians, one of whom was their father, backing them up. They performed their hit single, ''Crazy Car,'' which, in the week after it first aired on Nick, was downloaded 25,000 times from the iTunes store.</p>
        <p>''Welcome,'' a Viacom executive told the advertisers, ''to the land where kids rule.''</p>
        <p>A few days later, the focus-group results came in. Twenty-seven of 32 Teaneck youngsters gave ''iCarly'' a grade of A or A+. When Cohn inquired whether the whole no-parents setup struck any of the kids as ''unrealistic,'' the answer was that none of the kids even brought the matter up until they were asked about it directly; in fact, their nearly uniform opinion was that tampering with this setup by bringing back Carly's parents would ruin the show.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Dee is a novelist and a contributing writer for the magazine. His last article was about OutKast.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jonathan Dee is a novelist and a contributing writer for the magazine. His last article was about OutKast.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
