<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tolstoy Was Right: Flop Musicals Are All Unique</title>
    <meta content="08gree" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/theater/08gree.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mordden, Ethan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">All That Glittered (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mordden, Ethan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EED81F30F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tolstoy Was Right: Flop Musicals Are All Unique</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tolstoy Was Right: Flop Musicals Are All Unique</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jesse Green interviews Ethan Morden, author of many books about Broadway theater; latest book All That Glittered is chronicle of Broadway drama 1919-1959; end of golden age of Broadway musicals discussed; chart lists Mordden's choices for most indispensable and most influential musicals; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE most hard-core theater aficionados, Ethan Mordden has deeply held and often blistering opinions. Unlike most, he has earned a place for those opinions in works of widely praised scholarship, including a seven-book history of the Broadway musical from 1920 to 2005. Though he would like to add one more book to that series, covering the period from 1900 to 1920, he says no one would read it. Instead his latest book, ''All That Glittered,'' just published by St. Martin's Press, is a chronicle of the golden age of drama on Broadway: 1919 to 1959 by his reckoning.</p>
        <p>The judgments he makes in these books are pungently stated and often contrarian: ''Les Misérables'' is ''superb music theater''; ''The Lion King'' is ''a millionaire's 'Howdy Doody Show.' '' But even his more conventional conclusions -- for instance, about the most indispensable and influential musicals (see chart at left) -- emerge from the kind of long view and deep investigation that almost no writer has previously brought to bear on the subject. He is as familiar with ''Spring Awakening'' (2006) as with ''The Prince of Pilsen'' (1903). And likes both.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Broadway’s golden age may be over, but for the historian Ethan Mordden the melody lingers on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE most hard-core theater aficionados, Ethan Mordden has deeply held and often blistering opinions. Unlike most, he has earned a place for those opinions in works of widely praised scholarship, including a seven-book history of the Broadway musical from 1920 to 2005. Though he would like to add one more book to that series, covering the period from 1900 to 1920, he says no one would read it. Instead his latest book, ''All That Glittered,'' just published by St. Martin's Press, is a chronicle of the golden age of drama on Broadway: 1919 to 1959 by his reckoning.</p>
        <p>The judgments he makes in these books are pungently stated and often contrarian: ''Les Misérables'' is ''superb music theater''; ''The Lion King'' is ''a millionaire's 'Howdy Doody Show.' '' But even his more conventional conclusions -- for instance, about the most indispensable and influential musicals (see chart at left) -- emerge from the kind of long view and deep investigation that almost no writer has previously brought to bear on the subject. He is as familiar with ''Spring Awakening'' (2006) as with ''The Prince of Pilsen'' (1903). And likes both.</p>
        <p>Aside from his 13 theater books -- No. 14 will be a biography of Florenz Ziegfeld -- Mr. Mordden, 58, has written eight novels of modern gay life, including the popular ''Buddies'' series. In a conversation with Jesse Green over coffee in Manhattan, excerpted below, he eventually made his two main topics seem like one.</p>
        <p>Q. ''All That Glittered'' begins with a blow-by-blow description of a play that opened in 1918 -- not just the plot but also the back story, the hubbub and what happened at intermission. It reads as if you were there with a notebook in the wings. How do you manage that trick with material that's so ephemeral?</p>
        <p>A. It's very hard, but there's evidence. Scrapbooks. Clippings. A lot of the actors made early talkies, so you get an idea of what they were like onstage. Also, critics were good about describing plots and the feel of the performance. Even so, you have no idea what Katharine Cornell was like just from reading about her.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you fill in the blanks using previous histories?</p>
        <p>A. No. Previous histories aren't useful. I know; my first book was a history of the American musical, and luckily it's long gone, because I was 22 years old and it was very derivative. Books on the musical often are; everyone's using the same anecdotes. For instance I quoted Ethel Waters saying that the whole history of her race could be told in one song, Irving Berlin's ''Suppertime.'' I thought her joyous rendering of ''Old Man Harlem'' more essential -- yet didn't say so, because that wasn't the traditional line.</p>
        <p>Q. For the newer books you did much more detailed original research, almost living in the archives at the Billy Rose Theater Collection. But to animate what you'd learned, you still had to make an artistic leap.</p>
        <p>A. Sometimes you extrapolate, but you can find out more than you might think. Back in the old days you'd come fresh from college to New York -- 22 and, you hope, charming -- and the older gay guys would take you to dinner. They'd pick up the check, and in return they'd get to trot out all their old stories that their friends were sick of. Keep in mind: these are former chorus boys who became stage managers, and if there's anyone who can tell you what ''Lady in the Dark'' was like, it's the stage manager at the Alvin. Gertrude Lawrence might know what she did, but to find out exactly how the set changed from the psychiatrist's office to the next scene, you talk to someone who did it night after night.</p>
        <p>Q. But it's not just ''Lady in the Dark'' you recreate. You provide minute detail on flops almost nobody saw.</p>
        <p>A. My editor when I started the series couldn't understand why I emphasized flops. He quoted Spiro T. Agnew: ''When you've seen one slum, you've seen them all.'' In fact it's the opposite. Tolstoy knows: Good musicals are all alike, but flop musicals are each unhappy in their own way. You want to linger on them.</p>
        <p>Q. What was the first Broadway musical you saw?</p>
        <p>A. ''The King and I,'' and Gertrude Lawrence was still in it. I was 3 years old. All the classic musicals of that era I saw: ''Kismet,'' ''Can-Can,'' ''Damn Yankees,'' ''The Pajama Game.'' Always after having absorbed the cast album of course. And then I would go to the show and mentally photograph it, because I needed theater. If you come from an unhappy family, if your parents are so impossible that they are no source of support, you have to find it somewhere else.</p>
        <p>Q. Why the theater, though?</p>
        <p>A. In those days, theater was smart and made you smart. One of my first albums was ''Carousel.'' When her friend asks Julie Jordan why she sits by the window every morning, Julie sings, ''I like to watch the river meet the sea.'' You're 5 years old and you wonder, ''What does that mean?'' And as you think about it, it makes you understand the world a little more.</p>
        <p>Q. Or at least makes you understand how a dreamy, melancholy misfit thinks.</p>
        <p>A. There is that, yes.</p>
        <p>Q. For all their erudition, your books are chatty, catty, famously overstated and even vulgar.</p>
        <p>A. Sometimes you have to slap the reader's face to get his attention. He knows novels and movies may pose moral questions, but most theatergoers think every musical is ''Annie Get Your Gun.''</p>
        <p>Q. But your tone is also, frequently, elegiac.</p>
        <p>A. The golden age is over. Ethel Merman, Bert Lahr, choreographers like de Mille and Bob Fosse. Young people resent hearing that they're too late, so they overpraise shows they like. They want to collect their own classics. It's not their fault. After all, they can't help when they were born.</p>
        <p>Q. But how do you know that you're not falling into the same trap?</p>
        <p>A. Because I've seen both. It's not about hating whatever is new. I don't believe that older people in the 1920s, when Kern and Berlin were joined by the Gershwins and all those great people, would say, ''Whatever happened to Karl Hoschna?'' or ''Why can't they write a score like the 'The Prince of Pilsen'?'' I think they were saying, ''God, this new stuff is good.''</p>
        <p>Q. So how did you, born in 1949, escape that relativism?</p>
        <p>A. When I got into this, I was so young that we were still in the middle of the golden age. Theater was a shared experience that all middle-class people had. When the recording of ''My Fair Lady'' came out, we made a special trip into Wilkes-Barre to buy it. And as we were driving home, I held the album up in the window of the car so people could see we had it.</p>
        <p>Q. What happened? Did people change, or what was being produced?</p>
        <p>A. The culture got interested in other things. In those days if you weren't conversant with what was happening on Broadway, people looked down on you. A smart, ambitious young guy in the 1920s -- Moss Hart, say -- wanted to be a champion playwright on Broadway. That was the culture's rock star then. So his and Kaufman's ''Merrily We Roll Along'' in 1934 is a tragedy about a sellout playwright. But when they made the musical in 1981, they couldn't have a tragedy about that, because nobody cared about playwrights anymore.</p>
        <p>Q. So instead he's a sellout movie producer.</p>
        <p>A. Nowadays a Moss Hart would want to be Aaron Sorkin because no play on Broadway is as interesting as ''The West Wing.'' It's the best dramatic writing in the last 30 years.</p>
        <p>Q. And is that all right with you?</p>
        <p>A. No. But no one's asking me. When Cool came in, it was the end of theater. Cool is not eloquent. Cool is: ''What are you rebelling against?'' ''What have you got?'' If you can say that, then theater is dead, because theater is moral, it's glamorous, it's about being smart, it's about sophisticated gay people helping the heteros understand that they're stupid and boring.</p>
        <p>Q. This is, no doubt, an example of your famous overstatement.</p>
        <p>A. Well, that's gay people's role in the culture, isn't it? Now, though, they're liberated from that role. They can be real boys; they don't have to know about Auntie Mame. They still have an ironic perspective on the world because they grew up pretending to be straight. But they don't have what I call the Knowledge.</p>
        <p>Q. And that's why the golden age is over?</p>
        <p>A. I was with a young friend, playing him the tape of Barbra Streisand's final night in ''Funny Girl.'' We were both gloating over this wonderful thing, and I said, ''Did you see 'Funny Girl'?'' And he said, ''I wasn't born then.'' I hadn't even thought of that. To me it's all last Thursday.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
