<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fiction Chronicle</title>
    <meta content="Skurnick.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Skurnick.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">FitzGerald, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kadare, Ismail</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mekler, Eva</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1247" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fiction Chronicle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fiction Chronicle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lizzie Skurnick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RADIANT DAYS. By Michael A. FitzGerald. (Shoemaker &amp; Hoard, paper, $15.) Take a young man, successful but lacking in experience. Add a woman, opaque and mysterious, her past a dark negative the narrator holds up to the light, finding only his own reflection. Throw in a war, a disillusioned journalist as the antagonist whose world-weary asides counter the young man's tedious ignorance. It's an old story, made fresh by the first-time novelist Michael FitzGerald, who places his novel at the cusp of the Web boom and the end of the war in the Balkans, when Anthony Sinclair, a CNET producer disgusted by the soulless ease of his life, meets Gisela, a Hungarian bartender. He soon finds himself traveling from San Francisco to Budapest with her, supposedly to retrieve her son from an orphanage. There, they meet Marsh, a young British journalist covering the conflict, whose affection for Anthony takes the form of brutal proddings. (As they walk the streets of a trashed Serbian city in Croatia, Marsh tells Anthony to put his hands up and remain silent: ''Maybe just save your opinions for something you know about, like snowboarding, or whatever it is you did in college?'') As Gisela's story unravels, so does Anthony. But ''Radiant Days'' is more than a case study of Western apathy, circa 1995. With painful precision, FitzGerald shows us how little of Anthony -- and the fractured countries he visits -- there remains to redeem.</p>
        <p>MORTALITY: Short Stories. By Nicholas Royle. (Serpent's Tail, paper, $14.95.) How do you save a collection of stories about failed love from devolving into melancholy glop? If you are Nicholas Royle, you imbue it with thrillingly demented elements from the realm of the fantastic -- a rainbow in Paris that refuses to dissipate, or a pair of lovers encased in a cast that a jealous boyfriend proceeds to shatter. The first half of ''Mortality'' is full of airy narratives, stories that whoosh off into the ether like a car missing a turn on a steep hairpin. (Indeed, two stories send characters to their fates in similar ways.) The more successful stories of the collection come later, fully fleshed with gothic conceits reminiscent of Roald Dahl's wicked stories for adults. (Among them is ''Skin Deep,'' in which a man kills his wife, stuffs her, then takes her boyfriend hunting). It's a rare gift to be able to weave the pulpy and purple. The meaty stories in ''Mortality'' have more authority than Royle's postmodern flights of fancy -- which are less art than artful dodge.</p>
        <p>AGAMEMNON'S DAUGHTER: A Novella and Stories. By Ismail Kadare. (Arcade, $24.) When a work has been translated from Albanian to French to English, it's difficult to tell whose pen wrote which words. Still, it could have been worse. In the '80s, Kadare was forced to camouflage his novel ''The Shadow'' as the work of the German novelist Siegfried Lenz in order to smuggle it out of his native Albania, then a Communist dictatorship. (The manuscript later appeared under Kadare's own name.) ''Agamemnon's Daughter,'' the title story in a collection of three, takes place in the mid-1980s. During a May Day parade, the narrator sees his ex-lover take her place by the side of her father, who is on the rise in the regime. Presumably as a parting gift, the narrator has been given an unprecedented honor, a ticket to sit on the grandstand with the dignitaries; as he makes his way through the crowds, he is beset by the unvoiced question of what he's done to earn it. In the novella, neighbors have suffered and made others suffer under a brutal regime that evokes that of the Albanian dictator Enver Hoxha. The same shared betrayal haunts the book's other stories, ''The Blinding Order,'' about the Ottoman Empire, and ''The Great Wall,'' about the Central Asian warrior Tamerlane's forays into China. After Kadare was awarded the inaugural Man Booker international prize in 2005 for ''The Successor,'' debate swirled over how fully he had capitulated under the regime. Indeed, it's unclear whether ''Agamemnon's Daughter'' is ultimately an apology or a protest. Either way, the translation is sometimes fusty, perhaps the result of its many handlers. (When was the last time you heard the expression ''dressed to the nines''?) Less forgivable are Kadare's overwrought glissandos on Suzana's nether regions, which he compares to the Arc de Triomphe, a monster growling in the bushes and Albania under Communist rule -- ''a parched, desiccated estuary dotted about with puny blades of yellowing desert grass,'' in case you were wondering.</p>
        <p>MR. THUNDERMUG. By Cornelius Medvei. (HarperCollins, $14.95.) Although a book in which an intelligent baboon is set down amid humankind inevitably brings Kafka to mind, the protagonist of Medvei's slight, whimsical first novella is luckily more Stuart Little than Gregor Samsa. Armed with the inexplicable gift of the English tongue, the baboon, Mr. Thundermug, appears in a human city under mysterious circumstances, baboon wife and children in tow. The city dwellers exist in some hazy DMZ between ''The Cat in the Hat'' and Calvino, and greet him with a curious equanimity that shortly branches out into irritation. Medvei is English, but he takes numerous opportunities to display borscht-belt humor: residents of an insane asylum are less concerned that Thundermug is a talking baboon than they are with his ''combative manner and caustic wit,'' and a postmistress, unimpressed with Thundermug's ability to speak the language, tells a gobsmacked patron he ''doesn't speak it very well.'' Although Mr. Thundermug has a number of clashes with a decidedly inhuman bureaucracy -- at a hospital, a school and a housing department -- these encounters don't mean Medvei is making a serious attempt to scrutinize society, as Kafka did. Instead, the author shirks traditional narrative in order to highlight his lyrical prose -- and the delicate lithographs he made to illustrate his own book.</p>
        <p>THE POLISH WOMAN. By Eva Mekler. (Bridge Works, $21.95.) When does memory slip the bonds of reality to become a wish? That's the question posed by ''The Polish Woman,'' a meticulous, raw study of the uneasy relationship between Catholic and Jewish Poles. In New York in 1967, Karolina Staszek, a Polish immigrant, becomes consumed with the suspicion that she is a Jew who had been placed with a Catholic family during World War II. The Jewish family in question, the Landaus, find the story seductive but improbable -- until Karolina reveals a battery of memories unlikely to be the invention of even the canniest con artist. Told without artifice or irony, Mekler's story of multigenerational immigration owes more to coolly composed novels like Lore Segal's ''Her First American'' than to impressive acts of literary contortion like Nicole Krauss's ''History of Love.'' Despite its literary trappings, ''The Polish Woman'' is also a straightforward mystery, littered with clues, red herrings and narrators who always know less than the reader. When Karolina first confides in Philip Landau, he suddenly recalls the warning of his parents, who escaped Poland: ''The Poles were the worst, they'd declared over and over, with the pain and bitterness of personal betrayal, the worst.'' When the two eventually travel to Poland to prove Karolina's claim, they are also chasing these brief flashes of recognition, which tell the story of their shared past better than a tattered birth certificate -- and explain why they have both become phantoms in their own lives. By the time the ending veers into John Grisham territory, Mekler has already transcended plot in favor of uncompromising examination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New books by Michael A. FitzGerald, Nicholas Royle, Ismail Kadare, Cornelius Medvei and Eva Mekler.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RADIANT DAYS. By Michael A. FitzGerald. (Shoemaker &amp; Hoard, paper, $15.) Take a young man, successful but lacking in experience. Add a woman, opaque and mysterious, her past a dark negative the narrator holds up to the light, finding only his own reflection. Throw in a war, a disillusioned journalist as the antagonist whose world-weary asides counter the young man's tedious ignorance. It's an old story, made fresh by the first-time novelist Michael FitzGerald, who places his novel at the cusp of the Web boom and the end of the war in the Balkans, when Anthony Sinclair, a CNET producer disgusted by the soulless ease of his life, meets Gisela, a Hungarian bartender. He soon finds himself traveling from San Francisco to Budapest with her, supposedly to retrieve her son from an orphanage. There, they meet Marsh, a young British journalist covering the conflict, whose affection for Anthony takes the form of brutal proddings. (As they walk the streets of a trashed Serbian city in Croatia, Marsh tells Anthony to put his hands up and remain silent: ''Maybe just save your opinions for something you know about, like snowboarding, or whatever it is you did in college?'') As Gisela's story unravels, so does Anthony. But ''Radiant Days'' is more than a case study of Western apathy, circa 1995. With painful precision, FitzGerald shows us how little of Anthony -- and the fractured countries he visits -- there remains to redeem.</p>
        <p>MORTALITY: Short Stories. By Nicholas Royle. (Serpent's Tail, paper, $14.95.) How do you save a collection of stories about failed love from devolving into melancholy glop? If you are Nicholas Royle, you imbue it with thrillingly demented elements from the realm of the fantastic -- a rainbow in Paris that refuses to dissipate, or a pair of lovers encased in a cast that a jealous boyfriend proceeds to shatter. The first half of ''Mortality'' is full of airy narratives, stories that whoosh off into the ether like a car missing a turn on a steep hairpin. (Indeed, two stories send characters to their fates in similar ways.) The more successful stories of the collection come later, fully fleshed with gothic conceits reminiscent of Roald Dahl's wicked stories for adults. (Among them is ''Skin Deep,'' in which a man kills his wife, stuffs her, then takes her boyfriend hunting). It's a rare gift to be able to weave the pulpy and purple. The meaty stories in ''Mortality'' have more authority than Royle's postmodern flights of fancy -- which are less art than artful dodge.</p>
        <p>AGAMEMNON'S DAUGHTER: A Novella and Stories. By Ismail Kadare. (Arcade, $24.) When a work has been translated from Albanian to French to English, it's difficult to tell whose pen wrote which words. Still, it could have been worse. In the '80s, Kadare was forced to camouflage his novel ''The Shadow'' as the work of the German novelist Siegfried Lenz in order to smuggle it out of his native Albania, then a Communist dictatorship. (The manuscript later appeared under Kadare's own name.) ''Agamemnon's Daughter,'' the title story in a collection of three, takes place in the mid-1980s. During a May Day parade, the narrator sees his ex-lover take her place by the side of her father, who is on the rise in the regime. Presumably as a parting gift, the narrator has been given an unprecedented honor, a ticket to sit on the grandstand with the dignitaries; as he makes his way through the crowds, he is beset by the unvoiced question of what he's done to earn it. In the novella, neighbors have suffered and made others suffer under a brutal regime that evokes that of the Albanian dictator Enver Hoxha. The same shared betrayal haunts the book's other stories, ''The Blinding Order,'' about the Ottoman Empire, and ''The Great Wall,'' about the Central Asian warrior Tamerlane's forays into China. After Kadare was awarded the inaugural Man Booker international prize in 2005 for ''The Successor,'' debate swirled over how fully he had capitulated under the regime. Indeed, it's unclear whether ''Agamemnon's Daughter'' is ultimately an apology or a protest. Either way, the translation is sometimes fusty, perhaps the result of its many handlers. (When was the last time you heard the expression ''dressed to the nines''?) Less forgivable are Kadare's overwrought glissandos on Suzana's nether regions, which he compares to the Arc de Triomphe, a monster growling in the bushes and Albania under Communist rule -- ''a parched, desiccated estuary dotted about with puny blades of yellowing desert grass,'' in case you were wondering.</p>
        <p>MR. THUNDERMUG. By Cornelius Medvei. (HarperCollins, $14.95.) Although a book in which an intelligent baboon is set down amid humankind inevitably brings Kafka to mind, the protagonist of Medvei's slight, whimsical first novella is luckily more Stuart Little than Gregor Samsa. Armed with the inexplicable gift of the English tongue, the baboon, Mr. Thundermug, appears in a human city under mysterious circumstances, baboon wife and children in tow. The city dwellers exist in some hazy DMZ between ''The Cat in the Hat'' and Calvino, and greet him with a curious equanimity that shortly branches out into irritation. Medvei is English, but he takes numerous opportunities to display borscht-belt humor: residents of an insane asylum are less concerned that Thundermug is a talking baboon than they are with his ''combative manner and caustic wit,'' and a postmistress, unimpressed with Thundermug's ability to speak the language, tells a gobsmacked patron he ''doesn't speak it very well.'' Although Mr. Thundermug has a number of clashes with a decidedly inhuman bureaucracy -- at a hospital, a school and a housing department -- these encounters don't mean Medvei is making a serious attempt to scrutinize society, as Kafka did. Instead, the author shirks traditional narrative in order to highlight his lyrical prose -- and the delicate lithographs he made to illustrate his own book.</p>
        <p>THE POLISH WOMAN. By Eva Mekler. (Bridge Works, $21.95.) When does memory slip the bonds of reality to become a wish? That's the question posed by ''The Polish Woman,'' a meticulous, raw study of the uneasy relationship between Catholic and Jewish Poles. In New York in 1967, Karolina Staszek, a Polish immigrant, becomes consumed with the suspicion that she is a Jew who had been placed with a Catholic family during World War II. The Jewish family in question, the Landaus, find the story seductive but improbable -- until Karolina reveals a battery of memories unlikely to be the invention of even the canniest con artist. Told without artifice or irony, Mekler's story of multigenerational immigration owes more to coolly composed novels like Lore Segal's ''Her First American'' than to impressive acts of literary contortion like Nicole Krauss's ''History of Love.'' Despite its literary trappings, ''The Polish Woman'' is also a straightforward mystery, littered with clues, red herrings and narrators who always know less than the reader. When Karolina first confides in Philip Landau, he suddenly recalls the warning of his parents, who escaped Poland: ''The Poles were the worst, they'd declared over and over, with the pain and bitterness of personal betrayal, the worst.'' When the two eventually travel to Poland to prove Karolina's claim, they are also chasing these brief flashes of recognition, which tell the story of their shared past better than a tattered birth certificate -- and explain why they have both become phantoms in their own lives. By the time the ending veers into John Grisham territory, Mekler has already transcended plot in favor of uncompromising examination.</p>
        <p>Lizzie Skurnick is the editor of Old Hag, a literary blog.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lizzie Skurnick is the editor of Old Hag, a literary blog.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
