<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Natural, Equal, Universal</title>
    <meta content="Wood2.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Wood2.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hunt, Lynn</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Inventing Human Rights: A History (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Natural, Equal, Universal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Natural, Equal, Universal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GORDON S. WOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wood, Gordon S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INVENTING HUMAN RIGHTS</p>
        <p>A History.</p>
        <p>By Lynn Hunt.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 272 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $25.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A historian looks at the origin of our focus on human rights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INVENTING HUMAN RIGHTS</p>
        <p>A History.</p>
        <p>By Lynn Hunt.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 272 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $25.95.</p>
        <p>ccording to many people in the West today, human rights trump all other claims and values, including those of custom, community and culture; everyone in the world, including every individual in strange faraway places like Darfur, has certain inalienable rights simply because he or she is a human being. As conventional as this claim has become for us, in the entire sweep of history it is quite extraordinary and of fairly recent origin. How did it come about and what has been its history? These are the questions Lynn Hunt has sought to answer in this remarkable little book. Indeed, because she covers so much ground in so few pages and with such clarity, ''Inventing Human Rights'' is a tour de force of compression.</p>
        <p>Hunt, the Eugen Weber professor of modern European history at the University of California, Los Angeles, and a distinguished expert on 18th-century France, says that ''human rights require three interlocking qualities: rights must be natural (inherent in human beings), equal (the same for everyone) and universal (applicable everywhere).'' This conception of human rights, she explains, had its origins in the Western Enlightenment of the 18th century. Although the English had issued a Bill of Rights in 1689, that document derived from the particularities of English law and English history and did not declare the equality, universality or naturalness of rights. It was left to Thomas Jefferson and the American Congress in 1776 to issue the first notable human rights proclamation. But it was the French Declaration of Rights of Man and Citizen of 1789 that had the greatest impact on Western thinking.</p>
        <p>Hunt readily concedes that many people, including men without property, slaves and women, were left out of these declarations of universal and equal rights. Thus ''we should not forget the restrictions placed on rights by 18th-century men, but to stop there,'' she says, ''patting ourselves on the back for our own comparative 'advancement,' is to miss the point. How did these men, living in societies built on slavery, subordination and seemingly natural subservience, ever come to imagine men not at all like them and, in some cases, women too, as equals?'' Answering this question, she says, will help us ''understand better what human rights mean to us today.''</p>
        <p>The short answer is that 18th-century individuals developed a new and profound sense of sympathy, or to use a more exact 20th-century term, ''empathy,'' for the autonomy and well-being of other human beings. We too easily forget how contemptible or nonexistent other people often were in the eyes of many throughout much of history, not just foreign ''others'' but even members of their own society. Madame Du ChÛtelet, for example, did not hesitate to undress in front of her male servants, ''not considering it a proven fact that valets were men.'' For individuals like Du ChÛtelet to come to appreciate that persons of different classes had selves and bodies like their own thus constituted a radical shift in consciousness. This new capacity for empathy is what made the equal possession of human rights ''self-evident.'' And, Hunt correctly contends, that emotion is still the source of our concern for the victims of cruelty and brutality in our time.</p>
        <p>Hunt has no full explanation for how this new sense of selfhood came into being. She devotes one chapter (out of five) to arguing that an explosion of novel reading in the period contributed greatly to the development of empathy across class, sex and national lines. ''Novels,'' she contends, ''made the point that all people are fundamentally similar because of their inner feelings.'' But this heightened novel reading seems much more a consequence than a cause of the new feelings of equality and sympathy.</p>
        <p>Whatever the underlying causes may have been, and they were many and complicated, there is no doubt that people in the 18th century, as Hunt clearly demonstrates, developed a new aversion to all sorts of cruelties and barbarities that previous centuries had taken more or less for granted, including the persistence of slavery, torture and extremely harsh criminal punishments.</p>
        <p>Hunt devotes a chapter to torture and cruel punishments because their abolition helps her better illustrate the complicated character of the changes that took place. Torture and cruel punishments ended, she says, not because judges gave up on them or because Enlightenment writers opposed them, but because ''the traditional framework of pain and personhood fell apart, to be replaced, bit by bit, by a new framework, in which individuals ... recognized in other people the same passions, sentiments and sympathies as in themselves.''</p>
        <p>The 18th-century American and French declarations unleashed ''an implacable logic'' that expanded rights to all sorts of individuals and groups, including Jews and other members of minority religions, slaves and women. In the 19th century, however, rights became attached to particular nations and ethnicities, and they lost much of their equal and universal character. ''It took two devastating world wars,'' Hunt writes, ''to shatter this confidence in the nation.''</p>
        <p>Only following the Universal Declaration of Human Rights of 1948, which ''crystallized 150 years of struggle,'' did rights once again come to dominate the conscience of much of the world. Human rights, Hunt concludes, have now become ''our only commonly shared bulwark'' against the brutalities and cruelties that still afflict much of humanity.</p>
        <p>Gordon S. Wood is the Alva O. Way university professor and professor of history at Brown University. His most recent book is ''Revolutionary Characters: What Made the Founders Different.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gordon S. Wood is the Alva O. Way university professor and professor of history at Brown University. His most recent book is ''Revolutionary Characters: What Made the Founders Different.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
