<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Kind of Car Is a Ford Madox Ford?</title>
    <meta content="Schillinger.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Schillinger.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">James, Clive</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Cultural Amnesia: Necessary Memories From History and the Arts (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Kind of Car Is a Ford Madox Ford?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What Kind of Car Is a Ford Madox Ford?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIESL SCHILLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schillinger, Liesl</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CULTURAL AMNESIA</p>
        <p>Necessary Memories From History</p>
        <p>and the Arts.</p>
        <p>By Clive James.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 876 pp.</p>
        <p>W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A capacious and capricious encyclopedia of essays about everyone Clive James considers worth knowing about in the 20th century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CULTURAL AMNESIA</p>
        <p>Necessary Memories From History</p>
        <p>and the Arts.</p>
        <p>By Clive James.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 876 pp.</p>
        <p>W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $35.</p>
        <p>A decade ago in Berlin, sunk in a plush seat in the Konzerthaus on the Gendarmenmarkt, I sneaked Clive James's ''Unreliable Memoirs'' from my handbag to distract myself from a concert that was being conducted at Looney Tunes velocity. Sinking into the pages, I forgot about the music lovers around me, the chandeliers above and the strenuously laboring musicians below, and slipped into the world of James's hardscrabble Australian boyhood. Absorbed in his account of a disastrous youth-group performance -- he was supposed to crouch on the floor and wait for a large girl named Maureen to somersault over him -- I read: ''She came hurtling out of the back annex, along the corridor, through the connecting door, into the hall, up to the springboard and into space. She drove me into the floor like a tack.'' I burst out laughing ... and was jolted back into awareness of my august setting by 80 enraged spinning heads and sputtered shushes from three rows of German aesthetes. I had failed to spot the warning printed on the cover of the book, plucked from the ticker tape parade of critical praise it had earned in Britain: ''Do not read this book in public. You will risk severe internal injuries from trying to suppress your laughter.''</p>
        <p>Reading James's new book, ''Cultural Amnesia: Necessary Memories From History and the Arts'' -- a capacious and capricious encyclopedia of essays about everyone he considers worth knowing about in the 20th century (including people who lived long before: Tacitus, to name one) -- I was surprised to learn, in his chapter on Dick Cavett, that ''Unreliable Memoirs'' had met with a cool reception in America. Critics slammed it, he explains, for ''trying to be truthful and fanciful at the same time.'' He writes, ''Since I had clearly had no other aim in mind, I read these indictments with sad bewilderment.'' Like the actor Tony Curtis, whom he apostrophizes in another chapter of this volume, and unlike Hitler (though Hitler, he notes, ''told quite good jokes''), James is a natural master of the art form in which ''serious delivery avails itself of comic timing.'' It is a form that isn't often brought to bear on journalism and letters in this country; but lucky for him, James is not from this country.</p>
        <p>Clive James is an unusual beast: a comic public intellectual. Born in Australia in 1939, and raised by his mother (his father died in a plane crash on the way home from a Japanese P.O.W. camp at the end of World War II), he arrived in England in 1962 to find the ideal agar for his mischievous polymath appetites. Absorbing foreign languages and literatures like a ravenous arts-devouring molecule, he spread across England's cultural scene as a television critic, novelist, essayist, poet and nonfiction author, and as a lightning-tongued guest or host on countless TV programs. There is no exact American parallel for the kind of brainy small-screen circuses where James has clowned and cracked his whip; but imagine Jon Stewart's ''Daily Show'' mingled with NPR's ''Wait Wait ... Don't Tell Me!'' and ''The Charlie Rose Show'' -- if the host were, say, Simon Schama. Nor is there an exact parallel for James himself. He suggests that the American who comes closest to deserving the ''comic public intellectual'' crown is Cavett, the former talk show host. His theory on why Cavett's reign did not last longer is that, in the United States, ''the idea that one man could be both playful and serious was never deemed to be quite natural.'' For James, ''playful and serious'' has been the default setting for 67 years. But in ''Cultural Amnesia,'' he experiments with sustained earnestness, mostly suppressing his inner Bill Bryson and letting his inner Bill Moyers have its day. Bryson, it should be mentioned, took his own turn at imparting ''A Short History of Nearly Everything.'' James takes up where Bryson left off: recapping what happened once man rose from the slime and began sauntering into cafes.</p>
        <p>In this book, James means to present seriously the lives and ideas that 21st-century students ought to know about as they set out to educate themselves. Why does this matter? Citing the Bengali author Nirad C. Chaudhuri (one of his picks), he explains, ''A civilization continues through the humane examination of its history.'' Deny that if you dare. The book, you can guess, is one the author wishes he could have skimmed before he left behind his scabby-kneed ''Little Rascals'' boyhood and hit Sydney University in the '50s, craving erudition but possessing little literary baggage. When he first met freshmen sophisticates who bandied the names of revered authors, he was dazzled and daunted. ''What kind of car, I wondered, was a Ford Madox Ford? What sort of conflict was an Evelyn War?''</p>
        <p>Soon he was name-dropping with the rest of them. Unlike the rest, however, he picked the names back up once they fell, and read them until he had understood their contributions. Then he began to encounter and interview the living canon. Meeting W. H. Auden, who was wearing a food-spattered tie, he wondered, ''How could his poems be so neat and clean, and he so otherwise?'' A run-in with Carlos Fuentes in Mexico City taught him the correct pronunciation of the name of the Basque philosopher Miguel de Unamuno, whose writings led James to ponder the link between eternity and modernity. A conversation with Martin Amis, about how, ''no matter how much you admire a novel, after about a year you forget everything in it,'' confirmed him in his practice of rereading much of what he'd already consumed. ''If we can't remember it all, we should at least have some idea of what we have forgotten,'' he writes; that is the intention of this book. ''The writer represents all the expressive people to whom he has ever paid attention, even if he disapproved of what they expressed,'' James explains.</p>
        <p>His cast of ''expressive people'' includes obvious choices like Borges, Hitler, Diaghilev and Camus; personal heroes like the pre-Anschluss Viennese cafe wits Alfred Polgar, Peter Altenberg and Egon Friedell (the author of ''Cultural History of the Modern Age,'' an ancestor of this book); and scores of other luminaries, ranging from the Italian philologist Gianfranco Contini to the modern German littérateur Marcel Reich-Ranicki to Einstein -- that's Alfred, the musicologist, not his cousin Albert. Among 106 profiles, James's Who's Who features only 11 women -- most of them tragic and Slavic, except for Coco Chanel and Margaret Thatcher, whom he twits for having once said ''Solzhenitskin.'' He observes, ''Most things that Prime Minister Thatcher is remembered for saying were not said very memorably.'' He forgets her eminently ''Bartlett's''-worthy remark: ''If you want anything said, ask a man. If you want anything done, ask a woman.'' Saying, of course, has always been James's strong suit.</p>
        <p>Each chapter is not so much a biography of the character in its title as a catchall for the fertile associations the author brings to the name. Thoughts of W. C. Fields provoke a broadside against censorship; praise of Duke Ellington leads to censure of bebop. Eleven pages on F. Scott Fitzgerald contain an attack on Hemingway and an argument for the singularity of artistic genius; 21 pages on Arthur Schnitzler address Richard Burton's hairstyle in ''Where Eagles Dare,'' the lack of solidarity among Jewish men of letters in prewar Austria and the depressing, inevitable exhaustion of romantic love. An appreciation of Heinrich Heine's good manners doubles as a denunciation of the rudeness of fans in today's celebrity culture; a tribute to Paul Valéry includes an aside about ''Malcolm Muggeridge's proclaimed ability to tell which women were on the pill by the lack of light in their eyes.'' As a further example of the whimsy of the collection, James's idol Egon Friedell, ''half genius and half flimflam man,'' gets 19 pages; Trotsky gets 3.</p>
        <p>On the whole, the portraits are thoughtful and entertaining; James takes pains to season them with piquant details and memorable aphorisms to hold the interest of learned, jaded palates. Anyone may recognize Cyril Connolly as the author of ''Enemies of Promise,'' but who knew that he used ''a cold rasher of cooked bacon as a bookmark''? The greenest poli-sci major may know that Joseph Goebbels was Hitler's propaganda minister; but James knows how Goebbels spent D-Day: lunching with a pencil heiress, playing four-hand piano and singing lieder. And why wouldn't the Baroness Sidonie Nadherny von Borutin marry the satirical writer Karl Kraus, despite their long romance? James hints the answer may lie in one of Kraus's aperÃ</p>
        <p>Liesl Schillinger is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Liesl Schillinger is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
