<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fabulist</title>
    <meta content="08wwln--Q4.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/magazine/08wwlnQ4.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-08-07: QUESTIONS FOR NATHAN ENGLANDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Englander, Nathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solomon, Deborah</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ministry of Special Cases, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDF1F30F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fabulist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Fabulist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SOLOMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Solomon, Deborah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deborah Solomon interview with Nathan Englander, short story writer whose first novel, The Ministry of Special Cases, is about to be published; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: You're about to publish your first novel, ''The Ministry of Special Cases,'' about a poor Jewish couple in Buenos Aires whose only son is ''disappeared'' in 1976. Did you spend a lot of time in Argentina researching the book? No. I was first there in 1991, for a friend's wedding and honeymoon. It was a great honeymoon. I've never been married, but I have been on a honeymoon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The short-story writer talks about why he set his firstnovel in Argentina and named his protagonist Kaddish, what nose jobs say about our politics and his hopes for world peace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: You're about to publish your first novel, ''The Ministry of Special Cases,'' about a poor Jewish couple in Buenos Aires whose only son is ''disappeared'' in 1976. Did you spend a lot of time in Argentina researching the book? No. I was first there in 1991, for a friend's wedding and honeymoon. It was a great honeymoon. I've never been married, but I have been on a honeymoon.</p>
        <p>What does it say about the quality of your friends' relationship if they took you along on their honeymoon? They're both happily remarried now.</p>
        <p>For a first novel, ''The Ministry of Special Cases'' seems unusually inventive, avoiding the familiar account of adolescent angst and giving little sense of your own history as an Orthodox Jew educated at a yeshiva in suburban Long Island. It's true. In terms of personal experience, my only other option was to set this novel at the Roosevelt Field mall. But it would still be about the same thing -- community and identity and injustice. It would still be about Kaddish.</p>
        <p>You're referring to your protagonist, Kaddish Poznan, a man who erases the inscriptions on tombstones for a living and is named for the Jewish prayer of mourning. Isn't that a little heavy? I thought about it for a long time. I knew how loaded this name was. There is a long Jewish tradition of using symbolic names to trick the angel of death.</p>
        <p>In the novel, Kaddish's own face is erased when he accepts a nose job for himself and his wife as payment for a cemetery job. We do this to ourselves. People are taking knives and spending a fortune and having their faces altered to look like another face. In America, there is one acceptable face, and it doesn't look like a real face. It looks like the other faces that are not real in this acceptable way. I am trying to say something about the self-erasing and self-policing of identity.</p>
        <p>But wouldn't that be more true in a totalitarian culture? I wholeheartedly agree, which is why I set the book in a country with a military regime. I am fascinated by Argentines because they're shaped by politics in a very deep way. For me, growing up in suburbia, politics was not this invasive force. It's not like I am a different person because of Jimmy Carter.</p>
        <p>What sort of fiction do you read? I love the Russians -- Gogol and Dostoevksy and Chekhov -- and I also love Kafka and Camus's ''Plague.'' I love ''1984.'' I love books about people being trapped.</p>
        <p>Have you ever been psychoanalyzed? No. I would deny everything.</p>
        <p>What kind of name is Englander? Someone must have had shoes from England. I don't know. We all pretend we're not from the Pale of Settlement.</p>
        <p>It has been eight years since you published your collection of stories, ''For the Relief of Unbearable Urges.'' What have you been doing all this time? A novel is not a long short story, and I had to learn how to write one. It was so important to me that my novel not feel like, ''Oh, look at these linked stories that don't crumble when you lay them side by side.''</p>
        <p>You were living in Israel when your story collection came out; these days, you're back in New York. I'm a big Jerusalemite. I moved there in 1996 to write literary short stories and starve to death and have this romantic life -- there was going to be world peace, and we were going to hold hands from Tel Aviv to Baghdad.</p>
        <p>Sorry it didn't work out. I'm an optimistic pessimist. I always think the world is ending, but if you ask me about Middle East peace, I say Jerusalem could have peace tomorrow. Things are hopeless unless everybody chooses for them not to be hopeless.</p>
        <p>What does it mean that you've always received positive reviews? That just brought a whole world of jinx down on my head. Erase that part of the tape!</p>
        <p>DEBORAH SOLOMON</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-08-07: QUESTIONS FOR NATHAN ENGLANDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
