<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Take a Bow, Loser, The Spotlight's Yours</title>
    <meta content="08ishe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/theater/08ishe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy (1929-94)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Grey Gardens (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Christine Ebersole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Ebersole, Christine</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beale, Edie Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EED81F30F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Take a Bow, Loser, The Spotlight's Yours</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Take a Bow, Loser, the Spotlight’s Yours</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood article uses Broadway musical hit Grey Gardens as example of America's sneaky fascination with failure; stars of show feel they are as entitled to respect as their famous cousin Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis; examples of other shows that display affection for life's also-rans cited; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE career as an opera singer didn't quite pan out. Neither did the marriage. As a mom she was pretty much a washout too, unless you consider keeping your adult daughter caged in a filthy house in East Hampton a mark of accomplishment.</p>
        <p>Her daughter's path through life has not exactly taken her to the heights either. A furtive stab at a life in showbiz fizzled quickly. The fancy fiancé got the heebie-jeebies. Now her single mark of distinction is a flair for repurposing textiles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>America, a country renowned as the land that enshrined success as a prize to be cherished above all others, has lately evinced a sneaky fascination with failure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE career as an opera singer didn't quite pan out. Neither did the marriage. As a mom she was pretty much a washout too, unless you consider keeping your adult daughter caged in a filthy house in East Hampton a mark of accomplishment.</p>
        <p>Her daughter's path through life has not exactly taken her to the heights either. A furtive stab at a life in showbiz fizzled quickly. The fancy fiancé got the heebie-jeebies. Now her single mark of distinction is a flair for repurposing textiles.</p>
        <p>And yet these two hapless, hopeless women, the junior and senior Edith Beales, are ensconced in that generally most sunny and celebratory of entertainment vehicles, an old-school Broadway book musical. Serenading audiences at the Walter Kerr Theater eight times a week, they charm as they disarm in the ballad of wasted lives and blighted hopes that is ''Grey Gardens.''</p>
        <p>Behold a new face of the Broadway musical, bearing a wry comic grimace that reflects the new mood abroad in America. A country renowned -- for good or ill -- as the land that enshrined success as a prize to be cherished above all others has lately evinced a sneaky fascination with failure. The losers on ''American Idol'' are almost as famous as the winners -- sometimes more so. Kicked off one contest show, a new-minted pseudo-celebrity becomes a star of the next. Paris Hilton's very pointlessness constitutes the whole of her appeal; no one really wants her to acquire a talent.</p>
        <p>''Grey Gardens,'' with its tale of vertiginous downward mobility, is a cultural artifact expressing the new mood perfectly. The singing Beales, more lovable in the musical than in the documentary film it is based on, embody the idea that glorying in your freakishness or failure may be healthier -- and dammit, more American! -- than scurrying from the spotlight in shame.</p>
        <p>Christine Ebersole's loony Little Edie Beale feels just as entitled to our attention as that cousin of hers who did so well. (You know, Jackie Kennedy Onassis?) And after a strange but lively evening in the haunted house of her soul, we cannot but agree.</p>
        <p>Chronicling the lives of losers, flops and failures is of course not an entirely new impulse, for the American theater (see ''Death of a Salesman,'' or anything by Eugene O'Neill) or even the Broadway musical (see anything by Stephen Sondheim). But its subterranean prevalence in the current crop of musicals is an inspiriting sign that audiences may be turning away from the perky escapism, often trimmed in nostalgia, that has been marketed by so many shows of recent vintage. ''Grey Gardens'' is not outselling ''Jersey Boys'' by any means, but it is hanging tough.</p>
        <p>And it is not the only current Broadway tenant that reflects a popular affection for story arcs that aren't exactly rainbows of hope. It joins ''Avenue Q,'' a snarky comic ode to the satisfactions of quasi-loserdom in your 20s, and ''The 25th Annual Putnam County Spelling Bee,'' a satiric celebration of misfit teens, on what might be redubbed the Not-So-Great White Way.</p>
        <p>The biggest hit on Broadway, ''Wicked,'' strip-mines the escapist cheer from the ''Wizard of Oz'' story with determined ruthlessness, glorifying a certain once-reviled green gal in the process. The return of ''A Chorus Line,'' its mood ring permanently glowing with angst, likewise befits the current mood, as does the revival of Mr. Sondheim's study in marital inadequacy, ''Company.''</p>
        <p>The affection for life's also-rans is equally strong at the moment in the more popular media. Exhibit A in the case for the country's new love affair with flopdom would have to be ''American Idol,'' arguably the most influential showbiz phenomenon of the last decade.</p>
        <p>On the surface this singing contest may appear to be firmly in a triumphalist mode in keeping with the American idea of glorifying the victorious: You too, unprepossessing nobody from nowhere, can be an overnight sensation. And yes, the winner, chosen by fiat of the people themselves, emerges with a recording contract and a future in boldface columns.</p>
        <p>But recall that the template for the show was created in Britain, a nation with a culture deeply suspicious of unqualified success. In the British popular press media stars are shredded like yesterday's newspapers almost immediately after the final blare of their coronation marches has faded.</p>
        <p>This cheerfully merciless attitude pervades the long process by which a winner is selected. In its early stages ''American Idol'' includes a carnival of the most deplorably deluded contestants, some of whom turn their rejection into an occasion for showboating in the media spotlight. (As those who have seen Ms. Ebersole's mesmerizing performance as the profoundly out-of-touch Little Edie can vouch, in her heyday she would have been a choice selection for this stage in the contest.)</p>
        <p>And it could be argued that failing to win ''American Idol'' is a far more assured path to national renown than taking the crown. Would Jennifer Hudson have her Oscar if she had not earned a measure of scandalized good will at her early ouster from the show to fuel her post-''Idol'' career? Possibly not.</p>
        <p>Noting this insidious trend Stephen Colbert, rabid (mock) upholder of traditional American values on ''The Colbert Report,'' recently admonished the country for ''rewarding failure'' by putting the debut album of Chris Daughtry at the top of the pop charts. Mr. Daughtry only made it to No. 4 on the show, Mr. Colbert railed, but he's outselling the fellow who made it to the top.</p>
        <p>Now a rebel cult is taking the worship of the talentless even further this season on ''American Idol.'' With Howard Stern, classic high school loser turned winner, leading the charge, a subversive Internet campaign is afoot to elect Sanjaya Malakar, by most accounts the most egregiously awful performer, as the big winner.</p>
        <p>Consider too that the feel-good movie of last year, the multiple Oscar nominee ''Little Miss Sunshine,'' is a miniature epic of deluded ambition. The father of the mousy tot dreaming of a Junior Miss title was a glassy-eyed promoter of the classically American winner-take-all mentality whose thirst for success essentially casts him in the role of the family villain.</p>
        <p>He had to learn that winning isn't everything in today's America; the ethos of the movie argues that winning isn't really anything. Better to be a happy misfit, like the rest of the family, than a soulless success like the scary ambulatory Barbie dolls who actually win kiddie beauty pageants.</p>
        <p>Even the cubicled lives of office drones have gained a foothold in the cultural marketplace lately, via both the sitcom ''The Office'' and the acclaimed new novel ''Then We Came to the End,'' by Joshua Ferris, about workers in an ad agency fiddling with paper clips as they slouch toward oblivion. It seems everywhere you look in the marketplace of popular entertainment, merit badges are now being bestowed for underachievement.</p>
        <p>Maybe this new mood enshrining failure as the new success is related to the last decade or so of dissatisfaction with the country's ostensible political winners, and the policies they've pursued. But it surely reflects a population embarking on the new century with a perhaps not unhealthy dent in its self-esteem.</p>
        <p>In this context the cheerful escapism retailed by so many Broadway musicals, even of recent vintage, can feel unusually hollow and meaningless. A clear-eyed gaze at the real odds of life can only be salubrious as a correction to the art form's tendency toward unexamined optimism and the mollifying bromide that things will work out forthe best.</p>
        <p>The Beales of ''Grey Gardens,'' which has deepened and sharpened in its move to Broadway this season, are peculiarly apt as embodiments of this American bad mood in the 21st century. Their disappointed lives were tangentially connected to the saga of the iconic Kennedys that dominated the most hopeful postwar years of the 20th. At the end of the musical's first act Little Edie is jilted by Joseph Kennedy Jr., who would go on to die heroically in combat in World War II. And Jacqueline Bouvier and her sister, Lee, appear as excited youngsters in thrall to their glamorous cousin.</p>
        <p>In the years in between Acts I and II little Jacqueline grew up to marry John F. Kennedy and become first lady. After her husband's death she burnished his legend by making the comparison between his brief but idealistic reign and the shining nobility of the court of King Arthur. The connecting tissue was of course the Broadway musical ''Camelot,'' which opened shortly after Kennedy was elected to the presidency. Try to imagine a 21st-century musical paying sincere tribute to the tragic but inspiring story of these Kennedys, and your mind goes blank. The macabre Beales somehow speak more captivatingly to the current moment.</p>
        <p>But it is worth making the distinction between a comic but empathetic regard for people mishandled by life -- an attitude exemplified by entertainments like ''Little Miss Sunshine'' and the musical version of ''Grey Gardens'' -- and a similar but nastier impulse in current culture: the raging tide of schadenfreude that drives the pervasive coverage of celebrity meltdowns and mishaps.</p>
        <p>More than a hint of ghoulish malice spices the frenzied attention to the foibles of Britney Spears, Lindsay Lohan and of course Anna Nicole Smith. Before her death from a drug overdose, Ms. Smith had starred in a reality TV series typifying a genre of entertainment deeply saturated in the human need to see that others are faring far worse than ourselves. Watching shows like ''The Surreal Life'' or ''Flavor of Love'' or ''The Osbournes'' can make us feel better about our fameless existences by exposing the pathos and desperation it often seems to leave in its wake.</p>
        <p>''American Idol'' and the many contest shows it has helped spawn -- from ''The Apprentice'' to ''Project Runway'' to ''America's Next Top Model'' -- manage to indulge the impulse to cheer and the impulse to jeer, which probably helps explain their continued popularity. Those who like to watch the transformative power of fame endow a nobody with an instant halo of happiness can take pleasure in it; but so can those who like to watch train wrecks in various media humiliated in front of a national audience.</p>
        <p>When the musical of ''Grey Gardens'' was first announced, I was apprehensive that it might turn out to be a stage version of those voyeuristic forays into the sad lives of pseudo-celebrities. The 1975 Maysles brothers' documentary that inspired it is a cult favorite, but the camera can be a merciless instrument. The pathos of Little and Big Edie, immured in squalor that is all too crisply captured on film, was for me a little hard to take, colorful characters though they were.</p>
        <p>What saves the musical from being a morbid exercise in secondhand camp is the leavening warmth and feeling its authors, Doug Wright (book), Scott Frankel (music) and Michael Korie (lyrics), bring to the task of chronicling the Beales' unfulfilled lives. Imagining a back story of family strife and disappointment for both the junior and senior Edies, they remind us that life's knocks have a way of warping all of us -- even the most privileged -- into slight (or sometimes extreme) caricatures of ourselves. In the second act, when the Beales have been transformed into a pair of living ghosts haunting a decaying mansion, the songs they sing open windows into their hearts, softening their gargoylishness.</p>
        <p>As absurd as they appear the Beales are comfortingly human too. Their decline from hopeful dreamers to withdrawn oddballs may be extreme, but it traces in unusually gothic style an arc that shapes many a human journey. The lives we live as adults are rarely in neat accord with the heady dreams of youth. The seismic change that occurs in the fortunes of the Beales while the audience is chatting away merrily at intermission is a sneaky metaphor for the stealthy progress of fate in our own lives.</p>
        <p>Few will leave the theater thinking: Little Edie Beale, c'est moi! But everyone of a certain age (say 30) has probably lived through a few of those startling moments when you take stock of your life as it is and wonder: How did I get here, exactly? When did the curves come that moved me away from one destiny and toward another? I guess it all must have happened during intermission.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
