<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Player</title>
    <meta content="Rockwell.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Rockwell.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Columbia Records</org>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Label, The: The Story of Columbia Records (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Player</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Long Player</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ROCKWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rockwell, John</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LABEL</p>
        <p>The Story of Columbia Records.</p>
        <p>By Gary Marmorstein.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 602 pp.</p>
        <p>Thunder's Mouth Press. $29.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the better part of a century, Columbia Records has been a force in music.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LABEL</p>
        <p>The Story of Columbia Records.</p>
        <p>By Gary Marmorstein.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 602 pp.</p>
        <p>Thunder's Mouth Press. $29.95.</p>
        <p>Writing a history of Columbia Records must have seemed a piquant idea, and ''The Label,'' by Gary Marmorstein, indeed tells an epic tale, full of the requisite clashing egos in the executive suite and (figurative) blood on the boardroom floor, with some of the great music of our time as underscoring.</p>
        <p>All juicy corporate sagas offer such intrigue, maybe, but Marmorstein's subject is particularly promising. For a century, more or less, and certainly from after World War II into the 1980s, Columbia was an American household name. It played Avis to RCA Victor's Hertz for a long while, but later seemed to catch up. It and its affiliate labels, especially Epic, shaped, reflected and profited from American musical taste, with the most sophisticated classical (except for opera, which they slighted), jazz and Broadway offerings and a wide swath of rhythm and blues, country and, eventually, rock recordings. The Columbia Record Club spread the company's discs deep into the heartland. And, one might think, the story has a built-in ending, now that the purchase of recorded artifacts is giving way to Internet downloading.</p>
        <p>Like the welter of competing start-ups that accompanies any new technology, Columbia emerged out of overlapping companies with long-forgotten names early in the last century. The big breakthrough came in 1948, when its long-playing record transformed the industry. Columbia boasted some of the legendary executives in the business -- above all the sophisticated, charismatic Goddard Lieberson, but also including John Hammond (who was sometimes given mythic credit for ''discovering'' everyone from Billie Holiday to Aretha Franklin to Bob Dylan to Bruce Springsteen) and the flamboyant vulgarians Clive Davis and Walter Yetnikoff, and ending with the avocational classical vocalist Norio Ohga, then the chairman of Sony, which had devoured Columbia.</p>
        <p>Marmorstein refers to the great social and cultural shifts of the 20th century and to the poetic musings of Evan Eisenberg and others on phonography, the deeper philosophical study of recorded sound. But his real interest lies in chatty anecdotes about the executives, producers, artists-and-repertory men, art directors and publicists -- and the musicians as seen through their eyes -- who crisscrossed through this skein of corporate combining and recombining.</p>
        <p>A lot of work has gone into this book, and all of it shows. Marmorstein, the author of ''Hollywood Rhapsody: Movie Music and Its Makers, 1900 to 1975,'' has pored over the many books and interviews devoted to his key players. He has conducted his own interviews. He has combed through internal corporate memos (although ''The Label'' does not claim to be an authorized history). The result is a sometimes charming string of stories and thumbnail sketches, funny or outrageous or moving. Marmorstein knows and cares about a wide range of music, although he seems less comfortable with classical music and rock, and is curiously sympathetic to Mitch Miller's bullheaded resistance to rock 'n' roll.</p>
        <p>But the dizzying diversity of the tales he is trying to tell has defeated him. Trouble occurs at the outset, when a dogged cavalcade of obscure executives and companies with funny names tumble one upon the other. Marmorstein chats on about minor squabbles among program-note annotators but slights key figures like William Paley and Frank Stanton of CBS. ''At this point,'' he writes ruefully, ''a scorecard might help.'' Indeed.</p>
        <p>After the midcentury, Marmorstein's organization becomes chaotic. In trying to follow the fate of a particular executive, no matter how minor, he loses track of chronology and narrative logic. He repeats himself. He makes sloppy mistakes: Jon Landau did not call Springsteen ''the future of rock 'n' roll'' but, in one of the most famous of rock quotations, ''rock 'n' roll future.'' John Raitt was a baritone, not a tenor. George Szell and Rudolf Serkin recorded the Brahms First Piano Concerto, not the Brahms First Symphony. ''Amberson,'' the name of Leonard Bernstein's company, does not mean ''amber stone'' in German; ''Bernstein'' does. All books have errors, but this one has far too many.</p>
        <p>Marmorstein's style is full of slangy contractions, and while he can turn a vivid phrase, sometimes his constructions are downright weird, or both vivid and weird: ''Waters, in the shank of her own Columbia evening, wrote. ...'' Or: ''Lieberson, whose emotional chambers were rarely left ajar. ...'' Or: ''The 'Roses Are Red' single sailed like a comet up through the charts, its tail hailing the long, lucrative union of Vinton and Epic.'' Or: ''... hauling the stonework of American blues across the Atlantic to erect monuments of guitar-heavy electric R&amp;B.''</p>
        <p>Successful corporate histories tend to focus on one dominant personality, or a clash between two or three. Marmorstein has such a figure in Goddard Lieberson, who could use a comprehensive modern-day biography. Marmorstein respects him as the visionary he was but seems to hold him at arm's length, offended by what he (or some of his interviewees) sees as Lieberson's snobbery.</p>
        <p>The story of Columbia is that of so many corporations, and not just in entertainment. From technological wizards to hustling capitalist dreamers to artistic visionaries to egomaniacs to lawyer-driven bottom-liners, Columbia spiraled downward in cultural significance even as its profits swelled.</p>
        <p>And yet, and yet: there are great stories here, and a great story, and great music too, all dimly discernible through the breezy clutter of Marmorstein's prose. Maybe someday, someone will tell that story with the elegance and insight it deserves.</p>
        <p>John Rockwell, a former arts critic for The Times, is a freelance writer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Rockwell, a former arts critic for The Times, is a freelance writer.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
