<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jolly Good Show  Or Was It?; Those Plummy Tones Don't Work, Except When They Do</title>
    <meta content="08bran" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EFD81F30F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jolly Good Show  Or Was It?; Those Plummy Tones Don't Work, Except When They Do</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley article discusses effects of British actors' accents on American audiences; advantages and disadvantages of accent explored; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COULD it be that the mere presence of an English accent is enough to bewitch American audiences into overrating performances by British actors? That's the cheeky suggestion made recently by the British actor, novelist, critic and all-around cultural Renaissance guy Stephen Fry. ''I shouldn't be saying this -- high treason really -- but I sometimes wonder if Americans aren't fooled by our accent into detecting a brilliance that may not really be there,'' he told the British magazine Radio Times. ''I mean, would they notice if Jeremy Irons or Judi Dench gave a bad performance? Not that those two paragons ever would, but it's worth considering.''</p>
        <p>Blimey, that's food for thought, as is this: ''When American TV and movies call for a twist of limey in their cocktail, it's usually a character they're after -- supervillain, emotionally constipated academic, effete eccentric, that kind of thing.'' He may be on to something there. After all, didn't the creators of the three-part ''Die Hard'' franchise twice reach out for Britons -- Mr. Irons and Alan Rickman -- to play foils both evil and classy enough to square off against Bruce Willis?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COULD it be that the mere presence of an English accent is enough to bewitch American audiences into overrating performances by British actors? That's the cheeky suggestion made recently by the British actor, novelist, critic and all-around cultural Renaissance guy Stephen Fry. ''I shouldn't be saying this -- high treason really -- but I sometimes wonder if Americans aren't fooled by our accent into detecting a brilliance that may not really be there,'' he told the British magazine Radio Times. ''I mean, would they notice if Jeremy Irons or Judi Dench gave a bad performance? Not that those two paragons ever would, but it's worth considering.''</p>
        <p>Blimey, that's food for thought, as is this: ''When American TV and movies call for a twist of limey in their cocktail, it's usually a character they're after -- supervillain, emotionally constipated academic, effete eccentric, that kind of thing.'' He may be on to something there. After all, didn't the creators of the three-part ''Die Hard'' franchise twice reach out for Britons -- Mr. Irons and Alan Rickman -- to play foils both evil and classy enough to square off against Bruce Willis?</p>
        <p>Clearly the game is afoot, as one of Mr. Fry's countrymen might put it. So in the same puckish spirit as Mr. Fry's provocation, three critics for The Times were asked to weigh in on the state of linguistic fair play in theater, film and television.</p>
        <p>I WAS surprised to discover that quantum mechanics sounds sexier without an Oxbridge accent. This revelation came to me, somewhat to my mortification, when Michael Frayn's ''Copenhagen,'' a play about the atomic physicists Niels Bohr and Werner Heisenberg, opened on Broadway in 2000.</p>
        <p>After seeing the London production of the same work at the National Theater a year and a half earlier, I had written a furrowed-brow essay about how much better the British theater was at presenting intellectually challenging dramas than its American counterpart. And yet while the London version of ''Copenhagen'' left me admiring and respectful, the American one blew me away.</p>
        <p>What was the difference? It was the same script, same recondite subject matter, same director (Michael Blakemore). But the three members of the Broadway cast -- Philip Bosco, Michael Cumpsty and Blair Brown -- were all veterans of the New York stage. When they spoke, they didn't sound as pretty, crisp or unassailably confident as their London counterparts.</p>
        <p>And this was where they had the edge. A play that in London had registered as a cool concerto of an essay, impeccably modulated and dispassionate, had become a fiery, sometimes savage battle of wills.</p>
        <p>The mellifluousness associated with an education from the Royal Academy of Dramatic Arts in London may be music to the ears of many theatergoing Americans. (So silken, so stately, so, well, so darned cultured.) But it can also be a handicap, allowing an actor to coast on the surface of poetic writing when he should be digging beneath it.</p>
        <p>I thought of this again when I saw Bill Irwin in the 2005 revival of Edward Albee's ''Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?'' on Broadway. Mr. Irwin was playing George, the history professor, a part I had first seen portrayed by Richard Burton on screen. I wasn't aware of how indelibly Burton's lyrical cadences had imprinted themselves on my memory, until I heard Mr. Irwin tear them apart.</p>
        <p>Burton's crushed-velvet intonations had conjured an irresistibly smoky despair. But Mr. Irwin's variety of tone, which could convincingly accommodate shrillness and the occasional stutter, created a sharply detailed character anatomy, as opposed to Burton's impressionist portrait.</p>
        <p>Of course there are some plays that cry out for the cut-glass shimmer of old-style British actors, or at least for people who can do a fair impression of one. Noël Coward demands the voice of Mayfair. (Try saying ''Don't quibble, Sibyl'' without the requisite plumminess.) But I'm not just talking about BBC-style Received Pronunciation. Many of Harold Pinter's characters are working class, and Americans seem to have the hardest time of all in conveying the singular rhythms of Pinterspeak.</p>
        <p>Shakespeare can be spoken any which way, as far as I'm concerned, as long as the voices are clear and audible and the speakers truly understand the text. British actors are generally at an advantage here, by virtue of a classical training that does not presume that artificial amplification will always be available.</p>
        <p>But it doesn't necessarily take a Briton to do justice to Tom Stoppard, whose dialogue is replete with tongue twisters and intellectual rhapsodies. Like Mr. Frayn's ''Copenhagen,'' ''The Coast of Utopia,'' Mr. Stoppard's sprawling trilogy about philosophizing Russian revolutionaries, is more exciting in New York (at Lincoln Center, where it runs through mid-May) than it was at the National in London.</p>
        <p>Granted, in the London production everyone seemed to be more on the same page, or reading from the same sheet music. The American cast (which includes the odd Briton, Canadian and Irishman) is more eclectic, more emphatic and less nuanced. Which is sometimes just what British erudition needs to acquire the racing pulse that makes theater come alive.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
