<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Mommies</title>
    <meta content="Roiphe.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/books/review/Roiphe.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Homes, A M</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Mistress's Daughter, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE1DF1130F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Mommies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Mommies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATIE ROIPHE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roiphe, Katie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE MISTRESS'S DAUGHTER</p>
        <p>By A. M. Homes.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 238 pp. Viking. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At age 31, the novelist A. M. Homes was contacted by her birth mother.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE MISTRESS'S DAUGHTER</p>
        <p>By A. M. Homes.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 238 pp. Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>s a novelist, A. M. Homes has made a minor speciality of luridness. In all of her writing there is a latent sense that a crime has been or is about to be committed. Her memoir, ''The Mistress's Daughter,'' is no exception: it has the same foreboding, the same ambience of barely controlled menace. It opens with the sentence: ''I remember their insistence that I come into the living room and sit down and how the dark room seemed suddenly threatening, how I stood in the kitchen doorway holding a jelly doughnut and how I never eat jelly doughnuts.'' And as Homes moves through her account of her origins, the prevailing mood is that of film noir.</p>
        <p>Homes was 31 when she was contacted by her biological mother, Ellen Ballman. It emerges that her real father, Norman Hecht, was Ellen's boss -- older, married, an ex-football player, with children of his own. Homes tells us that she was adopted by a couple whose own son had died six months earlier. Before they brought her home, ''the trusted pediatrician'' was ''dispatched to the hospital to make an evaluation of the merchandise -- think of movies where the drug dealer samples the stuff before turning over the cash.'' Such details will be familiar to readers of Homes's fiction: a lawyer from ''In a Country of Mothers'' calls the adoptive parents and says, ''your package has arrived and it's wrapped in pink ribbons.''</p>
        <p>Like Bret Easton Ellis, A. M. Homes writes sleek, violent cartoons of contemporary existence, and it's fascinating to watch this novelist of extremes handle the delicate material of her own life. Homes's imagination inhabits the wildest shores of satire, where a bored husband and wife not only have affairs but smoke crack and set fire to their suburban house with a grill; where a wife who is a little angry with her husband after a party cuts his neck with a kitchen knife; where a fat man is envisioned ''chewing on the small bones of a roasted baby something -- chicken, lamb, child.'' There is rage behind this stylish nihilism, and it finds its purest expression in this memoir: the figures in Homes's life often behave as if she had invented them.</p>
        <p>Her biological mother calls when Homes neglects to send a valentine: ''You can just go to the roof of your building and jump off.'' And after she gets in touch with her biological father, he takes her to hotels where they sit in fern bars like an illicit couple. Homes herself lurks in a parked car outside his house and sees a girl pulling back a curtain. (''Is she my sister?'') There is a lot of stalking in ''The Mistress's Daughter.''</p>
        <p>Other, more potentially ordinary moments turn sinister. The needle piercing Homes's skin during a DNA test is ''beyond sexual.'' Describing a book reading, she writes: ''From the moment I arrive, I have the sense they are there -- exactly who, I am not sure -- but I can tell I am being watched, sized up. There is the strange sensation that something else is going on -- there are people here who have come for a reason other than to hear me read.'' The relentless flatness and darkness of Homes's imagination is both explained and exploited in the pages of her memoir.</p>
        <p>In one of the book's more powerful scenes, Homes imagines driving a car into the wall of her adoptive parents' house. She is enraged, but she stops herself when she remembers how much her adoptive mother loves her china. Next, she imagines going inside, taking the dishes off the shelves and then driving the car into the wall, ''though it wouldn't be quite the same.'' It is in these rogue moments of tenderness that one feels her psychological quandary: how caught she is between wanting to live in the house and wanting to smash it to pieces.</p>
        <p>Of course, a situation where extra parents suddenly turn up after one is fully grown lends itself to strangeness, almost to kitsch. Her new mother sends Homes a child's birthday card shaped like a teddy bear and signed ''Love, Mommy Ellen.'' Her new father gives her a heart-shaped locket appropriate for a little girl. Homes agrees to meet Ellen at the Oyster Bar of the Plaza, with all of its evocations of Eloise. The woman arrives in a ratty white fur jacket, and orders Harveys Bristol Cream. That is the last time Homes sees her before she dies of kidney disease.</p>
        <p>In many ways, this book is really about a wild goose chase. There is no epiphany here. In all the moments when some shimmering self might rise intact from the detritus, it does not. In the cardboard boxes with her mother's possessions (which Homes labels with a characteristic lack of euphemism, ''Dead Ellen 1-4'') she finds nothing to provide some unaccustomed comfort in the world, nothing that will save her -- only containers filled with sheet music, unopened bills, phone messages and receipts, some of which she puts in ministorage.</p>
        <p>And then, as if an active part of this psychological spectacle, the second half of the book falls to pieces. Homes begins an obsessive search on the Internet for her antecedents, even hiring two researchers to help her. What follows is a random, frantic amassing of detail. She uncovers biographical fragments about people who are related to her, and some who are not. She muses on the general difficulties of her relatives' immigrant experience. But somehow in this wild quest for identity she loses focus, and in the process, any remnant of narrative control. Where, one begins to feel along with her, is A. M. Homes?</p>
        <p>Still, if ''The Mistress's Daughter'' is not entirely satisfying, if it loses some of its furious precision -- its perverse, artful inquisition into the motives of its principals -- as a document of a flawed, incoherent self, it remains fierce and eloquent. And even some of its messier sections are gripping. Take the chapter in which Homes writes an imaginary deposition for her biological father. It consists of a list of questions running down the page: ''Did you ask your daughter to meet you in hotels? Why not coffee shops? What is the nature of your thoughts about your daughter?'' In its hallucinatory way, this list fairly accurately represents the true plot of the book: the questions Homes wanted to ask, the answers she will never receive. As she writes, ''I will always be something glued together, something slightly broken.''</p>
        <p>She also says, ''I do not want this to be the most depressing story ever told'' -- though one imagines if there is anyone on earth who could write such a story it could well be Homes. But this book veers toward the sentimental, concluding with an unusually straightforward tribute to her inspiring adoptive grandmother. Here the reader cannot help thinking of the ferocity of Homes's fiction: the suburban house going up in flames, the gunshots in the mall. Normally, she is not one to reach for consoling niceties, for flourishes of redemption and images of human endurance. How can the ruthless author of ''Music for Torching'' and ''The Safety of Objects'' allow herself this easy way out of a story that can have no easy way out? It feels false.</p>
        <p>What does not feel false is a sentence on the last page: ''I am my mother's child and I am my mother's child, I am my father's child and I am my father's child, and if that line is a little too much like Gertrude Stein, then I might be a little bit her child too.''</p>
        <p>Katie Roiphe is the author of the forthcoming ''Uncommon Arrangements: Seven Portraits of Married Life in London Literary Circles, 1910-1939.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Katie Roiphe is the author of the forthcoming ''Uncommon Arrangements: Seven Portraits of Married Life in London Literary Circles, 1910-1939.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
