<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHAT'S ON SUNDAY NIGHT</title>
    <meta content="08tvcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/08/arts/08tvcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D81F30F93BA35757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHAT'S ON SUNDAY NIGHT</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What’s on Sunday Night</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>9 P.M. (13, 49) THE WIND IN THE WILLOWS -- He may be the world's most exasperating amphibian. But Mr. Toad, the exuberant spendthrift (played by the British comedian Matt Lucas, above) with a fondness for boats, cars and snazzy attire who is at the center of this new ''Masterpiece Theater'' adaptation of the Kenneth Grahame children's classic, has friends to spare. They include the stern Badger (Bob Hoskins), the easygoing Ratty (Mark Gattis) and the ever-loyal Mole (Lee Ingleby). Anna Maxwell Martin brings up the rear as the Jailor's Daughter, who befriends Toad after his shenanigans land him in prison, and Imelda Staunton is the Barge Lady, who almost outwits the clever green schemer after his prison break. But who can blame the group for their misadventures? As Ratty says to Mole as they row dreamily down the stream, ''Believe me, my young friend, there is nothing -- absolutely nothing -- half so much worth doing as simply messing about in boats.''</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (National Geographic) MIAMI DRUG CARTEL -- Two specials explore the history of crime, starting with this look at the mobsters from Cuba and South America who incited the war over the illicit cocaine trade in Miami during the 1980s. At 9, ''Philly Mob'' looks at the investigators who helped the F.B.I. cripple organized crime in Philadelphia after the murder of the mob boss Angelo Bruno in 1980.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (HBO) THE SOPRANOS -- The boss is back: Tony Soprano may have survived a brush with death, but he isn't so sure that each remaining day is a gift, what with his wife at his throat, his children suffering growing pains, and some of his most trusted allies sharpening their fangs. Tonight, in the first of the final nine episodes, Tony and Carmela (James Gandolfini and Edie Falco, above left) travel to the Adirondacks with Bobby and Janice (Steven R. Schrippa and Aida Turturro, right) for what turns out to be a busy weekend.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (A&amp;E) GENE SIMMONS FAMILY JEWELS -- This is the big reveal of Gene and Shannon's his-and-her face-lifts, which required a total of eight hours of nipping and tucking. Their children probably develop some wrinkles of their own as they recoil from their father's battered visage and worry about complications that keep their mother in the hospital.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (Showtime) THE TUDORS -- In Part 2 of this bodice-ripping mini-series about a young, body-beautiful Henry VIII (played by the smoldering Jonathan Rhys Meyers) and the many loves of his life, Henry considers an alliance with Spain, and Elizabeth gives birth to his illegitimate son.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (HBO) ENTOURAGE -- The boys from Queens (Adrian Grenier, Kevin Connolly, Kevin Dillon and Jerry Ferrara) return for Part 2 of their third season in Hollywood's fast lane and find the road paved with potholes. Vince's hot new agent (Carla Gugino) wants him to do an Edith Wharton period film, while a lunch with Ari (Jeremy Piven) is meant to take the sting out of the split. Meanwhile Turtle plans a birthday bash for Vince, but escalating costs send him in search of alternative financing.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN SHATTUCK</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>9 P.M. (22 , 26) THE WIND IN THE WILLOWS He may be the world’s most exasperating amphibian. But Mr. Toad, the exuberant spendthrift (played by the British comedian Matt Lucas, above) with a fondness for boats, cars and snazzy attire who is at the center of this new “Masterpiece Theater” adaptation of the Kenneth Grahame children’s classic, has friends to spare. They include the stern Badger (Bob Hoskins), the easygoing Ratty (Mark Gattis) and the ever-loyal Mole (Lee Ingleby). Anna Maxwell Martin brings up the rear as the Jailor’s Daughter, who befriends Toad after his shenanigans land him in prison, and Imelda Staunton is the Barge Lady, who almost outwits the clever green schemer after his prison break. But who can blame the group for their misadventures? As Ratty says to Mole as they row dreamily down the stream, “Believe me, my young friend, there is nothing  absolutely nothing  half so much worth doing as simply messing about in boats.”.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>9 P.M. (13, 49) THE WIND IN THE WILLOWS -- He may be the world's most exasperating amphibian. But Mr. Toad, the exuberant spendthrift (played by the British comedian Matt Lucas, above) with a fondness for boats, cars and snazzy attire who is at the center of this new ''Masterpiece Theater'' adaptation of the Kenneth Grahame children's classic, has friends to spare. They include the stern Badger (Bob Hoskins), the easygoing Ratty (Mark Gattis) and the ever-loyal Mole (Lee Ingleby). Anna Maxwell Martin brings up the rear as the Jailor's Daughter, who befriends Toad after his shenanigans land him in prison, and Imelda Staunton is the Barge Lady, who almost outwits the clever green schemer after his prison break. But who can blame the group for their misadventures? As Ratty says to Mole as they row dreamily down the stream, ''Believe me, my young friend, there is nothing -- absolutely nothing -- half so much worth doing as simply messing about in boats.''</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (National Geographic) MIAMI DRUG CARTEL -- Two specials explore the history of crime, starting with this look at the mobsters from Cuba and South America who incited the war over the illicit cocaine trade in Miami during the 1980s. At 9, ''Philly Mob'' looks at the investigators who helped the F.B.I. cripple organized crime in Philadelphia after the murder of the mob boss Angelo Bruno in 1980.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (HBO) THE SOPRANOS -- The boss is back: Tony Soprano may have survived a brush with death, but he isn't so sure that each remaining day is a gift, what with his wife at his throat, his children suffering growing pains, and some of his most trusted allies sharpening their fangs. Tonight, in the first of the final nine episodes, Tony and Carmela (James Gandolfini and Edie Falco, above left) travel to the Adirondacks with Bobby and Janice (Steven R. Schrippa and Aida Turturro, right) for what turns out to be a busy weekend.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (A&amp;E) GENE SIMMONS FAMILY JEWELS -- This is the big reveal of Gene and Shannon's his-and-her face-lifts, which required a total of eight hours of nipping and tucking. Their children probably develop some wrinkles of their own as they recoil from their father's battered visage and worry about complications that keep their mother in the hospital.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (Showtime) THE TUDORS -- In Part 2 of this bodice-ripping mini-series about a young, body-beautiful Henry VIII (played by the smoldering Jonathan Rhys Meyers) and the many loves of his life, Henry considers an alliance with Spain, and Elizabeth gives birth to his illegitimate son.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (HBO) ENTOURAGE -- The boys from Queens (Adrian Grenier, Kevin Connolly, Kevin Dillon and Jerry Ferrara) return for Part 2 of their third season in Hollywood's fast lane and find the road paved with potholes. Vince's hot new agent (Carla Gugino) wants him to do an Edith Wharton period film, while a lunch with Ari (Jeremy Piven) is meant to take the sting out of the split. Meanwhile Turtle plans a birthday bash for Vince, but escalating costs send him in search of alternative financing.</p>
        <p>KATHRYN SHATTUCK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
