<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reyna Discovers You Can Go Home Again</title>
    <meta content="12vecsey" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/sports/soccer/12vecsey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Red Bulls</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reyna, Claudio</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beckham, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E5DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reyna Discovers You Can Go Home Again</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reyna Discovers You Can Go Home Again</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Claudio Reyna is, if you will, the anti-Beckham. In his homecoming to America, the crowds will never squeal his name the way they probably will for David Beckham's calculated arrival in Los Angeles later this season. But Major League Soccer needs Reyna nearly as much as it needs the English import.</p>
        <p>At age 33, Claudio Reyna finally comes home this Sunday, with the responsibility for shoring up a New York club with 12 years of dismal history, not what Major League Soccer ever wanted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Red Bulls’ Claudio Reyna is, if you will, the anti-Beckham. But Major League Soccer needs Reyna nearly as much as it needs the English import.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Claudio Reyna is, if you will, the anti-Beckham. In his homecoming to America, the crowds will never squeal his name the way they probably will for David Beckham's calculated arrival in Los Angeles later this season. But Major League Soccer needs Reyna nearly as much as it needs the English import.</p>
        <p>At age 33, Claudio Reyna finally comes home this Sunday, with the responsibility for shoring up a New York club with 12 years of dismal history, not what Major League Soccer ever wanted.</p>
        <p>Reyna has worn the captain's armband in foreign lands, and as the national team captain all over America, but now he gets to be the instant captain of the Red Bulls only a few miles from Springfield, N.J., where he grew up. On Sunday the Red Bulls -- born as the MetroStars -- will play their home opener at 3 p.m. against F.C. Dallas in cavernous Giants Stadium. Reyna, who bruised his leg in the scoreless draw on the road last Saturday, expects to play, even though the trainers are marveling at the color scheme of the bruise. ''I'm a freak show,'' he said.</p>
        <p>M.L.S. can use an emotional upgrade in the New York area, which would not seem to be Reyna's specialty. By contrast, Beckham will arrive in Los Angeles, probably unable to live up to the blind expectations of an American public mesmerized by the spurious glamour of reality shows. The league would settle for an occasional screamer of a free kick, the one true world-level skill Beckham ever had, even in his prime.</p>
        <p>The New York team has been a disaster from the beginning, when a former Serie A player from Italy, Nicola Caricola, showed a Marvelous Marv Throneberry talent by putting the ball into his own net to lose the home opener in 1996, and then later again that season.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars have brought in star European players -- Roberto Donadoni, Lothar Matthäus and Youri Djorkaeff -- but none of them could elevate the hapless team in New Jersey. Now they have brought home Reyna, who was in Europe during the first years of M.L.S.</p>
        <p>And that's a good thing. Reyna recalls being a callow youth with Bayer Leverkusen in the Bundesliga, watching two older teammates who had gone home to Germany, just as Reyna has now come home to America.</p>
        <p>''There was Bernd Schuster, one of the great players in Spain, and Rudi Völler, who had a great career in Italy, and they would practice hard every day,'' Reyna recalled the other day. Besides, desperate young German players saw their way to a spot on the varsity if they could leave the young American on the gelid field.</p>
        <p>''It isn't exactly the same here,'' Reyna said, diplomatically. ''In Germany, more players are seasoned professionals. Here, guys are just breaking through.''</p>
        <p>As the American captain, Reyna played back in the midfield, defending against the world's best offenses, trying to distribute to his teammates.</p>
        <p>''On the national team, in theory, the players are better,'' Arena said, ''but here he'll have to set up and score goals, be a good two-way player.''</p>
        <p>The coach and the captain came along together, winning three national titles together at the University of Virginia, and shocking the world with a victory over Mexico and an unlucky loss to Germany deep into the 2002 World Cup in South Korea. Then they crashed together last summer in Germany. Arena still notes how Reyna barely missed a goal against the Czech Republic in the first loss, played gallantly in a draw against Italy, before ending his international career on one disastrous play against Ghana.</p>
        <p>Uncharacteristically trying to advance the ball by himself, Reyna crumpled to the ground with a strained ligament, having coughed up the ball to a Ghanaian player who promptly scored. Reyna came off with the injury later in the half.</p>
        <p>''They happened at the same time,'' Reyna said, meaning the injury and the mistake. He played 112 times for his country, and now he is being asked to pull the Red Bulls together.</p>
        <p>''He reminds me of Jeter,'' said Arena, a Yankee fan forever. ''Jeter's not talking about it, but he's doing it. On the field, he trains as hard as anybody. He doesn't cut corners. He sets an example others want to follow. In my years with D.C. United and the national team, let's face it, not everybody does that.''</p>
        <p>Arena added: ''He's taken young players to the side. He goes out socially with them. He's picked up a few restaurant bills.''</p>
        <p>Reyna joins a league that now has 13 teams and 10 separate owners, rather than the handful of wealthy soccer enthusiasts who once controlled the league. The Red Bulls need credibility just as they need a regional rivalry.</p>
        <p>''Eventually, it would be great to have another team in the New York area,'' Arena said, but it would also be fantastic to have a team in Philadelphia or Baltimore, so people could go down the turnpike. We need rivalries.''</p>
        <p>Reyna reminisced briefly about the local derbies (he pronounced them ''darbies,'' British-style) he encountered in Europe. Soccer buffs have their own our jealousies. Yesterday, four friends joined me at Caffe L'Angolo in Greenwich Village, watching A.C. Milan beat Bayern Munich, 2-0, to reach the semifinal round of the Champions League.</p>
        <p>Someday there might be a comparable Americas match between the Red Bulls and a Mexican champion or a Brazilian champion. In his own quiet way, Claudio Reyna is a bridge for all those hopes.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: geovec@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
