<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recliner Inches Closer To the Backyard Grill</title>
    <meta content="12recliner" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/garden/12recliner.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chairs</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">La-Z-Boy Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, William L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DB123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recliner Inches Closer To the Backyard Grill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recliner Inches Closer to the Backyard Grill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM L. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamilton, William L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>La-Z Boy introduces outdoor recliner; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE'S no evidence to suggest that anyone is dragging recliners out into the yard, but in one of the latest developments of what the furniture industry calls a trend toward creating ''outdoor rooms,'' La-Z-Boy has introduced an outdoor recliner.</p>
        <p>The Whitley recliner, priced at $599, is an exclusive at Sam's Club stores. It coordinates with the six-piece Whitley collection of outdoor armchairs, ottomans, sofa and coffee table, priced at $1,549, one of three new collections from La-Z-Boy, also available only at Sam's Clubs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A staple of American homes joins the move to “outdoor rooms.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE'S no evidence to suggest that anyone is dragging recliners out into the yard, but in one of the latest developments of what the furniture industry calls a trend toward creating ''outdoor rooms,'' La-Z-Boy has introduced an outdoor recliner.</p>
        <p>The Whitley recliner, priced at $599, is an exclusive at Sam's Club stores. It coordinates with the six-piece Whitley collection of outdoor armchairs, ottomans, sofa and coffee table, priced at $1,549, one of three new collections from La-Z-Boy, also available only at Sam's Clubs.</p>
        <p>The new lines are characteristic of a growing category that manufacturers call deep seating, which is upholstered outdoor furniture comparable in comfort and styling to indoor furniture.</p>
        <p>The Whitley recliner, with buxom, Edwardian proportions executed in a synthetic wicker weave, has a seat depth of 26 inches and a cushion that is 7 3/4 inches high, more easy chair than deck chair. (Five years ago a standard outdoor cushion would most likely have been half that height or less.)</p>
        <p>The chair is able to recline courtesy of a steel movement tucked under the seat, weatherproofed like the undercarriage of a car.</p>
        <p>But as I kicked back in a Whitley recliner on the floor of Sam's Club in Secaucus, N.J., on Saturday, a few questions came up as inevitably as the footrest. Does anyone want an outdoor recliner? Does the Whitley, which La-Z-Boy believes is the first, represent a pinnacle in the outdoor living trend? Or has deep seating gone off the deep end?</p>
        <p>Jennifer Sievertsen, the vice president for brand marketing at La-Z-Boy, who oversaw the development of its outdoor furniture with Brown Jordan International, the company licensed to produce it, said she thought a recliner -- an uncontestable cocoon of indoor inertia -- was ''not that much of a stretch outdoors.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sievertsen explained: ''The trends indoors have moved to the outdoor arena of the home, so this is quite a logical extension.''</p>
        <p>Chris Carmicle, the president of the national accounts and imports division at Brown Jordan International, had his own explanation for the recliner.</p>
        <p>''This is the hook,'' Mr. Carmicle said of a strategy to interest men -- who do not balk at paying premium prices for grills and other backyard toys -- in going along with their wives' choices of more expensive outdoor furniture.</p>
        <p>Deep seating requires deeper pockets. ''It's the only room in your house your neighbors can see without being invited in, Mr. Carmicle said. ''I'd think twice about putting green PVC stacked chairs out there.''</p>
        <p>In four hours of outdoor living indoors at Sam's Club on Saturday, no one sat in the Whitley chair on display, even after my demonstrations of its ability to recline.</p>
        <p>Fully reclining in the chair felt like lying in a hospital bed: relaxing, but immobilizing, too. (It weighs 82 pounds, not something you jog to the other end of the pool when it's needed.)</p>
        <p>A sales associate said that several had been sold, and that three were in stock. But at $599, he said, the outdoor recliner was ''not an item that flies out of the store.''</p>
        <p>On Monday, Ray Allegrezza, editor in chief of Furniture Today, a trade weekly, confirmed that recliners were still a staple in American homes. But bringing a new generation of them outdoors -- and men with them, ready to recline as though the roof had blown away -- could be an unchanged vision for a changing audience, he observed.</p>
        <p>''If recliners are for guys,'' Mr. Allegrezza said, ''then they're not talking about me.''</p>
        <p>MARKET REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
