<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patriots Face Early Tests by Playoff Teams</title>
    <meta content="12nfl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E5DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patriots Face Early Tests by Playoff Teams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New England Patriots, who established themselves as the early Super Bowl favorites with a free-agency spending spree this off-season, will have plenty of early tests for their revamped roster.</p>
        <p>In the N.F.L. schedule released yesterday, the Patriots open the regular season on Sept. 9 against the Jets, their American Football Conference East rivals, at the Meadowlands, and then play host to the Chargers, another Super Bowl contender whom they defeated in San Diego in the second round.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New England Patriots, who established themselves as the early Super Bowl favorites with a free-agency spending spree this off-season, will have plenty of early tests for their revamped roster.</p>
        <p>In the N.F.L. schedule released yesterday, the Patriots open the regular season on Sept. 9 against the Jets, their American Football Conference East rivals, at the Meadowlands, and then play host to the Chargers, another Super Bowl contender whom they defeated in San Diego in the second round.</p>
        <p>On Nov. 4, the Patriots will play what is a nearly annual event: a game against the Colts in Indianapolis to kick off the second half of the season.</p>
        <p>The Patriots lost to the Colts in the A.F.C. Championship Game last season. The Patriots have the league's third-toughest schedule based on opponents' 2006 records, and they play eight games against teams that were in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>They also have a stretch in which they play four of five games on the road, starting with their first game in Dallas since 1996. But the run-up to the playoffs will probably favor the Patriots, who have three straight home games in mid-December.</p>
        <p>They will take on those challenges with a roster bolstered by the signings of linebacker Adalius Thomas and receiver Donte' Stallworth, among others.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the 2007 season, the Colts' run defense, which nearly undid the team before it steadied in the playoffs, also figures to be in the spotlight. Indianapolis opens against the visiting Saints and running back Reggie Bush before heading to Tennessee, where quarterback Vince Young awaits. In Week 7, the Colts return to Jacksonville, where the Jaguars gained 375 rushing yards last December.</p>
        <p>After playing host to the Patriots, the Colts will travel to San Diego to play the Chargers and LaDainian Tomlinson. On Dec. 9, the Colts will return to Baltimore, the team's original home where they received a bitter reception last January even before they eliminated the Ravens from the playoffs in the second round.</p>
        <p>Plenty of intriguing individual matchups are on the league schedule. The Titans and the Saints -- Young versus Bush -- play in Week 3. In Week 4, the Texans play the Falcons in Atlanta, a game that would normally be overlooked except that it now features the subplot of whether the Falcons stuck with the correct quarterback.</p>
        <p>Their former backup, Matt Schaub, is the Texans' new starter after a trade made clear that Atlanta's new coach, Bobby Petrino, was putting the team in Michael Vick's hands.</p>
        <p>Giants Coach Tom Coughlin, who received a limited vote of confidence by receiving a one-year contract extension after last season, may be on the hot seat early. The Giants play each of their National Football Conference East opponents -- plus the Jets and the Green Bay Packers -- in the first five weeks.</p>
        <p>Then, on Oct. 28, they will face the Miami Dolphins in London in the National Football League's first regular-season game outside North America.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
