<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adam and Eve After Eden And Billie Holiday Too</title>
    <meta content="12rich" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/arts/dance/12rich.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070414T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Joyce Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Richardson, Desmond</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="online_producer">de Lavallade, Carmen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chaya, Masazumi</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DB123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adam and Eve After Eden And Billie Holiday Too</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Adam and Eve After Eden and Billie Holiday Too</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Butler's heyday as a ballet choreographer was in the 1950s, but his presence and repertory lingered for two decades or so. By that time Mr. Butler, who died in 1993, was considered a little old-fashioned. Narrative, intensely dramatic ballets like his were out of style.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Butler was ahead of his time in blending ballet and modern dance, both of which he had trained in, and in his un-self-conscious racial color-blindness. ''John Butler: An American Master,'' which opened on Tuesday night at the Joyce Theater, suggests that there might have been more to Mr. Butler's choreography than was once apparent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“John Butler: An American Master” suggests that there might have been more to Mr. Butler’s choreography than was once apparent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Butler's heyday as a ballet choreographer was in the 1950s, but his presence and repertory lingered for two decades or so. By that time Mr. Butler, who died in 1993, was considered a little old-fashioned. Narrative, intensely dramatic ballets like his were out of style.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Butler was ahead of his time in blending ballet and modern dance, both of which he had trained in, and in his un-self-conscious racial color-blindness. ''John Butler: An American Master,'' which opened on Tuesday night at the Joyce Theater, suggests that there might have been more to Mr. Butler's choreography than was once apparent.</p>
        <p>Part of that may be attributable to the 21st-century spin given to two of his dances by the Richmond Ballet, which presented the program. Anne Sidney Davenport brought a sleek, clear body line and a calmly assertive push to the role of the errant Eve in ''After Eden,'' set to truly musty-sounding music by Lee Hoiby and restaged by Lawrence Rhodes. The pas de deux depicts the conflicting yearning and resentment felt by a post-Garden Eve and Adam, powerfully danced by the guest artist Desmond Richardson, whose smooth integration of pyrotechnical razzle-dazzle and sure acting might well have pleased Mr. Butler.</p>
        <p>Gesture was important to Mr. Butler, the program suggests, though not traditional mime. So much is said in the fluting hands alone, for example, of Eve and of Billie Holiday in ''Portrait of Billie,'' which opened the program. Asha Thomas and Clifton Brown, both of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, have grown impressively since their already strong performances of the ballet during the Ailey winter season.</p>
        <p>But they have good material to grow with in the pas de deux, restaged by Carmen de Lavallade and Masazumi Chaya. What could have been an over-the-top depiction of the triumphs and perils of fame, experienced by an artist whose own emotional fragility colored nearly every song she sang, is here a searingly restrained journey into an abyss. In hindsight, after long years of so-called abstract dance, it is possible to see considerable stylization in Mr. Butler's work.</p>
        <p>He made the dramatically expressive ballet duet, a once-popular genre, into something vivid and probing. There are pleasures to be had in his ''Carmina Burana,'' a group piece created in 1959 for the New York City Opera and restaged here by Malcolm Burn.</p>
        <p>One hearing of Carl Orff's emptily overstuffed score is about five too many. But Mr. Butler's ways of linking and passing along of moving bodies, in choreography influenced by his training and performing with Martha Graham, gives the shifting processionals an absorbing extra interest. Despite an occasional look of first-night nerves and muddied male turns, the Richmond dancers brought life to this classic in a cast lead by Danaë Carter, Igor Antonov, Valerie Tellmann and Justin McMillan. And in the end we are in their debt for this chance to become reacquainted with an artist who, whether or not a master, was an indisputably distinctive part of American dance history.</p>
        <p>The Richmond Ballet will perform ''John Butler: An American Master'' through Sunday night at the Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea; (212) 242-0800 and joyce.org.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 14, 2007, Saturday  A dance review on Thursday about ''John Butler: An American Master,'' performed by the Richmond Ballet and guest artists at the Joyce Theater in Manhattan, misidentified the presenter. It was the John Butler Foundation, not the Richmond Ballet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 14, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A dance review on Thursday about ''John Butler: An American Master,'' performed by the Richmond Ballet and guest artists at the Joyce Theater in Manhattan, misidentified the presenter. It was the John Butler Foundation, not the Richmond Ballet.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
