<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playoff Hockey To Suit Every Fan Around New York</title>
    <meta content="12anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E1D8123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playoff Hockey To Suit Every Fan Around New York</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>WEST ORANGE, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hockey fans in the New York area will see more ice in the next week than they did on the streets all winter. And they don't have to drive on it or even worry about slipping on it.</p>
        <p>For only the third time, the Devils, the Rangers and the Islanders are all in the Stanley Cup playoffs. And for the first time, they will be skating in three separate opening-round series, beginning tonight with the Tampa Bay Lightning in New Jersey, the Rangers in Atlanta and the Islanders in Buffalo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hockey fans in the New York area will see more ice in the next week than they did on the streets all winter. And they don't have to drive on it or even worry about slipping on it.</p>
        <p>For only the third time, the Devils, the Rangers and the Islanders are all in the Stanley Cup playoffs. And for the first time, they will be skating in three separate opening-round series, beginning tonight with the Tampa Bay Lightning in New Jersey, the Rangers in Atlanta and the Islanders in Buffalo.</p>
        <p>In 1994 and 1990 all three teams qualified, but both years the Rangers eliminated the Islanders in the first round (en route in 1994 to their only Cup since 1940, thank you Mark Messier, Brian Leetch and Mike Richter), while the Devils advanced past Buffalo and Boston in 1994, but lost to Washington in 1990.</p>
        <p>But since 1994, the Devils have won the Stanley Cup three times -- in 1995, 2000 and 2003. And of the three New York-area teams, they have the best chance to win it again this year for what is always the best reason: in Martin Brodeur, the Devils have hockey's best goaltender. And one of the best in National Hockey League history.</p>
        <p>Brodeur deserves to be bronzed in the Hockey Hall of Fame with his idol, Patrick Roy, and the best goaltenders of half a century ago -- Terry Sawchuk, Jacques Plante and Glenn Hall.</p>
        <p>For all his regular-season success as a two-time Vézina Trophy winner and as a prime candidate for the Hart Trophy as this season's league's most valuable player, Brodeur has been even better in the playoffs. With an 89-64 record over his 153 games, he has a dazzling 1.89 goals-against average with 21 shutouts and a .921 save percentage.</p>
        <p>Three more shutouts and Brodeur would surpass Roy's record 23. Brodeur already has the record for the most shutouts in a playoff year, seven (in 2003), and he's the only goaltender to have twice had three shutouts in one playoff series (in five games against Boston in the 1995 conference quarterfinals, and in seven games against Anaheim in the 2003 finals).</p>
        <p>Against Tampa Bay in the conference semifinals four years ago, the Devils won in five games, with a 14-8 edge in goals, on their way to their third Cup. But this time the Lightning arrives with two dangerous scorers, center Vincent Lecavalier, who had 52 goals in the regular season to lead the league, and his right wing, Martin St. Louis, who was tied for fifth with 43.</p>
        <p>''This time of year,'' Brodeur said yesterday at South Mountain Arena, where the Devils practice, ''you start paying more attention to details. To the other team's personnel, their power play, their set plays and to things like when Lecavalier is behind the net. He likes to make plays from behind the net like Wayne Gretzky did, but he's bigger.''</p>
        <p>To deter Lecavalier and St. Louis, the Devils will depend on their line of center John Madden and wings Jay Pandolfo and Sergei Brylin.</p>
        <p>''It's important for us to be aware of where they are all over the ice,'' Madden said. ''You've got to play 'em physical, got to play 'em smart.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur is not infallible, of course. Last year, the Devils were eliminated in five games in the conference semifinals by the Carolina Hurricanes, the eventual Cup champions. Three years ago, they lost to the Philadelphia Flyers in five games in the opening round. But Roy, Sawchuk, Plante and Hall didn't win all their playoff games.</p>
        <p>After their sad seven-year drought without a playoff berth, the Rangers were swept by the Devils in last year's opening round, but they appear stronger this time. Their goaltender, Henrik Lundqvist, doesn't have Brodeur's résumé, but he has been the league's hottest goaltender recently, reducing his goals against average to 2.34 for the season.</p>
        <p>Last year, right wing Jaromir Jagr was wearing down in the playoffs, but he's healthier. The Rangers can also depend this time on left wing Brendan Shanahan, their 38-year-old elder statesman who was on three Cup champions with the Detroit Red Wings, and center Matt Cullen, whose 4 goals and 14 assists helped Carolina win the Cup a year ago.</p>
        <p>Unlike the Devils and the Rangers, the Islanders can't be sure what to expect from their goaltender, Wade Dubielewicz. He has played only eight games since his emergency callup from Bridgeport of the American Hockey League when Rick DiPietro had postconcussion problems, but he helped the Islanders win their last four games, including the finale in a shootout.</p>
        <p>The Islanders were once the N.H.L.'s nouveau riche when they won four consecutive Cups from 1980 to 1983, but over their last 12 seasons, they qualified for the playoffs only four times and never won a series. And in the Sabres, they have to play perhaps the best team in the league.</p>
        <p>But at least all three New York-area teams are in the playoffs again, and in three separate opening-round series. And you never know what will happen because the playoffs are different from the regular season. Fighting is usually minimal because no team wants to be short-handed.</p>
        <p>And there are no shootouts. They play to a finish the old-fashioned way, with sudden-death overtime. Which just puts more importance on the goaltenders.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
