<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stem Cell Bill Clears Senate, and Bush Promises a Veto</title>
    <meta content="12stem" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/us/12stem.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fetal Tissue</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luo, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D8123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stem Cell Bill Clears Senate, and Bush Promises a Veto</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stem Cell Bill Clears Senate, and Bush Promises a Veto</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL LUO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Luo, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate passes bipartisan measure that eases limits on federal financing of embryonic stem cell research; legislation falls one vote shy of what is needed to override Pres Bush's promised veto; Senate also passes alternative measure, supported by Bush, that allows stem cell research on embryos that are naturally dead; scientists say compromise measure would enable little new research, citing lack of consensus in determining when embryo is naturally dead and challenges of generating usable embryonic stem cells from dead embryos; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate on Wednesday passed a bipartisan measure that eases limits on the federal financing of embryonic stem cell research, setting up another confrontation over the issue with President Bush.</p>
        <p>The legislation, which passed 63 to 34, attracted near-unanimous support from Democrats and 17 Republicans, many of whom spoke over the last two days on the Senate floor in often emotional terms about the hope offered by the bill for eventual cures to a variety of debilitating diseases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The measure eases limits on the federal financing of embryonic stem cell research, setting up a confrontation with the president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Senate on Wednesday passed a bipartisan measure that eases limits on the federal financing of embryonic stem cell research, setting up another confrontation over the issue with President Bush.</p>
        <p>The legislation, which passed 63 to 34, attracted near-unanimous support from Democrats and 17 Republicans, many of whom spoke over the last two days on the Senate floor in often emotional terms about the hope offered by the bill for eventual cures to a variety of debilitating diseases.</p>
        <p>''When I think about embryonic stem cell research, I imagine diabetics without insulin pumps,'' said Senator Orrin G. Hatch, Republican of Utah.</p>
        <p>''I imagine patients with Parkinson's disease who sprint rather than shuffle.'' I conceive of patients with spinal cord disease or injuries who stand up and walk again.''</p>
        <p>Polls show a substantial majority of Americans support embryonic stem cell research. But even counting three Democrats who were not present for the vote on Wednesday, the legislation fell one vote shy of what is needed for a veto-proof majority in the Senate. Last year's bill passed 63 to 37.</p>
        <p>After the Senate vote, Mr. Bush repeated his vow to veto the bill, saying it ''crosses a moral line that I and many others find troubling.'' The measure is nearly identical to one he rejected last year, the only time he has used his legislative veto power during his administration.</p>
        <p>Even if the Senate is able to muster the votes to override a veto, the legislation is unlikely to become law. The House version, which passed earlier this year, fell far short of the tally needed for an override.</p>
        <p>Many conservatives oppose embryonic stem cell research because they believe that the embryos that would be destroyed to retrieve the stem cells are human beings.</p>
        <p>The Senate also passed on Wednesday, 70 to 28, an alternative stem cell measure that allows for research on embryos that are ''naturally dead.'' Proponents portrayed it as a compromise that would advance medical research while skirting the ethics issues.</p>
        <p>Senator Norm Coleman, Republican of Minnesota and a co-sponsor of the bill who could face a tough re-election bid in 2008, said the measure, which is supported by the Bush administration, affords an opportunity to ''get beyond the culture wars.''</p>
        <p>But in interviews, several stem-cell scientists said the Coleman measure would, in reality, enable little new research, citing the lack of consensus in determining when an embryo is ''naturally dead'' and the challenges of generating usable embryonic stem cells from dead embryos.</p>
        <p>''We find this to be an absolutely bizarre bill because the presumption upon which it is based is flawed,'' said Dr. John Gearhart, director of the stem-cell program at Johns Hopkins University.</p>
        <p>Currently, federal money can be used for research on only a limited number of existing embryonic stem cell colonies, or lines, that were created before Aug. 9, 2001.</p>
        <p>If enacted, the measure loosening federal restrictions on embryonic stem cell research would make available government money for research on stem cell lines derived from embryos that have been in storage for use in in-vitro fertilization treatments but were set to be discarded.</p>
        <p>''The real question is, Do we throw them away or use them to ease suffering?'' said Senator Tom Harkin, an Iowa Democrat who has been a leader on the issue.</p>
        <p>But Senator Sam Brownback, Republican of Kansas, argued that other avenues of research on adult and amniotic stem cells afforded more promise. Mr. Brownback also articulated the view shared by many conservative Christians that life begins at conception and that even embryos no larger than the size of a pinhead deserve to be treated with dignity.</p>
        <p>''The embryo is not potential human life,'' he said. ''It is human life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
