<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Time, the Shock Jock's Sidekick Couldn't Shield the Boss</title>
    <meta content="12imus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/arts/12imus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839665"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">MSNBC</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EEDB123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Time, the Shock Jock's Sidekick Couldn't Shield the Boss</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">This Time, the Shock Jock’s Sidekick Couldn’t Shield the Boss</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinberg, Jacques</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just before Don Imus infamously referred to the Rutgers women's basketball team on his radio show on April 4 as ''nappy-headed hos,'' another voice could be heard describing them as ''some hard-core hos.''</p>
        <p>That voice belonged to Bernard McGuirk, the producer and booker on ''Imus in the Morning'' for more than two decades, who does double duty on the air as one of a half-dozen supporting cast members. Their task -- and Mr. McGuirk's charge in particular -- is often to give their boss some illusion of deniability or distance. Only then can they express what he might want to say about blacks, Jews, gays or women but perhaps feels he can't, given his stature as an interviewer of the famous and important.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Don Imus allowed himself to wade into deep trouble alongside his producer Bernard McGuirk, instead of watching safely from the shoreline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just before Don Imus infamously referred to the Rutgers women's basketball team on his radio show on April 4 as ''nappy-headed hos,'' another voice could be heard describing them as ''some hard-core hos.''</p>
        <p>That voice belonged to Bernard McGuirk, the producer and booker on ''Imus in the Morning'' for more than two decades, who does double duty on the air as one of a half-dozen supporting cast members. Their task -- and Mr. McGuirk's charge in particular -- is often to give their boss some illusion of deniability or distance. Only then can they express what he might want to say about blacks, Jews, gays or women but perhaps feels he can't, given his stature as an interviewer of the famous and important.</p>
        <p>Among the many striking aspects of this particular instance is that it represented a rare, though hardly unprecedented, occasion in which Mr. Imus took Mr. McGuirk's bait and allowed himself to wade into deep trouble alongside his producer, instead of watching safely from the shoreline. Last night, the lingering outrage over Mr. Imus's comment resulted in Mr. Imus's losing his television outlet; MSNBC, which simulcasts his program, announced that it was dropping it. CBS Radio, his primary employer, has yet to announce any plans to follow suit.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes when you're trying to be funny in the way we're trying to be funny, you go too far,'' Larry Kenney, whose spot-on imitations of the Rev. Jerry Falwell and Senator Edward M. Kennedy, among others, have been an ''Imus'' staple for more than three decades, said earlier yesterday, before the MSNBC announcement. ''I'm not saying Imus did that this time. I'm saying overall that's what happens when you do this kind of humor,'' Mr. Kenney said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGuirk, for example, periodically fashions an oversize FedEx envelope into a cone on his head to do a profane caricature of Cardinal Edward M. Egan of New York. Using a high-pitched Irish brogue (the same voice Mr. McGuirk long used to lampoon Cardinal John O'Connor, before his death), the producer-as-cardinal said on the March 16 installment of the show that ''the only thing Hillary Clinton has in common with the late great President John Fitzgerald Kennedy, God rest his soul, is that they both enjoyed extramarital affairs with women.''</p>
        <p>A former altar boy who is the son of Irish immigrants, Mr. McGuirk, who is in his mid-40s and writes his own material, also had his Cardinal Egan make homosexual slurs about Anderson Cooper and describe Mr. Imus's wife as having multiple sexual partners in her husband's absence. Mr. Imus, watching from alongside Mr. McGuirk onstage in Boston, where the show was being broadcast live, could be seen laughing but said nothing in response.</p>
        <p>As he always does, Mr. McGuirk's cardinal ended his homily: ''In the name of the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghost,'' he said, ''it is Imus on life support we want the most.'' The other players, including Charles McCord, Mr. Imus's news reader, responded in unison, ''Lord, hear our prayer.''</p>
        <p>Similarly Rob Bartlett, another impressionist who often appears on the show (and who has appeared on Broadway) visited on Dec. 4 to do one of his regular characters: Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales, only reimagined as a belligerent illiterate evocative of Jose Jimenez, the Spanish-accented simpleton from the old ''Steve Allen Show.''</p>
        <p>On Dec. 4 Mr. Bartlett as Mr. Gonzalez lamented the intransigence of President Bush, whom he addressed as ''el jefe,'' on a host of issues, saying, ''He don't listen to nothing from nobody,'' before adding, ''I'm talking Helen Keller time here.''</p>
        <p>Neither CBS Radio nor MSNBC has singled out anyone else for his role in the back-and-forth about Rutgers, for which Mr. Imus has apologized repeatedly in recent days. Whether Mr. McGuirk or any other Imus employee is to be punished has yet to be determined. That said, the entire cast will effectively be serving a two-week suspension on radio alongside the host, beginning Monday. Some people have continued to say that the penalty is not severe enough. Senator Barack Obama of Illinois told ABC News yesterday that Mr. Imus should be fired.</p>
        <p>CBS Radio said late yesterday afternoon that Mr. Imus, who earns an estimated $10 million annually, will not be paid during his suspension. Still unresolved, at least as of late afternoon yesterday, was whether anyone else on the Imus staff would lose his pay or what would replace the show in its absence.</p>
        <p>For the most part the Imus supporting cast is a group of middle-aged white men, all of whom do some comedy writing or performing on the show. Sometimes their fingerprints are little seen. For example Mr. McCord, who has served as Mr. Imus's straight man (and often straitjacket) for more than three decades, ghost-writes Mr. Kenney's outrageous monologues as Mr. Falwell and Mr. Kennedy, Mr. Kenney said.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 26, for example, the fake Mr. Falwell said of the N.B.A. All-Star weekend, ''Congratulations to Commissioner David Stern for staging a, well, basically a race riot -- 403 arrests, brother Don, over half for prostitution. Whores, Brother Imus. Scarlet sisters.''</p>
        <p>But if anyone is to make a racial crack, or an unflattering reference to Jews, it is often Mr. McGuirk, sometimes in the guise of C. Ray Nagin, the mayor of New Orleans, who is black, or often in his own voice. He has, for example, been known to refer to the New York Knicks as chest-bumping pimps.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGuirk did not respond to a message left yesterday with his assistant in the Imus office. But in an interview with The New York Times in May 2000 he defended the breadth of the show's humor, even if some blacks in particular might be offended in the process.</p>
        <p>''It's meant to be descriptive, not pejorative,'' he said . ''If the N.B.A. were peopled by a bunch of Romanians, we'd be making fun of Romanians. To not satirize someone just because of their race, I think that would be patronizing and racist in itself.''</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is, I'm not a bigot,'' he said in 2000, before adding that he had ''lived amongst blacks all my life,'' having grown up in the James Monroe Houses in the South Bronx. Mr. McGuirk also said that the co-op in Long Beach, N.Y., where he later lived had a directory in the lobby that ''read like Schindler's list, for crying out loud.''</p>
        <p>''Yes, I arrive at the studio at 5 a.m. each day, but before I do, on my way out I shine my lawn jockeys, and then I stop at the cemetery and knock over Jewish tombstones,'' he said. ''Oh please.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
