<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Says Jury Can Hear of Basketball Star's Cover-Up Efforts in Shooting</title>
    <meta content="12williams" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/nyregion/12williams.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Jayson</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EEDA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Says Jury Can Hear of Basketball Star's Cover-Up Efforts in Shooting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Court Says Jury Can Hear of Basketball Star’s Cover-Up Efforts in Shooting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Jersey Supreme Court ruled on Wednesday that prosecutors could tell jurors of efforts by the former New Jersey Nets star Jayson Williams to erase evidence of his involvement in the 2002 shooting death of a limousine driver in Mr. Williams's home. Mr. Williams faces a retrial on a charge of reckless manslaughter.</p>
        <p>In reversing a lower court decision, the state's highest court found that Mr. Williams's attempt to remove fingerprints from a shotgun, hide bloody clothing and other actions moments after shooting the driver, Costas Christofi, in the chest could be presented to a jury as evidence of a ''consciousness of guilt.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Jersey Supreme Court says former Nets star Jayson Williams’s actions moments after a 2002 shooting could be presented to a jury as evidence of a “consciousness of guilt.”</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New Jersey Supreme Court ruled on Wednesday that prosecutors could tell jurors of efforts by the former New Jersey Nets star Jayson Williams to erase evidence of his involvement in the 2002 shooting death of a limousine driver in Mr. Williams's home. Mr. Williams faces a retrial on a charge of reckless manslaughter.</p>
        <p>In reversing a lower court decision, the state's highest court found that Mr. Williams's attempt to remove fingerprints from a shotgun, hide bloody clothing and other actions moments after shooting the driver, Costas Christofi, in the chest could be presented to a jury as evidence of a ''consciousness of guilt.''</p>
        <p>In 2004, Mr. Williams was convicted of fabricating and tampering with evidence in an attempt to cover up the circumstances of the shooting. The jury acquitted Mr. Williams of aggravated assault and unlawful possession of a weapon, but failed to reach a verdict on the charge of reckless manslaughter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams was acquitted of the more serious charge of aggravated manslaughter after his lawyers argued that the shooting, which took place in the bedroom of Mr. Williams's home in Alexandria Township, was accidental.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams's lawyers contended before the Supreme Court that a new jury should not hear what happened after the basketball star snapped the barrels of the shotgun shut, which they said caused the weapon to go off.</p>
        <p>No date has been set for the retrial.</p>
        <p>Associate Justice Jaynee LaVecchia, writing for the majority in the 4-to-3 opinion, said the ''defendant's post-shooting conduct can support inferences having a logical tendency to prove that defendant was aware that the victim's fatal injuries were not the product of an accident but were caused by defendant's recklessness.''</p>
        <p>She added, ''We hold that post-crime 'consciousness of guilt' evidence is relevant to 'state of mind' disputes arising in criminal prosecutions for reckless conduct.''</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Williams's lawyers and the Hunterdon County prosecutor have been barred by the court from discussing the case. But other prosecutors and defense lawyers viewed the decision as significant in determining how future criminal cases are conducted, although for very different reasons.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said the ruling eliminated certain requirements that had in the past blocked their use of some post-crime actions by defendants as indications of a ''consciousness of guilt.''</p>
        <p>Catherine A. Foddai, an assistant Bergen County prosecutor, who had filed a ''friend of the court'' brief in the case on behalf of the state's prosecutors association, said the ruling struck down one of four tests that courts had used to determine if such actions by defendants could be admitted in evidence.</p>
        <p>But defense lawyers contended that they saw no such easing of the evidentiary requirements. Instead, Larry Lustberg, a member of the state's trial lawyers' association, which had submitted a brief supporting the position of Mr. Williams's defenders, said the high court had sharply broken in this ruling with its past practice of deferring to trial courts in such matters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lustberg said: ''This ruling allows someone to be convicted for what they did after the act in question rather than the act in question. And this is an usurpation of the trial court's role by the Supreme Court, and it upsets the generally agreed upon criteria.''</p>
        <p>In a dissenting opinion, Chief Justice James R. Zazzali said that Mr. Williams's ''deplorable'' post-shooting behavior had no relevance to any potential recklessness at the time of the shooting and was consistent only with the recognition that he had ''made a tragic and stupid mistake.'' The chief justice also said that the actions were more likely to prejudice the jury than to provide evidence of the events surrounding the shooting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
