<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Have No Defense for Pérez's Seven Ball Fours</title>
    <meta content="12mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/sports/baseball/12mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pérez, Oliver</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D8123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Have No Defense for Pérez's Seven Ball Fours</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Have No Defense for Pérez’s Seven Ball Fours</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID PICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Picker, David</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oliver Pérez's last outing at Shea Stadium in 2006 went a lot better than his first one in 2007.</p>
        <p>Pérez started Game 7 of last year's National League Championship Series and left the mound to a standing ovation after he kept the Mets' World Series hopes alive. During spring training this year, he kept his walks to a minimum and locked up a spot in the rotation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Starting pitcher Oliver Pérez walked seven Philadelphia batters and hit one in two and two-thirds innings as the Phillies eased to a victory over the Mets Wednesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oliver Pérez's last outing at Shea Stadium in 2006 went a lot better than his first one in 2007.</p>
        <p>Pérez started Game 7 of last year's National League Championship Series and left the mound to a standing ovation after he kept the Mets' World Series hopes alive. During spring training this year, he kept his walks to a minimum and locked up a spot in the rotation.</p>
        <p>All that seemed a long time ago last night. Pérez walked seven Philadelphia batters, tying a career high, and hit one in two and two-thirds innings as the Phillies eased to a 5-2 victory over the Mets.</p>
        <p>''We lost today and this is over,'' Pérez said, already looking ahead to his next start for the Mets (5-3). ''So tomorrow is another day.''</p>
        <p>Before the season, Jimmy Rollins of the Phillies (2-6) proclaimed that his team was the team to beat in the National League East. Pérez helped them look that way.</p>
        <p>Pérez first pitched himself into a jam in the second inning, filling the bases on walks. But with two outs, he induced a grounder to shortstop by the Phillies' starting pitcher, Adam Eaton, to end the inning and keep the game scoreless.</p>
        <p>The third inning was awful for Pérez and the Mets. After getting two quick outs, Pérez allowed the next six batters to reach base. The Phillies loaded the bases on a single and two walks. But this time, Pérez walked Wes Helms on four pitches and Aaron Rowand on seven, then hit Rod Barajas with a pitch, giving the Phillies a 3-0 lead.</p>
        <p>''At that time, I was just thinking about every pitch,'' Pérez said. ''I know I was missing a lot of pitches. I can do nothing about that.''</p>
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph pulled Pérez for Aaron Sele, who struck out Eaton to end the hemorrhaging. Sele, who pitches in long relief, was solid, retiring eight of the first 10 batters he faced and lasting through the seventh inning.</p>
        <p>After the game, the most popular man in the Mets' clubhouse was their pitching coach, Rick Peterson. About 30 members of the news media swarmed him to find out what had gone wrong with Pérez, who walked no one in his first outing, an 11-1 victory over the Braves last Friday.</p>
        <p>''I think he had two spurts where he had seven consecutive balls,'' Peterson said. ''Then you start aiming and it compounds itself.'' He added with a laugh, ''I wish I had this kind of attention after he pitched his last game.''</p>
        <p>Randolph said he did not think the cold weather and light rain that began to fall late in the game had anything to do with Pérez's control problems. Pérez, who was 3-13 last season and walked 68 batters in 112 2/3 innings for the Pittsburgh Pirates and the Mets, noted that his pitches were not missing by much.</p>
        <p>With Sele holding up, the Mets chipped away at the lead. They cut it to 3-1 in the fourth inning when Moises Alou grounded into a double play with the bases loaded, allowing Carlos Beltrán to score from third base.</p>
        <p>In the fifth, José Reyes knocked in José Valentín from second base with a single up the middle. The fans chanted for both Josés as they ran the bases. They fell silent, however, when Reyes was caught trying to steal second with Paul Lo Duca at the plate.</p>
        <p>Other than that, the Mets' offense was almost nonexistent. Reyes was the only player with more than one hit, and the entire teams managed only five hits.</p>
        <p>''We haven't swung the bats good,'' Lo Duca said to reporters. ''Why don't you guys write about that?''</p>
        <p>The Phillies extended their lead with Shane Victorino's sacrifice fly in the sixth inning and Rowand's run-scoring double in the seventh, making it a three-run game. Both runs were charged to Sele, who allowed four hits and two walks and struck out two.</p>
        <p>The four and a third innings of relief were a career high for Sele, who joined the Mets in the off-season.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to get extended innings and pitch and all that stuff,'' Sele said. ''But hopefully my opportunities are few and far between because that means we're winning.''</p>
        <p>Eaton, meanwhile, seemed to get better as the game went along. He struck out Beltrán looking and David Wright swinging in the sixth inning. Eaton allowed two runs and four hits in seven innings.</p>
        <p>Rollins, who has become a public enemy at Shea because of his comments, also chipped in. He tripled in the sixth inning and scored on Victorino's sacrifice fly. Each time he stepped to the plate, the fans reminded him, with boos, exactly which team they thought was the one to beat.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
