<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thompson Discloses He Is in Remission From Lymphoma</title>
    <meta content="12thompson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839694"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Fred D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zeleny, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thompson Discloses He Is in Remission From Lymphoma</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF ZELENY and LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zeleny, Jeff; Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Sen Fred D Thompson discloses that he has been living with cancer for more than two years, but says it will not prevent him from considering bid for Republican presidential nomination; says he is in remission from lymphoma and decided to announce his condition to gauge public reaction before making final decision; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Senator Fred D. Thompson of Tennessee, perhaps better known as the district attorney on the television drama ''Law &amp; Order,'' disclosed Wednesday that he has been living with cancer for more than two years, but said it would not prevent him from considering a presidential bid.</p>
        <p>For more than a month, Mr. Thompson has been exploring jumping into the 2008 campaign, hoping to capitalize on a perceived void in the Republican field. He said that he is in remission from lymphoma, but that he decided to announce his condition so he could gauge the reaction before making his final decision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Former Senator Fred D. Thompson of Tennessee, perhaps better known as the district attorney on the television drama ''Law &amp; Order,'' disclosed Wednesday that he has been living with cancer for more than two years, but said it would not prevent him from considering a presidential bid.</p>
        <p>For more than a month, Mr. Thompson has been exploring jumping into the 2008 campaign, hoping to capitalize on a perceived void in the Republican field. He said that he is in remission from lymphoma, but that he decided to announce his condition so he could gauge the reaction before making his final decision.</p>
        <p>''I have had no illness from it, or even any symptoms,'' Mr. Thompson said in a statement. ''My life expectancy should not be affected.''</p>
        <p>The revelation about his health, which Mr. Thompson disclosed on Fox News Channel and ABC Radio, seemed only to fuel speculation about his prospective candidacy. He is scheduled to meet with Republicans next week on Capitol Hill and deliver a high-profile political speech next month in California.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruce D. Cheson, a nationally known cancer expert at Georgetown University Medical Center in Washington, said that he last examined Mr. Thompson in February and that imaging scans detected no evidence of the disease.</p>
        <p>''There is no reason he shouldn't do whatever he wants, even if it involves running for president of the United States,'' Dr. Cheson said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson, 64, is the latest in a string of political figures to disclose his cancer. Rudolph W. Giuliani and Senator John McCain, both Republican presidential candidates, are also cancer survivors, and Elizabeth Edwards, the wife of the Democratic candidate John Edwards, announced last month that her cancer had returned.</p>
        <p>As many Republicans voice frustration about their chances in the 2008 election, a cadre of political allies has been vigorously promoting a candidacy for Mr. Thompson. A sampling of polls in the last month have placed Mr. Thompson near the top of the Republican field.</p>
        <p>Representative Zach Wamp, a Tennessee Republican who is heading a movement to draft Mr. Thompson into the race, said the announcement signaled his seriousness about a candidacy.</p>
        <p>''There obviously was some urgency to letting everyone know,'' Mr. Wamp said. ''It looks to me like a person who may very well be running for president.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Cheson said he first examined Mr. Thompson on April 7, 2005, about six months after the former senator had noticed a lump under his jaw. Pathologists at the National Institutes of Health ultimately determined that it was a marginal zone lymphoma, which is an unusual type of a common cancer and affects the immune system.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cheson said that he could have withheld any therapy for months because the cancer was slow-growing. But Mr. Thompson chose to receive radiation to the neck ''because he did not want to have a visible lump in his neck given his high profile,'' Dr. Cheson said.</p>
        <p>When enlarged lymph nodes progressed in the groin and other areas, Mr. Thompson decided ''he wanted to get the disease out of his system,'' Dr. Cheson said. So in April 2006, Dr. Cheson prescribed Rituxan, a recently developed form of antibody drug that produced ''a complete remission.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson, who has weaved a career in the law, politics and acting, was elected to the Senate to fill Al Gore's seat. Later, he won a full term, but did not seek re-election, leaving the Senate in 2003 for ''Law &amp; Order'' on NBC.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, advisers to Mr. Thompson have made inquiries in early voting states, but he has yet to pay a visit. Most Republican candidates are traveling to Iowa this weekend for the state party's annual dinner, but not Mr. Thompson.</p>
        <p>''There is quite an interest to meet him and see him,'' said Ray Hoffman, chairman of the Iowa Republican Party. ''But his people got back to me and said he was still shooting 'Law &amp; Order.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
