<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reinventing the Clubhouse in the Sky</title>
    <meta content="12TREEintro" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treehouses</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Louie, Elaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1DB123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reinventing the Clubhouse in the Sky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE LOUIE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Louie, Elaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Treehouses for adults are becoming more popular and more functional and are being used as hotels, offices and guest rooms as well as traditional quiet place to get away from it all; treehouses around world noted; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Michael Garnier and Peter Nelson organized the first World Treehouse Conference in 1997, treehouses for adults were still pretty rare. ''It was the bolder people who were doing them, the pioneers,'' said Mr. Garnier, who builds treehouses professionally and runs the Out 'n' About Treehouse Treesort near Cave Junction, Ore., where the conference is held each October.</p>
        <p>But that was before an engineering breakthrough developed by conference participants, the so-called Garnier Limb, allowed treehouses greater stability and longer life, and before a spate of how-to and coffee-table books helped popularize them. Within a few years, elaborate treehouses, many costing upwards of $100,000, were becoming almost faddish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Michael Garnier and Peter Nelson organized the first World Treehouse Conference in 1997, treehouses for adults were still pretty rare. ''It was the bolder people who were doing them, the pioneers,'' said Mr. Garnier, who builds treehouses professionally and runs the Out 'n' About Treehouse Treesort near Cave Junction, Ore., where the conference is held each October.</p>
        <p>But that was before an engineering breakthrough developed by conference participants, the so-called Garnier Limb, allowed treehouses greater stability and longer life, and before a spate of how-to and coffee-table books helped popularize them. Within a few years, elaborate treehouses, many costing upwards of $100,000, were becoming almost faddish.</p>
        <p>''It's accepted now that adults can have treehouses,'' said Mr. Nelson, who published four of those books. A partner at TreeHouse Workshop, a building company in Seattle, Mr. Nelson has made up a mantra for some of his clients: ''Of course we can have treehouses; we're baby boomers, and we can have whatever we want, and we can have it now, and we have a lot of money.''</p>
        <p>In the last three years, the demand has reached ''a fevered pitch,'' he added.</p>
        <p>A slight exaggeration, perhaps, but he and other treehouse builders in the United States and elsewhere reported significant upticks in business over that time. This year, Mr. Nelson said, his company expects to build 25 treehouses, up from 10 in 2004. Roderick Romero, a Manhattan artist and musician who also designs treehouses (Val Kilmer, the actor, is one of his clients), will produce four this year, double his output in the last several years. In Paris, Alain Laurens, who in 2000 founded La Cabane Perchée, a treehouse design studio, said he will build 35 in 2007, up from 25 in 2004, for clients in Spain, Italy, France and Portugal.</p>
        <p>As souped-up treehouses have proliferated -- there are now at least several hundred of them in the United States, according to Mr. Garnier -- their designs and functions have become more diverse. ''There was this initial surge,'' said Bill Allen, whose nonprofit firm, Forever Young Treehouses in Burlington, Vt., builds wheelchair-accessible structures. ''Now people are thinking more about different ways they can use them.'' Some of his own treehouses, he said, are used for weddings, tai chi and Alcoholics Anonymous meetings.</p>
        <p>The appeal of treehouses has a lot to do with the calm and sense of connection they can impart, in Mr. Allen's view, whatever uses they are put to. ''They are peaceful gathering places,'' he said, ''really perfect community buildings, for example.'' As much as their charm may seem bound up in childhood memories, they speak to us largely because ''they're so different from the idea we all grew up with,'' he said. The latter-day treehouse, in other words, is a comforting, inviting place: ''It's the opposite in spirit of that members-only enclave, the He-Man Woman Haters Club.''</p>
        <p>A Comfort Stop Along a Virginia Trail</p>
        <p>THREE years ago, when Rachel D. Fowlkes bought a 120-acre farm in Abingdon, Va., she discovered that the Virginia Creeper Trail -- a 35-mile public hiking-and-biking path -- ran through her property. Ms. Fowlkes, the executive director of the Southwest Virginia Higher Education Center, a partnership of eight colleges and universities, saw an opportunity for fun and profit: She hired Peter Nelson and his partner, Jake Jacobs, of TreeHouse Workshop, a builder in Seattle, to construct a 300-square-foot duplex treehouse to be used as a small, singular hotel. Nestled in a pin oak tree 13 feet above the ground and made of fir, cedar and locust, the treehouse may look rustic, but it has a sink with hot and cold water, a microwave oven, a coffee maker, a hot plate, an under-counter refrigerator and a fireplace. A built-in dining table seats two; upstairs, the one bedroom has a bathroom with a shower and a flush toilet. (An electric baseboard provides heat.) Woody Crenshaw, a lighting designer in Floyd, Va., has created soon-to-be-installed lanterns and sconces of hammered metal and hand-blown glass. Mr. Nelson finished the house last week, at a cost of $175,000, and when the furniture arrives shortly, Ms. Fowlkes plans to be the first guest; later this summer she will begin renting the treehouse for $200 a night.</p>
        <p>A California Retreat For Mother and Daughter</p>
        <p>WHEN Christiana Wyly was in high school in Switzerland, she read the Italo Calvino novel ''Il Barone Rampante,'' or ''The Baron in the Trees,'' and was captivated by its story of a boy who climbs into the trees and stays there for the rest of his life. Nearly a decade later, Ms. Wyly, an investor and a director of Zaadz, a sort of MySpace for the spiritual and environmentally conscious set, was still thinking about the book when she commissioned a 150-square-foot, $75,000 treehouse to serve as both a guest cottage and a refuge for herself and her daughter, Viola, at their home in the Santa Monica Mountains in Los Angeles County.</p>
        <p>Designed by Roderick Romero, an artist and musician in Manhattan who builds treehouses under the name Romero Studios, the house, completed in February, is shaped like a Moroccan lantern (to match the Moroccan furniture in the main house 100 feet away) and made of salvaged redwood from old olive oil tanks (the top and bottom are copper). Mr. Romero covered the staircase -- eucalyptus branches fastened to eucalyptus railings and arches by hidden screws -- with resin and salt; when the salt dissolved, it left little indentations, giving the steps traction. Ms. Wyly, 25, said she visits her treehouse retreat daily, to read, meditate and practice yoga, and to spend time with Viola, 4. ''It's a quiet space,'' she said, ''completely silent except for the wind moving through the trees.''</p>
        <p>A Bird's-Eye View for All Seasons, Coffee and a Talk in Japan</p>
        <p>TAKASHI KOBAYASHI, a clothing buyer turned professional treehouse builder who lives in Kamakura, Japan, was not to the treehouse born. ''Japan doesn't have a tradition of treehouses,'' said Mr. Kobayashi, 49. ''There's little private land with big trees.''</p>
        <p>But that didn't stop him from building his first treehouse in 1993, on a piece of land he rented in Tokyo; since then, he has built 25 more, most of them for elementary schools. In September, Dentsu, an advertising agency in Tokyo, hired him to design a treehouse for a Nescafé commercial now running on Japanese television; it shows Mr. Kobayashi and a well-known actor, Toshiaki Karasawa, talking and drinking coffee in the tree. Using driftwood gathered in Obihiro, on the northern island of Hokkaido, Mr. Kobayashi built an oval bird's nest of a house, 12 feet high and 9 feet in diameter, reached by a circular staircase, for about $38,000. The house is located on a field there owned by the town of Kamishihoro, where it remains an enticing, if off-limits, gift from Nestlé, the makers of Nescafé, to the people of Hokkaido.</p>
        <p>According to Momoko Nakai, an account planner for Nestlé at Dentsu, visitors can look but not climb the treehouse. ''The treehouse itself is safe,'' Ms. Nakai said, but ''you never know what happens. People might peek over too far.''</p>
        <p>In Ohio, a House That's Open to Everyone</p>
        <p>WHEN Bill Allen builds treehouses, he does not look for the perfect tree, sturdy with thick, embracing limbs and an abundant canopy of leaves. Mr. Allen's nonprofit company, Forever Young Treehouses in Burlington, Vt., founded in 2002, designs its houses to be accessible to handicapped and chronically ill children, and ''the first thing we look for is the ground dropping away'' from the start of the access ramp, he said, so that the ramp doesn't need to climb too high to reach the house. He also likes to build in a grove of trees so the ramp can meander from tree to tree.</p>
        <p>Everybody's Treehouse, which cost $450,000 and which Mr. Allen completed in January in the Mount Airy Forest park in Cincinnati, is a typical Forever Young project. Its 160-foot ramp winds among 14 trees (red and white oaks, maples and ash) as it climbs 15 feet to a 2,000-square-foot house with two asymmetrical cedar-shingle roofs that give it a Hansel-and-Gretel look. The structure is made of tongue-and-groove pine boards with an ipê-wood deck and has eight windows; most start 32 inches from the floor, an ideal height for wheelchair occupants. ''For a kid in a wheelchair,'' Mr. Allen said, ''it gives a different perspective of what the world looks like, of what a tree looks like, of what a forest looks like.''</p>
        <p>A Bed Among the Branches In the South of France</p>
        <p>ALAIN LAURENS, a former chairman of a major French advertising agency, left his position there in 1999 to found La Cabane Perchée, a Paris-based studio that designs and builds treehouses. The firm's projects are unusually elegant by treehouse standards, but none so much so as Le Lit Perché, a roomy 42-square-foot bed made from six segments of mattress perched on a red cedar platform within a railing of slender steel cables. Mr. Laurens, 59, built the first one in 2005, 24 feet above the ground at his own country house in Bonnieux, in the South of France, and has since built 12 more for customers.</p>
        <p>Le Lit Perché, which costs $15,000, ''is for people to sleep in trees'' without having to spend the money to build an entire treehouse, Mr. Laurens said. It features a pulley system that raises and lowers a basket that can be filled with food, wine or other supplies. For those who find being suspended in mid-air (or completely exposed to the elements) scary, and not conducive to romance, the bed can be placed as low as six feet off the ground.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
