<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Met's Hot Pursuit of Theater Delivers a Drama of Its Own</title>
    <meta content="12gelb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/arts/music/12gelb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Metropolitan Opera</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gelb, Peter</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Swenson, Ruth Ann</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EEDB123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Met's Hot Pursuit of Theater Delivers a Drama of Its Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Met’s Hot Pursuit of Theater Delivers a Drama of Its Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Gelb, the new general manager of the Metropolitan Opera, is determined to enhance the dramatic component of opera at the house by hiring strong directors from the world of theater and film and by cultivating singers who are not just top-notch vocalists but compelling actors.</p>
        <p>Singing must come first in opera, and Mr. Gelb has emphasized that he of all people understands this. But if his determination to raise the dramatic impact of opera has caused him to undervalue a singer as fine as the soprano Ruth Ann Swenson, then Mr. Gelb may be going too far in his campaign to make the Met a hotspot of musical drama.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Gelb, the new general manager of the Metropolitan Opera, may be going too far in his campaign to make the Met a hotspot of musical drama.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peter Gelb, the new general manager of the Metropolitan Opera, is determined to enhance the dramatic component of opera at the house by hiring strong directors from the world of theater and film and by cultivating singers who are not just top-notch vocalists but compelling actors.</p>
        <p>Singing must come first in opera, and Mr. Gelb has emphasized that he of all people understands this. But if his determination to raise the dramatic impact of opera has caused him to undervalue a singer as fine as the soprano Ruth Ann Swenson, then Mr. Gelb may be going too far in his campaign to make the Met a hotspot of musical drama.</p>
        <p>This issue was on the minds of many in the audience on Friday, when Ms. Swenson sang the demanding role of Cleopatra in the first performance this season of Handel's ''Giulio Cesare,'' a revival of a fussy and ineffective 1988 production by John Copley. The ecstatic ovation Ms. Swenson received that night, complete with confetti showers of ripped-up program books, was not just a reward for an impressive performance.</p>
        <p>The audience was expressing its support for Ms. Swenson's courage and dedication. In an interview with The New York Times prior to the performance Ms. Swenson, 47, had spoken of her battle with breast cancer. Just six weeks earlier she had finished a round of chemotherapy. You can only imagine how such debilitating treatments impact the delicate mechanism of voice production.</p>
        <p>But the ovation was also something of a ''take that'' to Mr. Gelb. In the Times interview Ms. Swenson asserted that he has reservations about her work. Next year she is scheduled to sing only five performances of Violetta in Verdi's ''Traviata.'' (Another four have been given to Renée Fleming.) And after that, that's it for this soprano who has served the company loyally since her 1991 debut.</p>
        <p>Despite tiny vocal glitches that may have been due to the lingering effects of chemotherapy, Ms. Swenson sang exquisitely that night, with agile coloratura passagework, luminous sound and lyrical grace. During the curtain calls she looked understandably emotional as she basked in the audience's bravos. (She next sings the role in tomorrow night's performance at the Met.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Gelb is running an art house that is also a tough and expensive business. It is certainly true that in the coloratura soprano repertory Ms. Swenson has some stiff competition these days from exciting artists who have proved popular with Met audiences. Among them are the petite French soprano Natalie Dessay, who began her career as an actress and is riveting onstage; the gorgeous Russian superstar Anna Netrebko, who utterly dominated the Met's recent presentation of Bellini's ''Puritani''; and the vivacious German coloratura Diana Damrau, who, as the alluring sorceress Aithra in the company's premier production of ''Die Ägyptische Helena,'' a Strauss rarity, stole the show, some said, from the star, Deborah Voigt. (That was not my take; I thought Ms. Voigt was outstanding.) It is understandable that Mr. Gelb would want to court such dazzling performers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Swenson does not have a glamorous persona, nor is she the most involving actress. Still, she has a lovely and unaffected stage presence. And, what matters most, she sings beautifully.</p>
        <p>Many coloratura sopranos develop a very bright, sometimes hard-edged quality in their sound. This almost goes with the vocal territory, which requires constant flights into the high soprano range and the ability to dispatch virtuosic runs and roulades.</p>
        <p>Ms. Swenson's voice has always been creamy and luscious. She sings with healthy technique, supporting her sound from the diaphragm, which allows her to fill a house the size of the Met with seeming effortlessness.</p>
        <p>The rap on Ms. Swenson, though, has been that for all the beauty of her singing she can be tepid and bland, and that her diction sometimes lacks clarity. As Cleopatra she did not really convey the calculating ruthlessness of the manipulative queen, though she brought tenderness and melancholic beauty to the character's soul-searching arias.</p>
        <p>In a role that suits her pleasant and guileless stage persona, Ms. Swenson can be close to ideal, for example, her innocent and heart-winning portrayal of Gilda in Verdi's ''Rigoletto.'' Last season she was an adorable, sassy and vocally splendid Adina in Donizetti's ''Elisir d'Amore.''</p>
        <p>Of course you could argue that Ms. Swenson is exactly the kind of artist who would benefit most by working with the creative stage directors that Mr. Gelb has been bringing to the Met. In assessing the work of opera directors, it is easy to be swayed by the imagery and scenic impact of the production. More attention should be paid to how effective directors are at coaxing portrayals from the cast.</p>
        <p>Take the Met's production of Mozart's ''Don Giovanni'' that the actress and director Marthe Keller introduced in 2004. Ms. Keller elicited nuanced and rich portrayals from the singers. The excellent soprano Christine Goerke, who sang Donna Elvira, was especially grateful for Ms. Keller's sensitive direction.</p>
        <p>Ms. Goerke often jokes that she is ''built like a linebacker.'' Yet in the right production she can be a riveting actress with Junoesque charisma. Though Donna Elvira is prone to hysterical fits and obsessions over Giovanni, Ms. Keller sees her as a vulnerable and sympathetic character, qualities that came through in Ms. Goerke's wrenching portrayal.</p>
        <p>Though Ms. Swenson has been willing to take risks when working with trustworthy directors, she has had disappointments in this regard at the Met. She was hoping that her portrayal of the touchstone title role in the Met's new staging of Donizetti's ''Lucia di Lammermoor'' in 1998 would be a career milestone. But Nicolas Joël's production was muddled and clunky. She sang very well, but she seemed uncomfortable. The Met will open next season with a new ''Lucia'' by the acclaimed stage director Mary Zimmerman. But Ms. Dessay is slated to sing the title role.</p>
        <p>The prospect of Ms. Dessay's Lucia in a Zimmerman production is enticing. Still, your heart goes out to Ms. Swenson. The new star coloraturas, like all opera singers, have their share of detractors. Some fault Ms. Netrebko for what they believe is unsure command of coloratura technique and Bel Canto style; others complain that she overacts. Some critics thought Ms. Damrau's Rosina in Bartlett Sher's inventive new production of Rossini's ''Barbiere di Siviglia'' this season was too willful and intense; a sweet but resolute young woman emerged as a quarrelsome spitfire. While I do not really agree, the criticisms are not unfair.</p>
        <p>The point is that passionate opera buffs will always disagree about singers. Surely there is room at a company like the Met for a wide range of artists. The sheer beauty and dependability of Ms. Swenson's singing should not be taken for granted. Mr. Gelb said he has not ruled out inviting her to return if an appropriate role comes along. Ms. Swenson is not counting on this. You cannot blame her.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
