<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arrest Children For Bad Behavior?</title>
    <meta content="l12herbert" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Avon Park (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buchholz, Sandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yatvin, Joanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gelberg, Denise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4D9123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arrest Children For Bad Behavior?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letters from Sandra Buchholz, Joanne Yatvin and Denise Gelberg agree with Bob Herbert's April 9 column deploring arrest of Florida child who was having tantrum in class</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''6-Year-Olds Under Arrest,'' by Bob Herbert (column, April 9), about the arrest of a 6-year-old girl in Florida:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''6-Year-Olds Under Arrest,'' by Bob Herbert (column, April 9), about the arrest of a 6-year-old girl in Florida:</p>
        <p>I am a psychologist who has worked with children both in and out of a school system from preschool through high school. I am also a mother and a grandmother. I have seen children of all ages and sizes have anxiety attacks, tantrums and wild, uncontrollable behaviors.</p>
        <p>Never in my very long career has it even been suggested that the way to deal with these situations is to further traumatize the child by calling in the police.</p>
        <p>There are many ways of helping children in the throes of a panic attack to calm them down and help them regain control. I strongly feel that this is a case of child abuse, of endangering the welfare of a child, psychological as well as physical, as well as of gross incompetence and meanness of spirit.</p>
        <p>Sandra Buchholz  Little Neck, Queens, April 9, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a former school principal, I witnessed many children's tantrums in busy classrooms. Although we sometimes had to ask parents to come and get their children, we never called the police, and no child or adult ever got hurt.</p>
        <p>Children in the middle of a tantrum are often afraid of their own violence, and skillful teachers know how to calm them with quiet talk and caring gestures. If there is a need for apologies or reparations, the principal can discuss that with children afterward and let them decide how to set things right.</p>
        <p>Once, a middle-school boy was sent to my office for yelling out in anger and throwing his books on the floor. Since he was clearly seething about some injustice he wasn't ready to explain, I suggested that he go into the office lavatory and yell as loud and as long as he wanted. He went there and followed my advice.</p>
        <p>A few minutes later, he came out, completely calm, and said he wanted to go back to class. I let him go, and we were able to resolve the incident rationally the next day.</p>
        <p>Joanne Yatvin  Portland, Ore., April 9, 2007</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a 30-year teaching veteran of the primary grades, I can remember a time when it was virtually unheard of to have a small child scream, hit and kick in class, to be so upset that he or she could not be calmed by the soothing voice or sympathetic ear of a teacher. But over the last several years, it has regrettably become a regular occurrence.</p>
        <p>But ultimately, rather than haul these distressed children off to jail, should we not collectively -- as a society -- seek the reasons for their disturbing behavior?</p>
        <p>Denise Gelberg  Ithaca, N.Y., April 9, 2007</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
