<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain Says Democrats Play 'Small Politics' Over Iraq</title>
    <meta content="12mccain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain Says Democrats Play 'Small Politics' Over Iraq</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>LEXINGTON, Va., April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain accuses his potential Democratic presidential rivals of playing 'small politics' by opposing war in Iraq; says withdrawal would lead to chaos across Middle East, embolden Al Qaeda and expose US to another 9/11 or worse; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John McCain of Arizona accused his potential Democratic presidential rivals on Wednesday of playing ''small politics'' by opposing the war in Iraq, saying withdrawal would lead to chaos across the Middle East, embolden Al Qaeda and expose the United States to ''another 9/11 -- or worse.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, a Republican whose presidential candidacy has been shaken by his support of the war, spoke in vivid and even apocalyptic terms as he issued a forceful call for the United States to press on in Iraq. And he repeatedly portrayed Democrats as acting out of political opportunism -- and Republicans as acting on principle -- in the debate over the war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator John McCain of Arizona accused his potential Democratic presidential rivals on Wednesday of playing ''small politics'' by opposing the war in Iraq, saying withdrawal would lead to chaos across the Middle East, embolden Al Qaeda and expose the United States to ''another 9/11 -- or worse.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain, a Republican whose presidential candidacy has been shaken by his support of the war, spoke in vivid and even apocalyptic terms as he issued a forceful call for the United States to press on in Iraq. And he repeatedly portrayed Democrats as acting out of political opportunism -- and Republicans as acting on principle -- in the debate over the war.</p>
        <p>''America has a vital interest in preventing the emergence of Iraq as a Wild West for terrorists, similar to Afghanistan before 9/11,'' he said in a speech here at the Virginia Military Institute before hundreds of cadets clad in gray-and-white uniforms. ''By leaving Iraq before there is a stable Iraqi governing authority, we risk precisely this, and the potential consequence of allowing terrorists sanctuary in Iraq is another 9/11 or worse.''</p>
        <p>''In Iraq today, terrorists have resorted to levels of barbarism that shock the world, and we should not be so naïve as to believe their intentions are limited solely to the borders of that country,'' Mr. McCain said. ''We Americans are their primary enemy, and we Americans are their ultimate target.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain made his speech at a critical moment both in his campaign and in the debate in Washington over what to do in Iraq. Congress is preparing to send President Bush a bill that would set timetables for removing troops from Iraq; Mr. Bush has vowed to veto it, a course that Mr. McCain again endorsed.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's presidential bid has been increasingly buffeted by his advocacy of the war. The senator faced criticism after he said during his trip to Baghdad last week that he was struck by the signs of improvement since his last visit there, and yesterday Democrats questioned his assessments of the war.</p>
        <p>''The idea that the situation in Iraq is improving because it only takes a security detail of 100 soldiers, three Blackhawk helicopters, and two Apache gunships to walk through a market in the middle of Baghdad is simply not credible or reflective of the facts on the ground,'' said Senator Barack Obama of Illinois, a Democratic presidential candidate.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's speech was as striking as much for the argument that he made for staying in Iraq as for the extent to which he assailed Democrats for wanting to end the war. Again and again, he portrayed Democrats as acting only out of political motivation, and said their ambitions were threatening the safety of troops on the ground in Iraq as well as America's standing in the world. Three of the leading Democratic presidential candidates -- Mr. Obama, John Edwards of North Carolina and Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York -- have all endorsed various plans for American troop withdrawals.</p>
        <p>''Democrats, who deny our soldiers the means to prevent an American defeat, have chosen another road,'' he said, speaking evenly in a still room to an audience that sat silently until he was done. ''It may appear to be the easier course of action, but it is a much more reckless one, and it does them no credit even if it gives them an advantage in the next election.''</p>
        <p>He described Democratic leaders as smiling and cheering when Congress passed legislation setting a deadline for withdrawing United States troops from Iraq. ''What were they celebrating?'' he asked. ''Defeat? Surrender? In Iraq, only our enemies were cheering.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. McCain said he was giving no thought to political considerations in embracing a war that, if unpopular with the American electorate in general, is in fact strongly supported by Republicans primary voters. ''In Washington, Democrats view it as a political opportunity, and Republicans view it as a political burden,'' he said at a news conference.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. McCain seemed to lay the groundwork for an argument he could make later in this election cycle, should the escalation policy fail. He noted that he had long called for sending more troops into Iraq, the policy Mr. Bush adopted this year, suggesting that it might have worked better had more troops been sent in earlier.</p>
        <p>''Having been a critic of the way this war was fought and a proponent of the very strategy now being followed, it is my obligation to encourage Americans to give it a chance to succeed,'' Mr. McCain said.</p>
        <p>Some Republicans have in recent weeks been advising Mr. McCain to move away from discussing his position on the war. With his speech here, Mr. McCain made clear he intended to do no such thing.</p>
        <p>''Our defeat in Iraq would constitute a defeat in the war against terror and extremism and would make the world a much more dangerous place,'' he said. ''The enemies we face there harbor the same depraved indifference to human life as those who killed 3,000 innocent Americans on a September morning in 2001.''</p>
        <p>McCain Cuts Staff Positions</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, April 11 (AP) -- The troubled presidential campaign of Senator McCain is eliminating some nonsenior staff positions and cutting some consultants' contracts. The campaign characterized the moves as ''minor adjustments'' that are part of an overall effort to revamp its fund-raising office and budgeting operation.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain ordered a financial overhaul after he reported raising only $12.5 million from January through March, third behind his top Republican rivals, Mitt Romney and Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
