<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NBC News Drops Imus Show Over Racial Remark</title>
    <meta content="12dismiss" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/business/media/12dismiss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Broadcasting Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Msnbc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nbc Universal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Story, Louise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Imus, Don</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharpton, Al (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Obama, Barack (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Al Sharpton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">NBC News</org>
        <org class="online_producer">MSNBC</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Imus, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EED9123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NBC News Drops Imus Show Over Racial Remark</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">NBC News Drops Imus Show Over Racial Remark</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER and LOUISE STORY; Jacques Steinberg contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill; Story, Louise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NBC News cancels Don Imus's talk show on its MSNBC cable news channel because of his racially disparaging remark about Rutgers University women's basketball team; move comes amid widening calls for Imus to lose both MSNBC show and his Imus in the Morning show on CBS Radio, which originates the show; CBS Radio, Imus's main employer, issues statement saying it will stick by two-week suspension of show that it announced earlier, but that it would 'monitor the situation' closely; demands that Imus's show be canceled have grown in intensity every day since Apr 4, day he called Rutgers women 'nappy-headed hos'; numerous advertisers say they would refuse to sponsor show in future; Rev Al Sharpton, among leaders of movement to force Imus off the air, says he is organizing rally outside CBS corporate headquarters to press CBS to cut ties to Imus; Sen Barack Obama, Democratic presidential contender who has appeared on Imus show in past, calls for MSNBC and CBS to dissociate themselves from Imus; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NBC News dropped Don Imus yesterday, canceling his talk show on its MSNBC cable news channel a week after he made a racially disparaging remark about the Rutgers University women's basketball team.</p>
        <p>The move came after several days of widening calls for Mr. Imus to lose his show both on MSNBC, which simulcasts the ''Imus in the Morning'' show, and CBS Radio, which originates the show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The move came after several days of widening calls for Don Imus to lose his show both on MSNBC and CBS Radio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NBC News dropped Don Imus yesterday, canceling his talk show on its MSNBC cable news channel a week after he made a racially disparaging remark about the Rutgers University women's basketball team.</p>
        <p>The move came after several days of widening calls for Mr. Imus to lose his show both on MSNBC, which simulcasts the ''Imus in the Morning'' show, and CBS Radio, which originates the show.</p>
        <p>CBS Radio, which is the main employer of Mr. Imus, said in a statement last night that it would stick by the two-week suspension of the show that it and NBC News announced earlier; the suspension begins Monday.</p>
        <p>But CBS said it would, in the interim, ''continue to speak with all concerned parties and monitor the situation closely.''</p>
        <p>The demands that Mr. Imus's show be canceled have grown in intensity every day since last Wednesday when he made the comments, in which he labeled the women ''nappy-headed hos.''</p>
        <p>Numerous advertisers said yesterday that they would refuse to sponsor the show in the future. Among the advertisers were General Motors, American Express, Sprint Nextel, GlaxoSmithKline, TD Ameritrade and Ditech.com.</p>
        <p>NBC said the cancellation was effective immediately. Mr. Imus was scheduled to be the host of a telethon today and tomorrow on radio station WFAN and simulcast on MSNBC to benefit three children's charities. The network will instead program three hours of news coverage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Imus did not respond to telephone messages last night. But Bo Dietl, a security expert who is a frequent guest on Mr. Imus's show, said last night that he had just talked by telephone with the host, and that his mood was ''very down, very upset about what occurred with MSNBC.''</p>
        <p>''I said to him that they didn't even give him time to talk to the victims,'' Mr. Dietl said. ''He agreed with me.''</p>
        <p>The Rev. Al Sharpton, who has been among the leaders of the movement to force Mr. Imus off the air, said in a telephone interview that ''we have been halfway successful so far'' and that he and others would continue to press CBS to join NBC in cutting ties to Mr. Imus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharpton said he was organizing a rally to take place today outside CBS's corporate headquarters on West 52nd Street in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''This has never been about Don Imus,'' Mr. Sharpton said. ''I have no idea whether he is a good man or not. This is about the use of public airwaves for bigoted, racist speech.''</p>
        <p>Senator Barack Obama, the Illinois Democrat who is running for president, called on MSNBC and CBS Radio to disassociate themselves from Mr. Imus, and said that he would never go on the show again. He said he had appeared once, more than two years ago.</p>
        <p>''He didn't just cross the line,'' Mr. Obama said in an interview with ABC News. ''He fed into some of the worst stereotypes that my two young daughters are having to deal with today in America.''</p>
        <p>In its statement, NBC News said the decision ''comes as a result of an ongoing review process, which initially included the announcement of a suspension.''</p>
        <p>''It also takes into account many conversations with our own employees.''</p>
        <p>The statement went on: ''What matters to us most is that the men and women of NBC Universal have confidence in the values we have set for this company. This is the only decision that makes that possible.''</p>
        <p>NBC also apologized again to the Rutgers team for ''the pain this incident has caused.''</p>
        <p>NBC executives said last night that the decision had been made jointly by the NBC Universal president, Jeff Zucker, and the president of NBC News, Steve Capus.</p>
        <p>Several NBC employees said that discussions about Mr. Imus had been going on throughout the company over the last few days and that the sentiment among the employees turned out to be a critical factor in the decision to cancel his show.</p>
        <p>In one example of that sentiment, Al Roker, the popular weatherman for the ''Today'' show, wrote a commentary on that show's Web site calling for the Imus show to be canceled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zucker made the point in an e-mail message he sent to NBC employees last night that conversations with employees had been a driving factor. ''Over the past several days, we have had to grapple with an incredibly difficult and sensitive issue,'' Mr. Zucker said in the e-mail message.</p>
        <p>''After our announcement of the suspension of Don Imus, we have had ongoing discussions with a number of employees and employee groups within our business. The result of these discussions has been very clear. NBC Universal has a strong reputation for integrity and our employees value that integrity tremendously.</p>
        <p>''Those conversations have led to the decision Steve Capus and I made today.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Capus in an interview on MSNBC last night said that in his view, the comment Mr. Imus made was racist. He added that it was far from the first time Mr. Imus had made insensitive or offensive comments on his show.</p>
        <p>''There have been any number of other comments that have been enormously hurtful to far too many people,'' Mr. Capus said. ''And my feeling is that there should not be a place for that on MSNBC.''</p>
        <p>MSNBC paid a fee to CBS to simulcast the show, about $4 million a year. It was spending about $500,000 a year to produce the show for television. For that investment, it earned what it labeled a modest profit.</p>
        <p>But the show, which has been seen on MSNBC since 1996, was helpful to NBC in other ways. It provided a forum and promotional platform for many NBC News personalities. The show is of far more value to CBS Radio, and its flagship station, WFAN, which, in addition to the rights fees from NBC, get nearly $20 million in advertising and syndication revenue from the show; the show's individual radio affiliates, collectively, earn another $20 million in revenue, according to people apprised of the show's finances. The show is also widely syndicated by Westwood One, which is managed by CBS.</p>
        <p>But NBC executives, who asked not to be identified because they were not authorized to discuss personnel matters, said that the program had only minimal impact on MSNBC's budget.</p>
        <p>In an interview on MSNBC last night, Mr. Capus said advertising money was not a determining factor.</p>
        <p>''What price do you put on your reputation?'' Mr. Capus said. ''And the reputation of the news division means more to me than advertising dollars. Because if you lose your reputation, you lose everything.''</p>
        <p>CBS executives, including the chairman, Leslie Moonves, continued to hold meetings yesterday with groups protesting Mr. Imus's remark. Among these was the National Association of Black Journalists, which was one of the first groups to demand the cancellation of his show.</p>
        <p>Mr. Imus also held a meeting with CBS executives yesterday, according to one executive who was informed of the meeting. CBS put off any further action beyond the suspension, the executive said, in part because Mr. Imus had asked for time to meet with members of the Rutgers team. He was tentatively scheduled to hold that meeting some time today.</p>
        <p>At an afternoon rally on the Rutgers campus, students chanted anti-Imus slogans and waved protest signs. State Senator Nia H. Gill of New Jersey, who earned a law degree from Rutgers, called on the college to boycott companies that advertise on the show and said she would introduce a measure in the Legislature calling for New Jersey to stop buying products from companies that advertise with him.</p>
        <p>The controversy helped push the ratings of ''Imus in the Morning'' on MSNBC to their highest level in months. On Tuesday, 624,000 people tuned in, a 50 percent increase from a week ago, according to estimates from Nielsen Media Research. An additional 1.6 million people typically listen to the program on the radio, according to Arbitron.</p>
        <p>Starting this week, large advertisers began telling MSNBC and CBS not to broadcast their ads during ''Imus in the Morning.'' The companies, like Procter &amp; Gamble and Staples, said they were dismayed that their brands had been associated with Mr. Imus's offensive remark.</p>
        <p>''Those comments, they're just not consistent with our values, and we're not going to be a part of it,'' said Stephen Dupont, a spokesman for Ditech.com, a home loan company, which asked MSNBC on Monday to remove its ads from the show.</p>
        <p>Although advertisers have been aware that the program often veered into politically incorrect territory and beyond, ''this kind of woke a lot of people to the dark side of Imus,'' said Fran Kelly, chief executive of Arnold Worldwide, an advertising agency. ''He's got every right to be on the air and say what he wants to say, but advertisers have every right to vote with their dollars.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
