<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Already Thin Rotation Takes Another Hit</title>
    <meta content="12yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/sports/baseball/12yankees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Minnesota Twins</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mussina, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D8123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Already Thin Rotation Takes Another Hit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Already Thin Rotation Takes Another Hit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>MINNEAPOLIS, April 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The revival of the Yankees' starting rotation lasted two games. Mike Mussina walked off the mound in the third inning at the Metrodome on Wednesday, the latest victim of a leg injury and the latest casualty on the staff.</p>
        <p>Mussina has a strained left hamstring and will miss his next start. Chien-Ming Wang and outfielder Hideki Matsui are on the disabled list because of hamstring strains, and Johnny Damon was a candidate last week when he strained his right calf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Mussina walked off the mound in the third inning Wednesday night, the latest victim of a leg injury and the latest casualty on the pitching staff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The revival of the Yankees' starting rotation lasted two games. Mike Mussina walked off the mound in the third inning at the Metrodome on Wednesday, the latest victim of a leg injury and the latest casualty on the staff.</p>
        <p>Mussina has a strained left hamstring and will miss his next start. Chien-Ming Wang and outfielder Hideki Matsui are on the disabled list because of hamstring strains, and Johnny Damon was a candidate last week when he strained his right calf.</p>
        <p>Mussina's injury did not have a great impact on the game, because Sean Henn pitched well in long relief. But the Minnesota Twins blitzed Kyle Farnsworth for four runs in the eighth to win, 5-1, behind eight strong innings from Ramón Ortiz.</p>
        <p>The Yankees will not put Mussina on the disabled list and the trainer Gene Monahan told Mussina he might be pitching off a mound by the weekend. Mussina said he could still touch his toes, and he was walking normally after the game.</p>
        <p>''Considering what could be going on, I could have blown it to the point where I was limping off the field, or hurt my arm or did something else,'' Mussina said. ''When you're dealing with muscle pulls and muscle strains, it's certainly not the end of the world. We'll take good care of it, and hopefully it won't be too long.''</p>
        <p>Just who is taking care of it could be an issue. Mussina's injury comes at a time when some players are privately questioning the new conditioning program. General Manager Brian Cashman hired Marty Miller last winter to replace the strength and conditioning coach Jeff Mangold, creating a new title of director of performance enhancement.</p>
        <p>Cashman also promoted Dana Cavalea to be an assistant to Miller, who had not been in baseball since 1997 and most recently spent nine years as the director of fitness at the Ballen Isles Country Club in Palm Beach Gardens, Fla.</p>
        <p>Miller also earned a master's degree in performance enhancement and injury prevention from California University of Pennsylvania in 2004. But injury prevention is not going so well for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''We wish we could pinpoint it as a team, whether or not it's the way we're working or if it's because we're all getting old,'' Damon said. ''I know in New York, it was pretty cold. That could have contributed to mine and Matsui's.</p>
        <p>''It's an unfortunate thing,'' Damon added. ''Those guys are working their tails off trying to get us right. But, unfortunately, there's a lot of different things that are going on, and obviously fingers get pointed. Hopefully, it's an unnecessary thing and something that's going to help us out in the long run. But, obviously, it raises some eyebrows.''</p>
        <p>Miller's program is voluntary, but some players have opted out of it, believing it is too strenuous. Mussina participates in the program, which he said was ''different than it has been -- different ideas, different approaches.''</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre said he believed the injuries were coincidental, and Mussina would not blame the problems on the conditioning staff.</p>
        <p>''I would say that's unfair,'' Mussina said. ''It could have happened no matter who was doing it, and it's still ultimately our responsibility to make sure we're in shape and taking care of ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Miller is generally not permitted to speak with members of the news media. But he spoke to his hometown newspaper, The Palm Beach Post, for an article published last week, explaining that his job was to be a liaison with the trainers, not merely a strength coach.</p>
        <p>''I've been able to come in here and really kind of change this whole department around,'' Miller told the newspaper.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason for Mussina's injury, the Yankees are even thinner in an area that was shaky to begin with. Carl Pavano and Andy Pettitte had quality starts here this week, but the starters' earned run average was 9.97 over the first five games.</p>
        <p>That included a loss by Darrell Rasner, who will slide into Mussina's spot and start next Tuesday at Yankee Stadium. The Yankees would then hope that Mussina is ready by April 21, when they play the Boston Red Sox at Fenway Park.</p>
        <p>Wang has not yet made a rehabilitation start, and Jeff Karstens, who has elbow stiffness, could be active sooner. But the Yankees would prefer to go with Mussina in Boston, and for now they are optimistic. Torre said he did not think Mussina would need tests on the hamstring.</p>
        <p>''We'll wait a day or so to see where we are,'' Torre said. ''But it doesn't seem to be a real bad one.''</p>
        <p>Mussina has had several groin injuries in the past few years, but he could not remember ever hurting his hamstring. Still, he recognized the injury when he felt it in the bottom of the third, and he waved out the pitching coach, Ron Guidry, after the count went to 2-1 on Luis Castillo that inning.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't lobbying for anything,'' said Mussina, who left the mound without trying a practice pitch.</p>
        <p>There were two on and no outs when Henn entered, but he induced two pop outs to Derek Jeter, who whirled and fired to second to start an inning-ending double play.</p>
        <p>The score was tied, 1-1, when Farnsworth entered to start the eighth. He walked Castillo, the speedy leadoff man, and the inning got worse from there.</p>
        <p>''That's a bad guy to walk on four pitches,'' Torre said. ''He just had trouble locating.''</p>
        <p>Castillo stole second and scored on a one-out single by Joe Mauer. A single and two doubles followed before Farnsworth was lifted with the Yankees trailing by four runs.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Alex Rodriguez did not hit a homer Wednesday, but he drove in the Yankees' run with a sacrifice fly in the fourth and added a double in the ninth. He has an extra-base hit in all eight Yankees games this season.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
