<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warriors Find Odd Place, and Like It</title>
    <meta content="12warriors" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/sports/basketball/12warriors.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Golden State Warriors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Golden State Warriors</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nelson, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6D8123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warriors Find Odd Place, and Like It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Warriors Climb Into an Odd Place, and Like It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Don Nelson walked into a barbershop in downtown Oakland, Calif., yesterday afternoon, he said, he heard five cars honk loudly in succession. Drivers popped their heads out and shouted good luck to Nelson, the once and present coach of the Golden State Warriors.</p>
        <p>''The juice is back, the crowd is in it and there's excitement again,'' Nelson said in a telephone interview. Referring to the horns, he said with a hearty laugh, ''I didn't hear that at the beginning of the season.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Golden State Warriors have not made the playoffs since 1994 and they sit precariously in the eighth and final playoff spot in the Western Conference with four games left.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Don Nelson walked into a barbershop in downtown Oakland, Calif., yesterday afternoon, he said, he heard five cars honk loudly in succession. Drivers popped their heads out and shouted good luck to Nelson, the once and present coach of the Golden State Warriors.</p>
        <p>''The juice is back, the crowd is in it and there's excitement again,'' Nelson said in a telephone interview. Referring to the horns, he said with a hearty laugh, ''I didn't hear that at the beginning of the season.''</p>
        <p>Now, with a fresh haircut, he is approaching the frantic rush at the end of the season with a fervor equal to that of the fans.</p>
        <p>The Warriors (38-40) have not made the playoffs since 1994 -- in Nelson's last stint at Golden State -- and they sit precariously in the eighth and final playoff spot in the Western Conference with four games left. They are a half-game ahead of the Los Angeles Clippers (37-40), who hold the tie breaker.</p>
        <p>It is no wonder that Nelson was up and yelling at the television when the Hornets defeated the Clippers in overtime Tuesday, boosting the Warriors past Los Angeles. ''I was coaching the dang thing,'' he said. Golden State owns the tie breaker over the Hornets (37-41), so Nelson's allegiance was clear.</p>
        <p>Last season, the Clippers were the N.B.A.'s feel-good team, the one to break a long postseason drought (nine years), not to mention breaking the laughable curse of being that other Los Angeles team.</p>
        <p>Worse than being a punch line, the Warriors have been the most invisible team in California in the past decade. Chris Mullin, the former Warrior and now the team's vice president, hired Nelson before the season to change that.</p>
        <p>That is why Nelson said it would be his fault if the Warriors' playoff drought extended to 13 seasons. When the team slipped to seven games below .500 on Feb. 28, after a 30-point shellacking by Chicago, Nelson blamed himself.</p>
        <p>''I thought I could get this team to the playoffs, but it doesn't look like it's going to happen,'' Nelson said at the time. ''I feel that I failed in a lot of ways, really.''</p>
        <p>Those words were intended for motivation, Nelson said. And it worked, thanks to a boost of good health.</p>
        <p>The All-Star point guard Baron Davis returned to the lineup on March 5 in Detroit after recovering from arthroscopic knee surgery. The Warriors won that game and have gone 12-4 in the games he has played since. Davis has averaged 19.3 points and 6.8 assists a game in that span.</p>
        <p>''Whatever success we have, we owe it to Baron,'' Nelson said. ''I remember when he was with Charlotte and how good he was, almost unstoppable. He hadn't been that player for a few years due to injuries. Now he's back and he's the leader of the team. He's also one of the best defensive point guards in the game. He's got the whole team playing better defense.''</p>
        <p>Nelson's signature is his unconventional offense. He has started a small lineup with the 6-foot-9 Al Harrington, acquired as part of an eight-player trade with the Pacers in January, at center. With power forward Stephen Jackson, the other important player from that trade, and a three-guard front of Davis, Jason Richardson and Monta Ellis, a top candidate for the most improved player award, the Warriors are fast and accurate from outside.</p>
        <p>They have gone 5-1 with this lineup, averaging 116.2 points and shooting 41.4 percent from 3-point range.</p>
        <p>''The big thing is Nellie, the players fit his style,'' Mullin said in a recent telephone interview. ''He's got these guys believing and got their roles in place.''</p>
        <p>While Mullin, who was on the Warriors in 1994, can appreciate the importance, for fans and players, of earning a playoff berth, ''it's not,'' he said, ''a destination or an end point. It is a step, a necessary small step.''</p>
        <p>But first, the footsteps. The Clippers, who play the Lakers on Thursday, have to lose one more game than the Warriors the rest of the way if Golden State is to qualify for the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''They have a better inside presence than we do,'' Nelson said of the Clippers. ''They're probably a better team than we are, but we're playing at such a high level right now, it's anybody's ballgame.''</p>
        <p>The Warriors have had significant victories, beating Phoenix, Dallas and Utah, all division winners, at home, holding 25-point leads in all three games. On April 17, the Warriors will try to make it a three-game season sweep against Dallas, the team Nelson previously coached.</p>
        <p>How fitting it would be if that game determines whether the Warriors get into the playoffs -- for the right to play the Mavericks again.</p>
        <p>''I think it would be good for basketball,'' Nelson said. ''I'd love to play Dallas or anybody else. I don't want to say that would mean we arrived -- more that we've turned the corner.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
