<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Working on Overhaul, Russia Halts Adoption Applications</title>
    <meta content="12adopt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/us/12adopt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Adoption</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Guatemala</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemetson, Lynette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Guatemala</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Guatemala</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7D9123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Working on Overhaul, Russia Halts Adoption Applications</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Working on Overhaul, Russia Halts Adoption Applications</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNETTE CLEMETSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clemetson, Lynette</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russia temporarily stops accepting new applications from American adoption agencies as part of overhaul of its accreditation process; State Dept figures show Americans adopted 3,706 Russian children last year, making Russia third most popular destination for overseas adoptions, after China and Guatemala; China is tightening its requirements and Guatemala is revising its procedures (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Americans wishing to adopt from Russia may face an indefinite wait. The country has temporarily stopped accepting new applications from American adoption agencies as part of an overhaul of its accreditation process.</p>
        <p>Over the last several months, licenses to work in Russia have expired for most of the roughly 50 American adoption agencies with programs there. Licenses for the last two agencies, the Alliance for Children in Wellesley, Mass., and Children of the World Adoption Agency, in Syosset, N.Y., expired yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Russia has temporarily stopped accepting new applications from American adoption agencies as part of an overhaul of its accreditation process.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Americans wishing to adopt from Russia may face an indefinite wait. The country has temporarily stopped accepting new applications from American adoption agencies as part of an overhaul of its accreditation process.</p>
        <p>Over the last several months, licenses to work in Russia have expired for most of the roughly 50 American adoption agencies with programs there. Licenses for the last two agencies, the Alliance for Children in Wellesley, Mass., and Children of the World Adoption Agency, in Syosset, N.Y., expired yesterday.</p>
        <p>Many adoption officials say the expirations represent nothing more than a slow-moving bureaucratic process. The officials added that they expected new licenses to be approved within months.</p>
        <p>Last year, according to State Department figures, Americans adopted 3,706 Russian children, making Russia the third most popular destination for overseas adoptions, after China and Guatemala. It is one of several countries revising its international adoption procedures.</p>
        <p>China will tighten its requirements in May. Among the many restrictions, it will no longer approve adoptions for applicants older than 50.</p>
        <p>Guatemala is revising its procedures to comply with the Hague Convention on Intercountry Adoptions, a treaty to regulate international adoptions that the United States plans to ratify this year.</p>
        <p>''What is happening in Russia is part of a fundamental restructuring of international adoption across several countries,'' said Adam Pertman, executive director of the Evan B. Donaldson Adoption Institute, an adoption research and advocacy organization. ''In most of the countries involved, the changes are part of a widespread change in global practices to protect children, and that is a good thing in the long term.''</p>
        <p>Tom DiFilipo, president of the Joint Council on International Children's Services, a membership organization for international adoption agencies, said people hoping to adopt from Russia should not be alarmed.</p>
        <p>''Whenever there is a bureaucratic delay, children suffer, children stay in orphanages longer, and that is where our concern is,'' Mr. DiFilipo said. ''But families should not panic. This is a delay. This is not a moratorium.''</p>
        <p>Tensions within Russia over international adoptions have intensified in recent years after several widely publicized cases of neglect, abuse and death of Russian adoptees by American parents.</p>
        <p>Georgia and Tom Aralis, of Mount Prospect, Ill., adopted their 2 year-old son, Demetri, from Russia last June, and they are scheduled to return to Russia this month to adopt another son, Daniel. Ms. Aralis, 36, said that the judge who handled their first adoption raised the abuse cases at their hearing.</p>
        <p>''He asked us outright how we were going to treat the child, how we were going to discipline the child, because they knew of abuses of Russian children in the United States,'' she said. ''But that was a fair question. We got no impression that they did not want Americans to be adopting.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
