<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Dash to Playoffs, Jagr Hitched Rangers to His Star</title>
    <meta content="12rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/sports/hockey/12rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Atlanta Thrashers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Thrashers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jagr, Jaromir</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1D8123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Dash to Playoffs, Jagr Hitched Rangers to His Star</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Dash to Playoffs, Jagr Hitched Rangers to His Star</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., April 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To look at the score sheet from the Rangers' game against St. Louis in early March, a shootout victory that the Rangers believe saved their season, Jaromir Jagr appears inconsequential. He scored no goals, had no assists. He did not record a shot on goal.</p>
        <p>But to look at a score sheet is to miss everything that has made Jagr's season extraordinary. His scoring is down. His ice time is down. But he has all but willed the Rangers into their current playoff spot, a sixth-seeded team heading to Atlanta to face the Thrashers in a first-round series beginning Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>His scoring and ice time are down, but Jaromir Jagr has all but willed the sixth-seeded Rangers into the playoffs where they will face the Atlanta Thrashers on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To look at the score sheet from the Rangers' game against St. Louis in early March, a shootout victory that the Rangers believe saved their season, Jaromir Jagr appears inconsequential. He scored no goals, had no assists. He did not record a shot on goal.</p>
        <p>But to look at a score sheet is to miss everything that has made Jagr's season extraordinary. His scoring is down. His ice time is down. But he has all but willed the Rangers into their current playoff spot, a sixth-seeded team heading to Atlanta to face the Thrashers in a first-round series beginning Thursday.</p>
        <p>The Rangers trailed the Blues that day, 2-0, after the second period. It was a score that reflected the Rangers, who were in 11th place in the Eastern Conference and looking lethargic. But before the third period started, Jagr told his teammates they had to win or they would never make the playoffs. And in overtime, Jagr showed how much he meant it. Already exhausted from an extended shift, Jagr raced up ice, the only Ranger chasing Blues forward Radek Dvorak as Dvorak skated in for a shot. Jagr never stopped hustling and swatted the shot away.</p>
        <p>''I remember that,'' Jagr said this week, looking back at the season, shrugging when asked what it meant. ''Everybody would do it. They would even do it quicker than me.''</p>
        <p>Jagr laughed at his own expense, remembering that he was so winded at that point that he could not return to the ice as the overtime continued. As the score remained tied, Coach Tom Renney moved Jagr to third in the shootout that came after overtime to give him more time to catch his breath. Then Jagr scored in the shootout to keep the Rangers alive in a game they would eventually win.</p>
        <p>That day was a snapshot of Jagr's regular season. By all statistical accounts, it was a disappointing one. He scored 30 goals and had 66 assists. A season ago, he scored 54 goals with 69 assists. He dropped from 24 power-play goals to 7. Asked why, Jagr shrugged again. He has no answer.</p>
        <p>But ask any of the Rangers about Jagr and not one will minimize his impact. Coming out of the All-Star Game break, Jagr said his only goal was to lift his struggling team into the playoffs. He would indeed lead the way, but not by scoring goals in bunches. Instead, he backed up everything he asked his teammates to do by also doing it himself.</p>
        <p>Since that March day against St. Louis, the Rangers have gone 12-3-3.</p>
        <p>''It's always important when a player of his stature is doing what we call the little things,'' forward Brendan Shanahan said. ''It sends a message to all of the younger players. Here's a guy who's played 16 years in the N.H.L. and has a closet full of trophies, and he's doing all these little things. That's leadership.''</p>
        <p>Jagr entered this season by taking the reins as the Rangers' captain, aiming to improve on the team's first-round playoff collapse a year ago. He scored his 600th career goal early in the season, but little else went smoothly. Jagr, bouncing back from off-season shoulder surgery, struggled to score. The team began to reshape itself with a desperate, defensive mind-set. And after Jagr's proclamation coming out of the All-Star Game break, they started to claw their way up the standings.</p>
        <p>''We were talking about this recently,'' center Matt Cullen said. ''There's a lot of guys in here that have a lot to prove, and I think Jags feels that way as much as anybody. That sort of hunger is really important going into a playoff drive.''</p>
        <p>Jagr's hunger stems from his belief that where he leads this team will be a big part of the ultimate measure of him as a player. He has already won two Stanley Cups, in 1991 and '92 with Pittsburgh, but Jagr was young and playing alongside Mario Lemieux.</p>
        <p>Now Jagr is 35 and the Rangers are his team.</p>
        <p>''I always want to be one of the best players,'' Jagr said. ''If you do not make the playoffs, you cannot be. There are 16 teams that go to the playoffs. If you are not on one, you cannot look at yourself as a good player. You can't. It's impossible. That's the way I look at it. That's why the playoffs are so important to me.''</p>
        <p>Jagr's leadership is not the obvious kind. He does not often stand up and give speeches. His words in the locker room are carefully chosen and timed. That is why when he told his teammates before the third period against St. Louis that it was their Game 7, he had their attention.</p>
        <p>On a day-to-day basis, Jagr's loudest words are delivered in the form of jokes and his laughter echoes through the Rangers' workout rooms. He pokes fun at himself as well as anyone else within earshot.</p>
        <p>His ego has allowed for the presence of a strong leader, Shanahan, to be brought in as a free agent before the season. And it leaves room for Renney to place his defense-first stamp on the team. Jagr has accepted less ice time, meant to keep him fresher, and played defense as hard as he has in his career.</p>
        <p>Renney has spent the entire season lauding the role Jagr has played.</p>
        <p>''He looks fresh,'' Renney said. ''He's attacking. He's back-checking. He's playing all three zones with and without the puck as hard as a guy that big can. He's been a real inspiration to our team by the nature of how he's played and the support he shows his teammates, the things he says to people. He's been outstanding.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers' management helped back up Jagr at the trading deadline. In the face of rumors that Jagr would be traded, the team instead jettisoned a player who had aligned himself against Jagr: defenseman Aaron Ward. He was shipped to Boston for defenseman Paul Mara a few weeks after continually complaining about an argument he and Jagr had on the bench during a game.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Jagr has easily accommodated the arrival of forward Sean Avery, who came in a Feb. 5 trade. Jagr even credits that trade for a large measure of the Rangers' recent success.</p>
        <p>Avery said he has been equally impressed.</p>
        <p>''I never really got to play that much against him,'' Avery said. ''If anything, I'm excited to see how he turns it on in the playoffs because I think we all know there's definitely another gear in there for him.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers would be thrilled if their once high-scoring superstar began scoring at his old clip in the playoffs. But they also understand the value of what he has been doing while the goals failed to materialize.</p>
        <p>''I think last year he had a career personal season and it ended in such disappointment,'' Shanahan said. ''I think this year he's really focused on making this year a more successful team season.''</p>
        <p>And if you look closely, the person that team is following is, inevitably, Jagr.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
