<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel on Problems at Walter Reed Issues Strong Rebuke</title>
    <meta content="12medical" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/washington/12medical.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Walter Reed Army Medical Center (Washington, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">West, Togo D Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marsh, John O Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shane, Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Reed, Walter, Army Medical Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel on Problems at Walter Reed Issues Strong Rebuke</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Panel on Walter Reed Woes Issues Strong Rebuke</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SCOTT SHANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shane, Scott</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Independent panel led by two former secretaries of Army, Togo D West Jr and John O Marsh Jr, issues sweeping indictment of leadership failures, inadequate training and staffing shortages in assessing dilapidated facilities and red tape for wounded Iraq war veterans at Walter Reed Army Medical Center in Washington; finds high standard of care for troops when first evacuated from war zones and hospitalized fell apart when they became outpatients; report says current system for assessing soldiers' disabilities must be completely overhauled; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An independent panel assessing dilapidated facilities and red tape for wounded Iraq war veterans at Walter Reed Army Medical Center on Wednesday issued a sweeping indictment of leadership failures, inadequate training and staffing shortages.</p>
        <p>The panel, headed by two former secretaries of the Army, Togo D. West Jr. and John O. Marsh Jr., found that a high standard of care for troops when they were first evacuated from war zones and hospitalized fell apart when they became outpatients, with a ''breakdown in health services'' and ''compassion fatigue'' on the part of overworked staff members.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An independent panel issued a sweeping indictment of leadership failures, inadequate training and staffing shortages at Walter Reed Army Medical Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An independent panel assessing dilapidated facilities and red tape for wounded Iraq war veterans at Walter Reed Army Medical Center on Wednesday issued a sweeping indictment of leadership failures, inadequate training and staffing shortages.</p>
        <p>The panel, headed by two former secretaries of the Army, Togo D. West Jr. and John O. Marsh Jr., found that a high standard of care for troops when they were first evacuated from war zones and hospitalized fell apart when they became outpatients, with a ''breakdown in health services'' and ''compassion fatigue'' on the part of overworked staff members.</p>
        <p>''Leadership at Walter Reed should have been aware of poor living conditions and administrative hurdles and failed to place proper priority on solutions,'' the panel said in a summary of its draft report released at a meeting at Walter Reed.</p>
        <p>The report called the current system for assessing soldiers' disabilities ''extremely cumbersome, inconsistent, and confusing,'' saying it must be ''completely overhauled.'' It called for the creation of a ''center of excellence'' on treatment, training and research on two conditions suffered by thousands of troops in Iraq: traumatic brain injury and post-traumatic stress disorder.</p>
        <p>The panel, called the Independent Review Group, was appointed by Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates in February after The Washington Post reported on the problems at Walter Reed, the Army's century-old medical center in Washington. A presidential commission and a Department of Veterans Affairs task force are also assessing the troubles.</p>
        <p>The conditions at Walter Reed, including moldy, rat-infested quarters and a bureaucratic maze that left severely injured soldiers in limbo for months, have become a symbol of the government's broader failure to help troops injured in Iraq and Afghanistan. President Bush visited patients at the facility March 30 and said, ''I apologize for what they went through, and we're going to fix the problem.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Mr. Gates, Cynthia O. Smith, said Wednesday that he ''welcomes the findings and believes our wounded warriors deserve the best treatment possible both as inpatients and outpatients.''</p>
        <p>The initial reports in February led to a shake-up of Army leadership. Army Secretary Francis J. Harvey fired Walter Reed's commander, Maj. Gen. George Weightman, and replaced him with Lt. Gen. Kevin Kiley, the Army surgeon general.</p>
        <p>But critics said General Kiley had been told about the problems and failed to act. Mr. Gates then publicly criticized the Army's response as inadequate, and both Mr. Harvey and General Kiley stepped down.</p>
        <p>Since then, the Army has moved aggressively to make improvements at Walter Reed. Patients have been moved out of the most squalid building. Some 28 new case managers have been added to help wounded soldiers navigate the medical system. A telephone hot line has been opened and information handbooks have been distributed to families of wounded service members.</p>
        <p>In remarks at Wednesday's meeting, Mr. West, a former military lawyer who served as both secretary of the Army and secretary of veterans affairs under President Bill Clinton, strongly criticized the tortuous bureaucracy that assesses soldiers' disabilities.</p>
        <p>''The horrors inflicted on our wounded service members and their families in the name of the physical disability review process simply must be stopped,'' Mr. West said.</p>
        <p>He said the Army's system currently requires four proceedings before an official board, causing delays and excessive paperwork and producing ''inexplicable differences in standards and results.''</p>
        <p>''We can and must do better,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. West also said the panel concluded there was inadequate understanding of how to diagnose and treat the brain injuries that have become a signature of the Iraq war, where thousands of troops have been wounded by improvised explosive devices, and the mental effects of long exposure to the constant threat of attack.</p>
        <p>''We believe there is a need for greater and better coordinated research in this area,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Under legislation introduced Wednesday by Senators Evan Bayh of Indiana and Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York, both Democrats, troops suffering from traumatic brain injuries would be kept on active duty, rather than being retired, so they would receive more medical attention.</p>
        <p>Steve Robinson, a longtime veterans' advocate with Veterans for America, said he welcomed the findings of the review panel. But he said the panel should address the problems of discharged soldiers who were not getting V.A. benefits they needed.</p>
        <p>''What are we going to do about the thousands of people who have unjustifiably lost their V.A. benefits forever?'' Mr. Robinson said. ''It's not enough just to fix the problems starting from the point that President Bush went to Walter Reed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
