<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Developer That Bought Times Building Puts Up For-Sale Sign</title>
    <meta content="12times" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/nyregion/12times.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070424T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Tishman Speyer Properties</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Developer That Bought Times Building Puts Up For-Sale Sign</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Developer That Bought Times Building Puts Up For-Sale Sign, Hoping to Triple Its Money</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What a difference 885 days make.</p>
        <p>This week, Tishman Speyer Properties put the historic headquarters of The New York Times Company on West 43rd Street on the block for $500 million -- nearly three times the amount Tishman Speyer paid for it, $175 million, in November 2004.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The historic headquarters of The New York Times Company on West 43rd Street is on the block for $500 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What a difference 885 days make.</p>
        <p>This week, Tishman Speyer Properties put the historic headquarters of The New York Times Company on West 43rd Street on the block for $500 million -- nearly three times the amount Tishman Speyer paid for it, $175 million, in November 2004.</p>
        <p>''It's indicative of how fast rents have moved up and how much capital is chasing deals,'' said Dan Fasulo, managing director of Real Capital Analytics, which tracks real estate deals. ''There's just so much money in the market. I don't see it stopping in the short term.''</p>
        <p>The average rent for first-class office space in Midtown has climbed to a record high of $70.77 per square foot, according to a report released on Tuesday by Cushman &amp; Wakefield, a real estate broker. In addition to American investors and pension funds, foreign investors have also found New York attractive, because it is less expensive than cities like London, Paris and Hong Kong. At the same time, interest rates are still relatively low and the dollar is weak against the euro.</p>
        <p>''People from Europe come here and think they're getting a bargain,'' Mr. Fasulo said.</p>
        <p>It seems as if every week brings news of another record-breaking deal for office towers or residential buildings in a city grappling with prosperity and success. Some analysts wonder what will happen when the real estate boom runs out of air. In the meantime, there is growing concern that rising office rents could drive some companies out of New York, while housing costs are making New York less hospitable for poor, working-class and even middle-class families.</p>
        <p>Robert C. Guccione, the founder of Penthouse magazine, has put a $59 million price on his 25-room mansion on the Upper East Side, while the average apartment in Manhattan sells for $1.2 million.</p>
        <p>Harry B. Macklowe, the developer, recently bought eight first-class office buildings in Midtown for a total of $7.2 billion, or more than $1,100 a square foot.</p>
        <p>In December, a New Jersey real estate family, the Kushners, announced that it was buying the 41-story skyscraper at 666 Fifth Avenue for $1.8 billion, or $1,200 per square foot, from Tishman Speyer.</p>
        <p>At $500 million, the company or investor that buys The New York Times headquarters would be paying $666.66 a square foot, seemingly a bargain by comparison. But the 750,000-square-foot, 15-story building, which opened in 1913, is no one's idea of a first-class office tower. It needs an expensive, top-to-bottom overhaul before it can be rented to corporate tenants.</p>
        <p>But there are not that many alternatives in Midtown.</p>
        <p>''It's the only office building north of 42nd Street that can deliver in the next 24 months more than 300,000 square feet of contiguous space'' that would rent for less than $100 per square foot, said Darcy A. Stacom, the broker at CB Richard Ellis who sold the property for The Times in 2004 and is now handling it for Tishman Speyer.</p>
        <p>The Times Company plans to move this year into its new headquarters, a skyscraper between 40th and 41st Streets, across Eighth Avenue from the Port Authority Bus Terminal.</p>
        <p>At the time the deal was struck, some real estate executives suggested that Tishman Speyer had overpaid for the Times building. But rents have marched steadily upward since then, while vacancy rates plummeted. So far this year, Manhattan office buildings are selling for an average of $834 a square foot, up from $300 in 2004, according to Real Capital Analytics.</p>
        <p>''The value of the building has increased significantly since we bought it,'' said Rob Speyer, senior managing director of Tishman Speyer. ''It's in the best interest of our investors to realize that value.''</p>
        <p>Right now, financial institutions -- everything from investment banks to hedge funds and private equity companies -- are driving the market. They collectively accounted for more than a third of the space leased in Manhattan so far this year. Those companies are also paying the highest rents, with financial companies signing more than 12 of the 18 leases this year for space costing $100 or more per square foot, according to Cushman &amp; Wakefield.</p>
        <p>But skyrocketing rents are one reason that JPMorgan Chase &amp; Company is looking at moving thousands of employees from Midtown to Lower Manhattan, where rents are one-third less. It is also why Citigroup announced last year that it was moving 1,200 executives to Jersey City from downtown. Two years earlier, Citigroup moved 1,900 employees out of Lower Manhattan, most of them to a corporate campus in Warren, N.J.</p>
        <p>''The flip side of all this prosperity,'' said Kathryn S. Wylde, president of the Partnership for New York City, ''is that lower- and middle-income workers are being priced out of the housing market and the technical and operational jobs at our major industries can no longer afford the rents.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 24, 2007, Tuesday  An article on April 12 about the $500 million asking price for the building at 229 W. 43rd Street that houses the headquarters of The New York Times -- nearly three times the amount a developer paid for it in November 2004 -- included an outdated reference to an Upper East Side mansion with a high price tag. The 25-room building, which is listed at $59 million, is no longer owned by Robert C. Guccione, the founder of Penthouse magazine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 24, 2007, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on April 12 about the $500 million asking price for the building at 229 W. 43rd Street that houses the headquarters of The New York Times -- nearly three times the amount a developer paid for it in November 2004 -- included an outdated reference to an Upper East Side mansion with a high price tag. The 25-room building, which is listed at $59 million, is no longer owned by Robert C. Guccione, the founder of Penthouse magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
