<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Bill Seeks Power For Medicare On Drug Costs</title>
    <meta content="12medicare" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/washington/12medicare.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7D9123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Bill Seeks Power For Medicare On Drug Costs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Senate Bill Seeks Power for Medicare on Drug Costs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate Democratic leaders push legislation that would allow Medicare to negotiate lower drug prices for millions of older Americans; law that added drug benefit to Medicare in 2003 prohibited Medicare officials from negotiating with drug manufacturers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senate Democratic leaders pushed Wednesday for legislation that would allow Medicare to negotiate lower drug prices for millions of older Americans. Their bill does not go as far as one passed by the House, which requires such negotiations.</p>
        <p>In 2003, Congress added a drug benefit to Medicare, but prohibited Medicare officials from negotiating prices with drug manufacturers. The benefit is delivered by private insurers and their agents, pharmacy benefit managers, which negotiate with drug makers and have obtained substantial discounts in return for steering patients to particular products.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bill, which would allow Medicare to negotiate lower drug prices for millions of older Americans, does not go as far as one passed by the House, which requires such negotiations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senate Democratic leaders pushed Wednesday for legislation that would allow Medicare to negotiate lower drug prices for millions of older Americans. Their bill does not go as far as one passed by the House, which requires such negotiations.</p>
        <p>In 2003, Congress added a drug benefit to Medicare, but prohibited Medicare officials from negotiating prices with drug manufacturers. The benefit is delivered by private insurers and their agents, pharmacy benefit managers, which negotiate with drug makers and have obtained substantial discounts in return for steering patients to particular products.</p>
        <p>Democrats won control of Congress last year on a platform that promised to ''fix the Medicare prescription drug program, putting seniors first by negotiating lower drug prices.'' On Jan. 12, just eight days after the new Congress convened, the House passed a bill stating that the secretary of health and human services ''shall negotiate with pharmaceutical manufacturers the prices that may be charged'' to Medicare drug plans.</p>
        <p>The Senate majority leader, Harry Reid, Democrat of Nevada, said Monday that he expected the full Senate to take up the issue next week. The principal legislation to be debated on the Senate floor would allow but not require the secretary of health and human services to negotiate with drug companies to secure lower prices for Medicare beneficiaries.</p>
        <p>The bill, drafted by Senator Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana, the chairman of the Finance Committee, would repeal the part of the 2003 law that prohibits such negotiations. The drug benefit would still be delivered by private entities, and the government could not establish a price list or a uniform list of covered drugs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baucus's proposal faces criticism from the left and the right. Many Democratic senators want to require the government to negotiate. Most Republicans want to preserve the current ban.</p>
        <p>The White House said in January that President Bush would veto the House bill if it got to him. At a White House meeting last week, aides to the president urged employer groups, insurance companies and drugstores to lobby against the Senate measure as well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baucus said his bill would ''untie the secretary's hands,'' so he could ''strike better deals'' for some drugs.</p>
        <p>Senator Debbie Stabenow, Democrat of Michigan, said she wanted to require Medicare to negotiate drug prices, as provided in the House bill. But she added, ''I am a realist,'' and the first step toward that goal is simply to repeal the ban on negotiations.</p>
        <p>Senator Olympia J. Snowe, Republican of Maine, said she was ''surprised and disappointed'' that Senate Democratic leaders were not trying to require negotiations. Ms. Snowe and Senator Ron Wyden, Democrat of Oregon, have introduced a bill that would require the secretary to negotiate prices for certain drugs, including those available from only one source, with no competition from similar brand-name or generic drugs.</p>
        <p>''I would have thought that, since the Democrats are now in control, they would have tried to do more,'' Ms. Snowe said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wyden said the Democrats' strategy was intended to secure 60 votes, the number needed to overcome a possible filibuster.</p>
        <p>Republicans like Senator Charles E. Grassley of Iowa said the drug benefit was working well, with costs to the government and to beneficiaries far below the levels initially predicted. Medicare officials say the average beneficiary premium for the basic drug benefit is $22 a month, about 40 percent lower than the original projection.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grassley said the Democratic proposals were ''political pandering,'' a result of campaign slogans that do not translate well into legislation. Senator Pat Roberts, Republican of Kansas, said, ''The 2008 election year is here a lot earlier than we had anticipated.''</p>
        <p>The Congressional Budget Office says that neither the House bill nor the Senate version would save much money.</p>
        <p>Peter R. Orszag, director of the budget office, said negotiations on a few high-priced drugs ''could potentially generate cost savings.''</p>
        <p>But over all, he said, Mr. Baucus's bill ''would have a negligible effect on federal spending'' because the government would not have the leverage to negotiate discounts deeper than those already being obtained by private Medicare drug plans.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
