<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shaving My Wallet A Lot Better Than My Face</title>
    <meta content="12skin" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/fashion/12skin.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Skin Deep"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5DD123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shaving My Wallet A Lot Better Than My Face</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shaving My Wallet a Lot Better Than My Face</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED A. BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Fred A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GILLETTE and Schick make more money selling razor blades than razors, right?</p>
        <p>So, if someone invented a permanent razor blade, they would do anything they could to keep it off the market, right?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Infinity Razor has a blade that will shave as well in 10 years as it does today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GILLETTE and Schick make more money selling razor blades than razors, right?</p>
        <p>So, if someone invented a permanent razor blade, they would do anything they could to keep it off the market, right?</p>
        <p>That's why I was willing to believe the claim made in a television infomercial: that the Infinity Razor has a blade that will shave as well in 10 years as it does today. Some brilliant entrepreneur, I persuaded myself, had invented a permanent blade, but was forced -- by corporate oligarchs -- to offer it only on late-night television.</p>
        <p>And that's how I found myself at Theinfinityrazor.com. Ordering was an experience in itself, a lesson in the seamy side of e-commerce. A small window in the corner of my screen played the commercial, with its high-tech name-dropping (carbon steel, tungsten carbide) and absurd claim making. (''The last razor you'll ever have to buy. To prove it, we shaved grit off sandpaper '')</p>
        <p>I was required to enter my credit card number before proceeding, never a good sign. And then, after making a selection -- two Infinity razors for $19.95 -- I was bombarded with additional offers.</p>
        <p>How about four extra razors? O.K., you don't want four extras, so how about two? What about steak knives? Or a fogless shaving mirror? (Since I shave in the shower, I agreed to that one.)</p>
        <p>Then I was told that ''regular'' shipping would take four to six weeks, an eternity to someone trying to prove the replaceable razor blade consortium corrupt. So I chose ''rush.'' Suddenly, with $18.90 in shipping and handling fees, my $19.95 razor (plus fogless mirror) was costing $56.75.</p>
        <p>And there was no turning back. Once I chose a shipping option -- expecting a chance to review my order -- the Web site thanked me for my patronage. My money was gone, like the ball in the last hole of a miniature golf course.</p>
        <p>I felt swindled. And that was before the razor arrived. Distinguished only by a red infinity symbol on its gray handle, it was a flimsy disposable razor, barely long enough for a grown-up to hold on to.</p>
        <p>And here's the rub (and I mean rub): The blade was so dull it wouldn't shave me even once, much less thousands of times. I got a cheek massage instead. For a shave, I relied on my Gillette Mach3 (which, by the way, is an excellent razor, though it does require expensive replacement blades).</p>
        <p>I decided to see if I could get a refund. Searching for ''infinity razor'' on Google, I discovered Infomercialratings.com, a site where people evaluate the products sold in the wee hours. The Infinity Razor received scathing reviews, with headings like ''Low Quality'' and ''Just don't waste your money.'' If only I had Googled before buying.</p>
        <p>Back at Theinfinityrazor.com, I read the fine print: ''The Infinity Razor comes with a lifetime replacement guarantee -- which means if you ever think it is not shaving you as close as it should, send it back, and we will send you a replacement.''</p>
        <p>The last thing I wanted was a replacement. In fairness, there was also a money-back offer, but it didn't include the cost of shipping. I would have to stand in line at the post office to return the razor, hoping to receive $19.95 (in four to six weeks?).</p>
        <p>A call to customer service asking for a corporate response was not immediately returned.</p>
        <p>I wrapped the Infinity Razor and shoved it into a drawer. And then it occurred to me: The promise the company made is true. The razor will shave exactly as well in 10 years as it does today.</p>
        <p>Skin Deep</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
