<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Theatrics as Lawyers Duel At Ex-Judge's Trial in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="12battle" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/nyregion/12battle.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFD9123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Theatrics as Lawyers Duel At Ex-Judge's Trial in Brooklyn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Court Theatrics as Lawyers Duel at Ex-Judge’s Trial in Brooklyn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brick, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Certain occupations require people -- or permit them -- to spend the day screaming at somebody. Two men seemingly inclined toward such work, Michael S. Washor and Michael F. Vecchione, have found a prominent forum at the judicial corruption trial in State Supreme Court in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>After nearly four weeks of testimony about Gerald P. Garson, with a damning surveillance recording in evidence and few major facts in dispute, the lead defense lawyer, Mr. Washor, has sought to cast the prosecutor, Mr. Vecchione, as overzealous and vindictive. So under the care of a patient, indulgent and seemingly amused visiting judge from Orange County, the show has been the thing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The behavior of a pair of lawyers has become the main event at a judicial corruption trial taking place in State Supreme Court in Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Certain occupations require people -- or permit them -- to spend the day screaming at somebody. Two men seemingly inclined toward such work, Michael S. Washor and Michael F. Vecchione, have found a prominent forum at the judicial corruption trial in State Supreme Court in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>After nearly four weeks of testimony about Gerald P. Garson, with a damning surveillance recording in evidence and few major facts in dispute, the lead defense lawyer, Mr. Washor, has sought to cast the prosecutor, Mr. Vecchione, as overzealous and vindictive. So under the care of a patient, indulgent and seemingly amused visiting judge from Orange County, the show has been the thing.</p>
        <p>''I'm not running a law school here,'' Mr. Washor told the judge, Justice Jeffrey G. Berry, at one point, suggesting that his adversary had failed to make an appropriate argument. Later, during cross-examination, he loudly asked a witness: ''Are you making this up as you go along?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Washor's performance has been cast against the uncharacteristically calm demeanor presented by Mr. Vecchione, a high-ranking assistant district attorney.</p>
        <p>Respected for his investigative prowess, Mr. Vecchione is not renowned for his warmth. In past cases, he has frequently turned from the bench, flapping his arms in exasperation. Yelling is in his nature; cursing, too.</p>
        <p>He fears neither sarcasm nor strong oratory. Seeking high bail amounts in a case involving nonconsensual organ donations, he once described a racketeering indictment as ''nothing short of a case of medical terrorism.'' In private conversations, he will sometimes turn to a third party and ask, ''What's the matter with this guy?''</p>
        <p>For the most part, he has not taken Mr. Washor's bait. But their showdown has helped fill the gallery of an expansive courtroom, one generally reserved for ceremonies.</p>
        <p>Not that there were many empty seats in the first place. The defendant, Mr. Garson, a former State Supreme Court justice, has been charged with accepting gifts to manipulate matrimonial cases. The audience for his trial has included a good number of displeased divorcées.</p>
        <p>The case was the genesis of a broad inquiry into judicial and political corruption in Brooklyn, which Mr. Vecchione has been working on for years.</p>
        <p>From across the courtroom, Mr. Washor has spared little obvious effort to provoke him, making accusations of skulduggery, shouting at witnesses and elaborately grandstanding. Before the trial began, the defense had been dealt a setback that left few other obvious strategies: an appellate court allowed prosecutors to use a certain video surveillance recording as evidence.</p>
        <p>On the recording, Mr. Garson is shown in his judicial robing room with a divorce lawyer. He accepts an envelope containing $1,000, watches the lawyer leave, opens the envelope and counts the money. Then he walks around sighing and muttering, calls the lawyer back into the room, returns the envelope but ultimately accepts the money again.</p>
        <p>Mr. Washor, faced with that evidence, has sought to portray the prosecutors as reckless and their witnesses as untrustworthy, invoking a small library of references from ''The Caine Mutiny'' to ''The Strange Case of Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde.''</p>
        <p>For cross-examination, Mr. Washor positions himself all the way at the back of the courtroom well, some 10 feet from a microphone for which he has no need. A velvet rope hangs unclasped, allowing him to pace all the way into the gallery. By turns he grips a pen or his eyeglasses, transforming each into an instrument for punching the air. He makes jokes, but when prosecution witnesses respond with humor, he shifts his tone to grave offense.</p>
        <p>Cross-examining his client's former law clerk, Mr. Washor asked about his relationship with Justice Garson. The witness responded that he had grown uncomfortable around the justice.</p>
        <p>''I didn't ask about your comfort level,'' Mr. Washor responded, loudly. ''I'm not a travel agent.''</p>
        <p>Some of his insults seem calculated to stir Mr. Vecchione to an unseemly display of aggression. Nearly every time Mr. Vecchione prepares to play an audio recording, for example, Mr. Washor yawns in exaggerated fashion.</p>
        <p>During the testimony of a disbarred divorce lawyer who has pleaded guilty to giving unlawful gratuities, the witness described what he had been told after his arrest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Washor objected, arguing that the testimony should not be allowed unless the witness could say specifically which prosecutor had spoken to him. The witness complied, recounting that it was Mr. Vecchione who had led the investigation.</p>
        <p>At that point, Mr. Washor interrupted again. Justice Berry cleared the courtroom.</p>
        <p>''Judge, we've got a major problem here,'' Mr. Washor said. ''The prosecutor has just made himself a witness in this case.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Washor asked for a mistrial, arguing that the only other remedy was to put Mr. Vecchione on the witness stand.</p>
        <p>''By the way, I would love to have the opportunity to cross-examine my colleague Mr. Vecchione,'' Mr. Washor said, ''but this is not the forum for game-playing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Vecchione argued that it was Mr. Washor himself who had prompted the witness to name him.</p>
        <p>''I asked the question just the way Mr. Washor said I should,'' Mr. Vecchione said.</p>
        <p>Justice Berry did not grant a mistrial. Later, Mr. Washor asked to see a copy of the witness's cooperation agreement. Mr. Vecchione walked across the courtroom.</p>
        <p>''Let the record reflect that defense counsel has had these documents for a good number of years,'' he said, ''but I will give them two additional copies.''</p>
        <p>The disbarred divorce lawyer remained on the witness stand for two weeks, then was called back. Mr. Washor taunted him, calling him Mr. Garson's ''pet.''</p>
        <p>When he had finished cross-examination one day, Mr. Washor asked the judge to remind the witness not to discuss his testimony. That is a standard instruction, but Mr. Washor said he did not trust the prosecutors to follow normal courtroom rules.</p>
        <p>The jury was already gone. Mr. Vecchione turned his back to the bench and muttered a profanity. He is expected to rest his case today. Then Mr. Washor will get his turn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
