<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Panel Admonishes A Beleaguered Smithsonian</title>
    <meta content="12smithsonian" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/us/12smithsonian.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839677"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Smithsonian Institution</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Small, Lawrence M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Smithsonian Institution</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Panel Admonishes A Beleaguered Smithsonian</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Senate Panel Admonishes a Beleaguered Smithsonian</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Members of Senate panel warn Smithsonian Institution officials that they must create new, more accountable management structure or risk jeopardizing support from lawmakers and public; question officials about dire conditions of its buildings and disclosure of extravagant spending that led to resignation of Lawrence M Small as its top official (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Adopting the tone of a stern parent with a wayward child, senators warned the Smithsonian Institution on Wednesday that it must create a new, more accountable management structure or risk jeopardizing support from lawmakers and the public.</p>
        <p>At a hearing of the Senate Rules and Administration Committee, which oversees the Smithsonian, officials of the institution fielded questions about the dire condition of its buildings and the disclosures of extravagant spending that led to the resignation of its top official, Lawrence M. Small, last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The committee chairman said the institution must adopt a new system of governing and a more aggressive fund-raising strategy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Adopting the tone of a stern parent with a wayward child, senators warned the Smithsonian Institution on Wednesday that it must create a new, more accountable management structure or risk jeopardizing support from lawmakers and the public.</p>
        <p>At a hearing of the Senate Rules and Administration Committee, which oversees the Smithsonian, officials of the institution fielded questions about the dire condition of its buildings and the disclosures of extravagant spending that led to the resignation of its top official, Lawrence M. Small, last month.</p>
        <p>The committee chairman, Senator Dianne Feinstein, Democrat of California, said the Smithsonian must adopt not only a new system of governing but also a more aggressive fund-raising strategy rather than expecting the federal government to foot the entire bill to fix its crumbling museums. The Smithsonian has said it needs an estimated $2.5 billion for revitalization, construction and maintenance projects.</p>
        <p>''You have an endangered institution now,'' Ms. Feinstein said. ''You have an institution that is clearly underfunded. It's got real problems that have got to be solved or they're only going to compound and get worse.''</p>
        <p>''Unless there is clear oversight,'' she said, ''I don't know how you justify public funding. The whole oversight structure has to be rethought.''</p>
        <p>The Smithsonian, which comprises 19 museums, 9 research centers and the National Zoo, gets 70 percent of its $1 billion annual operating budget from the government, with the rest coming from private donations and commercial ventures. The 17-member board meets four times a year and includes six members of Congress, the vice president and the chief justice of the United States.</p>
        <p>''The board of regents has not substantially changed since 1846,'' said Ms. Feinstein, referring to the year of the Smithsonian's founding. ''Given their day jobs,'' she said of the eight government officials on the board, ''I wonder if they can dedicate the time, attention and expertise that is so desperately needed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Small resigned as the Smithsonian's secretary on March 26 after an embattled seven-year tenure that concluded with an internal audit showing that the institution had paid for lavish personal expenses of his. And an external review committee recently reported that the Smithsonian's art institutions were ''unable to lead the nation'' because of drastic underfinancing, weaknesses in their collections and the dilapidated state of some buildings.</p>
        <p>Ms. Feinstein focused on Mr. Small's ''extraordinary housing allowance,'' of some $1.15 million a year. It included, she noted, ''an 8.32 percent mortgage interest, even though Mr. Small had no mortgage,'' and $203,000 in maintenance expenses, among them $12,000 for swimming pool upkeep.</p>
        <p>Smithsonian executives were also questioned about a report on Wednesday in The Washington Post that Mr. Small and Sheila P. Burke, who is the Smithsonian's deputy secretary and chief operating officer, were highly paid directors of the Chubb Group of Insurance Companies even as the Smithsonian renewed a contract last year giving Chubb more than $500,000 of business annually.</p>
        <p>Cristián Samper, director of the institution's National Museum of Natural History, who is serving as acting secretary of the Smithsonian, replied, ''That is one of the issues we will be reviewing with the governance committee.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Samper was referring to a panel that was created in mid-March to address the institution's unwieldy structure and mounting problems. The new committee will evaluate the Smithsonian's bylaws, measuring them against the best practices of comparable institutions. The committee is led by Patty Stonesifer, co-chairwoman of the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, who said the Smithsonian was already revising a variety of policies and taking steps ''to restrict the use of funds that appear to be personal in nature.''</p>
        <p>The controversy surrounding Mr. Small is a significant blow to the Smithsonian at a time when it is trying to persuade Congress to increase its government financing by about $100 million, from $634.9 million in this fiscal year. President Bush has proposed an increase of $44 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
