<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DUKE PROSECUTOR THROWS OUT CASE AGAINST PLAYERS</title>
    <meta content="12duke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/us/12duke.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Durham (Nc)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Duke University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Duff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barstow, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Roy (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seligmann, Reade</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, David F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finnerty, Collin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nifong, Michael B (Dist Atty)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina/Durham</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Duke University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cooper, Roy A</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Seligmann, Reade</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Evans, David F</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Finnerty, Collin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nifong, Michael B</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1D8123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="2082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DUKE PROSECUTOR THROWS OUT CASE AGAINST PLAYERS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">All Charges Dropped in Duke Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DUFF WILSON and DAVID BARSTOW; Duff Wilson reported from Raleigh, N.C., and David Barstow from New York. Brenda Goodman contributed reporting from Atlanta, and Mosi Secret from Durham, N.C.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barstow, David; Wilson, Duff</byline>
      <dateline>RALEIGH, N.C., April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>North Carolina Atty Gen Roy A Cooper clears three former Duke University lacrosse players of all sexual assault charges; calls Durham County Dist Atty Michael B Nifong 'rogue prosecutor'; says Nifong relied on 'faulty and unreliable' accusations; says players--Reade W Seligmann, David F Evans and Collin Finnerty--were wrongly accused by 'unchecked' and 'over-reaching' district attorney who ignored contradictory evidence; case provoked bitter debate over race, class and Nifong's tactics; Cooper says he considered but then rejected bringing criminal charges against accuser after reviewing sealed court files including records of her mental health history; woman continues to insist she was attacked at team party year ago; Cooper says he will leave any official sanctions against Nifong to North Carolina State Bar, which has already formally accused him of ethical violations; emotional news conference is held by three former teammates, their lawyers and families; case recalled; timeline from accusation to dismissal; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>North Carolina's attorney general declared three former Duke University lacrosse players accused of sexually assaulting a stripper innocent of all charges on Wednesday, ending a prosecution that provoked bitter debate over race, class and the tactics of the Durham County district attorney.</p>
        <p>The attorney general, Roy A. Cooper, said the players -- Reade W. Seligmann, David F. Evans, and Collin Finnerty -- had been wrongly accused by an ''unchecked'' and ''overreaching'' district attorney who had ignored contradictory evidence and instead relied on the stripper's ''faulty and unreliable'' accusations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>North Carolina’s attorney general said an overzealous district attorney had wrongly accused lacrosse players of sexual assault.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>North Carolina's attorney general declared three former Duke University lacrosse players accused of sexually assaulting a stripper innocent of all charges on Wednesday, ending a prosecution that provoked bitter debate over race, class and the tactics of the Durham County district attorney.</p>
        <p>The attorney general, Roy A. Cooper, said the players -- Reade W. Seligmann, David F. Evans, and Collin Finnerty -- had been wrongly accused by an ''unchecked'' and ''overreaching'' district attorney who had ignored contradictory evidence and instead relied on the stripper's ''faulty and unreliable'' accusations.</p>
        <p>''We believe that these cases were the result of a tragic rush to accuse and a failure to verify serious allegations,'' Mr. Cooper said at a news conference.</p>
        <p>''We have no credible evidence that an attack occurred,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cooper said he had considered but ultimately rejected the possibility of bringing criminal charges against the accuser, who continues to insist she was attacked at a team party on March 13, 2006, and asked him to go forward with the case. Mr. Cooper said his investigators had told him that the woman ''may actually believe the many different stories that she has been telling.'' He said his decision not to charge her with making false accusations was also based on a review of sealed court files, which include records of the woman's mental health history.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cooper reserved his harshest criticism for the Durham County district attorney, Michael B. Nifong, at one point even depicting him as a ''rogue prosecutor.''</p>
        <p>''In this case, with the weight of the state behind him, the Durham district attorney pushed forward unchecked,'' said Mr. Cooper, who took over the case in January. ''There were many points in the case where caution would have served justice better than bravado. And in the rush to condemn, a community and a state lost the ability to see clearly.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Cooper said that for now he would leave any official sanctions to the North Carolina State Bar, which has already taken the extraordinary step of formally accusing Mr. Nifong of numerous ethical violations, including withholding exculpatory evidence and misleading the judge who presided over the case. Mr. Cooper said he would instead seek new legislation to give the North Carolina Supreme Court greater power to remove prosecutors.</p>
        <p>''We need to learn from this and keep it from happening again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At an emotional news conference of their own on Wednesday, the three former teammates, flanked by defense lawyers and families, spoke of relief and vindication, but also of their lingering anger toward Mr. Nifong and many in the news media for what they described as a rush to believe the worst about them.</p>
        <p>''This entire experience has opened my eyes up to a tragic world of injustice I never knew existed,'' Mr. Seligmann said. ''If police officers and a district attorney can systematically railroad us with absolutely no evidence whatsoever, I can't imagine what they'd do to people who do not have the resources to defend themselves. So rather than relying on disparaging stereotypes and creating political and racial conflicts, all of us need to take a step back from this case and learn from it.</p>
        <p>''The Duke lacrosse case has shown that our society has lost sight of the most fundamental principle of our legal system: the presumption of innocence.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seligmann, 21, of Essex Fells, N.J.; Mr. Evans, 24, of Annapolis, Md.; and Mr. Finnerty, 20, of Garden City, N.Y., were initially charged with rape, sexual offense and kidnapping -- crimes that could have put them in prison for three decades. The rape charges were dropped in December.</p>
        <p>From the start, all three repeatedly proclaimed their innocence. ''These allegations are lies,'' Mr. Evans insisted on the day of his indictment.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, looking a bit older but every bit as resolved, Mr. Evans looked across a roomful of reporters and said, ''We are just as innocent today as we were back then.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong could not be reached for comment Wednesday. But his lawyer, David B. Freedman, said Mr. Nifong was ''devastated'' by the attorney general's criticisms of his conduct. Mr. Freedman said that while Mr. Nifong had ''no problem'' with the decision to exonerate the players, he was deeply wounded by Mr. Cooper's attack on his judgment and performance.</p>
        <p>''He's a person who has dedicated himself to public service for 29 years,'' Mr. Freedman said in a telephone interview on Wednesday night. ''All he cares about is public service.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong has denied violating any ethics rules, although he has acknowledged mishandling some evidence and making intemperate and unjustified remarks about the Duke lacrosse team. In the first weeks of his investigation, for example, Mr. Nifong told reporters he was certain that a rape had occurred and called the lacrosse players ''hooligans'' who were hiding behind a ''wall of silence.''</p>
        <p>In fact, three co-captains, including Mr. Evans, had cooperated fully with the police. Other team members canceled interviews on the advice of lawyers. ''There was never a blue wall of silence,'' Mr. Evans said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>If the ethics charges against him are upheld, Mr. Nifong faces a range of possible penalties, including disbarment. A preliminary hearing Friday will decide Mr. Nifong's motion to dismiss the most serious charges.</p>
        <p>Some parents of the players, meanwhile, have suggested that they might sue Mr. Nifong and Durham County. ''All options are on the table,'' Joseph B. Cheshire, a lawyer for Mr. Evans, said Wednesday when asked about possible legal action against Mr. Nifong.</p>
        <p>The accuser could not be reached for comment. Her father, a retired truck driver, said that his family continued to believe her accusations. ''I think if it had gone to court, it would be a different story altogether,'' he said in an interview at his home on Wednesday night. ''The jury would hear both sides of it. But they didn't want it to go to court. They made that clear last year.''</p>
        <p>Duke's president, Richard H. Brodhead, who weathered heavy criticism throughout the case, particularly from supporters of the three players, issued a statement welcoming the exonerations and praising the players. ''They have carried themselves with dignity through an ordeal of deep unfairness,'' Mr. Brodhead said.</p>
        <p>Even some community leaders who had previously argued that the case should have gone to trial did not object to Mr. Cooper's decision. The North Carolina chapter of the N.A.A.C.P. released a statement saying it respected and accepted the work of the attorney general's office. Irving Joyner, a law professor at North Carolina Central University, who had been monitoring the case for the N.A.A.C.P., echoed that theme, saying, ''Based on my personal knowledge of him and high respect of him, I accept his conclusions.''</p>
        <p>Likewise, the Rape, Abuse and Incest National Network, one of the largest such groups in the nation, released a statement saying it was satisfied with the attorney general's decision to drop all charges.</p>
        <p>With its overtones of race, sex and privilege, the Duke case instantly drew national news media attention. The accuser was a poor, black, local single mother working at an escort service while enrolled at the predominantly black North Carolina Central University in Durham; the Duke students were relatively well-off, white out-of-staters -- members of a storied lacrosse team at one of the nation's most prestigious universities. The accuser's vivid account of racist and misogynistic taunts also fueled a simmering debate about the off-field behavior of elite athletes and the proper role of big-time sports on America's college campuses.</p>
        <p>Yet as the months passed, as the specifics of her accusations kept shifting, and as defense lawyers skillfully highlighted other glaring weaknesses and contradictions in the evidence, the case came to be seen by many as justice run off the rails by political correctness and the political ambitions of Mr. Nifong.</p>
        <p>When the accusations arose, Mr. Nifong was in a close political campaign. Appointed acting district attorney in 2005 by Gov. Michael F. Easley, he was seeking election against a better-known opponent. Mr. Nifong, who mentioned the case at some campaign appearances, won the crucial primary election -- and most of the black vote -- on May 2, weeks after announcing indictments against two of the players.</p>
        <p>The players' supporters have long contended that Mr. Nifong used the Duke case to advance his political prospects.</p>
        <p>''In his search for a false conviction, this is a man who appealed to racial and class hatred,'' Mr. Cheshire said at Wednesday's news conference.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong just as vehemently denied the accusations of political manipulation. But in bringing charges, Mr. Nifong discounted evidence of innocence -- including alibi evidence from time-stamped photographs and cellphone records -- and relied almost entirely on the woman's photo identification of the three suspects and on a report by the sexual assault nurse who examined the woman.</p>
        <p>The photo lineup procedure was riddled with errors and contradictions and appeared to violate Durham, state and federal guidelines. The police, instructed by Mr. Nifong, showed the woman pictures only of lacrosse team members, with no filler photographs of people who could not possibly be suspects.</p>
        <p>The sexual assault nurse's report of blunt force trauma was undermined by other accounts of her activities as a stripper the weekend before the lacrosse party. There was no other forensic evidence to support her account. And other than the accuser, no one claimed to have witnessed the assault --including a second dancer hired for the evening and the 20 or so men at the party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cooper succinctly summed up the evidence this way: ''No D.N.A. confirms the accuser's story. No other witness confirms her story. Other evidence contradicts her story. She contradicts herself.''</p>
        <p>One of those contradictions forced Mr. Nifong to drop the rape charges in December. The woman, who had repeatedly said she endured violent penile penetration, suddenly said she could no longer be sure what had penetrated her. This came after it had been revealed that sophisticated DNA tests found no traces from any of the three defendants -- or any other Duke lacrosse player -- on her body or clothes. DNA from other men, however, was found.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong at first vowed to proceed with the remaining charges of kidnapping and sexual offense. But in January, facing ethics charges and mounting criticism from editorial pages and bloggers, he asked Mr. Cooper to take over the case. Mr. Cooper said he and his staff spent three months reinvestigating the case, interviewing Mr. Nifong, police investigators, defense lawyers, the accuser and other witnesses.</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Cooper said, it was not even a close call. Their investigation, he emphasized, ''shows clearly'' that there was insufficient evidence to bring any charges.</p>
        <p>On the Duke campus, some students greeted Mr. Cooper's decision as a welcome relief from months of turmoil. ''The Duke bashing got old really quickly,'' said Tucker Page, a junior from Portland, Ore. ''To pigeonhole all students as racist and sexist -- it felt like the media was personally attacking us.''</p>
        <p>After the accusations surfaced, Mr. Brodhead, the university president, canceled the lacrosse season and accepted the coach's resignation. He also appointed panels to examine the team's behavior and the university's handling of the case. He invited Mr. Finnerty and Mr. Seligmann back to school after the rape charges were dropped, but they declined. Mr. Evans had graduated the day before he was charged.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Evans is working, while Mr. Finnerty and Mr. Seligmann said they were looking forward to continuing their educations. All three said the searing experience of being falsely accused before their fellow students and an entire nation had drawn them closer to their families. ''To hell and back,'' is how Mr. Evans described the past year.</p>
        <p>Duke officials said the furor had not hurt their admissions or fund-raising efforts. The university had 19,170 applicants this year -- including record numbers of African-Americans (2,190), Asians or Asian-Americans (5,173) and Latinos (1,303). The men's lacrosse team, ranked third in the nation just before the accusations, was recently ranked fourth by Lacrosse Magazine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nifong aside, the most lasting damage may be to the credibility of North Carolina's criminal justice system. Mr. Cooper, who said he would issue a report next week detailing all the evidentiary weaknesses in the Duke case, said the prosecution had indeed raised broader questions about the state's criminal justice system.</p>
        <p>''This case,'' he said, ''shows the enormous consequences of overreaching by a prosecutor.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
