<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prospering in an Implosion; Subprime Market's Fall Plays to the Strengths Of a Bold Contrarian</title>
    <meta content="12lend" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/business/12lend.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Capital Markets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Devaney, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bajaj, Vikas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EED9123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prospering in an Implosion; Subprime Market's Fall Plays to the Strengths Of a Bold Contrarian</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Subprime Market Implodes, a Contrarian Prospers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIKAS BAJAJ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bajaj, Vikas</byline>
      <dateline>KEY BISCAYNE, Fla.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Devaney has ammassed fortune by dealing in asset-backed bonds through his United Capital Markets company; often makes decisions against conventional market wisdom, turning big profits while others falter; his early beginnings in business are profiled; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a clubby market where securities based on risky mortgages, credit card debt and other financial assets are traded, John Devaney is known for making brash pronouncements -- and for often being proved right.</p>
        <p>''I personally hate subprime,'' Mr. Devaney declared at an American Securitization Forum conference in late January, ''and I'm kind of hoping the whole thing explodes.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the markets rise and fall, the owner of United Capital Markets has been able to profit handsomely by taking advantage of the wide swings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a clubby market where securities based on risky mortgages, credit card debt and other financial assets are traded, John Devaney is known for making brash pronouncements -- and for often being proved right.</p>
        <p>''I personally hate subprime,'' Mr. Devaney declared at an American Securitization Forum conference in late January, ''and I'm kind of hoping the whole thing explodes.''</p>
        <p>He certainly got his wish. Within a month of his remarks, several big lenders to people with weak credit -- specialists in what is known as the subprime market -- began collapsing. Now, as investors and policy makers ponder the wreckage, it is clear that asset-backed securities, or bonds, played an important role in subprime's rapid rise and its messy fall.</p>
        <p>And as a number of big players swoop in, hoping to make a killing while cleaning up the mess, Mr. Devaney is counting on his contrarian instincts to serve him well in the uncertain atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Devaney, 36, has amassed a fortune he estimates at $250 million by becoming a major dealer in asset-backed bonds through his company, United Capital Markets. As the powerfully fickle market has gone through several giddy booms and wrenching shake-ups in the last decade, he and other nimble traders in a small fraternity of investors have been able to profit handsomely by taking advantage of the market's wide swings.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people would argue that markets are very efficient,'' he said during an interview at his home here on the Intracoastal Waterway, where he keeps his 140-foot boat and has filled the walls of his mansion with paintings by Renoir, Cezanne and others. But ''in these over-the-counter markets, fear and confidence hold completely equal weightings to driving prices up and down as do the fundamentals.''</p>
        <p>Asset-backed securities have become an important source of capital for consumer and business debt, generating fortunes on Wall Street. But despite remaining a relative outsider, Mr. Devaney has done very well indeed.</p>
        <p>His success over the last six years has made him prominent in Florida social, political and philanthropic circles, donating to a range of causes from literacy programs to the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>Peers and colleagues describe him as both a court jester who entertains and shocks contemporaries at conferences and a visionary who stays up late to glean details from dense bond documents. They wonder, though, whether he can continue to stay ahead of the game.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there is anyone in the business who wouldn't want to be John Devaney,'' said Mark H. Adelson, a senior analyst with Nomura Securities in New York, ''to have the insights and guts to do what he did, as well as the managerial skills, the analytic skills to pull it off.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Devaney says he buys when others are selling in a panic. He sells when others are ready to buy, analysts and fellow traders say.</p>
        <p>His experience trading mobile home loans, credit card debt and airplane leases after the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11 shows that while the secondary market for securitized assets has grown huge, it is still inefficient at gauging and pricing risk, especially for out-of-favor assets and in times of stress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Devaney said he first realized he could profit from the market's flaws in 1998, when investors rushed out of risky bonds after the hedge fund Long-Term Capital Management buckled and Russia defaulted on its debts. Unnerved by those crises, many investors dumped bonds backed by aggressive home equity loans made to people with good credit.</p>
        <p>''It was just like it is now: 'Oh! Oh! Another news tidbit of New Century news. Oh, my god!' '' he said in a mockingly hysterical tone, referring to the mortgage company that has filed for bankruptcy protection.</p>
        <p>From the prospectuses for those securities, Mr. Devaney divined that bondholders would get their money back even if 30 percent of the homeowners defaulted on their loans. He bought the bonds for 50 cents on the dollar for himself and for clients.</p>
        <p>As the scare faded and it became apparent that homeowners would not default in big numbers, he sold for handsome profits. It was a formula he has used time and again ever since.</p>
        <p>Mr. Devaney is filled with a frenetic energy as he speaks, his voice rising as he builds up his arguments. He gesticulates extensively and stands up several times, once to demonstrate with his hands the small size of the rented house where he started his firm in 1999. He long ago kicked off his shoes; his BlackBerry and its holster are strewn on the floor.</p>
        <p>The packaging and selling of mortgages into bonds, a process known as securitization, is not new. It has been used for decades by Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the government-sponsored mortgage buyers, and it has helped lower the cost of mortgages.</p>
        <p>Beginning in the 1990s, though, Wall Street started securitizing all manner of financial assets, including riskier mortgages that Fannie and Freddie could not buy. Last year, the industry issued $1.23 trillion in asset-backed bonds, nearly half being mortgage related. That is up from less than $300 billion in 1999.</p>
        <p>With interest rates at historic lows in recent years, investors eagerly snapped up high-yielding asset-backed bonds, sometimes at a premium to their face value.</p>
        <p>It now appears, though, that subprime lenders pumped up their business as the housing boom faded by not requiring down payments and, in many cases, not bothering to verify borrowers' incomes. Those practices, coupled with weakening home prices, have led to a surge in defaults.</p>
        <p>''People don't know what is under the hood of these securities,'' said Scott C. Syphax, president and chief executive of the Nehemiah Corporation of America, a nonprofit group that provides down-payment assistance to low-income borrowers.</p>
        <p>Investors in subprime bonds believed they would be protected by losses because of how the securities were structured. So far, most have been, but Mr. Devaney and others believe that the holders of some bonds could be hurt as defaults rise further. He hopes to profit from their loss.</p>
        <p>Asset-backed bonds are sliced into several segments, each with its own risk rating -- AAA, BBB, BB and so on. Investors in the top grades earn a lower interest rate but are paid first. Those at the bottom earn a bigger return, but if too many homeowners miss payments, they are left holding an empty bag.</p>
        <p>The AAA segment typically makes up the biggest portion of the securities, but it could not exist if enough investors were not willing to buy lower-quality portions.</p>
        <p>It is in those subordinated segments that Mr. Devaney operates.</p>
        <p>The son of a lawyer and a tutor, Mr. Devaney grew up in Key Biscayne. He showed an early aptitude for math that was encouraged by his mother, the tutor.</p>
        <p>When he was a teenager, his parents divorced; his older brother dropped out of high school and struggled with drug addiction, leaving Mr. Devaney adrift. He was thrown out of a boarding school for sneaking off campus to attend parties. ''I just didn't care,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He started shaping up in college. Admitted under probation to Colorado State University, he studied finance and English. He bought a 2,500-square-foot house and made his monthly payments by renting out rooms to friends. During two summer vacations, he earned $60,000 by reviving a moribund bar at a hotel in Miami in exchange for a share of the profits.</p>
        <p>In a sign of what was to come, he also made $120,000 trading options in the shares of Motorola. (He lost most of that money in a single bet on the options after he graduated.)</p>
        <p>After returning to Florida, Mr. Devaney worked attwo small investment firms selling and trading bonds before he started United Capital in 1999.</p>
        <p>The firm now employs more than 80 people. Mr. Devaney owns the largest land holding here, including the house that was the setting for the Al Pacino movie ''Scarface.''</p>
        <p>He manages a hedge fund that has $620 million in assets and that had an estimated return of 40 percent last year. His nascent investment-banking business recently became the financial partner for a five-million-square-feet condominium project near Boca Raton.</p>
        <p>His reputation was established, in part, from big parties on his yacht, Positive Carry, a term for borrowing at a lower rate than you earn from your investments, at industry conferences. At the meetings, he frequently sponsors performances by Jay Leno and bands like Counting Crows and the Doobie Brothers. His Gulfstream jet is outfitted with broadband Internet service, he says, so he can trade while he is traveling.</p>
        <p>Joseph M. Donovan, who retired as the head of Credit Suisse's asset-backed business in January, says Mr. Devaney, whom he likes, reminds him of a lot of successful strong-willed bond traders. ''He is outspoken, and he is brash,'' Mr. Donovan said. ''He has a way of making his voice heard maybe louder than his resources would otherwise indicate.''</p>
        <p>The image of the lavish and loud millionaire rankles Mr. Devaney, who said he had stopped drinking when his wife became pregnant with the first of their three children.</p>
        <p>The plane, boat and parties save time, he said, help make a name for his company, and provide tax benefits.</p>
        <p>''It's not to be flamboyant; it's for advertising,'' he said. ''We don't have a huge sales force like Merrill Lynch or Morgan Stanley or Credit Suisse.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Devaney's ambitions are big. He hopes eventually to take United Capital public and raise money in a corporate bond offering so he can have a steady source of capital. Last year, the firm traded $29.9 billion in asset-backed securities and earned net income of $90 million.</p>
        <p>But to take his firm to the next level, Mr. Devaney would have to delegate more responsibility and diversify away from the riskier segments of the financial markets.</p>
        <p>''I can take less risk,'' he said. ''I have already arrived.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
