<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What to Expect When a Sitcom's Expecting: Desperate Friends and Life Lessons</title>
    <meta content="12heff" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/arts/television/12heff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">ABC Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Westfeldt, Jennifer</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DB123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What to Expect When a Sitcom's Expecting: Desperate Friends and Life Lessons</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What to Expect When a Sitcom’s Expecting: Desperate Friends and Life Lessons</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Notes From the Underbelly'' is a revolting sitcom about pregnancy. Watch and you'll lose your appetite for life. The characters are alternadads and shopaholics who consider ''Lost'' pornography and make sex jokes that belong in 40th-birthday cards by the Har-Dee-Har line.</p>
        <p>''Notes'' has one of those pushy set-ups in which a noxious central couple is supposed to be normal, while their friends are wacky and desperate. Just turn it off and forget, for the evening, that you have ever heard of television. (It starts tonight on ABC. Forget that too.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>“Notes From the Underbelly” is a revolting sitcom about pregnancy. Watch and you’ll lose your appetite for life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Notes From the Underbelly'' is a revolting sitcom about pregnancy. Watch and you'll lose your appetite for life. The characters are alternadads and shopaholics who consider ''Lost'' pornography and make sex jokes that belong in 40th-birthday cards by the Har-Dee-Har line.</p>
        <p>''Notes'' has one of those pushy set-ups in which a noxious central couple is supposed to be normal, while their friends are wacky and desperate. Just turn it off and forget, for the evening, that you have ever heard of television. (It starts tonight on ABC. Forget that too.)</p>
        <p>Andrew (Peter Cambor) wants a baby, and Lauren (Jennifer Westfeldt, who played the title role in ''Kissing Jessica Stein''), his wife, does not. Then, before the opening credits of the first episode, Lauren wants a baby after all.</p>
        <p>She becomes pregnant. She finds it hard to give up expensive clothes. Andrew finds it hard to give up nothing. He's gung-ho for fatherhood. He's so annoying in the first episode, he might break some sort of prime-time record.</p>
        <p>Lauren comes to embrace pregnancy with the generic neurotic pluck that now defines most bland television blondes. To underscore how boring she is, her two friends are good-and-evil caricatures: a cookie-sweet housewife, Julie (Melanie Paxson), and a barracuda single lawyer, Cooper (Rachael Harris), who sleeps around.</p>
        <p>There are too many good comic actors in Hollywood for a show like this to have a dud cast and, sure enough, both Ms. Paxson and Ms. Harris have skills. Ms. Harris's flat affect and convincing sophistication are an antidote to the tone-deaf goofing on display elsewhere. And Ms. Paxson comes through in scenes of bravura condescension, as when Julie instructs a barista on how to make a custom whipped coffee drink. ''Now stay focused,'' she chirps. ''And I'll walk you through it.''</p>
        <p>By Episode 2 Andrew has decided he wants Lauren to quit her job as a college counselor at a prep school. As a landscape architect he wants to be the family's sole breadwinner.</p>
        <p>By the episode's end everybody has learned the dangers of multitasking and the wonders of work.</p>
        <p>''I thought I could do it all, but I can't,'' Andrew says in a moonlit reconciliation scene with Lauren. ''Notes'' has a nice continuity to it. Just as almost nothing before this has been funny, this fake-poignant moment isn't touching.</p>
        <p>Notes From the Underbelly  ABC, tonight at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time.</p>
        <p>Created by Stacy Traub; Kim Tannenbaum, Eric Tannenbaum, Barry Sonnenfeld and Ms. Traub, executive producers. A production of the Tannenbaum Company, Hill Three Productions in association with Warner Brothers Television. Based on the novel by Risa Green.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jennifer Westfeldt (Lauren), Peter Cambor (Andrew), Michael Weaver (Danny), Rachael Harris (Cooper), Melanie Paxson (Julie) and Sunkrish Bala (Eric).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
