<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Colleges Need A Reply. May I See Your Notes?</title>
    <meta content="12Online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/fashion/12Online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839635"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Online Shopper"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4DD123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Colleges Need A Reply. May I See Your Notes?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Colleges Need a Reply. May I See Your Notes?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''WARM congratulations,'' said the letter, which came last week addressed to my 18-year-old daughter.</p>
        <p>The phone rang while Zoe was filing the letter with the others -- she also received an ''I look forward to meeting you on campus'' and a ''We are pleased to provide you'' letter on heavy embossed stationery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A wealth of admission letters. Now what is the problem again?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''WARM congratulations,'' said the letter, which came last week addressed to my 18-year-old daughter.</p>
        <p>The phone rang while Zoe was filing the letter with the others -- she also received an ''I look forward to meeting you on campus'' and a ''We are pleased to provide you'' letter on heavy embossed stationery.</p>
        <p>'' 'Angelina' is on line one,'' I informed her. ''And 'Brad' sent you another mash note.''</p>
        <p>Angelina is our code name for one of the small liberal arts colleges in the Midwest (enrollment 1,450, student-to-faculty ratio nine to one) that luckily wasn't as picky as the Ivies this year. Although Harvard accepted fewer than 9 percent of its star-studded applicants, Angelina still had eyes for B students from the West Coast. So did Brad (enrollment of 1,418; student-to-faculty ratio of 12 to 1).</p>
        <p>''And 'Jennifer' left a message earlier,'' I said. ''She hopes you don't pick 'Angelina.' ''</p>
        <p>Welcome to admitted-student season, when many of the same high school seniors who worried that they might not get in anywhere are being courted like celebrities by colleges that accepted them. The tables turn in April, when admissions officers are well aware that the students they want probably got into other similar colleges, too.</p>
        <p>Which should be a relief. Except for one tiny problem. After my daughter and her friends were warned that acceptance rates are dropping at the top colleges, they all applied to twice as many colleges as they would have back in the days before everyone started worrying about how likely they were to be rejected.</p>
        <p>And as a result, they ended up with a nice problem to have. They were accepted to too many colleges, including ones they've never seen. In the end, they can pick only one college. From our town in Northern California, Claire is trying to figure out if she would prefer Bard College to Boston University. Would Lucy like New York University?</p>
        <p>So how to choose? The ideal way would be to visit the colleges that sent acceptance letters. But not everyone has the time or money to travel to see multiple campuses before the May 1 deadline for sending a deposit to most colleges.</p>
        <p>I wondered if the Internet could help. When my daughter and her friends were trying to identify which colleges to apply to, they gathered information from college Web sites, online ratings sites and college discussion forums.</p>
        <p>So now that they had to narrow their choices, was there a different way to glean information online?</p>
        <p>For advice, I phoned Beatrice Flair, a college counselor at Benjamin Franklin High School in New Orleans, a public charter school that encourages students to aim for the top colleges nationwide.</p>
        <p>Ms. Flair was familiar with the problem.</p>
        <p>''I had a kid one year who applied to 28 schools and got into most of them,'' she said. ''With every school that is Tier 1, there is no way to tell ahead of time if you're going to get in.''</p>
        <p>''So how do you narrow it down from 28 to 1?'' I asked. ''Start by looking at the schools' Web sites?''</p>
        <p>''Many kids have already used the information on those sites to the nth degree, and what more can be there that they don't already know?'' Ms. Flair said. ''Unless there's a section of specific information for admitted students. That would be a place to go. Also, you might find e-mail addresses for admissions reps and professors. Send them questions. Use their answers to compare schools.''</p>
        <p>Another well-known source of information is Collegeconfidential.com, where students and parents compare notes about colleges. Less well known is one of the site's new sections -- called ''campus visits'' -- with hundreds of reports (filed anonymously) that describe everything from atmosphere in the dining hall (''the staff in the cafeteria were very unfriendly,'' wrote TheVeganActress of Knox College) to the small details (''little or no air conditioning. Dirty bathrooms,'' drummerdude--07 wrote of Dartmouth).</p>
        <p>But don't rely too heavily on one opinion. ''It's good to communicate with people who have had the opportunity to visit, but at the same time, take their comments with a grain of salt,'' Ms. Flair said. Similarly, it's time to stop worrying about ratings. While a college-ranking site like Usnews.com (where the premium online edition of ''America's Best Colleges 2007'' costs $14.95) may be useful if you're on a waiting list and want to find out if that college admitted any wait-listed students last year, some counselors say it's time to stop obsessing over a college's general ranking.</p>
        <p>Michele Hernandez, a college consultant and author of ''A Is for Admission,'' (Warner Books 1999), said: ''What does it matter if one school is No. 1 and one is No. 3? You can't split hairs like that when what matters now is to get beneath the surface and find out which school you'll really like being at the most. Now is the time to look at the social things, and how's the parking, all the things that you'll care about when you get there.''</p>
        <p>A site that uses those measures to compare colleges is College Prowler, which also publishes 233 college guidebooks. It has finished processing survey data from current students. This information is on a searchable database at Collegeprowler.com (an annual subscription is $39.95).</p>
        <p>''We grade schools in nontraditional categories, and we're particularly strong at helping you make sure you're going to fit in socially,'' said Luke Skurman, chief executive of College Prowler.</p>
        <p>For instance, if you're set on the Big Ten and are unsure whether you'll be happier at Illinois, Wisconsin or Michigan, you can use Collegeprowler.com to compare the colleges in such categories as Greek life (in which the three earn grades ranging from A-minus to A-plus) and night life (Michigan gets B-plus and the other two A-minus).</p>
        <p>The biggest drawback to the College Prowler guides is that there aren't enough of them.</p>
        <p>''We're adding more,'' Mr. Skurman said. ''Every time someone searches for a term on our Web site, we see the schools where our actual customers really are the most interested in. College of New Jersey, Drew University, Texas Tech, Lake Forest, Sewanee, DePaul, they're all books we're going to be starting very shortly.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Flair, the college counselor, said students shouldn't agonize over a decision.</p>
        <p>''If they've made good choices when they were applying, then they have a lot of good places to choose from,'' she said.</p>
        <p>I hope my daughter follows that advice. I'm sure Angelina will understand if Zoe prefers Jennifer after all.</p>
        <p>Online Shopper E-mail: Slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
