<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He's Not My Grandpa. He's My Dad.</title>
    <meta content="12dads" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/fashion/12dads.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070419T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839641"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3DD123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He's Not My Grandpa. He's My Dad.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">He’s Not My Grandpa. He’s My Dad.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS VINCIGUERRA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vinciguerra, Thomas</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LATE in 1996, while rehearsing for a production of ''A Christmas Carol'' in New York, Tony Randall was giddily anticipating becoming a father -- at the age of 77.</p>
        <p>''What I look forward to,'' he said during a break, ''is when the kid is 15 and we go out in the yard to play ball. I'll only be 90.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The children of a late-life father live with the fear he will die before they grow up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LATE in 1996, while rehearsing for a production of ''A Christmas Carol'' in New York, Tony Randall was giddily anticipating becoming a father -- at the age of 77.</p>
        <p>''What I look forward to,'' he said during a break, ''is when the kid is 15 and we go out in the yard to play ball. I'll only be 90.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Randall never made it. He was 84 when he died in 2004, leaving behind not only a 7-year-old daughter, Julia, but also a 6-year-old son, Jefferson.</p>
        <p>In December 1996, inspired in part by Mr. Randall's well-publicized late fatherhood (his wife was 26 at the time), I wrote an article for The New York Times about men having children at a stage in life when their peers were usually contemplating a move to Florida or their next cardiogram. One proud papa dubbed them start-over dads, or SODs for short.</p>
        <p>The news of Mr. Randall's late fatherhood -- and that of other celebrity SODs around the same time -- evoked a fair amount of tut-tutting. Some joked that these creaky specimens wouldn't be able to head off their tykes as they marred the walls with crayon or played in traffic. Others thought SODs inherently selfish, knowing they might die before their new children were grown. ''To intentionally deprive a child of a father is an awful sin,'' one reader wrote in reaction to my article.</p>
        <p>Under the circumstances, it seemed natural to check in with some of the same fathers 10 years later to see how they are faring in their eighth or even ninth decade. Mortality is the issue paramount in most of their minds, although whether it is more so compared with other men their age is difficult to say.</p>
        <p>A decade ago, Sy Coopersmith, a psychotherapist who lives in Great Neck, N.Y., told me that his young daughter, Andie, ''wants to know if I'm going to live, and I say, 'I hope so -- until you're a grown woman.' '' So far, so good. Andie is 16, and Mr. Coopersmith is 75. That he could die before his daughter reaches adulthood ''is a reality that I live with,'' he said. ''When we got married, my wife had me promise that I'd give her at least 10 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coopersmith could be reasonably confident about keeping that promise: when Andie was born, he was just shy of 60. At that age, according to the National Center for Health Statistics, the average American man can expect to live 20.5 years longer.</p>
        <p>Many well-known figures have lately joined the SOD ranks. Among them are Rod Stewart, who had a son when he was 60; Paul McCartney (a daughter at 61); and Kenny Rogers (identical twin boys at 65). In 2004, at 63, the actor George Lazenby had a son; a twin boy and girl followed in 2005. Julio Iglesias, 63, is expecting his wife to give birth shortly.</p>
        <p>SODs remain a pretty consistent bunch. Generally they are affluent professionals, who can afford new children during their golden years. They usually want to oblige the maternal instincts of a younger wife, or they hope that new children will help give them new life.</p>
        <p>They also remain a determinedly tiny minority. Among registered United States births in 2004, in only 2,127 cases were the fathers 60 or older, according to the Center for Health Statistics. In 1994 the figure was 2,534. In each year, that was barely 0.1 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>''It's such a new phenomenon that there's a dearth of studies about it,'' said Andrew J. Cherlin, a professor of sociology at Johns Hopkins and the author of books about the American family. ''We've never had men living so long and having new families. I know many men who become fathers at age 40, 45 or 50 because they met their wives in midlife and decided to have children. Graying at the temples is not new among fathers. But a head of white hair is.''</p>
        <p>There are growing indications that SODhood may entail risks for children. In recent years studies have suggested that older fathers are more likely to have children with autism, schizophrenia, dwarfism and other serious problems.</p>
        <p>''There's certainly evidence of damaged sperm in older men, and for a long time there's been a tendency to blame women for these congenital defects,'' said Dr. Robert N. Butler, the president of the International Longevity Center.</p>
        <p>But David Popenoe, a director of the National Marriage Project at Rutgers University, noted a biological trade-off. ''This may surprise you, but in many cases these older fathers' testosterone levels have dropped, so they tend to be more nurturing,'' he said. ''There are some real hormonal changes here.''</p>
        <p>Certainly many SODs grow more relaxed as they grow older.</p>
        <p>''I must say the feeling is good,'' said Saul Cohen, 69, the chairman of Maxim Securities Group in Manhattan and the father of Lily, 10. ''I don't think I react like I used to. I'm not as quick off the trigger. I'm more laid-back.''</p>
        <p>Andie Coopersmith said that her father is both mellow and involved: ''He knows everything that's going on with me. But just because he's older, he's not more strict. Most kids think that he has me on a leash, but he doesn't.''</p>
        <p>A major benefit of being a start-over dad is that the men no longer need to scramble up the professional ladder. ''It's so pleasant,'' said Dr. J. Allan Hobson, 73, a former Harvard Medical School professor of psychiatry and the father of twin 10-year-olds, Andrew and Matthew. ''My success as a scientist depended on my neglecting my first set of children. Now that I'm retired, we have a lot more time together.''</p>
        <p>As they have matured, the children of many SODs have grown to appreciate their status. Pamela Lowe of Manhattan used to get teased because her father, Morton, was 69 when she was born.</p>
        <p>''I was so embarrassed when the little girls came up to me,'' said Pamela, who will be 18 in May. ''Now I'm so proud that he's different.''</p>
        <p>As time passes, the children of late-life fathers find themselves in an unusual position, with step-siblings who are old enough to be their parents. In extreme cases, different sets of children of the same father can find themselves competing for love and inheritances.</p>
        <p>''Issues of divorce still affect children in their 20s, 30s, even 40s,'' said Dan Hogan, the executive director of Fathers &amp; Families, a Boston-based group that encourages men to stay involved with their families after divorce. ''They often have very strong feelings, sometimes surprisingly so.''</p>
        <p>That is true for the adult daughter of one start-over dad. She bears her father's second wife and daughter no ill will. But she prefers not to be in touch with them.</p>
        <p>''My father was a self-involved narcissistic guy,'' said the woman, who is quoted anonymously to respect her family's privacy. ''I spent my life trying to get his attention. But I could only get it for a millisecond. So my relationship with his second wife was greatly complicated. I feel that my father replaced not only my mother, but me, when he married again.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, she said that her father once told friends, ''I wish you could hear from my daughter, but she hasn't been born yet.''</p>
        <p>If emotional problems for SOD families are difficult, physical problems are inescapable. In 2001, Dr. Hobson, the retired psychiatry professor, had a stroke that left him in poor health. Moe Belin of Manhattan, the 84-year-old father of Mollie, 17, suffered a heart attack three years ago. He passed out in the bathroom and came to in the hospital.</p>
        <p>''The only thing I thought when I woke up was, 'Mollie, Mollie, I went and got sick on her,' '' he recalled. ''It bothers me that I put this little girl through all that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Belin recovered. He still hits the gym at 6:30 a.m. Each night, Mollie stops at his bedside to ask, ''How do you feel, 1 to 10?'' Usually he gives her a reassuring number, and then she goes off to sleep.</p>
        <p>Sometimes no amount of reassurance can help. The writer George Plimpton died at 76 in 2003, leaving behind 9-year-old twin girls. His widow, Sarah, had very much wanted them. Now she is reconsidering what being a SOD entails.</p>
        <p>''It's a wonderful idea that these men are having these children,'' Mrs. Plimpton said. ''But at the first sign of trouble with the father's health, things often go rapidly downhill. It's not for the faint of heart.''</p>
        <p>MR. Randall's widow, Heather, wonders if she did the right thing for her children by her decision. ''I suppose I have some strains of guilt over that,'' she told the talk-show host Larry King. (Mr. King is a start-over dad himself, having had two children in his 60s.)</p>
        <p>Lori Cohen Ransohoff also has regrets. She was married to Dr. Joseph Ransohoff, a neurosurgeon 41 years her senior. When he died in 2001, their children -- Jake, then 11, and Jade, 5 -- were hit hard.</p>
        <p>''I don't ever really remember preparing the kids,'' Mrs. Ransohoff said. ''He was so healthy I just took it for granted. I never thought that far ahead. Looking back, I realize that was foolish. Now I tell my daughter, 'Maybe you shouldn't marry an older man.' ''</p>
        <p>She laughed a bit. ''Here I am, giving her advice I didn't follow.''</p>
        <p>Jade Ransohoff, now 11, doesn't know what to think. ''A lot of my friends think they have the worst life when their parents are divorced,'' she said. ''But they get to see both of them. Having your dad dead is different. You don't get to see him.''</p>
        <p>In some sense, to be a start-over dad is to live in semi-denial, acknowledging the inevitable while not being incapacitated by it. Echoing Mr. Randall, Morton Lowe, now 87, speaks of his future with Pamela.</p>
        <p>''When I make the 90th, I'll be very happy,'' Mr. Lowe said. ''If she can make it through college, and I can be there, then maybe I can walk her down the aisle.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 19, 2007, Thursday  An article last week about men who become fathers late in life referred incorrectly to their children who have different mothers. The children of those men would be half-siblings, not step-siblings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 19, 2007, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article last week about men who become fathers late in life referred incorrectly to their children who have different mothers. The children of those men would be half-siblings, not step-siblings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
