<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Bell Hearing, More Action Outside Court Than In</title>
    <meta content="12bell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/nyregion/12bell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD9123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Bell Hearing, More Action Outside Court Than In</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Bell Hearing, More Action Outside Court Than In</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELLEN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Ellen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The three detectives charged in the shooting that killed Sean Bell returned to court for a brief hearing yesterday, surrounded by a cast of supporters and detractors who will most likely become fixtures as the case wends its way toward trial.</p>
        <p>Detectives Michael Oliver, Gescard F. Isnora and Marc Cooper slipped in and out of the courthouse through a side door, taking pains to avoid photographers. But Michael Palladino, president of the Detectives' Endowment Association, planted himself firmly on the front steps of the courthouse, trying to make himself heard over members of the New Black Panther Party who were chanting, ''Today's pigs, tomorrow's bacon!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hearing Wednesday was over in 10 minutes, but the battle lines being drawn outside the Queens Criminal Courts Building promised to last.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The three detectives charged in the shooting that killed Sean Bell returned to court for a brief hearing yesterday, surrounded by a cast of supporters and detractors who will most likely become fixtures as the case wends its way toward trial.</p>
        <p>Detectives Michael Oliver, Gescard F. Isnora and Marc Cooper slipped in and out of the courthouse through a side door, taking pains to avoid photographers. But Michael Palladino, president of the Detectives' Endowment Association, planted himself firmly on the front steps of the courthouse, trying to make himself heard over members of the New Black Panther Party who were chanting, ''Today's pigs, tomorrow's bacon!''</p>
        <p>The hearing was over in 10 minutes, but the battle lines being drawn outside the Queens Criminal Courts Building in Kew Gardens promised to last.</p>
        <p>Mr. Palladino said the detectives' right to a fair trial had already been damaged by ''the acts and antics of people like Al Sharpton,'' who led protests of the shooting, and that a change of venue might be necessary. A few yards away, a lawyer for Mr. Bell's parents complained about ''outright lies and falsehoods being spread about Sean Bell.''</p>
        <p>''They're wounding the family every time they do it, and they know they are,'' said Peter St. George Davis, who is representing William and Valerie Bell. Mr. Bell, standing quietly behind his lawyer, said only that he does not intend to miss a single court date.</p>
        <p>''I love my son,'' he said. ''I'll be here, rain or shine.''</p>
        <p>The Bell shooting has been compared to the death of Amadou Diallo, who was shot and killed in a storm of 41 police bullets in 1999. In that case, defense lawyers were granted a change of venue and the case was tried in Albany, where the four officers involved were all acquitted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bell, 23, was leaving Club Kalua with friends after his bachelor party on Nov. 25, hours before he was to be married, unaware that they were being followed by an undercover officer who believed that one of them may have been armed. The officer called for backup, and in the confrontation that followed, five officers fired 50 shots into the men's car as it moved toward them, killing Mr. Bell and wounding the other men, Joseph Guzman, 31, and Trent Benefield, 23. No gun was found in the car.</p>
        <p>Detectives Oliver and Isnora both face charges of first- and second-degree manslaughter, which could bring a sentence of 25 years in prison if they are convicted. Detective Cooper faces two misdemeanor charges of reckless endangerment, which could bring a sentence of a year in prison.</p>
        <p>The hearing itself yesterday broke little new ground. Lawyers for the three officers pressed for the release of preliminary discovery they are entitled to by statute, including the grand jury minutes, coroner's report and toxicology reports. At the next court date, May 14, they will establish a time frame for defense motions, which could include a motion to dismiss the indictments or separate the officers' cases from one another. Defense lawyers could also request a change of venue or waive the right to a jury trial, which would place the case before Justice Arthur Cooperman of State Supreme Court in Queens.</p>
        <p>''We've been talking about that nonstop,'' but have not reached a firm conclusion, said Philip E. Karasyk, who is representing the undercover officer, Detective Isnora. Mr. Karasyk said he was eager for the release of discovery, which will allow the process to move forward toward trial.</p>
        <p>''When this guy gets up there and he tells his story, I just do not believe that 12 fair-minded people are going to say he was unreasonable to believe he was about to be shot at,'' Mr. Karasyk said.</p>
        <p>''We want to get this over with,'' he added. ''Every day is hell for these guys.''</p>
        <p>The courtroom filled early with stakeholders:</p>
        <p>On the right side, behind Charles Testagrossa, the assistant district attorney who presented evidence to the grand jury, sat Mr. Sharpton, Mr. Guzman, Mr. Benefield and many members of Mr. Bell's family. On the left side sat rows of men in dark suits who were supporters of the police, among them Mr. Palladino and Patrick Lynch, the president of the Patrolmen's Benevolent Association. Mr. Sharpton and Mr. Bell's associates left without speaking after the hearing, climbing into a stretch limousine and two sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bell's parents remained, while their lawyers complained that the three detectives should be required to enter the courthouse through the front door, rather than side entrances. They also lashed out at recent reports that Mr. Bell shot a man last summer, reports later retracted by the man who was shot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis scoffed at police complaints about bad publicity, noting newspaper articles in March about Detective Oliver joining four friends for an expensive dinner before his arraignment.</p>
        <p>''They're creating their own media coverage,'' he said. ''You can't ask for a change of venue based on the fact that the media is reporting that you're out spending $4,000 on dinner.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Palladino, however, said the reports had the potential to infect a jury pool.</p>
        <p>''There is a foundation that this country was built upon, of due process and innocent until proven guilty,'' he said. ''That foundation has been weakened and may have been compromised.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
