<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Allies Meet to Discuss Afghan War, as Taliban Offensive Looms</title>
    <meta content="12gates" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/world/asia/12gates.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shanker, Thom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Robert M (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Taliban</org>
        <org class="online_producer">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gates, Robert M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E6DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Allies Meet to Discuss Afghan War, as Taliban Offensive Looms</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Allies Meet to Discuss Afghan War, as Taliban Offensive Looms</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOM SHANKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shanker, Thom</byline>
      <dateline>QUEBEC, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense Sec Robert M Gates meets with defense ministers from nations contributing troops to NATO mission in southern Afghanistan to discuss war there as spring thaw opens way for new Taliban offensive; meeting was requested by Canada, which lost six soldiers on Apr 8; question facing ministers is whether alliance has ability and will to sustain most complicated and bloody combat mission in NATO history for years to come; Gates hopes to ensure more comprehensive approach to NATO mission, in which reconstruction and development are linked seamlessly with combat operations; Taliban and Qaeda, which suffered heavy losses in conventional battles last year, are expected to focus this year on hit-and-run attacks, suicide bombings and improvised roadside explosives (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates and allied defense ministers gathered here on Wednesday to discuss the war in Afghanistan at a moment of reckoning for the nations carrying the brunt of combat there.</p>
        <p>The spring thaw is again opening the way for a new Taliban offensive. And even as the allies prepare for another season of fighting, critics of the Bush administration continue their accusations that the focus on the Iraq war has jeopardized the early military victory in Afghanistan in 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Critics of the Bush administration say that the focus on the Iraq war has jeopardized the early military victory in Afghanistan in 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates and allied defense ministers gathered here on Wednesday to discuss the war in Afghanistan at a moment of reckoning for the nations carrying the brunt of combat there.</p>
        <p>The spring thaw is again opening the way for a new Taliban offensive. And even as the allies prepare for another season of fighting, critics of the Bush administration continue their accusations that the focus on the Iraq war has jeopardized the early military victory in Afghanistan in 2001.</p>
        <p>The session of defense ministers from nations contributing troops to the NATO mission in southern Afghanistan, the spiritual home of the Taliban, was requested by Canada, which lost six soldiers on Sunday, the costliest day for its military since the Korean War.</p>
        <p>The recent squabbles, over the insistence by some NATO countries on limiting how their troops can be used in Afghanistan, have gone quiet, at least in public. And shortages in equipment and personnel for the new NATO mission in Afghanistan have been reduced. They are now mostly seen in a lack of helicopters and transport planes, and military trainers, Pentagon officials said.</p>
        <p>The question facing Mr. Gates and his counterparts from Australia, Britain, Canada, Denmark and the Netherlands, with lower-level officials invited from Estonia and Romania, is more strategic, and more stark: Does the alliance have the ability, and the will, to sustain the most complicated and bloody combat mission in NATO history for years to come? It is universally agreed that is what will be required.</p>
        <p>Officially, the purpose of the session here is to ''facilitate dialogue'' and ''share best practices'' so the allies can pull together, a senior Defense Department official said.</p>
        <p>Even so, the senior official acknowledged that continued shortfalls in fulfilling commitments of troops and equipment for the mission would be on the table as the ministers gather Wednesday night and all day Thursday.</p>
        <p>The senior Defense Department official said Mr. Gates's goals for the session were to ensure a more comprehensive approach to the NATO mission in Afghanistan, one in which reconstruction and development are linked seamlessly with combat operations.</p>
        <p>The goal is for military operations to clear southern Afghan regions of fighters for the Taliban and Al Qaeda, but for those missions to be followed rapidly by investments in infrastructure and other reconstruction. The hope is that a sustained security presence will help create zones hospitable to international aid agencies and the Afghan government to set up long-term municipal services.</p>
        <p>As of the first week of March, the international mission in Afghanistan had 35,000 troops from 26 NATO nations and 11 other allies. About 15,000 of them were from the United States. In addition, the American military has 11,000 troops in Afghanistan on separate counterterrorism and training missions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates arrived here with no new offers of troops or equipment, officials said.</p>
        <p>As the ministers gathered, military officers and intelligence specialists were analyzing surveillance in anticipation of an imminent spring offensive by the Taliban and Al Qaeda. Those attacks have not yet begun in earnest, according to American military assessments.</p>
        <p>''But this is an experienced and adaptable adversary,'' said Anthony H. Cordesman, a military analyst at the Center for Strategic and International Studies in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cordesman expressed doubts that Taliban forces would wage the unusually large attacks they did last year because they suffered significant losses in conventional battles against NATO, Afghan and allied troops.</p>
        <p>Instead, he said, Taliban and Qaeda forces are expected to focus on hit-and-run attacks, suicide bombings and improvised roadside explosives that have been used with such devastating effect in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Many military officers and Pentagon officials with time on the ground in Afghanistan contend that the coalition should do more at the lowest levels to help the Afghan people.</p>
        <p>Instead, many development and reconstruction efforts today are from the top down, with insufficient progress to improve the lives of those at the bottom of the economic and social ladder in Afghanistan's far-flung and backward provinces, these officials say.</p>
        <p>Americans who have deployed to Afghanistan say this is especially true in rural areas that are most susceptible to coercion by the Taliban, warlords or drug traffickers.</p>
        <p>In those areas, NATO and its allies are expected this spring to try to put much more emphasis on schools, roads, power, potable water, irrigation, economic development and the justice system, even as they continue combat operations against insurgents, to Pentagon and military officials said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
