<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rising Inflation May Mean More Fed Rate Increases</title>
    <meta content="12fomc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/business/12fomc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lacker, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peters, Jeremy W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Open Market Committee</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rising Inflation May Mean More Fed Rate Increases</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rising Inflation May Mean More Fed Rate Increases</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY W. PETERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peters, Jeremy W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Minutes from March meeting of Federal Open Market Committee show that officials agreed that more interest rate increases might be needed to tame rising inflation, though they also expressed concern that economy could slow more than forecast; stocks fall sharply after release of minutes; Jeffrey Lacker, hawkish president of Federal Reserve Bank of Richmond, says rate increases might be needed if inflation does not fall back (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At their last meeting, Federal Reserve officials agreed that more interest rate increases might be needed to tame rising inflation, though they also expressed concern that the economy could slow more than forecast.</p>
        <p>Minutes from the March meeting of the Federal Open Market Committee, released yesterday, reinforced its position that inflation remained the biggest threat to the economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal Reserve officials also expressed concern that the economy could slow more than forecast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At their last meeting, Federal Reserve officials agreed that more interest rate increases might be needed to tame rising inflation, though they also expressed concern that the economy could slow more than forecast.</p>
        <p>Minutes from the March meeting of the Federal Open Market Committee, released yesterday, reinforced its position that inflation remained the biggest threat to the economy.</p>
        <p>Investors interpreted that yesterday to mean that a rate cut in the near future was unlikely.</p>
        <p>They had initially read the Fed's statement from that meeting as encouraging the idea that an interest rate cut could happen within the next few months.</p>
        <p>Stock prices fell sharply after the minutes were released at 2 p.m. The Dow Jones industrial average lost 89.23 points, or about 0.7 percent, in yesterday's session. The broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 9.52 points, or 0.66 percent.</p>
        <p>The minutes showed that central bankers grappled with a growing uncertainty about which direction the economy was headed.</p>
        <p>So for the first time since Ben S. Bernanke became chairman in February 2006, the Fed decided to omit language indicating its bias toward ''additional firming'' of rates in the statement that accompanied its decision to hold short-term interest rates at 5.25 percent.</p>
        <p>''In light of the increased uncertainty about the outlook for both growth and inflation, the committee also agreed that the statement should no longer cite only the possibility of further firming,'' the minutes said.</p>
        <p>''Instead, the statement should indicate that future policy adjustments will depend on the evolution of the outlook for both inflation and economic growth.''</p>
        <p>The Fed ''is feeling an increased intensity and unpredictability of crosswinds in the outlook,'' Brian A. Bethune, an economist with Global Insight, said in a research note.</p>
        <p>The revised language allows the Fed room to move rates in either direction.</p>
        <p>''They're adding flexibility by acknowledging that there's at least some possibility of a rate cut,'' said Ethan Harris, chief United States economist of Lehman Brothers. ''But that doesn't mean they're taking the eye off the ball here in terms of inflation.''</p>
        <p>The Fed minutes echoed recent statements by Mr. Bernanke and other Fed officials who have maintained that their focus was on inflation.</p>
        <p>After the Fed's March 21 statement, stocks rallied on the hope that interest rates would soon fall. That is a notion that Mr. Bernanke and others at the Fed have sought to dispel in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>Speaking yesterday in North Carolina, Jeffrey Lacker, the hawkish president of the Federal Reserve Bank of Richmond, said that rate increases might be needed if inflation did not fall back.</p>
        <p>Other Fed officials have made similar statements in recent days. Frederic S. Mishkin, a Fed governor, and Richard W. Fisher, president of the Federal Reserve Bank of Dallas, also hinted this week at further rate increases if inflation continued to rise.</p>
        <p>''A number of Fed officials have come out and repeated their mantra,'' Mr. Harris of Lehman said. ''They're saying things have to be quite painful if we're going to cut rates.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
