<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doubts Cloud Takeover Talk for Gold Fields</title>
    <meta content="12gold" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/business/12gold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gold</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hoaxes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gold Fields Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bloomberg Lp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">De La Merced, Michael J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Africa</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Gold Fields Limited</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bloomberg Business News</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doubts Cloud Takeover Talk for Gold Fields</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Doubts Cloud Takeover Talk for Gold Fields</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL J. de la MERCED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De La Merced, Michael J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares in South African mining company Gold Fields gain as much as 11 percent in trading after report published by Bloomberg News said that American financier Edward Pastorini planned to make offer for company; several news services picked up story, but doubts arose just as quickly; Gold Fields releases statement denying rumors; Bloomberg publishes update, casting doubt on its original report and fueling suspicions that it is victim of hoax (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shares in the South African mining company Gold Fields, one of the world's largest gold producers, shot up as much as 11 percent in trading yesterday after a report published late Tuesday by Bloomberg News said that an American financier planned to make an offer for the company.</p>
        <p>Several news services, including Reuters and The New York Times, in its online DealBook, picked up on the report. But doubts arose just as quickly, and Gold Fields, based in Johannesburg, released a statement denying the rumors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A report that said the South African mining company Gold Fields was the target of a buyout offer may have been a hoax.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shares in the South African mining company Gold Fields, one of the world's largest gold producers, shot up as much as 11 percent in trading yesterday after a report published late Tuesday by Bloomberg News said that an American financier planned to make an offer for the company.</p>
        <p>Several news services, including Reuters and The New York Times, in its online DealBook, picked up on the report. But doubts arose just as quickly, and Gold Fields, based in Johannesburg, released a statement denying the rumors.</p>
        <p>Yesterday afternoon, Bloomberg published an update, casting doubt on its original report and fueling suspicions that it had fallen victim to a hoax.</p>
        <p>At a time when private equity firms can make $45 billion leveraged buyout deals, an offer for Gold Fields, with a market value of $12.5 billion, seemed plausible. But other publications noted that the supposed financier, Edward Pastorini, could not be found on Google or news search sites like Factiva or Nexis. The first match of that name on Google was the keeper of a lighthouse in Saugerties, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The original article was published online and released through Bloomberg's news service at 5:19 a.m. yesterday New York time. It was written by Stewart Bailey, a reporter in Johannesburg, who cited internal documents in reporting that an American financier named Edward Pastorini planned to announce a cash-and-stock offer for Gold Fields.</p>
        <p>That bid would not come until June or July, after the group had accumulated about 10 percent of Gold Fields' shares.</p>
        <p>In his article, Mr. Bailey wrote that he had corresponded with Mr. Pastorini by e-mail and phone.</p>
        <p>Alphaville, a blog run by The Financial Times in London, quickly questioned the report, wondering why a veteran investor would broadcast his intentions at least two months before making a formal offer.</p>
        <p>In an article published at 5:36 p.m. yesterday, William Selway, a Bloomberg reporter in San Francisco, wrote that the source of the internal documents was a Gold Fields executive who requested anonymity. He also noted that a phone number given by Mr. Pastorini was linked to a Florida partnership that had made fake takeover bids for several companies. Mr. Pastorini's e-mail address, Mr. Selway wrote, was an AOL account.</p>
        <p>In an e-mail message to Bloomberg yesterday, Mr. Pastorini decline to divulge any background information and reaffirmed his intention to bid for Gold Fields.</p>
        <p>Matthew A. Winkler, Bloomberg's editor in chief, said yesterday that the news service would continue to investigate Mr. Pastorini. Meanwhile, Gold Fields shares closed up 22 cents yesterday, at $19.50.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
