<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Postseason Draws Near, Nets' Three Stars Turn It On</title>
    <meta content="12nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/sports/basketball/12nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Washington Wizards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jefferson, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E2D9123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Postseason Draws Near, Nets' Three Stars Turn It On</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Postseason Draws Near, Nets’ Three Stars Turn It On</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets' decisive 6-0 spurt against the Washington Wizards on Tuesday night started with a short jumper by Vince Carter in the lane. That was followed by consecutive fast-break layups from Richard Jefferson and Jason Kidd.</p>
        <p>It took all of 1 minute 11 seconds for the Nets to turn a 5-point deficit into a 1-point lead, and for the Nets' three stars to demonstrate that they remain one of the most dangerous combinations in the N.B.A.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With their victory Tuesday night, the Nets won for the sixth time in eight games and received marvelous performances from their go-to players for the second consecutive game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nets' decisive 6-0 spurt against the Washington Wizards on Tuesday night started with a short jumper by Vince Carter in the lane. That was followed by consecutive fast-break layups from Richard Jefferson and Jason Kidd.</p>
        <p>It took all of 1 minute 11 seconds for the Nets to turn a 5-point deficit into a 1-point lead, and for the Nets' three stars to demonstrate that they remain one of the most dangerous combinations in the N.B.A.</p>
        <p>With their 96-92 victory, the Nets won for the sixth time in eight games and received marvelous performances from their go-to players for the second consecutive game.</p>
        <p>Jefferson scored a season-high 35 points, surpassing the previous high of 27 points he had Saturday night in the Nets' 120-114 victory over the Wizards. Carter had 31 points and 6 assists Tuesday, after picking up his third career triple-double (46 points, 16 rebounds, 10 assists) on Saturday. And Kidd had 14 rebounds and 11 assists, only three nights after recording the 86th triple-double of his career.</p>
        <p>Nearing the end of a regular season filled with injuries and inconsistency, the big three appear healthy and motivated at the right time. The Nets (37-40) are only two games behind the Wizards for the sixth seed in the Eastern Conference playoffs.</p>
        <p>''I think we understand the importance of these games,'' Jefferson said. ''We've all been in the playoffs multiple times. We've all had success in the playoffs. We understand what it takes. You see games that you got to get.''</p>
        <p>The Nets have lacked victories over quality opponents, but they will have a chance for one Thursday night when they play the Cavaliers in Cleveland in what could be a preview of the first round of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Jefferson has punctuated the success of the Nets' big three.</p>
        <p>Jefferson, who is averaging 16.3 points and 4.4 rebounds this season, twisted his right ankle in the postseason last year, and the injury carried over to this season. He did not have his usual explosiveness from the start, and he had arthroscopic surgery on the ankle, causing him to miss 21 games.</p>
        <p>He said his ankle would not be completely healed until after the season. For now, though, he is showing that he is good enough to make an impact. Jefferson remains one of the Nets' most aggressive players in driving to the basket and one of the most willing to run in transition.</p>
        <p>In the past two games, Jefferson has also effectively pulled up for long-range shots, making 8 of 13 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>''I want to get back to being one of the elite forwards in this game,'' he said. ''That's something that hasn't been there all year long. I want to get back there where you're one of the best small forwards, you're considered an All-Star every single year, almost to that level.''</p>
        <p>This could be the last chance that Carter, Kidd and Jefferson have to prove their worth as a unit. Carter can opt out of the final year of his contract after the season, Kidd is 34 and the Nets have considered trading him, and Jefferson, when healthy, is always a popular commodity on the trade market.</p>
        <p>But first, they need to guide the Nets through their remaining five regular-season games.</p>
        <p>''It's guys laying it on the line, trying to get ourselves in the playoffs, trying to secure a spot,'' Carter said. ''Everybody's laying it all out there now.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
