<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canadian Rail Workers Reject Contract Offer</title>
    <meta content="12rail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/business/worldbusiness/12rail.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839750"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Canadian National Railway Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Transportation Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Canadian National Railway Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EED9123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="413" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canadian Rail Workers Reject Contract Offer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Canadian Rail Workers Reject Contract Offer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Austen, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Labor disruptions again hit Canadian National Railway after workers overwhelmingly reject tentative contract leading to pickets and lockouts in some cities; union says it will try to limit current walkout's impact on rail customers; railroad locks out about 280 workers in five cities who had originally intended only to remain off jobs for few hours; Canadian National says lockouts are necessary to maintain railroad's operating schedules; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Labor disruptions again hit the Canadian National Railway after workers overwhelmingly rejecting a tentative contract leading to pickets and lockouts in some cities.</p>
        <p>A 15-day strike in February led to plant closings and shipping disruptions throughout North America, but the union said on Wednesday that it would try to limit the current walkout's impact on rail customers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Workers at the Canadian National Railway have resumed picketing after overwhelmingly rejecting a tentative contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Labor disruptions again hit the Canadian National Railway after workers overwhelmingly rejecting a tentative contract leading to pickets and lockouts in some cities.</p>
        <p>A 15-day strike in February led to plant closings and shipping disruptions throughout North America, but the union said on Wednesday that it would try to limit the current walkout's impact on rail customers.</p>
        <p>However, later in the day, the Montreal-based railroad locked out about 280 workers in five cities who had originally intended only to remain off the job for a few hours.</p>
        <p>About 2,800 conductors and yard workers began a rotating strike after 79 percent of the members of the United Transportation Union at the railroad rejected a one-year agreement providing for a 3 percent wage increase and a signing bonus of 1,000 Canadian dollars ($870).</p>
        <p>Tim Secord, the national legislative director of the Ottawa-based union, said the rotating pickets were re-established just before midnight Tuesday to pressure the railroad to resume talks.</p>
        <p>''C.N. has now seen fit to lock out our members at these locations effectively escalating the level of disruption,'' Mr. Secord said on Wednesday night. ''That is not what we want.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Canadian National, Mark Hallman, said the lockouts were necessary to maintain the railroad's operating schedules.</p>
        <p>''We have to have a predictable source of manpower resources,'' Mr. Hallman said, adding that the railroad will continue to lock out striking workers ''at the company's discretion.''</p>
        <p>The union will continue with its plan for rotating strikes despite the lockouts, Mr. Secord said, although it will not take any action that could disrupt commuter trains in Montreal and Toronto.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Secord, the union's members are largely satisfied with the economic portions of the tentative agreement. Their concerns he said, are more focused around work rules and surveillance of employees by the railroad.</p>
        <p>The previous walkout led to shipping delays and parts shortages that forced the Ford Motor Company of Canada to temporarily close an assembly plant in Ontario.</p>
        <p>Chemical, paper, lumber, coal, sulfur and grain producers also experienced production and shipping problems. Canadian ports, which handle merchandise from Asia bound for the United States, often on Canadian National trains, also became congested, adding to delays.</p>
        <p>After the federal government threatened to introduce back-to-work legislation that would have imposed a contract through arbitration, the two sides worked out the tentative agreement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hallman said the railway would operate with management employees, as it did in February, if the labor shutdown expands.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
