<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Advisers' E-Mail Accounts May Have Mixed Politics and Business, White House Says</title>
    <meta content="12emails" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/washington/12emails.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican National Committee</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DA123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Advisers' E-Mail Accounts May Have Mixed Politics and Business, White House Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Advisers’ Approach on E-Mail Draws Fire</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White House officials say that political advisers to Pres Bush may have improperly used their Republican National Committee e-mail accounts to conduct official government business and that some of these e-mails, which are required to be preserved under federal law, may have been lost as result; accounts are supposed to be used only for campaign related work; Democrats want to know if officials intentionally used political e-mail accounts to escape scrutiny and circumvent law; White House begins its own inquiry and says it is working with national committee to discover what is missing and whether it can be retrieved (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Political advisers to President Bush may have improperly used their Republican National Committee e-mail accounts to conduct official government business, and some communications that are required to be preserved under federal law may be lost as a result, White House officials said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Of the 1,000 White House officials with political duties, 22 -- including Karl Rove, the chief political strategist -- have Republican National Committee accounts that are supposed to be used only for campaign-related work. But recent revelations that some officials have used those accounts for Bush administration business, including discussions of a plan to dismiss United States attorneys, has prompted a Congressional investigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some officials may have improperly used Republican National Committee accounts for government business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Political advisers to President Bush may have improperly used their Republican National Committee e-mail accounts to conduct official government business, and some communications that are required to be preserved under federal law may be lost as a result, White House officials said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Of the 1,000 White House officials with political duties, 22 -- including Karl Rove, the chief political strategist -- have Republican National Committee accounts that are supposed to be used only for campaign-related work. But recent revelations that some officials have used those accounts for Bush administration business, including discussions of a plan to dismiss United States attorneys, has prompted a Congressional investigation.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Scott Stanzel, deputy White House press secretary, said the administration had recently begun its own inquiry, and had concluded that its policy governing political e-mail accounts was unclear, that the White House was not aggressive enough in monitoring political e-mail and that some people who had the accounts did not follow the policy closely enough.</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Stanzel said, ''some official e-mails have potentially been lost.'' He said Mr. Bush had told the White House counsel's office ''to do everything practical to retrieve potentially lost messages.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stanzel and a second administration official, who is involved in the review and was authorized by the White House to speak on condition of anonymity, said the White House was working with the national committee to discover what was missing and whether it could be retrieved.</p>
        <p>If e-mail messages have been lost, Mr. Stanzel said, they are most likely those sent before 2004. That year, the national committee adopted a policy of preserving e-mail sent by White House officials using its accounts.</p>
        <p>Democrats want to know whether White House officials intentionally used political e-mail accounts to escape scrutiny or circumvent the law requiring preservation of records. They reacted with suspicion on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''This sounds like the administration's version of the dog ate my homework,'' said Senator Patrick J. Leahy, Democrat of Vermont and chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee, which is investigating the dismissal of the prosecutors.</p>
        <p>''I am deeply disturbed that just when this administration is finally subjected to meaningful oversight,'' Mr. Leahy said, ''it cannot produce the necessary information.''</p>
        <p>Representative Henry A. Waxman, the California Democrat who is chairman of the House Committee on Oversight and Government Reform, has asked the White House to produce records relating to nongovernment e-mail accounts by April 18. But a Democratic aide, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the White House told Mr. Waxman's committee on Wednesday that it would not be able to comply fully.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman issued a brief statement: ''This is a remarkable admission that raises serious legal and security issues. The White House has an obligation to disclose all the information it has.''</p>
        <p>The flap grows out of the investigation into the dismissals of the prosecutors. E-mail messages provided to Congress in that inquiry showed that Scott Jennings, a deputy political director for Mr. Bush, used his national committee address, ending in gwb43.com, to discuss them with aides to Attorney General Alberto R. Gonzales, including D. Kyle Sampson, who resigned amid the ensuing uproar.</p>
        <p>In January, an assistant to Mr. Jennings used a gwb43.com account to circulate a document discussing Democrats who are being singled out for defeat in 2008. ''Please do not e-mail this out or let people see it,'' the e-mail read, adding, ''It is a close hold, and we're not supposed to be e-mailing it around.''</p>
        <p>Other messages have brought scrutiny as well, including exchanges between Susan Ralston, a former assistant to Mr. Rove, and Jack Abramoff, the lobbyist convicted of corruption charges.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ralston apparently preferred to e-mail Mr. Abramoff and associates on her national committee Blackberry. In one exchange, Mr. Abramoff and a colleague worried about an e-mail message that wound up in the White House system.</p>
        <p>''Dammit,'' Mr. Abramoff wrote, ''it was sent to Susan on her rnc pager and was not supposed to go into the WH system.''</p>
        <p>At issue is how the White House complies with two seemingly competing laws. One is the 1978 Presidential Records Act, which requires the administration to ensure that its decisions and deliberations are ''adequately documented'' and that records flowing out of those decisions are preserved.</p>
        <p>The other is the Hatch Act, which prohibits federal officials from engaging in political business on government time.</p>
        <p>In order to comply with the Hatch act, the Clinton administration also permitted certain officials to hold dual e-mail accounts. But Bush White House officials say theirs is the first administration to operate in the era of instant communications.</p>
        <p>They say compliance has grown more complicated, and the White House rules have not kept pace with technology. As a result of their review, Mr. Stanzel and the senior official said the White House has put into effect a policy requiring, among other things, that officials with national committee e-mail accounts obtain permission for those accounts from the White House counsel's office.</p>
        <p>The new policy also requires officials with two accounts to sign a ''statement of understanding, saying they understand their obligations here and intend to comply with them,'' the senior official said.</p>
        <p>Asked if he had any evidence that officials were intentionally using the national committee accounts to circumvent record-keeping requirements, Mr. Stanzel said he had not interviewed White House aides about how they made decisions on e-mail accounts.</p>
        <p>''I can't speak to people's individual e-mail practices,'' he said. ''I think the best we can say is were trying to do a comprehensive review.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
