<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Philadelphia School Sells a Second Eakins</title>
    <meta content="12pain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/12/arts/design/12pain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1839666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Christie's</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Eakins, Thomas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Walton, Alice L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EEDB123FF931A25757C0A9619C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Philadelphia School Sells a Second Eakins</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Philadelphia School Sells a Second Eakins</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Less than four months after Philadelphians thwarted its bid to buy ''The Gross Clinic,'' an 1875 masterpiece by Thomas Eakins, an Arkansas museum founded by the Wal-Mart heiress Alice L. Walton has quietly purchased another much-loved Eakins painting from the Philadelphia medical school that sold the first.</p>
        <p>The canvas, the 1874 ''Portrait of Professor Benjamin H. Rand,'' is destined for the new Crystal Bridges Museum of American Art, now under construction in Bentonville, Ark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Arkansas museum has quietly purchased a Thomas Eakins painting from a Philadelphia medical school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Less than four months after Philadelphians thwarted its bid to buy ''The Gross Clinic,'' an 1875 masterpiece by Thomas Eakins, an Arkansas museum founded by the Wal-Mart heiress Alice L. Walton has quietly purchased another much-loved Eakins painting from the Philadelphia medical school that sold the first.</p>
        <p>The canvas, the 1874 ''Portrait of Professor Benjamin H. Rand,'' is destined for the new Crystal Bridges Museum of American Art, now under construction in Bentonville, Ark.</p>
        <p>Like ''The Gross Clinic'' it depicts a revered doctor who taught at Thomas Jefferson University, which sold both paintings.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rand, who once taught Eakins anatomy, donated his portrait to the university when he retired in 1877. Proceeds from the sale, which experts familiar with the deal put at about $20 million, will go toward the expansion of its educational and research programs and development of its 13-acre Center City campus.</p>
        <p>Marc Porter, president of Christie's, the New York auction house, negotiated the deal on behalf of the university. Christie's said the painting arrived this week at its Rockefeller Plaza headquarters for conservation.</p>
        <p>Last fall Crystal Bridges and the National Gallery of Art negotiated a deal jointly to buy ''The Gross Clinic'' from Thomas Jefferson for a stunning $68 million. Mindful of Eakins's resonance as a native son of Philadelphia, the university, announcing the sale, gave local institutions 45 days to match the offer. The prospect of the painting's departure set off a passionate city-wide fund-raising campaign by the Philadelphia Museum of Art and the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts to keep the painting in the city.</p>
        <p>This time Thomas Jefferson alerted those institutions to the deal in advance. ''Both the Philadelphia Museum and the Pennsylvania Academy were aware that this painting was available, and both knew about the sale well ahead of time,'' said Robert L. Barchi, president of the university. ''The board and senior management felt the sale was the appropriate thing to do.''</p>
        <p>As part of a general effort to lend paintings from its collection in anticipation of its 2009 opening, Crystal Bridges will allow the Rand portrait to go on view this spring at the Philadelphia Museum, which owns a trove of Eakins works. The date has yet to be determined.</p>
        <p>''We want to keep the painting in the public eye,'' said Robert G. Workman, executive director of Crystal Bridges. ''It's important that the Rand portrait be seen in the context of the other Eakins.''</p>
        <p>''The Portrait of Professor Benjamin H. Rand'' depicts the doctor sitting at his desk gazing down pensively at a book, one finger pointing at a page while he absent-mindedly strokes a cat on his desk with the other hand.</p>
        <p>At the time he was painting the Rand portrait, Eakins was teaching night classes at the Pennsylvania Academy. Among his students were the still-life painters William Michael Harnett and John Frederick Peto.</p>
        <p>''Eakins was doing all those figure paintings with still lives which Harnett and Peto could have seen in his studio,'' said John Wilmerding, a professor of art history at Princeton University and an adviser to Mrs. Walton. ''The collection of objects on his desk are presented almost as if they were a still life.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilmerding said Eakins painted the portrait shortly after completing a series of works devoted to men outdoors and another to women playing the piano indoors. ''This painting brings both subjects together,'' he explained, citing its unusual play of the masculine against the feminine.</p>
        <p>On the desk is a gleaming microscope; casually draped over a chair is a red shawl presumably belonging to an unseen woman. The painting subtly refers to the ''two sides of the brain,'' Mr. Wilmerding explained, playing the sensual and the physical off the intellectual.</p>
        <p>''The Gross Clinic,'' which famously depicts a surgeon operating on a man's thigh as students survey the bloody spectacle, was rejected by the art committee of the Centennial Exhibition in Philadelphia in 1876 and relegated to a display of medical instruments and hospital equipment. But the less controversial Rand portrait was proclaimed one of the best paintings at the event.</p>
        <p>The latest sale is not the end to Thomas Jefferson University's Eakins saga. It still owns an Eakins portrait of the anatomy professor William S. Forbes.</p>
        <p>''We will entertain the possibility of selling this one too,'' Dr. Barchi said. ''But like the others, it is our hope to be able to keep it on public display.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
